<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880408-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-08-88 1733EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ChildDeath 2ndLd-Writethru a0686 04-08 0660</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Child Death, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0686,0678</SECOND>
<HEAD>Second Death of 3-Year-Old at Welfare Hotel</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 14 grafs to UPDATE with news conference on girl's
injuries, mother's boyfriend, results of autopsy, remove
now-outdated material. Pickup 14th graf, `Maya lived...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A battered 3-year-old being used as a
panhandling prop died just after a concerned passerby sent her to a
hospital, the second death in two weeks of a toddler who lived at
the city's largest welfare hotel, police said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The girl's mother's boyfriend was charged with murder.
   <PERSON>Maya Figueroa</PERSON> had ``bruises and contusions on her face, back and
neck. Some of these bruises appeared to be recent,'' police Capt.
<PERSON>Michael Gardner</PERSON> said at a news conference.
   Police questioned the girl's mother, <PERSON>Elise Vasquez</PERSON>, 32, who was
in <ORGANIZATION>Bellevue Hospital</ORGANIZATION> after giving birth <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to her fifth
child.
   The girl was pronounced dead <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, 20 minutes after
she arrived at <ORGANIZATION>New York University Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Aaron
Rosenthal</PERSON>, assistant chief of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> detectives.
   An autopsy <DATE>Friday</DATE> indicated the toddler died of blunt force
injuries of head and abdomen with internal injuries and bleeding,
said <PERSON>Ellen Borakove</PERSON> of the city medical examiner's office. The case
was officially ruled child abuse and a homicide, she said.
   The girl had been sent to the hospital by a man who saw her on a
street corner with <PERSON>Benito Sanches</PERSON>, 29, who had been panhandling,
police said. Maya was in a stroller and her 18-month-old brother
was in <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON>' arms, <PERSON>Rosenthal</PERSON> said.
   ``Maya appeared to be in serious condition with trauma at least
around the face,'' <PERSON>Rosenthal</PERSON> said.
   He said <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> had a habit of using the children to panhandle.
   ``He'll take two of the children of his girlfriend, put them in
a stroller and go out and solicit funds in their presence,''
<PERSON>Rosenthal</PERSON> said.
   The passerby, who had not been identified, stopped a cab, gave
the driver <MONEY>$5</MONEY> and told him to take <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> and the children to a
hospital. The cab driver told police what had happened.
   <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> said police were seeking the passerby.
   ``We appeal to him to come forward. We would like to speak to
him about what was going on,'' said <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON>.
   Sanches is a drug abuser with a past record who came to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in <DATE>May 1980</DATE> with the Cuban boat lift, <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> said.
He was charged with second-degree murder, said police Officer <PERSON>Jim
Coleman</PERSON>.
   Maya lived with her mother, her brother and <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Prince George Hotel</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>East Side</LOCATION>, where the city houses
463 homeless families, or about 2,600 people.
   The city provides housing for about 28,000 homeless people,
12,000 of them in welfare hotels and the remainder in shelters,
said spokeswoman <PERSON>Suzanne Trazoff</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Human Resources
Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two weeks ago, 3-year-old <PERSON>Quintin McKenzie</PERSON> was scalded to death
in a bathtub at the hotel. His mother, <PERSON>Merian McKenzie</PERSON>, was charged
with second-degree murder and her husband, <PERSON>Calvin C. McKenzie</PERSON>, was
charged with assault for allegedly beating the toddler.
   ``These are terrible stories,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Trazoff</PERSON>.
   ``The Prince <PERSON>George</PERSON> has a large number of social services,'' she
said. A social service office, open during daytime hours, is
located in the hotel and a variety of programs are available,
including preschool and day care programs, she said.
   When asked why no one apparently noticed that the child had been
beaten, <PERSON>Ms. Trazoff</PERSON> speculated that the child's family may not have
requested any social services.
   The spokeswoman said <ORGANIZATION>HRA</ORGANIZATION> was checking its records to see if the
family had ever asked for help from the agency.
   The 18-month-old boy, whose name was not released, was admitted
to the hospital for observation although he had no visible signs of
abuse.
   Sanches and <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON> had lived together for 16 months,
<PERSON>Rosenthal</PERSON> said. <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON>'s two other children live with
relatives. The baby she had just had at <LOCATION>Bellevue</LOCATION> was the first the
couple had together.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880409-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-09-88 0801EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ChildDeath 1stLd-Writethru a0460 04-09 0757</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Child Death, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0460,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three-Year-Old Girl, Used As Panhandler's Prop, Dies</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 4 grafs after 4th graf, `Welfare workers ...,' to
move up 13th and 14th grafs pvs, `Detectives were ...,' and add
mother's comments. Picks up 5th graf pvs, `At the time ...,' but
deleting 13th and 14th grafs pvs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIRGINIA BYRNE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A panhandler who used a dying 3-year-old girl
and her brother to win sympathy has been charged in her beating
death, and police appealed for further help from the passerby who
tried to save her life.
   <PERSON>Benito Sanches</PERSON>, 36, a ``crack'' cocaine addict who came to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1980</DATE> Cuban boat lift, was charged <DATE>Friday</DATE> with
second-degree murder in the death of his girlfriend's daughter,
<PERSON>Maya Figueroa</PERSON>, police said.
   She was the second toddler in two weeks to die a violent death
at the city's biggest welfare hotel, The <ORGANIZATION>Prince George Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   Welfare workers had investigated the family for complaints of
abuse and neglect, but caseworkers had found no evidence of child
abuse, said <PERSON>Suzanne Trazoff</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the city <ORGANIZATION>Human
Resources Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   Detectives were investigating whether the girl's mother, <PERSON>Elise
Vasquez</PERSON>, 32, was involved in the alleged abuse, police Capt.
<PERSON>Michael Gardner</PERSON> said.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the night Maya died, <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON> was in <LOCATION>Bellevue
Hospital</LOCATION>, where she had given birth to her fifth child, a boy, the
day before.
   In an interview with the <ORGANIZATION>Daily News</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> before signing
herself out of the hospital, <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON> was quoted as saying she
did not believe <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> had hurt Maya and said that ``he loved the
child like it was his own. ...
   ``She would call him `Dada.' She wanted to be with him and to
play with him. He would take her panhandling because she liked to
be with him,'' <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON> said. ``She has been going out with him
for two years and he never laid a hand on her or any of the other
kids.''
   At the time of the battered girl's death <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <PERSON>Maya</PERSON> and her
18-month-old brother were being used by <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> as panhandling
props, police said. They said he had used them before to solicit
money.
   ``He hoped to get sympathy and compassion that way,'' said <PERSON>Aaron
H. Rosenthal</PERSON>, assistant chief of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> detectives.
   Maya was in her stroller when a concerned passerby noticed her
as <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> begged for coins at 28th Street and Second Avenue at
<TIME>9:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The man flagged down a taxi, gave the driver
<MONEY>$5</MONEY>, hustled the three into the cab and ordered the driver to take
them to a hospital, police said.
   Maya was declared dead on arrival at the emergency room at <ORGANIZATION>New
York University Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>. Her brother, whose name was
withheld, was admitted to the hospital for observation although he
showed no signs of abuse.
   Authorities questioned the cab driver; they hoped to locate the
good Samaritan and find out what he saw that night.
   ``We appeal to him to come forward. We would like to speak to
him about what was going on,'' <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> said.
   An autopsy <DATE>Friday</DATE> indicated the toddler died of blunt force
injuries to her head and abdomen with internal injuries and
bleeding, said <PERSON>Ellen Borakove</PERSON> of the city medical examiner's
office. The case was ruled child abuse and a homicide.
   Maya had ``bruises and contusions on her face, back and neck.
Some of these bruises appeared to be recent,'' <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> told a news
conference.
   The two children, their mother and <PERSON>Sanches</PERSON> lived at the <PERSON>Prince
George</PERSON> on <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>East Side</LOCATION>, which has 2,600 residents, mainly
homeless families. <PERSON>Ms. Vasquez</PERSON>'s two other children, ages 12 and
14, live with relatives in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, police said.
   Two weeks ago, 3-year-old <PERSON>Quintin McKenzie</PERSON> was scalded to death
in a bathtub at the <ORGANIZATION>Prince George</ORGANIZATION>. His mother, <PERSON>Merian McKenzie</PERSON>, was
charged with second-degree murder, and her husband, <PERSON>Calvin C.
McKenzie</PERSON>, was charged with assault for allegedly beating the
toddler.
   At the <PERSON>Prince George</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, a steady stream of people flowed
in and out of the two steel doors guarding the threadbare lobby.
Many of them pushed strollers or had young children by the hand.
   ``I have to say it: it's drugs,'' said a 21-year-old woman with
a stroller, who identified herself only as <ORGANIZATION>Maria</ORGANIZATION>. ``If they don't
get money for the drugs, they take it out on the kids.''
   ``It's drugs,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Maria New</PERSON>, who chairs the <ORGANIZATION>Pediatrics
Department</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>New York-Cornell Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``<PERSON>McKenzie</PERSON> was
drugs, and now this one, all drugs.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06126015 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06126015 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TRAVEL; HISTORY; MEXICO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WEARY of burning your retinas on the same old Mexican beach vacation? How
about a visit to "El Mundo Maya" instead?;    If it's a phrase you haven't
heard yet, be prepared: El Mundo Maya -- the world of the Maya -- is one of
the waves of the future in vacation travel to Mexico and Central America. You
may also hear it referred to as "La Ruta Maya," the route of the Maya, but the
idea is similar -- travel to the developed and undeveloped Mayan sites in
Mexico, Belize, Guatemala, Honduras and El Salvador.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ECOTOURISM PUSH EXTENDS TO 'EL MUNDO MAYA'
TOURS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Destination: Mexico
See also related story on P. 1T, 6T, 7T, 8T, and 9T of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     And there are hundreds of them, stretching from heavily visited places,
such as <LOCATION>Tulum</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s Yucatan, to <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Copan</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>
and lesser-known sites in war-torn <LOCATION>El Salvador.</LOCATION>;    Whether <PERSON>Mundo Maya</PERSON> or <ORGANIZATION>Ruta
Maya</ORGANIZATION>, the words will most likely also be linked to what has already become one
of the big trends in travel for the <DATE>1990s</DATE>: ecotourism. Ecotourism basically
means environmentally sensitive and socially conscious travel to wilderness
areas, especially those in underdeveloped parts of the world.;    The
underlying idea is that such travel, if it is well-managed, can prevent damage
to pristine areas, while generating enough income to keep the natives from
ravaging the same environment -- rain forests, for example -- to eke out a
living.;    In the <DATE>last two years</DATE>, a series of meetings among commercial and
governmental tourism officials in the five nations has found general accord
with linking tourists on a Mayan route through <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Central
America</LOCATION>. It even seems likely that a Mundo Maya "passport" will be created at
some point, to ease travel among the nations.;    But the concern of many
environmentalists is that <ORGANIZATION>El Mundo Maya</ORGANIZATION> will simply become another way for
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> to generate tourist dollars.;    The commercial operators are "more
concerned with tourism, and we're more concerned with preservation," says <PERSON>Bill
Garrett</PERSON>, founder and president of <ORGANIZATION>La Ruta Maya Conservation Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and a
former editor of <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> wrote an article for the <DATE>October
1989</DATE> Geographic that outlined ambitious plans to preserve and protect the
Mayan sites and their surrounding rain forests and preserves.;    <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON>
recalls watching in horror as guides ran boats close to a huge flock of
flamingos near <LOCATION>Celestun</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>, and made loud noises to spook
the birds into flight so tourists on the boats could get better pictures.
That's ecoterrorism, not ecotourism, he says.;    "At some point, they're
going to have to enforce the rules," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> says. "Most tourists aren't going
to get mad and go home if you say, 'Don't break the rules.' ";     IF YOU'RE
INTERESTED; Those seeking a reliable ecotourism operator can purchase the
<ORGANIZATION>Directory of Alternative Travel Resources</ORGANIZATION> by sending <MONEY>$7.50</MONEY> to One World Family
Travel Network, 81868 Lost Valley Lane, <PERSON>Dexter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> 97431; (503) 937-3351. A
travel guide, "La <PERSON>Ruta Maya</PERSON>," has just been published by Lonely Planet and is
available at many bookstores for <MONEY>$14.95</MONEY>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MIKE SHOUP, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910505  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  507  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday May 5, 1991
00126015,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06041234 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06041234 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: Matt Hale photo; Thorstein, Chichicastenango guide, before
a crumbling chapel (color).; PHOTO: Matt Hale photo; Getting ready for market:
superb weaving from a Maya mother (color).; PHOTO: Erica Wheater / The Image
Bank; No pretext for a visit to Guatemala is more compelling than to make
acquaintance with the Maya (color).; PHOTO: Andrea Pistolesi / The Image Bank;
The Grand Plaza at Tikal (color).  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  GUATEMALA; TRAVEL; GUIDELINE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ONCE, in this city, I asked an upper-class teen-ager if she knew any Maya
people.;    "No," she answered in English. "I don't think I've ever even seen
any."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MAYAN GUATEMALA
FORGET CHICHEN ITZA -- TIKAL IS THE PLACE
TO GET ACQUAINTED WITH MAYA, ANCIENT AND LIVING  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to the end of this article.
David Roberts is the author of "Moments of Doubt and Other Mountaineering
Writings" and has written for Outside magazine, Smithsonian and the Atlantic.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     She was, of course, mistaken: At every bus stop in the capital, Mayan men
and women stand waiting for their rides to work. Yet the teen-ager's ignorance
was somehow logical.;    Her ancestors, the Spanish conquistadors, had wiped
out nine of every 10 Maya Indians they had found in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> in the 16th
century.;    <DATE>Four hundred years later</DATE>, her people, called Ladinos, run a
government that does little more than the minimum to improve the lot of the
surviving indigenes, whom they call simply "Indios" and who constitute more
than <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the popula tion.;    The golden age of the ancient Maya,
the most advanced pre-Columbian civilization in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>, lasted from
A.D. 250 to 900.;    During that time, they built such magnificent cities as
<ORGANIZATION>Chichen Itza</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Palenque</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Uxmal</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Copan</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>Caracol</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>. The greatest Mayan city of all is <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION>, which has become <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s
No. 1 tourist attraction.;    But many of the visitors to the <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION> ruins
don't realize that more than 3 million Maya live in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> today -- more
than are found in the other Central American countries and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> put
together. <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> remains the heartland of Mayan civilization.;    No
pretext for a visit to <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> is more compelling than to make acquaintance
with the Maya -- both ancient and living.;    There are many other reasons to
travel to our nearest Central American neighbor: The alpine beauty of the
volcanic highlands, a remarkably favorable exchange rate between the dollar
and the quetzal, a cross-cultural openness in the hinterlands that, in the
words of photojournalist <PERSON>Galen Rowell</PERSON>, reminds one of the free-and-easy hippie
ambiance of <LOCATION>Katmandu</LOCATION> in the 1960s.;    And, despite continuing skirmishes
between guerrillas and the army, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> is safe for visitors. There is
little of the anti-American feeling found in <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> and
Panama.;    Visitors fly into the capital, <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>. A day there is long
enough, time to wander through its excellent museums housing everything from
ancient Mayan artifacts to modern art, before heading west.;    A smoggy
metropolis, the city was leveled by earthquakes in <DATE>1917</DATE> and <DATE>1976</DATE>, and as a
result little remains of colonial architecture.;    Only 30 miles west lies
<LOCATION>Antigua Guatemala</LOCATION>, where the Spanish built a colonial capital to rival <LOCATION>Mexico
City</LOCATION>. The population today is only 16,000, but the town breathes the
melancholy grandeur of the conquest.;    Half-ruined baroque churches by the
dozen; clean cobblestone streets and bright-hued housefronts; a glimpse of
cool inner patios spangled with hand-painted tiles; and rising 7,000 feet
above the village, the steep blue cone of <ORGANIZATION>Volcan Agua</ORGANIZATION>, its summit lost in
mist.;    The road wends on, deeper into the highlands, till you come suddenly
upon <LOCATION>Lake Atitlan</LOCATION>, rimmed by tall mountains whose shoulders slope into the
dark water.;    Tucked in a wrinkle of its north shore is the village of
<LOCATION>Panajachel</LOCATION>, full of Cakchiquel-speaking Maya and blissed-out hippies, both
young and aging, from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION> and even the <LOCATION>United
States.</LOCATION>;    A morning ferry traverses the lake to the village of <LOCATION>Santiago
Atitlan</LOCATION>. Cross the waters and you have changed cultures, though at first blush
the markets and churches look the same.;    In <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, though, the women
wear white garments, called huipils, instead of the red and blue huipils in
<LOCATION>Panajachel</LOCATION>. The people speak Tzutuhil instead of Cakchiquel.;    They were
once, in fact, enemies, and if you knew how to probe skillfully enough, you
might still uncover the old Tzutuhil bitterness against their neighbors, who
allied themselves with the butcher <PERSON>Pedro de Alvarado</PERSON>, a lieutenant of <PERSON>Hernando
Cortes</PERSON>, who conquered <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> in <DATE>1524</DATE>, bringing Christianity with him.;   
Nothing in Mayan life today is more bizarre than the amalgamation of pagan
with Catholic beliefs.;    In the <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> church, there is a statue of a
"saint" called Maximon, supposed to be a combination of <ORGANIZATION>Judas</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Pedro de
Alvarado</PERSON> and the Mayan god <ORGANIZATION>Mam</ORGANIZATION>. Other towns have a Maximon, whom the people
revile every year during Holy Week. In <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, for some reason, at Easter
they take <PERSON>Maximon</PERSON> out of his cupboard, stick a cigar in his mouth and revere
him.;    The most intriguing highland town is <LOCATION>Chichicastenango</LOCATION>, 25 miles north
of <LOCATION>Lake Atitlan</LOCATION>. The town is an ancient center of the Quiche (KEE-chay), who
are among the most traditional of today's Maya.;    The market is held every
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Rich in the superbly woven textiles for which the Maya
are famous, the market also displays cunning painted boxes, jade necklaces and
the lurid masks the <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION> use in their dances.;    From the highlands,
travelers can fly to the <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION>, in the northern lowlands, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s wild
west. There is only one paved road -- the main route to Tikal.;    The
countryside is seamed with rivers, and the outboard-powered dugout canoe is as
vital to commerce as the diesel truck.;    <PERSON>Flores</PERSON>, a tiny island town in <LOCATION>Lake
Peten Itza</LOCATION>, is worth a few days' stay.;    From there, you can hire a taxi for
the 40-mile trip to <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION>. Chichen Itza in the Yucatan, the most visited of
all Mayan cities, feels somehow tame, gardened and restored.;    But in <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION>,
deep in the tangled rain forest of the <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION>, a primal rawness lingers about
the ruins. A team of archaeologists from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> worked
for 13 years in <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>1970s.</DATE>;    They found more than 3,000
buildings spread over six square miles. Yet for all their labor, most of the
great city remains unexcavated.;    In <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION>, find your way to <LOCATION>El Mundo
Perdido</LOCATION>, the lost city, whose squat pyramids were built in the Pre-classic
era, long before anything else in <LOCATION>Tikal.</LOCATION>;    Or prowl through the <LOCATION>North
Acropolis</LOCATION> and locate the huge, grotesque molded heads hidden in dank side
chambers.;    Walk the <PERSON>Maler Causeway</PERSON> out to <ORGANIZATION>Group H</ORGANIZATION>, where the walls abound
in enigmatic Mayan graffiti. Climb to the roof comb of <ORGANIZATION>Temple IV</ORGANIZATION>, at 212 feet
the tallest building ever found in pre-Columbian <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, and see how, for all
its grandeur, <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION> is nearly swallowed by the jungle that stretches to the
far horizon.; If you go . . .; (check) Getting There; Several airlines,
including <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> and American, fly to <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>. From there, daily
flights go to Flores in the <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION>. These cannot be booked from the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> but are seldom sold out.;    (check) TOURS -- Several American travel
companies offer one- or two-week guided tours of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. One of the best is
run by <ORGANIZATION>Sobek Expeditions</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box <DATE>1089</DATE>, Angels Camp 95222;(800) 777-7939.
Other tour operators include Overseas Adventure Travel, (617) 876-0533; <PERSON>Tara
Tours</PERSON>, (800) 327-0080; and <ORGANIZATION>Festival Tours</ORGANIZATION>, (800) 327-2838. The <ORGANIZATION>Guatemalan
Tourist Information Office</ORGANIZATION> is (305) 358-5110.;    (check) RENTAL CARS -- The
best way to see the highlands is by rental car, but it is easier and
remarkably inexpensive (about <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a day or less) to hire a car and driver for
days at a time.;    (check) WHERE TO STAY -- The Hotel Atitlan in <LOCATION>Panajachel</LOCATION>,
with its secluded beach and splendid flower garden, may be the most delightful
inn in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. The Mayan Inn in <LOCATION>Chichicastenango</LOCATION> is a close rival. In
<PERSON>Flores</PERSON> there are a number of decent, cheap hotels (<MONEY>$15</MONEY>-<MONEY>$20</MONEY> per night). The
Jungle Inn at <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION> has clean rooms and a funky ambiance.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAVID ROBERTS, Special to the Mercury News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Guatemala City  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910210  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,352  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday February 10, 1991
00041234,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-15603</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJDAFAA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921003
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 OCT 92 / Travel: Mexico's Chichen Itza - 'Fantastico, no?' / In the
Yucatan, Nicholas Woodsworth tackles Mayan maths and astronomy and takes a
turn around the square in Merida
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NICHOLAS WOODSWORTH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
'Now this,' said <PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON> pointing, 'is called <ORGANIZATION>El Castillo</ORGANIZATION> in Spanish. It
means the castle. But it is not a castle. It is a highly accurate
multi-purpose calendar.'
WE TURNED in the direction he indicated, but saw neither a castle nor a
calendar. Instead, set in the middle of a vast grassy area where guided
tourist groups scurried to and fro, we saw a broad terraced pyramid rising
75ft into the air. Built of grey stone, it was the exact colour of the heavy
storm clouds that hung in the sky behind it.
On each of its four sides a steep flight of steps led up to a flat-topped
temple at its summit. Like ants on an antheap, the stairs and temple-top
were crawling with hundreds of figures dressed in bright red-and-yellow
nylon rain-jackets. Rain threatened.
Our own party was a large, mixed group - mostly German, Italian and Japanese
 -and few of us had an easy command of English. But this did not stop <PERSON>Senor
Gomez</PERSON> from delivering his guided commentary in a succession of rapid, jerky
bursts that left little time for reflection on what it all might mean. This,
after all, was a busy day at <ORGANIZATION>Chichen Itza</ORGANIZATION>, the most famous of the Yucatan's
Maya Indian ruins, and it looked as if the weather might break at any
minute.
'Now why do I say <PERSON>El Castillo</PERSON> is a multi-purpose calendar?'
A Japanese lady lifted a video camera to her eye and began filming him.
'Well, the Mayas were very interested in measuring time. There are 91 steps
on each of the four faces of the pyramid. That makes 364. Add one more for
the platform at the top and that makes 365, the exact number of days in one
year.' He beamed at us as if this explained it all. But there was more.
'Also, the staircases on each of the pyramid's nine levels show the 18
months of the Maya solar year, and the 52 panels on each side show the
52-year periods of the <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION> calendar cycle.' <PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON> was getting into
his stride.
'How did the Mayas combine their ritual calendar of 260 days and their solar
calendar of 365 days so the same calculations were possible on both? Easy -
they found a common divisor. Both numbers are divisible by five. By
multiplying five times 52 cycles of 365 days by 73 cycles of 260 days, they
obtained 18,980 days, or 52 years, permitting perfect computations within
the Maya 52-year calendar cycle.'
We stared at him, speechless.
'Fantastico, no?'
Senor Gomez glared around him, as if waiting to be challenged on the clarity
of his explanation. Nobody challenged him. The Japanese lady stopped
filming. 'Say again,' she said.
'No time,' shouted <PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON> over his shoulder as he strode off across the
grass, perspiring in the warm and muggy air. 'Now follow me to the <ORGANIZATION>Ball
Court</ORGANIZATION>. It is a very interesting game. Under Maya rules, the captain of the
team that won was sacrificed to the gods. It was a great honour. Funny, no?
Come. I have many, many things to show you.'
I had had enough and wandered off to climb <PERSON>El Castillo</PERSON>. A puffing 91 steps
later, I was standing on the top and looking out over the endless, dull
green, table-flat jungle of the Yucatan peninsula.
How odd that in the midst of this great expanse of nothing a people more
than 1,000 years ago should have built great cities. How much odder that
they developed a high theocratic culture with advanced mathematics and
astronomy at its pinnacle.
It was scarcely surprising, I thought, that in a tour lasting barely two
hours <PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON> found himself hard put to explain the complexities of
Mayan civilisation. Its subtle yet exacting combination of science and
spirituality has baffled trained minds ever since ruined cities began
re-emerging from the Yucatan jungles a century ago. Together, Mayan culture
and <PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON> had certainly baffled my mind.
But the complexities of pre-history have not stopped Yucatan from becoming
one of the most popular regions for visitors to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> today. Almost
everyone who comes to the peninsula that divides the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> from the <LOCATION>Gulf
of Mexico</LOCATION> is attracted by the lure of the ancient Mayas. They end up
enjoying it not just for the ruins of the Mayas of the past  - which tend to
be over-crowded, commercialised and difficult to understand - but for a
special atmosphere created by the Mayas of the present.
Rain began to splatter in heavy, warm drops. Straggling crowds streamed
through acres of monuments to seek shelter in refreshment stands and tour
coaches. On the way home to our hotels, a long, dreary drive through low
tropical bushland, the rain continued to fall in heavy sheets. By the time
we reached <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> <TIME>some two hours later</TIME>, water had flooded the narrow streets
of the town, stalled cars at intersections, and was lapping over the
sidewalks.
Unable to stir out, I spent the afternoon watching the rain fall onto the
lush vegetation of the inner courtyard garden of the <ORGANIZATION>Grande Hotel</ORGANIZATION>. A long,
cool drink at hand, I lay back in a rattan-woven planter's chair, the kind
in which colonials in every tropical outpost from <LOCATION>Calcutta</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Kumasi</LOCATION> have
taken their ease. Surrounded by pillastered columns, etched-glass windows,
tropical hardwood furniture and slowly-whirling fans, I felt like a Merida
sisal king.
In the mid-1850s, some 300 years after the Spanish conquistadors had
virtually enslaved the <LOCATION>Mayas</LOCATION>, Spanish landowners discovered sisal. Used for
making rope and matting, the fibre found a ready market in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. By the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>, the great plantation owners had made Merida a
gracious colonial city boasting more millionaires per capita than any other
in the world.
They sent their children to the best schools in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, imported treasures
from all over the world, and led the luxurious life of an aristocracy. To
the baroque cathedrals, governors' palaces and colonial plazas built by
earlier generations of Spaniards in <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION>, they added scores of
French-inspired mansions and the <PERSON>Paseo Montejo</PERSON> - a miniature Champs Elysees.
The boom in sisal is long over but <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION>'s traditions and independent
spirit, like its architecture, food, music and language, remain. For
centuries Yucatecans have lived isolated lives on their southern peninsula.
Cut off from the rest of the country by vast swamps and jungles, they have
always been a group apart, and proud of it.
And what of those Yucatecans who are descended from the builders of the
pyramids? Present-day <PERSON>Mayas</PERSON> - many of them remain pure-blooded - may have
lost political independence and the ability to calculate precise dates 90m
years in advance, but they remain gentle, intelligent, good-humoured people.
To anyone coming from other large Mexican cities where traditional machismo
is so much part of the culture, <ORGANIZATION>Merida</ORGANIZATION>'s 500,000 inhabitants seem an
unusually relaxed and friendly lot.
By the time darkness fell, the rain had stopped, the streets had dried, and
I was able to venture out for that favourite <ORGANIZATION>Merida</ORGANIZATION> past-time, the evening
paseo. Crowds of strollers had gathered on the Plaza Mayor, and <DATE>Christmas</DATE>,
only days away, had brought to the square a special atmosphere.
Trees, lamp-standards and statues were festooned with coloured lights and
paper. At wheeled streetside stalls, dark-haired women in embroidered
blouses were selling snacks of fried plantain, roasted corn and refreshing
glasses of sweet, almond-flavoured horchata. From long poles balanced on
their shoulders, ambulating hawkers sold children's toys: balloons, horns,
masks and flutes. Dressed in their holiday best, enormous families piled
into horse-drawn carriages for an idle tour of the town.
There was no lack of entertainment. Outside the door of the <ORGANIZATION>Grande Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, a
sidewalk marimba band was floating hot Latin rhythms out into the <TIME>night</TIME>. Up
the street in the cathedral, a choir was singing <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>'s Requiem. And on
the square itself, tiny children with dark, bright eyes were re-enacting the
<LOCATION>Nativity</LOCATION>. In 80'F heat, four-year-old Wise Men in silver paper crowns and
cotton-wool beards led a sad-looking Mexican donkey loaded with gifts to a
manger in a mock-up <LOCATION>Bethlehem</LOCATION>.
But I contented myself with just a turn or two around the square. I had work
to do. By my bedside table lay a complex tome by the learned Prof <PERSON>Demitrio
Morales</PERSON>. Its title: The <ORGANIZATION>Maya World</ORGANIZATION>. Tomorrow I would be visiting <LOCATION>Uxmal</LOCATION>,
another of the Yucatan's great archaeological sites. I was determined this
time, with the professor's help, not to be taken by surprise by a certain
<PERSON>Senor Gomez</PERSON>.
There are no direct flights between the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Nicholas Woodsworth</PERSON>
flew to Yucatan with <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> tel: 081-572-5555), which
flies via <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to the Yucatan resort city of <LOCATION>Cancun</LOCATION>. Car hire in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> is
expensive - about Dollars 80 a day - but many local companies organise tours
of Mayan archaeological sites.
The best time to visit Yucatan is between <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>April</DATE>, when rainfall
is at its lowest. Expect, nonetheless, a warm and humid tropical climate,
and take rainwear.
In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, information about travel in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> can be obtained from the
<ORGANIZATION>Mexican Tourist Office</ORGANIZATION> at 60 <ORGANIZATION>Trafalgar Square</ORGANIZATION>, WC2N 5DS. Tel: 071-734-1058.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page X
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06136179 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06136179 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: New York Times; Area dominated by Dos Pilas  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  GUATEMALA; HISTORY; FOUND  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Archaeologists digging in the jungle of Guatemala have found the tomb and
remains of an eighth-century ruler who they believe began the policies of
militarism and territorial expansion that eventually led to the collapse of
the classical Maya civilization.;    Dr. Arthur A. Demarest, an archaeologist
at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, announced Tuesday that the discovery
was made beneath the ruins of a pyramid at Dos Pilas, the ancient capital of
the Petexbatun region of Guatemala.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TEAM SAYS IT FOUND TOMB OF WARLIKE KING WHO
DESTROYED MAYAS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The tomb contained the skeleton of a man accompanied by a regal headdress
of jade, conch and pearl, obsidian blades probably used in bloodletting
ceremonies and ceramics inscribed with hieroglyphics.;    <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s burial site; 
Scholars at the site said they were almost certain that the skeleton is that
of Ruler 2, so called because the hieroglyphics giving his name have not been
deciphered. A monument at the pyramid indicates that this is the burial site
of that particular king, and the writing on pottery found inside the tomb is
expected to confirm the skeleton's identity.;    "It looks like we've got a
large dead king in there," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said in an interview by telephone from
Guatemala.;    The tomb's discovery, along with excavations of extensive
fortifications at <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION> and other evidence of relentless warfare, is
expected to figure in new interpretations of the <LOCATION>Mayas</LOCATION> as a more militaristic
people than had been thought by earlier scholars.;    It could also illuminate
the causes of the mysterious fall of lowland Mayan culture beginning in the
<DATE>eighth century</DATE> and culminating in the 10th.;    Militaristic past;  "This is
going to change the textbooks radically," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said. "Ruler 2 was a
pivotal figure in the initiation of the catastrophic sequence of events in
which the polity broke up into a dozen warring states that militarized the
landscape within a period of 50 years and may have destroyed the ecology of
the region.";    Ruler 2 reigned between 698 and 725 over the Petexbatun
region, which spanned some 2,000 square miles along the <LOCATION>Pasion River</LOCATION> in
northern <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>. Ruler 2 and his successor conquered neighboring
city-states and created the largest kingdom in Mayan history. The Mayas'
classic period began with the rise of large cities and elaborate ceremonial
centers around A.D. 250 and, in the south at least, collapsed by the year
900.;    Other archaeologists said this was one of the most significant recent
discoveries in Mayan studies. But many of them were not yet prepared to accept
<PERSON>Demarest</PERSON>'s interpretation that a rapid escalation of warfare and territorial
expansion doomed the Mayan civilization.;    Theory disputed;  <PERSON>Dr. Jeremy A.
Sabloff</PERSON>, an authority on Mayan archaeology at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pittsburgh</ORGANIZATION>,
called <ORGANIZATION>Demarest</ORGANIZATION>'s research "very important and exciting" but said he doubted
that a single factor, like destructive warfare, accounted for the fall of the
Mayan civilization.;    <PERSON>Dr. David Webster</PERSON>, an archaeologist at <ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania
State University</ORGANIZATION> who specializes in Mayan warfare, said the discovery "will
tell us a great deal about the dissolution of these kingdoms and about the
role of warfare in this dissolution.";    Excavations at <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>
said, focused attention on a major shift in scholarly attitudes toward the
Mayan culture. Until recent years, scholars tended to idealize the Mayas as
peaceful and industrious people. The only warfare was supposed to be the
limited, ritualized battles fought between rulers as part of dynastic
struggles, but rarely involving the common people.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910515  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  569  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 15, 1991
00136179,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891114-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-14-89 0207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-JungleCity Bjt   11-14 0663</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Jungle City, Bjt,0685</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruins Reveal Early Emergence of Mayan Civilization</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A jungle-shrouded city of pyramids and
temples in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> was built as long ago as 630 B.C., showing
that Mayan civilization blossomed about four centuries earlier than
believed, scientists say.
   The findings may make the ancient city of Nakbe in northern
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> one of the oldest in the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION>, researchers said.
   ``It's a very significant discovery,'' said <PERSON>Arthur Demarest</PERSON>,
anthropology chairman at <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>.
the findings by archaeologist <PERSON>Richard Hansen</PERSON> and colleagues at
<ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young University</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>University of
San Carlos</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We have substantial evidence that this is the earliest Maya
urban center ever found,'' <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said.
   BYU anthropology chairman <PERSON>Donald Forsyth</PERSON> added, ``We're now
going to have to push the beginning of Maya civilization back
further into the past.''
   Archaeologists once believed advanced Mayan civilization emerged
around A.D. 300 and ended 600 years later during what is described
as the ``classic period.'' Research conducted during 1978-83 at <LOCATION>El
Mirador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, pushed that date back to 200 B.C.
   But in excavating <LOCATION>Nakbe</LOCATION>, 350 miles north of <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION> and
not far from <LOCATION>El Mirador</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON>'s 50-member team determined that
roughly 100 stone pyramids and other buildings were from about 630
B.C. to 400 <ORGANIZATION>B.C</ORGANIZATION>. So were some of the site's 65,000 pottery pieces,
sculptures, figurines and other artifacts.
   Dates can be determined by the radioactivity of carbon in
organic material associated with buildings. Pottery is dated by
comparison with the style of shards from elsewhere in <LOCATION>Central
America</LOCATION>.
   ``We have from <DATE>1000</DATE> B.C. to 600 B.C. a small village with wooden
buildings,'' <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said by telephone from his home in <LOCATION>Rupert</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>. ``Then all of a sudden _ boom! They brought in rock and fill
and buried the village and made platforms. On those they placed
their buildings.''
   <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION>'s buildings include 35- to 150-foot-tall
platforms and flat-topped pyramids, many of which are topped by
three small temples and sculpture depicting important gods and
kings. The buildings are solid, without interior rooms.
   The scale of construction reflects the emergence of an
administrative and religious elite to command thousands of workers,
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said.
   Anthropologist <PERSON>John Graham</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, said an even earlier center of advanced Mayan
civilization may be found.
   Still, <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> said, the <PERSON>Nabke</PERSON> study ``is part of the most
exciting Maya discovery of recent decades.''
   The discovery solves a puzzle for archaeologists: The Mayans
seemed to evolve more slowly from farming communities to cities
than other pre-Columbian civilizations to the north and south. But
archaeologists say <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION> proves that Mayan development occurred
more or less in step with the rise of the Olmec culture in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>,
thought to be the oldest civilization of the Americas.
   An archaeologist mapped some of <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION>'s architecture in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
Hansen first visited in <DATE>1987</DATE> and his team conducted the first
full-scale excavation <DATE>last February</DATE> through <DATE>April</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON>'s team hacked their way through dense jungle for three
days and 40 miles to reach Nakbe from the nearest road. They hauled
water from a swamp 4 miles away. Demarest admiringly called it
``macho archaeology.''
   Among the most important finds at <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION> is a sculpture on a
limestone slab that probably dates from about 400 <ORGANIZATION>B.C.</ORGANIZATION> and is about
10 feet tall, 4 feet wide and 18 inches thick.
   The sculpture of two royal figures and a god ``is the earliest
and largest preclassic sculpture ever found,'' <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said.
   Other discoveries include seashells and obsidian glass tools
that indicate emergence of long-distance trade. There also are
signs of a society taming its environment: gutter-like water
collection systems on six buildings and 60-foot-wide stone-and-mud
roads, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said.
   He said he believes transformation from village to city happened
because trade and the need for water and transportation fostered
emergence of an administrative and religious elite, which then
ordered construction of temples.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-11380</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CDYAPADFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920425
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 APR 92 / Books: The losers' champion
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By VICTORIA SCHOFIELD
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
STOLEN CONTINENTS: THE INDIAN STORY by <PERSON>Roland Wright John Murray</PERSON> Pounds
19.95, 424 pages
'FOR FIVE centuries,' writes <PERSON>Roland Wright</PERSON>, 'we have listened only to the
history of the winners.' Stolen Continents redresses the balance by
portraying the European 'discovery' of the continents of <LOCATION>North and South
America</LOCATION> from a 'native' perspective.
In selecting the <ORGANIZATION>Aztecs, Mayas</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Incas</LOCATION>, Iroquois and <ORGANIZATION>Cherokee</ORGANIZATION>, he has focused
on the most complex societies for whom the greatest source material is
available. 'The five I have chosen must therefore stand for the many who
will never tell their stories because they are extinct. The silence of the
<LOCATION>Caribbean Taino</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Newfoundland Beothuk</LOCATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Ona of Tierra del Fuego</ORGANIZATION>
is the most terrible eloquence of all.'
Wright portrays the history of these five groupings during three phases:
invasion, resistance, rebirth. The book is timely, not just because this
year marks the 500th anniversary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s first voyage across the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, but because <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> follows the story through to the vociferous
nationalism of today.
His account is passionate and moving. Through reconstruction of wide-ranging
primary sources the reader can relive the agonies of the original
inhabitants at the hands of the invaders. But whereas we may be accustomed
to the devrecounted in the sixteenth-century Florentine Code, the continued
persecution of the indigenous population comes as a surprise. The memoirs of
the Guatemalan Mayan activist <PERSON>Rigoberta Menchu</PERSON>, written in <DATE>1982</DATE>, are so
horrific that <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> admits some people may not believe that such horrors
really happened.
Wright sees the superior European attitude towards the 'primitive' natives
as almost laughable were the consequences not so tragic. The 'Requirement'
read by the sixteenth-century Spaniards to the local people at each
encounter demanded they submit to God, the Pope and the Church. 'And if you
do not do this . . . with the help of God I shall come mightily against you,
and I shall make war on you everywhere . . . and I shall do all the evil and
damage to you that I am able. And insist that the deaths and destruction
that result from this will be your fault.' This 'shabby document', as <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>
points out, was a symbolic necessity to justify outright plunder. The
Indians understood neither its meaning nor its intent.
Apologists for the European 'invasion' rightly point out that what decimated
the local people was not so much warfare but European diseases. But <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>
stresses the consequences of Lord <PERSON>Jeffrey Amherst</PERSON>'s command against the
Iroquois in <DATE>1762</DATE>. 'Infect the Indians with sheets upon which smallpox
patients have been lying or by any other means which may serve to
exterminate this accursed race.' The epidemic raged all <DATE>summer</DATE>, says <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>.
'One by one the leaders who survived it were compelled to sue for peace.'
Whether he is talking about the <LOCATION>Incas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Aztecs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mayas</LOCATION>, of <LOCATION>South</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION>, or the Cherokee and Iroquois of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, the 'Indian
story' is a tawdry one of misunderstanding and betrayal. Time and again the
new arrivals in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> reneged on their treaty obligations with the
original inhabitants who had once made them welcome.
There never was any expectation that the 'white' and 'Indian' cultures might
coexist. Thousands of books of Mayan hieroglyphs were destroyed because the
Spaniards could not understand them. When finally the remaining few were
deciphered, they revealed advanced astronomical information. In their
attempt to eradicate the Inca culture, the Spaniards banned Ouecha song,
music and theatre. Even well-meant reforms backfired.
Although the title of the book indicates that the continents of North and
<LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> have been 'stolen' from their pre-Columbian inhabitants, the
reader is left in no doubt that 500 years later the 'theft' is still being
contested by those who have not lost sight of their ancient culture or
language. 'If <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> really had majority rule, it would be a Maya
republic,' says <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>. In the Andes 12m people speak the Inca language.
There are more Iroquois living in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> than there have been for
three and a half centuries. And the eastern Cherokees have managed to remain
in the <LOCATION>Great Smoky</LOCATION> mountains where they lived in pre-Columbian times.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XX
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082490-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 266512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 24, 1990, Friday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 4; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
764 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AT THE GALLERIES: GHOST OF FRIDA KAHLO HAUNTS SHOW 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEAH OLLMAN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TIJUANA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In <DATE>1988</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>La Jolla</ORGANIZATION>'s Iturralde Gallery (then La Casa del Arte) showed a series 
of lithographs by <ORGANIZATION>Lucia Maya</ORGANIZATION> that were inspired by the extraordinarily prolific 
and passionate life of Mexican artist <PERSON>Frida Kahlo</PERSON>. Maya's affinity for <PERSON>Kahlo</PERSON>'s 
precise, naturalistic style of rendering and her symbolic, surreal imagery made 
the series as much a dialogue between kindred spirits as a homage to a 
legendary life. 
</P>
<P>
This month, an extensive selection of <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s paintings, prints and drawings can 
be seen at the <ORGANIZATION>Centro Cultural Tijuana</ORGANIZATION> in a show titled "Umbral de las 
Transfiguraciones" (Threshold of Transfigurations). Though <PERSON>Kahlo</PERSON>'s striking 
visage is nowhere to be found here, her pointed, poignant approach is present 
throughout. 
</P>
<P>
Maya, who was born on <LOCATION>Catalina Island</LOCATION> and now lives in <LOCATION>Guadalajara</LOCATION>, never 
musters the same blend of toughness and vulnerability that makes <PERSON>Kahlo</PERSON>'s work 
so singularly intriguing. Her intent, though, differs substantially. The mood 
she consistently creates is less intimate and revealing than <PERSON>Kahlo</PERSON>'s and, 
instead, feels like a melange of received styles: saccharine sweetness, Gothic 
horror and surreal poetry. 
</P>
<P>
Maya's debt to the heritage of surrealism runs the deepest, especially in her 
use of familiar forms such as the human heart, in disjunctive, startling 
contexts. The heart appears throughout her work -- as vital organ, container of 
the 
</P>
<P>
soul, the spirit, and source of emotion. 
</P>
<P>
In the drawing, "Epifania de la Tierra" (Epiphany of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>), hearts sprout 
from the soil like saplings yearning for the sun. On the horizon of this 
fertile field, uprooted trees soar into a sky charged with unrest. In the 
foreground, a young woman unearths one of the hearts to find a child's pair of 
legs attached. Her wide-eyed innocence mirrors our own before this bizarre 
vision of birth and tempestuous demise. 
</P>
<P>
Maya makes an analogy between the heart's arteries and a tree's branches in 
several images, part of a larger expression of her view of the affinity between 
human and organic realms. Two large, dynamic drawings of trees double as 
portraits of twisting torsos, rooted to the ground but with branches/arms 
reaching upward, striving for a higher reality. In "Madre Corazon" (Heart 
Mother), one of three delicate drawings on the theme of maternal, life-giving 
power, Maya substitutes a heart and healthy foliage for a woman's head and 
shoulders. 
</P>
<P>
The most profound use of the image of the heart appears in the painting, 
"Exodo" (Exodus), one of the quietest but most moving works in the show. A 
gray-haired man stands against a screen of tall, mist-enshrouded trees, his 
pale hazel eyes staring wistfully ahead. Beneath his arm he carries a small 
house, with a roof resembling a human heart and walls frayed into a web of 
ungrounded roots. A small patch of earth near him is stained red, indicating, 
perhaps, the site of the unrooting. "Exodo" illustrates in simple terms the 
adage that home is where the heart is, while also conveying a more complex and 
powerful portrait of loss, separation and exile. 
</P>
<P>
Maya layers seemingly incongruous emotional and physical states throughout her 
work, evoking images both provocative and unsettling. Often she wraps her 
female figures in white, cocoon-like shrouds, linking them to both nascent and 
decaying states. They lie immobile, in a permanent dream state, the favorite 
realm of the founders of surrealism. 
</P>
<P>
Death and life shadow each other closely here, two facets of the same evolving 
entity called existence. Their transfiguration from one into the other is 
rendered seamless in the painting, "Concepcion Inmaculada" (Immaculate 
Conception), where an auburn-maned woman and a similarly coiffed skeleton share 
a single white, billowing smock, bloated by the figure's pregnancy. The cycle 
of birth and death becomes truly circular here, part of a continuum played out 
at once by a single individual. 
</P>
<P>
Much of <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s work is, indeed, rich with poetic possibilities, but much is 
also mired in a stiff sentimentality. Her languorous sirens and brooding lovers 
drip with melodrama, cheap and over-acted, and her tight, linear drawing style 
sometimes stiffens and becomes static and lifeless. Underlying all of her work, 
however, is the potent realization that life and death, love and loss, the 
human and the organic all nurture each other while deepening each others' 
mysteries. 
</P>
<P>
Lucia Maya's work can be seen at the <ORGANIZATION>Centro Cultural Tijuana</ORGANIZATION> (on Paseo de los 
Heroes) through <DATE>Aug. 31</DATE>. Also on view in a separate show, through <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>, is a 
strong selection of prints on the theme of the Mexican revolution. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mexican artist Lucia Maya's 1987 drawing "Madre Corazon." ; Photo, 
"Exodo" (Exodus), is a quiet, but moving work in Maya's show. BRUCE K. HUFF / 
Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Art Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111489-0064 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134434 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 14, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1332 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NEW-FOUND SITE IN JUNGLE MAY BE FIRST MAYAN CITY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THOMAS H. MAUGH II, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> archeologist has identified what is apparently the earliest major center 
of Mayan civilization yet found, a discovery that extends the era of Mayan 
cities back four centuries into a period that was thought to be dominated by 
simple village life. 
</P>
<P>
The extensive stone monuments and temples in the newly discovered city of 
<ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION>, in the dense tropical forest of northern <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, show "that the 
advances which created the most sophisticated pre-Columbian society in the <LOCATION>New 
World</LOCATION> may have occurred much earlier than was previously assumed," said <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<PERSON>Richard Hansen</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The discovery will shed new light on why the Maya "accomplished things no other 
tropical forest society accomplished in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The excavations at <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION>, announced <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, are "of extraordinary 
importance to our understanding of the origin of Mayan civilization," said 
anthropologist <PERSON>David Friedel</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Southern Methodist University</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The new findings follow on the heels of surprising reports this <DATE>summer</DATE> by 
anthropologist <PERSON>Arthur Demarest</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION> that the Mayan society 
-- previously believed to be one of history's most peaceful civilizations -- 
collapsed in the <ORGANIZATION>9th Century</ORGANIZATION> AD as the result of internecine warfare. 
</P>
<P>
These new discoveries from the beginning and end of Mayan civilization, <PERSON>Friedel</PERSON> 
added, are "revealing with breathtaking clarity not only their (the Maya's) 
vision of the world, but the breadth and complexity of their political 
organization." 
</P>
<P>
The new find dates from a period when the <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION> were transforming themselves 
from a centuries-old rural agrarian society to a more sophisticated and complex 
urban society. Researchers are particularly interested in the factors that led 
to this transformation because it sheds light on the more general question of 
how societies are formed. 
</P>
<P>
Although they are not yet sure, the researchers believe that urbanization arose 
as a mechanism to counter the innate hostility of the environment, to promote 
trade, and to consolidate religious and political ideologies. 
</P>
<P>
Nakbe lies in the isolated central department (state) of <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, 
about 350 miles from <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION>. The site was first identified as a 
potential location of advanced Mayan civilization in <DATE>1930</DATE> by archeologists 
performing an aerial survey of the region. But no significant work occurred at 
the site until the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> team carried out its excavations from <DATE>February</DATE> through 
<DATE>April</DATE> of this year. 
</P>
<P>
That delay arose primarily as a result of the site's isolation. Nakbe "is three 
days on foot from the nearest road," <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said. "We used 123 mules to 
transport our stuff in, then kept 14 mules hauling water and supplies for the 
three months we were there. They had to cross swamps and wade through muck up 
to their bellies. It's hard to appreciate the problem if you haven't been 
through it." 
</P>
<P>
But he noted that the isolation probably protected the site from looting. 
</P>
<P>
Their excavations revealed thousands of artifacts, tombs and temple structures, 
some ranging from 40 to 65 feet in height. Other buildings on the site, which 
have not yet been excavated, are estimated to be as tall as 150 feet, which 
would rival pyramids from the more modern Mayan city of <LOCATION>Tikal</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The excavated buildings date from 600 to 400 BC, in the so-called middle 
Pre-Classic period. Previously, the most advanced structures from this period 
to be discovered were crude villages with low stone platforms measuring from 
three to six feet tall. <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> has not yet dated the taller pyramids. 
</P>
<P>
The researchers also dug up more than 65,000 potsherds, ceramics, human and 
animal figurines, seashells and obsidian and stone tools, which should reveal 
many details about everyday life in this first Mayan city. 
</P>
<P>
They also found an artifact that may prove to be one of the most significant 
Mayan sculptures ever discovered, a 10-foot-high fragmented slab of intricately 
carved limestone erected by Pre-Classic Mayan rulers. It depicts two 
individuals in royal clothing facing each other. One has his hand extended, 
pointing to a deity between them. <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> believes the stone slab commemorates 
an important historical event whose nature he plans to discuss in a forthcoming 
publication. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> and his colleagues also found the remnants of an even earlier village 
below <LOCATION>Nakbe</LOCATION>, filled with soil and rubble. 
</P>
<P>
"The construction appears to have preserved the village below," <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said in 
a telephone interview from his home in <LOCATION>Rupert</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ida</LOCATION>. "It's almost like finding a 
Mayan version of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>," the Neapolitan city preserved intact when it was 
buried by an eruption of <ORGANIZATION>Mt. Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The construction of <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION> must have been an enormous task, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said. "All of 
the building materials had to be hauled to the location, rock by rock and 
basket by basket, by hundreds of Mayan workers to construct the massive 
platforms and buildings." 
</P>
<P>
Even drinking water was a problem. During their excavations, the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> team 
members had to haul water nearly four miles to the site on mules. "The Maya 
didn't have mules or beasts of burden to do that with," <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said. That lack 
led them to develop systems to collect rainwater from the roofs of temples and 
other buildings and channel it into storage facilities. 
</P>
<P>
Another problem that must have impeded construction, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said, is that the 
city was surrounded by swamps. "In order to maintain local trade and exchange, 
they had to construct causeways . . . large, rubble-filled constructions up to 
two yards high and 20 yards wide," he said. 
</P>
<P>
That construction would have allowed them access to neighboring farmlands and 
would have consolidated political authority. 
</P>
<P>
The Maya were unique, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said, because "they were able to achieve the 
greatest level of sophistication in the face of a very hostile environment." 
What researchers are trying to determine, he added, "is why they became 
sophisticated all of a sudden." 
</P>
<P>
The very hostility of the environment may have been a major civilizing 
influence, <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> speculated. "It was so difficult to live there that it 
required centralized authority to maintain logistics and the life style they 
desired." 
</P>
<P>
Another clue to the civilizing influences was the large amount of seashells and 
obsidian discovered at <LOCATION>Nakbe</LOCATION>, all of which had to be imported from elsewhere. 
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> and others speculate that centralized authority was established in part 
to carry out such imports in exchange for a variety of goods, including food, 
chocolate, cotton textiles, forest products, medicines and jaguar pelts. 
</P>
<P>
"Seashells are very important to Maya public ceremonial life," said <ORGANIZATION>SMU</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<PERSON>Friedel</PERSON>. "Great conch shells were used to fashion trumpets that were blown to 
declare the presence of the gods. Small shells were used as little bells and 
tinklers sewn onto the clothes of the elite for public ceremonies." Eventually 
the shells were also used as a form of money. 
</P>
<P>
Obsidian, he added, "was highly prized for ritual bloodletting and was a sacred 
material for all the people of meso-America." 
</P>
<P>
"Another factor, which we are hot on the trail of, is the role of religious 
ideology as an impetus in developing huge cities," <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> said. The early 
leaders "had a huge control of labor to build these enormous buildings, and it 
appears from our excavations that the sole purpose was ideological. It's not 
funerary; we don't find burials like in later periods." 
</P>
<P>
The buildings did not necessarily serve as churches either, he said. "I'm more 
inclined to think that these buildings were constructed with the idea of 
consolidating the authority of an emerging elite and tying that into religious 
theology. That fits very well with what we know of later Maya mythology, where 
the king became divine and had divine ancestry." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> speculates that it was sometime during the era of <ORGANIZATION>Nakbe</ORGANIZATION>'s construction 
that the authority of kings stopped being earned by achievement and started 
being passed down from fathers to sons. 
</P>
<P>
But solving these riddles, he said, "will take years and years of 
investigation." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Artist's drawing shows the layout of major buildings in ancient Mayan 
city of Nakbe, which scientists have dated from 600 to 400 BC. Associated 
Press; Photo, Encroaching jungle growth obscures a 45-foot pyramid and its 
stone stairway in the ruins at Nakbe, apparently the first Mayan city. UCLA; 
Map, Nakbe, Guatemala. Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ARCHEOLOGY -- GUATEMALA; MAYAS; NABKE (GUATEMALA); HISTORIC SITES; HANSEN, 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ElephantEuthanized     12-24 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Elephant Euthanized,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Matriarch of San Diego Zoo Elephant Herd Euthanized After Accident</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 51-year-old elephant at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> had
to be killed because of injuries she suffered after falling
headfirst into a concrete moat, officials said.
   Maya, an Asian elephant who was the oldest mammal at the zoo,
apparently suffered torn ligaments in her legs <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as she tried
to climb out of the moat surrounding her enclosure, said zoo
spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON>.
   Veterinarians resorted to a fatal dose of sedative when Maya was
unable to stand on her own following a treatment of fluids,
painkillers and steroids.
   ``I counted 27 people there trying to help,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
``When she would try to rock and stand up, there was a lot of
calling and urging to her.''
   Elephants cannot convalesce while sitting or lying down because
their weight exerts life-threatening pressure on their lungs,
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said 51 is fairly elderly for an elephant, but they have
been known to live into their 60s in captivity.
   Maya, who was captured in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and brought to the zoo <DATE>Nov. 8,
1941</DATE>, was bumped into the moat by another elephant. Two nearby
keepers didn't see the <DATE>fall</DATE> but heard the commotion.
   The 7,100-pound elephant was walking without difficulty in the
moat, but she apparently crippled herself while trying to climb out
on bales of hay that zookeepers set up like steps, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said.
   Maya then was fitted with a harness and lifted by crane into a
sitting position. But it was evident when workers tried to get her
to stand that her legs wouldn't support her, and she was then put
to death.
   Elephants have been knocked into the moat before without
suffering serious injury, but <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Maya</PERSON>'s age may have made
her accident worse. Tests after her death showed she suffered from
degenerative arthritis in her legs.
   He described her as a generally calm, easygoing creature, but
one who often would assert herself to show she still led the herd.
   ``There's some concern over how the remaining four elephants
will react,'' <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. ``They'll notice she's gone and I'm sure
it will be upsetting to them.''
   After the accident, the zoo's <LOCATION>Elephant Mesa</LOCATION> was closed to the
public for the rest of the day.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081489-0062 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 94612 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 14, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
<P>
Correction Appended 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1568 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
MAYAS' DEMISE: A WAR WITHIN?; 
</P>
<P>
SITE REVEALS HEAVY FORTIFICATIONS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THOMAS H. MAUGH II, Times Science Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The mystery of the Maya demise has haunted anthropologists for centuries, but 
researchers may be on the verge of solving the sudden disappearance of one of 
history's most advanced civilizations. 
</P>
<P>
The Maya were "the most sophisticated, literate, complex people in the <LOCATION>New 
World</LOCATION>," according to anthropologist <PERSON>Arthur Demarest</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION>. 
They erected massive pyramids, created a highly accurate calendar, perfected 
the art of astronomical observation, produced beautiful multicolored pottery 
and intricately carved stone monuments and established widespread trade routes. 
</P>
<P>
But after flourishing throughout much of <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> from the 3rd to the 
<DATE>8th Century</DATE>, they all but disappeared in the <ORGANIZATION>9th Century</ORGANIZATION>, dispersing into small 
villages and seemingly losing most of their talents. 
</P>
<P>
Historians and archeologists have long pondered the reasons for this downfall, 
arguing at different times that losses of trade routes, changes in climate, 
endemic disease and many other related factors contributed to their downfall. 
In the past, most of the theories shared the premise that the Mayas were 
largely a peace-loving people who engaged in limited warfare only for 
ritualistic purposes and who met their demise through little fault of their 
own. 
</P>
<P>
But new discoveries made this <DATE>summer</DATE> in the lowlands of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> by a team 
headed by <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> present a sharply different picture of the end of the Maya 
era. Demarest has discovered a heavily fortified Mayan city, called <ORGANIZATION>Punta de 
Chimino</ORGANIZATION>, that is "more massive than a medieval castle" in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In the nearby city of <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION>, he has found hastily erected stoneworks that 
suggest that the city was under heavy siege. These new discoveries, combined 
with previous excavations in the area, indicate that, at the height of the 
Mayan hegemony, the Mayan people were involved in ferocious internecine warfare 
that sapped their vitality and tore apart the fabric of their civilization. 
</P>
<P>
The researchers have few clues yet about what caused the sudden escalation of 
warfare that brought about the end of Mayan civilization -- although some 
evidence suggests the haunting possibility that it was triggered by 
over-exploitation of the environment, deterioration of the soil and pressure on 
food resources. 
</P>
<P>
But even though they do not know why the warfare started, the scientists 
believe they know who started it. Stelae (stone pillars with intricate 
carvings) from <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION> identify a leader, known only as Ruler 2 because 
archeologists have not had time to translate his name, "who appears to be one 
of the kings from the beginning of the <ORGANIZATION>8th Century</ORGANIZATION> who embarked on a program of 
territorial conquest," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Based on many recent discoveries of evidence of warfare, especially this 
<DATE>summer</DATE>'s, <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> has concluded that, for a period of perhaps 50 to 60 years 
beginning about AD 825, warfare spread like a contagion throughout the region. 
Eventually, the economic system collapsed under the weight of the strain 
imposed by the intense combat and defensive measures and individual states 
within the area fell "like dominoes." 
</P>
<P>
By far the most important discovery made this <DATE>summer</DATE> is the <ORGANIZATION>Punta de Chimino</ORGANIZATION> 
site, which sits on a peninsula that juts into <PERSON>Lake Petexbatun</PERSON> in northwestern 
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, four days' journey from <LOCATION>Guatemala City</LOCATION> by plane, Jeep, canoe and 
mule. Researchers had known that a village existed on the site but had not 
explored it. 
</P>
<P>
"We went there to do a survey for a week," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said by telephone from 
<LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, where he has been recuperating from pneumonia and the 
parasitic diseases that are the bane of archeologists. The 36-year-old <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> 
is the leader of a team of several American and Guatemalan archeologists, a 
dozen <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt</ORGANIZATION> graduate students and 50 Guatemalan workers that has been 
granted an exclusive permit by the Guatemalan government to dig up hundreds of 
square miles of the Mayan heartland in the <LOCATION>Peten</LOCATION> jungle. The <MONEY>$1-million</MONEY> project 
is funded by the <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>H. F. Guggenheim Peace 
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and the largest archeological grant ever awarded by the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Humanities. 
</P>
<P>
Punta de Chimino "was not a very important component of our work," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> 
said. But what they found there made them change their plans instantly. 
</P>
<P>
The Mayas who lived in <LOCATION>Punta</LOCATION> de Chimino excavated a massive ditch, 450 feet 
long and 50 feet deep, that cut the city off from the mainland, making it 
completely surrounded by water. In excavating the ditch through bedrock, 
<PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said, the <LOCATION>Mayas</LOCATION> moved three times as much rock and stone as had been 
used to construct the city itself. "It's as if the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> were spending 
<PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of its budget on defense," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Punta de Chimino</ORGANIZATION> also had walls around its sides to protect it from attacks by 
canoes, and protected portages through which food could be brought in during a 
siege. "One of the reasons people have used to argue that Mayans were not 
warlike was the fact that their centers were completely indefensible," he said. 
"This is the exact opposite of that." 
</P>
<P>
Inside the walls of <ORGANIZATION>Punta de Chimino</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> found "a kind of shrunken Mayan 
state. It has all the characteristics of a Mayan ceremonial center, but on a 
smaller scale." Included were a single ball court (the Mayas played a sort of 
hybrid between soccer and basketball with great intensity; losers were 
sometimes sacrificed), one temple, one funerary, one set of stairways with 
hieroglyphics, and so on. 
</P>
<P>
The fortress also had a large open area within the innermost wall that could 
have been used as a refuge for the population from the mainland. 
</P>
<P>
"It would have been almost impossible to take the place. It was really 
impregnable," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said. "Those are terms you don't normally use in 
discussing Mayan architecture." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Punta de Chimino</ORGANIZATION> is "probably one of the few sites where the stereotype of 
archeology is accurate," he said. "It's like <PERSON>Indiana Jones</PERSON> and the Temple of 
Doom." 
</P>
<P>
At nearby <PERSON>Dos Pilas</PERSON>, evidence of a different kind also suggests a sudden 
intensification of warfare. Dos Pilas is the classic, indefensible Mayan city, 
in the middle of the jungle with ready access from all sides. But sometime 
toward the end of the <ORGANIZATION>8th Century</ORGANIZATION>, the inhabitants of Dos Pilas erected two 
concentric rings of walls around the center of the city, defacing monuments and 
burying important artifacts in their haste. 
</P>
<P>
Debris recovered from inside the walls indicates that large numbers of people 
inhabited the area at least briefly, suggesting that the city was under siege. 
When and how it fell, however, is still a mystery. 
</P>
<P>
But before it did, Ruler 2 apparently conquered a number of smaller fortresses. 
</P>
<P>
Demarest and his colleagues also discovered, but have only tentatively 
explored, an extensive series of caves near <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION> that have not been 
entered by humans for more than 1,000 years. He believes that the caves may 
also have been used as a place of refuge during a siege. 
</P>
<P>
In one of the caves, they discovered ritual offerings of broken pots and flint 
knives, as well as the mummified remains of a boy who had been sacrificed and 
painted with red ocher. Exploring the unexpected caves "was one of the first 
times I've found myself irrationally exhilarated," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Demarest's discoveries are so recent that few of his colleagues, aside from 
those on the expedition itself, are aware of them. One who has been informed is 
anthropologist <PERSON>Richard E. W. Adams</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, 
who thinks <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON>'s discoveries are "swell stuff." 
</P>
<P>
The new discoveries, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> said, "go a long way toward documenting in detail 
this whole business of warfare as an element in the collapse of the Mayan 
civilization." 
</P>
<P>
Archeologists' picture of the Mayan civilization has been gradually changing 
over the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>. Historians of Mayan art, in particular, had begun to 
paint a picture of a more warlike population than had been previously believed. 
</P>
<P>
Mayan hieroglyphics show repeated images of warriors clad in jaguar pelts or 
bird-like costumes, bearing woven shields and lances, capturing the noble elite 
of nearby tribes and bringing them back to their own temples for ritualistic 
bloodletting, removal of their hearts and decapitation. 
</P>
<P>
But this war was sharply circumscribed. Mayan art shows no instances of cities 
under siege, temples ransacked, or any of the other depredations of large-scale 
conflict. Instead, the fighting seems to be representative more of a rite of 
passage for prestige than an actual combat for resources or plunder. 
</P>
<P>
But about AD 825, <PERSON>Adams</PERSON> said, "something went terribly wrong" and kings like 
Ruler 2 began actual conquest of nearby cities and settlements. By the middle 
of that century, <LOCATION>Dos Pilas</LOCATION> had extended its hegemony to cover an area of nearly 
690 square miles -- a huge amount of land in comparison to the areas controlled 
by other Mayan cities -- before it ultimately collapsed. 
</P>
<P>
"But if one group changes the rules (of warfare), other groups have to adopt 
the new rules and you get a kind of arms race," <PERSON>Demarest</PERSON> said. "Intensification 
of warfare spreads by contagion, and the ultimate result can be regional 
devastation. In this case, the Dos Pilas hegemony broke up into heavily 
fortified sites, small independent states warring rather savagely with each 
other. It may not be the principal cause of the collapse of the Mayan 
civilization, but it is certainly a principal cause." 
</P></TEXT>
<CORRECTION-DATE>
<P>
August 18, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</CORRECTION-DATE>
<CORRECTION>
<P>
FOR THE RECORD 
</P>
<P>
Photo Credit -- A photo credit on the Aug. 14 Science / Medicine page was 
incorrect. The photo of a Maya hieroglyph was taken from the book "The Blood of 
Kings" by Linda Schele and Mary Ellen Miller. 
</P>
</CORRECTION>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Hieroglyph showing Maya king preparing for battle. About AD 825, 
'something went terribly wrong.' From 'The Blood of Kings'by LINDA SCHELE and 
LARRY MILLER; Map, GUATEMALA, Punta de Chimino, PATRICIA MITCHELL / Los Angeles 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DEMAREST, ARTHUR; MAYAS; ARCHEOLOGY -- GUATEMALA; ANTHROPOLOGY -- GUATEMALA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060190-0092 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 227354 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 1, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
779 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TERROR IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD; 
</P>
<P>
SLAYING: RESIDENTS OF ARBUTUS STREET IN HUNTINGTON PARK HAD CONSIDERED 
THEMSELVES SOMEHOW IMMUNE TO A SURGE IN MURDERS IN THE SURROUNDING COMMUNITY. 
BUT NO LONGER. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LOUIS SAHAGUN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Teresa Soria</PERSON> was taking out the trash <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> when a little boy 
wearing blue pajamas ran across the street with tears in his eyes begging for 
help. 
</P>
<P>
"My mother is laying on the floor," the boy said, trembling. "There is blood 
all over." 
</P>
<P>
Soria sent him to another neighbor who, after peering into the living room of 
the home in the <DATE>6700</DATE> block of Arbutus Street in <LOCATION>Huntington Park</LOCATION>, gathered up 
the 8-year-old boy, and his younger brother and sister, and called police. 
Officers arrived to discover the brutal murder of <PERSON>Bertha Gomez</PERSON>, 31, who was 
shot while her children slept. 
</P>
<P>
The crime has brought terror to the tidy neighborhood of Spanish-style homes, 
whose residents had considered themselves somehow immune to a surge in murders 
in the surrounding community. 
</P>
<P>
In a town that has but four homicide detectives, it has also stretched the 
resources of a 60-member police force already overwhelmed with an alarming 
number of mostly gang- and drug-related violent crimes -- including 27 drive-by 
shootings since <DATE>January</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The number of serious crimes, including murder, rape and auto theft, has risen 
from 3,406 incidents in <DATE>1985</DATE> to 4,968 in <DATE>1989</DATE> -- an increase of <PERCENT>31.5%</PERCENT>, police 
spokesman <PERSON>Tom Weselis</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We've had nine homicides in five months, compared with 12 all last year," he 
said. "Our guys are busier than hell, running nonstop from crime to crime to 
crime." 
</P>
<P>
Similarly, patrol officers have been working 65-hour weeks in an effort to keep 
up with an increase in calls for assistance in the three-square-mile city of 
70,000 people. 
</P>
<P>
"My phones are ringing all the time from people wanting to organize 
Neighborhood Watch programs, because they don't want to be the next victim," 
<PERSON>Weselis</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Police and city officials blame the problem on the fact that the <ORGANIZATION>Police 
Department</ORGANIZATION> has not expanded along with the population over the last five years. 
</P>
<P>
In an effort to beef up the force, the city plans to use more than <MONEY>a million 
dollars</MONEY> in cash seized in local drug busts to hire five new officers. "Five is 
not enough, but it will help," <PERSON>Weselis</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The latest murder followed a double homicide on <DATE>Feb. 27</DATE>, in which two robbers 
broke into a <LOCATION>Huntington Park</LOCATION> condominium and terrorized six members of a family 
for hours before killing a pregnant woman and her 8-month-old fetus. Two 
suspects were arrested in late <DATE>March</DATE> after two investigators put in a total of 
260 hours tracking leads and evaluating evidence, including fingerprints lifted 
at the crime scene. 
</P>
<P>
In the <PERSON>Gomez</PERSON> case, investigators also "have lots of leads" and believe that the 
woman may have been killed by members of an "auto insurance fraud ring" that 
she knew, Detective <PERSON>Steve Hess</PERSON> said. He declined to elaborate on the possible 
motivation for the slaying. 
</P>
<P>
"We have three suspects in mind, none of whom wore gloves when they ransacked 
the house," <PERSON>Hess</PERSON> said. "We also have the bullet in the victim's brain, which we 
can compare with a murder weapon." 
</P>
<P>
In addition, <PERSON>Gomez</PERSON>'s 8-year-old son "was very strong, very alert and able to 
give us a strong, accurate and consistent account of what happened," the 
detective said. 
</P>
<P>
The boy told investigators that three masked men entered the house about <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. One of them carried a handgun and another had a knife. One of the men, 
in <LOCATION>Spanish</LOCATION>, ordered the children to go to bed. The boy and the two other 
children, ages 2 and <DATE>5</DATE>, did as they were told, police said. 
</P>
<P>
The oldest child awoke <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> about <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> and found his mother's 
body. About <TIME>15 minutes later</TIME>, he told neighbors that "we've been robbed and my 
mother has blood in her mouth." 
</P>
<P>
Despite the evidence in the case, many residents have been unable to sleep 
since word spread along tree-lined Arbutus Street that the shy, introverted 
woman was found bound and gagged on the floor of her bedroom with a gunshot 
wound in her head. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't understand why it happened here," neighbor <PERSON>Jaime Maya</PERSON>, 23, said 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. "Everybody around here grew up together. We wave to each other on the 
street. It's been peaceful. 
</P>
<P>
"I never thought I'd buy a gun," <PERSON>Maya</PERSON> added. "But this has opened my eyes." 
</P>
<P>
A few doors down, <PERSON>Marina Acosta</PERSON>, a 40-year-old mother of two teen-agers, said 
she has been sleeping on the living room couch because she is afraid to stay in 
her bedroom at night. 
</P>
<P>
"When someone knocks on the door I'm afraid to open it," <PERSON>Acosta</PERSON> said, studying 
the occupants of every vehicle that passed the home she has lived in for 17 
years. "I'm thinking about moving to another block." 
</P>
<P>
"I don't want to live here anymore either, but where can you run?" wondered 
another neighbor, who asked that her named not be used. "We're going to have to 
grin and bear it." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Teresa Soria, daughter Teresa Vidourri and granddaughter Jacqueline 
stand across street from where mother of three was killed. ; Photo, Jaime Maya, 
with wife Liza and daughter Annika, looks across street at house where 
31-year-old woman was killed. "I don't understand why it happened here," he 
says. AL SEIB / Los Angeles Times; Map, Huntington Park, Los Angeles Times ; 
Photo, (A2) Killing Shakes Huntington Park: The shooting death of 31-year-old 
Bertha Gomez at her home in Huntington Park has brought terror to the tidy 
neighborhood and strained the community's police department, which is facing a 
rise in violent crimes. Jaime Maya, right, passing the house with Dominic 
Garcia, says he had never thought of buying a gun, "but this has opened my 
eyes." AL SEIB / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
HUNTINGTON PARK (CA); GANGS -- LOS ANGELES COUNTY; MURDERS -- LOS ANGELES 
COUNTY; DRUG TRAFFICKING -- LOS ANGELES COUNTY; CRIME STATISTICS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57101 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat093_a_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-093 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> CARIBBEAN </F>
<F P=101> Cuba </F>
<H3> <TI>   Congolese Minister on Cooperation Prospects </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Congolese Minister on Cooperation Prospects </PHRASE></F></HT>

GMT 11 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> FL1205003094 </F>
<F P=104>  Havana Radio Rebelde Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <ORGANIZATION>Congolese Science</ORGANIZATION> and Technology Minister 
(<ORGANIZATION>Buenaventud Maya</ORGANIZATION>'s) visit to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> continues with meetings at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Finlay Institute</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Genetic 
Engineering and Biotechnology Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
  On 12 <DATE>May</DATE>, (Maya) will fulfill his busiest agenda since his 
arrival in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> <DATE>five days ago</DATE>. He will participate in work 
meetings at the <ORGANIZATION>National Assembly of the People's Government</ORGANIZATION>, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Cuban Sugarcane Byproducts Institute</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Livestock 
Enhancement Research Center</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Public Health Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  On 13 <DATE>May</DATE>, (Maya) will meet with <PERSON>Ernesto Melendez</PERSON>, minister 
of <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Investment and Economic Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>. This meeting 
will close the visit to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> which (<ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>) has described as 
productive for mutual cooperation prospects. 

</TEXT>
