<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 1856EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Tornadoes-Aftermath Bjt   08-29 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tornadoes-Aftermath, Bjt,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Way of Life Disappears In Minutes for Tornado Victims</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Illinois Tornadoes, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT LEE ZIMMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PLAINFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Classes were supposed to start here
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, but after a few howling minutes of chaos there was no
class, no school, and for many residents, no home.
   The twisters that tore into this northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> community and
several neighboring towns <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> killed at least 24 people and
injured more than 300. As they flipped cars and tore roofs off
houses, the tornadoes also threatened to bury hundreds of lives.
   ``Life in <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> and surrounding towns
will never be the same,'' said an editorial in <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>Joliet
Herald-News</ORGANIZATION>. ``It has only been a few hours since the tragedy
struck. It will take days, weeks and years to recover.''
   Scores of residents were left homeless. Some residents who had
been planning a new beginning were suddenly faced with nothing.
   <PERSON>Jerry O'Shea</PERSON>, a new teacher, was getting ready for the start of
classes and left <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION> minutes before the twisters
hit. He returned <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a school in ruin.
   ``This was going to be my first day teaching,'' <PERSON>O'Shea</PERSON> said.
``Welcome to <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>.''
   In the <PERSON>Warwick</PERSON> subdivision of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, about 35 miles southwest
of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, new homes finished in the last six months were reduced
to their foundations in minutes. Joliet officials had to explain to
a touring Gov. <PERSON>James R. Thompson</PERSON> that it wasn't a construction zone.
   ``All these homes were occupied,'' said <PERSON>Joliet Alderman Warren
Dorris</PERSON>. ``We lost 31 (homes) and we had three fatalities here. It's
just a shock.''
   There were even more homeless at a seven-building apartment
complex in <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>. Parts of the complex were
destroyed, and authorities were only allowing people into
relatively undamaged buildings to retrieve personal belongings.
   Norm Treonis, chairman of the company that owns the apartment
complex, said he was working to put displaced residents into some
of the company's other vacant apartments, rent-free, for up to two
months.
   Workers also were issuing checks on the spot to reimburse
residents for security deposits and rent. By <TIME>late morning Treonis</TIME>
had issued checks to more than 100 people for amounts ranging from
<MONEY>$200</MONEY> to <MONEY>$600</MONEY>.
   Most storefronts along <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>'s main thoroughfare, <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION>
Street, were shuttered <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. But two insurance agencies were
doing a brisk business.
   ``We've had three dozen calls since <TIME>eight o'clock this
morning</TIME>,'' said <PERSON>Mike Hull</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Insurance Agency Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> Township people also hurried to clean yards and
what was left of their homes.
   ``We're just waiting for the insurance guy to come out,'' said
<PERSON>Jim Schmidt</PERSON>, owner of a frame house that suffered extensive damage
in the storm. ``Obviously it's going to be a while.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> had three shelters for the homeless.
While providing for immediate needs such as food and clothing, the
organization was also concerned about the long-term mental impact
of the disaster.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> will provide ``someone to talk to and some stress
counseling,'' said spokeswoman <PERSON>Michele McCrillis</PERSON>.
   ``A lot of people _ it hasn't hit them yet,'' she said. ``The
full shock isn't going to hit them probably for a little while.''
   The flat area southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> is sometimes referred to as
``Tornado Alley.'' On <DATE>June 23, 1976</DATE>, three people were killed when
a twister passed through nearby <LOCATION>Lemont</LOCATION>. A <DATE>1969</DATE> tornado killed 33
people in <LOCATION>Oak Lawn</LOCATION>, a southwest <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> suburb.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 1322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-IllinoisTornadoes 5thLd-Writethru a0531 08-29 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Illinois Tornadoes, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0531,0868</SECOND>
<HEAD>National Guard Targets Looters After Twisters Kill At Least 24</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `Gov. James ...' with 3 grafs to UPDATE with
governor's request to have area declared federal disaster area,
quote from Thompson and state offer of low-interest loans; Picks up
7th graf pvs., `Elsewhere in ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CX1, CX2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN DISKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CREST HILL, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>National Guardsmen</ORGANIZATION> and fire officials
searched a muddy cornfield today for more victims of tornadoes that
flattened scores of homes and killed at least 24 people.
   The dead included at least nine people found near a demolished
apartment complex where six residents were missing, <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION> Fire
Chief <PERSON>Dave Martis</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   At least 306 people were treated at hospitals after the cluster
of tornadoes touched down in four spots <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, cutting
an eight-mile trail of destruction leading to the northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>
city of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>. At least 11 people were listed in critical
condition today.
   In nearby <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, residents began returning to the rubble of
their homes.
   ``It was like an eggbeater went through the inside of the
house,'' said 41-year-old <PERSON>Bruce Marshall</PERSON> as he tried to fashion a
makeshift cover for his roofless home.
   Gov. <PERSON>James R. Thompson</PERSON> declared Will County a state disaster
area, and requested that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> declare the area a federal
disaster to provide additional relief.
   ``Nothing in my personal experience ... compares with this,''
<PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> said during a tour of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> today.
   Illinois Treasurer <PERSON>Jerry Cosentino</PERSON> announced that the state will
provide at least <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> for low-interest loans to tornado
victims.
   Elsewhere in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, thunderstorms <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> halted power to
70,000 customers in central and western <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>. A tornado touched
down south of Tecumseh in southern <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and storms that ripped
through northern <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> left at least one person dead. <PERSON>Pat Jones</PERSON>,
27, was killed when the house he was building in <LOCATION>South Bend</LOCATION>
collapsed.
   At least two tornadoes were spotted in northwestern
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, but no injuries were reported.
   Preliminary tallies made in the dark from the tornadoes in
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> suggested more than 100 houses were destroyed, in addition
to the apartment complex and a high school. The storms blacked out
17,000 homes and businesses, tossed trucks like toys and flattened
crops.
   ``Cars were flying all over the place,'' said <PERSON>Tony Aloisio</PERSON>, who
was driving by and stopped to help. ``It happened so fast that all
I could do was sit there and watch. Then <TIME>15 minutes later</TIME> the skies
got blue like it had never even happened.''
   About 30 Guardsmen took up positions in the three affected
communities overnight and 150 were to arrive later in the day to
search for victims and provide security, said Col. <PERSON>Phil Becker</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> brigade commander.
   At least four people were arrested for looting, and five others
were taken into custody for interfering with rescuers, authorities
said.
   ``I saw everything out there,'' said Will County Executive
<PERSON>Charles Adelman</PERSON>. ``Refrigerators, TV sets, washing machines, cars
stacked three high.''
   The twisters _ experts were unsure exactly how many _ hit
<LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, 40 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, neighboring Crest Hill, and
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> to the northwest.
   Crest Hill Mayor <PERSON>Don Randich</PERSON> was among the first firefighters to
arrive at the apartment complex. ``There were people wandering
around, dazed,'' he said. ``Automobile horns were blowing, but
there was no one in the cars. It was total confusion.''
   Martis said the bodies of nine people were found near the
apartment complex. Seven bodies, including that of a 4-month-old
baby, were lying in a cornfield, some of them 400 feet from their
apartments, and two were found in a car nearby, <PERSON>Martis</PERSON> said.
   Rescuers went from apartment to apartment, throwing rubble off
of the three-story buildings with shovels or just their hands.
   The death toll was unclear. There were 24 confirmed fatalities
as of <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, and there may be 30 dead, said <PERSON>John Plunk</PERSON>,
acting director of the <ORGANIZATION>Illinois Emergency Services and Disaster
Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said about 600 people left homeless were given
shelter.
   <PERSON>Michael Hejka</PERSON>, 28, was at a friend's house in <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, a
community of 4,500, when the tornado hit. ``I saw trees bending,
and I said to my buddy, `It's a tornado!''' Hejka said. ``I said,
`Jump into the bathtub.' He jumped in, and I jumped in right on top
of him. The whole house lifted up, and then came down.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION> was demolished and some of the 175
students and teachers inside were hurt. Catastrophe was averted
because coaches rushed dozens of athletes from a gym before the
roof collapsed.
   ``We had some very short warnings,'' said teacher <PERSON>Steve
Schernerhorn</PERSON>. ``We immediately took cover.''
   Teacher <PERSON>Mike Salisburg</PERSON> said cars in the parking lot were thrown
hundreds of yards.
   Will County is part of a frequently hit ``tornado alley.'' A
tornado hit <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Township</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>, injuring six people and
demolishing 14 homes. In <DATE>1976</DATE>, a twister hit <LOCATION>Lemont</LOCATION>, 10 miles from
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, killing three people and injuring as many as 40. That
tornado damaged 375 houses and businesses.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 0203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-IllinoisTornado 9thLd-Writethru a0776 08-29 1076</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois Tornado, 9th Ld-Writethru, a0776, a0751,1118</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE with varying official counts of
the dead, more expected, picks up 16th graf of a0751, `Commonwealth
Edison... </NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CX6,7; LaserColor CX106. LaserGraphic.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JIM PAUL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CREST HILL, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tornadoes ripped through several
northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> towns <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, blowing residents out of apartment
buildings and leveling at least 100 homes and a school. As many as
26 were reported dead and the death toll was expected to rise.
   Local hospitals said at least 290 people were being treated for
storm-caused injuries.
   The tornadoes touched down at least four times just after <TIME>3:30
p.m. CDT</TIME> along a seven-mile southwesterly path from the community
of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, about 40 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Illinois State Police</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In <ORGANIZATION>Crest Hill</ORGANIZATION>, on the outskirts of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, eight people were
killed when the twister flattened an apartment complex, said
<LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION> Fire Chief <PERSON>Dave Martis</PERSON>. Four bodies, including that of a
4-month old baby, were lying in a cornfield next to the complex,
and four others were pulled from the collapsed buildings and a car.
   ``When the storm went through, some of the buildings
disintegrated,'' <PERSON>Martis</PERSON> said. ``High winds blew some of the people
into the corn field.''
   Guy Allton, 16, watched the storm from his house near <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield
High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We went outside, and there was picnic tables flying past our
faces and stuff,'' <PERSON>Allton</PERSON> said.
   Afterward he helped pull people from nearby houses, including
two badly hurt babies.
   ``Everything was messed up,'' <PERSON>Allton</PERSON> said. ``Lots and lots of
people hurt.''
   Officials' counts of the dead varied from 20 to 26, and some
said they expected to find more bodies when searching resumed
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Illinois Emergency Services and Disaster Agency</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Lynn
Bobo</PERSON> said late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that 26 people were killed.
   The Will County coroner said 20 bodies had been brought to a
central morgue as of <TIME>11:45 p.m. CDT</TIME>. Others might be in transit,
but some may have been counted twice, said coroner <PERSON>Duane Krueger</PERSON>.
   Five people died in <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>John Watson</PERSON>, ambulance
services chief for the <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   Four people were killed in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, including three in a
subdivision under construction, said Police Chief <PERSON>Dennis Nowicki</PERSON>.
   ``I'm not confident the death toll won't rise,'' said Will
County Executive <PERSON>Charles Adelman</PERSON>, noting that it wasn't known how
many people were inside the heavily damaged <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION>.
   There were several arrests for looting, <PERSON>Adelman</PERSON> said.
   It wasn't immediately clear where the others of the 23 were
found.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> was called out <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> evening to help state
police prevent looting and control crowds in the area, said <PERSON>Ms.
Bobo</PERSON>, the emergency services spokeswoman.
   <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Edison</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>John Hogan</PERSON> reported 17,000
customers without power in the area hit by the storms.
   <PERSON>Judi Mack</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>St. Joseph Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, said
the hospital had received 157 storm victims. Only 25 were admitted
with injuries ranging from minor to severe, she said.
   Thirty-five people were taken to <ORGANIZATION>Silver Cross Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, where
they were in serious to fair condition, said spokeswoman <PERSON>Susan
Larson</PERSON>. Several other hospitals also reported treating storm
victims.
   <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION> was destroyed and some teachers and
students were injured, said <PERSON>Steve Schernerhorn</PERSON>, who with other
teachers and student athletes crouched in the halls as the roof was
blown off.
   ``We had some very short warnings. We immediately took cover,''
he said in a telephone interview. He said about 25 houses near the
school were destroyed.
   Dozens of athletes were in the gym shortly before the tornado
hit, but coaches moved them to another part of the school just
before the gym roof collapsed onto the floor.
   Principal <PERSON>Jim Waldorf</PERSON> said as many as 175 people were in the
school at the time of the storm, and a number of them suffered
minor injuries.
   Teacher <PERSON>Mike Salisburg</PERSON> said some cars in the school parking lot
were thrown as far as several hundred yards.
   Major damage was also reported at <ORGANIZATION>St. Mary's Elementary School</ORGANIZATION>
nearby.
   <PERSON>Eric Curtis</PERSON>, 24, who lives a half-mile northwest of the high
school, said he was at home when the twister hit.
   ``I felt real bad pressure in my head,'' <PERSON>Curtis</PERSON> said. ``I saw my
dad running toward the house.''
   The Curtis house suffered only minor damage, but others in the
neighborhood were wrecked.
   <PERSON>Michael Hejka</PERSON>, 28, arrived at his friend's house five minutes
before the tornado hit.
   ``I saw trees bending, and I said to my buddy, `It's a
tornado!''' Hejka said. ``I said, `Jump into the bathtub.' He
jumped in, and I jumped in right on top of him. The whole house
lifted up, and then came down.''
   Phone lines into the area were jammed; many were reported down.
   At least nine emergency shelters were set up by local disaster
agencies and the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> was supplying clothing, toiletries and food.
   Will County is part of a frequently hit ``tornado alley,'' the
<ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said. A tornado hit <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Township</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>April 1984</DATE>, injuring six people and demolishing 14 homes. In <DATE>June
1976</DATE>, a twister hit <LOCATION>Lemont</LOCATION>, 10 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>,
killing three people and injuring as many as 40. That tornado
damaged 375 houses and businesses.
   <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Edison</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>John Hogan</PERSON> reported 17,000
customers without power in the area hit by the storms.
   <ORGANIZATION>State Police</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Robert Fletcher</PERSON> said at least 50 houses
were leveled, about 30 of them north of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> and 20 or 30
near the <ORGANIZATION>Louis Joliet Mall</ORGANIZATION> just outside <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>.
   Other <ORGANIZATION>State Police</ORGANIZATION> officials reported 15 to 20 houses damaged in
unincorporated areas of <LOCATION>Will County</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Watson</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>, said emergency
workers found 40 homes flattened southeast of the city.
   At least six people were injured in pileups on Interstate 55
caused by violent winds, said <ORGANIZATION>State Police</ORGANIZATION> Lt. <PERSON>Clifford Mann</PERSON>. The
interstate at <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 30 was down to one lane of traffic because of a
semi tractor-trailer rig blown over, he said.
   Crops were flattened west and north of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>.
   Many roads were blocked by trees, and toppled electric towers
and downed lines sparked fires in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mezera</PERSON> said.
   In <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, a dumpster was lodged in the upper branches of a
tall tree, an empty dump truck was on its side and an empty van was
found after it fell off a bridge into the <LOCATION>DuPage River</LOCATION>. Seachers
were combing the banks of the debris-clogged stream.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 2007EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-IllinoisTornadoes 2ndLd-Writethru a0681 08-29 0825</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois Tornadoes, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0681,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescuers Search for Missing in Tornado-Shattered Towns</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with aid offer from Soviets;
SUBS grafs 11-13, bgng `He declared ...' with 3 grafs to UPDATE
with federal disaster relief promised, add detail on offer, report
of death; picks up 14th graf, `More than...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CX8,9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CREST HILL, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescuers on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> searched a
tornado-devastated swath of northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> for the missing and
the dead, while folks began salvaging belongings from homes the
twisters shredded ``like an eggbeater.''
   At least 24 people died and more than 300 were injured <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
by the tornadoes, which steamrolled across a region known as
``Tornado Alley,'' about 35 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   Scores of people were left homeless. Others spent the day
cleaning their yards, hammering on temporary roofs, sifting through
rubble, piling up belongings in pickup trucks lining the streets in
neighboring <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>. Offers of aid have poured in, including one
from the Soviet embassy in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Theresa Rabaduex</PERSON>, a 23-year-old school bus driver who lived in a
complex ripped apart by the storm in <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION>, said tenants in
her building were being moved to free lodging ``but that doesn't do
you any good if you don't have any of your things. I don't even
have a bed.''
   She walked through the debris, trying to find her three black
cats. ``That's all that really matters to me,'' she said.
   ``It was like an eggbeater went through the inside of the
house,'' <PERSON>Bruce Marshall</PERSON> said as he tried to fashion a makeshift
cover for his roofless home in neighboring <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>.
   The storms struck virtually without warning <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> afternoon
along an eight-mile path. Hit hardest were the small towns of <ORGANIZATION>Crest
Hill</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>. Portions of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> also were damaged,
including a new subdivision of houses torn down to their
foundations just a few months after they were built.
   Gov. <PERSON>James R. Thompson</PERSON> said he's seen a lot of disasters during
14 years in office, but ``nothing in my personal experience ...
compares with this.''
   ``Anything that is still standing is pure luck,'' he said after
touring the stricken area <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``All I can say is thank God the death toll is not in the
hundreds. We are very, very lucky.''
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> declared the region a disaster area. The Soviet
officials called the governor's office seeking information on how
to help, <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> said.
   Illinois will provide at least <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in state deposits for
low-interest loans to tornado victims, said state Treasurer <PERSON>Jerry
Cosentino</PERSON>.
   There were 24 fatalities confirmed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, and toll could
reach 30 dead, said <PERSON>John Plunk</PERSON>, acting director of the <ORGANIZATION>Illinois
Emergency Services and Disaster Agency</ORGANIZATION>. Officials said another
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> man died of carbon monoxide poisoning from a generator
he used when power was lost in his home.
   More than 300 people were treated at hospitals, and authorities
said more than 70 remained hospitalized <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. At least 11 of
them were listed in critical condition.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s weather, sunny and cool, gave the area some relief,
and the forecast called for fair skies the rest of the week.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Guardsmen</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION> used dogs, foot patrols and
infrared photography to search for more victims in a muddy corn
field, but found none. Six people were believed missing from a
seven-building apartment complex next to the field.
   The infrared scan from a helicopter was intended to detect
differences in temperature that might lead them to victims.
   At least nine of the storm's deaths occurred near the
apartments, where some victims were blown 400 feet out of the
building, said Chief <PERSON>Dave Martis</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION> Fire District,
which includes <ORGANIZATION>Crest Hill</ORGANIZATION>.
   Downed power lines were scattered across several streets and
nearly 7,000 customers remained without power <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Aurora</LOCATION> area.
   The smell of fresh wood permeated the air as residents used
chain saws to remove trees tossed like matchsticks across their
yards.
   ``I've got lots of family members helping, and some four or five
guys from surrounding towns,'' said <PERSON>Don Kinley</PERSON>, 53, of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>,
who lost most of the second floor of his home.
   ``I don't know them _ they just want to help,'' said <PERSON>Kinley</PERSON>,
tears running down his cheeks.
   <PERSON>Mike Thomas</PERSON>, owner of a <LOCATION>Naperville</LOCATION> wiring company, said he
decided to take the day off to help <PERSON>Kinley</PERSON> and other people because
``They'd probably do it for me.''
   Night clothes hung from trees that had leaves ripped from
branches. Cars remained in front yards, where they were dumped by
the storms. A garbage bin was impaled high in a tree.
   <PERSON>Mike Dehler</PERSON>, a 26-year-old restaurant manager sifted through the
debris outside what used to be his third-floor apartment.
   ``There's my water bed,'' <PERSON>Dehler</PERSON> said, pointing to a deflated
silver mattress. ``Hopefully I'm going to find some clothes in
these dressers. All I have is what I have on.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900830-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-90 0757EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TornadoWarning 1stLd-Writethru a0428 08-30 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tornado Warning, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0428,0645</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornado Struck Without Warning, Residents Say</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS lead to RECAST, deleting figurative use of `out of the
blue;' SUBS 9th graf, `The system...', to CORRECT title of Illinois
agency to Emergency Services and Disaster Agency sted Emergency
Services Disaster Agency. Also in Thursday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Illinois Tornadoes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PLAINFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Survivors of northern <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION>' deadly
storm say it struck virtually without warning, and a weather
forecaster said that even when there are warnings, ``in most cases
it's too late.''
   ``Your chances of being warned before a tornado hits aren't all
said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, pointing out that the notice comes only after a
tornado has been sighted.
   Multiple tornadoes <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> left at least 24 dead and more than
300 injured.
   ``We didn't get any warning,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Police</ORGANIZATION> Chief <PERSON>Don
Bennett</PERSON>.
   The tornadoes that swooped into <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> appeared out of a
single thunderstorm that rumbled across northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> for about
two hours, spitting hail 2 to 3 inches in diameter as it went.
   The weather service issued a severe thunderstorm watch at about
<TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> as the storm approached <LOCATION>Rockford</LOCATION>, then followed it up
with more notices as the storm moved southeast, warning of
dangerous lightning, heavy rain and strong winds.
   ``Remember ... severe thunderstorms can and occasionally do
produce a tornado with little or no advance warning ... so be on
the lookout,'' read one warning.
   But the storm seemed to be limited to hail and high winds.
   ``The system seemed to have gotten less threatening,'' said <PERSON>John
Plunk</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Illinois Emergency Services and Disaster
Agency</ORGANIZATION>. ``Then this hit out of the blue. When it forms that fast
and moves that quickly, there's nothing you can do.''
   At <TIME>3:45 p.m.</TIME>, the first call came in to the weather service
reporting a tornado touchdown at <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, said forecaster
<PERSON>Richard Kenneman</PERSON>. The weather service moved a bulletin at <TIME>3:51
p.m.</TIME>, but by that time the twisters had already smashed through the
town and into <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, about 15 miles away.
   <PERSON>Janet Fazio</PERSON> said the few teachers and administrators at
<ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION> at the end of the day didn't know the storm
was coming until a school worker eyed it while closing a window
that had blown open.
   ``The emergency radio didn't even go off in the main office,''
said <PERSON>Mrs. Fazio</PERSON>, a secretary.
   The tornadoes virtually destroyed the school, which had been
scheduled to open for classes <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Most teachers and
administrators had left for the day when the storm struck, and some
took shelter in the school vault.
   In a <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> subdivision 35 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rich
Alberti</PERSON> got the warning from his wife, <PERSON>Michelle</PERSON>, moments before
their house was destroyed.
   ``I was sleeping and she was getting ready to take a shower,''
<PERSON>Alberti</PERSON> said. ``She told me to look out. As soon as I saw it, I
knew it was a tornado. There weren't seconds to spare.''
   Kenneman said tornadoes themselves are too small to be detected
by available radar, but thunderstorms sometimes contain radar
patterns that indicate a tornado may be developing. The
thunderstorm <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> did not contain the telltale indications that
twisters were lurking inside, <PERSON>Kenneman</PERSON> said.
   More sophisticated radar is being developed. But, he said, even
fair warning can't always protect against nature's most devastating
force.
   ``Even assuming the whole warning process plays through
successfully and people hear the warning, there are some tornadoes
that are violent enough that they are flat out not survivable,''
<PERSON>Kenneman</PERSON> said.
   ``We have to live with the fact that, unless we want to live in
concrete reinforced bunkers and drive 80,000-pound steel cars, that
we are going to be vulnerable when weather is severe enough,'' he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082990-0062 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 268511 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 29, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 2; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
842 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TORNADOES KILL 23, FLATTEN 100 HOMES IN ILLINOIS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TRACY SHRYER and BOB SECTER, TIMES STAFF WRITERS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CREST HILL, Ill. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The most powerful series of tornadoes in this area in more than two decades 
tore a path of death and destruction across suburbs southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, killing at least 23 people and flattening 100 homes, an 
apartment complex, a church and a high school in a matter of minutes. 
</P>
<P>
Four separate tornadoes spawned by a hot, muggy storm cell touched down amid 
the subdivisions and cornfields in the vicinity of <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, about 30 miles 
outside <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Area hospitals reported more than 280 people injured, many of them critically. 
Officials said they expected the number of deaths and injuries to rise through 
the <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, Gov. <PERSON>James R. Thompson</PERSON> activated two <ORGANIZATION>Illinois National Guard</ORGANIZATION> units 
to help police maintain order and restore public services. As of late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, 
two people had been arrested for looting in the area. 
</P>
<P>
One of the twisters slammed into the <ORGANIZATION>Cedar Woods Apartment Complex</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Crest 
Hill</LOCATION> about <TIME>3:40 p.m.</TIME>, knocking some three-story brick buildings to the ground 
and stripping the top two floors off others. 
</P>
<P>
Police officers said they pulled several bodies from the rubble and were 
frantically searching for more victims as daylight faded. Some victims were 
thrown from buildings by the force of the storm and landed more than 200 yards 
away in a cornfield. 
</P>
<P>
"It was total devastation; it looked like a bomb had hit," said one fireman who 
helped pull bodies from the field. He said most of the dead were clad only in 
shorts. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>St. Mary Immaculate Church</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> was almost completely destroyed. 
</P>
<P>
The storm mangled power and telephone lines and cut vital services to tens of 
thousands of residents in the area. It caused numerous traffic accidents on 
<LOCATION>Interstate 55</LOCATION> as high winds tossed dozens of cars and trucks off the road. At 
least six people were injured in their vehicles. 
</P>
<P>
Downed power lines sparked several small fires, officials said. Residents in 
some affected areas were warned not to drink tap water. 
</P>
<P>
At least two deaths were reported at <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION>, which was hit 
point-blank by one of the tornadoes only a day before the beginning of the 
regular school year. At the time, several teachers and administrators were 
inside the building preparing for the start of classes, and members of the 
football and women's volleyball teams were practicing. 
</P>
<P>
The students raced inside the structure just moments before the twister smacked 
into it, blowing the roof off and toppling many walls. Miraculously, none of 
the youngsters were among those reported killed. 
</P>
<P>
"We had some very short warnings," said <PERSON>Steve Schernerhorn</PERSON>, a school 
administrator. "We immediately took cover . . . . There is no school left . . . 
. All the houses in front of the school are pretty much gone." 
</P>
<P>
Nearby, 16-year-old Guy <PERSON>Allton</PERSON> watched from his home as the school crumbled. 
"We went outside and there were picnic tables blowing past our faces and 
stuff," <PERSON>Allton</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. "Everything was messed up. Everything on 
<ORGANIZATION>James Street</ORGANIZATION> is totaled. Lots and lots of people hurt." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Candi Vance</PERSON>, another <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> student, was not at school when the storm hit 
but barely escaped with her life anyway. The 16-year-old <PERSON>Vance</PERSON> was visiting her 
grandmother in the <ORGANIZATION>Lilly Cash</ORGANIZATION> subdivision in <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> when a tornado swooped 
out of the sky. 
</P>
<P>
The two women had just begun to scramble down the stairs to the basement when 
the roof and much of the rest of the house collapsed. "It came down; the steps 
fell on top of us," <PERSON>Vance</PERSON> recalled. "All I could see was the sky. There's 
nothing left . . . . No one can believe we made it out alive." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Vance</PERSON> was treated at <ORGANIZATION>St. Joseph's Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> for a twisted ankle 
and bruised bones in her knee. Her grandmother suffered cuts on one leg from 
the knee to the ankle and was bleeding badly when she was brought into the 
hospital. 
</P>
<P>
As night fell, huge traffic jams filled the roads throughout the southwestern 
suburbs as commuters returning from work tried to navigate through darkened 
streets obstructed by floodwaters and debris. Police roadblocks and the lack of 
stoplights added to the congestion. 
</P>
<P>
Several hundred people with injuries ranging from minor cuts to serious head 
wounds were shuttled by ambulances to hospitals in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>. One of the 
facilities was so overwhelmed that it set up an emergency treatment center in 
its parking lot. 
</P>
<P>
Authorities set up several shelters in area churches and schools for those who 
had lost their homes or were having trouble coping with the lack of 
electricity. Clair Swan, superintendent of schools in suburban <LOCATION>Shorewood</LOCATION>, said 
all three of his district's schools would be used as shelters. 
</P>
<P>
"At least 1,000 people, maybe more, will sleep here tonight," he predicted. 
</P>
<P>
Many area residents also opened their doors to those in need. A local radio 
station in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> was broadcasting the names and addresses of residents who had 
called in with offers to put up the homeless. 
</P>
<P>
Area businesses also offered relief, including a bed-and-mattress shop that 
said it would let displaced people come in and sleep on the floor samples. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Tornado Damage, AP / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
TORNADOES; DISASTERS -- ILLINOIS; DISASTER VICTIMS; CASUALTIES; STORMS -- 
ILLINOIS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900830-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-90 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-IllinoisTornadoes 1stLd-Writethru a0468 08-30 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Illinois Tornadoes, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0468,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornado Survivors Turn Attention Toward Shelter, Toilets</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts 3 grafs after the 9th, `More than 70..,' to update
with relief truck explosion. Picks up 10th graf pvs, `Utility
crews...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT LEE ZIMMER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PLAINFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Robert Whitesel</PERSON> had lived on Nuclear
Drive for 29 years, and the street name seemed grimly appropriate
as he surveyed the tornado-whipped wreckage of his house and those
of his neighbors.
   ``You have to laugh _ you can't cry,'' <PERSON>Whitesel</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
``I'll probably rebuild it. In the meantime, I'll live with my
daughter.''
by the tornadoes, which steamrolled virtually without warning
across a region known as ``Tornado Alley,'' about 35 miles
southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. Damage was estimated at more than <MONEY>$100
million</MONEY>.
   Hit hardest were the small towns of <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>,
where hundreds were left homeless.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Guardsmen</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION> used dogs, foot patrols and
infrared photography to search for more victims in a muddy
cornfield but found none.
   Six people were believed missing from a seven-building apartment
complex next to the field. At least nine deaths occurred near the
apartments.
   Plainfield residents packed a high school gym <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to
hear how various government agencies could help. President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
declared the region a disaster area and <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> offered at least
<MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> for low-interest loans.
   The crowd observed a moment of silence for those who died. Then
they got down to the needs of the living _ getting shelter,
portable toilets for neighborhoods without running water, trash
bins for the untold tons of debris.
   More than 70 people remained hospitalized today, at least 11 in
critical condition, authorities said. In addition, a <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> man
died of carbon monoxide poisoning from a generator he used when
power was lost in his home.
   And four people were injured today, one critically, when a
mobile kitchen sent in for relief workers exploded and caught fire.
   The explosion occurred when a propane tank overflowed while
being filled from a supply truck and the fuel was ignited by a
flame from a stove in the kitchen set up in a truck trailer, Fire
Chief <PERSON>George Plese</PERSON> said.
   A fire official had to clamp a hose leading from the supply
truck to the kitchen tanks, cut it, then pull the truck away to
stop the fire. ``We had a very dangerous situation,'' <PERSON>Plese</PERSON> said.
   Utility crews worked through the <TIME>night</TIME> to restore telephone and
electric service. About 5,000 customers remained without
electricity, officials said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army</ORGANIZATION> and other charitable groups were
out in force, but self-sufficiency also was evident.
   ``It's the kind of community where neighbors or family say `Stay
with us,' '' said the Rev. <PERSON>Donald Niswonger</PERSON> as he dished out beef
stew, pizza and lasagna at the <ORGANIZATION>Plymouth Congregational Church</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Roman Catholic Archbishop Joseph Imesch</PERSON> said an
evening Mass for the victims and their families. The tornado ``will
be a reminder of how fragile life is,'' he said.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION>, newly hired English teacher <PERSON>Jerry
O'Shea</PERSON> stood amid water and broken glass in front of a shattered
trophy case in the main hallway.
   ``This was going to be my first day teaching,'' <PERSON>O'Shea</PERSON> said.
``Welome to <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>. I don't know what I'll do now.''
   Most stores along <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>'s main street were shuttered, but
two insurance agencies were doing brisk business. ``We've had
three-dozen calls since <TIME>8 o'clock this morning</TIME>,'' said <PERSON>Mike Hull</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Insurance Agency Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900830-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-90 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-IllinoisTornadoes 1stLd-Writethru a0638 08-30 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois Tornadoes, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0638,0759</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survivors Ponder Capriciousness of Tornadoes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs with death toll climbing to 27, picks up
8th graf pvs, `Hunt had ...; Bruch in 19th graf pronounced brook</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos CX5,6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDSEY TANNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PLAINFIELD, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Biology teacher <PERSON>Stephen Hunt</PERSON> died when a
tornado grabbed a truck in front of <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield High School</ORGANIZATION> and
dropped it onto the second floor of the science department, where
he worked.
   Only rooms away, business teacher <PERSON>Linda Kinnikin</PERSON> survived
unscathed.
   Behind the school, which was demolished, the twister leveled
<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gene Fassiotto</PERSON>'s home, plucking their car from a now
nonexistent garage and depositing it upside down where the living
room once stood.
   Across the street, <PERSON>Lois Moffitt</PERSON>'s brick ranch-style house still
stands.
   The capriciousness of the tornadoes that spun across northern
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> is painfully obvious to the survivors of the
storms.
   ``They say tornadoes touch down and jump all over the place,''
<PERSON>Mrs. Kinnikin</PERSON> said, shaking her head <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as she examined the
rubble that killed her colleague.
   ``In a matter of a minute's time, it all changed,'' she said.
   The death toll climbed to 27 <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when a 3-year-old girl and
16-year-old boy died of injuries they suffered in the storms. More
than 300 people were injured.
   Hunt had been talking with <PERSON>Mrs. Kinnikin</PERSON> only a few minutes
before the tornado hit.
   ``He was a dedicated teacher,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Kinnikin</PERSON> said softly, her
eyes brimming with tears.
   Asked how she survived, she shook her head.
   ``I heard so much debris hitting the windows of the building,''
she recalled. ``There was no visibility because the rain was coming
down so hard.
   ``And when the window blew, I took off running for the men's
bathroom. My department chair and I huddled together in the men's
bathroom. I said `Oh, my God' three times, and it was over.''
   When she climbed out of the rubble, she saw the walls in ruins,
the roof blown off, and smashed cars in the parking lot thrown into
a heap.
   At least two dozen people died in the tornadoes that hit <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Crest Hill</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, about 35 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   The twisters left more than 1,000 homes uninhabitable and caused
over <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> in damage. The region has been declared a state
and federal disaster area.
   And the random misfortunes didn't necessarily stop when the
storms left. On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, a truck serving as a mobile kitchen for
relief workers exploded and caught fire in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, injuring four
people, one critically.
   Authorities said a propane tank overflowed while being loaded
and the fuel was ignited by a flame from a stove.
   Three people died on the <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> school grounds during the
storm, including Hunt.
   <PERSON>Bruch Reed</PERSON>, 15, said Hunt had like been like a second father to
him.
   ``I've done so much thinking about the people who died,'' said
<PERSON>Reed</PERSON>, who was at a park a few blocks away when the storm hit and
who was unhurt.
   ``I suppose we should'' feel guilty, ``not just because I
survived, but because my house was untouched,'' <PERSON>Reed</PERSON> said.
   ``You always think it doesn't happen, and won't happen to you,''
he said. ``It doesn't matter who you are or where you are, it can
happen.''
   <PERSON>Shirley Fassiotto</PERSON> knows. Her home was reduced to boards, bricks
and plaster strewn about the lot.
   ``We had just gotten to the basement when the walls came down,''
she said.
   Glancing across the street at <PERSON>Mrs. Moffitt</PERSON>'s home, she added:
``You wonder. ... She just missed the path (of the twister), who
knows how.''
   ``It doesn't matter what kind of house you have or where you're
situated, the path is so erratic,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Moffitt</PERSON>, who was
visiting a daughter in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> when the storm hit. Windows in her
home were shattered, and the roof was slightly damaged.
   Across the street and down a few houses, <PERSON>Don Erikson</PERSON>, 60, was
less lucky. He was looking out his living room picture window when
the storm hit.
   The tornado drove chunks of glass into his body and threw him
onto the couch. It also tossed his furniture around like toys and
blew off the roof _ but left several paper cups sitting on a
counter.
   <PERSON>Erikson</PERSON> was in fair condition <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at a <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> hospital.
``He lost a lot of blood,'' said his son, <PERSON>Jeff Erikson</PERSON>, 30.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880331-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-88 1317EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TornadoSeason     03-31 0545</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tornado Season,0559</SECOND>
<HEAD>It's The Time of Year For Funnels</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SCOTT ROTHSCHILD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rumbling spring thunderstorms have announced the
beginning of the unofficial tornado season that runs from <DATE>April</DATE>
through <DATE>June</DATE> across <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and other Tornado Alley states in the
nation's heartland.
   From <DATE>1951 through 1986</DATE>, there have been an average of 118
tornadoes in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> per year, according to the state climatologist's
office in <LOCATION>College Station</LOCATION>.
   More than <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of those occur between <DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>June</DATE>,
records show. In <DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>June</DATE> an average of 18 to 19 tornadoes
occur each month, but in <DATE>May</DATE>, when weather conditions are the most
unstable, that average increases to about 36.
   A few twisters were already recorded in early <DATE>March</DATE> in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> but
they did little or no damage. A tornado that touched down <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
in <LOCATION>central Louisiana</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Bunkie</LOCATION>, destroyed two brick homes.
   ``People should have plans of what they'll do in tornadoes. If
they wait until it gets there, it's going to be too late,'' said
<PERSON>Buddy McIntyre</PERSON>, a forecaster with the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   Last <DATE>May 22</DATE>, a killer storm flattened the small <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> town
of <LOCATION>Saragosa</LOCATION>, killing 30 people and injuring 162. In mid-November,
11 people died in <LOCATION>East Texas</LOCATION> when a series of tornadoes trashed
towns from <LOCATION>Cherokee County</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``A tornado is such a devastating kind of storm. No matter how
much preparation you do there is some property damage and some loss
of life. But there are some things you can do to protect yourself
and property,'' said <PERSON>Laureen Chernow</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the
governor's division of emergency management.
   One is to know the difference between the tornado watches and
tornado warnings issued by the weather service.
   A watch means weather conditions are suitable for development of
a tornado, and people should keep a careful lookout for potential
funnel clouds.
   A tornado warning means one has already developed and has been
spotted. Take cover immediately and don't go outside, but if you
are in a car or mobile home you will be safer taking cover in the
nearest ditch or depression.
   At home, the best place to stay is a basement or underground
storm shelter. If no such shelter is available, go inside a closet
in the center of the house or bathroom or lie flat under a heavy
table.
   McIntyre noted that most fatalities in a tornado are from flying
debris, so ``we tell people to squat down, cover their heads and
present a low profile.''
   <PERSON>James R. McDonald</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Disaster
Research</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Texas Tech University</ORGANIZATION>, says many people mistakenly try
to outrun tornadoes in their cars.
   During the <DATE>1979</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Wichita Falls</ORGANIZATION> tornado that killed 53, <ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION>
said, ``people jumped in their cars and drove down Main Street at
90 mph.'' Twenty-six people died while trying to outrun the twister.
   Another misconception is about opening windows. It was once
believed that windows needed to be open to equalize air pressure
between the storm and the inside of a house to prevent the house
from exploding.
   <PERSON>McIntyre</PERSON> said there are enough natural openings in a house to
equalize air pressure, and ``if that tornado wants to open your
windows, it'll do that for you.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900831-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-31-90 0620EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Tornadoes-Warning     08-31 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tornadoes-Warning,0409</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radar System That Might Have Warned of Twisters Wasn't Working</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CLIFF EDWARDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tornado-warning radar system had been disabled
by lightning hours before killer twisters struck several towns in
   But the forecaster said he didn't believe the system could have
forecast the tornadoes that killed 27 people and injured more than
300 <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> across a region known as ``Tornado Alley,'' about 35
miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>.
   The weather service's <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> office issued a severe
thunderstorm warning for the area, but did not alert residents to
the tornadoes until six minutes after they had touched down in the
communities of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Crest Hill</ORGANIZATION>.
   The office is equipped with an early version of Doppler radar,
which might have provided five to 10 minutes advance warning of the
twisters, said forecaster <PERSON>Carl Williams</PERSON>.
   ``But there's just no way that you can say that it could have
done that,'' <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said in a telephone interview. ``It's a
primitive system and I don't think it's being out had any effect at
all.''
   <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said the Doppler radar has not been in wide use in most
weather service offices, but an ``add-on'' Doppler was installed in
<DATE>1974</DATE> on radar equipment dating back to <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   But the Doppler radar in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> was knocked out by lightning
hours before <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s storms.
   The Doppler system can detect both those winds that are
approaching and moving away. When winds are detected moving in both
directions at the same time and at high speeds, meteorologists can
quickly determine that they are dealing with a tornado.
   A newer system called NEXRAD is being tested at the weather
service's <ORGANIZATION>National Severe Storms Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>, officials said. But
that system may not be installed until <DATE>1995</DATE>, <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reported today that the weather service has
dispatched a team of researchers from the <ORGANIZATION>National Severe Storms
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Norman</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, to assess the effectiveness of its
forecasters and timeliness of the alerts they issued <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``We will do a complete assessment of the event,'' <PERSON>Robert
Maddox</PERSON>, director of the laboratory, told the newspaper. ``We will
look at the weather observations and the data available to forecast
offices, and if the team can agree on them we will offer
recommendations for improvements.''
   Calls to the <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> lab went unanswered early today.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06118116 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06118116 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, map; PHOTO: Associated Press; Tiffany Trekell stands amid storm damage
Friday in Andover, Kan. Rescue efforts continued through the night.; MAP:
Mercury News. Fatal tornadoes.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  WEATHER; RESULT; DEATH; KANSAS; OKLAHOMA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Tornadoes ripped through Kansas and Oklahoma on Friday, killing at least 30
people -- 22 of them in one small town.;    Andover Mayor Jack Finlason told
reporters at least 22 people were killed in his town, near Wichita, by a
twister that damaged 500 homes. Law enforcement officials weren't immediately
able to confirm the death count.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PLAINS TWISTERS KILL AT LEAST 30
ONE KANSAS TOWN COUNTS 22 DEAD; HUNDREDS
INJURED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Three deaths were reported in <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> and two in <LOCATION>Elk County.</LOCATION>;    <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>
authorities blamed tornadoes for at least three deaths in the northeastern
part of that state.;    In <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION>, a town of 5,000, the mayor reported
devastation.;    "The southeast part of town, especially the mobile home park,
is completely leveled. The injuries are too numerous at this point to assess,"
<PERSON>Finlason</PERSON> said.;    The Golden Spur Mobile Home Park was destroyed. Authorities
planned to search for victims there throughout the night.;    "There are
still, we're afraid, injured people trapped," said <PERSON>Stan Cox</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Butler County</LOCATION>
sheriff's captain.;    A 13-year-old girl in <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION> was carried 400 feet into
a tree.;    Corrugated metal, insulation, and other debris was wrapped around
utility poles. All power was out in the town late Friday.;    <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Joan
Finney</PERSON> authorized <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> troops and <ORGANIZATION>Kansas Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> officers to
go to the Wichita-Andover area for reinforcements.;    In <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, one woman
died when her car was swept off <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 64 in <LOCATION>Pawnee County</LOCATION>, west of <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>, said
<ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> dispatcher <PERSON>Patrick Sawyer</PERSON>. Another person was killed near
<LOCATION>Westport</LOCATION>, about 25 miles west of Tulsa.;    Cars rolled up into balls;  One
person died when a tornado hit a street in <LOCATION>Copan</LOCATION>, a few miles south of the
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> line, said <LOCATION>Bartlesville</LOCATION> police officer <PERSON>Larry Topping.</PERSON>;    Cars in <LOCATION>Copan</LOCATION>
"were rolled up like little balls," Topping said.;    <LOCATION>Tonkawa</LOCATION>, about 100 miles
northwest of <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>, was hit by two twisters, one in the morning and one in the
<TIME>evening</TIME>. Between the onslaughts, <PERSON>Jack Barnes</PERSON> was helping clear downed limbs
from another family's roof when a branch snapped back in his face, killing
him, said police Chief <PERSON>Frank Hall.</PERSON>;    <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> lawmakers were ordered to
evacuate the <LOCATION>Statehouse</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> because of storms heading for
Topeka.;    <PERSON>Harold Harris</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> watched a twister touch down on a farm
northwest of town.;    "We saw the tornado coming across the field," he said.
"A barn disappeared and it tore the devil out of the house.";    200
hospitalized;  A sheriff's official in <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> estimated that up to 200 people
were taken to hospitals.;    A tornado touched down at <ORGANIZATION>McConnell Air Force
Base</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> about <TIME>6:30 p.m.</TIME>, causing a few minor injuries and heavily
damaging the base hospital, community center, bowling alley, gymnasium and
other buildings, said Sgt. <PERSON>Larry Dean</PERSON> of the base public affairs office.;   
Tornadoes also hit <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and Louisiana.;    In <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, a twister damaged
houses, farms and trees south of Beatrice as thunderstorms and hail up to the
size of golf balls pummeled the state's southeastern, eastern and northeastern
portions.;    Flooding around <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>;  A twister battered <LOCATION>Grand Isle</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>. New Orleans-area subdivisions were awash in floodwater, and
unrelenting rain postponed the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>New Orleans Jazz</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Heritage
Festival.</ORGANIZATION>;    The festival, attended by more than 300,000 people <DATE>last year</DATE>,
was put off until today because rain flooded the infield at the racetrack
where it is held.;    Intense storms pelted areas of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> with hail up to
the size of golf balls and knocked out power to thousands, officials said.;   
In <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, the state <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> closed a 30-mile section of Interstate 80
between <LOCATION>Laramie</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Wolcott Junction</PERSON> in the state's southern section.;    As
much as a foot of snow was on the ground in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>'s higher elevations, and
lesser amounts fell throughout the state.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Andover, Kan.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910427  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  641  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday April 27, 1991
00118116,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06119093 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06119093 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Associated Press; Members of one suburban Kansas family,
after posting notice of their survival, sift through the ruins of their
Andover home, one of more than 500 destroyed in the Wichita area by Friday's
lethal twisters. (color); PHOTO: Photographs by Associated Press; A
firefighter searches debris left by the tornadoes in Andover, Kan., where 19
people died in a mobile-home park. (color); PHOTO: Eugene Thompson's horse
ended up in a swimming pool, soaked but alive. (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  WEATHER; TORNADO; DISASTER; DAMAGE; DEATH; MULTIPLE; KANSAS; INJURY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Suzie Storrer jumped from her car and ran as the wind howled round her.;   
The tornado, a huge funnel of destruction, had passed through only minutes
before Friday and the road was impassable. She nearly stumbled and kicked off
her high-heeled shoes, running all the harder for home. The children, Misty
and Kelsey, were there. Storrer did not even notice that her nylons were
tearing as she ran over glass and other debris in the street.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GET TO THE BASEMENT!'
TWISTER SURVIVORS WATCH AS FUNNELS RIP AWAY
ROOFS, NEIGHBORHOODS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  GRIM SEARCH: Bulldozers sift through wreckage of trailer park; death toll
still rising. Back Page (20A)  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The houses around her were gone, shattered by the force of the wind. So
great was the devastation that she could not tell where her own home had once
been. She looked around for the familiar landmarks, and they were all gone.;  
 Then she saw the girls, sitting on a curb across the street from what had
been their house. A great wave of relief swept over <PERSON>Storrer</PERSON> as she cried out
and embraced her daughters. She would find out later that Misty, her
14-year-old, had herded her 10-year-old sister, the two dogs and cat into the
basement just as the twister hit.;    This small bedroom community, just to
the east of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, bore the harshest brunt of the dozens of tornadoes that
whipped through six states <DATE>Friday</DATE>, killing at least 29 people -- 19 of them in
<LOCATION>Andover.</LOCATION>;    In all, more than 70 tornadoes touched down from <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said. Twenty-six people died in <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>
and three in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>. The twisters also left more than 200 injured and at
least 1,500 homeless.;    But the most serious damage was in and around the
<LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> area.;    "What I saw made me heartsick," said <PERSON>Kansas</PERSON> Gov. <PERSON>Joan Finney</PERSON>
after an aerial tour. "The suffering must be intense." She issued a state
disaster declaration, the first step in seeking federal assistance for the
devastated area.;    The worst tornado;  The most destructive of the tornadoes
left a path about a mile wide and 43 miles long. It first touched down
southwest of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> and then began, as all twisters do, to move to the
northeast. At least two trailer parks south of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> were destroyed and then
the tornado churned toward <ORGANIZATION>McConnell Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>. The base hospital was
heavily damaged, the legal office was blown apart and a number of other
buildings were hit, including a wing of one of the base schools.;    The
tornado then took dead aim at <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION>, a town of about 5,000. <PERSON>Alberta Wheeler</PERSON>,
who has lived in <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION> with her husband, <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON>, since <DATE>1946</DATE>, was in the
kitchen of her brick home when the phone rang. It was her son, <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>,
calling from a <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION> bowling alley.;    "He said, 'Mom, hit the basement.
There's buildings falling down all over the place,' " she recounted as she sat
next to her now-roofless house. "I said that I was baking a pie and didn't
have time. And he said, 'Forget the damn pie and get to the basement!' ";   
Barely time to hide;  The basement steps were five feet from the telephone,
but the tornado was on the house by the time the <ORGANIZATION>Wheelers</ORGANIZATION> reached the bottom
steps. And, in no time, their residence of 45 years was all but gone.;    "It
just took a few minutes to tear everything up," she said. Or, as her daughter,
<PERSON>Holly</PERSON>, put it: "It looked like some hellacious giant came through and walked
on everything.";    Several hundred yards down the road, workers dug through
the Golden Spur Mobile Home Park, where all of the dead of <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION> were found.
The trailer park was flattened, as if all of the 290 mobile homes had been put
through a shredding machine. The search for bodies continued through the
morning and afternoon, while some residents complained that officials were not
allowing them back into the area quickly enough to sift through the ruins and
salvage what they could.;    Down the block, <PERSON>Lonnie Bartlett</PERSON> picked up a
pizza, walked home and looked out the back window. He raced to the basement,
along with his wife and son.;    "It wasn't even that noisy," said <PERSON>Bartlett</PERSON>.
"It was kind of a swoosh.";    Like the others, his house is gone.;    A few
doors down, the Inglands crouched under the basement stairs and then looked up
to see daylight because their house had been flattened. Then, cautiously, they
made their way out.;    'Like gophers';  "It was like gophers popping their
heads up," <PERSON>Andy Ingland</PERSON> said, describing the post-tornado scene as his
neighbors in the subdivision reappeared.;    Throughout the day, like others
in this devastated area, residents looked for their belongings. A car in
<LOCATION>Ingland</LOCATION>'s front yard was crunched like a soda can that had been stepped on,
and he pointed out a heavily damaged <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> yards away. No one seemed to know
who owned either car, or how far the cars had traveled before coming to rest.;
   <ORGANIZATION>Ingland</ORGANIZATION> said he had seen the tornado coming, watched it grow stronger and
more menacing as it approached.;    "That cloud was so big, so dark," he said.
"We just kept hoping the thing would lift up, but it just kept coming and
coming.";    During the day, he and his wife and friends had packed up what
could be salvaged from the wreckage, and not all the news was bad. The clothes
were dirty but could be cleaned. He had found his wallet. They had found all
of his wife's jewelry on the floor. And, of course, they were alive.;    "I'll
tell you what, I'll never own another house that doesn't have a basement," he
said.;    Fickle destruction;  As with almost all twisters, there was a
certain fickleness about this one. Ingland's living room was destroyed, but a
statue remained untouched on the fireplace mantel. Only one dish fell from
<PERSON>Alberta Wheeler</PERSON>'s china hutch, while a piece of lumber pierced her wall only a
few feet away.;    At <PERSON>Suzie Storrer</PERSON>'s, the family was able to find her
husband's wedding ring and her engagement ring -- but not the refrigerator or
washer and dryer.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  J. Michael Kennedy Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  ANDOVER, Kan.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910428  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,101  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 28, 1991
00119093,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900314-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-90 0058EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-KansasTornado 4thLd-Writethru a0403 03-14 0728</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kansas Tornado, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0403,0752</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornado Kills One Person; Up to 15 Homes and Businesses Damaged</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with two fatalities, 14 injured, a dozen
tornadoes hitting area, two missing in Hesston, number of
businesses damaged, details on deaths, tornado damage in Iowa,
other details; no pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos HUT1, DC11</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL BATES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HESSTON, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least a dozen tornadoes <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> battered
south-central <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, killing a 6-year-old boy and another person,
injuring 14 others and extensively damaging more than 100 homes,
authorities said.
   Tornadoes also blew through sections of <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, causing widespread property damage, but no serious
injuries, authorities said.
   In <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, authorities were searching for two missing people.
   The town of about 3,000 poeple ``took a direct hit and there is
major damage,'' said a dispatcher with the <ORGANIZATION>Kansas Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>.
   Gov. <PERSON>Mike Hayden</PERSON> traveled to <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, which was left without
electricity.
   About <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the town sustained major
damage from the tornado, and debris was strewn everywhere, said
<PERSON>Phillip Kloster</PERSON>, manager of the nearby town of <LOCATION>Newton</LOCATION> who was
helping at the command post in <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>.
   Thirteen people hurt in the <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> twisters were taken to the
<ORGANIZATION>Newton Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>, about eight miles south of <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, said
spokeswoman <PERSON>Chris McKellip</PERSON>. Most had scratches, cuts and bruises.
   A 56-year-old woman who'd been traveling through <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION> when
the twister struck was treated for a broken arm at <ORGANIZATION>Wesley Medical
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, said a hospital spokeswoman.
   A dozen tornadoes touched down within a wide area of
south-central <PERSON>Kanas</PERSON> after <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME>, and continued into the
<TIME>evening</TIME>, said <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol Trooper Martin Berneking</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We have approximately between 75 and 100 homes that have been
anywhere from completely destroyed to fairly seriously damaged,''
said <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION> city administrator <PERSON>Jay Wieland</PERSON>. At least five
businesses were destroyed and 15 were damaged.
   ``Surprisingly, we have very few people at this point who are
reported missing,'' <PERSON>Wieland</PERSON> said. ``We have temporary housing set
up at the high school and at the college. We have <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> on
their way in now to help secure the area.''
   About 50 people went to <ORGANIZATION>Hesston High School</ORGANIZATION>'s gym to spend the
night, said Principal <PERSON>Marvin Estes</PERSON>.
   The 6-year-old boy died at a home south of <LOCATION>Burrton</LOCATION>, which is
about 15 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, when a chimney and fireplace
collapsed into a basement, said <PERSON>Harvey County Sheriff</PERSON>'s
Investigator <PERSON>Byron Motter</PERSON>. Another child suffered minor head wounds
in the basement, where seven people had sought shelter from the
storm.
   Another person died in a home near the small town of Goessel,
which is about 10 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Marion County
Sheriff Ed Davies</ORGANIZATION>. The victim's name was not released.
   In <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION>, the home of <PERSON>Charla Buscher</PERSON>, 14, was seriously
damaged by the twister.
   ``We're all really shook up,'' said Charla. ``A lot of the
houses here are leveled ... We had a car wash. It's gone.
   ``The northwest corner of <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION> is just, it's gone,'' she
said. ``There's nothing left. It just looks like as if it's just
starting construction''
   At a <ORGANIZATION>Pizza Hut</ORGANIZATION>, about 15 customers and employees took cover from
the storm in a walk-in freezer and two bathrooms, ``the two safest
places in the building,'' said restaurant supervisor <PERSON>John Anderson</PERSON>.
The storm tore the roof off the restaurant, but no one was injured.
   ``I was outside and I heard it roaring,'' said <PERSON>Dennis Eck</PERSON>, an
employee at a gas station, ``I flipped switches and we hit the
deck. The pumps are all torn up. We've got roof damage.''
   Eck said businesses north of his service station were
demolished, and that the post office suffered extensive damage.
   <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> workers were on the scene. Initial reports said
the worst damage in <LOCATION>Hesston</LOCATION> was on the western edge of town.
   <PERSON>Wieland</PERSON> said power would be restored in a day and a half to two
days, and that emergency repairs were being made to water service.
   In the small eastern <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Worthington</LOCATION>, a tornado
destroyed the fire house, 10 homes and three businesses, disaster
officials said. Fifty residents left homeless sought shelter with
the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>.
   About 10 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Worthingin</LOCATION>, a twister leveled at
least three houses and damaged 13 farms, said <ORGANIZATION>Disaster Services
Director Dianne De Sotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``People were spotting them everywhere,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 1006EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-IllinoisTornadoes-Rescuers     08-29 0425</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Illinois Tornadoes-Rescuers,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescue Workers Find Bodies Amid Rubble of Tornadoes</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Illinois Tornadoes, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By COLLEEN DISKIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CREST HILL, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rescue workers alternated between
exhilaration at finding the living beneath beams and shattered
glass and despair over holding dead children in their arms as they
dug through the rubble left by tornadoes.
   ``It will be many nights before I have a good night's sleep
again,'' said Will County Executive <PERSON>Charles Adelman</PERSON>, who helped
comb a cornfield next to the <LOCATION>Crest Hill Lake</LOCATION> apartment complex.
   At least eight died at the complex <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as tornadoes skipped
through several northern <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> towns, killing at least 24 people
in <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, 40 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, neighboring Crest Hill,
and <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION>. At least 293 people were treated
at hospitals.
   Four of the dead, including a 4-month-old baby, were found flung
into the cornfield next to the nine-building apartment complex.
   ``People were literally blown out of the building,'' said Crest
Hill Mayor <PERSON>Don Randich</PERSON>. Two of the dead were found in cars nearby
and two others were found in the building's rubble.
   Six of the apartment buildings were gutted and three had parts
of their roofs blown away. Clothing, cars and appliances were
strewn across the landscape.
   ``When the storm went through ... some of the buildings were
disintegrated,'' said <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION> Fire Chief <PERSON>Dave Martis</PERSON>, who was in
charge of the rescue effort at the site.
   At least 150 volunteer rescue workers rushed to the site,
including officers from more than 30 area police and fire
departments, said <ORGANIZATION>Plainfield Police</ORGANIZATION> Chief <PERSON>Don Bennett</PERSON>.
   Rescuers went from apartment to apartment, throwing rubble off
of the three-story buildings with shovels _ or just their hands.
   Workers searched each building twice, sifting through debris
until well after dark.
   Volunteers aided by dogs, floodlights, cranes and bulldozers
looked for bodies. A <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter shone a floodlight
on the cornfield.
   Though some workers wanted to keep looking through the <TIME>night</TIME>,
<PERSON>Martis</PERSON> called off the effort at <TIME>9:30 p.m</TIME>. He said it was too dark
and dangerous to continue.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Guardsmen</ORGANIZATION> and fire officials resumed the search today.
   In <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION>, four people died, including three in a subdivision
where some houses were still under construction, said <ORGANIZATION>Joliet Police</ORGANIZATION>
Chief <PERSON>Dennis Nowicki</PERSON>.
   ``I had a little baby die in my arms ... and a little girl,''
said a <LOCATION>Joliet</LOCATION> paramedic who did not identify himself. ``The last
thing she said was she wanted her mommy, and her mommy was laying
there next to her dead, too.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900903-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-03-90 1623EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IllinoisTornadoes     09-03 0576</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Illinois Tornadoes,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>For Those Without Insurance, Tornado Aftermath Particularly Hard</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SARAH NORDGREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CREST HILL, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A rusty toaster, a child's plastic sand
bucket and some soggy clothes were just about all that an angry
twister left behind when it came to call on <PERSON>Carol Levenston</PERSON> and her
4-year-old son.
   While hundreds of other <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> tornado victims last week stood
in line to see their insurance agents, <LOCATION>Levenston</LOCATION>, whose second
child is due any day, pecked through the pile of rubble she once
called home.
   ``We had just really got started here,'' said <PERSON>Levenston</PERSON>, 30.
``We thought about (insurance) but we just never expected this to
come about.''
   The tornadoes killed 27 people and demolished more than 270
homes and 14 apartment buildings <DATE>last Tuesday</DATE> in the small towns of
<LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION>, some 30 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. An
additional 639 dwellings were damaged.
   By <DATE>week's end</DATE>, many residents were meeting with insurance
agents, calling building contractors and beginning to look to the
future.
   ``We're totally covered,'' said <PERSON>Scott Ellerbrock</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>.
   Ellerbrock joked he is ``31 years old going on 80,'' after the
storm left only two walls of his house intact. He said his
insurance agent had already issued him a check and that, for his
family, the worst was over.
   ``Take your best shot _ I can take it,'' the <ORGANIZATION>Dow Chemical Co.</ORGANIZATION>
worker said. ``I've been through hell and I made it.''
   Ellerbrock plans to rebuild on the same site _ this time a
larger house for his wife and two young children.
   Throughout the area, insurance agents scurried to meet demand
left in the wake of the twisters.Many residents praised the quick
response of their agents.
   ``They came out <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> _ figured it was a total loss
for me,'' said <PERSON>Richard Vogen</PERSON> as he carried a few chairs from his
three-bedroom home.
   Vogen said his agents issued him a check on the spot.
   Two disaster relief centers were set up by the state and federal
governments to assist some victims with loans and outright grants.
   The newly appointed director of the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Emergency Management
Agency</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Wallace Stickney</PERSON>, toured the disaster area <DATE>Monday</DATE> and
visited the two centers. <PERSON>Stickney</PERSON>, who also flew over the
devastation in a helicopter, praised the quick response of federal
and state emergency workers.
   ``We may be able to beat the response by a couple of hours next
time, but I think we've set a record here that's going to be hard
to match in the future,'' <PERSON>Stickney</PERSON> said.
   It is <PERSON>Stickney</PERSON>'s first major disaster since taking over <ORGANIZATION>FEMA</ORGANIZATION> two
weeks ago.
   <PERSON>Ron Buddecke</PERSON>, a regional <ORGANIZATION>FEMA</ORGANIZATION> official, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that the
agency antifipates serving a lot of people with insufficent
insurance or no insurance.
   Many residents of the modest Crestlakes Apartment complex in
<LOCATION>Crest Hill</LOCATION>, where at least nine of the fatalities occurred, said
their losses had not been covered.
   <PERSON>Paul Hendrix</PERSON>, 30, pulled ``a pillowcase full'' of clothes from
his apartment <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Hendrix said his losses were compounded by
looting on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE> while he was working at an auto
dealership.
   ``I couldn't even afford to take off,'' said <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>.
   Even for the insured, the road was not easy. In <LOCATION>Plainfield</LOCATION>, an
unidentified man wept as he pleaded over the phone with his
insurance company.
   ``You can't call me,'' the man said. ``I have no phone. My home
has been destroyed. I'm sorry. I'm upset.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890518-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-89 1416EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-StormsRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0558 05-18 0866</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Storms Rdp, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0558,0882</SECOND>
<HEAD>Twisters Skip Across Texas, More Rain in Forecast</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with fifth death, body found today;
tornado today in Houston; Picks up 5th graf, `Elsewhere, the...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AT1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAY JORDEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More rain fell today in the saturated South after
deadly storms unleashed more than 20 tornadoes across <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>,
shattering one town and forcing hundreds to leave their homes in
low-lying areas.
   One tornado killed a woman, and four people were swept to their
deaths in swollen creeks. The body of the fifth victim, a
12-year-old boy, was found in a creek west of <LOCATION>Ennis</LOCATION> today. Fifty
people suffered storm-related injuries.
   Thunderstorms lingered over southeastern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, eastern <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>
and western <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> <TIME>this morning</TIME>. Rain was forecast for today
from the <LOCATION>Mississippi Valley</LOCATION> across eastern parts of the <LOCATION>Central
Plains</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, eastern <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, western <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, western
<LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, western <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>.
   Although the severity of the thunderstorms over <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> lessened
<TIME>this morning</TIME>, new flash flood watches and warnings and some tornado
watches were posted throughout the state because of the likelihood
of more rain, especially in the <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> area. A tornado briefly
touched down in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE>, but there were no immediate reports
of damage.
   Elsewhere, the low pressure system that brought persistent rains
to the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> moved out to sea on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. But at least 100
families in northern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> remained in emergency shelters as
they waited for the <LOCATION>Passaic River</LOCATION> to crest today about two feet
above flood level.
   A predawn tornado <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> ravaged the small <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> town of
<LOCATION>Jarrell</LOCATION>, killing a woman who had been asleep in her mobile home.
The twister roared through the town of 1,000 people 40 miles from
<LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, demolishing 33 houses, 12 mobile homes and 16 businesses,
said <PERSON>David Barham</PERSON> of the state's emergency management office.
   Thirty-nine homes were damaged, along with the school gym roof.
   The tornado sheared utility poles, pulled down power lines,
uprooted trees, overturned several cars and trucks, including six
tractor-trailers on an interstate and spread debris along a
seven-mile path, authorities said.
   About two dozen people were injured and treated at hospitals.
   ``I heard a bolt of lightning and it wasn't more than five
minutes before all hell broke loose,'' said <PERSON>W.G. Schurhammer</PERSON>, whose
apartment house was damaged. ``By the time I heard it, I dove for
the corner and the windows broke.''
   A tornado <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> cut a quarter-mile-wide swath for
as much as 30 miles through east <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, destroying homes and
injuring at least nine people. A twister near <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> injured eight
people, authorities said.
   Another twister touched down six miles northwest of <LOCATION>Lufkin</LOCATION>,
destroying eight homes in <LOCATION>Allentown</LOCATION>, said <LOCATION>Angelina County</LOCATION> sheriff's
officers. At least nine people were injured, they said.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, flooding forced hundreds of <LOCATION>Dallas-Fort Worth</LOCATION> area
residents to leave their homes. Floodwaters caused a levee failure
along the <LOCATION>Trinity River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and rising tributaries were
forcing more evacuations today.
   ``You could hear the roar of the creek right behind our
trailers,'' said <PERSON>Don Reiter</PERSON>, who escaped high water <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Kennedale</LOCATION>. ``We didn't take anything because it came so fast. Our
cars are gone, our boats are gone. What we have on our back is just
what we have.''
   In south <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, a car driven by a 56-year-old woman stalled as
she tried to cross a bridge. Firefighters barricading the bridge
urged her not to attempt the crossing, said firefighter <ORGANIZATION>Dennis
Ground</ORGANIZATION>.
   Ground said the woman scrambled to the top of the car and was
told to stay there. But ``the water got so rough it just knocked
the car off. Whether she had been in it or on top of it, it still
would have occurred,'' Ground said.
   The body of 73-year-old Grand Prairie man was found in his
truck, which had been swept into a flooded creek branch. A man was
killed when his car was swept into <ORGANIZATION>McAnear Creek</ORGANIZATION> south of <LOCATION>Fort
Worth</LOCATION>.
   Rescuers plucked people from yards, trees and car tops. The
pilot of a radio station helicopter pulled two girls and their
mother from the roof of their car just before it was swept away in
a rain-swollen creek in <LOCATION>Cleburne</LOCATION>.
   Of the six emergency shelters opened by the <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Red Cross
<DATE>Wedenesday</DATE>, only two remained open <TIME>this morning</TIME>, said spokeswoman
<PERSON>Sandra Pomeroy</PERSON>. She didn't know how many people were in the
shelters, but said, ``We served 150 breakfasts today. We served 200
dinners <TIME>last night</TIME> and yesterday we served 300 lunches.''
   <PERSON>Bobby Valentine</PERSON>, manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> baseball team,
sought help from a radio station helicopter to reach two of his
horses that were trapped by rising waters behind his <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>
home.
   He was able to lead the horses to safety, but his son's pony
drowned.
   ``It was something, jumping off the helicopter into water
waist-deep,'' <PERSON>Valentine</PERSON> said.
   In some parts of the state, more than 6 inches of rain fell,
boosting monthly precipitation totals already far above average.
The <LOCATION>Dallas-Fort Worth</LOCATION> area has received 9.62 inches of rain for the
month. The area average is 4.5 inches and the record for <DATE>May</DATE> is
13.66 inches.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890609-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-09-89 1125EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Tornadoes 2ndLd-Writethru a0522 06-09 0793</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tornadoes, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0522,0814</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornado Hits Florida Town, Killing Three; Two Dead In Louisiana</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with detail, quote from Florida,
picking up 3rd graf pvs, `We can't...'. SUBS grafs 18 to end, bgng `Most
of...' with 8 with more detail from Florida, and storm damage in Alabama.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NU2; Florida LaserPhoto upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Officials in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> today mourned five people
killed in storms but said they were lucky that powerful twisters
blasting out of <ORGANIZATION>Gulf</ORGANIZATION> thunderstorms hadn't caused more fatalities.
   One tornado <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> wracked the <LOCATION>Florida Panhandle</LOCATION> fishing
village of <ORGANIZATION>Eastpoint</ORGANIZATION>, killing three members of a family. It
destroyed 19 houses and narrowly missed a nursing home.
   ``We haven't found the house (where the family died) yet. Their
bodies were found several hundred yards from where the house once
was,'' said <PERSON>Pat McWhinnie</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Franklin County</LOCATION> sheriff's dispatcher.
   In <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, cleanup efforts began today in the wake of <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME>'s storms. Tornadoes hit seven parishes in the southern part
of the state, killing two people in mobile homes in the town of
<ORGANIZATION>Grosse Tete</ORGANIZATION> and damaging scores of homes there and 15 miles east in
<LOCATION>Baton Rouge</LOCATION>.
   ``We can't imagine how more aren't dead,'' said <PERSON>Willie Hurdle</PERSON>, an
<LOCATION>Iberville</LOCATION> Parish official who surveyed the scene at <ORGANIZATION>Grosse Tete</ORGANIZATION>.
``This is devastating. There's about 20 houses that aren't even here
anymore.''
   About two dozen others were injured in the tornado.
   Police sealed the town off to prevent looting and used dogs to
search the rubble for bodies or survivors.
   Officials used a chain saw to free an elderly woman from the
wreckage of her home.
   Gov. Buddy <PERSON>Roemer</PERSON> toured the area by helicopter. He said two
companies of <ORGANIZATION>Louisiana National Guard</ORGANIZATION> soldiers would be sent to help
authorities enforce a night curfew to discourage looters.
   Baton Rouge Fire Chief <PERSON>Ron Spillman</PERSON> said four tornadoes touched
down 19 times in <LOCATION>East Baton Rouge Parish</LOCATION>, destroying or damaging
almost 70 mobile homes and 25 to 30 houses.
   From 400 to 600 people lived in the destroyed or damaged
residences, <PERSON>Spillman</PERSON> estimated. A shelter was set up at a high
school for those left homeless.
   <PERSON>Kimberly Carver</PERSON> was asleep in her mobile home at the <ORGANIZATION>Pecue Lake
Mobile Home Park</ORGANIZATION> when one of the twisters ripped through the
neighborhood.
   ``Somehow, I just ended up between the mattress and box springs.
Everything in my bedroom was flying. If I wasn't between the
mattress and the box <DATE>spring</DATE>, I would have gotten hurt. It happened
so fast,'' <PERSON>Carver</PERSON> said.
   Authorities reported three injuries in <LOCATION>Baton Rouge</LOCATION>, none serious.
   <ORGANIZATION>Gulf State Utilities</ORGANIZATION> crews worked into the morning to restore
power to about 3,500 residents in the <LOCATION>Baton Rouge</LOCATION> area.
   <PERSON>John Boss</PERSON>, a photographer for the State-Times in <LOCATION>Baton Rouge</LOCATION>, and
<PERSON>Rita F. Gilmer</PERSON> were caught in the middle of the storm near a bridge
over the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>.
   ``Two houses blew up right across the levee from where we were,''
he said. ``Limbs were snapping off trees and flying all over us. We
were afraid we were going to be hit by all the debris. I was scared
to death. It was hell.''
   In <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Franklin County Sheriff Warren Roddenberry</ORGANIZATION> said
<DATE>today</DATE>, ``We were extremely lucky. The devastation we've had and no
more than three fatalities and two minor injuries is just amazing.''
   A grandmother, mother and son died when the tornado hit their
home in <ORGANIZATION>Eastpoint</ORGANIZATION>, about 85 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Tallahassee</LOCATION>.
   Most of the demolished houses in <ORGANIZATION>Eastpoint</ORGANIZATION> were mobile homes,
officials said. Eight cars and several utility sheds also were
destroyed. A hardware store lost its roof, and a boat building
business was demolished.
   ``It was monstrous _ like the tornado in the `Wizard of Oz,' ''
said <PERSON>Tracey Hardman</PERSON> after seeing the twister. ``It was awesome.''
   The tornados were the worst to hit the <LOCATION>Panhandle</LOCATION> in three years,
said <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Ray Lowe</PERSON>.
   Earlier <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> park ranger was hurt when a tornado
carried away the shelter at <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Islands National Seashore</ORGANIZATION> in which
she had taken refuge. <PERSON>Amanda Rhodes</PERSON> suffered a broken arm and cuts
when she was blown 10 to 15 yards. The 20-by-30-foot wood-frame
entrance station was demolished, officials said.
   Elsewhere in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, another tornado ripped the roof from a
grocery store near <LOCATION>Perdido Key</LOCATION>, southwest of <LOCATION>Pensacola</LOCATION>, causing at
estimated <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> in damage, said <PERSON>Cheryl Lively</PERSON>,
spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>Escambia County Emergency Operations Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Another tornado demolished a home near the neighboring
communities of <PERSON>Holley</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Navarre</LOCATION> about 20 miles east of <LOCATION>Pensacola</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Santa Rosa County</LOCATION> authorities said. No injuries were reported.
   Tornados and thunderstorms also swept through coastal <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>,
damaging dozens of homes, but no serious injuries were reported,
authorities said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881128-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-28-88 1018EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Tornadoes-RaleighShelters     11-28 0508</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tornadoes-Raleigh Shelters,0524</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tornadoes Leave Raleigh Residents Shaken</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Storm Rdp and PM-Tornadoes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOBBS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RALEIGH, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Tony DeVita</PERSON> still clutched his ``tornado
pillow'' hours after killer storms ripped through the <LOCATION>Raleigh</LOCATION> area
today, killing five people and injuring about 150 others.
   The tornadoes scoured a five-mile path through the heavily
populated northern section of <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>'s capital city and its
suburbs before leaping to neighboring counties. Along the way, the
tornadoes ripped up <ORGANIZATION>DeVita</ORGANIZATION>'s town house.
   ``It sounded like a rush of water, followed by a bunch of
shaking,'' <PERSON>DeVita</PERSON> said. ``The roof was totally gone, the patio doors
were gone and every window was smashed. The carpet was rolled up
like someone was going to replace it.''
   DeVita, 34, grabbed a pillow and got behind his bedroom door. He
still held the pillow during an interview at a shelter in a central
<LOCATION>Raleigh</LOCATION> school.
   Forty-six people stayed at the shelter after the storms hit
between <TIME>1 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>
   ``If you felt a big, hot hair dryer blowing by you and the whole
place was shaking apart and if this (pillow) was the only thing that
protected your face, you'd hold onto it,'' <PERSON>DeVita</PERSON> said, calling it
his ``tornado pillow.''
   ``I had to dig my way out'' from the corner of the room, he said.
``I was kind of buried in rubble. In fact, I later found plaster in
my ears.''
   DeVita left his town house wearing only pajamas. He borrowed
clothes from neighbors _ a pink jacket from one, gray sweatpants
from another and socks from someone at the shelter. He still was
without shoes.
   Residents of the complex where he lived were told to evacuate
because of a gas leak. Mayor <PERSON>Avery Upchurch</PERSON> said at midmorning that
the danger of gas leaks had passed.
   DeVita and others weren't allowed to drive out because of the
leak, so they walked and waited for buses to take them to the
shelter.
   Elsewhere, when the sun rose, dazed residents emerged to survey
the destruction.
   ``My God, my God,'' said <PERSON>Ellie Sprankel</PERSON>, as she stood on a ridge
for a sweeping view of her town house subdivision and an adjacent
apartment complex in <LOCATION>north Raleigh</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Sprankle</PERSON> said she had lived eight years in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and was
accustomed to tornado watches and warnings but had never experienced
one.
   ``They used to tell me it's like a freight train coming, but what
it's really like is a train on top of you,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Carolyn Davis</PERSON> surveyed her two-story town house by candle light
before sunrise. A large pine tree had slammed into her roof and its
top protruded through the ceiling into a bedroom.
   ``My insurance company is going to love this,'' she said. ``One
month, I've been here just one month. I can't believe it.''
   <PERSON>Jerry Thornton</PERSON> gasped in disbelief when he saw that a section of
his town house roof was gone.
   ``I didn't need to see that,'' <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON> said. ``What a way to end
the Thanksgiving weekend.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900604-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-04-90 1100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MidwestStorms 1stLd-Writethru a0480 06-04 0829</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Midwest Storms, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0480,0848</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storms Follow Worst Indiana Tornadoes in 16 Years; Death Toll 14</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with second boy dying in Indiana,
death toll up to 14 nationwide, governors seeking federal aid,
UPDATES and CORRECTS Indiana death toll from 8 to 10; clarifies that
damage in Illinois not limited to two counties named. Picks up 8th
graf pvs, `In Albion...'. INSERTS 1 graf after 17th graf pvs, `More
severe ..., to include car pileup; picking up 18th graf, `At least
...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CS2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CONNIE CASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Tornadoes and thunderstorms throughout the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> killed 14
people, injured scores and left hundreds more homeless. Ten of the
dead were in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, where about 50 twisters touched down.
   The most disastrous tornado tore a five-mile swath through the
southwestern <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Petersburg</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. It killed six
people, injured at least 57 and destroyed more than 150 homes.
   ``It looked to me like there had been a bombing run made right
