<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1110EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Quake-County-Glance 1stLd-Writethru   10-18 0363</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quake-County-Glance, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0621,0370</SECOND>
<HEAD>County-by-County Damages, Deaths and Injuries</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, San Francisco ...' to UPDATE number of deaths
to nine sted eight and injuries to more than 200 sted 100.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a county-by-county summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and reporter
observations:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here is a county-by-county summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and reporter
observations:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 0221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Quake-Glance     10-18 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Quake-Glance,0615</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-SF Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE QUAKE:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CASUALTIES:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DAMAGE:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>GOVERNMENT RESPONSE:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD SERIES:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a look at the earthquake that jolted <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1936EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake-TownByTown 1stLd-Writethru a0817obert-Drugs
10-18 0587</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-Town By Town, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0817,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Town By Town Damages, Deaths and Injuries</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES and provides additional details throughout.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-SF Quake Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>OAKLAND</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>RICHMOND</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SAN FRANCISCO</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SAN MATEO</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>REDWOOD CITY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>BURLINGAME</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SAN JOSE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SANTA CRUZ</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>LOS GATOS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WATSONVILLE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>HOLLISTER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MONTEREY COUNTY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MARIN COUNTY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a town-by-town summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and observations:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 0930EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SFQuake 3rdLd-Writethru-2Takes a0567-71-74 10-18 1262</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SF Quake, 3rd Ld - Writethru - 2 Takes, a0567-71-74,1291</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>PRECEDE San Francisco</HEAD>
<HEAD>Nation's Deadliest Earthquake Since 1906 Hits Northern California</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 18 grafs to UPDATE with rescue efforts today, new
fatality, injury counts, additional detail; combines pvs into 2 takes.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic, LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Aftershocks continued today as rescuers
struggled to free motorists from an elevated highway collapsed by
an earthquake that jarred <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>, killing more than
270 people and injuring hundreds more.
   The quake <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, measuring 6.9 on the Richter scale,
collapsed buildings across the region as well as a section of the
<LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION> and at least two spans in the
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> area. Severed gas lines sparked fires, including one in
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> that burned a block of buildings.
   The magnitude of the catastrophe emerged slowly as officials
made contact with hard-hit areas, where many telephones were cut
off. As many as 1 million people were left without power and other
services.
   ``This is just a devastating, terrible, terrible situation
beyond everybody's imagination,'' said <PERSON>Marty Boyer</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Alameda
County</LOCATION> spokesman.
   Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> <TIME>this morning</TIME> put the death toll at 271.
State emergency services spokesman <PERSON>John Peterson</PERSON> said at least 272
people had died and 650 were injured. At least 253 people were
killed when a half-mile section of the upper level of Interstate
880 in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> collapsed onto the lower level, said <PERSON>Dave Wilson</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>state Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You could hear it crunching down _ but you couldn't see
anything. It was just a big white cloud,'' said <PERSON>Leroy FitzGerald</PERSON>,
who works nearby. ``You could hear people screaming for help.''
   Tractors, bulldozers and dump trucks were called out, and trucks
and vans took bodies from the site <TIME>this morning</TIME>.
   The quake hit at <TIME>5:04 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesay</DATE> along a segment of the might
<LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION> eight miles northeast of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> and 75 miles
south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Aftershocks today included one measuring
4.5 on the Richter scale at <TIME>3:25 a.m.</TIME>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>National
Earthquake Information Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Golden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said damage would total ``the better part of a <MONEY>billion
dollars</MONEY>.''
   ``You could see dozens, huge booms of smoke going into the
air,'' said <PERSON>Greg Higgins</PERSON>, who was driving near <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, close to
the quake's epicenter, when it struck. ``It was complete
pandemonium.''
   The quake sent thousands of terrified office workers rushing
into the streets of <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, and many remained
stranded hours later.
   ``I've never been through anything like this in my life,'' said
<PERSON>Mary Garcia</PERSON>, who works in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> building. ``I was on the
17th floor and the building just rocked and rocked. I was scared
out of my mind coming down the 17 floors.''
   Authorities urged people to fill their bathtubs in case water
was cut off. <LOCATION>San Francisco Mayor Art Agnos</LOCATION> urged commuters to stay
home today rather than further taxing the transportation system,
crippled by the closing of the Bay Bridge. A section of its top
collapsed onto the lower roadway.
   At least two bridges in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> area collapsed, highways
leading out of the city were damaged, and mountain passes outside
of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> were closed because of landslides and fissures in the
road, the <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, at least eight people died, and looting and
vandalism were reported in the city's major crack dealing area
after dark. ``When the power is off, opportunists come out,''
police <PERSON>Dispatcher Chris Curran</PERSON> said.
   Agnos asked the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> to help. National Guardsmen were being
mobilized, including engineers, military police and medical workers.
   Still, <PERSON>Agnos</PERSON> said, ``The city is in reasonably good shape. We've
survived this so far.''
   Sixty-thousand baseball fans were evacuated from <LOCATION>Candlestick
Park</LOCATION> before the start of Game Three of the World Series. No major
injuries were reported at the stadium, which sustained structural
damage, and there was no word <TIME>this morning</TIME> on when the game would
be played.
   Fire engines and ambulances, sirens howling, picked their way
through a darkened <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Headlights and an occasional
office building running on emergency generators stood out. Buses
were jammed and traffic was backed up.
   Commuters were left with no major transportation routes east out
of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> because of the closing of the Bay Bridge, two
other spans and the <LOCATION>Oakland-San Francisco</LOCATION> subway, which apparently
was unscathed by the quake.
   Tourist ferries helped fill the void, giving stranded commuters
free rides from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION>.
   People walked around <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, sat outside dingy hotels or
on stoops and curbs, listening to radio reports of the disaster.
Without power, there was no television. Restaurants and bars opened
with candlelight.
   Agnos said five people died in the city after buildings
collapsed on cars, and three died in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION>
district in a spectacular fire that burned much of the evening
before being brought under control.
   Up to 20 people were hurt in the fire, officials said.
   Police Chief <PERSON>Fred Jordan</PERSON> said the fire appeared to have consumed
an entire block, estimated by Agnos to be 12 buildings. The fire
apparently was caused by a natural gas leak, <PERSON>Agnos</PERSON> said.
   State emergency officials said at least five people died in
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz County</LOCATION>, including three crushed in collapsing buildings.
   One San Jose resident suffered a heart attack during the quake
and died.
   <PERSON>Willis Jacobs</PERSON> of the earthquake center said the quake was
centered about eight miles northeast of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, or 75 miles
south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, along the <LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION>. That is the
major earthquake fault blamed for the <DATE>1906</DATE> disaster that destroyed
much of the city and killed hundreds _ 700, according to
traditional estimates, and more than 2,500, according to recent
studies.
   In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s Haight-Fillmore district, cracks were visible
on some stoops and buildings, some in the stucco and some
structural. Many buildings in the neighborhood are Victorian-style
homes that survived the <DATE>1906</DATE> earthquake.
   A 30-foot section of the upper deck of the bridge connecting
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> collapsed, leaving three cars dangling
between the levels.
   <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>California Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> reported a <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney</ORGANIZATION>
building in downtown <PERSON>Hollister</PERSON> collapsed, as did a bridge on a
highway near <LOCATION>Hollister</LOCATION>.
   Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> cut short a trade mission to <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, and flew home. ``The devastation is just horrible and
we're just shocked,'' <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> said before returning.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> dispatched <ORGANIZATION>Transportation</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary <PERSON>Samuel Skinner</PERSON> to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to assess the damage. Vice
President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> landed early today at <ORGANIZATION>Moffett Naval Air
Station</ORGANIZATION>, between <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
   The quake was felt in <LOCATION>Reno</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, 225 miles to the northeast; as
far north as the <LOCATION>Russian River</LOCATION> area, 70 miles to the north; 180
miles southeast in <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION> and 80 miles due east in <LOCATION>Stockton</LOCATION>.
High-rises in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 350 miles south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, also
shook.
   At least four smaller aftershocks were recorded, said <PERSON>Bruce
Presgrave</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Earthquake Information Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Golden</LOCATION>.
More were expected, but <PERSON>Presgrave</PERSON> said he did not expect them to be
strong.
   There were no reports of damage to the Golden Gate Bridge that
connects <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>, to the north. The <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>
bridge, which crosses 10 miles south of <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION>, was
closed for inspection, as was the <ORGANIZATION>Dumbarton Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, about 30 miles
south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Oakland Airport</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>San Francisco International Airport</LOCATION>
were both closed. The <LOCATION>San Jose International Airport</LOCATION> was open with
only minor damage.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1152EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Quake-Glance 1stLd-Writethru a0480 10-18 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quake-Glance, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0480,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-SF Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with developments.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE QUAKE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CASUALTIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DAMAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>LOOTING</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FEDERAL GOVERNMENT</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD REACTION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD SERIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a summary of developments in the earthquake that rocked
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881215-0201 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-15-88 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-WindProblems 1stLd-Writethru a0697 12-15 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wind Problems, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0697,0789</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane-Force Winds Bash California; 1 Dead, 300,000 Without
Power</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with more than 440,000 electric
customers affected, homecoming for aircraft carrier delayed, two
highways closed due to snow; picks up 8th graf, `The winds...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANTHONY MARQUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Howling winds clocked at up to 102 mph
battered <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, claiming at least one
life, overturning trucks, toppling trees and cutting power to more
than 440,000 electric customers.
   The winds littered scenic <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> with downed power
lines, branches and trash, and authorities closed dangerous highways
and issued travel warnings.
   The <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> waterfront was ravaged by the winds, which
tore yachts adrift, sank several and sent waves up to 10 feet high
slamming into seawalls. A 60-foot floating dock at <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s
Pier 43 sank.
   ``We've had lots of trees knocked down, power outages and phone
problems,'' said <PERSON>Dan Nicholas</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Sonoma County Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Santa Rosa</LOCATION>, north of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. ``Some homes have been damaged
to the point where the people had to be evacuated and put up in
motels overnight.''
   Three-year-old <PERSON>Oli Asghar</PERSON> died <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> apartment
fire sparked by a candle used because of a wind-caused power outage.
His parents and three brothers and sisters were left homeless, fire
officials said.
   Some 442,000 <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION> customers throughout
<LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> were left in the dark by the winds, said
officials for the utility whose repair crews worked through the
<TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``This is definitely ... one of the largest outages because of
the velocity of the winds,'' said <ORGANIZATION>PG&amp;E</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Ron Rutkowski</PERSON>.
   The winds also delayed the aircraft carrier USS <PERSON>Carl Vinson</PERSON> from
reaching its dock in <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>. The carrier was scheduled to
arrive <DATE>Thursday</DATE> following a six-month tour, but <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> officials
postponed the homecoming until <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Winds weren't the only weather problem in <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>.
Driving snow <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> forced the closure of Highway 101
from <PERSON>Paso Robles</PERSON> to <PERSON>San Luis Obispo</PERSON>, a 30-mile stretch about 230
miles south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   The winds were caused by the strong flow of air from a high
pressure system over <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION> to a low pressure center in
<LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>
meteorologist <PERSON>Randy Hartley</PERSON>.
   In northern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, the same ``upper air'' weather system brought
gusting winds up to 115 mph to northern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, said meteorologist
<PERSON>Bill Alder</PERSON>. Winds there felled power lines, toppled tractor-trailer
trucks, delayed mail deliveries, closed schools and fanned several
brush fires early <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Utah Power &amp; Light Co.</ORGANIZATION> crews worked into the afternoon to restore
electricity at the sites of scattered outages throughout a
four-county area.
   UP&amp;L spokesman <PERSON>Dave Mead</PERSON> said he had no firm estimate on the
number of people left without electricity, but said ``you certainly
would be safe saying several thousand.''
   In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, power lines strewn across heavily traveled
<LOCATION>Lakeville</LOCATION> Highway near <LOCATION>Petaluma</LOCATION>, about 40 miles north of <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>, forced authorities to close it overnight. Two private
planes at the <LOCATION>Petaluma</LOCATION> airport apparently were damaged by the winds,
said <PERSON>Nicholas</PERSON>.
   About 3,000 <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> personnel aboard the USS <PERSON>Carl Vinson</PERSON>, returning
from a six-month deployment to the <LOCATION>Western Pacific</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Indian Ocean and
North Arabian Sea</ORGANIZATION>, had their holiday port call delayed several hours
because of the winds.
   Petty Officer <PERSON>John Gwinn</PERSON>, aboard the huge ship, said he was eager
to reach shore where his wife, <PERSON>Sheree</PERSON>, and 3-month-old son, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON>,
were waiting.
   ``For me, it's hard. I've never seen my kid,'' he said.
   Winds clocked at more than 50 mph howled around <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>
waterfronts, and the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> was kept busy retrieving small
boats torn from their moorings. Sausalito police said a tugboat sank
early <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Famed attorney <PERSON>Melvin Belli</PERSON>'s 110-foot motor yacht ``Adequate
Award'' was also damaged when a boat dragged its anchor across
<LOCATION>Richardson Bay</LOCATION> and slammed into it at <ORGANIZATION>Schoonmaker Marina</ORGANIZATION>.
   A controlled-burn fire in <LOCATION>Tuolumne County</LOCATION> flared because of the
winds and burned 100 acres on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Several small fires were
also reported in the <ORGANIZATION>Stanislaus National Forest</ORGANIZATION>.
   Other wind-related problems included malfunctioning elevators in
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, delayed flights and re-routed air traffic at <LOCATION>San
Francisco International Airport</LOCATION> and closure of the Richmond-San
Rafael Bridge to pickups with camper shells and other broad-sided
vehicles.
   The winds, blowing northward, were clocked at 102 mph early
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> atop Mt. Diablo about 40 miles east of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, where
remote sensing gear is located, said meteorologist <PERSON>Mike Pechner</PERSON>. The
wind hit 80 mph <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. Hurricane force winds are 74 mph or
greater.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891017-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-89 2158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake 6thLd-Writethru a0817 10-17 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0817,0894</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CBS says one dead, major damage. new quotes.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Earthquake Rocks San Francisco</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphoto NY56, Others Upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICH CARTIERE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A violent earthquake rocked <LOCATION>Northern
California</LOCATION> during <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>'s rush hour, caving in a section
of the <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, terrifying World Series fans in
<LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION> and shaking buildings as far as 200 miles away.
   CBS-TV reported one person had been killed on the bridge. There
were no other immediate confirmed reports of deaths or injuries,
but ABC-TV and CNN both said some people were injured at
<LOCATION>Candlestick</LOCATION>, where the game was canceled and fans were evacuated.
   It was not immediately clear how extensive the damage was from
the quake, which struck at <TIME>5:04 p.m. PDT</TIME> and registered 6.9 on the
Richter scale. It was centered near <LOCATION>Hollister</LOCATION>, 80 miles southeast
of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Benito County</LOCATION>.
   ``The thing struck just as everyone was going home,'' said <PERSON>Tom
Mullins</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>California Office of Emergency
Services</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>. ``We've got reports coming in from <LOCATION>San
Benito</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> counties of heavy damage.''
   <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>California Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> reported a <ORGANIZATION>J.C. Penney</ORGANIZATION>
building in downtown <PERSON>Hollister</PERSON> collapsed and a bridge on Highway
   There were unconfirmed reports that a shopping mall collapsed in
<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, 50 miles south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>San Francisco Airport</LOCATION> was evacuated, and some people there were
hit with falling plaster.
   One major fire was blazing in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Marina District</LOCATION>
and another near the library at <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at
<LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>. A huge plume of smoke visible for miles over <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>.
   Hundreds of people fled <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Rapid Transit</ORGANIZATION> subway and
elevated stations in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> suburbs. The system
was shut down.
   Televised footage of the bridge connecting <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> showed that a 30-foot section of the upper deck had
collapsed, leaving two cars dangling between the two levels.
Reports said most occupants got out of their cars safely.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said the federal government was
prepared to send help to the earthquake area in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and he
the damage.
   At <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> a radio reporter told listeners,
``The entire building started to shake ... you could hear people
yelling and screaming all over the building.''
   She said there were ``obvious problems'' at the health
department across the street. ``Water was literally gushing out of
the building from a window on the second floor,'' the unidentified
reporter said.
   Citizens of <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION>, north of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, were warned to shut
off their gas because the smell of gas was all over town.
   <PERSON>Frank Baldwin</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey's Earthquake Center</ORGANIZATION> said
the quake's magnitude was 6.9 on the Richter scale. It occurred at
<TIME>5:04 p.m. PDT</TIME> and was centered in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, area, 75
miles south of <LOCATION>San Francico</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION>.
   The quake was felt as far away as <ORGANIZATION>Reno</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, 225 miles to the
northeast.
   The quake knocked out phones and power, including electricity at
<ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> bureau in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION> bridge, which crosses the bay about 10 miles south
of <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION> was closed for inspection.
   <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Police Officer <PERSON>Dwayne Collins</PERSON> said there were
reports that buildings and statues in the historic <LOCATION>South of Market</LOCATION>
district near downtown had collapsed.
   ``I thought I was losing my balance, then I saw the lamppost
sway one foot each direction. Then I saw falling glass, broken
glass on the street, but luckily not near me, `` said Les Galvacs
who was walking down Market Street in downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>David Balague</PERSON>, 22, was on the 14th floor of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of America</ORGANIZATION>
building. ``I've never been so scared. People were fighting to get
under the desks.''
   Fans at Candlestick screamed as the stadium swayed shortly
before the <LOCATION>San Francisco Giants</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Athletics</ORGANIZATION> were to have
begun the third game of the World Series.
   ``This upper deck was absolutely shaking, the light stanchions
were blowing back and forth, phones have gone out,'' <PERSON>Suzyn Waldman</PERSON>,
a reporter covering the World Series for WFAN-AM in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> told
listeners shortly after the quake hit. ``Everyone is standing
around here, people in the upper deck absolutely terrified to move
not knowing what to do.''
   A man in <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>, southwest of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, told a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
radio station, ``My house is OK, but everything in it is gone. My
refrigerator is standing in the middle of the kitchen.'' He said
10,000 gallons of water from his swimming pool crashed through his
picture window into his home.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude. Thus a reading of 7.5 reflects an earthquake 10 times
stronger than one of 6.5.
   An earthquake of 6 on the scale can cause severe damage. A 7
reading is a ``major'' earthquake, capable of widespread heavy
damage. The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> earthquake of <DATE>1906</DATE>, which occurred before
the Richter scale was devised, has been estimated at 8.3 on the
Richter scale.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1741EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SFQuake 13thLd-Writethru a0787 10-18 1293</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SF Quake, 13th Ld-Writethru, a0787,1327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nation's Deadliest Earthquake Since 1906 Hits Northern California</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, At least ... million residents., and 22nd graf,
State emergency ... were injured., to UPDATE with 1,400 injured; SUBS 27th
graf, The quake ... Richter scale., to UPDATE aftershocks information.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphics, LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARY McGRATH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OAKLAND, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Aftershocks to <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s killer quake
shook the battered <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> area today as work crews gave
up hope of finding anyone alive beneath a wrecked freeway and
stunned Californians struggled to put order back in their lives.
the catastrophic earthquake, which in 15 seconds wrecked buildings
across nearly 100 miles. A section of the Bay Bridge and at least
two spans near <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> fell, and electric power was cut for as
many as 1 million residents.
   Severed gas lines touched off fires, including one in <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> that burned a block of buildings, but all the blazes were
out or under control today.
   Extensive damage was reported in parts of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San
Benito</LOCATION> counties 70 miles to the south, which were closest to the
epicenter of the earthquake.
   The quake, 6.9 on the Richter scale, was the second-deadliest in
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history, surpassed only by the great <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> earthquake
of <DATE>1906</DATE>, when 2,500 or more were killed.
   The magnitude of the disaster emerged slowly today as officials
made contact with hard-hit areas _ outlying suburbs and towns where
many telephones were cut off.
   ``The devastation is just horrible,'' said Gov. <PERSON>George
Deukmejian</PERSON>, who cut short a trade mission to <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. Lt. Gov.
<PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> said damage would total ``the better part of <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>.''
   <LOCATION>San Francisco Mayor Art Agnos</LOCATION> urged commuters to stay home
rather than tax the transportation system, crippled by the closing
of the Bay Bridge. But as dawn spread over the glass-strewn streets
of the region, people tried to revive a sense of normalcy, some
making their way to work by ferry, by foot or over highways not
blocked by damage. The Bay Area Rapid Transit system reopened <TIME>this
morning</TIME>, as did the <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> airports.
   Many people stayed home, however, their workplaces shut down in
the quake's aftermath. Most schools and many other institutions
were closed as well.
   <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s financial district was unusually quiet. The
<ORGANIZATION>Pacific Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> opened, but business was slow as traders
worked by candlelight, flashlight and light filtering through
skylights.
   Traffic was light on bridges into <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and in most city
neighborhoods.
   A <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> city councilman, <PERSON>Bill Maher</PERSON>, said electric power
had been restored to about two-thirds of the city by morning and
should be fully restored by the end of the day.
   ``The city is in reasonably good shape,'' <PERSON>Agnos</PERSON> said. ``We've
survived this so far.''
   The mayor estimated 40 buildings in the city were unusable or
severely damaged.
   Pacific <PERSON>Bell</PERSON> said its telephone network suffered no significant
damage, but the system was being overloaded by a huge increase in
calls into and out of the region.
   In a grimly futile operation near <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s bayfront, crews
worked to clear concrete debris and searched for victims along a
mile-long portion of Interstate 880, the <ORGANIZATION>Nimitz Freeway</ORGANIZATION>, whose
upper level collapsed on a lower roadway crowded with rush hour
traffic.
   <PERSON>Dave Wilson</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>state Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION> said at
least 253 people died in the highway disaster. Authorities declined
to say how many bodies had been recovered, but said they based
their estimate on the number of cars believed crushed in the
debris. They said seven victims had been identified.
   Some people were pulled alive from the wreckage after the quake,
but <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Lionel Wilson</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> searchers believed no
more survivors remained.
   Tractors, bulldozers and dump trucks were called out <TIME>this
morning</TIME>, and trucks and vans took bodies from the site.
   ``You could hear it crunching down _ but you couldn't see
anything. It was just a big white cloud,'' witness <PERSON>Leroy FitzGerald</PERSON>
said of the collapse. ``You could hear people screaming for help.''
level also collapsed, dropping onto a lower roadway and leaving
three cars dangling.
   State emergency services spokesman <PERSON>Tom Mullins</PERSON> said at
midafternoon that at least 272 people had died overall and 1,400
were injured.
   The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> coroner's office said <DATE>today</DATE> it had confirmed
10 earthquake-related deaths. Authorities reported five deaths in
<LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION> and one in <LOCATION>San Mateo County</LOCATION>, areas just to the
south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   Officials in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz County</LOCATION> said five people were killed
around the coastal city of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> signed a disaster-relief
declaration and said ``we will take every step and make every
effort'' to help. Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Transportation</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary <PERSON>Samuel Skinner</PERSON> flew over the area for about an hour today
to survey the damage.
   The president said he would make a personal inspection in a few
days. <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> officials said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> probably would go on <DATE>Friday</DATE>
or <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The quake hit at <TIME>5:04 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> along a segment of the huge
<LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION> eight miles northeast of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> and 75 miles
south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Dozens of aftershocks followed, including
one that measured 5.9 on the Richter scale shortly after the main
shock.
   The quake was felt in <LOCATION>Reno</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, 225 miles to the northeast,
and high-rises shook in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 350 miles south of <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>.
   Forty buildings reportedly collapsed in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Santa Cruz County</LOCATION> emergency services coordinator <PERSON>Dina
Phillips</PERSON> estimated <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY> in damage. <PERSON>Lori Aldrete</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>California Association of Hospitals</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> said the
<ORGANIZATION>Watsonville Community Hospital</ORGANIZATION> was evacuated, but no other details
were available.
   In <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>, about 10 miles southwest of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, Police Chief
<PERSON>Larry Todd</PERSON> said many buildings had collapsed, and there were some
reports of looting.
   At least two bridges in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> area collapsed, highways
leading out of the city were damaged, and mountain passes outside
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> were closed due to landslides and fissures in the road,
the <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The quake sent thousands of terrified office workers rushing
into the streets of <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   ``I've never been through anything like this in my life,'' said
<PERSON>Mary Garcia</PERSON>, who works in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION> building. ``I was on the
17th floor and the building just rocked and rocked. I was scared
out of my mind coming down the 17 floors.''
   Looting and vandalism were reported in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s major
crack dealing area, along Third Street. ``When the power is off,
opportunists come out,'' said police <PERSON>Dispatcher Chris Curran</PERSON>.
   Agnos asked the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> to help. National Guardsmen were being
mobilized, including engineers, military police and medical workers.
   Sixty-thousand baseball fans were evacuated from <LOCATION>Candlestick
Park</LOCATION> before the start of Game Three of the World Series. No major
injuries were reported at the stadium, which sustained structural
damage. Baseball Commissioner <PERSON>Fay Vincent</PERSON> said no decision had been
made on when or where to resume the Series.
   There were no reports of damage to the state's six nuclear
reactors, said <PERSON>Greg Cook</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Nuclear Regulatory Commission</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
   The 6.9 Richter reading made this the sixth-most powerful quake
to strike <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> this century, and the most powerful since a
7.0 quake centered in <LOCATION>Eureka</LOCATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude. An earthquake of 6 can cause severe damage. A 7 is a
``major'' quake, capable of widespread heavy damage. The <DATE>1906</DATE>
earthquake, which occurred before the scale was devised, has been
estimated at 8.3.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881216-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-16-88 1041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Quake-Storms 2ndLd-Writethru a0505 12-16 0855</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quake-Storms, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0505,0874</SECOND>
<BYLINE>Earthquake Rattles Southern California, High Winds To The North</BYLINE>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with power outages in Southern
California, forecasters predicting more foul weather; Picks up 8th
graf, `The earthquake ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHLEEN MACLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A moderate earthquake rattled <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> a day after
snow and sleet blanketed the fire-blackened region, while
hurricane-force winds pounded <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>, cutting power to
hundreds of thousands and leading to three children's deaths.
   The winds, clocked at up to 102 mph, died down <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
shortly before the temblor hit 500 miles to the southeast in a state
suffering in recent weeks from an attack of nature's worst elements.
   The winds fanned fires, uprooted trees and overturned trucks.
More than 575,000 <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Gas &amp; Electric Co.</ORGANIZATION> customers lost power
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, said utility spokeswoman <PERSON>Jan Stewart</PERSON>.
By <DATE>late Thursday</DATE>, 22,000 remained without electricity. The wind also
knocked out power to more than 14,000 people in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>.
   Two people died as dozens of cars crashed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in 10
accidents along ice-slick Interstate 15 in the Cajon Pass 55 miles
east of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>John Savage</PERSON>.
   ``One of the problems is here we don't have the snow equipment to
take care of this _ it doesn't happen here,'' said Highway Patrol
Officer <PERSON>Frank Stricker</PERSON>.
   Snow up to 7 inches deep closed lanes of Interstate 5 over <LOCATION>Tejon
Pass north of Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s main north-south route, and
coastal Highway 101 near <LOCATION>San Luis Obispo</LOCATION> about 150 miles north of
the city.
   Thousands of motorists were stranded, travel elsewhere was
difficult and some schools in <LOCATION>San Luis Obispo County</LOCATION> were closed,
officials said.
   Weather forecasters predicted much of the same through the
<DATE>weekend</DATE>, saying 1 to 2 feet of snow was possible in southern
mountain ranges.
   The earthquake late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> rattled windows and knocked wall
hangings askew from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> 110 miles to the
east. There were no immediate reports of serious damage or injuries.
   The quake registered a moderate 4.8 on the Richter scale and was
centered 13 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Hall Daly</PERSON>, a
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>.
   Just <DATE>a week earlier</DATE> the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Basin</LOCATION> was swept by warm,
fierce <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> winds. Wind-fanned fires burned dozens of homes in
two suburbs <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and blackened 3,000 acres of brushy terrain the
next day.
   In northern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, canyon winds gusting to 115 mph knocked out
power to 50,000 people <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and 3,000 remained
without power late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, said <ORGANIZATION>Utah Power &amp; Light</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Dave
Mead</PERSON>.
   Twenty-four schools and the <ORGANIZATION>Internal Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ogden</LOCATION>
closed. At least five tractor-trailer rigs were blown over in <LOCATION>Davis
County</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Great Salt Lake</LOCATION> and mail delivery in northern <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> was
delayed or halted, officials said.
   In <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>, power outages led to two deadly
candle-sparked fires, officials said. In <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, 3-year-old <PERSON>Oli
Asghar</PERSON> died <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and his family was left homeless.
   In <LOCATION>Pittsburg</LOCATION>, about 30 miles to the north, 6-year-old <PERSON>Mounkoun
Lee</PERSON> died <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE> of smoke inhalation after he was trapped
inside his burning home. His 5-year-old sister, <PERSON>Angela</PERSON>, died at
<ORGANIZATION>Children's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   It caught fire after her parents neglected to extinguish a candle
next to a bed they were using for light when wind knocked out power,
officials said.
   In <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION> north of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>, ``we've had lots of
trees knocked down, power outages and phone problems,'' said <PERSON>Dan
Nicholas</PERSON> of county <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>. ``Some homes have been
damaged to the point where the people had to be evacuated and put up
in motels overnight.''
   On the bay's long waterfront, the winds sent waves up to 10 feet
high slamming into seawalls and sank a 60-foot floating dock at <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>'s Pier 43. Piles of metal and other debris were left on
streets.
   A tugboat sank in <LOCATION>Richardson Bay</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Sausalito</LOCATION>, two boats sank
at a <LOCATION>China Basin</LOCATION> dock just south of downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, and the
<ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> kept busy retrieving small boats torn from their
moorings, officials said. Famed attorney <PERSON>Melvin Belli</PERSON>'s 110-foot
yacht, Adequate Award, was damaged when another boat dragging its
anchor slammed into his in <LOCATION>Richardson Bay</LOCATION>.
   Much bigger craft had problems as well. The aircraft carrier USS
<PERSON>Carl Vinson</PERSON> and its 3,000-man crew,wrapping up a six-month tour, had
to delay a holiday port call until today, said Petty Officer <PERSON>Roger
Turner</PERSON>.
   The wind blew out store windows in <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hayward</LOCATION>,
and shattered glass blocked major roadways.
   Several trucks along a 10-mile stretch of Interstate 580
southeast of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> were toppled, the <ORGANIZATION>Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said.
   A downed power line in <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION>'s geysers area sparked a
fire that burned 250 acres, but threatened no homes. In <LOCATION>Tuolumne
County</LOCATION> near the <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> border, a controlled-burn fire flared and
blackened 100 acres. Several small fires were reported in the
<ORGANIZATION>Stanislaus National Forest</ORGANIZATION>.
   The winds also delayed flights and diverted air traffic to and
from <LOCATION>San Francisco International Airport</LOCATION> and caused elevators to
malfunction in the city.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891104-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-04-89 0354EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SFQuake     11-04 0202</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SF Quake,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>3.6-Magnitude Tremor in San Francisco; No Damage Reported</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN LEANDRO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A slight earthquake jolted the <LOCATION>San Francisco
   The quake, which struck at <TIME>11:16 p.m. PST</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, registered 3.6
on the Richter scale and was centered four miles north of <LOCATION>San
Leandro</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Pat Jorgenson</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>United States
Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>San Leandro</LOCATION> is southwest of
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, in the so-called <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> suburban area.
police and fire spokesmen in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>.
   The temblor wasn't technically considered an aftershock to the
<DATE>Oct. 17</DATE>, magnitude-7.1 quake that devastated the region, said <PERSON>Tom
Flynn</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>state Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>. The
big quake was on the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> fault, centered 55 miles south of
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>San Leandro</LOCATION> is east of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   An earthquake of 3.5 on the Richter scale can cause slight
damage in the local area, 4 moderate damage, 5 considerable damage,
6 severe damage. A 7 reading is a ``major'' earthquake, capable of
widespread heavy damage; 8 is a ``great'' quake, capable of
tremendous damage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891022-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-22-89 2354EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SFQuake-County-Glance     10-22 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SF Quake-County-Glance,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>County-by-County Damage, Deaths and Injuries</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a county-by-county summary of death, injury and damage
reports from <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and reporter
observations:
   ALAMEDA COUNTY (<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and communities east of <LOCATION>San Francisco
Bay</LOCATION>) _ Mile-and-a-quarter-long section of upper deck of Interstate
880 in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> collapsed, with 38 bodies recovered from the freeway
wreckage so far. One man, 57-year-old Buck Helm of <LOCATION>Weaverville</LOCATION>, was
found alive in the wreckage <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and was in critical but stable
condition at a hospital <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Up to 150 people were evacuated from a housing project <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
when severe cracks were found in another section of I-880 that
borders their apartments. The <ORGANIZATION>County Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>
says <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> sustained <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of the county's 349 injuries and
<MONEY>$1.5 billion-plus</MONEY> in damages. The <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION> reported 200 businesses,
including nine residential hotels, and 1,400 homes were damaged, at
least 10 buildings destroyed and 600 people displaced.
   SAN FRANCISCO _ Ten deaths, 566 injuries, 1,800 people
displaced, most in the devastated <LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION> district. Property losses
estimated at <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>.
   Sixty residential buildings were destroyed in the <LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION>. More
than 1,000 apartment buildings damaged, but no citywide figures
were available <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on the total number of buildings damaged.
About 2,000 Marina residences, including those damaged beyond
repair, remained without gas and electric service <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The two
main state office buildings near the Civic Center are closed
indefinitely because of major structural damage.
   SAN MATEO COUNTY (borders <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to south) _ No deaths,
282 injuries, damage estimated at <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY>. 600 homes damaged,
320 in <LOCATION>Pacifica</LOCATION>. Three businesses destroyed and 600 damaged. Facade
of the <ORGANIZATION>Amfac Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Burlingame</LOCATION> collapsed, injuring seven.
   SANTA CRUZ COUNTY (south of <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>) _ Four deaths, all in
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, 862 injuries and 4,500 people displaced. Damage
estimated at <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, including <MONEY>$83 million</MONEY> to the city of <LOCATION>Santa
Cruz</LOCATION>, where six downtown commercial buildings must be razed.
<LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Capitola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Scotts Valley</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Boulder Creek</ORGANIZATION> also
hard-hit.
   Houses in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>, site of the 6.9 quake's
epicenter, and along the coast lost to fires and landslides.
County-wide, at least 275 homes destroyed and 2,066 damaged.
Several mountain passes closed by landslides and fissures in roads.
   SANTA CLARA COUNTY (city of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> and communities on
southeastern end of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>) _ Five deaths, 650 injuries
including 93 people admitted to hospitals. Damage estimate <MONEY>$560
million</MONEY>. Sixty-five homes and six businesses destroyed. Damage,
including the most minor to severe, to 104,000 dwellings and 384
businesses, according to city reports to county <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION>. Thirty
buildings collapsed in <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>, on fringe of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz
Mountains</LOCATION>. Highway 17 in <LOCATION>Scotts Valley</LOCATION>, east of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION>, closed
by rockslide.
   SAN BENITO COUNTY (south and east of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>) _ No deaths.
Seventy-five minor injuries. Damage estimate <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>. Twelve
commercial buildings and light industrial buildings heavily
damaged. Thirty-two single-family homes destroyed, 92 homes damaged.
   MONTEREY COUNTY (south of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>) _ Two deaths, six
injuries. Seventy homes damaged. Damage estimate <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>.
Salinas sustained <MONEY>$3.6 million</MONEY> in damage to 15 homes and 29
businesses. <ORGANIZATION>Moss Landing Marine Lab</ORGANIZATION>, a university research
facility, destroyed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891025-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-25-89 1807EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake-CountyGlance     10-25 0583</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-County Glance,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>County-by-County Look at the Quake</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a county-by-county summary of death, injury and damage
reports from the <DATE>Oct. 17</DATE> earthquake as gathered from the <ORGANIZATION>California
Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>, other agencies and reporters:
   ALAMEDA COUNTY (<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and communities east of <LOCATION>San Francisco
Bay</LOCATION>) _ Mile-and-a-quarter-long section of upper deck of Interstate
880 in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> collapsed, with 39 bodies recovered from the
wreckage so far.
   The entire viaduct will be razed, even the part that did not
collapse, and rebuilt to standards designed to withstand
earthquakes, transportation officials say. I-880, built for <MONEY>$10.2
million</MONEY> in <DATE>1957</DATE>, was the state's first elevated freeway.
   The <ORGANIZATION>County Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION> said 2,550 people were
left homeless. The <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION> reported <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> suffered <PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of the
county's 349 injuries and <MONEY>$1.5 billion-plus</MONEY> in damages. In all, the
office said 264 businesses, including nine residential hotels, and
1,517 homes were damaged and at least 11 buildings destroyed.
Damage to <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> port facilities estimated <MONEY>$105 million</MONEY>.
   SAN FRANCISCO _ Twelve deaths including one in Bay Bridge
collapse, 300 injured and treated at hospitals, an undetermined
number who sustained less serious injuries. The <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION> said 1,100
people were homeless. Damages estimated at <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY>, and Mayor
Art Angos says total could be more than <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY>.
   Sixty residential buildings were destroyed in the <LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION>
district. In preliminary reports, 250 buildings in the city are
described as unsafe and up to 1,000 need extensive repairs. Damage
to public buildings is estimated at <MONEY>$388 million</MONEY>, and the total to
public property <MONEY>$512 million</MONEY>.
   The Bay Bridge, the main link between the city and <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, is
shut until at least <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE> for repairs. The elevated <ORGANIZATION>Embarcadero
Freeway</ORGANIZATION> will be closed for about three months, officials said.
   SAN MATEO COUNTY (borders <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to south) _ Two hundred
eighty-two injuries, damage estimated at <MONEY>$350 million</MONEY>, 600 homes
damaged, three businesses destroyed and 637 damaged.
   SANTA CRUZ COUNTY (south of <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>) _ Five deaths, four in
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, 730 injuries, 9,500 homeless. Damage estimated at more
than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. City officials of <LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION> say damage there
near <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY>, and damage to city of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> estimated at
<MONEY>$160 million</MONEY>. <LOCATION>Capitola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Scotts Valley</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Boulder Creek</ORGANIZATION> also
hard-hit.
   The quake's 7.1 epicenter was located in a state park in the
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>, triggering landslides and touching off fires.
In the county, at least 275 homes destroyed and 2,066 damaged.
Highway 17 in <LOCATION>Scotts Valley</LOCATION>, which was completely blocked by a
slide after the quake, now open for one lane of controlled traffic.
   SANTA CLARA COUNTY (city of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> and communities on
southeastern end of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>) _ Five deaths and 650
injuries, including 93 people admitted to hospitals. The <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION> said
70 people were homeless. Damage estimate <MONEY>$560 million</MONEY>. Sixty-five
homes and six businesses destroyed. Damage to 104,000 dwellings and
384 businesses, according to city reports to county <ORGANIZATION>OES</ORGANIZATION>. Thirty
buildings collapsed in <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>, on fringe of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>.
   SAN BENITO COUNTY (south and east of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>) _ One hundred
ten injuries, 412 homeless. Damage estimate <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>.
Twenty-three businesses, 68 homes and 104 mobile homes destroyed;
28 businesses, two public buildings and 400 homes damaged.
   MONTEREY COUNTY (south of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>) _ Two deaths, 14 injuries,
260 homeless. One hundred eleven homes, 32 commercial buildings and
20 mobile homes damaged, seven homes destroyed. Damage estimate
<MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>. <ORGANIZATION>Moss Landing Marine Lab</ORGANIZATION>, a university research
facility, destroyed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891021-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-21-89 1935EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SF-Quake-Glance 1stLd-Writethru a0575 10-21 0761</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF-Quake-Glance, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0575,0781</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summary of Quake-related Developments</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf under `casualties' to UPDATE with rescue of survivor.
SUBS 2nd graf under `The quake and its aftershocks' to UPDATE with more
than 2,000 aftershocks, another registering over 4.0.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DAMAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CASUALTIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE QUAKE AND AFTERSHOCKS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FEDERAL ASSISTANCE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD SERIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>HIGHWAY CLOSURES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>QUAKE HOTLINE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WEATHER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890808-0081 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-08-89 1336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-CaliforniaQuake 6thLd-Writethru a0546 08-08 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-California Quake, 6th Ld - Writethru, a0546,0613</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sharp Quake Jolts San Francisco Bay Area</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf pvs, `An aftershock ...' to UPDATE with second
aftershock.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SNJ1, 2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CATALINA ORTIZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A sharp earthquake shook the <LOCATION>San Francisco
Bay</LOCATION> area for 10 seconds early today, breaking glass, causing rock
slides and apparently prompting a man to jump to his death from a
fifth-story window, authorities said.
   The quake, measuring 5.1 on the Richter scale, occurred at <TIME>1:13
a.m.</TIME> and was centered on the <LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION> about 13 miles south
of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>. It was felt as far as
San <PERSON>Luis Obispo</PERSON>, 230 miles south of here.
   No major damage was reported.
   The quake struck as state and federal emergency officials were
about to begin a two-day test of earthquake communications
procedures. The drill involved a mock earthquake in the <LOCATION>Bay</LOCATION> area in
which 5,000 people die.
   ``It felt like I was having my bed rolled around on a
skateboard. I woke up and I was moving,'' said <PERSON>Henry J. Peterson</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, next to <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
   Two aftershocks measuring 4.2 and 4.5 rippled through the <TIME>area
later this morning</TIME>. State officials warned there could be more
quakes in <LOCATION>northern California</LOCATION> in the next five days, with a quake
up to 6.2 possible but not likely.
   In <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>, 50 miles south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, a 19-year-old man
was apparently startled awake by the earthquake and jumped out of
his bedroom window, police dispatcher <PERSON>Lisa Douglas</PERSON> said in a
statement.
   The shaking sent rocks tumbling onto highways, said a <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz
County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> emergency dispatcher who declined to
give her name. ``They cleared the debris by hand and all roads are
now cleared,'' she said.
   ``There was some damage in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>,'' said <LOCATION>San
Jose</LOCATION> police Officer <PERSON>Jay Forbes</PERSON>. ``It was mainly broken windows and
mirrors. Nothing serious.''
   The false ceiling in a vacant <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION> business came down, and
half a dozen businesses reported broken windows, police said.
   ``I felt a little rumble and then all the windows started
shaking real bad,'' said <PERSON>Chris Soliday</PERSON>, a clerk at an all-night
convenience store in <LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>. ``Some stuff in the aisles fell
down. There's broken glass, dented cans, some beer bottles broken.''
   The epicenter was in almost exactly the same place as a 5.0
quake on <DATE>June 27, 1988</DATE>, said <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> geophysicist <PERSON>Dave Oppenheimer</PERSON>.
   Residents shaken awake by the temblor described it as jolting
and rolling.
   ``It was the strongest I've ever felt,'' said <PERSON>Bernie Beck</PERSON>, 38,
who lives in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Haight-Ashbury</LOCATION> district.
   ``I live in an old building that was built after the <DATE>1906</DATE> quake,
and it really had me going,'' <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> said. ``It felt like you were
sitting on a saw horse, rocking back and forth.''
   <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s Great Quake, which occurred in <DATE>1906</DATE> before the
Richter scale was devised, has been estimated at 8.3. Recent
estimates say more than 2,000 people died in the quake and the fire
it touched off, which burned much of the city.
   The open-ended Richter scale is a measure of the energy released
by an earthquake, as measured by ground motion recorded on a
seisomograph.
   Each increase of one number, as in a jump from magnitude 5.5 to
6.5, means that the ground motion is 10 times greater. A quake of
3.5 can cause slight damage in populated areas, while a quake of
6.0 can cause severe damage. In <DATE>March 1964</DATE> an earthquake in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>
hit 8.5 on the Richter scale, killing 114 people.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101889-0063 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 122123 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 18, 1989, Wednesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
927 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HUGE QUAKE STRIKES BAY AREA; 
</P>
<P>
6.9 TEMBLOR: PORTION OF BAY BRIDGE COLLAPSES. BLOCK-LONG APARTMENT IN SAN 
FRANCISCO IS ABLAZE. SIX ARE KILLED AND POWER IS KNOCKED OUT ACROSS HUNDREDS OF 
MILES. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ERIC MALNIC, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A massive earthquake struck south of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, killing at 
least six, injuring hundreds more, damaging thousands of buildings and 
collapsing a portion of the roadway decking on the <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay 
Bridge</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The quake, which hit at <TIME>5:04 p.m.</TIME> and lasted about 15 seconds, measured at 
magnitude 6.9, four times stronger than the powerful <LOCATION>Sylmar</LOCATION> quake that rocked 
the northern <LOCATION>San Fernando Valley</LOCATION> <DATE>Feb. 9, 1971</DATE>, killing 58 and causing more than 
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> damage. 
</P>
<P>
An apartment building covering an entire city block caught fire in <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Marina District</LOCATION>. The flames spread unchecked, enveloping the entire 
structure, which eventually collapsed in embers. Several nearby buildings 
appeared threatened. 
</P>
<P>
At the recently renovated <LOCATION>San Francisco International Airport</LOCATION>, ceilings 
collapsed and tumbled into crowded passengers areas. 
</P>
<P>
The earthquake, which was felt as far as 300 miles away, knocked out electrical 
power, television broadcasts and telephone communications across hundreds of 
miles. 
</P>
<P>
The quake struck as thousands of fans were crowding into <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s 
Candlestick Park for the third game of the <DATE>1989</DATE> World Series. The game was 
canceled and players reportedly left the stadium in their uniforms. 
</P>
<P>
Network broadcasters monitoring the pregame activities from other cities saw 
the game go off the air and spread word of the disaster to the millions across 
the nation preparing to watch at the game on television. 
</P>
<P>
Several spectators at <LOCATION>Candlestick Park</LOCATION> were injured by falling debris. 
Officials ordered the stadium evacuated. 
</P>
<P>
Several motorists were tossed from the Bay Bridge into the water, more than 100 
feet blow, when the temblor collapsed a 50-foot section of the roadway. The 
extent of their injuries was not immediately determined. 
</P>
<P>
Several other major roadways suffered heavy damage. A section of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 101, one 
of the main arteries to the south, buckled in several places near <LOCATION>San Francisco 
Airport</LOCATION>. A double-decked portion of Interstate 880 in the <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> appeared to 
have collapsed. It is a main commuter freeway connecting <LOCATION>East Oakland</LOCATION> with the 
<ORGANIZATION>Oakland-San Francisco Bay Bridge</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Ambulances, their sirens screaming, attempted to race through gridlocked 
streets toward downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, where several major buildings collapsed. 
</P>
<P>
Evening rush-hour traffic came to a halt, with traffic signals knocked out 
throughout much of the area. Many commuters left their cars in parking lots and 
tried to go home by foot. Market Street was filled with people as aftershocks 
continued. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco City Hall</LOCATION> and the state building housing the <ORGANIZATION>state Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> 
were evacuated. Both buildings had severe damage inside. 
</P>
<P>
Close to the Civic Center, a large section of a four-story building came down, 
and eyewitnesses said the bodies of at least two women were removed. 
</P>
<P>
"The whole topside, I saw the building coming down, and I just went forward, 
trying to get out of there," said <PERSON>Cliff Bailey</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Fire Capt. <PERSON>John Traversaro</PERSON> said that "four or five people, it 
could be considerably more" were killed in this building alone. 
</P>
<P>
At the nearby federal building, <PERSON>Marcus Williams</PERSON> said, "I didn't want to be 
buried alive. As I ran down the stairs, people were screaming. This was the 
worst one I ever felt." 
</P>
<P>
At the <ORGANIZATION>state Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, Justice <PERSON>David M. Eagleson</PERSON> said, "There were 
pictures knocked off the walls, books on the floor and cracked plaster. We were 
really hit. Things are really a mess." 
</P>
<P>
Justice <PERSON>Allen E. Broussard</PERSON> said he was completing a meeting with staff 
attorneys when the temblor hit. "There was so much dust in the air you could 
hardly see what happened," he said. 
</P>
<P>
"It was horrible on the Muni Metro," said <PERSON>Kim Gordon</PERSON>, an insurance company 
employee who was riding <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s subway system. "We were underground and 
it was shaking real bad. We all thought we were going to die." 
</P>
<P>
She said that when her train arrived at the next station, the passengers were 
let out but had to grope their way to the surface in the dark. 
</P>
<P>
Seismologists at <ORGANIZATION>UC Berkeley</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Caltech</ORGANIZATION> put the epicenter on the <LOCATION>San Andreas 
Fault</LOCATION>, 10 miles north of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> in the same vicinity of a 5.4 quake that 
struck in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Damage and injuries in the communities surrounding the epicenter were said to 
be extensive, with people trapped in damaged buildings in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> and further 
south in <LOCATION>Hollister</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>Hayward</ORGANIZATION> couple, <PERSON>Steve</PERSON> and <PERSON>Christie Stevenson</PERSON>, said they tried to run out of 
their front door, but "it was impossible to run." <PERSON>Steve Stevenson</PERSON> said they 
"held onto a tree in the front yard and watched the water in the swimming poor 
come out in three-foot waves." 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON>'s press secretary, <PERSON>Kevin Brett</PERSON>, said the 
governor had been awakened in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, where he had gone on a 
trade mission, at about <TIME>1:15 a.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> time. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Brett</PERSON> said it had not yet been decided whether the governor would cancel the 
rest of his trip and return to the state. 
</P>
<P>
The historic <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> earthquake of <DATE>1906</DATE> was estimated later by 
seismologists to have reached a magnitude of 8.3. By that scale, each number 
represents a 10-fold increase in magnitude -- meaning that the earlier quake 
was considerably more than 10 times stronger than <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>1906</DATE> quake devastated the city. In the three days that followed that quake, 
fires destroyed 490 blocks within a four-square-mile area near the financial 
district. Five hundred were killed, thousands were injured and more than 28,000 
buildings ultimately were lost. In <DATE>1906</DATE> dollars, damage was estimated at <MONEY>$400 
million</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Compact car rests in a crevice created when a section of the San 
Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge collapsed during earthquake. ABC-TV via Associated 
Press; Photo, Members of Oakland A's look around in confusion as fans in 
Candlestick Park react to earthquake that struck just at World Series game 
time. ; Photo, A section of roadway on the San Francisco Bay Bridge collapsed 
during the quake. This photo was taken from a television screen. Associated 
Press; Map, Quake Site, Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102189-0108 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 123784 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 21, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 9; Column 1; Letters Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
179 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MASSIVE EARTHQUAKE JOLTS BAY AREA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In between emergency responses from our fire station, I watched the heroic 
efforts of our brother and sister firefighters in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> as they 
attempted to suppress the fires and rescue people trapped in structures. The 
mayor had put out a call for all off-duty fire fighting personnel to 
immediately report to their fire stations. 
</P>
<P>
While watching the coverage, my mind kept drifting back to an obscure article I 
had read earlier in the day. This article described how <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Mayor Art 
Agnos had reduced the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Fire Department staffing by 76 positions 
four months earlier. I kept waiting for someone to ask Agnos about these 
reductions, but no questions were forthcoming. 
</P>
<P>
There is no doubt that the remaining personnel of the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> Fire 
Department would give their all during this major disaster, but when the dust 
is settled, I am sure they will ask Agnos if he still feels the same way about 
his cuts in the fire department -- and I can't wait to hear his answer! 
</P>
<P>
DALLAS JONES 
</P>
<P>
President 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Los Angeles County</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
Fire Fighters Local 1014 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Letter to the Editor 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101889-0066 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 122132 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 18, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 4; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1204 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENTISTS LAST YEAR HAD PINPOINTED TUESDAY'S SITE AS LIKELY TO BE JOLTED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KENNETH REICH, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake, the strongest on the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> fault since the <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> quake on <DATE>April 18, 1906</DATE>, came in a place that had been identified by 
scientists just last year as the most likely spot for a major jolt in <LOCATION>Northern 
California</LOCATION> within the next 30 years. 
</P>
<P>
The epicenter of the temblor, eight miles east-northeast of the city of <LOCATION>Santa 
Cruz</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>, was at virtually the same spot as earthquakes 
in the 5-magnitude range that occurred on <DATE>June 27, 1988</DATE>, and <DATE>Aug. 8, 1989</DATE>. A 
6.5-magnitude quake was centered there in <DATE>1865</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>, in a <DATE>1988</DATE> report on regions of high earthquake 
probability in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, said there was a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> chance of another 6.5-magnitude 
earthquake in the immediate vicinity by the year <DATE>2018</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The report cited even higher probabilities for major temblors on the <LOCATION>San 
Andreas</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Parkfield</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>central California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Coachella</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Southern 
California</LOCATION> in the same period, but it pinpointed the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> mountains as 
the most vulnerable spot in <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>, in part because the area 
marked the southernmost point of maximum ground slippage during the <DATE>1906</DATE> 
earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
A period of 83 years is short as far as earthquake intervals go, and during 
this time, scientists said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, pressure was probably building up in 
the southern neighboring segment of the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION>, which had not slipped as 
much. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas Heaton</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> scientist in charge of the agency's 
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> field office, said that the <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> earthquakes now must be seen 
as "preshocks" of the <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s 6.9 temblor. He said "foreshocks" would not be 
the proper term, since months had elapsed before the more powerful earthquake 
struck. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Heaton</PERSON> said that a still larger shock is unlikely. But he joined <ORGANIZATION>Caltech</ORGANIZATION> 
scientists in saying that aftershocks as strong as 5.9 magnitude should be 
expected, and that the pattern of aftershocks could last for months. A 5.9 
aftershock would be as strong as the <DATE>1987</DATE> Whittier quake in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
area. 
</P>
<P>
After both the <DATE>1987</DATE> and the <DATE>1988</DATE> earthquakes in the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz mountains</LOCATION>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>state Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> issued 
warnings of increased risk of sizable shakes, ranging up to 6.5 magnitude, 
within the next few days in the vicinity. 
</P>
<P>
But these warnings said that if nothing happened, then the chances of a major 
earthquake would recede to normal for the vicinity. The trouble was, the area 
was more prone to quakes at this time than any other place in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> on 
the <LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION>. Only the nearby Hayward fault may harbor as great a 
danger of a catastrophic earthquake in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION>, the longest and best-known earthquake fault in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 
extends from <ORGANIZATION>Point Arena</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mendocino County</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Salton Sea</LOCATION>. It has been the 
site of the deadliest and most destructive earthquakes in the state's recorded 
history. 
</P>
<P>
Although <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s quake was powerful, <LOCATION>Waverly Person</LOCATION>, chief of the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Earthquake Information Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Golden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, cautioned that at 6.9 
magnitude, it should be considered only a "strong" shock, not a "major" one, as 
a quake in the 7.0 to 7.9 range would be classified, or a "great" one, as a 
quake of 8.0 or above would be. 
</P>
<P>
Person and others in the <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> warned <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that the 
probability is <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> that a temblor more powerful than <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s will strike in 
<LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> sometime in the next three decades. 
</P>
<P>
But, as it was, <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s quake was about four times stronger than the 
devastating Sylmar-San Fernando earthquake of <DATE>1971</DATE> and 10 times stronger than 
the <DATE>1987</DATE> Whittier quake. Each point of magnitude represents a 10-fold increase 
in the power of an earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
Person said that, like most <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> earthquakes, this was most likely to be 
a strike-slip quake, with one side of the fault grinding horizontally past 
another. But he said a final evaluation would have to await on-scene inspection 
teams that will be sent into the epicenter area today by the <ORGANIZATION>Geological 
Survey</ORGANIZATION>'s Menlo Park office. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim Dewey</PERSON>, a research geophysicist at the <ORGANIZATION>National Earthquake Center</ORGANIZATION>, said 
preliminary evaluations indicated that the fracture was about 10 miles deep, 
and that the quake rupture extended about 30 miles south down the fault from 
the epicenter. 
</P>
<P>
Person said that the area of strongest shaking was around <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, although 
this evaluation too will have to await field evaluations, as will a final 
confirmation of the magnitude of the earthquake. 
</P>
<P>
The nearest metropolitan area to <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, has seen 
nearly a dozen earthquakes of 5 magnitude or greater in the <DATE>last 10 years</DATE>, but 
several of them have been on the Calaveras fault, which generally runs just 
east of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, more than 10 miles east of <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION> at this point. 
</P>
<P>
Scientists do not yet understand whether the quakes on the Calaveras fault may 
have been a precursor, or somehow added pressure, on the <LOCATION>San Andreas</LOCATION>. But when 
a 5.1 earthquake did strike on the Calaveras in <DATE>1988</DATE>, some earthquake 
scientists expressed concern that this could be the case. 
</P>
<P>
Between the late <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1979</DATE>, there were no quakes of magnitude 5 or larger 
near the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>. But in <DATE>August, 1979</DATE>, a 6.4-magnitude quake struck under 
<ORGANIZATION>Coyote Lake</ORGANIZATION> east of <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION> and south of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, and since then there have 
been a number of quakes. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>August</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> scientists had expressed concern at the step-up in 
5-magnitude quakes south of the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>. They noted that a similar series of 
moderately strong quakes had preceded the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> quake of <DATE>1906</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, a <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> scientist who studies tidal forces, supported by two 
eyewitnesses, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that at a private lecture in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> on 
<DATE>Oct. 10</DATE>, he had stated that a strong quake in the vicinity was probable on or 
about <DATE>Oct. 16</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Iben Browning</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Sandia Park</LOCATION>, <PERSON>N. M.</PERSON>, said he had based his prediction on an 
assessment of tidal forces caused by the moon's relationship with the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. He 
said he had decided to keep the assessment private because he feared that 
publicity about it would cause people to panic. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
MAJOR QUAKE DAMAGE 
</P>
<P>
1 -- Major fires hit <ORGANIZATION>Marina District</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
2 -- Civic Center area buildings damaged, a 4-story building south of Market 
collapsed, killing 5. 
</P>
<P>
3 -- Central Freeway (101 inside <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> city limits) buckled and closed. 
</P>
<P>
4 -- <ORGANIZATION>Embarcadero Freeway</ORGANIZATION> damaged and shut. 
</P>
<P>
5 -- Interstate 280 from junction with Rt. 101 to downtown closed. 
</P>
<P>
6 -- Candlestick Park damaged, evacuated. 
</P>
<P>
7 -- <LOCATION>San Francisco Airport</LOCATION> closed, control tower reportedly in shambles. 
</P>
<P>
8 -- Portion of <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION> at eastern end collapsed; one 
person reported killed. 
</P>
<P>
9 -- Bay Area Rapid Transit system shut down. 
</P>
<P>
10 -- Double-decked portion of Interstate 880 (<ORGANIZATION>Nimitz Freeway</ORGANIZATION>) collapsed. 
Estimates were as high as 200 dead and hundreds injured. 
</P>
<P>
11 -- Highway 17 in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> closed at Summit St. overcrossing because of 
collapse. 
</P>
<P>
12 -- <LOCATION>Oakland Airport</LOCATION> closed. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
OTHER AREAS OF DAMAGE 
</P>
<P>
Major damage to interchange of <ORGANIZATION>Bayshore Fwy</ORGANIZATION> (101) and State Route 92 in <LOCATION>San 
Mateo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Damage to 3rd Avenue overpass in <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Portions of Interstate 280 closed in <LOCATION>Los Altos</LOCATION> due to buckling. 
</P>
<P>
Two killed at <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> shopping mall. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, MAJOR QUAKE DAMAGE, ROBERT ALLEN / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EARTHQUAKES -- SAN FRANCISCO; FORECASTS; EARTHQUAKES -- CALIFORNIA; SAN ANDREAS 
FAULT; SANTA CRUZ (CA); CALAVERAS FAULT; SCIENTISTS; SEISMOLOGY; EARTHQUAKES -- 
NORTHERN CALIFORNIA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891028-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-28-89 1348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SFQuake-Glance     10-28 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-Glance,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Summary of Quake-Related Developments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DAMAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CASUALTIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE QUAKE AND AFTERSHOCKS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FINANCIAL ASSISTANCE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD SERIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>HIGHWAY CLOSURES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891020-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-89 2119EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake-Glance 1stLd-Writethru a0739 10-20 0631</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-Glance, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0739,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: UPDATES throughout with new information on damage and casualties;
SUBS first graf of weather item to update with temperatures in 40s sted
30s; tightens</HEAD>
<HEAD>Summary of Quake-related Developments</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>DAMAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>CASUALTIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE QUAKE AND AFTERSHOCKS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FEDERAL ASSISTANCE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WORLD SERIES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>HIGHWAY CLOSURES</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>WEATHER</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Summary of developments related to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> earthquake:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891018-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-89 1558EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake Bjt 2Takes 10-18 1158</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake, Bjt, 2 Takes,1189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Search for Survivors, Bodies after Second-Deadliest U.S. Quake</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Deukmejian expected back about 4 p.m. EDT; state Transportation
Dept. news conference skedded 6 p.m. EDT.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic, LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER McNULTY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   By smell and sound, dogs and technicians
searched <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for the last possible survivors of the killer
Bay Quake, and Californians by the thousands picked their way
through glass-strewn streets in search of a semblance of normal
life.
   Across <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, hopes faded for finding
anyone alive within the tons of steel and concrete left when
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s earthquake brought one level of Interstate 880 down atop
another.
   More than 250 people were feared entombed in that twisted
wreckage, and at least 18 others were dead elsewhere in the quake
area. Some 650 people were injured, said state emergency services
spokesman <PERSON>John Peterson</PERSON>.
   ``To the best of our knowledge now, there are not any people
still alive on this freeway,'' said <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Lionel Wilson</PERSON>
said of the collapsed roadway.
   Searchers had been hindered by darkness and the condition of the
wrecked freeway, which <ORGANIZATION>Acting Oakland City</ORGANIZATION> Manager <PERSON>Craig Kocian</PERSON>
described as ``a house of cards'' that could collapse further at
any time unless rescuers work carefully.
   The 1\ miles of the Nimitz Freeway that collapsed was one of
oldest in the area, built in <DATE>1950s</DATE>, and apparently was not included
in a program to make spans earthquake-proof, said state
<ORGANIZATION>Transportation Department</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Kyle Nelson</PERSON>.
   In just 15 seconds, the earthquake destroyed or damaged hundreds
of buildings along 100 miles of the <LOCATION>San Andreas Fault</LOCATION>, collapsed a
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, cracked roads, and severed gas and power lines,
sparking fires.
   The temblor, the nation's second-deadliest, surpassed only by
the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> earthquake of <DATE>1906</DATE>, measured 6.9 on the Richter
scale and was felt 350 miles away.
   Even as residents and officials tried to evaluate the damage,
available for recovery, and said ``we will take every step and make
every effort'' to help.
   The president said he probably would fly to the area for a
personal inspection but left open when that might happen. Vice
toured the quake-ravaged area by helicopter <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The federal government normally pays at least <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of the
cost of rebuilding bridges and public facilities that are
destroyed, and provides low-cost loans. The order covered seven
counties.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and was trying to determine whether the relief order
should be expanded.
   Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> said damage was ``the better part of <MONEY>$1
billion</MONEY>.'' Other estimates were in the billions in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
alone.
   Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> headed home from a trade mission to <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Marina District</ORGANIZATION>, where a fire fueled by gas
destroyed a block of 12 apartment buildings, about 500 people
packed a cafeteria at <ORGANIZATION>Marina Middle School</ORGANIZATION> for breakfast after
spending the night on cots and mats.
   Deputy Fire Chief <PERSON>Mike K. Farrell</PERSON> said he strongly suspected
people were trapped in collapsed buildings. ``We're going to bring
in dogs to see if people are trapped in there. I saw three- and
four-story buildings that are now one-story buildings.''
   <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> donated sonic equipment to help detect any sounds of
people trapped alive in rubble, said <PERSON>Scott Shafer</PERSON>, a spokesman for
Mayor Art Agnos. Nine people are known dead and ``I expect we'll
find more bodies,'' he said.
   State <PERSON>Sen. Milton Marks</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> estimated damage in the
<LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION> area alone at <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. <PERSON>Shafer</PERSON> said damage throughout the
city would run into the billions.
   The transportation system was crippled by the closing of the <LOCATION>San
Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, and Agnos urged commuters to stay
home <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Tourist ferries that helped <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by giving commuters free
rides to <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> charged the normal <MONEY>$4</MONEY> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>San Francisco International</LOCATION> airports reopened and <ORGANIZATION>BART</ORGANIZATION>, the
rapid transit system, was open.
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> Rose, one of about 400 people who spent the night at an
emergency <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> center, said, ``I have antiques, silver and
nice things. But when you really get down to it _ and I never
thought I'd feel this way _ these things don't matter. The material
things do not make life.''
   About 50 volunteers worked at the shelter and more walked in to
offer their services <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>. ``People have been
wonderful. We had an incredible community response,'' said <PERSON>Marian
Richie</PERSON>, a volunteer <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> nurse.
   Students from the <ORGANIZATION>University of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION> visited the
shelter <DATE>Tuesday night</DATE> to ask what was needed, went back to campus
and returned with food, cots and blankets, <PERSON>Richie</PERSON> said. ``It's an
absolute grass-roots response. I've never seen anything like it.
People come up and say, `How can I help?'''
   It looked like a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s financial
district, with little visible damage, though many buildings were
closed. A sign on the <ORGANIZATION>International Building</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Street _
the equivalent of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Wall Street _ said, ``Building closed!
No power. No exceptions!''
   More than 1 million people lost electricity, including the
financial district office of <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch</ORGANIZATION>, where operations
manager <PERSON>Joe Centis</PERSON> said he arrived at <TIME>5:30 a.m.</TIME> and found wire room
operator <PERSON>Tom Begley</PERSON> using a power-safe phone to call in orders that
came in <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> after the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> market closed.
   Officials said power in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> would be restored
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, people picked their way to work through broken glass
and broken buildings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Employees of <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp;
Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, like others, waited outside their office while engineers
inspected it.
   ``If they let us in, we'll be lucky,'' said <PERSON>Judy Colwell</PERSON>, who
suffered a bone bruise on her arm during the quake. Water from a
broken main still dripped from light fixtures on a third floor
overhang of the building's facade.
   Ironworkers at a high-rise under construction near I-880 were on
standby to help untangle the wreckage of the highway. The
building's temporary floors were askew and the workers' elevator
had fallen and lay embedded in the pavement.
   ``We put it up, so we're going to have to go up and straighten
it up,'' <PERSON>Jim Osburn</PERSON> said of the building. ``It's always more
dangerous to take it down than it is to take it up, but somebody
will have to go up there and make it safe.''
   While some people arrived for work, others were finishing a long
night.
   ``I've been out here since 7 o'clock,'' said <PERSON>Randy Rogers</PERSON>, one
of three men shoveling fist-sized chunks of fallen masonry into a
pickup truck.
   Red Cross volunteers began house-hunting for evacuees who spent
the night in cafeterias and gymnasiums. ``Hopefully we'll have them
all out in a couple of days,'' said <PERSON>Tekoa King</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> nurse.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890403-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-03-89 2041EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Earthquake 1stLd-Writethru a0638 04-03 0398</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Earthquake, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0638,0404</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sharp Jolt Hits San Francisco Peninsula</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 10th graf, `April 6,' to CORRECT date of great San Francisco
earthquake to April 18, sted April 6.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A strong earthquake shook the <LOCATION>San
Francisco Peninsula</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but there were no immediate reports
of injury or serious damage.
   ``I went outside and watched the windows rattle,'' said <PERSON>Marcey
Beaupre</PERSON>, manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Super Yarn Mart</ORGANIZATION> in nearby <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. ``I
got 20 windows and all they did was rattle. Nothing happened.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> set a preliminary magnitude of 5.0 on
the Richter scale for the temblor, while the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION>'s seismographic stations at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> rated it at 4.4.
   A 5.0 quake is considered powerful enough to cause considerable
damage in populated areas.
