<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900924-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-24-90 0422EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Farmer'sAlmanac     09-24 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farmer's Almanac,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old Farmer's Almanac Predicts Cold, Snowy Winter for Much of
Country</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By NORMA LOVE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mixed in with the ads for trusses and
carousel music in the 199th Old Farmer's Almanac are predictions
for a cold, snowy winter and advice on helping a baby grow: Put
manure in the infant's shoes.
   The 224-page, 199th edition hits newsstands and supermarkets
this week with its traditional weather predictions, planting and
tide tables, anecdotes and folklor.
   It claims <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy in its weather forecasts, but
editor and part-owner <PERSON>Judson Hale</PERSON> says that figure is not cast in
stone.
   ``I can't in seriousness say <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT>,'' he said in a
telephone interview from his <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> office. He missed the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>
drought in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Nevertheless, the almanac is predicting a ``real old-fashioned
winter'' east of the Rockies with below-normal temperatures over
much of the country except <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, sections of the <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and lower
<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> valleys and the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, it predicts, will have warmer than normal weather in
<DATE>February</DATE> and <DATE>March</DATE>.
   The almanac also forecasts a generally warmer <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE>
than normal, but a cool and wet <DATE>fall</DATE>.
   The almanac says its forecasts are based on a combination of a
secret formula devised by its founder and the ``most modern
scientific calculation based on solar activity.''
   Hale also strays into earthquake forecasts, noting that the moon
will be 221,545 miles from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on New Year's Eve, closer than
its average of 251,000 miles.
   ``Some people would believe it would have an influence on an
earthquake if an earthquake was thinking about happening,'' he
said. Believers argue that when the moon is closer and its
gravitational pull is stronger, there is greater stress on rock
layers that might rupture and cause a quake.
   The almanac even offers folklore advice on babies. On
conception, the almanac offers this folk wisdom: If a woman lays
her hat or coat on a strange bed, she will have a child.
   To have a boy, she should hold a nickel in her mouth at the time
of conception. To make the baby grow tall, folksters suggest
putting manure in the child's shoes.
   The yellow-covered Old Farmer's Almanac has changed little since
it was first published in <DATE>1792</DATE>.
   The Old Farmer's Almanac is not to be confused with its upstart
rival, the Farmer's Almanac, which is about a third as thick, 23
years younger, and is given away to businesses for advertising
purposes.
   The distinguishing trademark of the Old Farmer's Almanac is a
hole in the corner, put there at great expense and inconvenience,
its publishers say, to preserve the tradition of hanging the book
on a nail in the pantry or outhouse.
   ``It does indicate it is, in a sense, a calendar,'' <PERSON>Hale</PERSON> says.
   Hale spent the <DATE>summer</DATE> scouring previous issues for lore to
include in an expanded 200th anniversary edition next year.
   ``I'm up to <DATE>1931</DATE>,'' he said. ``I have 65 pages of notes.''
   Almanac readers will get a chance to contribute. The essay topic
for the 200th edition: How the Old Farmer's Almanac Has Influenced
My Life.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880927-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-27-88 0312EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Farmer'sAlmanac Bjt   09-27 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farmer's Almanac, Bjt,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old Farmer's Almanac: From Weather Forecasts To Muskie Hypnotizing
Lobsters</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CR2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE RECHT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 197th edition of the Old Farmer's
Almanac contains a forecast for a white Christmas in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION>, a
prediction of woe for <ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> fans, and former <PERSON>Sen. Edmund Muskie</PERSON>'s
technique for mesmerizing lobsters.
   Published in tiny <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, the oldest continuously
published almanac in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> hits newsstands today with
its usual, homey brand of ``new, useful and entertaining matter''
for the 9 million readers it claims.
   A competing Farmer's Almanac, which is marking its 55th year,
was released earlier this month. That publication is sold to banks,
insurance companies and other businesses for distribution to
customers as a promotion and claims a circulation of more than 5
million.
   Started in <DATE>1792</DATE>, the 224-page Old Farmer's Almanac also contains
its usual fearless extended weather forecast for <DATE>1989</DATE> for 16 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
regions.
   Editor <PERSON>Judson Hale</PERSON> claims <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy with the secret
formula and the ``most modern scientific calculation based on solar
activity,'' although it failed to predict last <DATE>summer</DATE>'s devastating
drought.
   Looking ahead, the almanac predicts heavy snow starting around
Thanksgiving from <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> and down the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>,
with a frigid <DATE>December</DATE> in some sections before temperatures rise
and the weather dries.
   That means a white <DATE>Christmas</DATE>, but ``snow stopping in time for
cork popping'' at New Year's.
   While <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, southern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and the desert <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>
should prepare for below-normal temperatures, the rest of the
country will get a warmer winter than usual.
   For the <DATE>summer</DATE>, the almanac calls for cooler, wetter weather
along the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, normal temperatures in <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
and the Deep South, and drier weather in the <LOCATION>Ohio Valley</LOCATION> through
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION>.
   But for the often-disappointed fans of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>'s beloved Red Sox,
next <DATE>September</DATE>'s forecast is the most crucial: It comes with the
warning, ``Sox in first, expect the worst.''
   The familiar black and yellow publication, punctuated this year
with sporty red highlights, again offers predictions for consumers,
who can expect fake caviar, low-calorie tortilla chips, scented
newspaper ads and the ``ultimate indignity'' _ garbage rationing _
in the coming 15 months.
   The casual reader may also be drawn to educational features,
such as the ``straight facts about warts'' and ways to get rid of
them ranging from ``bizarre and complicated'' to ``extremely
disgusting'' and ``downright criminal.''
   Muskie, the former Democratic senator from <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
secretary of state, offered a followup to a <DATE>1984</DATE> article on
hypnotizing chickens with his own ``foolproof ways to hypnotize a
lobster.''
   By stroking the tail in a downward motion, ``curling it as you
go,'' he said, you can impress friends by getting the lobster to do
a claw stand on its head.
   A vigorous shake should bring the lobster back to its senses,
but if that doesn't work, <PERSON>Muskie</PERSON> wrote, just whisper in its ear,
``Drawn butter, drawn butter.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880616-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-88 0226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Drought-Almanac     06-16 0252</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Drought-Almanac,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Old Farmer's Almanac' Reader Complains About Missed Forecast</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Drought-Iowa, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CINCINNATI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After watching his half-acre of grass wither
and dry this <DATE>spring</DATE>, <PERSON>Witham Smith</PERSON> wrote a letter to the ``Old
Farmer's Almanac.''
   <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, a regular reader of the almanac, asked whether the
196-year-old publication's forecasters, having missed the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>'s
drought, could at least predict the dry spell's end.
   He received a pretty dry answer from <PERSON>Judson D. Hale Sr.</PERSON>, editor
of the almanac.
   ``We didn't predict that it was coming and we can't predict when
it will end,'' <PERSON>Hale</PERSON> wrote <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, who lives in suburban Terrace Park.
   The almanac claims to be <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accurate, but <PERSON>Hale</PERSON>
acknowledged that it doesn't predict weather for <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE>
too well.
   This year, it predicted that it would be warmer and wetter than
normal in the <LOCATION>Greater Ohio Valley</LOCATION>. Heavy rain was predicted for
<DATE>June 14</DATE> to 17.
   The almanac usually gathers statistics for its predictions six
to 18 months in advance. The predictions are based on such
information as changes in sun spots, the size of polar ice caps,
and the location of warm water currents.
   ``Our <DATE>1989</DATE> edition will be published in <DATE>November</DATE>. It is really
hard to nail down the weather for <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE> that far in
advance because so many things happen,'' <PERSON>Hale</PERSON> said.
   ``They have been a little off before, but never this far,''
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said. ``They said we would be about half an inch off, but not
a drought like this.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890925-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-25-89 1630EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OldFarmer'sAlmanac     09-25 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Old Farmer's Almanac,0410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Farmer's Almanac Forecasts Mild Winter, Holiday Snow</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ADOLPHE V. BERNOTAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rest easy <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>! Abe Weatherwise,
prognosticator of the Old Farmer's Almanac, says it'll be a mild
winter across most of the country. And <LOCATION>New Englanders</LOCATION> can expect a
white <DATE>Christmas</DATE>.
   Abe, who claims <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy in ``<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s oldest
continuously published periodical,'' says only the northern third
of the country will have more snow than usual.
   The 198th edition of the 224-page almanac hits the newsstands
and supermarkets this week with its familiar planting and tide
tables, anecdotes and other tidbits, such as 100 ways how to avoid
untimely death. (No. 49. Avoid combing hair in the dark; No. 77.
Never whistle in a coal mine.)
   Abe, a collective pseudonym, says the almanac's predictions are
``based on state-of-the art analysis of recurring solar cycles.''
He predicts that a cold, wet and snowy <DATE>spring</DATE> in the North will be
balanced by warm, dry <DATE>spring</DATE> weather west of the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   The <DATE>summer of 1990</DATE>, says Abe, will be hot and dry in many areas
east of the Rockies.
   In <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, where 300,000 of the 4 million copies of the
customary yellow-covered almanac will be sold, heavier than average
snow is forecast from <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION> through the prairie provinces.
   ``The more serious the weather, the larger percentage we sell,''
says Executive Editor <PERSON>Tim Clark</PERSON>. ``They count on us more in <LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>
than in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>.''
   The Old Farmer's Almanac is the legal document for tides and
sunrises and sunsets in most states. In addition to giving readers
weather predictions, advertisements for hernia appliances, secrets
of winning lotteries and rules of thumb for rhubarb pie, the
almanac advises that cows and pigs bred for leanness will boost the
popularity of red meat and inflation will run at <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.
   The almanac also predicts the return of 4-inch-wide neckties for
men, short hair for women and lower prices for videocassette
recorders.
   The Old Farmer's Almanac is not to be confused with its upstart
rival, the Farmer's Almanac, which is about a third as thick, 23
years younger, and is given away to businesses for advertising
purposes.
   The distinguishing trademark of the Old Farmer's Almanac is a
hole in the corner, put there at great expense and inconvenience,
its publishers say, to preserve the tradition of hanging the book
on a nail in the pantry or outhouse.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911105-0012
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911105-0012.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Two Hundred Years of Farmerly Advice
   ----
   By Joanne Kaufman
</HL>
<DATE>
11/05/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A16
</SO>
<LP>
   When people meet Judson Hale, they are almost always
disappointed. "They expect me to be wearing overalls," said
the editor of The Old Farmer's Almanac, which just came out
with its 200th edition, further cementing its position as the
oldest continuously published periodical in the U.S. "But
I've worn a coat and tie since the third grade."
   They expect him to be a farmer (Mr. Hale grew up on a farm
but avoided farming. "I would go down to the barn and WATCH,"
he said); they expect him to talk with a Maine accent (Mr.
Hale is of Boston Brahmin stock); they expect him to be
aphoristic ("Red sky at morning; sailors take warning" is not
the sort of thing that springs readily to Mr. Hale's lips).
And they expect him to be old. "I'm fulfilling that part
now," the 58-year-old Mr. Hale said cheerfully.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In fact, <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> doesn't bother his head much about the
expectations of strangers and of talk-show hosts who are
always importuning him to appear on their programs holding a
rake. He has an almanac to put out, a task that seems to grow
more daunting every year. "I'm always scared to death when we
start a new issue," said <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>, who as 12th editor of the
Almanac is known in certain circles as <PERSON>Jud XII</PERSON>. "You can only
be as good as the last one. The 200th edition seems to have
been received well but I'm now nervous about <DATE>1993</DATE> and people
being let down.
   "I don't care if I disappoint marketing people or our
public relations people. I value advertisers, but my first
and foremost concern is for the readers and how they feel
about the publication."
   Indeed, readers have extremely strong feelings about The
Old Farmer's Almanac, which is, as it has been since
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s presidency, a compendium of weather forecasts,
astronomical calculations, recipes, planting tables and "new,
useful and entertaining matter" like "How to Get Rich Without
Doing Any Work," "What Hardly Anyone Knows About <PERSON>Ellis
Island</PERSON>," "The Facts and Fictions About Death Valley" and
"Peace and Hominy: Some Thoughts on Grits."
   According to <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>, longtime devotees of the Almanac
write or call the <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, N.H.-based publication to check the
optimum time for having surgery (folklore has it that one can
expect more bleeding when the moon is full). They weigh in --
with triumph -- when they catch mistakes in the sunrise
tables. And they make their feelings known -- with vigor --
when the Almanac makes unwarranted changes. "Dear Sir," a
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> reader once wrote, "I have read The Old Farmer's
Almanac for the <DATE>last 75 years</DATE> and I wish the damned fool that
changed the reading of the moon's column had died before he
done it. Yours, respectfully."
   "People expect The Old Farmer's Almanac to BE The Old
Farmer's Almanac," said <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>, who's been editor for the
past 21 years. "I think readers feel they own it, that it's
one of their inalienable rights as long as they can come up
with the <MONEY>$2.95</MONEY> to pay for it.
   "I think everyone who works at the Almanac sees it as a
responsibility," he added. "It's like owning a 17th-century
house. You shouldn't add a porch to it because the house
belongs to American architectural heritage as much as it
belongs to the present owners."
   <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>'s success as editor -- the <DATE>1991</DATE> OFA sold four
million copies with sales of six million projected for '92 --
can be partly explained by his strong identification with
readers, partly by his strong identification with the Almanac
itself. "I think <PERSON>Jud</PERSON> embodies the values the Almanac has
represented for so long," said <PERSON>John Pierce</PERSON>, publisher of the
OFA. "He believes that if you work hard you'll do well, that
it's important to be part of your community, that by staying
in touch with some aspect of the natural world we stay in
touch with ourselves, and that man is inherently a decent
species -- and those are all the values of the Almanac."
   Then, of course, there is the short explanation, that <PERSON>Mr.
Hale</PERSON> is simply adhering to the policy set forth by the
Almanac's founding editor, <PERSON>Robert B. Thomas</PERSON>: "Our endeavor is
to be useful but with a pleasant degree of humor."
   <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and grew up on a communal
organic farm in <LOCATION>Vanceboro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Me.</LOCATION>, a venture that was largely
funded by his parents, adherents of the Austrian scientist
and philosopher <PERSON>Rudolf Steiner</PERSON>. Educated at <LOCATION>Dartmouth</LOCATION>, he
cast about for a career until deciding in <DATE>1959</DATE> to accept the
offer of employment from his uncle <PERSON>Robb Sagendorph</PERSON>, then
editor of the <ORGANIZATION>OFA</ORGANIZATION> and its sister publication, the magazine
Yankee.
   Since the beginning of his tenure as editor, <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> has
had to confront several misconceptions about the Almanac,
among them the belief that the periodical -- with its
signature yellow cover festooned with woodcuts, rococo
scrollwork, cameos and antiquated typography -- is a
nostalgia book. "It isn't," <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> said flatly. "I want
people when they read the Almanac 100 years from now to look
at the <DATE>1992</DATE> edition and know what life in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> was like
in <DATE>1992</DATE>. And they will. There are television trends and
fashion trends and the current state of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The most enduring misconception about the Almanac, said
<PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>, is the belief that its raison d'etre is weather
forecasting. "It's 24 pages out of every issue and costs
<MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> a year, which is more expensive than any other 24
pages," he said. "But it isn't the major reason for the
Almanac's existence and it never was."
   About those weather forecasts. They are the work of
<ORGANIZATION>Richard Head</ORGANIZATION>, a former <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientist, who relies on current
and historical solar observations along with space-probe data
to come up with predictions that are, he calculates, about
<PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> accurate.
   "We say our predictions are <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> accurate," amended <PERSON>Mr.
Hale</PERSON>, who is astonishingly adept at bending the weather to
fit the Almanac's forecasts. If, for example, he's giving a
speech in a region told to expect "cool, cloudy, chance of
showers" and things turn out hot, dry and sunny, well, the
waggish editor is ready to explain. "The air conditioner is
on so it's cool," he'll begin. "And I didn't get much sleep
so everything is cloudy, and we all took showers this morning
so we're on our way to <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> accuracy."
   Marginally imperfect (ahem) though its forecasting may be,
the Almanac sells briskly to prospective brides who want to
pinpoint the sunniest <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <DATE>June</DATE>. Others are more
inclined to buy it for the recipes or for tips on growing
impressive vegetables. Some buy it just to hang up (the
Almanac has a hole in the upper left corner to accommodate
just such people). And there are those people who buy the
Almanac simply because it is 200 years old. "If this were the
fifth-anniversary issue it wouldn't be selling even half what
it is," said <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON>.
   Clearly, <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> hopes to turn the curious into converts.
"I think we feel we're doing some good," he said. "The Old
Farmer's Almanac is a constant. With things in the world
changing as fast as they are, we feel we're giving people a
lift."
   They are. Wherever <PERSON>Mr. Hale</PERSON> travels carrying the little
yellow book, people nod and smile fondly. "The Old Farmer's
Almanac," they say, "My grandmother used to read that."
   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Kaufman</PERSON> is a free-lance writer based in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06254066 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06254066 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WEATHER; FORECAST; FARM; BOOK  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Born the same year as the presidential veto, commercially baked crackers and
the New York Stock Exchange, The Old Farmer's Almanac is celebrating its 200th
anniversary as it observed the last 199.;   Again there is no shortage of odd
tales, recipes and weather forecasts for the coming year.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  200 YEARS OF IMPERFECT FORECASTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Quaint constancy is the endearing feature of the yellow-bound volume that
evolved from a slim booklet created in <DATE>1792</DATE> by <PERSON>Robert Thomas</PERSON>, a bookseller,
teacher and amateur astronomer from what is now <LOCATION>West Boylston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>;   Both
the original and the <DATE>1992</DATE> anniversary edition, released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, contain
"recipes, articles both current and historical, advice, an odd assortment of
useful and rather useless information, gardening hints and, yes, weather
forecasts," reads the forward in the glossy bookstore edition of the newest
almanac.;   Despite the space given to forecasts, editor <PERSON>Judson Hale</PERSON> said, The
Old Farmer's Almanac's claim of <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy is "a tradition, and we
don't take that seriously at all.";   This year's forecast, Farmers' Almanac
prognosticator <PERSON>Caleb Weatherbee</PERSON> said, calls for moderate temperatures this
<DATE>winter</DATE> and more rain than snow. The <DATE>summer</DATE> of '92 will be stormy and
turbulent, he said.;   Last year's forecast for <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> was well off the
mark, predicting thick snow in the <DATE>winter</DATE> and heavy rain from <DATE>May</DATE> to <DATE>July</DATE>;
neither materialized. It forecast near-drought for <DATE>August</DATE>, which actually saw
torrential rains and Hurricane Bob.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Concord, N.H.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910910  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  230  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, September 10, 1991
00254066,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880907-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-88 0306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Farmers'Almanac Bjt   09-07 0727</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farmers' Almanac, Bjt,0750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Almanac: A Penny Saved Is A Penny Spurned; Try A 12{-Cent `Bit'
Instead</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AU1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEWISTON, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Farmers' Almanac expects to see a
little less snow and a lot less drought next year, but what the
172-year-old digest of Americana really wants to see less of is
pennies.
   The penny, inspiration for homely expressions that have been a
staple of almanacs since <PERSON>Benjamin Franklin</PERSON> set up shop _ ``A penny
saved is a penny earned'' is one _ has outlived its usefulness,
concludes the <DATE>1989</DATE> edition of the Farmer's Almanac.
   ``Only tradition explains our stubborn attachment to the penny.
But sometimes traditions get ridiculous,'' the almanac says, living
down its reputation as a defender of long-held values.
   Instead, editor <PERSON>Ray Geiger</PERSON> has proposed a new coin worth 12{
cents, or one ``bit.''
   ``I can't think of anything you can buy with a penny. The penny
candy is all a nickel,'' said <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>, who with varying degrees of
success has led the publication's previous campaigns to restore
city names to postmarks, eliminate the nine-digit ZIP code and
print currency in colors other than green.
   ``You see a penny on the street and you no longer bother to pick
it up,'' and young children often find it's no longer worth their
time and effort to empty jars of pennies and package them in
50-cent rolls, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said in a recent interview.
   Also in the newly released edition is a prediction for another
``cold and mean'' <DATE>winter</DATE>, but not as rough as the last one, with a
little less snow in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Rockies</LOCATION>.
   The <DATE>summer of 1989</DATE> should be more pleasant, with drier than
average weather but no repeat of this year's drought, according to
<PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>. ``We didn't predict the drought, but neither did anybody
else,'' he said.
   But what really gets <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> heated up is the persistence of the
penny, whose purchasing power has diminished to the point where its
only uses are making change and collecting sales taxes, according
to the almanac.
   The almanac's plan for the bit _ a name derived from ``two
bits,'' the colloquial expression for a quarter _ takes into
account the change in monetary values.
   ``This perceives the dollar as being cut into eight equal
pieces, half a dollar is four bits, <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY> is six bits,'' the
almanac said. It points out that while <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> money is based on the
decimal system, stock markets routinely list prices in increments
of one-eighth of a dollar.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Mint</ORGANIZATION> churns out billions of pennies each year, and the
almanac suggests that as many as 200 billion of the coins may be
squirreled away in vaults, baby banks, cookie jars and shoe boxes.
   The almanac says the introduction of the bit would bridge the
gap between the dime and the <DATE>quarter</DATE>, for greater flexibility in
coin combinations that would produce 22{ cents, 27{ cents and so
forth, all the way up to <MONEY>97{ cents</MONEY>.
   To promote the idea, the almanac suggests a gold-toned coin that
would be about as thick as a dime, midway in size between the
nickel and the quarter.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Treasury Department</ORGANIZATION> declined to embrace the recommendation,
saying there has been no groundswell of support for a change.
   ``We've periodically examined the penny, and right now the
department has no plans to eliminate it. It's still an integral
part of the coinage system,'' said spokeswoman <PERSON>Felice Pelosi</PERSON>.
   Undaunted, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said he was prepared to travel to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
to solicit support for the change.
   ``Some people will think this is a nutty idea, but they thought
it was a nutty idea to bring back the old postmark, and that was a
singlehanded victory for the Farmers' Almanac,'' he said.
   Geiger's almanac, which is sold to banks, insurance companies
and other businesses for distribution to customers as a promotion,
claims a circulation of more than 5 million.
   Its 48 pages are a compendium of calendar data, household hints,
one-line jokes, inspirational messages, recipes and, of course,
weather predictions derived through a secret formula by the
almanac's forecaster, <PERSON>Caleb Weatherbee</PERSON>.
   Geiger, who turns 78 this month, is marking his 55th year as
almanac editor, a tenure he says ties the record established by the
original editor of the Old Farmers Almanac, a New Hampshire-based
publication founded in <DATE>1792</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900907-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-90 1241EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Farmers'Almanac     09-07 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farmers' Almanac,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>An Early Thanksgiving? Almanac Suggests Giving It Some Thought</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEWISTON, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Not one to tamper lightly with tradition,
the Farmers' Almanac suggests nonetheless that the date designated
for Thanksgiving is a turkey.
   In its <DATE>1991</DATE> edition, just off the presses, the venerable
publication says Americans should consider celebrating the holiday,
the fourth <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <DATE>November</DATE>, earlier in the <DATE>fall</DATE>.
   An earlier date would rid Thanksgiving of pre-Christmas
overtones, allow for more favorable travel weather and line it up
more closely with the harvest whose bounty it is meant to
celebrate, the almanac says.
   The almanac says the second <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <DATE>October</DATE>, the date on which
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> celebrates Thanksgiving, might be an appropriate
alternative. Almanac editor <PERSON>Ray Geiger</PERSON> invites readers to offer
their own ideas.
   ``We're only suggesting that we examine this thing. We're not
bold enough to say `do it!''' <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said in an interview.
   Thanksgiving, commemorating the feast held by members of the
<ORGANIZATION>Plymouth Colony</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1621</DATE> to celebrate that
year's harvest, has been observed at various dates over the years.
It has remained at its current date since <DATE>1863</DATE>, except for a brief
period when President <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> reset it for the third
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   ``Thanksgiving is a sacred holiday. What makes it sacrosanct is
not that it is observed on a certain date each year, but rather
what it means,'' the almanac says. ``When one ponders the real
reason for Thanksgiving, the date of celebration seems immaterial.''
   <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said the principal reason for change would be to separate
Thanksgiving from the overlapping demands posed by the start of the
Christmas season.
   ``You've got football, you've got <DATE>Christmas</DATE> pressing and you
don't know whether you're celebrating Thanksgiving or Christmas,''
he said.
   An earlier holiday would reduce the chances that travelers would
encounter ice or snow while heading to family gatherings, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>
said. And it would shift the holiday to a time closer to the end of
the harvest, when the woods still are ablaze with colorful foliage,
he said.
   By contrast, fields and orchards are bare in late <DATE>November</DATE> and
trees have lost their leaves. ``When we celebrate Thanksgiving
under these conditions, we seem to have lost our sense of timing,''
the almanac said.
   The date change could mark the start of a new crusade by the
174-year-old almanac, which in years past has prodded the
government to restore city names to postmarks and eliminate the
nine-digit ZIP code.
   Geiger's almanac is not to be confused with the Old Farmers
Almanac, the 198-year-old New Hampshire-based publication. Geiger
claims a circulation of about 5 million for the 48-page
publication, sold to banks, insurance companies and other
businesses that distribute it to customers as a promotional tool.
   Last year's campaign promoting the introduction of a coin it
calls the <LOCATION>Columbus Dollar</LOCATION> as a replacement for the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> bill is
making progress, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said, and bills introduced in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> are enjoying increased support.
   That proposal, along with the shuffling of Thanksgiving, does
not mean that the almanac is abandoning its longstanding profession
of traditional values.
   ``Tradition is a must for us, but we're not blinded by it,''
<PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said.
   Almanac traditions include calendar data, puzzles, household
hints, inspirational messages, one-line jokes and ``flavorite
recipes.''
   Another tradition is weather data. This year's edition predicts
a harsh winter _ chilling news to households concerned about rising
energy prices brought on by the crisis in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>.
   ``It's going to be a rough winter, rougher than last year, with
more snow and more cold weather in <DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>February</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>
said.
   ``But it's not going to be a prolonged winter. It's going to
ease off early in <DATE>March</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said. The almanac forecasts a
mild <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer</DATE> that won't be too hot.
   The forecasts are prepared by <PERSON>Caleb Weatherbee</PERSON>, who calculates
them in accordance with a secret formula based on sunspots, the
position of the planets and the tidal action of the moon, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>
said.
   ``His track record has been excellent, getting better every
year.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890912-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-89 0250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Farmers'Almanac     09-12 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farmers' Almanac,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Almanac Promotes $1 Columbus Coin, Phaseout of Penny and Paper Dollar</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JERRY HARKAVY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEWISTON, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Farmers' Almanac, renewing its crusade
to revamp the nation's coinage and currency, is promoting a <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin
to replace the dollar bill to pinch a few pennies for <ORGANIZATION>Uncle Sam</ORGANIZATION> and
taxpayers.
   The almanac's <DATE>1990</DATE> edition, just off the presses, also calls for
the elimination of the penny and 50-cent piece. The new <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin
could be called the <ORGANIZATION>Columbus Dollar</ORGANIZATION>, honoring the explorer who
discovered the New World, the publication said.
   The almanac endorses a bill introduced by Rep. <PERSON>Jim Kolbe</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>R-Ariz.</LOCATION>, to direct the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> to mint and circulate the <ORGANIZATION>Columbus
Dollar</ORGANIZATION> and halt production of the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> bill 18 months after the coin
is placed in circulation.
   Under the new system, the little-used <MONEY>$2</MONEY> bill likely would become
the most popular piece of currency, says almanac editor <PERSON>Ray Geiger</PERSON>.
   Geiger maintains that the new system would create a coinage and
currency system that reflects contemporary values and lifestyles.
   He quotes the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION> as saying replacement of the <MONEY>$1</MONEY>
bill by the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin would save the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> more than <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> a
year.
   ``It costs approximately <MONEY>2.6 cents</MONEY> to print a <MONEY>$1</MONEY> bill and the
bill lasts about 18 months before it goes to the shredder. It costs
3<MONEY>{ cents</MONEY> to mint a <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin, but the coin will last 20 years,'' he
said.
   ``The Farmers' Almanac, 173 years old, has always been a champion
of the common man, and we think the common man is entitled to
protect his right to a coinage that's sensible and realistic,'' he
said in an interview.
   Geiger's publication, not to be confused with the 197-year-old
New Hampshire-based Old Farmers Almanac, has previously prodded the
government to restore city names to postmarks, eliminate the
nine-digit ZIP code and print currency in colors other than green.
   <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON>, who claims a circulation of more than 5 million, said
this year's 48-page almanac contains the usual mix of calendar data,
household hints, one-line jokes and inspirational messages.
   It also has weather predictions by prognosticator <PERSON>Caleb
Weatherbee</PERSON> that are based on ``a secret formula based on sunspots,
the position of the planets and the tidal action of the moon.''
   <PERSON>Weatherbee</PERSON> predicts that the <DATE>winter</DATE> of 1989-90 will be milder
than usual with less snow, while next <DATE>summer</DATE> will be pleasant with
moderate rainfall.
   The campaign for the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin follows last year's proposal for a
new coin worth 12{ cents _ or one ``bit.'' As <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> saw it, the bit
would bridge the gap between the dime and quarter. That suggestion
didn't catch on.
   But the almanac remains adamant that the penny has got to go,
saying most of the 200 billion in circulation simply gather dust in
shoe boxes and piggy banks. It suggests that sales be rounded off to
the nearest nickel.
   On the <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin, <PERSON>Geiger</PERSON> said the <PERSON>Susan B. Anthony</PERSON> dollar coin
failed to become popular because it was not easily distinguished
from the quarter and because it was introduced as an alternative to
the paper dollar, rather than a replacement.
   The almanac even has a design ready for a new <MONEY>$1</MONEY> coin. Art
director <PERSON>Ed Greenwood</PERSON> drew a sample coin that features a portrait of
the explorer on one side and two of his ships on the other.
   The almanac suggests that the coin be gold toned, 1[ inches in
diameter, ungrooved or unribbed on the edges, with the thickness of
a quarter. It would also be light _ .015 ounce, or one-quarter the
weight of the old silver dollar.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06360237 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06360237 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; EDUCATION; BOOK  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ON DEC. 28, 1732, an ad in a Philadelphia newspaper announced the publication
of a new almanac complete with "witty verses, jests, and sayings" supposedly
compiled by one Richard Saunders. This advertisement would have remained quite
unremarkable, given the fact that there were numerous almanacs available to
people at that time.;   But the "Richard Saunders" mentioned in this ad was
really a pseudonym for Benjamin Franklin, and the new almanac, called "Poor
Richard's Almanac," became one of the most popular and influential
publications in all of colonial America.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Peninsula Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'POOR RICHARD'S' LEGACY LIVES ON  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EAST5, EX4/5, WL6 Education; Family Learning; William F. Russell's
books for parents and children include "Classics to Read Aloud to Your
Children" and "Classic Myths to Read Aloud."  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     I recently saw a copy of an old "Poor <PERSON>Richard</PERSON>'s Almanac," and I was struck
by how similar it was in its arrangement and style to another almanac that is
only slightly less historic, but is still published today: "The Old Farmer's
Almanac.";   In fact, this new year marks the 200th anniversary of the
beginning of "The Old Farmer's Almanac," and it may also be a good time for us
to consider this wonderful piece of Americana as a worthwhile and inexpensive
addition to our collection of home learning resources.;    THE TYPES of home
resources that I have been promoting as good acquisitions for "family
learning" activities are those that either inspire interest in learning or
confirm various learnings that were stimulated elsewhere, or both. A family
dictionary, for example, can be used to investigate a pronunciation or a word
usage that you heard on television, but that word (perhaps its spelling,
definition, or derivation) can lead you to investigate other words as well,
and you can come back from your trip to the dictionary with much more than you
went looking to find.;   I think "The Old Farmer's Almanac" fits this same
bill because it enables, as well as encourages, its readers to learn from the
world around them. Forget the weather predictions, which were of greater
interest and utility in centuries past, but are now mainly just a curiosity
for most readers, including farmers.;   Look instead at the wealth of
information about topics like astronomy, geography and history that can be
found here and probably not in any other single learning resource. The almanac
gives you the precise times for the rising and setting of the sun and the
moon, the position of each major constellation, the phases of the moon, the
time and place of eclipses and meteor showers during the year.;   But there is
more than astronomy here, for you'll also find the exact longitude and
latitude for hundreds of cities in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, as well as
items of historical interest for each day of the year, and many well-written
essays that can inspire family discussions and activities.;   YOU SEE, this
almanac -- like the family dictionary or a globe or an atlas -- can be a
springboard for all types of learning that can go on around the house. This is
what <PERSON>Franklin</PERSON>'s almanac did for our colonial ancestors, but we are more
fortunate in that we can use our almanac in conjunction with other home and
school and library resources to acquire an education that "is both broad and
deep.";   This <DATE>1992</DATE> "Old Farmer's Almanac" is of special value in family
learning because it is the bicentennial edition, and it includes several
features that focus on the events of the last 200 years, and especially on the
way things were in <DATE>1792</DATE>, when the first edition of the almanac was published,
when <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON> was president, when the average age in the country was
16, and when the almanac sold for sixpence.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William Russell column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/Am  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911225  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  619  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, December 25, 1991
00360237,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901219-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-19-90 2028EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Farmer'sAlmanac     12-19 0228</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Farmer's Almanac,0248</SECOND>
<HEAD>Folksy Almanac Takes on Big-City Magazine</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Old Farmer's Almanac, the folksy,
old-fashioned American tradition, has taken on <ORGANIZATION>New York Magazine</ORGANIZATION>,
the trendy chronicle of life in the big city.
   The 199-year-old Almanac filed a trademark infringement lawsuit
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> accusing the magazine of imitating the Almanac's
distinctive cover design with the <DATE>Dec. 3</DATE> issue.
   The Almanac's publisher, <ORGANIZATION>Yankee Publishing Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>,
said the covers were so similar that readers might be led to
believe the Almanac authorized or in some way sponsored its use by
<ORGANIZATION>New York Magazine</ORGANIZATION>.
   The lawsuit said the magazine, by imitating its trademarked
cover, had ``impaired the value of <ORGANIZATION>Yankee</ORGANIZATION>'s cover design and the
goodwill symbolized by it.''
   <PERSON>Susan Soriano</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the magazine, said the magazine
had not received the lawsuit and had no immediate comment.
   The disputed cover, titled ``The <DATE>1990</DATE> Christmas Gifts Almanac,''
promotes a story of gift suggestions for the holidays. It is
illustrated in a similar design as used by the Almanac.
   Yankee accuses the magazine of copying, among other things, the
overall distinctive yellow color, the use of red and green
highlights and a red and white border, and a nearly identical style
of typeface.
order barring the magazine from using the design in the future. It
also seeks unspecified damages.
   The Almanac has been published annually since <DATE>1792</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890926-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-26-89 0046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     09-26 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Lite Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FLOODWOOD, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Gary Liubakka</PERSON> is a newcomer to politics,
but he figures he's bound to get a hefty vote in next year's
gubernatorial race.
   That's because he's running as founder of the <ORGANIZATION>National Apathetic
Party</ORGANIZATION>. With a <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> voter turnout expected in the <DATE>1990</DATE>
election, Liubakka can claim the other <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the electorate
as constituents.
   ``They won't vote, and a `no' vote is a vote for me,'' the
36-year-old contractor said recently.
   The unofficial party _ it's known as <ORGANIZATION>NAP</ORGANIZATION> _ even has a mascot: a
battered eagle.
   The bird's neck is longer than most eagles' because it's been
stretched a few times. Its left wing is clipped from giving away so
many handouts. Its tail feathers are lost.
   On the rare occasions Liubakka removes his tongue from his
cheek, he'll betray serious worries about the state of the body
politic.
   ``Our intention is to slap everybody in the face with
ignorance,'' the unregistered candidate said, ``and hopefully this
blunt hint will get them out to vote more.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>DUBLIN, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Gary Liubakka</PERSON> is a newcomer to politics,
but he figures he's bound to get a hefty vote in next year's
gubernatorial race.
   That's because he's running as founder of the <ORGANIZATION>National Apathetic
Party</ORGANIZATION>. With a <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> voter turnout expected in the <DATE>1990</DATE>
election, Liubakka can claim the other <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the electorate
as constituents.
   ``They won't vote, and a `no' vote is a vote for me,'' the
36-year-old contractor said recently.
   The unofficial party _ it's known as <ORGANIZATION>NAP</ORGANIZATION> _ even has a mascot: a
battered eagle.
   The bird's neck is longer than most eagles' because it's been
stretched a few times. Its left wing is clipped from giving away so
many handouts. Its tail feathers are lost.
   On the rare occasions Liubakka removes his tongue from his
cheek, he'll betray serious worries about the state of the body
politic.
   ``Our intention is to slap everybody in the face with
ignorance,'' the unregistered candidate said, ``and hopefully this
blunt hint will get them out to vote more.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>POMONA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Gary Liubakka</PERSON> is a newcomer to politics,
but he figures he's bound to get a hefty vote in next year's
gubernatorial race.
   That's because he's running as founder of the <ORGANIZATION>National Apathetic
Party</ORGANIZATION>. With a <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> voter turnout expected in the <DATE>1990</DATE>
election, Liubakka can claim the other <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the electorate
as constituents.
   ``They won't vote, and a `no' vote is a vote for me,'' the
36-year-old contractor said recently.
   The unofficial party _ it's known as <ORGANIZATION>NAP</ORGANIZATION> _ even has a mascot: a
battered eagle.
   The bird's neck is longer than most eagles' because it's been
stretched a few times. Its left wing is clipped from giving away so
many handouts. Its tail feathers are lost.
   On the rare occasions Liubakka removes his tongue from his
cheek, he'll betray serious worries about the state of the body
politic.
   ``Our intention is to slap everybody in the face with
ignorance,'' the unregistered candidate said, ``and hopefully this
blunt hint will get them out to vote more.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900202-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-90 1019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Groundhog 2ndLd_Writethru a0513 02-02 0792</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Groundhog, 2nd Ld _ Writethru, a0513,0812</SECOND>
<HEAD>Punxsutawney Phil Doesn't Spot Shadow, Means Early Spring</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts one graf after 6th, `I've always...'. to ADD other
forecasting groundhogs. Picks up 7th graf, `Legend has...'. INSERTS
one graf after 16th graf, `The 14...'. to ADD groundhog hat worn by
handler. Picks up 17th graf, `Every other...'. ADDS three grafs
with details on other groundhogs.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PUNX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PUNXSUTAWNEY, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Punxsutawney <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s premier
groundhog, emerged from his burrow today and indicated in
``unmistakable groundhogese'' that he had failed to spot his
shadow, a sure sign <DATE>spring</DATE> is just around the corner, according to
<PERSON>Phil</PERSON>'s followers.
   ``He stood proud, tall and confident, surveyed the throng of
loyal followers, peered skyward toward the east and then fixed his
eyes groundward,'' said county judge <PERSON>Edwin Snyder</PERSON>. He is a member
of the <ORGANIZATION>Punxsutawney Groundhog Club</ORGANIZATION>'s exclusive Inner Circle, which
each year decides in advance whether <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> will ``see'' his shadow.
   <PERSON>Snyder</PERSON> said <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> ``turned to Groundhog President <PERSON>Jim Means</PERSON> and
signaled to him in unmistakable groundhogese, `There is no shadow
today.'''
   The squirming, 10-pound woodchuck was pulled from his man-made
burrow atop Gobbler's Knob at sunrise, <TIME>7:27 a.m.</TIME> Means held the
groundhog up to his ear to hear the once-a-year prediction, then
lifted him toward <PERSON>Snyder</PERSON>.
   The approximately 1,500 people who had gathered under cloudy
skies and in light rain cheered as <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>'s forecast was announced.
   ``I've always wanted to come to this event ever since I was a
kid,'' said <PERSON>Peter Teicher</PERSON>, 49, of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. ``I'm really
excited. I couldn't sleep <TIME>last night</TIME>. It's a real thrill.''
   Other prognasticating groundhogs around the country followed
<PERSON>Phil</PERSON>'s lead and also failed to see their shadows.
   Legend has it that if the famous groundhog sees his shadow when
he emerges from his bungalow at sunrise on <DATE>Feb. 2</DATE>, there will be
six more weeks of winter. If he doesn't, spring is supposedly just
around the corner.
   ``You know and I know that <DATE>Feb. 2</DATE> is too darn early to expect
<DATE>spring</DATE> to come,'' said <PERSON>Tim Clark</PERSON>, executive editor of The Old
Farmer's Almanac.
   But the two-legged variety of weather forecasters are still
curious about what <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> has to say on Groundhog Day.
   ``I definitely do watch to see what he does. I didn't say I
believe it. I say I watch it,'' said <PERSON>Albert Peterlin</PERSON>, a hydrologist
for the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Harrisburg</LOCATION>.
   ``This has a little bit of history and fact,'' he said.
``Animals respond to temperature and environment as it occurs.''
   Before today, <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> had predicted an early <DATE>spring</DATE> only nine times
since <DATE>1887</DATE>, when German-born farmers initiated the yearly event in
this small western <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> town.
   The farmers borrowed from the legend of Candlemas, a Christian
holiday celebrating the first time the infant Jesus was taken to
the temple. An old Scottish couplet claims, ``If Candlemas be fair,
there'll be two winters in the year.''
   Groundhogs, part of the rodent family, usually hibernate by
<DATE>December</DATE> and stay underground until <DATE>April</DATE> or so, but sometimes
venture out early if the weather is mild.
   ``<PERSON>Phil</PERSON>'s never been wrong,'' boasted Means, 66.
   The 14 local businessmen who comprise the Inner Circle decide
well in advance what <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>'s forecast will be. Group members stages
several rehearsals before <DATE>Groundhog Day</DATE>, when they don top hats and
tails for the event.
   Phil's handler, <PERSON>Bud Dunkel</PERSON>, sported a fake fur hat resembling a
groundhog.
   Every other day of the year, <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> lives at his heated,
air-conditioned hutch at the local library with two other
groundhogs, <PERSON>Philomena</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Barney</ORGANIZATION>.
   As far as The Old Farmer's Almanac is concerned, <DATE>February</DATE> _ at
least around Punxsutawney _ will be extremely cold and snowy
followed by similar weather in early <DATE>March</DATE>.
<DATE>February</DATE>, but a colder than usual <DATE>March</DATE> and <DATE>April</DATE>.
   ``If I were to give you the scientific point of view, I think it
would be cold for the rest of this <DATE>winter</DATE>,'' said meteorologist
<PERSON>Victor Nouhan</PERSON>. ``Of course, that's worth a grain of salt.''
   Groundhog <PERSON>Octorara Orphie</PERSON> also saw no shadow in central
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Quarryville</LOCATION>. And neither did <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Concord
Charlie</LOCATION> as he was ``wandering around campus to see if any flowers
are up,'' said <PERSON>Tom Bone</PERSON>, public information director for <ORGANIZATION>Concord
College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>.
   Ditto for <ORGANIZATION>French Creek Freddie</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>French Creek Wildlife
Preserve</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Upshur County</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Lee</ORGANIZATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Yellow River Game Ranch</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lilburn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga</LOCATION>.
   The newest addition to the groundhog lineup, Little Hog, made
his debut at the <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> Zoo with fans joining in a rousing
chorus of ``You Are My Sunshine'' on kazoos. But there was no
sunshine and no shadow there.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-APIndustryNews 5thAdd   12-24 0962</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Industry News, 5th Add,1208</SECOND>
<HEAD>TV Station Surrenders Taped Interview to Police</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CASPER, Wyo. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Arkansas Court Says Records Open</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LITTLE ROCK, Ark. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Dukakis Signs Bill Easing Secrecy of Criminal Records</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAWRENCE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Almanac Accuses New York Magazine of Stealing its Cover</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Charges Refiled Against Former Newspaper Editor</HEAD>
<DATELINE>JOHNSTOWN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Report Finds 1990 Unhappy Year for Journalists</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A television interview with a man whose wife
has been missing since <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> was seized by police who got a search
warrant to obtain the tape from KTWO-TV, managing editor <PERSON>Charles
Brown</PERSON> said.
   The woman's husband had complained in the interview that police
were spending too much time treating him like a suspect when they
should be searching for his wife.
   On <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE>, police seized the taped interview, saying it
``constitutes evidence.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said the station decided not to challenge the warrant, in
part because the husband had approached KTWO on his own.
Additionally, station officials didn't think the interview
contained any comments that the man hadn't already made to police,
he said.
   ``Our position was we take this on a case-by-base basis,'' <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
said. ``I think it just ought to be on a case-by-case basis. I
don't think you should turn stuff over voluntarily, but responding
to a search warrant is different.''
   According to an affidavit that accompanied the warrant, police
wanted the tape because it contained statements made by the husband
that they believe show he concealed a stolen gun and military
equipment found when officers searched the couple's house after she
disappeared.
   <PERSON>Michael Krampner</PERSON>, a lawyer working with the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Press
Association</ORGANIZATION>, said KTWO already had broadcast a portion of the
interview and so there was little argument for confidentiality of
the tape.
   ``As the law now is in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, journalists are no different
from any other citizens,'' he said. ``If they receive a subpoena to
come to court and tell what they know, they're just like any other
citizen, they have the obligation to respond to that. If a court
issues a valid search warrant ... obviously they have to stand
aside and let them search for it just like any other citizens.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891024-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-24-89 1417EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     10-24 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0581</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TROY, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s bathroom has been found.
   Archaeologists made the discovery on Ferry Street, site of the
house of <DATE>19th century</DATE> meatpacker <PERSON>Sam Wilson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>Stephen
Dworsky</PERSON> said. During the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> stamped his crates
``<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>,'' leading to the military joke that the meat was provided
by ``Uncle Sam.''
   The archaeologists ``are down six feet, and you can literally
see what was the floor to the bathroom,'' <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
   A park is being built on the site by <LOCATION>Hannaford Bros.</LOCATION>, a
supermarket company based in <LOCATION>Scarborough</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. The company is
building a store next to the park.
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s house stood on the site from sometime in the <DATE>19th
century until 1971</DATE>, when <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state demolished it to make way
for a road that was never built, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said. Hannaford bought the
site in <DATE>1988</DATE> for <MONEY>$277,000</MONEY>.
   When the park is finished, the house's foundation and bathroom
floor will on view to visitors, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW KENSINGTON, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s bathroom has been found.
   Archaeologists made the discovery on Ferry Street, site of the
house of <DATE>19th century</DATE> meatpacker <PERSON>Sam Wilson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>Stephen
Dworsky</PERSON> said. During the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> stamped his crates
``<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>,'' leading to the military joke that the meat was provided
by ``Uncle Sam.''
   The archaeologists ``are down six feet, and you can literally
see what was the floor to the bathroom,'' <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
   A park is being built on the site by <LOCATION>Hannaford Bros.</LOCATION>, a
supermarket company based in <LOCATION>Scarborough</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. The company is
building a store next to the park.
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s house stood on the site from sometime in the <DATE>19th
century until 1971</DATE>, when <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state demolished it to make way
for a road that was never built, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said. Hannaford bought the
site in <DATE>1988</DATE> for <MONEY>$277,000</MONEY>.
   When the park is finished, the house's foundation and bathroom
floor will on view to visitors, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SOUTH NORWALK, Conn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s bathroom has been found.
   Archaeologists made the discovery on Ferry Street, site of the
house of <DATE>19th century</DATE> meatpacker <PERSON>Sam Wilson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> Manager <PERSON>Stephen
Dworsky</PERSON> said. During the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> stamped his crates
``<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>,'' leading to the military joke that the meat was provided
by ``Uncle Sam.''
   The archaeologists ``are down six feet, and you can literally
see what was the floor to the bathroom,'' <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
   A park is being built on the site by <LOCATION>Hannaford Bros.</LOCATION>, a
supermarket company based in <LOCATION>Scarborough</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. The company is
building a store next to the park.
   Uncle <PERSON>Sam</PERSON>'s house stood on the site from sometime in the <DATE>19th
century until 1971</DATE>, when <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state demolished it to make way
for a road that was never built, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said. Hannaford bought the
site in <DATE>1988</DATE> for <MONEY>$277,000</MONEY>.
   When the park is finished, the house's foundation and bathroom
floor will on view to visitors, <PERSON>Dworsky</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102190-0065 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 295631 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 21, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Book Review; Page 10; Book Review Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
394 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JUST RELEASED IN PAPERBACK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
FICTION 
</P>
<P>
ANY OLD IRON by <PERSON>Anthony Burgess</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Square: <MONEY>$5.95</MONEY>). Two families, one 
<ORGANIZATION>Welsh</ORGANIZATION>, the other Jewish, are tied throughout a century by an unrequited love. 
</P>
<P>
DRUGSTORE COWBOY by <PERSON>James Fogle</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY>). Celluloid version was voted 
best movie of <DATE>1989</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>National Society</ORGANIZATION> of Film Critics, but the novel went 
rejected and unpublished until Hollywood beckoned. 
</P>
<P>
MILE ZERO by <PERSON>Thomas Sanchez</PERSON> (Vintage: <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY>). Key West is the converging point 
for a mismatched band, for whom the tip of the continent also represents their 
last hope. 
</P>
<P>
LAIR OF THE FOX by <PERSON>Daniel Pollock</PERSON> (Harper: <MONEY>$4.95</MONEY>). Welsh activist and Hollywood 
actress offers herself in exchange for film crew taken hostage by Kurdish 
terrorists. 
</P>
<P>
HIGHER GROUND by <PERSON>Caryl Phillips</PERSON> (Penguin: <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY>). History's vicissitudes are 
backdrop for pivotal actions taken by the subjects in each of the three 
stories. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
NONFICTION 
</P>
<P>
FARM: A Year in the Life of an American Farmer by <PERSON>Richard Rhodes</PERSON> (Touchstone: 
<MONEY>$9.95</MONEY>). Pulitzer Prize-winning author pays homage to a <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> family which 
typifies the constant struggle and success in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s bread basket. 
</P>
<P>
AND A VOICE TO SING WITH: A Memoir by <PERSON>Joan Baez</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Signet</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$5.95</MONEY>). Baez exposes 
the sides of her personality that buy into her own P.R. and that could warrant 
the moniker "Saint." 
</P>
<P>
IN THE NAME OF GOD: The <ORGANIZATION>Khomeini Decade</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Robin Wright</PERSON> (Touchstone: <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY>). 
Examination of <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s knack for manufacturing external hostilities to deflect 
attention from debilitating domestic conditions. 
</P>
<P>
THE MYSTERIOUS LANDS: An Award-Winning Naturalist Explores the Four Great 
Deserts of the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Ann Haymond Zwinger</PERSON> (Plume: <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY>). Study of each 
area's land formations, climate and wildlife. 
</P>
<P>
YOU GOTTA HAVE WA by <PERSON>Robert Whiting</PERSON> (Vintage: <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY>). Juxtaposes baseball as 
played by the Japanese, who insist on unity and self-sacrifice, and the 
Americans, who exhibit individuality and greed. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
SELF-HELP / REFERENCE 
</P>
<P>
THE OLD FARMER'S <DATE>1991</DATE> Almanac by <PERSON>Robert B. Thomas</PERSON>, edited by <PERSON>Judson Hale</PERSON> 
(<MONEY>$2.50</MONEY>). New additions to the usual planting, recipes and folklore are features 
on tracking lost pets through the lost and found ads, predicting earthquakes 
and classic child-rearing advice. 
</P>
<P>
WEATHER WISDOM: Facts and Folklore of Weather Forecasting by <PERSON>Albert Lee</PERSON> 
(<ORGANIZATION>Congdon &amp; Weed</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$7.95</MONEY>). Observations of nature that allow short-term 
weather predictions. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880927-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-27-88 0749EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     09-27 0948</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0988</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WARSAW, Poland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GREENWOOD, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CONCORD, N.H. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's welfare system is headed for a
major overhaul with the conclusion of complex negotiations on a
five-year plan aimed at moving welfare recipients into jobs and
helping them collect more child support.
   The initiative agreed on <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
negotiators had been close to death all <DATE>summer</DATE> as negotiators
sought a balance between conservatives favoring mandatory work and
liberals concerned about increasing benefits to the needy and
motivating people to enter the mainstream workplace.
   The <MONEY>$3.34 billion</MONEY> welfare plan comes in above the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s own
<MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> measure but would cost less than half of the initial
<MONEY>$7.1 billion</MONEY> plan passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The cornerstone of the compromise is a Job Opportunities and
Basic Skills (JOBS) program offering welfare parents _ including
those with preschool children _ services such as job search help,
education and job training. Child care and transportation aid would
be available to participants.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101589-0014 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 120634 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 15, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Book Review; Page 12; Book Review Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
377 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JUST RELEASED IN PAPER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
FICTION 
</P>
<P>
PALM LATITUDES by <PERSON>Kate Braverman</PERSON> (Penguin: <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY>). The fateful existence of 
three Latina women in a <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> barrio. 
</P>
<P>
HEAVEN'S PRISONER by <PERSON>James Lee Burke</PERSON> (Pocket: <MONEY>$3.99</MONEY>). A plane crash in 
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> thrusts <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vet, ex-detective, ex-drinker <PERSON>Dave Robicheaux</PERSON> into an 
unwanted morass. 
</P>
<P>
GREEN CITY IN THE SUN by <ORGANIZATION>Barbara Wood</ORGANIZATION> (Fawcett Gold Medal: <MONEY>$4.95</MONEY>). Dr. <PERSON>Deborah 
Treverton</PERSON> is summoned back to <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> to settle the family coffee business -- 
and a medicine woman's curse. 
</P>
<P>
STORIES IN AN ALMOST CLASSICAL MODE by <PERSON>Harold Brodkey</PERSON> (Vintage: <MONEY>$12.95</MONEY>). 
Eighteen stories written over 30 years about the contradictions within 
families. 
</P>
<P>
WHEN I AM AN OLD WOMAN I SHALL WEAR PURPLE: An Anthology of Short Stories and 
Poetry, edited by <PERSON>Sandra Martz</PERSON> (Papier-Mache Press: <MONEY>$10</MONEY>). Writings about the 
later seasons in a woman's life by daughters, sons and significant others. 
</P>
<P>
NONFICTION 
</P>
<P>
CHILD STAR: An Autobiography by <ORGANIZATION>Shirley Temple Black</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$5.95</MONEY>). Once 
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s tiniest star, Black reflects on her gigantic impact. 
</P>
<P>
DEADLY MEDICINE by <PERSON>Kelly Moore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dan Reed</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>St. Martin</ORGANIZATION>'s: <MONEY>$4.95</MONEY>). Genene Jones 
seemed to be the perfect nurse, always there in an emergency -- until she was 
convicted of 30 cases of infanticide. 
</P>
<P>
BROTHERS: Black and Poor -- A True Story of Courage and Survival by <PERSON>Sylvester 
Monroe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peter Goldman</PERSON> (Ballantine: <MONEY>$4.95</MONEY>.) Newsweek correspondent returns to 
his childhood home, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Taylor Court</ORGANIZATION> projects, and discovers a microcosm 
of the plight of black men in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
THE CLUSTERING OF <LOCATION>AMERICA</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Michael J. Weiss</PERSON> (Perennial: <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY>). You are not 
where you live, but your zip code can reveal a lot about you. 
</P>
<P>
SELF-HELP / REFERENCETHE OLD FARMER'S <DATE>1989</DATE> ALMANAC by <PERSON>Robert B. Thomas</PERSON> (Old 
Farmer's Almanac: <MONEY>$2.95</MONEY>) Since <DATE>1792</DATE>, this little book has presented an eclectic 
mix of planting tables, weather forecasts, recipes and astrological secrets. 
</P>
<P>
LIFE AFTER THE CITY: A Harrow-smith Guide to Rural Living by <PERSON>Charles Long</PERSON> 
(<ORGANIZATION>Camden House</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$12.95</MONEY>). Ruminating chapters on earning a living, transition 
strategies, social adjustments, and maintaining friendships. 
</P>
<P>
VERY LA: The <ORGANIZATION>Native</ORGANIZATION>'s Guide to the Best of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> by <PERSON>David Hoffman</PERSON> 
(Chronicle: <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY>). If you decide to stay, here's how to make the experience a 
little more enjoyable. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900726-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-26-90 1148EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Quakes-NewMadrid Adv30   07-26 1008</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Quakes-New Madrid, Adv30,1038</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 30</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, July 30, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Earthquake Projections Bring Unwanted Publicity</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUE MAJOR HOLMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALBUQUERQUE, N.M. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Iben <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> holds dozens of patents
in several specialties, but it's his earthquake projections that
are stirring up notoriety he says he'd rather do without.
   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said at a conference in <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> there was a
high probability of an earthquake along the <ORGANIZATION>New Madrid Fault</ORGANIZATION> this
<DATE>Dec. 2</DATE>.
   He was deluged by calls.
   He insists he did not predict an earthquake.
   ``The public always wants everything in black and white,''
<PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said.
   ``No one can tell you there is going to be an earthquake on <DATE>Dec.
2</DATE>, no one can know that. ... Everybody knows when he drives a car
that he's taking a risk that it will malfunction or crash. Yet
people do drive cars. They're dealing in probabilities.''
   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON>, 72, a large man with a graying burr haircut, says the
public does not understand _ and the press does not know how to
communicate _ the idea of probability.
   ``The closest you can translate probability into English is
`maybe.' But unless you say `maybe not,' they take it as an
absolute,'' he said.
   Browning is chief scientist for <ORGANIZATION>Summa Medical Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, an
<LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> biotechnology research and development company. His
Summa resume says he holds 66 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and foreign patents in optics,
electronics, mechanics, chemistry, electro-optics, hydraulics and
educational toys.
   Summa credits him _ he won't discuss what he does for the
company _ with developing new technology for compressing
electronically transmitted human speech.
   Over the years, he's been a development physicist with <ORGANIZATION>American
Optical Co.</ORGANIZATION>, worked in optics for <ORGANIZATION>Bell Aircraft Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and was a
scientist for <ORGANIZATION>Sandia National Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>.
   But gradually his interest in climatology grew, and he now
publishes the <PERSON>Browning Newslettter</PERSON> on world climate. He said he's
been accepted commercially as a climatologist since <DATE>1974</DATE> when he
became a consultant for <ORGANIZATION>Paine Webber Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   His formal training was elsewhere: a bachelor's degree in math
and physics from <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Texas State University</ORGANIZATION>, and a master's
degree in bacteriology physiology and a doctorate in physiology,
genetics and bacteriology from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>.
   ``It turned out that in my observations of climate that all of
the soft tools with which I approached biology were applicable to
climate,'' he said. ``It's a subject that is comparable in
complexity to biology.''
   Business needs climate information because the weather
determines how much food will be produced and where, whether the
transportation industry can get over the roads, whether anything
can be built, he said.
   He provided forecasts for the <DATE>1989</DATE> edition of the <ORGANIZATION>Rocky Mountain
Almanac</ORGANIZATION> and ``did as well or better than the Old Farmers' Almanac
predictions,'' said <PERSON>Lee Olson</PERSON>, almanac editor.
   ``He did predict the usual monsoons that come up in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> in
late <DATE>August</DATE>, that the <LOCATION>Colorado Great Plains</LOCATION> would receive extra
moisture and store up adequate moisture for the <DATE>1990</DATE> year,'' <PERSON>Olson</PERSON>
said. ``He had the ski season only partly. He had it right for an
early start, but it got dry around <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION> as I recall and his
timing was a little off on that.''
   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said his climatological observations are based on high
tidal forces, produced by four causes: the proximity of the moon to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>; the proximity of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to the sun; the alignment of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, moon and sun during the full moon and new moon; and the more
perfect alignment of those bodies during eclipses. The vector sum
would be the total tidal force produced.
   Such forces can trigger earthquakes, he said, and on <DATE>Dec. 2</DATE>,
there will be the highest vector sum high tidal force in 60 years
from 30 to 60 degrees north latitude. That area includes the <ORGANIZATION>New
Madrid Fault</ORGANIZATION>, running roughly from Marked Tree, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, through <LOCATION>New
Madrid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>.
   Since last year, when <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> raised the possibility of a
<ORGANIZATION>December New Madrid</ORGANIZATION> quake, the <ORGANIZATION>Arkansas National Guard</ORGANIZATION> has
scheduled earthquake exercises for around that time, one <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>
school district is considering canceling classes and sales of
earthquake insurance have picked up.
   But <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said whether a given fault is actually triggered
would depend on the pressure built up along it. That information
should come from area seismologists, he said firmly.
   If no earthquake occurs in or around <DATE>December</DATE>, <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said
people will be more inclined to ignore the danger of the <ORGANIZATION>New Madrid
Fault</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``That's what I fear more than anything else,'' he said.
``People don't trust authorities anymore; they never did trust them
much. Why should they? What have authorities done for them except
tax them to death?''
   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON>'s earthquake projections are controversial among
seismologists.
   <PERSON>Klaus Jacob</PERSON>, senior research scientist at <ORGANIZATION>Lamont-Doherty
Geological Observatory of Columbia University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Palisades</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
said correlating earthquakes to tidal forces doesn't work.
   ``It's more likely that in the next 10 years or 20 years we'll
have something (quake activity), rather than on this particular
day,'' <PERSON>Jacob</PERSON> said. ``You see, earthquakes don't care about
predictions. And people shouldn't worry about predictions. They
should worry about earthquakes.''
   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> said he told a convention of chief executive officers
in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 10, 1989</DATE>, that there was a 50-50 chance of
an earthquake registering 7 on the Richter scale on or about <DATE>Oct.
16</DATE> because a high triggering force was expected that date and
geologists had determined there was a strain on the <LOCATION>San Andreas
Fault</LOCATION>.
   An earthquake registering 7.1 hit <DATE>Oct. 17</DATE>, killing 67 people.
   <PERSON>Jacob</PERSON> said: ``He was just lucky. That's the law of large
numbers.''
   <PERSON>Arch Johnston</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Earthquake Research</ORGANIZATION>
and Information at <ORGANIZATION>Memphis State University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>Browning</PERSON> ``is certainly not justified scientifically.''
   ``The tidal force that <PERSON>Dr. Browning</PERSON> bases his theory on has been
examined thoroughly by seismologists, and there's no evidence that
tidal forces can trigger earthquakes. ... Earthquakes depend on the
internal processes of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, not the external processes of the
sun and moon.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, July 30</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900202-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-90 1521EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-GroundhogDay     02-02 0615</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Groundhog Day,0632</SECOND>
<HEAD>Punxsutawney Phil Forecasts Early Spring</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PUNX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PUNXSUTAWNEY, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Punxsutawney <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>, the country's No. 1
four-footed forecaster, squinted hard but failed to see his shadow
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, thus predicting an early <DATE>spring</DATE> for only the 10th time in
more than a century.
   The squirming, 10-pound groundhog was pulled from his manmade
burrow atop Gobbler's Knob at <TIME>7:27 a.m</TIME>. The crowd of about 1,500
