<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010290-0080 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 156534 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1990, Tuesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 8; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
883 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TELEVISION / LARRY STEWART: BOWL GAME LINEUP: TOO MUCH OF A GOOD THING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LARRY STEWART 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Yes, there is such a thing as too much football. 
</P>
<P>
Seven bowl games on New Year's Day is about four too many. 
</P>
<P>
While the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> presents a nice, neat postseason tournament, what the colleges 
present is a mess. 
</P>
<P>
Try watching seven games within an 11-hour span. It's enough to make your head 
spin worse than any New Year's Day hangover. 
</P>
<P>
The first game <DATE>Monday</DATE> was the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl game. <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> had to cut away from 
its coverage of the Rose Parade, but at least it didn't run into the 
overlapping problems that <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> did. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl game ended, <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> wasted little time switching to the 
Fiesta Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
It was nice and clean, far better than <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s switch from the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> Citrus 
Bowl game to the Rose Bowl game. 
</P>
<P>
ABC took its time making the switch. ABC started off by showing a promotional 
spot for the upcoming Rose Bowl game. Thanks, but we knew it was coming. 
</P>
<P>
Then came a promo for <ORGANIZATION>ABC Sports</ORGANIZATION>, then a 'thank-you" promo to an airline that 
provides it with free travel. Then there were two promos for <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> shows, 
followed by a news brief. 
</P>
<P>
What next? Three consecutive commercials. 
</P>
<P>
Finally, an introduction for the Rose Bowl game, followed by a taped interview 
with <PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Then came more <ORGANIZATION>ABC Sports</ORGANIZATION> graphics and two more commercials. 
</P>
<P>
Oh, by the way, the Cotton Bowl on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> was still going on. Arkansas scored on a 
long pass play and after a failed two-point conversion attempt, the Razorbacks 
trailed <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>, 31-27, with 1:29 left. 
</P>
<P>
OK, we were finally going to see the Rose Bowl game kickoff, right? Nah. 
</P>
<P>
First there was a Big Ten promo, more <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> graphics and then finally a glimpse 
of the Rose Bowl, where the crowd was finishing singing the <ORGANIZATION>National Anthem</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Then came an introduction from announcer <PERSON>Keith Jackson</PERSON>, and another taped piece 
on <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>, this one showing a <DATE>1971</DATE> pep talk. 
</P>
<P>
Next was another commercial, then a Pacific 10 promo followed by one more 
commercial. 
</P>
<P>
The teams finally took the field, and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> and commentator <PERSON>Bob Griese</PERSON> then 
offered a little pregame analysis, as if there already hadn't been enough. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, in the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> game, <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> missed a field-goal attempt 
and trailed <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, 7-0. 
</P>
<P>
Finally, the Rose Bowl game kickoff came, 18 minutes after the end of the 
Citrus Bowl game. 
</P>
<P>
One play after the kickoff at the Rose Bowl game, <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> recovered a 
fumble to set up its first touchdown to tie the score on the way to a rout of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Cornhuskers</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At least we were down to only two games, the Cotton Bowl game having ended. 
</P>
<P>
It was quite a task trying to watch the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame, the Citrus and the Cotton 
Bowl games all at the same time. 
</P>
<P>
The Cotton Bowl game was the last of the three early games to start. 
</P>
<P>
The Citrus Bowl game began shortly after ABC went from <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>But it didn't take long to realize there was going to be a time squeeze 
later in the day. 
</P>
<P>
Certainly Citrus Bowl game announcer <PERSON>Gary Bender</PERSON> sensed it. As officials 
discussed a <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> penalty, <PERSON>Bender</PERSON> said: "Come on, fellas, we've got a 
lot of football to play today." 
</P>
<P>
If you happened to be watching the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl game you saw <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<PERSON>Zack Dumas</PERSON> level <ORGANIZATION>Auburn</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Stacy Danley</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Announcer <PERSON>Don Criqui</PERSON> first said: "That's got to be the hardest hit of the 
'89-90 bowl season." 
</P>
<P>
Then, after viewing a replay, <PERSON>Criqui</PERSON> said: "It's the hardest hit I've seen in 
football in years." 
</P>
<P>
Indeed it was. 
</P>
<P>
A little later in the game, <PERSON>Criqui</PERSON>, talking about <ORGANIZATION>Auburn</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Shayne Wasden</PERSON>'s punt 
returns of 30 and 34 yards, said they broke the Orange Bowl game record. 
</P>
<P>
Maybe you can't blame <PERSON>Criqui</PERSON> for being confused. He worked the last eight 
Orange Bowl games. 
</P>
<P>
Speaking of flubs, <PERSON>O.J. Simpson</PERSON>, during halftime of the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl game, 
referred to <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>George Gipp</PERSON> as <PERSON>George Kemp</PERSON>, or something like that. 
However, <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> did catch the mistake and corrected himself. 
</P>
<P>
In referring to <PERSON>Gipp</PERSON>'s death, comparing it to the death of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> quarterback 
<PERSON>Sal Aunese</PERSON>, <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> said it occurred a few years ago. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> colleague <PERSON>Bob Costas</PERSON>, fearing <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON>'s attempt at sarcasm was probably 
lost on most viewers, added: "It was more than a few years ago. It was so long 
ago that a young <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> could play <PERSON>Gipp</PERSON> (in the <DATE>1940</DATE> movie, 'The <ORGANIZATION>Knute 
Rockne All-American</ORGANIZATION>')." 
</P>
<P>
During halftime of the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl game, <PERSON>Gayle Gardner</PERSON> -- yes, she still 
works for <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> -- did a nice taped interview with <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Dennis Erickson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON>, during halftime of the Fiesta Bowl game, offered an excellent 
feature on the once-troubled <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> football program and the death of <PERSON>Aunese</PERSON> 
this past <DATE>September</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
CBS, meanwhile, deserves kudos for a halftime segment it showed during the 
Cotton Bowl. It chronicled the highlights of college football during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, 
including <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1982</DATE> kickoff return against <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> broke a story that <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> defensive coordinator <PERSON>Barry Alvarez</PERSON> would 
become coach at <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The network had <PERSON>Ralph Wiley</PERSON> interview <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> later in the day, but because of 
technical problems, had to cut away from it earlier than planned. 
</P>
<P>
On <TIME>this long day and night</TIME> of football, the overall coverage and the announcing 
was fine. 
</P>
<P>
But something needs to be done about the logjam. The way things are now, it's 
impossible to see everything. 
</P>
<P>
Just trying is a real job -- and no fun. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, USC linebacker Michael Williams grabs Michigan fullback Jarrod Bunch. 
Bunch rushed six times for 11 yards and caught a pass for 11 yards. STEVE DYKES 
/ Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA123190-0130 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 329691 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 31, 1990, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part P; Page 9; Column 3; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
586 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MELVIN DURSLAG: A CRAZY EIGHT IS TOO MUCH FOR ONE TV SCREEN; 
</P>
<P>
COLLEGE FOOTBALL: THE OVERABUNDANCE OF BOWL GAMES ON NEW YEAR'S DAY MAKES IT 
IMPOSSIBLE TO WATCH THEM ALL. WHO CAME UP WITH THIS SYSTEM? 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MELVIN DURSLAG 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Inspecting the bowl football program on New Year's Day, you have a vision of 
herring in a net, flopping over one another. 
</P>
<P>
The current lineup embraces eight games, running from 8:30 in the <TIME>morning</TIME> (PST) 
until roughly <TIME>8:30 at night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
You are surprised the genii of college football have stopped at eight games. 
Between <TIME>midnight</TIME> and <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME>, they could book two more. 
</P>
<P>
And, of course, they could squeeze in another in prime time. 
</P>
<P>
Right now, they have arranged so many games <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> that an overlap occurs. For 
instance, the Citrus Bowl, the Cotton Bowl and the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl poach on 
each other's telecast. 
</P>
<P>
And all three arrive on the air at some time during the second half of the 
Gator Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
The Orange Bowl and the Sugar Bowl overlap, same as the Fiesta Bowl and the 
Rose Bowl. And all are coming off a previous day of activity featuring the <PERSON>John 
Hancock</PERSON> Bowl and the <LOCATION>Domino</LOCATION>'s Pizza Copper Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
A confused viewer of those two could leave his set believing he will be insured 
in 30 minutes, or the policy is free. 
</P>
<P>
You are a tolerant individual. You are patient and understanding, the milk of 
human kindness flowing by the liter through every vein. 
</P>
<P>
You are not aiming to rock the vessel. All you are trying to comprehend is 
whether college football has gone foaming-at-the-mouth mad. 
</P>
<P>
One isn't supposed to be dealing here with dummies. This is our highest 
intellectual order, the teachers of our young. 
</P>
<P>
And they allow a circumstance on New Year's Day calling for eight televised 
bowl games? 
</P>
<P>
If smart guys permit this excess, what would imbeciles do? 
</P>
<P>
So what has all this done to that spectacle billing itself as "the Granddaddy 
of 'Em All," the Rose Bowl? 
</P>
<P>
What it has done is reduce the Rose Bowl to selling nothing but age -- a game 
beginning in <DATE>1902</DATE> and continuing to the present, with intermittent stoppages. 
</P>
<P>
After the <DATE>1902</DATE> game, for instance, it stopped until <DATE>1916</DATE>, substituting that 
well-known ghetto sport, polo. It also tried chariot races. 
</P>
<P>
And then the Rose Bowl ground to a halt in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE> when the game was 
shifted to <LOCATION>Durham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C</LOCATION>. It was a war year, and <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> feared an air attack by 
the Japanese. 
</P>
<P>
What an insult to the <ORGANIZATION>Luftwaffe</ORGANIZATION> to OK the game on the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Although it was once the premier postseason game, the Rose Bowl has suffered 
serious slippage, not at the box office, but in the television ratings and in 
general prestige. 
</P>
<P>
And the ultimate contempt has been the willingness of other bowls to go 
head-and-head with it on TV. 
</P>
<P>
Offering <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> this time, the Rose Bowl needn't necessarily 
apologize. <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, on a good day, can knock off any amateur team in the 
hemisphere. 
</P>
<P>
And <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> is better than average. 
</P>
<P>
But it has become increasingly rare that connoisseurs about the land judge the 
Rose Bowl as an event of major national impact. It is more a parochial little 
war between the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 and the <PERSON>Big Ten</PERSON>, pretty much like <ORGANIZATION>Eton</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Harrow</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Since the Rose Bowl still dredges more money from television than any other 
bowl game -- that could be a fleeting condition -- it behooves the promoters 
each year to capture participants of muscle, teams with substantial followings. 
</P>
<P>
Those teams preferred are <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> are rated fair. What <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> lives in fear of is, say, <ORGANIZATION>Oregon 
State</ORGANIZATION> vs. <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Bucking seven other games New Year's Day, with such a matchup the network 
starts looking for a bridge. 
</P>
<P>
One is available in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, making the Rose Bowl a game of convenience, if 
nothing else. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010290-0075 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 156523 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1990, Tuesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
326 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
USC BEATS BO IN HIS LAST ROSE BOWL, 17-10 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GARR KLUENDER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Ricky Ervins</PERSON> scored on a 14-yard run with 1:10 to play, lifting 12th-ranked <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> 
to a 17-10 victory over third-ranked <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> in the Rose Bowl game at <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> 
on <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON>, in his last game as <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s coach, closed his career with a 
2-8 record in Rose Bowl games. 
</P>
<P>
The Trojans finished the season 9-2-1; <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> is 10-2. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s other bowl games: 
</P>
<P>
 -- <PERSON>Peter Tom Willis</PERSON> threw for 422 yards and five touchdowns, both Fiesta Bowl 
records, as fifth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> routed No. 6 <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> 41-17 <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The victory capped a 10-2 season for <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION>, which won its final 10 
games. <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> also finished at 10-2. 
</P>
<P>
It was the worst overall loss for <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> since <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> beat the Cornhuskers 
38-7 in <DATE>1977</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- <PERSON>Chuck Webb</PERSON> ran for 250 yards, the second-best rushing performance in Cotton 
Bowl history, as eighth-ranked <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> beat 10th-ranked <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, 31-27, at 
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Webb</PERSON>, a freshman, carried 26 times and scored twice, including a 78-yard run. 
Rice's <PERSON>Dicky Maegle</PERSON> set the Cotton Bowl record of 265 yards against <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1954</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Tennessee finished with an 11-1 record; <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> is 10-2. 
</P>
<P>
 -- <PERSON>Reggie Slack</PERSON> completed his last 12 passes before halftime and led 
ninth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Auburn</ORGANIZATION> to a 31-14 victory over 21st-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> 
of Fame Bowl at <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
After suffering two interceptions, Slack threw touchdown passes of 11 and 4 
yards to <PERSON>Greg Taylor</PERSON> that gave the Tigers the lead for good. <PERSON>Greg Frey</PERSON>, 
quarterback for <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>, was sacked four times. Auburn finished at 10-2, 
<ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> at 8-4. 
</P>
<P>
 -- In the Citrus Bowl at <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jeff George</PERSON> passed for a season-high 
321 yards and three touchdowns as 11th-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> defeated 15th-ranked 
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, 31-21. 
</P>
<P>
It was the first bowl game victory for the Illini (11-2) since their 17-7 win 
over <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1964</DATE> Rose Bowl. The Cavaliers finished at 10-3. 
</P>
<P>
The final rankings in the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll will be released today. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, USC quarterback Todd Marinovich eludes Michigan rush in Rose Bowl. GARY 
FRIEDMAN / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010389-0020 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 742 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 3, 1989, Tuesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 5; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
584 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
USC DEFEATED; IRISH, UCLA WIN IN BOWLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Notre Dame staked a claim to its 14th national football championship, and the 
roses went to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> as the glut of college bowls wound up with an 
extravaganza of seven games <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The top-ranked Fighting Irish completed the first 12-0 season in their storied 
football history with a 34-21 victory over third-ranked, previously undefeated 
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and the No. 11-ranked 
Woverines rallied in the second half to beat fifth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, 22-14, in the 
75th Rose Bowl at <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Ninth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> upheld the honor of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference, winning a 
record seventh straight bowl game by downing eighth-ranked <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, 17-3, in 
the Cotton Bowl at <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Clemson Beats Oklahoma 
</P>
<P>
In other games, No. 13 Clemson beat No. 10 <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, 13-6, in the Citrus Bowl 
at <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and No. 17 Syracuse dominated No. 16 <ORGANIZATION>Louisiana State</ORGANIZATION>, 23-10, 
in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl at <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In night games, No. 2 <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> played No. 6 <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> in the Orange Bowl at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 
and No. 4 <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> faced No. 7 Auburn in the Sugar Bowl at <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> will likely receive its first national title since <DATE>1977 today</DATE> when 
the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>' final poll of the media is released. Coach <PERSON>Lou Holtz</PERSON> will 
join Irish coaches <PERSON>Frank Leahy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ara Parseghian</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dan Devine</PERSON> in winning 
national titles in their third seasons at <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Leahy won in <DATE>1943</DATE>, <DATE>1946</DATE>, <DATE>1947</DATE> and <DATE>1949</DATE>, Parseghian in <DATE>1966</DATE> and <DATE>1973</DATE>, and <PERSON>Devine</PERSON> 
in <DATE>1977</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Knute Rockne</ORGANIZATION> won 6 other national titles before the AP poll began in 
<DATE>1936</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Junior quarterback <PERSON>Tony Rice</PERSON> led the way for <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>, passing for 2 
touchdowns and a career-high 213 yards. Rice also rushed for 75 yards. 
</P>
<P>
Notre Dame built a 23-6 half-time lead, and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> (11-1) had to settle 
for the first 11-victory season in its 96-year football history. 
</P>
<P>
USC (10-2) had a 14-3 half-time lead but was overpowered by <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (9-2-1) in 
the <DATE>second half</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The victory gave <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON> only his second victory in nine 
trips to the Rose Bowl and marked the first time the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> had won 
consecutive Rose Bowls since the 1964-65 seasons. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> defeated <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>20-17</DATE>, last year. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> fullback <PERSON>Leroy Hoard</PERSON> rushed for 142 yards and scored two 
<DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> touchdowns. Hoard put the <LOCATION>Wolverines</LOCATION> ahead, 15-14, with a 1-yard 
touchdown run early in the final period, then locked up the victory with 
another 1-yard scoring run with 1:52 left. He set up the last touchdown with a 
61-yard gain to the Trojan 9. 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>Rodney Peete</PERSON>, frustrated most of the game by the <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> defense, 
scored for <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> on runs of 1 and 4 yards. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA (10-2) used the efficiency of quarterback <PERSON>Troy Aikman</PERSON> and an overpowering 
defense to become the first school ever to win bowl games in 7 consecutive 
seasons -- all with <PERSON>Terry Donahue</PERSON> as coach -- before a partisan <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> crowd 
of 74,304. 
</P>
<P>
The Bruins' victory streak also includes 3 Rose Bowls, a Fiesta Bowl, an Aloha 
Bowl and a Freedom Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Aikman completed 19 of 27 passes for 172 yards and a touchdown, and converted 
12 of 20 third-down situations into first downs. Freshman <PERSON>Shawn Wills</PERSON> gained 
121 yards in 18 carries. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Cowboys</ORGANIZATION> are expected to make <PERSON>Aikman</PERSON> their first pick of the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Football League</ORGANIZATION> draft. Cowboy personnel director <PERSON>Gil Brandt</PERSON> congratulated 
<PERSON>Aikman</PERSON> under the goal posts after the game. 
</P>
<P>
However, it was the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> defense that carried the day, holding <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> (10-2) 
to 42 yards of offense and 4 first downs. 
</P>
<P>
Complete reports in Sports. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Michigan quarterback Demetrius Brown eludes USC linebacker Scott Ross in 
early action. JOE KENNEDY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112589-0099 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 139723 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 25, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
737 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MELVIN DURSLAG: GRANDDAD GETTING BOWLED OVER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MELVIN DURSLAG 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The way life measures up in matters postseason, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> or 
<ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> will be matched against <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> in the Rose Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
ABC, which produces an inordinate amount of cash to televise the game, exhales 
deeply. 
</P>
<P>
"Thank you, heaven," it says. "But for this blessing, it could have been 
<LOCATION>Washington State</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
When it comes to cutthroat New Year's Day football, now featuring seven games, 
the network doing the <ORGANIZATION>Rose Bowl</ORGANIZATION> is made to perspire, no longer sitting atop an 
automatic hit. 
</P>
<P>
Faded elegance, the Rose Bowl rarely offers the prime game, meaning those who 
promote it, or televise it, must hope, at least, for principals with wide 
followings. 
</P>
<P>
On the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, that would be <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>. In the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION>, it would be 
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But competition in the leagues has so deteriorated that the Rose Bowl, locked 
in with the two, is beginning to lose the carbonation that has given fizz to 
its match for so long. 
</P>
<P>
Normally today, you write off half the teams, or more, in each conference at 
the start of the season. And, by the end, you are looking pretty much at the 
same colors, mostly belonging to <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> on one side and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ohio 
State</ORGANIZATION> on the other. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> will have graced the scene three years in a row. And an audit 
discloses that over the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>, the visiting force has been <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> or 
<ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> 16 times. 
</P>
<P>
The monotony suggests a period in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> in which all the bit shooters drove 
Cadillacs. You never asked a man what kind of car he bought. You merely 
inquired, "What color?" 
</P>
<P>
The Rose Bowl bills itself as the Granddaddy of Them All, a tribute more to its 
age than its impact. It sells out, almost unfailingly, and its financial health 
is good. 
</P>
<P>
But all too often on the New Year's card, it is the tap dancer supplementing 
the headline act. In vaudeville, <PERSON>Fink</PERSON>'s Mules warmed up audiences as the Rose 
Bowl does today. 
</P>
<P>
Little old ladies in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> don't like it. Over gin the other day, one was 
heard to grumble: "We are being upstaged by something called the <ORGANIZATION>Federal 
Express Orange Bowl</ORGANIZATION>. What the hell is the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> Orange Bowl?" 
</P>
<P>
"Are you sure it isn't pony express?" another asked. 
</P>
<P>
"Pony express may be sponsoring a game in <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Operating the only major postseason game that is totally committed to two 
conferences, the Rose Bowl shuts itself off from teams that may be interesting 
that particular season. 
</P>
<P>
"But we don't have to enter the dogfight," the Rose Bowl explains. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, it doesn't. And, sidestepping the dogfight, it has wound up in the 
water closet, with TV ratings that have slipped and with such contempt 
developed by competitors for the Granddaddy of Them All that they have dared 
take it on, head to head, on the air. 
</P>
<P>
In the past, who would have been so audacious, so consummately brassy as to 
overlap the Rose Bowl? Would some hillbilly try to win a singing contest from 
<LOCATION>Pavarotti</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
"Look," you say gingerly to <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>. "Maybe the time has come to forget the 
lock-in and start thinking about the dogfight. Rose Bowl money can lick a lot 
of dogs." 
</P>
<P>
"We cherish our relationship with the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> and Pacific 10," <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> lashes 
back. "It has stood since <DATE>1947</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
"A newspaper we remember stood since <DATE>1903</DATE>," <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> is reminded. "It isn't 
with us anymore." 
</P>
<P>
"But our two conferences have stature and they have character," <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> 
responds. "They embody everything that is good in institutions of learning." 
</P>
<P>
"Are you selling learning or football?" you reply. "This is show business. And 
the same teams coming in every year are getting to be a yawn. Do you know what 
killed the six-day bike race? Its act never changed. And the same thing one day 
will kill Old Faithful at Yellowstone." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> used to be more inventive. Offering its first bowl game in <DATE>1902</DATE>, it 
shut it down as bad theater when <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> creamed <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, 49-0. 
</P>
<P>
Do you know what <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> came up with the next year? A polo match. That seemed 
a good idea, inasmuch as no team, up to that point, had lost 49-0 in polo. 
</P>
<P>
Pasadena then tried an ostrich race, followed by a race between a camel and an 
elephant. It also came on with a tug of war, which, today, might be called the 
<PERSON>John Hancock</PERSON> Tug of War. And, by <DATE>1916</DATE>, it was ready again for football. 
</P>
<P>
In postseason play, the Rose Bowl is sitting in on a high-stakes poker game. To 
succeed, folks there must produce more than a fund of happy recollections on 
how the pot used to be theirs. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ROSE BOWL (FOOTBALL GAME); FOOTBALL TEAMS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010389-0021 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 743 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 3, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 5; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
611 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
USC DEFEATED; IRISH, UCLA WIN IN BOWLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TOM LaMARRE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Notre Dame staked a claim to its 14th national football championship, and the 
roses went to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> as the glut of college bowls wound up with an 
extravaganza of seven games <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The top-ranked Fighting Irish completed the first 12-0 season in their storied 
football history with a 34-21 victory over third-ranked, previously undefeated 
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and the 11th-ranked 
Wolverines rallied in the second half to beat fifth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, 22-14, in the 
75th Rose Bowl at <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Ninth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> upheld the honor of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference, winning a 
record seventh straight bowl game by downing eighth-ranked <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, 17-3, in 
the Cotton Bowl at <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> Win 
</P>
<P>
In night games, No. 2 <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, which lost only to <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>, routed No. 6 
<LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, 23-3, in the Orange Bowl at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, and No. 4 <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> held off 
No. 7 <LOCATION>Auburn</LOCATION>, 13-7, in the Sugar Bowl at <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In other games, No. 13 Clemson beat No. 10 <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, 13-6, in the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> 
Citrus Bowl at <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and No. 17 Syracuse dominated No. 16 <ORGANIZATION>Louisiana 
State</ORGANIZATION>, 23-10, in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl at <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> will likely receive its first national title since <DATE>1977 today</DATE> when 
the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>' final poll of the media is released. Coach <PERSON>Lou Holtz</PERSON> will 
join Irish coaches <PERSON>Frank Leahy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ara Parseghian</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dan Devine</PERSON> in winning 
national titles in their third seasons at <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Leahy won in <DATE>1943</DATE>, <DATE>1946</DATE>, <DATE>1947</DATE> and <DATE>1949</DATE>, Parseghian in <DATE>1966</DATE> and <DATE>1973</DATE>, and <PERSON>Devine</PERSON> 
in <DATE>1977</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Knute Rockne</ORGANIZATION> won six other national titles before the AP poll began in 
<DATE>1936</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Junior quarterback <PERSON>Tony Rice</PERSON> led the way for <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>, passing for two 
touchdowns and a career-high 213 yards. Rice also rushed for 75 yards. 
</P>
<P>
Notre Dame built a 23-6 half-time lead, and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> (11-1) had to settle 
for the first 11-victory season in its 96-year football history. 
</P>
<P>
USC (10-2) had a 14-3 half-time lead but was overpowered by <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (9-2-1) in 
the <DATE>second half</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Second Victory in Nine Trips 
</P>
<P>
The victory gave <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON> only his second victory in nine 
trips to the Rose Bowl and marked the first time the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> had won 
consecutive Rose Bowls since the 1964-65 seasons. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> defeated <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>20-17</DATE>, last year. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> fullback <PERSON>Leroy Hoard</PERSON> rushed for 142 yards and scored two 
<DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> touchdowns. Hoard put the <LOCATION>Wolverines</LOCATION> ahead, 15-14, with a 1-yard 
touchdown run early in the final period, then locked up the victory with 
another 1-yard scoring run with 1:52 left. He set up the last touchdown with a 
61-yard gain to the Trojan 9. 
</P>
<P>
Quarterback <PERSON>Rodney Peete</PERSON>, frustrated most of the game by the <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> defense, 
scored for <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> on runs of 1 and 4 yards. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA (10-2) used the efficiency of quarterback <PERSON>Troy Aikman</PERSON> and an overpowering 
defense to become the first school ever to win bowl games in seven consecutive 
seasons -- all with <PERSON>Terry Donahue</PERSON> as coach -- before a partisan <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> crowd 
of 74,304. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Several Bowls Involved 
</P>
<P>
The Bruins' victory streak also includes three Rose Bowls, a Fiesta Bowl, an 
Aloha Bowl and a Freedom Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Aikman completed 19 of 27 passes for 172 yards and a touchdown, and converted 
12 of 20 third-down situations into first downs. Freshman <PERSON>Shawn Wills</PERSON> gained 
121 yards in 18 carries against the Razorbacks (10-2). 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Dallas Cowboys</ORGANIZATION> are expected to make <PERSON>Aikman</PERSON> the first player chosen in the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Football League</ORGANIZATION> draft. Cowboy personnel director <PERSON>Gil Brandt</PERSON> 
congratulated <PERSON>Aikman</PERSON> under the goal posts after the game. 
</P>
<P>
However, it was the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> defense that carried the day, holding <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> to 42 
yards of offense and four first downs. 
</P>
<P>
Complete reports in Sports. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Michigan's Leroy Hoard blows past USC's Michael Williams en route 
to a third-quarter first down. VINCE COMPAGNONE / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COLLEGE ATHLETICS; FOOTBALL GAMES; FOOTBALL CHAMPIONSHIPS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011389-0096 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 4961 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 13, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 3; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
195 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FIESTA BOWL DEFEATS ROSE BOWL IN TV RATINGS RACE, 17.0 TO 10.8 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AP 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
NBC's telecast of the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> football game between national champion <ORGANIZATION>Notre 
Dame</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 2</DATE> drew a 17.0 national rating, the highest of 
any bowl game this year, the network said. 
</P>
<P>
Playing opposite the Fiesta Bowl, <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s Rose Bowl had a 10.8 rating, lowest in 
the television history of the game, <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
The rating means an average of <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> of all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> TV households were tuned into 
the Fiesta Bowl, or about 15.4 million households. 
</P>
<P>
"The Fiesta Bowl, of course, was for the national championship, and it was the 
highest-rated of the year, facing what traditionally is the highest-rated bowl 
game," <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> research specialist <PERSON>Gray Seamans</PERSON> said. "And we beat it handily -- by 
<PERCENT>57%</PERCENT>." 
</P>
<P>
CBS' Cotton Bowl, in which <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> defeated <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, drew a 9.8 rating, lowest in 
its history, and the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> had an 8.1. The Citrus Bowl, on 
<ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>, had a 7.2 rating. 
</P>
<P>
National ratings were announced earlier for <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s Orange Bowl, 12.8, and <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s 
Sugar Bowl, 8.1, which were shown against one another in prime time. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Seamans</PERSON> said the highest-rated bowl game ever was the Orange Bowl's national 
championship showdown 2 years ago, which had a 25.1 rating. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FIESTA BOWL (FOOTBALL GAME); ROSE BOWL (FOOTBALL GAME); TELEVISION RATINGS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010289-0018 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 472 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 12; Column 4; Television Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
255 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
A BIG DAY FOR BOWL GAMES AND PARADES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVE LINAN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Today's an especially big day for football bowl games, but what about those who 
love a parade? 
</P>
<P>
At <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME>, the TV networks and local stations both will serve up live coverage 
of the 100th "Tournament of Roses Parade" from <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>. The grand marshal is 
<PERSON>Shirley Temple Black</PERSON>, who also presided over the event 50 years ago in <DATE>1939</DATE> 
when she was a child star. 
</P>
<P>
The parade will be shown on CBS (where the hosts will be <PERSON>Patrick Duffy</PERSON> and Joan 
Van Ark); NBC (<PERSON>Alex Trebek</PERSON> and Phylicia Rashad); ABC (<PERSON>Jim McKay</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joan 
Lunden</PERSON>); KTLA Channel 5 (<PERSON>Bob Eubanks</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephanie Edwards</PERSON>); KTTV Channel 11 (a 
3-D telecast with <PERSON>Bill Welsh</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Hart</PERSON>) and KMEX Channel 34 (<PERSON>Jessi Losada</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Maria Elena Salinas</PERSON>). 
</P>
<P>
There are also chances to catch the parade later in the day on repeat 
telecasts: at <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> (5)(11), at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> (11) and at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> (5). 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> also boasts a New Year's Parade, and <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> will be there to cover the 32nd 
annual "Cotton Bowl Parade" from <TIME>2-3 p.m.</TIME> (2)(8). 
</P>
<P>
Moving to the football field, here's a listing of the day's bowl games: 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame: LSU (8-3) vs. Syracuse (9-2), 10 a.m. (4)(36)(39). 
</P>
<P>
Cotton: <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> (9-2) vs. <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> (10-1), 10:30 a.m. (2)(8). 
</P>
<P>
Citrus: Clemson (9-2) vs. <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> (9-2), <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> (7)(3)(10)(42). 
</P>
<P>
Fiesta: <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> (11-0) vs. <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> (11-0), <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> (4)(36)(39). 
</P>
<P>
Rose: USC (10-1) vs. <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (8-2-1), <TIME>1:45 p.m.</TIME> (7)(3)(10)(42). 
</P>
<P>
Orange: <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> (10-1) vs. <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> (11-1), <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> (4)(36)(39). 
</P>
<P>
Sugar: Auburn (10-1) vs. <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> (10-1), <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME> (7)(3)(10)(42). STEVE 
LINAN 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The University of Michigan Band will march in the Rose Parade, then head 
for the Rose Bowl for the Michigan-USC football game. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010290-0054 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 156472 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 7; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1157 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TELEVISION: A HARD DAY'S NIGHT OF FOOTBALL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LARRY STEWART 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Yes, there can be too much football. 
</P>
<P>
There was some good football on New Year's Day -- particularly for <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Notre 
Dame</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> fans -- but seven games in one day is about four too many. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> presents a nice, neat postseason tournament, culminating with Super 
Bowl <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. What the colleges present is a mess. 
</P>
<P>
Watching seven games within an 11-hour span is enough to make your head spin 
more than a New Year's Day hangover. 
</P>
<P>
The first game <DATE>Monday</DATE> was the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame Bowl</ORGANIZATION>, which began shortly after <TIME>10 
a.m</TIME>. The last one, the Sugar Bowl, didn't end until <TIME>9:15 p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
ABC made the most of its late sign-off and asked viewers to call in their votes 
for the No. 1 team in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
At last count, <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> had a pretty healthy lead over <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>26%</PERCENT>, 
after 50,000 calls. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> each televised three games and <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> one. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> got a head start on <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> with the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame Bowl</ORGANIZATION> starting a half-hour 
earlier than the Citrus Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> had to cut away from its coverage of the Rose Parade a little early, but at 
least it didn't run into the overlapping problems later in the day that <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> 
did. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl ended at <TIME>1:27 p.m.</TIME> and the network wasted little time 
switching to the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
It was a far better switch than <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s from the <LOCATION>Citrus Bowl</LOCATION> to the Rose Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
ABC planned to be on the air from <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> at <TIME>1:45 p.m.</TIME>, and the kickoff was 
scheduled for shortly after 2. 
</P>
<P>
But, as things turned out, the kickoff was delayed until 2:21. 
</P>
<P>
The main reason for the delay was that the Citrus Bowl didn't end until 2:03. 
Then, making matters worse, <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> took its time making the switch, to say the 
least. 
</P>
<P>
After the <LOCATION>Citrus Bowl</LOCATION> was over, <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> showed a promotional spot for the upcoming 
Rose Bowl. Thanks, but we knew it was coming. 
</P>
<P>
Then came a promo for <ORGANIZATION>ABC Sports</ORGANIZATION>, then a "thank you" promotional spot to an 
airline that provides free air travel. 
</P>
<P>
There were two promos for <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> shows, followed by a news brief. 
</P>
<P>
It was almost 2:10. 
</P>
<P>
What next? Three consecutive commercials and a Channel 7 promo for <PERSON>Todd 
Donoho</PERSON>'s "New Year's Live" postgame show. 
</P>
<P>
Actually, <PERSON>Donoho</PERSON>'s show wasn't bad. He played it pretty straight, and his 
look-a-likes segment was interesting. <PERSON>John Robinson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Duke Snider</PERSON> was one of 
his best. 
</P>
<P>
Anyway, <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> was still a long way from the Rose Bowl kickoff. 
</P>
<P>
After some <ORGANIZATION>ABC Sports</ORGANIZATION> graphics, there was a Big Ten promo, then more graphics 
and finally a glimpse of the <LOCATION>Rose Bowl</LOCATION>, where the crowd was completing the 
national anthem. 
</P>
<P>
Then came an intro from announcer <PERSON>Keith Jackson</PERSON> and another taped piece on 
<PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>, this one showing a <DATE>1971</DATE> pep talk. 
</P>
<P>
Next was another commercial, then a Pacific 10 promo followed by one more 
commercial. 
</P>
<P>
At 2:16, the teams took the field, and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> and commentator <PERSON>Bob Griese</PERSON> 
offered a little pregame analysis. 
</P>
<P>
The Rose Bowl kickoff came 18 minutes after the end of the Citrus Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
ABC had met with Rose Bowl officials at about <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> and asked for a later 
kickoff, so the teams knew what was coming. 
</P>
<P>
But it was unnerving to viewers at home and fans at the game, making them wait 
and wait. 
</P>
<P>
The 18-minute break wouldn't have been so bad had <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> not crammed in all those 
commercials and promos. 
</P>
<P>
There were 20 minutes between the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> and Orange Bowl on <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>, but that 
network used the time mostly for analysis and features. 
</P>
<P>
It used the time for only a few commercials and promos. 
</P>
<P>
ABC producer <PERSON>Bob Goodrich</PERSON>, who was in charge of the Rose Bowl coverage, had 
plenty of material planned for his pregame show, but someone higher up at <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> 
decided against using it. 
</P>
<P>
Actually, <PERSON>Goodrich</PERSON>, director <PERSON>Larry Kamm</PERSON>, announcers <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Griese</PERSON> and the 
rest of the <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> crew put out an excellent Rose Bowl telecast -- once it got 
going. 
</P>
<P>
ABC got some definitive shots the holding call on <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s fake punt in the 
<DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, but the most conclusive shot wasn't shown until halftime of the 
Sugar Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
It showed that <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Bobby Abrams</PERSON> held, but it was far away from the play 
and the flag was late. 
</P>
<P>
Usually sideline reporters offer little, but <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>O.J. Simpson</PERSON> came up with 
some good information during the Orange Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Simpson, working the <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> sideline while <PERSON>Ralph Wiley</PERSON> handled the <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION> 
bench, explained why the entire teams of both schools went on the field before 
the kickoff. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> said when the <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> players saw the whole <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> team coming 
out, they did the same thing. 
</P>
<P>
Simpson also explained what went wrong on <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>'s fake field goal try early 
in the game, pointing out that the key receiver forgot to run a pattern. 
</P>
<P>
In the Orange Bowl booth, <PERSON>Dick Enberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bill Walsh</PERSON> had one of their best 
games. It was refreshing to hear how excited <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON> was. 
</P>
<P>
He even apologized for a profanity. Actually, all he said was 'that was a 
helluva play." 
</P>
<P>
Viewers of the <ORGANIZATION>Hall of Fame Bowl</ORGANIZATION> saw one of the all-time hits when <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<PERSON>Zack Dumas</PERSON> leveled <ORGANIZATION>Auburn</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Stacy Danley</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Announcer <PERSON>Don Criqui</PERSON> first said: "That's got to be the hardest hit of the 
'89-90 bowl season." 
</P>
<P>
Then, after viewing a replay, <PERSON>Criqui</PERSON> said: "It's the hardest hit I've seen in 
football in years." 
</P>
<P>
Criqui at one point forgot he was at the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl. Talking about 
<ORGANIZATION>Auburn</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Shayne Wasden</PERSON>'s punt returns of 30 and 34 yards, he said they broke 
the Orange Bowl record. 
</P>
<P>
Well, maybe you can't blame <PERSON>Criqui</PERSON> for being confused. He worked the last eight 
Orange Bowl games. 
</P>
<P>
Speaking of flubs, <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON>, during halftime of the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl, referred 
to <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>George Gipp</PERSON> as <PERSON>George Kemp</PERSON>. However, <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> did catch the 
mistake and corrected it. 
</P>
<P>
In referring to <PERSON>Gipp</PERSON>'s death, comparing it to the death of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> quarterback 
<PERSON>Sal Aunese</PERSON>, <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON> said it occurred a few years ago. 
</P>
<P>
Colleague <PERSON>Bob Costas</PERSON>, fearing <PERSON>Simpson</PERSON>'s attempt at sarcasm was probably lost on 
most viewers, added: "It was more than a few years ago. It was so long ago that 
a young <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> could play <PERSON>Gipp</PERSON> (in the <DATE>1940</DATE> movie, '<ORGANIZATION>Knute Rockne</ORGANIZATION> -- All 
American')." 
</P>
<P>
During halftime of the Fiesta Bowl, <PERSON>Gayle Gardner</PERSON> -- yes, she still works for 
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> -- had an excellent feature on the once-troubled <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> football program 
and the death of <LOCATION>Aunese</LOCATION> <DATE>last September</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
CBS deserves kudos for the halftime piece it showed during the Cotton Bowl. It 
chronicled the highlights of college football during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, including 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1982</DATE> kickoff against <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> broke a story <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> that <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> defensive coordinator <PERSON>Barry 
Alvarez</PERSON> would be leaving the school to become head coach at <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The network had <PERSON>Wiley</PERSON> interview <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> later in the day, but because of 
technical problems, had to cut away from it earlier than planned. 
</P>
<P>
On <TIME>this day and night</TIME> of football, the coverage and the announcing, overall, 
was fine. 
</P>
<P>
It's just that something needs to be done about the logjam. The way things are 
now, it's impossible to see everything. 
</P>
<P>
And that's depriving viewers. You don't see the <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> scheduling seven games on 
Super Bowl <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06298116 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06298116 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; FOOTBALL; CHAMPIONSHIP; GAME; ANALYSIS; BERKELEY; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  For those needing an early jump on their New Year's Day plans, the options may
include watching Cal's football team.;   The Bears, for now, are being watched
by executives from the upper tier of Jan. 1 games -- the Fiesta, Orange,
Florida Citrus and Sugar bowls -- with executives of less prestigious games --
the Hall of Fame is one -- ready to step in if the bigger bowls lose interest.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IT'S NOT TOO EARLY FOR CAL FANS TO THINK ABOUT NEW
YEAR'S DAY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Chart attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Granted, the distinction of playing on <LOCATION>New Year</LOCATION>'s Day has lost some of its
luster with eight -- yes, eight -- bowl games on the day's schedule. So to say
<LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> could be playing in a New Year's Day bowl game, as <PERSON>Brent Musburger</PERSON> did
during <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>'s 24-17 loss to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, still begs for some narrowing of the
scope.;   The only way to glean a Rose Bowl invitation, of course, is to win
the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference championship, which appears headed for Washington.; 
 The Orange also could take some work, because its selection committee uses
three criteria -- national ranking, television audience and fan support -- to
choose an at-large opponent for the Big Eight champion. The Bears were on last
week's Orange Bowl list of 16 and made this week's cut to 12.;   But <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> would
have to be ranked very high -- probably meaning the top three or four -- to
offset questions about its fan base and television appeal, an Orange Bowl
representative said. A group of 7,500 <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> fans traveled to <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, for
last year's Copper Bowl, a <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> spokesman said.;   If <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> can avoid losing
before <DATE>Nov. 17</DATE>, the day bowl bids are delivered, the Bears could net games as
lucrative as the Sugar Bowl, which offers <MONEY>$3.365 million</MONEY> to each team, or the
Fiesta Bowl, which has a <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> payout. The bid date means the Bears' bowl
hopes should be decided before the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> game.;   "We would consider a team
that finished tied for the league championship or lost competitively to the
top team and finished 10-1, depending on how the other bowl possibilities
would be," Fiesta representative <PERSON>Wayne Goodrich</PERSON> said. "We have roots in the
Pac-10. A school like <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> would have a presence on the day of our game.";  
Said <PERSON>Troy Mathieu</PERSON>, assistant executive director of the Sugar Bowl: "At this
point it's very early, but we are interested in the Pac-10 runner-up. . . .
Our game follows the Rose Bowl on <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>, (so) having a Pac-10 team in a bowl
game keeps the fans tuned in. But it's still early.";   The Citrus Bowl has a
soft spot for "Cinderella" teams such as <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>, Citrus president <PERSON>Bob Moore</PERSON> said,
but there's concern about how many Bears fans would go to <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, to
attend the game. The crowd enthusiasm against <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> helped allay that
worry, particularly with a Citrus Bowl representative in attendance, but the
Citrus committee also will look at how many fans go to <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>'s Pac-10 games on
the road.;   It's too early for the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl to put together a list,
said <PERSON>Jim McVay</PERSON>, the bowl's executive director, but <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> certainly has his
attention.;   "There are a lot of pluses," <PERSON>McVay</PERSON> said. "Great players, good
reputation, hell of a team. There aren't any negatives."; <LOCATION>CAL</LOCATION>'S NEW YEAR'S DAY
POSSIBILITIES; New Year's Day Bowl Games and the minimum payout <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference will share if the Bears are invited:; Bowl         
Payout          Matchup; Rose          <MONEY>$6.2 million</MONEY>    Pac-10 champion vs.;   
                           Big Ten champion; Orange        <MONEY>$4.2 million</MONEY>    Big
Eight champion vs.;                               at-large team; Sugar        
<MONEY>$3.635 million</MONEY>  <ORGANIZATION>Southeastern Conference</ORGANIZATION>;                              
champion vs. at-large team; Cotton        <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>      <ORGANIZATION>Southwest Conference</ORGANIZATION>
champion;                               vs. at-large team; Fiesta        <MONEY>$2
million</MONEY>      Two at-large teams; Citrus        <MONEY>$1.35 million</MONEY>   <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Coast
Conference</ORGANIZATION>;                               champion vs. at-large team; <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of
Fame  <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>      Two at-large teams; Peach         <MONEY>$800,000</MONEY>        Two
at-large teams; -- <PERSON>Ric Bucher</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RIC BUCHER, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911024  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  652  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, October 24, 1991
00298116,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112689-0166 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 140202 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 26, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 6; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
793 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HURRICANES PUT DENT IN HOPES OF ORANGE BOWL FOR SHOWDOWN; 
</P>
<P>
BOWLS: MIAMI GOES TO SUGAR BOWL AGAINST SEC CHAMPION. IT ALSO ADDS A FLAW TO 
THE NOTRE DAME-COLORADO MATCHUP. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Even before <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> knocked off top-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>, 27-10, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the 
Hurricanes and Fighting Irish accepted bids to New Year's Day bowl games. 
</P>
<P>
However, seventh-ranked <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s victory over the Irish spoiled the Orange 
Bowl's hoped-for showdown for the national championship between <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> 
(11-1) and second-ranked <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> (11-0), which earned an automatic berth by 
winning the <ORGANIZATION>Big Eight Conference</ORGANIZATION> championship outright for the first time since 
<DATE>1961</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame Athletic</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Dick Rosenthal</PERSON> said the Irish accepted the Orange 
Bowl bid because they haven't played in the New Year's Night game since <DATE>1975</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Rosenthal</PERSON> said the Fighting Irish also considered bids from the Sugar, <ORGANIZATION>Cotton</ORGANIZATION>, 
Fiesta and Citrus Bowls. 
</P>
<P>
Because the game is at night, the Orange Bowl could still get its showdown if 
things break just right earlier in the day. 
</P>
<P>
Colorado last played in the <LOCATION>Orange Bowl</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>, when it was Big Eight 
co-champion. <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> has been the conference representative at 
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> every year since. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> (10-1) accepted a bid to play the <ORGANIZATION>Southeastern Conference</ORGANIZATION> champion -- 
either No. 4 <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> (10-0), No. 10 Auburn (8-2) or No. 8 <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> (9-1) -- in 
the Sugar Bowl in <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>SEC</ORGANIZATION> runner-up, or possibly an <ORGANIZATION>SEC</ORGANIZATION> co-champion that does not go to the Sugar 
Bowl, will play in the Cotton Bowl against ninth-ranked <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> (9-2), the 
<ORGANIZATION>Southwest Conference</ORGANIZATION> champion. 
</P>
<P>
Third-ranked <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (10-1) joined No. 12 USC (8-2-1), the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 
Conference champion, in a rematch at the Rose Bowl in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION> by beating <ORGANIZATION>Ohio 
State</ORGANIZATION>, 28-18, to clinch the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten Conference</ORGANIZATION> championship. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> (8-3) will play the odd team out in the <ORGANIZATION>SEC</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of 
Fame Bowl at <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Fifth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> (8-2), the only team to beat <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, will play No. 6 
<LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> (10-1), which lost only to <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, in the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> at 
<LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
No. 15 Clemson (9-2) will play No. 17 <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> (9-2) <DATE>Dec. 30th</DATE> in the 
Gator Bowl at <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Big Ten runner-up and 11th-ranked Illinois (9-2) and <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION> 
co-champion <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> (10-2), No. 16, accepted bids to play in the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> 
Citrus Bowl on New Year's Day. Illinois lost only to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. 
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> lost only to <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Clemson</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Freedom Bowl was hoping to invite <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and its All-American running back 
<PERSON>Anthony Thompson</PERSON>, but the Hooisers were upset, 15-14, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Purdue</ORGANIZATION>. So 
the game at <LOCATION>Anaheim Stadium</LOCATION> will have <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> (7-3) and <PERSON>Emmitt Smith</PERSON> against 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> (7-4). 
</P>
<P>
No. 22 <ORGANIZATION>Penn State</ORGANIZATION> (7-3-1) accepted an invitation to the Holiday Bowl <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE> 
against <ORGANIZATION>BYU</ORGANIZATION> after beating No. 19 <PERSON>Pitt</PERSON>, 16-13. 
</P>
<P>
'It won't be 16-13 (in the Holiday Bowl)," <PERSON>Paterno</PERSON> said. "Maybe (BYU Coach) 
<PERSON>LaVell Edwards</PERSON> will take it easy because I'm his buddy. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"Or maybe we'll throw and he'll run," added <PERSON>Paterno</PERSON>, drawing laughter because 
the suggestion went contrary to the teams' offensive philosophies. 
</P>
<P>
No. 21 BYU (10-2) clinched the Western Athletic Conference championship and the 
automatic berth in the Holiday Bowl that goes with it by beating <LOCATION>San Diego 
State</LOCATION>, <DATE>48-27</DATE>, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at <PERSON>Jack Murphy</PERSON> Stadium in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> -- site of the 
Holiday Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Despite its defeat, <PERSON>Pitt</PERSON> (6-3-1) will play No. 14 <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> A&amp;M (7-3) in the 
<PERSON>John Hancock</PERSON> Bowl <DATE>Dec. 16</DATE> at <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Georgia (6-4) will play Syracuse (6-4) in the <LOCATION>Peach Bowl</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Atlanta Stadium</LOCATION> on 
<DATE>Dec. 30</DATE>. <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse</ORGANIZATION> each has one game remaining -- <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> at 
archrival <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse</ORGANIZATION> against <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. Both games are 
next weekend. 
</P>
<P>
No. 25 <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> (7-4), with losses to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, won its fifth consecutive game <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, 31-3, over <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, to 
earn a spot in the <LOCATION>Aloha Bowl</LOCATION> on Christmas Day against No. 24 <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> (8-2) in 
<LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Mississippi (7-4) beat <LOCATION>Mississippi State</LOCATION>, 21-11, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and accepted a bid to 
the Liberty Bowl on <DATE>Dec. 28</DATE> at <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, against <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> (8-3). The 
Falcons were eliminated from the WAC race and Holiday Bowl consideration by 
<ORGANIZATION>BYU</ORGANIZATION>'s victory. 
</P>
<P>
Arizona (6-4-1), by beating archrival <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>, 28-10, on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, will 
stay at home in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION> to play <ORGANIZATION>North Carolina State</ORGANIZATION> (7-4) in the inaugural 
Copper Bowl on <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In the Independence Bowl, <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION> (6-5) will play <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> (7-4) at <LOCATION>Shreveport</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Dec. 16</DATE> 
</P>
<P>
No. 18 <ORGANIZATION>Texas Tech</ORGANIZATION> (8-3), despite a 40-24 loss to 13-ranked <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, 
will face No. 23 Duke (8-3) in the All-American Bowl on <DATE>Dec. 28</DATE> at <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Ala</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (8-2) is on NCAA probation for recruiting violations and is ineligible 
for post-season play. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Fresno State</ORGANIZATION> (9-2), champion of the <ORGANIZATION>Big West Conference</ORGANIZATION>, will play <ORGANIZATION>Ball State</ORGANIZATION> 
(7-2-2), the Mid-American Conference titlist, in the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Raisin Bowl on 
<DATE>Dec. 9</DATE> at <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOOTBALL GAMES; FOOTBALL TEAMS; ORANGE BOWL (FOOTBALL GAME); FOOTBALL 
CHAMPIONSHIPS; UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI; UNIVERSITY OF NOTRE DAME 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06323217 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06323217 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, Chart; PHOTO: Associated Press; SOME CONSOLATION -- For Kirk Carruthers
and formerly No. 1 Florida State, a Cotton Bowl bid is better than nothing.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; FOOTBALL; GAME; PLAYOFF; DATE; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Bowl deadlines? Official dates?;   Of course they were meaningless. Dennis
Erickson, the coach of top-ranked Miami, never believed bowls suddenly would
be honorable and follow the rules.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BOWLS ANNOUNCE THEIR CHOICES
BUT, AS USUAL, EVERYONE KNEW WELL IN ADVANCE WHO
WOULD GO WHERE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Mercury News Staff Writer Ric Bucher contributed to this report.; Chart
attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "To me, that was a farce," he said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after the Hurricanes accepted a
bid from the Orange Bowl.;   "The bowl matchups were made I don't know how
long ago.";   Of course, nothing was supposed to be decided until noon <ORGANIZATION>PST</ORGANIZATION>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Bowls are subject to a <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> fine for breaking the deadline, but no
fines have been announced.;   The bowl selections have left some schools
disappointed and frustrated.;   No. 17 <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>, despite a two-game losing
streak, will play No. 5 <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> in the Sugar Bowl.;   After <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s 35-13
victory over <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>, several <ORGANIZATION>Penn State</ORGANIZATION> players were bitter that the bowl
deadline was broken to their detriment.;   "We thought that we should have
gone to the Sugar Bowl," wide receiver <PERSON>O.J. McDuffie</PERSON> said. "But if it's the
<LOCATION>Fiesta</LOCATION>, we're happy. We wanted a New Year's Day bowl game and got one. We're
satisfied.";   <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> also felt squeezed out of the Sugar Bowl picture.;   "I
think the only thing that is being hurt by that is the Sugar Bowl," said <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>
senior tight end Brent Woodall.;   "They are taking a team with a lesser
record. If they wanted to have the best game possible, they would have taken
the team with the highest ranking, and that's us.";   Cotton Bowl president
<PERSON>John Stuart</PERSON> said, "There's no perfect system -- you've got to start with that.
It's going to take a while to work all the kinks out.;   "From the fans'
standpoint, I hope it's going to get better.";   Next year things will change
as the bowl alliance begins. The Orange, <ORGANIZATION>Cotton</ORGANIZATION>, Sugar, Fiesta and Citrus have
aligned with five conferences and <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> to divide the spots. The Rose
Bowl, which has not produced an undisputed national champion since <LOCATION>Southern
Cal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1972</DATE>, is tied to the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10.;   Which of the
consortium's five bowls hosts the best game is determined by the rankings of
the champions of the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Southeastern</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Big Eight Conferences</ORGANIZATION>. The
bowl connected with the highest-ranked champion -- the Sugar has the
<LOCATION>Southeastern</LOCATION>, the Cotton has the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION>, and the Orange has the Big Eight
-- picks first from among the at-large teams. If the highest-ranked matchup is
among the at-large teams, then the Fiesta would host the premier game.;   But
even this solution won't solve all the problems.;   There would be nothing to
prevent the Sugar Bowl from selecting based on television ratings instead of
national rankings again, as it did this year by working out a deal with <ORGANIZATION>Notre
Dame</ORGANIZATION> instead of a higher-ranked team.;   "That's one of those items we'll just
have to feel out," <PERSON>Stuart</PERSON> said. "I think it happened this season for one
reason and one reason only -- they had to turn on TV sets. . . . I just see
the chances of stability as much greater."; BOWL GAMES AT A GLANCE; Bowl/     
               Time/       This season's; Site            Date      Network   
 matchup; <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>                <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>      SJS or <ORGANIZATION>Fresno State; Fresno   
      Dec.</ORGANIZATION> 14   SportsCh.   vs. <ORGANIZATION>Bowling Green</ORGANIZATION>; <LOCATION>Aloha</LOCATION>                     <TIME>12:30
p.m.</TIME>  <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>        <DATE>Dec. 25</DATE>   <ORGANIZATION>ABC         Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>;
Blockbuster               <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>      <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>           <DATE>Dec. 28</DATE>  
CBS         <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>; Independence              <TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME> 
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Shreveport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La</LOCATION>. <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE>   ABC         <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Liberty          
        5 p.m.      Air Force</ORGANIZATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>.  <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE>   <ORGANIZATION>ESPN        Miss</ORGANIZATION>.
St.; Gator                     <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>      <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
<DATE>Dec. 30</DATE> TBS        <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>; Holiday                   <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>     
BYU or <LOCATION>San Diego State</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>       <DATE>Dec. 30</DATE>   ESPN        vs. <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>; Copper
                   <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>      <LOCATION>Baylor</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.   <DATE>Dec. 30</DATE>   TBS      
  <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>; Freedom                   <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>      BYU or <LOCATION>San Diego State</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>         <DATE>Dec. 30</DATE>   <ORGANIZATION>Raycom</ORGANIZATION>      vs. <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>; Sun                      
<TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME>  <LOCATION>UCLA</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>  <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>   CBS         <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Peach   
                 8:30 a.m.   N.C. State</ORGANIZATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Atlanta         Jan. 1    ESPN   
    East Carolina</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame              <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME>     <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION> vs.; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.     <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    <ORGANIZATION>NBC         Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>; Citrus                    <TIME>10:30
a.m.</TIME>  <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.   <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    <ORGANIZATION>ABC         vs. Clemson</ORGANIZATION>; Cotton          
         10:30 a.m.  <LOCATION>Florida State</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>          <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    CBS         vs.
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> A&amp;M; <LOCATION>Fiesta</LOCATION>                    <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>      <LOCATION>Penn State</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>.   
<DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>         vs. <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>; Rose                      <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>     
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>        <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    ABC         vs. <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>; Sugar         
           <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME>   <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>     <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    ABC         vs.
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>; Orange                    <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>      <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>) vs.; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.  
  <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>    <ORGANIZATION>NBC         Nebraska</ORGANIZATION> or <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>; All times PST  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Staff and Wire Report  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911118  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  785  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, November 18, 1991
00323217,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010289-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 543 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 1; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1280 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE BOWL GAMES; 
</P>
<P>
ROSE BOWL; 
</P>
<P>
SCHEMBECHLER COULD USE LAST LAUGH AGAINST USC 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MAL FLORENCE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Whenever <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON> is reminded of his 1-7 record in the 
<LOCATION>Rose Bowl</LOCATION>, which is often, he jokes about it. 
</P>
<P>
It's a logical response, because he can't do anything now about what has 
happened in the past. 
</P>
<P>
Regardless of his lighthearted comments, <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON> would like to start 
chipping away at his record by beating <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> today in the 75th renewal of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Rose Bowl</ORGANIZATION> game. 
</P>
<P>
USC Coach <PERSON>Larry Smith</PERSON> doesn't have such skeletons rattling in his coaching 
closet. 
</P>
<P>
Nonetheless, there is a certain urgency for <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> to win today's game, 
considering that his Trojans lost to <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>last year</DATE>'s Rose Bowl 
game in his first appearance as a head coach. It would also take some of the 
sting out of a regular-season ending loss to <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
That defeat ranks as one of the most disappointing in 100 years of <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> 
football. If USC (10-1) had won, it would be defending a No. 1 ranking in 
college football against <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> quarterback <PERSON>Rodney Peete</PERSON> has said that it will be a long time before that 
defeat is little more than a memory. 
</P>
<P>
So how will the Trojans respond? Smith isn't sure. "We won't know until we come 
out on the field. We haven't been able to judge ourselves in that situation 
because it's the first time we've come off a loss this season," he said. 
</P>
<P>
As for <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (8-2-1), the <LOCATION>Wolverines</LOCATION> could be a national championship 
contender today if it weren't for early season losses to <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> 
by a total of 3 points. 
</P>
<P>
Much has been written that the USC-Michigan matchup is a secondary bowl game, 
inasmuch as No. 1-ranked <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION> and No. 3 <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> will be playing for 
the national championship in the <LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> at about the same time. 
</P>
<P>
Not surprisingly, <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON> and <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> contend that the "Granddaddy of them 
all," the Rose Bowl, doesn't take a back seat in viewing interest to any bowl. 
Subsequent television ratings will provide more insight. 
</P>
<P>
In any event, <DATE>today</DATE>'s Rose Bowl game has its intrinsic interest -- 
<PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>'s albatross-like record along with the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION>'s failure here in 
recent years, losing 12 of the past 14 Rose Bowl games. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, there's the relationship between the coaches. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> got his coaching 
start as a member of <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>'s staff at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> in the 
late <DATE>1960s</DATE> and early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
They've been friends ever since, and <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> attributes much of his coaching 
philosophy to his early apprenticeship under <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON> has lost only 5 games and won 18 in 2 seasons at <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>. In those losses, 
Trojan turnovers were decisive. <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> says they will be a key factor today. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> isn't likely to oblige, considering that quarterbacks <PERSON>Michael Taylor</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Demetrius Brown</PERSON> have thrown only 2 interceptions and have lost only 8 
fumbles the entire season. 
</P>
<P>
With the notable exception of the <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> game when <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> had 4 turnovers, the 
Trojans haven't been error-prone. 
</P>
<P>
Peete has thrown 10 interceptions, but that's misleading, considering his 
entire offensive output. He has completed 208 of 338 passes (<PERCENT>61.5%</PERCENT>) for an 
average of 241.3 yards a game and 18 touchdowns. 
</P>
<P>
By contrast, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s quarterbacks have attempted only 191 passes. The 
Wolverines are primarily a running team, featuring tailback <PERSON>Tony Boles</PERSON> and 
fullback <PERSON>Leroy Hoard</PERSON>, who are each averaging 5.5 yards a carry. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> will not be taken out of its running game," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said. "They're 
better at it than any team we've played." 
</P>
<P>
However, the <LOCATION>Wolverines</LOCATION> may be forced to pass more often than in previous games 
considering the Trojans are No. 2-ranked nationally in rushing defense, 
allowing an average of only 76.6 yards a game. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> has a more balanced offense, averaging 214.6 yards running and 247 yards 
passing compared with 256.6 and 153.4 for <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Both teams have what <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> calls bend-but-not-break defenses. <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> features 
one of the nation's best defensive linemen in tackle <PERSON>Mark Messner</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
However, <PERSON>Peete</PERSON>, who placed second to <ORGANIZATION>Oklahoma State</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Barry Sanders</PERSON> in the 
Heisman Trophy voting, seemingly provides <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> with an edge in an otherwise even 
matchup. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON> became the starting quarterback when <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> suffered a broken collarbone 
in the ninth game of the season against <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON> had 16 interceptions last season, a factor in losing his starting job to 
<PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>. However, he hasn't been intercepted since replacing <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, completing 
<PERCENT>61.7%</PERCENT> of his passes for 5 touchdowns. 
</P>
<P>
It's <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>'s show today as <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> was recently hospitalized with the flu and 
isn't expected to play. 
</P>
<P>
The Wolverines are aware of <ORGANIZATION>Peete</ORGANIZATION>'s capabilities. Said <PERSON>Messner</PERSON>: "He's very, 
very fast and he can beat you single-handedly." 
</P>
<P>
Notre Dame had some success blitzing <PERSON>Peete</PERSON> in a 27-10 victory, and it wouldn't 
be surprising if <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> uses the same tactic. 
</P>
<P>
The Wolverines don't seem to be up-tight, perhaps reflecting the mood of their 
coach, who has been accommodating and apparently relaxed since the team's 
arrival here. 
</P>
<P>
As for his 1-7 Rose Bowl record, <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON>, who has won more games than any 
other active college coach, dismisses it by saying: 
</P>
<P>
"If you win all the time, maybe you don't have as much appreciation for it. The 
thing that has balanced out my career is the fact I haven't been as successful 
in bowls. 
</P>
<P>
"If I had the same record I had in bowls as I do in the regular season, I'd 
probably be too cocky and have too big an ego." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Rose Bowl Notes 
</P>
<P>
Kickoff for today's game is <TIME>2 p.m</TIME>. A crowd of 95,000 to 100,000 is expected. . 
. . USC is a 6 1/2-point favorite. Even though <PERSON>Aaron Emanuel</PERSON> has been <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s 
most productive tailback in recent games, Coach <PERSON>Larry Smith</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Ricky 
Ervins</PERSON> would start today. "He has had excellent practices," <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said of 
<PERSON>Ervins</PERSON>, "but all of our tailbacks will play." He was mainly referring to 
<PERSON>Ervins</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Emanuel</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Scott Lockwood</PERSON>. Smith would also like to use <PERSON>Steven Webster</PERSON> 
if possible. <PERSON>Webster</PERSON>, a senior, has missed virtually the entire season with 
injuries. . . . <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Wilbur Odom</PERSON>, a sophomore, who has played in only one 
game, will back up <PERSON>Demetrius Brown</PERSON> at quarterback. 
</P>
<P>
USC is ranked fifth in the polls, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> 11th. . . . <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> concedes that 
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> has an edge over <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> in the kicking game. <PERSON>Mike Gillette</PERSON>, a catcher on 
the baseball team, is averaging 40.4 yards on punts. He set a school record 
with his 56-yard field goal against <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>. USC punter <PERSON>Chris Sperle</PERSON> is 
averaging 38.3 yards, and <PERSON>Quin Rodriguez</PERSON> made 14 of 19 field goals, 7 for 7 
inside the 30-yard line. . . . <PERSON>Erik Affholter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s All-American split end, 
set schools records in the regular season for receptions in a season (63) and 
career (118). <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> has accomplished wide receivers in <PERSON>Greg McMurtry</PERSON>, <PERSON>Chris 
Calloway</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Kolesar</PERSON>. However, that group has had a total of only 67 
receptions on a run-oriented team. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>T.J. Osman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s middle guard, on <PERSON>Bo Schembechler</PERSON>'s overall 4-11 bowl 
record: "He told us before we left that if we got a question about his bowl 
record to answer by saying that it's his record and not anything that we had to 
do with." . . . Asked to comment on <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> allowing 31 points against <ORGANIZATION>Ohio 
State</ORGANIZATION> in the second half of a final regular-season game, defensive tackle <PERSON>Mark 
Messner</PERSON> said: "We're still asking what happened. We had the same players and we 
were calling the same defenses, but they were going right through us." <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> 
won, though, 34-31, on a late, 41-yard pass from <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> to <PERSON>Kolesar</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> is 
ranked ninth nationally in scoring defense, allowing an average of 13.9 points 
a game. . . . <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> has a 3-1 record against <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> in the Rose Bowl and 3-3 
overall. The Trojans have an 18-7 Rose Bowl record. . . . <PERSON>Schembechler</PERSON> has lost 
only one Rose Bowl game by more than 8 points, a 24-14 loss to <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The mellowing of Michigan Coach Bo Schembechler, despite his 4-11 
overall bowl record, including 1-7 in the Rose Bowl, shows in a smile during a 
Wolverine workout while preparing for USC. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MICHIGAN 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090590-0123 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 271721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 5, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
663 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MELVIN DURSLAG: TEACHING HOW DEALS ARE DONE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MELVIN DURSLAG 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Those who administer college football are depressed. They aren't able to 
understand the money madness seizing the children who play the game. 
</P>
<P>
With eligibility left, the kids are going over the wall to join the pros. What 
has happened to the student-athlete? You ask one: 
</P>
<P>
"Are you interested in engineering?" 
</P>
<P>
"Indeed I am. I am dying to study the power plant of a Ferrari -- my Ferrari." 
</P>
<P>
It is regrettable that undergraduates in football don't have the healthy 
outlook of their university elders, who see the game as simple beauty, free 
from commercial pressure and general money-grubbing. 
</P>
<P>
For instance, colleges <DATE>today</DATE> play no more than 12 games. They are playing bowl 
games before the season even starts -- things called the <ORGANIZATION>Kickoff Classic</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Disneyland Pigskin Classic</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A college distinguished for its football has set up a private television deal 
with <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>. Lesser arrangements by universities result in as many as 11 games 
being seen on TV on a single <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Why can't the players comport themselves like those who run college football, 
detached from earthly goods, dedicated to the spirit of friendly rivalry that 
sportsmen seek? 
</P>
<P>
New Year's Day, you will see that the number of bowl games on television has 
been limited to eight. 
</P>
<P>
"You will note the restraint," university people will tell players thinking of 
jumping to the pros. "We easily could play 10 on New Year's, scheduling two 
games between <TIME>midnight</TIME> and 6 in the morning." 
</P>
<P>
Originally, college football favored us with four bowls on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> -- Rose, 
Orange, Cotton and Sugar. 
</P>
<P>
It expanded to five with something known as the <ORGANIZATION>Sunkist</ORGANIZATION> Fiesta Bowl. Then, 
presumably on a leveraged buyout, the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> Citrus Bowl took over the 
Tangerine Bowl and soon bumped New Year's Day viewing to six games. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl increased it to seven, the figure now escalating to eight 
with a switching of dates of the <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> Gator Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
Eight bowl games battling each other on the same day might appear as overkill, 
but what's a little cannibalization among educated people? 
</P>
<P>
Meantime, the Cotton Bowl has come to be called the <ORGANIZATION>Mobil Cotton Bowl</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Sugar Bowl the <ORGANIZATION>USF&amp;G</ORGANIZATION> Sugar Bowl. The Sun Bowl became the <PERSON>John Hancock</PERSON> Sun 
Bowl, until such time as the sponsor decided such billing was a deterrent to 
direct communication. 
</P>
<P>
The name was changed to <PERSON>John Hancock</PERSON> Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
And the universities, observing events, go along, because they are not as 
commercially oriented as today's players. 
</P>
<P>
Over in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, they got a postseason game certified known as the Copper Bowl. 
Linking up with a firm that makes mouth freshener, the game became known as the 
Copper BreathLess Bowl, but that would change to Copper Bowl, presented by 
BreathLess. 
</P>
<P>
Last heard from, the game was still breathing, but without its mouth-freshening 
sponsor. 
</P>
<P>
Mind you, this is watched unblinkingly by the colleges, role models for those 
student-athletes who would dump their schools for a lousy <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> a year from 
the pros. 
</P>
<P>
Since only one bowl game, the Rose, has fixed participants every year, the 
others must hoof it, entering into bloodlettings to beat out rivals for the 
best teams. 
</P>
<P>
Rules prevent bowls from contacting teams before specified dates, and, of 
course, no school would fudge, accepting bids prematurely, because this would 
set a bum example for the players. 
</P>
<P>
Watching a school that lacks integrity, a player with eligibility might be 
tempted to talk to a pro team in the alley about the draft. 
</P>
<P>
Now, say, you play for Clemson where home sellouts are automatic. Why open with 
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> when you can play <LOCATION>Cal State Long Beach</LOCATION>? 
</P>
<P>
Same financial result. 
</P>
<P>
So you wipe out <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, 59-0, enhance the winning record and prepare three 
weeks down the line to entertain <ORGANIZATION>Appalachian State</ORGANIZATION>. Picturing <PERSON>George Allen</PERSON>, 
<LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> coach, on the sideline <DATE>last Saturday</DATE>, you heard him mumble: "The 
future is 20 years ago." 
</P>
<P>
But <ORGANIZATION>Clemson</ORGANIZATION> establishes standards any admiring kid will want to emulate as he 
strolls the boulevard of life. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOOTBALL GAMES; SPORTS RULES AND REGULATIONS; TELEVISION PROGRAMMING; FOOTBALL 
PLAYERS -- ELIGIBILITY; COLLEGE ATHLETICS; SCHOOL ADMINISTRATORS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111290-0086 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 306883 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 12, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
644 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AILING BRUINS GOT WHAT DOCTOR ORDERED; 
</P>
<P>
UCLA: UPSET OF NO. 2 WASHINGTON PROVIDES A MUCH-NEEDED LIFT HEADING INTO 
RENEWAL OF USC RIVALRY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MAL FLORENCE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
UCLA's 25-22 upset of second-ranked <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> was 
significant in many respects. 
</P>
<P>
It provided a struggling team with an emotional lift and might have a 
long-range effect on the football program. 
</P>
<P>
It was also one of the most astounding victories in <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> history considering 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s 21-point favoritism and the Huskies' previous domination of 
Pacific 10 Conference opponents this season. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, by winning, the Bruins (5-5) have an opportunity to avert a second 
consecutive losing season if they beat <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the Rose Bowl. 
</P>
<P>
There is some irony, however, to <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>'s status. Even if the Bruins beat the 
Trojans and finish with a 6-5 record, they probably won't be invited to a bowl 
game. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA Athletic Director <PERSON>Peter Dalis</PERSON> said that his phone wasn't ringing 
repeatedly <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with calls from bowl representatives. 
</P>
<P>
"I haven't heard a thing since we lost to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> (<DATE>Sept. 22</DATE>)," <PERSON>Dalis</PERSON> said. 
"The Peach Bowl was the last bowl to pay any attention to us. All the oral 
commitments have been made. 
</P>
<P>
"The only way that you might slip into a bowl is if a bowl had an agreement 
with someone earlier and that team might not have a six-victory season and the 
bowl doesn't have a backup." 
</P>
<P>
A <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> rule prohibits schools with losing records from playing in a bowl game. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> is committed to the Peach Bowl <DATE>Dec. 29</DATE> in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, reportedly against 
<ORGANIZATION>North Carolina State</ORGANIZATION> or <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has a 5-3-1 record with games remaining against <ORGANIZATION>Illinois</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Purdue</ORGANIZATION>. 
Last year, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> was apparently set to play in the Freedom Bowl, before 
losing to <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Purdue</ORGANIZATION> and finishing with a 5-6 record. 
</P>
<P>
It is believed that conferences are as eager as some bowl representatives to 
place their teams in bowl games at the earliest possible date. 
</P>
<P>
For example, five Pac-10 teams are already in bowl games: <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, Rose; 
<ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>John Hancock</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, Freedom; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Aloha</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, Copper. 
</P>
<P>
Official invitations will not be presented until <DATE>Nov. 24</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA Coach <PERSON>Terry Donahue</PERSON> wasn't thinking about a bowl game after the Bruins' 
victory. 
</P>
<P>
"It puts us in a position to save our year, bowl, or no bowl, " <PERSON>Donahue</PERSON> said. 
"We have an opportunity for a winning season in our big game with our 
cross-town rival. 
</P>
<P>
"But there's more to it than that. When you beat the No. 2 team in the country 
in their stadium, with the weather conditions (wind and light rain) it helps 
your program, your confidence and the players who have been struggling." 
</P>
<P>
To put <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>'s accomplishment in perspective, it ranks with a 7-6 victory over 
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>'s Rose Bowl-bound "Vow Boys" in <DATE>1935</DATE>; the 14-12 victory over <LOCATION>Michigan 
State</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1966</DATE> Rose Bowl; a <DATE>20-17</DATE> victory in <DATE>1972</DATE> over <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, the 
defending national champion, and a 23-10 victory over <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1976</DATE> 
Rose Bowl game after the Bruins lost to the <LOCATION>Buckeyes</LOCATION>, 41-20, during the regular 
season. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA Notes 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s game with <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> will be unusual in that a Rose Bowl invitation will 
not be on the line for either team. That was the situation in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1980</DATE> 
(when both teams were on probation). Previously, the Rose Bowl bid was a prize 
for at least one team, or one team had already clinched a Rose Bowl berth, in 
every year since <DATE>1971</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA's defense, which has been maligned at times this season, held <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> 
to 283 total yards, 139 yards below its season average. UCLA defensive 
coordinator <PERSON>Bob Field</PERSON> said the team had four goals: 
</P>
<P>
"We didn't want (tailback) <PERSON>Greg Lewis</PERSON> to rush for 100 yards (he got 50). No. 2 
was not to allow them to break any run for more than 20 yards (they didn't). 
No. 3 was not to let them catch any pass for over 25 yards (which they did) and 
make (quarterback) <PERSON>Mark Brunell</PERSON> beat us with his arm, and not his feet. (He 
completed only 10 of 34 passes). We wanted to make him one dimensional, not 
two. We just played our base defense, simple and sound." 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COLLEGE ATHLETICS; FOOTBALL GAMES; UNIVERSITY OF SOUTHERN CALIFORNIA; 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890103-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-03-89 0233EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BowlGames-Newspage 1stLd-Writethru a0446 01-03 0247</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bowl Games-Newspage, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0446,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Notre Dame Wins Eighth National College Football Championship</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `In other...' to CORRECT Citrus Bowl score to
13-6 sted 13-10; picks up 4th graf pvs, `Seventeenth-ranked...; FIXES typo
in last graf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Top-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame</ORGANIZATION> defeated No. 3 <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> 34-21 in the
<LOCATION>Fiesta Bowl</LOCATION> to give the Fighting Irish their eighth national
championship in college football and the first since <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   Notre Dame's <PERSON>Tony Rice</PERSON>, a junior, threw for two touchdowns and a
career-high 213 yards as the Irish finished the season undefeated at
12-0.
   In other bowl games <DATE>Monday</DATE>, No. 11 <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> upset No. 5 <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION> 22-14 in the Rose Bowl; No. 9 UCLA beat No. 8 <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>
17-3 in the Cotton Bowl; and No. 13 Clemson edged No. 10 <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>
13-6 in the <LOCATION>Citrus Bowl</LOCATION>.
   Seventeenth-ranked <ORGANIZATION>Syracuse defeated No. 16 Louisiana State</ORGANIZATION> 23-10
in the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame Bowl; No. 2 <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> defeated No. 6 <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> 23-3
in the Orange Bowl; and No. 4 <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> defeated No. 7 Auburn
13-7 in the Sugar Bowl.
   Notre Dame's victory assured it of the top spot in the final
<ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll.
   Rice completed seven of 11 passes, including a 29-yard scoring
strike to <ORGANIZATION>Raghib Ismail</ORGANIZATION> late in the <DATE>second quarter</DATE> and a 3-yard pass
to <PERSON>Frank Jacobs</PERSON> early in the <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, which finished 11-1, had to be satisified with the
first 11-victory season in its 96-year football history.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06001047 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06001047 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COLLEGE; FOOTBALL; PLAYOFF; GAME; CHART; MAJOR-STORY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Chuck Neinas will have three television sets going today.;    "And I'll still
lose track of what's going on," Neinas said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BOWLING THEM OVER ON NEW YEAR'S DAY
COLLEGE GAME IS FEELING THE EFFECTS OF A
FULL SCHEDULE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  College Football
See also related articles on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It should be pointed out that <PERSON>Neinas</PERSON> considers himself "an above-average
football fan," which qualifies as a huge understatement. <PERSON>Neinas</PERSON>, the executive
director of the <ORGANIZATION>College Football Association</ORGANIZATION>, wants to keep up with all the
action.;    But it's not possible. His eyes don't move quickly enough, and
even the fastest remote control in the West would be woefully lacking.;   
"Eight games," <PERSON>Neinas</PERSON> says. "It's too much. It's not fair to the fans.";   
Especially for those fans with only one television set.;    Just when you
thought they couldn't stuff any more games into that overstuffed bag that is
New Year's Day, the bowls went ahead and did it. Starting at <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> with
the Gator Bowl and ending around <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> with the Sugar Bowl, there will be
eight games today, a football hater's worst nightmare.;    Eight is enough; 
And it's hardly a dream for the bowls, either. For them, eight is more than
enough. In fact, eight is ridiculous. Furthermore, eight is one of the reasons
some of critics suggest the bowl system could be in trouble in the <DATE>1990s.</DATE>;   
The glut of games on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> has the bowls extremely nervous. So do falling TV
