<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890428-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-89 0046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r e PM-APonTV-MisterRogers     04-28 0852</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Mister Rogers,0871</SECOND>
<HEAD>Miniseries Making Neighborhood Debut</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PG5 Sent April 26.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The miniseries comes to ``Mister <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>'
Neighborhood'' next week, and the show's cardigan-clad creator
promises a message as gentle and reassuring as ever.
   The three-part musical, titled ``Josephine the Short-Neck
Giraffe,'' tells the story of a young giraffe who yearns for a
long, graceful neck like all the other giraffes. She eventually
grows, <PERSON>Fred Rogers</PERSON> confided, ``not on the outside, but on the
important side.''
   ``It's very much like the usual message of the Neighborhood,
that you can be acceptable as you are,'' he said, smiling. ``It's
not so much the outsides of us that are important.''
   A song sung by <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> and her friend Hazel the elephant sums
it up best, according to <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You're much more than a neck, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>. And you're much more
than a trunk, Hazel. A chicken's more than a peck, and there's more
than a smell to a skunk,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> quietly sang during an interview
at <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s WQED-TV, home to his children's programs for the
past 35 years.
   The special week of new programs gets under way <DATE>Monday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Public
Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION> stations with a trip to the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild
Animal Park</LOCATION>, where viewers are introduced to real-life giraffes and
elephants. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION> visits a film processing lab to have
his animal photographs developed.
   The miniseries, which features a cast of 15, elaborate animal
costumes and five sets, runs <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Rogers
gently guides his young audience from one day to the next,
summarizing the main events and hinting at what might lie ahead for
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Neighborhood of Make-Believe</ORGANIZATION>, where animals sing, dance
and play the trombone, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> is befriended by <PERSON>J.R.</PERSON>, a shy
giraffe who overcomes his problems by helping <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> conquer
hers. He accomplishes that with help from Hazel the elephant, who
advises him to ``just let your heart speak.''
   ``There isn't a time that I see the scene in which <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION> talks
and sings with Josephine ... that I haven't gotten chills up my
spine,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said, tapping his right hand against his back.
``And this is something I've worked with for years. There's
something so redemptive about someone who is trying so hard to help
somebody else.''
   Rogers, 61, wrote ``Josephine the Short-Neck Giraffe'' for a
French class assignment at <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>. He
named J.R. the giraffe after fraternity brother <PERSON>John Reardon</PERSON>, who
went on to sing with the Metropolitan Opera and was a frequent
guest on ``Mister Rogers Neighborhood.'' <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON> died a year ago,
and the miniseries is dedicated to him.
   Rogers set the story to music in the late <DATE>1950s</DATE>, and about 1,000
records were pressed. Writer <PERSON>Barry Head</PERSON> transformed ``Josephine the
Short-Neck Giraffe'' into a poem for children in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   For years, <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> tried to have the musical produced on stage or
as an animated film.
   ``I still think it would be great for animation and a stage
production,'' he said. ``But I thought unless we get it out on the
air, I don't think anybody's going to know about it.''
   The story <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> wrote 39 years ago is vastly different from the
musical airing next week. It is the Neighborhood's 13th musical.
   ``At the end of the (original) story, when people are telling
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> that they like her just the way she is, she raises her
head to look at them because she hasn't really heard this message
before and her neck starts to grow. And it grows and grows and
grows until her neck is as tall as everybody else's,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said.
   In the musical, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>'s neck remains short.
   ``I think it shows how much we've grown,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``You
know, you don't have to look like everybody else to be acceptable
and to feel acceptable. And wishes don't always come true.
   ``Because for a year and a day I've been wishing, she sang. That
was one of her first songs. Her wish was for a longer neck, she
thought. But really her wish was to have people like her exactly as
she is. So often what we say we're wishing for isn't necessarily
what is behind the wish. This is very philosophical.''
   Will pre-schoolers be able to grasp such a serious message, even
in such a light-hearted setting?
   ``Maybe not in words, but let their hearts speak to them the way
<PERSON>Hazel</PERSON> said to <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION>, `Just let your heart speak,''' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``I
think that that's the way an awful lot of communication takes
place.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The miniseries comes to ``Mister <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>'
Neighborhood'' next week, and the show's cardigan-clad creator
promises a message as gentle and reassuring as ever.
   The three-part musical, titled ``Josephine the Short-Neck
Giraffe,'' tells the story of a young giraffe who yearns for a
long, graceful neck like all the other giraffes. She eventually
grows, <PERSON>Fred Rogers</PERSON> confided, ``not on the outside, but on the
important side.''
   ``It's very much like the usual message of the Neighborhood,
that you can be acceptable as you are,'' he said, smiling. ``It's
not so much the outsides of us that are important.''
   A song sung by <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> and her friend Hazel the elephant sums
it up best, according to <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You're much more than a neck, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>. And you're much more
than a trunk, Hazel. A chicken's more than a peck, and there's more
than a smell to a skunk,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> quietly sang during an interview
at <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s WQED-TV, home to his children's programs for the
past 35 years.
   The special week of new programs gets under way <DATE>Monday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Public
Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION> stations with a trip to the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild
Animal Park</LOCATION>, where viewers are introduced to real-life giraffes and
elephants. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION> visits a film processing lab to have
his animal photographs developed.
   The miniseries, which features a cast of 15, elaborate animal
costumes and five sets, runs <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Rogers
gently guides his young audience from one day to the next,
summarizing the main events and hinting at what might lie ahead for
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Neighborhood of Make-Believe</ORGANIZATION>, where animals sing, dance
and play the trombone, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> is befriended by <PERSON>J.R.</PERSON>, a shy
giraffe who overcomes his problems by helping <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> conquer
hers. He accomplishes that with help from Hazel the elephant, who
advises him to ``just let your heart speak.''
   ``There isn't a time that I see the scene in which <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION> talks
and sings with Josephine ... that I haven't gotten chills up my
spine,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said, tapping his right hand against his back.
``And this is something I've worked with for years. There's
something so redemptive about someone who is trying so hard to help
somebody else.''
   Rogers, 61, wrote ``Josephine the Short-Neck Giraffe'' for a
French class assignment at <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>. He
named J.R. the giraffe after fraternity brother <PERSON>John Reardon</PERSON>, who
went on to sing with the Metropolitan Opera and was a frequent
guest on ``Mister Rogers Neighborhood.'' <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON> died a year ago,
and the miniseries is dedicated to him.
   Rogers set the story to music in the late <DATE>1950s</DATE>, and about 1,000
records were pressed. Writer <PERSON>Barry Head</PERSON> transformed ``Josephine the
Short-Neck Giraffe'' into a poem for children in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   For years, <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> tried to have the musical produced on stage or
as an animated film.
   ``I still think it would be great for animation and a stage
production,'' he said. ``But I thought unless we get it out on the
air, I don't think anybody's going to know about it.''
   The story <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> wrote 39 years ago is vastly different from the
musical airing next week. It is the Neighborhood's 13th musical.
   ``At the end of the (original) story, when people are telling
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> that they like her just the way she is, she raises her
head to look at them because she hasn't really heard this message
before and her neck starts to grow. And it grows and grows and
grows until her neck is as tall as everybody else's,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said.
   In the musical, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>'s neck remains short.
   ``I think it shows how much we've grown,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``You
know, you don't have to look like everybody else to be acceptable
and to feel acceptable. And wishes don't always come true.
   ``Because for a year and a day I've been wishing, she sang. That
was one of her first songs. Her wish was for a longer neck, she
thought. But really her wish was to have people like her exactly as
she is. So often what we say we're wishing for isn't necessarily
what is behind the wish. This is very philosophical.''
   Will pre-schoolers be able to grasp such a serious message, even
in such a light-hearted setting?
   ``Maybe not in words, but let their hearts speak to them the way
<PERSON>Hazel</PERSON> said to <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION>, `Just let your heart speak,''' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``I
think that that's the way an awful lot of communication takes
place.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890426-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-26-89 0745EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-MisterRogers Adv28   04-26 0867</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Mister Rogers, Adv 28,0886</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday PMs, April 28, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Miniseries Making Neighborhood Debut</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCIA DUNN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The miniseries comes to ``Mister <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>'
Neighborhood'' next week, and the show's cardigan-clad creator
promises a message as gentle and reassuring as ever.
   The three-part musical, titled ``Josephine the Short-Neck
Giraffe,'' tells the story of a young giraffe who yearns for a
long, graceful neck like all the other giraffes. She eventually
grows, <PERSON>Fred Rogers</PERSON> confided, ``not on the outside, but on the
important side.''
   ``It's very much like the usual message of the Neighborhood,
that you can be acceptable as you are,'' he said, smiling. ``It's
not so much the outsides of us that are important.''
   A song sung by <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> and her friend Hazel the elephant sums
it up best, according to <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You're much more than a neck, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>. And you're much more
than a trunk, Hazel. A chicken's more than a peck, and there's more
than a smell to a skunk,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> quietly sang during an interview
at <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s WQED-TV, home to his children's programs for the
past 35 years.
   The special week of new programs gets under way <DATE>Monday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Public
Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION> stations with a trip to the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild
Animal Park</LOCATION>, where viewers are introduced to real-life giraffes and
elephants. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION> visits a film processing lab to have
his animal photographs developed.
   The miniseries, which features a cast of 15, elaborate animal
costumes and five sets, runs <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Rogers
gently guides his young audience from one day to the next,
summarizing the main events and hinting at what might lie ahead for
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Neighborhood of Make-Believe</ORGANIZATION>, where animals sing, dance
and play the trombone, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> is befriended by <PERSON>J.R.</PERSON>, a shy
giraffe who overcomes his problems by helping <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> conquer
hers. He accomplishes that with help from Hazel the elephant, who
advises him to ``just let your heart speak.''
   ``There isn't a time that I see the scene in which <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION> talks
and sings with Josephine ... that I haven't gotten chills up my
spine,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said, tapping his right hand against his back.
``And this is something I've worked with for years. There's
something so redemptive about someone who is trying so hard to help
somebody else.''
   Rogers, 61, wrote ``Josephine the Short-Neck Giraffe'' for a
French class assignment at <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>. He
named J.R. the giraffe after fraternity brother <PERSON>John Reardon</PERSON>, who
went on to sing with the Metropolitan Opera and was a frequent
guest on ``Mister Rogers Neighborhood.'' <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON> died a year ago,
and the miniseries is dedicated to him.
   Rogers set the story to music in the late <DATE>1950s</DATE>, and about 1,000
records were pressed. Writer <PERSON>Barry Head</PERSON> transformed ``Josephine the
Short-Neck Giraffe'' into a poem for children in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   For years, <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> tried to have the musical produced on stage or
as an animated film.
   ``I still think it would be great for animation and a stage
production,'' he said. ``But I thought unless we get it out on the
air, I don't think anybody's going to know about it.''
   The story <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> wrote 39 years ago is vastly different from the
musical airing next week. It is the Neighborhood's 13th musical.
   ``At the end of the (original) story, when people are telling
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> that they like her just the way she is, she raises her
head to look at them because she hasn't really heard this message
before and her neck starts to grow. And it grows and grows and
grows until her neck is as tall as everybody else's,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said.
   In the musical, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>'s neck remains short.
   ``I think it shows how much we've grown,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``You
know, you don't have to look like everybody else to be acceptable
and to feel acceptable. And wishes don't always come true.
   ``Because for a year and a day I've been wishing, she sang. That
was one of her first songs. Her wish was for a longer neck, she
thought. But really her wish was to have people like her exactly as
she is. So often what we say we're wishing for isn't necessarily
what is behind the wish. This is very philosophical.''
   Will pre-schoolers be able to grasp such a serious message, even
in such a light-hearted setting?
   ``Maybe not in words, but let their hearts speak to them the way
<PERSON>Hazel</PERSON> said to <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION>, `Just let your heart speak,''' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``I
think that that's the way an awful lot of communication takes
place.''
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   The miniseries comes to ``Mister <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON>'
Neighborhood'' next week, and the show's cardigan-clad creator
promises a message as gentle and reassuring as ever.
   The three-part musical, titled ``Josephine the Short-Neck
Giraffe,'' tells the story of a young giraffe who yearns for a
long, graceful neck like all the other giraffes. She eventually
grows, <PERSON>Fred Rogers</PERSON> confided, ``not on the outside, but on the
important side.''
   ``It's very much like the usual message of the Neighborhood,
that you can be acceptable as you are,'' he said, smiling. ``It's
not so much the outsides of us that are important.''
   A song sung by <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> and her friend Hazel the elephant sums
it up best, according to <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``You're much more than a neck, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>. And you're much more
than a trunk, Hazel. A chicken's more than a peck, and there's more
than a smell to a skunk,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> quietly sang during an interview
at <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s WQED-TV, home to his children's programs for the
past 35 years.
   The special week of new programs gets under way <DATE>Monday</DATE> on <ORGANIZATION>Public
Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION> stations with a trip to the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild
Animal Park</LOCATION>, where viewers are introduced to real-life giraffes and
elephants. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION> visits a film processing lab to have
his animal photographs developed.
   The miniseries, which features a cast of 15, elaborate animal
costumes and five sets, runs <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Rogers
gently guides his young audience from one day to the next,
summarizing the main events and hinting at what might lie ahead for
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Neighborhood of Make-Believe</ORGANIZATION>, where animals sing, dance
and play the trombone, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> is befriended by <PERSON>J.R.</PERSON>, a shy
giraffe who overcomes his problems by helping <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> conquer
hers. He accomplishes that with help from Hazel the elephant, who
advises him to ``just let your heart speak.''
   ``There isn't a time that I see the scene in which <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION> talks
and sings with Josephine ... that I haven't gotten chills up my
spine,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said, tapping his right hand against his back.
``And this is something I've worked with for years. There's
something so redemptive about someone who is trying so hard to help
somebody else.''
   Rogers, 61, wrote ``Josephine the Short-Neck Giraffe'' for a
French class assignment at <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Rollins College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1950</DATE>. He
named J.R. the giraffe after fraternity brother <PERSON>John Reardon</PERSON>, who
went on to sing with the Metropolitan Opera and was a frequent
guest on ``Mister Rogers Neighborhood.'' <PERSON>Reardon</PERSON> died a year ago,
and the miniseries is dedicated to him.
   Rogers set the story to music in the late <DATE>1950s</DATE>, and about 1,000
records were pressed. Writer <PERSON>Barry Head</PERSON> transformed ``Josephine the
Short-Neck Giraffe'' into a poem for children in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   For years, <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> tried to have the musical produced on stage or
as an animated film.
   ``I still think it would be great for animation and a stage
production,'' he said. ``But I thought unless we get it out on the
air, I don't think anybody's going to know about it.''
   The story <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> wrote 39 years ago is vastly different from the
musical airing next week. It is the Neighborhood's 13th musical.
   ``At the end of the (original) story, when people are telling
<PERSON>Josephine</PERSON> that they like her just the way she is, she raises her
head to look at them because she hasn't really heard this message
before and her neck starts to grow. And it grows and grows and
grows until her neck is as tall as everybody else's,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said.
   In the musical, <PERSON>Josephine</PERSON>'s neck remains short.
   ``I think it shows how much we've grown,'' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``You
know, you don't have to look like everybody else to be acceptable
and to feel acceptable. And wishes don't always come true.
   ``Because for a year and a day I've been wishing, she sang. That
was one of her first songs. Her wish was for a longer neck, she
thought. But really her wish was to have people like her exactly as
she is. So often what we say we're wishing for isn't necessarily
what is behind the wish. This is very philosophical.''
   Will pre-schoolers be able to grasp such a serious message, even
in such a light-hearted setting?
   ``Maybe not in words, but let their hearts speak to them the way
<PERSON>Hazel</PERSON> said to <LOCATION>J.R.</LOCATION>, `Just let your heart speak,''' <PERSON>Rogers</PERSON> said. ``I
think that that's the way an awful lot of communication takes
place.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Fri PMs, April 28</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062190-0189 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 236854 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 21, 1990, Thursday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Ventura County Life; Part J; Page 18; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
595 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JUST FOR KIDS; 
</P>
<P>
SANTA BARBARA ZOO; 
</P>
<P>
A TALL STORY; 
</P>
<P>
A DEFORMITY IN A GIRAFFE'S NECK HAS BECOME A LEADING ATTRACTION AT THE SANTA 
BARBARA ZOO. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JANE HULSE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
You've heard the one about the giraffe with a sore throat? Try the one about 
the giraffe with a kink in her neck. 
</P>
<P>
It's no joke to the people at the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION>. They're baffled by the 
very noticeable zigzag halfway up the neck of the 4-year-old female giraffe. 
</P>
<P>
It's so striking that the gangly animal has become one of the newer attractions 
at the zoo. A sign at the giraffe enclosure even points out the bizarre 
deformity and assures observers the animal is in no pain and that zoo 
veterinarians are monitoring her. 
</P>
<P>
"Our veterinarian contacted other giraffe keepers and no one had heard of 
anything like it," said <PERSON>Nancy Hollenbeck</PERSON>, assistant director of the zoo. 
</P>
<P>
To find out conclusively what is wrong would require that the giraffe be 
anesthetized and X-rayed, she said. That poses a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> risk of death, and 
zoo officials decided against it. 
</P>
<P>
"She walks normally, she eats normally, and she shows no sign of pain," said 
<PERSON>Hollenbeck</PERSON>. The current theory is that it's a muscle contraction that grew 
progressively worse until last <DATE>summer</DATE> and now seems to have stabilized. 
</P>
<P>
The giraffe's crooked neck isn't the only new oddity for visitors at the zoo. A 
pair of tapirs recently arrived from <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> to take up residence at 
the zoo. The giant hog-like animals with their long flexible snouts wallow in 
muddy water. 
</P>
<P>
They're far from cute, but the male and female are starting to show an interest 
in each other, and that's good news to zoo officials. The tapirs, relatives of 
the rhinoceros, are an endangered species. 
</P>
<P>
There's always something new to see at the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION> no matter how many 
times you've been there. Because it's a small, compact zoo, it's an easy place 
to take children. The entire 81-acre grounds can be covered in an afternoon. 
</P>
<P>
Located on a hilltop overlooking the ocean, the <LOCATION>Santa Ynez Mountains</LOCATION> and the 
<ORGANIZATION>Clark Bird Refuge</ORGANIZATION>, it's more than a zoo. The garden-like grounds make it a 
horticultural paradise, especially with the addition of a new cactus garden. 
</P>
<P>
Although it's small, the zoo is home to more than 150 kinds of animals -- rare 
animals like the lesser panda, the black and white ruffed lemur, and the golden 
lion tamarin. 
</P>
<P>
It has the usual sampling of elephants, lions, sea lions, monkeys, snakes, and 
a large collection of birds including the rare <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> mynah and a flock of 
flamingos. 
</P>
<P>
One of the newest exhibits is the nocturnal hall, a dark setting for the 
animals of the night who sleep during the day. Special lighting reverses night 
and day for the animals and makes it possible to see the night monkey and 
<PERSON>Geoffroy</PERSON>'s cat as they skitter around glassed-in enclosures that look like 
their natural habitats. 
</P>
<P>
The spookiest exhibit in the nocturnal hall is the re-creation of an old mine 
shaft that is home to a swarm of bats that cling to the beams and flutter 
around as the sounds of the night are piped in. 
</P>
<P>
For children, there's a lot to do at the zoo. A miniature train takes riders on 
a one-mile spin around the zoo grounds. A playground comes in handy when the 
kids need a break from the animals. Or, the children can buy crackers in the 
gift shop and feed the goats in the farmyard exhibit. 
</P>
<P>
WHERE AND WHEN: The <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Zoo</LOCATION> is open daily from <TIME>10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</TIME>, and 
from <DATE>June 11 through Sept. 3</DATE> (Labor Day) from <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m</TIME>. The elephant 
training demonstrations are usually at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> and the sea lions are generally 
fed at <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> Admission is <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> for senior citizens and children 2 
to 12 years, and free for those under 2 years. For more information call 
962-5339. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Children visiting the Santa Barbara Zoo focus their attention on a sea 
lion. Zoo includes a playground area. SCOTT HARRISON / For The Times; Photo, 
COLOR, (COVER) ON THE COVER: Taking care of the elephants at the Santa Barbara 
Zoo: It's a big job, but somebody has to do it. SCOTT HARRISON / For The Times. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081589-0085 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 95034 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 15, 1989, Tuesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 8; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
180 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
29-YEAR-OLD TOPPER THE GIRAFFE PUT TO SLEEP; AT ZOO SINCE 1962 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LORI GRANGE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Topper, a 29-year-old <LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION> giraffe, died <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> when his 
chronic foot problems prompted veterinarians to put him to sleep. 
</P>
<P>
The death of <ORGANIZATION>Topper</ORGANIZATION> leaves <ORGANIZATION>Checkers</ORGANIZATION>, one of his two longtime mates, as the only 
<LOCATION>Uganda</LOCATION> giraffe at the zoo, although three Masai giraffes -- a different 
subspecies -- live in an adjoining enclosure. 
</P>
<P>
Topper was brought to <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> at the age of 2 in <DATE>mid-October, 1962</DATE>, after 
being caught in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>. With Checkers and another mate, Freckles, who died in 
<DATE>1984</DATE>, the 18-foot-tall giraffe sired 21 children, many of whom have populated 
zoos throughout the world. 
</P>
<P>
His son Blackjack was for years the Wild Animal Park's breeding male giraffe. 
He died in <DATE>1987</DATE> at the age of 17. 
</P>
<P>
Topper, who suffered from painful foot problems, on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> was 
visited by several of his longtime keepers. He then was led into the giraffe 
barn, where veterinarians injected him with a lethal dose of a sedative. The 
giraffe collapsed onto hay bales, put in place to cushion his fall. 
</P>
<P>
Topper will be cremated at the zoo after an autopsy. LORI GRANGE 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122390-0201 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 326582 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 23, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 9; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
556 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S NIP AND TUCK TO GET MENAGERIE IN SHAPE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PORTSMOUTH, R.I. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The elephant lost its trunk. The 16-foot-tall giraffe lost its head. 
</P>
<P>
Both injuries were the result of a <DATE>1954</DATE> hurricane that roared through this 
<LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> town. But don't worry: The elephant and giraffe recovered and are 
doing just fine. Unlike most other creatures, these animals can grow back any 
missing parts. 
</P>
<P>
They are members of the menagerie here at <ORGANIZATION>Green Animals</ORGANIZATION>, the oldest topiary 
garden in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Topiary is the art of shaping shrubs and trees into geometric forms, ornamental 
designs, animals, birds, even humans. 
</P>
<P>
Green Animals, a seven-acre estate overlooking <LOCATION>Narragansett Bay</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Portsmouth</LOCATION>, 
has 80 pieces of topiary scattered among the snapdragons, dusty millers, 
verbenas, marigolds, nasturtiums, zinnias, and other flowers and ornamental 
grasses. 
</P>
<P>
Here at <ORGANIZATION>Green Animals</ORGANIZATION>, gardeners have clipped, trimmed and pruned shrubs and 
trees into such shapes as tea cups, spirals, gumdrops, flower baskets, a 
policeman, a man on a horse, a bird bath, a trophy cup, a sail boat, a 
pineapple, an obelisk and an oversized, overstuffed chair. 
</P>
<P>
From the animal world, gardeners have created dogs, peacocks, reindeer, a boar, 
a donkey, a camel, a hen, a lion, an ostrich, a rooster, a swan, a unicorn, an 
alligator, a pig, the elephant, the giraffe and a big, round teddy bear. 
</P>
<P>
Green Animals was started in <DATE>1872</DATE> by the industrialist <PERSON>Thomas Brayton</PERSON>. His 
chief gardener from <DATE>1905</DATE> to <DATE>1945</DATE> was <PERSON>Joseph Carreiro</PERSON>, who was succeeded by his 
son-in-law, <PERSON>George Mendonca</PERSON>, who ran the gardens until <DATE>1985</DATE>, when <PERSON>Ernie Wasson</PERSON> 
took over. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wasson</PERSON>, 40, is a transplanted Californian who received his degree in 
horticulture from <LOCATION>Cal State Humboldt</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The biggest and best topiary gardens in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> are here; <LOCATION>Longwood Gardens</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Ladew Gardens</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Disney World</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON>, a former 
<ORGANIZATION>Longwood Gardens</ORGANIZATION> horticulturist. 
</P>
<P>
When <PERSON>Thomas Brayton</PERSON> died in <DATE>1939</DATE>, his daughter, <PERSON>Alice Brayton</PERSON>, also a 
horticulturist, inherited the gardens. She owned and operated <ORGANIZATION>Green Animals</ORGANIZATION> 
until her death at age 94 in <DATE>1972</DATE>. She left the gardens to the Preservation 
Society of <LOCATION>Newport County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, the organization that owns many of the famous 
old mansions of <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Topiary gardens can be traced . . . to ancient <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. Topiarius in <LOCATION>Latin</LOCATION> means 
garden. Pliny the Younger, who lived from 62 to 110 AD, had a famous topiary 
garden," <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> has many topiary gardens. So does <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. There's a cemetery in the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION> mountains of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> that has 
topiary figures that are mind-boggling. A topiary garden in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> has a herd 
of elephants." 
</P>
<P>
But <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> remains the mecca of topiary gardens. "Almost every garden in 
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> has topiary," said <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON>, who recently returned from a visit to 40 
topiary gardens in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, including one that is 300 years old. 
In <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, topiary gardeners are known as tree barbers. 
</P>
<P>
Walking through <ORGANIZATION>Green Animals</ORGANIZATION> with his trimmer in hand, <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON> stopped to prune 
Spot the dog and again to snip away at the ostrich. A self-described 
perfectionist, <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON> often visits zoos to study animals in order to achieve 
realistic shapes for his garden creations. 
</P>
<P>
All the figures here at <ORGANIZATION>Green Animals</ORGANIZATION> are crafted from growing <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
privet, yew and boxwood. 
</P>
<P>
"Slow-growing shrubbery is, of course, preferred," said <PERSON>Wasson</PERSON> with a grin. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Ernie Wasson is in charge of keeping the sculptures at Green Animals 
topiary garden in shape. Here, a dog gets a little judicious trimming. ; Photo, 
COLOR, Green Animals is the oldest topiary garden in America. The seven-acre 
country estate in Portsmouth, R.I., has 80 pieces of topiary scattered among 
its gardens. Among the works are a few dozen animals, including this giraffe, 
which is tended by chief gardener Ernie Wasson. CHARLES HILLINGER / Los Angeles 
Times; Map, Green Animals, GEORGE CAREY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series; Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
TOPIARY; GARDENS; LANDSCAPING; PLANTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06110120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06110120 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; ENTREE -- A South African club has
been criticized for planning what may be the world's first giraffe barbecue.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ANIMAL; RIGHT; SOUTH-AFRICA; PLANNING; FOOD; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Plans for what is believed to be the world's first giraffe barbecue have drawn
protests from animal-rights groups, according to a report Thursday.;    The
Star newspaper said a social group called Die Afrikaner Klub plans to roast a
2,800-pound giraffe on an 18-foot-long spit May 4. It said it would take 20
hours to cook the animal.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CLUB PLANNING TO THROW A GIRAFFE ON THE BARBIE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The Star said the event appeared to be the world's first giraffe barbecue.;
   <PERSON>Charles Harper</PERSON>, chairman of the club, said there was strong interest in the
event and that the club already had sold 300 tickets at <MONEY>$40</MONEY> each.;   
Barbecues, called braais, are a popular form of entertainment in <LOCATION>South
Africa.</LOCATION>;    Several animal-rights groups denounced the plan. They said it was
irresponsible to kill a wild animal as "a gimmick.";    "It is extremely
barbaric to stick a giraffe on a spit. Surely we are trying to move away from
this type of thing. It totally devalues wildlife," said <PERSON>Christine Berry</PERSON> of
Beauty Without Cruelty.;    But a spokeswoman for the Society for the
Prevention of Cruelty to Animals said the barbecue was not illegal since
giraffes are not on the endangered-animal list. The society said it was no
worse than slaughtering a cow or a sheep.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Johannesburg, South AfRica  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910419  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  19A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  232  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 19, 1991
00110120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901123-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-23-90 0744EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-AZooStory Adv03   11-23 0446</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-A Zoo Story, Adv03,0565</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release Monday PMs Dec 3 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Hard Times at the Buenos Aires Zoo</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICENTE L. PANETTA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Rocky the lion roars with hunger
and Josefa the polar bear sweats in front of a fan. Porota, the
only hippo, stands in a concrete water tank not much larger than
she, looking doleful.
   The <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> zoo is in bad shape.
   About 1,800 animals are crowded onto 47 acres of land. The
budget of <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> a year is hardly enough to feed them, let
alone provide mates or enough living space and caretakers.
   ``The worst is that, a year ago, we had to kill the goats and
cows to feed other animals,'' said <PERSON>Juan Romero</PERSON>, a veterinarian who
is the zoo's director.
   Five years ago, a hippo died after eating a can and its head was
sold for <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> to buy food for other animals. Now, the head is
displayed in a trendy disco called Hippopotamus.
   A flamingo choked to death on a coin tossed by a visitor. Toto
the giraffe died after swallowing a plastic bag. A condor, used to
soaring over mountains, can barely spread his great wings without
hitting the bars of his cage.
   Porota is not the only solitary animal. The zoo also has only
one rhinoceros, giraffe and elephant.
   Replacing animals was too expensive for municipal
administrations that suffered inflation, recession and near
bankruptcy in recent years. An elephant can cost <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY> and a
rhino <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>.
   When it opened 102 years ago, the <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> zoo was an oasis
of shady paths and exotic animals in the noise and pollution of a
city that would grow to a population of 10 million.
   Now, the grass is gone from many enclosures, leaving only dust
and concrete. Some buildings are boarded up and there are few
attendants to remind visitors not to feed the animals, try to catch
them or poke them with sticks.
   Last month, the city leased the zoo to <PERSON>Gerardo Sofovich</PERSON>, a
television host and animal lover, who said he would invest <MONEY>$5
million</MONEY> to buy new animals and spruce the place up.
   Among his plans are building an aquarium and conducting public
education programs about animals and the outdoors.
   Some critics say <ORGANIZATION>Sofovich</ORGANIZATION>'s motives are more mercenary than
philanthropic. They claim his proposed admission fee of about <MONEY>$2</MONEY>
would recoup his investment in a single year and effectively close
the zoo to the poor.
   ``Sofovich ... doesn't want to improve the quality of life of
the animals, but rather enrich himself,'' said <PERSON>Raquel Celoria</PERSON>, who
leads a neighborhood group opposed to the deal.
   The Association for the <ORGANIZATION>Defense of Animal Rights</ORGANIZATION> believes the
number of animals should be reduced by half rather than increased.
   Other opponents cite <ORGANIZATION>Sofovich</ORGANIZATION>'s friendship with President <PERSON>Carlos
Menem</PERSON> and zoo director <PERSON>Romero</PERSON>, a former business partner, in
claiming favoritism.
   Romero responded: ``Those who are protesting now, why didn't
they do anything when the animals were starving?''
   ``People say stupid things,'' Sofovich commented. ``It's not as
if we're going to put in a disco, like some people say. We are
going to do what ... governments could not'' because they didn't
have the money.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday PMs Dec 3</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Rocky the lion roars with hunger
and Josefa the polar bear sweats in front of a fan. Porota, the
only hippo, stands in a concrete water tank not much larger than
she, looking doleful.
   The <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> zoo is in bad shape.
   About 1,800 animals are crowded onto 47 acres of land. The
budget of <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> a year is hardly enough to feed them, let
alone provide mates or enough living space and caretakers.
   ``The worst is that, a year ago, we had to kill the goats and
cows to feed other animals,'' said <PERSON>Juan Romero</PERSON>, a veterinarian who
is the zoo's director.
   Five years ago, a hippo died after eating a can and its head was
sold for <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> to buy food for other animals. Now, the head is
displayed in a trendy disco called Hippopotamus.
   A flamingo choked to death on a coin tossed by a visitor. Toto
the giraffe died after swallowing a plastic bag. A condor, used to
soaring over mountains, can barely spread his great wings without
hitting the bars of his cage.
   Porota is not the only solitary animal. The zoo also has only
one rhinoceros, giraffe and elephant.
   Replacing animals was too expensive for municipal
administrations that suffered inflation, recession and near
bankruptcy in recent years. An elephant can cost <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY> and a
rhino <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>.
   When it opened 102 years ago, the <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> zoo was an oasis
of shady paths and exotic animals in the noise and pollution of a
city that would grow to a population of 10 million.
   Now, the grass is gone from many enclosures, leaving only dust
and concrete. Some buildings are boarded up and there are few
attendants to remind visitors not to feed the animals, try to catch
them or poke them with sticks.
   Last month, the city leased the zoo to <PERSON>Gerardo Sofovich</PERSON>, a
television host and animal lover, who said he would invest <MONEY>$5
million</MONEY> to buy new animals and spruce the place up.
   Among his plans are building an aquarium and conducting public
education programs about animals and the outdoors.
   Some critics say <ORGANIZATION>Sofovich</ORGANIZATION>'s motives are more mercenary than
philanthropic. They claim his proposed admission fee of about <MONEY>$2</MONEY>
would recoup his investment in a single year and effectively close
the zoo to the poor.
   ``Sofovich ... doesn't want to improve the quality of life of
the animals, but rather enrich himself,'' said <PERSON>Raquel Celoria</PERSON>, who
leads a neighborhood group opposed to the deal.
   The Association for the <ORGANIZATION>Defense of Animal Rights</ORGANIZATION> believes the
number of animals should be reduced by half rather than increased.
   Other opponents cite <ORGANIZATION>Sofovich</ORGANIZATION>'s friendship with President <PERSON>Carlos
Menem</PERSON> and zoo director <PERSON>Romero</PERSON>, a former business partner, in
claiming favoritism.
   Romero responded: ``Those who are protesting now, why didn't
they do anything when the animals were starving?''
   ``People say stupid things,'' Sofovich commented. ``It's not as
if we're going to put in a disco, like some people say. We are
going to do what ... governments could not'' because they didn't
have the money.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890911-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-11-89 0117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Zoo'sDoctorDoolittle Bjt   09-11 0679</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zoo's Doctor Doolittle, Bjt,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>When This Doctor Talks to the Animals, They Run for Cover</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX6</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Dr. Mitchell Bush</PERSON> talks to the animals at
the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, they run for cover.
   ``I don't think there's any animal in the zoo that likes me,''
the zoo's chief veterinarian says ruefully.
   The same furry creatures that would have nuzzled the jovial
Doctor <PERSON>Doolittle</PERSON> cringe in fright when <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> appears, even though he
fought a valiant but unsuccessful round-the-clock battle <DATE>last
weekend</DATE> to save the life of the zoo's newest panda cub.
   Hsing-Hsing, the zoo's giant male panda, ``knows my voice,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
said. But when <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> starts talking, <LOCATION>Hsing-Hsing</LOCATION> lumbers down to his
moat and paces worriedly back and forth.
   Cheeky orangutans who cadge soft drinks from zoo visitors
scramble for safety when <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> shows up. The great apes, he says, can
spot him in a crowd of several hundred tourists and squeeze into a
blind corner in their cage, out of harm's way.
   ``My colleagues ask me, `how can you practice if none of your
patients likes you?''' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said.
   ``I don't relish being the villain, but that's just a fact of
life. I've become used to it. The reality of performing my job is
that it's not conducive to making friends with the animals.''
   A friendlier cageside manner might help, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> concedes. But let's
face it, he says. Who can blame the animals? Who would you prefer?
The veterinarian with his probing fingers and hypodermic needles? Or
the keeper who brings food, maid service and small talk into the
cage?
   ``Most animals like their keepers,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> says.
   A big, bearded bear of a Californian, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, 48, came to the
<ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION> from the faculty of <ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins Medical School</ORGANIZATION> early
in <DATE>1972</DATE>, just before <LOCATION>Hsing-Hsing</LOCATION> and his panda mate, Ling-Ling,
arrived from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> as a gift to President <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON> for the American
people.
   Over the years, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has presided over most of Ling-Ling's
heartbreaking attempts to breed successfully in captivity. She has
lost five cubs since <DATE>1983</DATE>, most of them victims of their mother's
recurring kidney or uterine infections.
   The latest cub, an unnamed male, died <DATE>last Sunday</DATE> after 39 hours
of fighting an infection transmitted by Ling-Ling. Assisted by a
dozen or more zoo veterinarians and pediatric specialists from
nearby <ORGANIZATION>Children's Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> injected the premature cub with
antibiotics and a serum containing <LOCATION>Hsing-Hsing</LOCATION>'s antibodies to
bolster its fragile immune system.
   The cub, which weighed only 3.1 ounces at birth, was removed from
its 250-pound mother and placed in an oxygen-rich incubator. There
it was fed a special formula through a tube into its stomach and
cuddled by a rubber glove filled with warm water to simulate
Ling-Ling's motherly paw.
   ``Every effort was made to pull this cub through its illness,''
said zoo director <PERSON>Michael Robinson</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> says the giant panda couple probably will be mating early
next <DATE>spring</DATE>, and once again he'll be crossing his fingers.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is working seven days a week treating everything
from elephants and rhinos to tiny hairy-footed hamsters. ``It seems
like one thing after another,'' he says.
   Among his more memorable challenges were performing a root canal
on a polar bear and playing midwife to a pregnant bongo, an African
forest antelope that tips the scales at 600 pounds and requires
three operating tables to lie on. ``A very stressful procedure,''
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> says.
   Of all his animals, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> says the bears are his happiest
patients. ``Bears just seem to go on and on and on, and they never
give us any problem,'' he said. The most difficult to treat are
giraffes, which tower 16 to 18 feet and risk injury or death when
they fall to the ground under anesthesia, even with ropes erected as
a safety net.
   How does he treat a giraffe for a sore throat?
   ``With benign neglect,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> replied. ``You very rarely hear a
giraffe get vocal, except when they're young. I haven't heard them
say a thing, so I assume there's no complaint.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891213-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-89 0436EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-People-Jackson-Fire     12-13 0159</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-People-Jackson-Fire,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retransmits a0476 to fix garbled summary line</HEAD>
<HEAD>Fire at Michael Jackson's Giraffe Barn Causes $300,000 in Damage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A giraffe barn on pop music
superstar <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON>'s ranch went up in flames, but the
animals were evacuated safely, authorities said.
   Firefighters on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> also kept flames from reaching a nearby
animal compound and chimpanzee house at the ranch in the <LOCATION>Santa Ynez
Mountains</LOCATION>, northwest of <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, officials said.
   When firefighters reached the remote ranch, the barn was
destroyed and the three giraffes kept there already were evacuated,
said Capt. <PERSON>Charlie Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Barbara County Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman.
   Jackson, whose menagerie includes a chimpanzee named Bubbles,
ostriches, llamas and boa constrictors, was not at the ranch at the
time, said a spokesman for the singer.
   The blaze left an estimated <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> in damage.
   The cause of the fire was under investigation, but it was
believed to have been accidentally ignited, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072289-0117 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 85512 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 22, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 12; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1736 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WILDLIFE -- UP CLOSE 'N' PERSONAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ANNE Z. COOKE 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Once upon a time, oh best beloved, there was a summer school for all the wild 
animals of the field and forest, veldt and savanna, water hole and river 
bottom. 
</P>
<P>
The school was at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> east of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, where 250 
animal species, 47 of them endangered, roam over 700 spacious acres in the dry, 
sunny <LOCATION>San Pasqual Valley</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <DATE>summer</DATE> school was for the birds -- and for the tigers, gorillas, 
wildebeests, rhinos and, yes, even for weak and puny man cubs. And for their 
parents, too. But at this school, the animals were the teachers and the 
students were the humans. 
</P>
<P>
The school was such a success and the humans learned so quickly that the 
animals got together and voted to continue the program. (Let the record show 
that the giraffes had to be bribed with carrots and that <PERSON>Gainda</PERSON>, the Indian 
rhinoceros, demanded more quality petting time.) 
</P>
<P>
So once again this <DATE>summer</DATE>, from now through <DATE>August</DATE>, the Wild Animal Park is 
offering one-, two-, three- and five-morning classes for youngsters from Grade 
1 through high school. The emphasis is on hands-on learning. Students join 
teachers, staff biologists and keepers to pet, feed, count, look at, listen to 
and -- most important -- learn about the creatures whose world we share. 
</P>
<P>
And for adults? They haven't been forgotten. From now through <DATE>September</DATE>, animal 
admirers and wildlife photographers ages 12 and up can sign up for special 
family and photo caravan safaris into the huge exhibits themselves. 
</P>
<P>
These open-air, bumpy expeditions, with 10 guests and two guides standing in 
the back of a truck, spend a couple of hours driving on the dirt roads through 
four of the park's five major habitats, the East and South African, and the 
<LOCATION>Asian Plains</LOCATION> and Asian Waterhole, about 320 acres in all. The guides stop the 
truck at various places to talk about the different animals and hand out 
carrots and apples. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
A Taste of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
"The caravans are a little taste of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Larry Killmar</PERSON>, curator of 
mammals. "They're not so rugged or stressful as a safari in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, but they 
get the people down close." 
</P>
<P>
Right! One minute you're adjusting your sunglasses, the next you're looking up 
to see three tons of beady-eyed rhino barreling up to the truck. Then he -- or 
she -- stops and thrusts that huge wrinkled face and rubbery lips right next to 
yours. 
</P>
<P>
You may want to shriek or faint. Yech -- kissed by a rhino! Instead, hand over 
an apple and grab your camera. This is a rare chance to shoot wildlife photos 
from a distance of six inches. 
</P>
<P>
Bring your telephoto lens too, to snap candids of this year's crop of shy 
babies. Says <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON>, who has been with the park since it opened in <DATE>1972</DATE>: 
"<DATE>April</DATE> to <DATE>August</DATE> is the heavy calving season. We can have as many as eight 
births in a day -- they happen right out there in the exhibits." 
</P>
<P>
If feeding fruit to rhinos seems unnatural when the park's goal is to create an 
authentic living setting for the animals, you are right. And when excessive 
contact with humans does interfere with the animals' social group behavior, 
park biologists eschew it. 
</P>
<P>
But, <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON> says, offering treats to unpredictable and easily spooked Indian 
rhinos is the safest way to manage these 6,000-pound creatures. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Familiarity Breeds Friendship 
</P>
<P>
"From day one we get the rhino calves used to touching by the keepers," <PERSON>Killmar</PERSON> 
says. "If you give them apples and carrots and goodies, they'll do anything for 
you. This allows us to move them around -- even crate them -- without using any 
tranquilizers." 
</P>
<P>
Each caravan has its own surprises. On a recent outing, Wild Animal Park 
spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> spotted a newly laid ostrich egg lying on the muddy river 
bank. The eggs are a favorite target for hawks, so he stopped to collect it. 
</P>
<P>
The visitors handed it around and agreed it felt large, heavy and very hard. 
Just the right size for an omelet, someone commented. "Do you know how to cook 
an ostrich egg?" Hanscom asked. "You put the egg and a rock in a pot of boiling 
water. When the rock's done, so is the egg." 
</P>
<P>
Youngsters coming to the park from the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> area usually are dropped off 
by their parents or ride the bus from <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, but residents of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
probably will find that the park is too far for a daily drive. 
</P>
<P>
A solution is to enroll the child in a one-day class (held each <DATE>Thursday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME>) and combine it with an all-day family visit to the park. Human cubs, 
grades one through six, join a "Wild Walkabout," visiting koalas and kangaroos 
and all the other strange fauna and flora from the Down Under continent, while 
students in grades seven to 12 enroll in the class called "Close Enough to 
Touch," similar to the photo caravans. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
For Budding Zoologists 
</P>
<P>
The older students actually accompany the keepers into the exhibits, through 
double-chain-link gates to help feed and count the zebras and gazelles and feel 
the giraffe's warm breath when it bends down for a carrot. 
</P>
<P>
If a budding zoologist begs for a three-day class, consider a mini-vacation for 
the family at one of the golf and leisure resorts east of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> or motel 
accommodations in that area. 
</P>
<P>
Start a day at the Wild Animal Park with a ride on the <PERSON>Wgasa Bush</PERSON> Line 
monorail. The monorail runs around the hills above the major habitats and 
provides an overview of the 2,500 animals that live behind special fencing 
called "inrigging." 
</P>
<P>
The fencing isn't all that tall, but it has a tremendous overhang at the top. 
As our monorail tour guide <PERSON>Becky Boomer</PERSON> announced: "The animals get up next to 
the fence and look up. When they see something over their heads, they think 
they can't jump out." 
</P>
<P>
On the ride, keep an eye out for a family of wild golden eagles circling 
overhead. The eagles are a few of the wild birds that have taken up residence 
in the surrounding hilltops and are getting fat on the gophers and mice that 
help themselves to animal feed. 
</P>
<P>
"We call them locals," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> says, explaining that the Wild Animal Park 
spends between <MONEY>$41,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$46,000</MONEY> monthly on animal food. The grocery bill 
would be higher, but the park actually grows some of its own browse food, such 
as eucalyptus, on the park's 1,800 acres. 
</P>
<P>
After the ride, visitors walk around the 1 1/4-mile <ORGANIZATION>Kilimanjaro Trail</ORGANIZATION> for a 
closer look into the special, smaller exhibits: the <LOCATION>Sumatran</LOCATION> tiger's woody 
hollow, the elephant enclosure, the lowland gorilla's lair and the cheetah's 
grassy plain. The animals are fascinating to watch, but their presence points 
to the Wild Animal Park's real purpose. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Protective Coloration 
</P>
<P>
The park's protective coloration -- the <LOCATION>Nairobi Village</LOCATION>'s thatched snack bar, 
outdoor cafe, T-shirt shop, souvenir store, live animal shows, the petting 
kraal -- is designed like a theme park to attract humans. But, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> says, 
the park's real purpose is 'to breed endangered species, and to study breeding 
problems of animals in captivity." 
</P>
<P>
For instance, he says, researchers discovered that flamingos wouldn't lay 
fertilized eggs unless there were at least 100 birds in the flock. "It's the 
number that seems to click the hormones and make them go," he says. 
</P>
<P>
"And the Southern White Rhino . . . for years, the two in the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo 
just ignored each other. Then they brought 20 females out here to the animal 
park and moved the male out here to retire, but all he needed was space and a 
harem. In 11 years, he sired 65 calves." 
</P>
<P>
However, numbers aren't always a determining factor. There are cheetahs in the 
wilds, but genetic studies reveal that they're very inbred, probably because 
they live in isolated family groups. As a result, many females are sterile or 
there's a high infant mortality. So the park is breeding cheetahs with better 
genes, then making them available to other zoos. 
</P>
<P>
The park's <DATE>summer</DATE> programs are scheduled almost every day of the week. Photo 
caravans run on <DATE>Wednesday, Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE> afternoons from <DATE>May 
through September</DATE>. Groups of 10 booking together can go any day. Each caravan 
is 1 3/4 hours long; tickets are <MONEY>$50</MONEY> for adults 16 and older and <MONEY>$35</MONEY> for 
children 12-15 with an adult. Children under 12 are not permitted on this 
caravan. The East African and the Asian Plains caravan leaves at <TIME>2:30 p.m</TIME>. The 
caravan to the South African habitat and the Asian Waterhole leaves at <TIME>4:30 
p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
You can take both tours for a full 3 1/2-hour safari; <MONEY>$75</MONEY> for adults and <MONEY>$50</MONEY> 
for children. Because <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION> members get a big discount 
on all special tours, it may be possible to save money by joining the zoo at 
the time you enroll. The photo caravans always are sold out and must be booked 
in advance. 
</P>
<P>
The Family Caravans are similar to photo caravans but emphasize learning about 
and visiting family groups of animals rather than photography. They run <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
evenings from 5:30 to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> Tickets are <MONEY>$55</MONEY> for one adult with one child, and 
<MONEY>$80</MONEY> for one adult with two children. Children must be 8 or older and be with an 
adult. 
</P>
<P>
The five-day <DATE>summer</DATE> school runs <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE> from 9 to <TIME>11:30 a.m.</TIME>, 
with a separate class for each grade level from 1 to 9. The three-day 
summer-school program runs <DATE>Monday, Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1 
p.m</TIME>. The fee is <MONEY>$50</MONEY> and five different classes serve different grade levels. 
</P>
<P>
The one-day program runs each <DATE>Thursday</DATE> from <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> and costs <MONEY>$22</MONEY> 
to <MONEY>$35</MONEY>. Different classes are designed for three age groups. 
</P>
<P>
The "Keeper Connection" is a two-session career exploration class for 
10th-to-12th graders who are considering animal-related careers. The fee is 
<MONEY>$50</MONEY>; the first session in <DATE>August</DATE> is on the 11th, and participants have a choice 
for the second second sesssion of any day between <DATE>Aug. 14</DATE> and 18. 
</P>
<P>
You can enroll by telephone and pay by credit card. Call the <ORGANIZATION>Summer School 
Hotline</ORGANIZATION> at (619) 740-9383, or the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> at (619) 236-0163. You also can 
write to the <ORGANIZATION>Summer School</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 551, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 
92112-0551, but expect a several-week processing delay. 
</P>
<P>
Wild Animal Park hours are <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> through <DATE>Sept. 4</DATE> (Labor Day), and <TIME>9 
a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> after. The park is 30 miles north of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on Interstate 15, 
then east on Highway 78. From <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> take Interstate 5 south to <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>, 
then <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 78 east to the park. A ticket package (entrance, monorail ride, 
animal shows and exhibits) is <MONEY>$12.95</MONEY> for adults, <MONEY>$6.20</MONEY> for ages 3-15, ages 2 
and under free. Stroller and wheelchair rentals are available. No pets, please; 
the wild animals frown on it. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Rubbernecking giraffe at Wild Animal Park. ; Photo, Top, wild animals 
greet visitors on photo safari who have traveled through San Diego Animal Park 
on a pickup truck. Above, Sunny Verghese gets chummy with heavyweight rhino 
named Gainda. ; Photo, Giraffe investigates the hand of friendship at animal 
park. ANNE Z. COOKE; PAUL COOKE 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAN DIEGO WILD ANIMAL PARK; WILDLIFE REFUGES; ZOOS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890610-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-89 1518EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BrightandBrief     06-10 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>Bright and Brief</SECOND>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Reba Goins</PERSON> has never played basketball,
much less shot a free throw in front of television cameras and a
crowd of thousands, but she'll have <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> at stake when she steps
to the line at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Forum this week.
   The winner of a drawing sponsored by a snack-food maker, <PERSON>Mrs.
Goins</PERSON>, 57, will receive <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> for each of five free throw attempts
she makes during halftime at Game 4 of the Lakers-Pistons NBA
Championship playoff game <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Even if <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> misses all five free throws, she will still
take home <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>.
   Hoping for the best, she is undergoing a crash course in
free-throw shooting under the watchful eye of her son-in-law at a
local elementary school gymnasium.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said she shot about 50 free throws <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   How many did she make?
   ``Oh, two or three,'' she said.
   Still, she's been lucky so far, as evidenced by the fact that she
made the contest at all.
   ``I was just doing my shopping and saw an entry form and filled
it out,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said. ``Then, <DATE>last Saturday</DATE>, I received a
letter by <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> telling me I had won. They (contest
sponsors) called <DATE>Monday</DATE> to see if I was going and I told them `yes'
in a hurry.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Reba Goins</PERSON> has never played basketball,
much less shot a free throw in front of television cameras and a
crowd of thousands, but she'll have <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> at stake when she steps
to the line at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Forum this week.
   The winner of a drawing sponsored by a snack-food maker, <PERSON>Mrs.
Goins</PERSON>, 57, will receive <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> for each of five free throw attempts
she makes during halftime at Game 4 of the Lakers-Pistons NBA
Championship playoff game <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Even if <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> misses all five free throws, she will still
take home <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>.
   Hoping for the best, she is undergoing a crash course in
free-throw shooting under the watchful eye of her son-in-law at a
local elementary school gymnasium.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said she shot about 50 free throws <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   How many did she make?
   ``Oh, two or three,'' she said.
   Still, she's been lucky so far, as evidenced by the fact that she
made the contest at all.
   ``I was just doing my shopping and saw an entry form and filled
it out,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said. ``Then, <DATE>last Saturday</DATE>, I received a
letter by <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> telling me I had won. They (contest
sponsors) called <DATE>Monday</DATE> to see if I was going and I told them `yes'
in a hurry.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890610-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-10-89 1522EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     06-10 0607</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0629</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting a0498 to restore slugline.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CLEVELAND, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Reba Goins</PERSON> has never played basketball,
much less shot a free throw in front of television cameras and a
crowd of thousands, but she'll have <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> at stake when she steps
to the line at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Forum this week.
   The winner of a drawing sponsored by a snack-food maker, <PERSON>Mrs.
Goins</PERSON>, 57, will receive <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> for each of five free throw attempts
she makes during halftime at Game 4 of the Lakers-Pistons NBA
Championship playoff game <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Even if <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> misses all five free throws, she will still
take home <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>.
   Hoping for the best, she is undergoing a crash course in
free-throw shooting under the watchful eye of her son-in-law at a
local elementary school gymnasium.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said she shot about 50 free throws <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   How many did she make?
   ``Oh, two or three,'' she said.
   Still, she's been lucky so far, as evidenced by the fact that she
made the contest at all.
   ``I was just doing my shopping and saw an entry form and filled
it out,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said. ``Then, <DATE>last Saturday</DATE>, I received a
letter by <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> telling me I had won. They (contest
sponsors) called <DATE>Monday</DATE> to see if I was going and I told them `yes'
in a hurry.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Reba Goins</PERSON> has never played basketball,
much less shot a free throw in front of television cameras and a
crowd of thousands, but she'll have <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> at stake when she steps
to the line at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Forum this week.
   The winner of a drawing sponsored by a snack-food maker, <PERSON>Mrs.
Goins</PERSON>, 57, will receive <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> for each of five free throw attempts
she makes during halftime at Game 4 of the Lakers-Pistons NBA
Championship playoff game <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Even if <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> misses all five free throws, she will still
take home <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>.
   Hoping for the best, she is undergoing a crash course in
free-throw shooting under the watchful eye of her son-in-law at a
local elementary school gymnasium.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said she shot about 50 free throws <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   How many did she make?
   ``Oh, two or three,'' she said.
   Still, she's been lucky so far, as evidenced by the fact that she
made the contest at all.
   ``I was just doing my shopping and saw an entry form and filled
it out,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Goins</PERSON> said. ``Then, <DATE>last Saturday</DATE>, I received a
letter by <ORGANIZATION>Federal Express</ORGANIZATION> telling me I had won. They (contest
sponsors) called <DATE>Monday</DATE> to see if I was going and I told them `yes'
in a hurry.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06059234 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06059234 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Knight-Ridder News Service; Hunter Willie Phillips stands at the
buffalo fence, which already has killed many wild animals  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOTSWANA; GOVERNMENT; POLICY; CHANGE; ANIMAL; ZONING; EQUIPMENT; .....;
CONTROVERSY; ENVIRONMENT; ORGANIZATION; OPPOSE; DAMAGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SEVERAL HUNDRED feet below, a rust-colored scar cuts like a razor through the
glistening Okovanggo swamps. Willie Phillips taps a leathery finger on the
airplane window.;    "There's the new buffalo fence," the big-game hunter
said. "Come back here next spring, and you'll see dead animals all along it."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BOTSWANA'S GIANT FENCE IS KILLING WILDLIFE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The fence runs along the northwest rim of the Okovanggo, an
8,500-square-mile wilderness teeming with game in <LOCATION>northwest Botswana</LOCATION>, where
the <LOCATION>Okovanggo River</LOCATION> makes a fan-shaped inland delta before dying in the sands
of the <ORGANIZATION>Kalahari Desert.</ORGANIZATION>;    Besides cutting migration routes for some of the
<ORGANIZATION>Okovanggo</ORGANIZATION>'s rarest herds, the "buffalo fence" under construction also places
outside the fence one of the wildest and most remote sections of the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>,
the <LOCATION>Magwegqana</LOCATION> peninsula.;     'It's a paradise';    "It's a paradise, I'm
telling you, a paradise," <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said. "And it'll all be cattle country
now.";    The fence is the latest part of a long-range plan by the government
to cordon this sprawling, desert nation into cattle and wildlife zones.;   
The fences already have opened massive tracts of formerly wild country to
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s cattle industry. They also have killed tens of thousands of wild
animals -- giraffe, springbok, zebra, eland -- that become tangled in the
sharp wires as they follow their centuries-old migrating routes. In the <DATE>last
decade</DATE>, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s population of 300,000 wildebeest was reduced to a little
more than 1,000; they either died in the fences or of thirst in their
water-poor enclaves.;     Government defends fences;    Government officials
defend the program as necessary to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s lucrative beef trade.
Environmentalists, they say, exaggerate the threat and underestimate the
ability of wildlife to adapt to the fences.;    <PERSON>Ove Nielsen</PERSON>, chairman of the
<ORGANIZATION>Botswana Meat Commission</ORGANIZATION>, complains that foreigners are trying to turn his
country into "a gigantic zoo.";    <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, long considered one of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s
most conservation-minded countries, recently has come under increasing attack
from international environmental groups -- partly because of the new fences
and partly for the proposed dredging of 15 miles of river leading out of the
swamps.;     Dredging draws attention;    The dredging, intended to tap the
<ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>'s precious water, has drawn more international attention in recent
weeks. <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> threatened to boycott <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s diamond industry if the
dredging isn't stopped. But many people think the buffalo fence poses the
greater threat.;    "As far as I'm concerned, this is worse than the
dredging," said one environmentalist in <LOCATION>Gaborone</LOCATION>, the capital.;    <ORGANIZATION>Coert Van
Hasselt</ORGANIZATION>, a lawyer based in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, represents a coalition of
environmental groups threatening to launch a global boycott of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s beef
industry because of the fences.;    One concern is the timing of the
construction. Many of the Okovanggo's animals have left the swamp area to
migrate north toward the <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> highlands, where the rains begin in early
<DATE>January</DATE>. If the fence is finished in the next few months, environmentalists
argue, these animals will be caught outside.;     Delay promised;    In
response, the <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> government promised only to plant the tall, wooden
posts for the fence, but to hold off stringing the steel wire until the rains
subside and the animals return to the central Okovanggo.;    But a <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>
investigator said this month that an inspection showed that the wire was being
put in place and that the new fence's first casualty -- a young giraffe -- had
been found tangled and dead along one completed stretch.;    To
environmentalists, it is as though one of the world's greatest natural
treasures is being sacrificed for the benefit of a handful of major cattle
owners.;    To many Botswanans -- and to many landowners throughout <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> --
it is as though they are being asked to remain primitive and poor so
well-heeled foreigners will have a place to come on vacation.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RICK LYMAN, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Okovanggo Delta, Botswana  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910228  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  638  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 28, 1991
00059234,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     06-13 0960</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,1004</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WICHITA, Kan. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>STAUNTON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Olympic ice skater <PERSON>Tai Babilonia</PERSON> says she
is ready to return to the rink, nine months after a suicide attempt
during a time she ``hit rock bottom.''
   Miss Babilonia posed with her skating partner <PERSON>Randy Gardner</PERSON> in
Times Square on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to announce their professional return
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at a show in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   ``I'm excited about being back with my partner andscared to death
about performing again,'' said <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>. ``But it was my
decision to come back. I missed it.''
   Nine months ago, <LOCATION>Miss Babilonia</LOCATION>, 29, tried to kill herself by
taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
   <PERSON>Miss Babilonia</PERSON>, who has been skating since she was 7 years old,
said she was ``burnt out'' on skating. ``I had taken on too much,
more work than I can handle, and that just sort of caught up with
me,'' she said.
   Miss <PERSON>Babilonia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> won the world figure skating title in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1979</DATE>. The pair had to drop out of the <DATE>1980</DATE>
Olympic Winter Games in <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, when <PERSON>Gardner</PERSON> suffered a
leg injury.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910604-0003
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910604-0003.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Zoo Story: When Bad Things Happen to Good Beasts
   ----
   By Amy Gamerman
</HL>
<DATE>
06/04/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A16
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- Judy, a Baringo giraffe at Chicago's Lincoln
Park Zoo, has twisted her ankle. Over at the St. Louis Zoo, a
King penguin is limping from a torn toenail. An elephant at
Washington's National Zoo is down in the mouth with an
impacted tooth. And at the San Diego Zoo, a Gila monster is
feeling as hideous as it looks, thanks to a nasty mouth
infection.
   Zoo animals, like the people who come to gawk at them, get
sick once in a while. The difference is that their doctors
never charge them and sometimes they even make house calls.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "I would say our health plan is as good as Blue Cross,"
said <PERSON>Dr. Robert A. Cook</PERSON>, chief veterinarian for the <ORGANIZATION>New York
Zoological Society</ORGANIZATION>, which encompasses the <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, the
Central Park Zoo and the <LOCATION>New York Aquarium</LOCATION>. "Dental's
included . . . there's no deductible."
   Dr. <ORGANIZATION>Cook's Animal Health Center</ORGANIZATION>, a handsome two-story
building on the grounds of the <LOCATION>Bronx Zoo</LOCATION>, is one of the
biggest zoo hospitals in the country. The health center
oversees the well-being of the society's more than 9,000
animals. If a recent visit is any indication, members of this
zoological health plan receive better medical care than most
of their <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION> neighbors -- the human ones, that is.
   It starts with a no-holds-barred checkup for every
newcomer. A recent morning found <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> busy arranging for
the arrival of a group of tamarin monkeys from another zoo,
which would stay at the clinic for a month-long quarantine
period.
   "They'll undergo TB tests, chest X-rays,
electrocardiogram, <ORGANIZATION>CBC</ORGANIZATION> {complete blood count}, a biochemical
profile, a viral screen, a physical exam-plus dental work, if
they need it," said <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>, an easy-going fellow with a
cage-side manner soothing to tamarins and tapirs alike.
   His day had started, like most, with the <TIME>7:30 a.m.</TIME> rounds
accompanied by the center's two other veterinary clinicians.
Apart from the quarantined animals -- a group of deer, some
caged sugar gliders (marsupials from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>) and a <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>
rat bound for the zoo's <ORGANIZATION>Mouse House</ORGANIZATION> -- the clinic's patients
that day included a diabetic monkey, an orphaned baby black
buck (the spiral-horned Indian antelope), a
bedraggled-looking <PERSON>Shama</PERSON> thrush suffering from feather loss,
and <PERSON>Whoopi</PERSON>, an ailing penguin from the <LOCATION>New York Aquarium</LOCATION>.
   "She had lost a lot of weight and wasn't keeping food down
-- she has a fungal infection," said <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>. "She's been on
experimental treatment for about two months."
   Grabbing a walkie-talkie, <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> set out on a quick tour
of the wards -- a series of indoor/outdoor cages, clean
despite the healthy zoo stench. Whoopi was poking around her
outdoor enclosure as a veterinary technician tried to
interest her in a fish.
   "I just repeated an endoscopy -- a flexible fiberoptic
examination of the stomach -- on her yesterday," said <PERSON>Dr.
Cook</PERSON>.
   And how exactly does one go about examining the stomach of
a penguin? In the clinic's large surgery, which boasts an
operating table, electrocardiograph unit and ultrasound
machine, <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> showed off his tool of choice.
   "This is used for looking at the colon of humans. We use
it for looking at the stomachs of animals," he said. "Most of
our equipment comes from ordinary hospitals."
   The king-sized operating table with hydraulic lifts is
another matter. The veterinary team uses it for working on
hefty patients such as a gorilla or zebra. Anything bigger --
a camel, for instance -- can simply be laid out on the
surgery floor. And for operating on newborn birds and other
diminutive patients, veterinarians rely on microscopes and
microsurgical tools.
   Keeping animals anesthetized during surgery requires even
more specialized equipment. A four-foot-long endotracheal
tube is used on giraffes' throats, and gas masks of all
shapes and sizes line one wall, including a test-tube-sized
mask used on snakes and small birds. To put a sea lion under,
<PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>'s team fashioned a gas mask from a plastic
disinfectant jug.
   The biggest challenge zoo vets may face is getting the
invalid to the hospital. When it comes to dealing with a
stubborn patient -- a Siberian tiger, say -- the clinic
boasts a veritable arsenal of scoped rifles, blowpipes and
pole syringes -- all of which can be used to anesthetize
animals from a safe distance. In the clinic's pharmacy, <PERSON>Dr.
Cook</PERSON> pulled out a paper target.
   "Every once in a while I practice on the rifle range," he
said. "You have to be pretty good."
   The knocked-out animals are then carried over to the
clinic on stretchers or boards, where vets take advantage of
the animal's anesthetized state to do a full physical
checkup, do a little root canal, even clean their teeth.
   Not that every animal makes it to the clinic. Say you've
got a sick elephant. "We'd go to the elephant," <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>
said, showing off a full array of portable hospital equipment
-- including an X-ray machine.
   He also goes to the whales. On a recent weekday, <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>
made his house calls at the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Aquarium -- which he or
a colleague will visit twice a week, along with the <ORGANIZATION>Central
Park Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. First on the list was <ORGANIZATION>Nuka</ORGANIZATION>, a 1,500-pound walrus
with an eye infection. <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Nuka</ORGANIZATION> are old
acquaintances: He had guided her through a painful tusk
infection requiring four operations in one year.
   Now, a tuskless <ORGANIZATION>Nuka</ORGANIZATION> bounded up out of her pool to greet
her trainer, <PERSON>Martha Saif</PERSON>, a lanky blonde in T-shirt and
shorts who came with bucket of fish and a bottle of eyedrops.
<PERSON>Ms. Saif</PERSON> had been administering the drops several times a day
on the instructions of <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> and a veterinary
ophthalmologist.
   "She's come a long way as far as that eye goes," <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>
said, as <ORGANIZATION>Nuka</ORGANIZATION> snuffled up squid after patiently enduring a
quick examination.
   Since most of the sea mammals at the aquarium are trained,
these examinations are relatively painless for doctor and
patient alike. It would be hard to imagine a better patient
than <PERSON>Marina</PERSON>, a beluga whale with a scraped eye, who
obediently pulled up at poolside and lifted her head over the
edge on <PERSON>Ms. Saif</PERSON>'s instruction.
   "She's much improved -- the area of redness has cleared up
quite a bit," <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> said, as <PERSON>Ms. Saif</PERSON> put in the whale's
eye ointment. After receiving several fish as a reward,
<PERSON>Marina</PERSON> placidly presented her tail for <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> to take a
blood sample.
   "That's terrific, <LOCATION>Marina</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Ms. Saif</PERSON>, sounding a lot
like the parent of a child getting its finger pricked, as <PERSON>Dr.
Cook</PERSON> carefully inserted a butterfly needle.
   A dolphin with some minor scrapes on its tail and a seal
with a cut snout rounded out <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON>'s visit. Occasionally,
he'll even work on fish. "I did multiple surgery on a lung
fish with cancer," he said modestly.
   But veterinary skill and dedication notwithstanding, zoo
patients do eventually go the way of all flesh. While showing
a visitor out of the <ORGANIZATION>Animal Health Center</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> paused to
ask a technician to turn on a fan.
   "A geriatric antelope passed away in the night," he
explained, as a sickly odor spread down the corridor from the
necropsy room, where pathologists conduct a full autopsy on
every deceased animal.
   The departed are gone but not forgotten. Zoo pathologists
see to it, by preserving a piece of all the animal's organs
in a large jar for future research. A back room in the clinic
is a veritable library of animal organs, with jars going back
as far as 20 years. In a bizarre twist, death has made
neighbors of "<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s Hartebeest, 5-691," "Hispaniolan Boa,
<DATE>'87</DATE>" and "Sea Lion, 10-10-90" -- all of which are grouped on
neighboring shelves, a stone's throw from the bottled
reproductive tract of a wisent (the nearly extinct European
bison).
   So after spending a 12-hour day in such exotic company --
living and dead -- what kind of pet does <PERSON>Dr. Cook</PERSON> go home to?
A tame lion cub, perhaps, or a lama tethered in his backyard?
   "A parrot," he said. "My wife's allergic to cats and
dogs."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870713-0046 </DOCNO>
<HL> A Lovelorn Parakeet,
Lame Horse Find Ills
Were All in the Bones
---
Chiropractic for Animals Is
A Fast-Growing Specialty;
Some Vets Are Skeptical
---
By Roger Ricklefs
<DD> 07/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> BUFFALO GROVE, Ill.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For a chiropractor, manipulating the bones in the neck may be strictly routine. 
But when the patient is a giraffe, it is a little tougher. 

   <PERSON>Daniel R. Kamen</PERSON>, a chiropractor here, first climbed up an 11-foot ladder. 
Then he placed his hands on the giraffe's neck. 

   Whack! 
The giraffe swung its powerful neck against <PERSON>Mr. Kamen</PERSON> and knocked him to the ground. 
"I felt ridiculous, but I wanted to see if it could be done," the 31-year-old chiropractor says. 

   Touchy giraffes are just one problem facing practitioners of one of the medical world's faster-growing specialties, animal chiropractic. 
A growing number of chiropractors are manipulating (or, as they put it, "adjusting") the bones of horses, dogs, cats, llamas and parakeets. 

   At least as a sideline, "several hundred" chiropractors now look at Fido as well as his owner, estimates <PERSON>Werner E. Hoff</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Trenton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, chiropractor. 
This compares with perhaps a dozen when he first tackled an animal's bad back a decade ago, <PERSON>Mr. Hoff</PERSON> says. 

   A few chiropractors now practice on animals full time, including several who are also veterinarians. 
<PERSON>Mr. Kamen</PERSON> has even started an association of animal chiropractic -- called "Animals Crackers." 

   The animal-chiropractic field, however, hasn't been universally acclaimed. 
"We aren't aware of any body of scientific literature established to prove that chiropractic is useful or not useful for animals," says <PERSON>Arthur Freeman</PERSON>, the executive vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Veterinary Medical Association</ORGANIZATION>. 
"I don't think veterinary chiropractic has been around long enough," <PERSON>Dr. Freeman</PERSON> adds. 

   Whatever the strictures, animal chiropractors say they are getting results -- even where traditional veterinarians flopped. 
For instance, an anorexic dog regained its appetite after chiropractic relieved its hind-leg lameness, says <PERSON>Sharon L. Willoughby</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Port Byron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, chiropractor-veterinarian. 

   <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> says her work has restored a female parakeet's love life. 
Following a neck injury, the patient sat in the bottom of her cage, didn't eat and didn't move about. 
Her cage-mate -- a male -- fed her by dropping food in her mouth. 

   "Her bones were so tiny that when I adjusted her neck, I thought I had broken it," <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> says. 
But within minutes, the invalid started turning her neck to preen her feathers. 
Though she had never laid an egg before, she soon laid and hatched six. 
"Chiropractic made her much more amorous," <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> says. 

   In <LOCATION>Buffalo Grove</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Michael Soto</PERSON>, a jeweler and racehorse owner, turned to <PERSON>Mr. Kamen</PERSON> when a back problem plunged one of his horses into a losing streak. 
After the treatment, the horse won <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> in one race and <MONEY>$4,500</MONEY> in another. 

   Another equine example: <PERSON>Kathryn Sickling</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> businesswoman and horse breeder, recalls a favorite horse made lame by a nerve injury. 
Three veterinarians prescribed rest, but that didn't help. 
One vet talked of euthanasia. 

   Ready to "try anything," she says, <PERSON>Ms. Sickling</PERSON> called in <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON>. 
She also shelled out <MONEY>$80</MONEY> to have a professional masseur massage her beloved beast. 
"A week later, I was riding the horse. 
Nobody could believe it," <PERSON>Ms. Sickling</PERSON> says. 
"A few years ago, nobody ever thought about chiropractic for animals. 
So many animals are killed that don't need to be." 

   Animal chiropractors concede that traditional veterinary techniques often work where theirs would serve no purpose. 
But <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> says the success others had with chiropractic made her switch careers. 
After 13 years as a veterinarian, "I couldn't see why I wasn't getting more animals better," she says. 
"Sixty-five percent of my income came from giving vaccinations and removing sex organs," she adds. 
"I was really burned out. 
I considered going into acupuncture." 

   Then one of her clients decided to take a chronically lame dog to a chiropractor. 
"I thought it was pretty silly, but the dog started walking more normally thereafter," <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> says. 
"This was a turning point in my life." 

   <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> gave up her veterinary practice and started studying chiropractic to earn her second doctorate. 
Today, she lives in a large house with a dog, two cats, five chickens and a goat that likes to walk on her horse's back. 
She practices chiropractic only on animals. 

   To work on a horse, <PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> climbs up on a couple of bales of hay. 
Some chiropractors place a padded 2-by-4 against a large animal's bones and pound the board with a mallet. 
<PERSON>Dr. Willoughby</PERSON> uses her bare hands. 
To develop the strength to manipulate a large animal's bones, she had to practice weight lifting. 

   But the animal chiropractor's worst problem is the law. 
According to the <ORGANIZATION>Veterinary Medical Association</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Dr. Freeman</PERSON>, laws in all 50 states restrict medical treatment of animals to veterinarians. 
