<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900524-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-90 0157EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-MontanaSenate     05-24 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Montana Senate,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Four GOP Candidates Scrap for Chance to Take on Montana's Baucus</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB ANEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Max Baucus</PERSON> remembers well the surprise
defeat that <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> voters dealt fellow Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John
Melcher</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE>, and he's maneuvering early to avoid a similar fate.
   The two-term senator faces little challenge in the Democratic
primary on <DATE>June 5</DATE>, but he's amassing a stash of campaign cash to
combat the winner of the four-way Republican primary.
   Baucus has raised about <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> for what he expects will be a
<MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> campaign, the most expensive in the history of rural
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
pumped <MONEY>$205,000</MONEY> into the state GOP, including <MONEY>$138,000</MONEY> in the last
month of the campaign, to help challenger <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> overtake
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> said the national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> has targeted him in hopes of a
repeat.
   ``Republican candidates have said they and the <ORGANIZATION>Republican
National Committee</ORGANIZATION> will do whatever it takes to win this seat,''
<PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> said.
   The likely beneficiary of that Republican support is unclear.
   A statewide poll taken in <DATE>April</DATE> showed no clear leader in the
<ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> race between Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON> and businessman-scientist
<PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>. State <PERSON>Sen. Bill Farrell</PERSON> and former business
executive <PERSON>John Domenech</PERSON> lagged behind.
   In the Democratic primary, <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> is heavily favored over <PERSON>John
Driscoll</PERSON>, a member of the state <ORGANIZATION>Public Service Commission</ORGANIZATION>, and
Billings evangelist Curly <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Driscoll</PERSON> has attacked <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> for obtaining <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of his
campaign financing from out-of-state interests. But most of the
debate has been among the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> candidates.
   <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> has made an issue of his lifelong ties to <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,
contrasting his background to that of Vorhauer, who became a state
resident only <DATE>last fall</DATE>, and <PERSON>Domenech</PERSON>, who moved to Bozeman four
years ago.
   <PERSON>Farrell</PERSON> has accused <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> of not addressing the issues.
Vorhauer and <PERSON>Farrell</PERSON> have taken a pro-choice position on abortion,
while <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> and <PERSON>Domenech</PERSON> are anti-abortion.
   For the most part, the Republicans have similar views on other
issues and emphasize differences in style and personality.
   Kolstad, 58, was a state legislator for 20 years and operates a
family farm and ranch in north-central <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. He joined <PERSON>Stan
Stephens</PERSON> in the <DATE>1988</DATE> gubernatorial race to become the No. 2 person
in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s first GOP administration in 20 years.
   <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> was the last to enter the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> race, but yielded to
entreaties from President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, former
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and other national GOP leaders seeking a
well-known challenger.
   <PERSON>Farrell</PERSON>, 41, who owns a trucking company, stresses the
blue-collar roots that he believes set him apart from the other
candidates.
   <PERSON>Domenech</PERSON>, 36, quit his job as president of a pharmaceutical
testing firm to run for the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. He touts his business
experience and said he decided to run because he was angry about a
lack of economic opportunities in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   Vorhauer, 48, best known as the inventor of the <DATE>Today</DATE>
contraceptive sponge, has divided his time between <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> since <DATE>1979</DATE>. He helped found or develop four
businesses in western <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, 48, was born and raised in <LOCATION>Helena</LOCATION>, the son of a
prominent <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> ranching family. He entered politics in <DATE>1972</DATE> when
he was elected to the state <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. Two years later he went on to
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and served two <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> terms before being elected to the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1978</DATE>. He was re-elected in <DATE>1984</DATE> with <PERCENT>57 percent</PERCENT> of the
vote.
   Driscoll is making his second challenge to <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>; he finished
last in a three-way Democratic primary in <DATE>1978</DATE>. <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>, who has
made preaching against alcohol and drug abuse the centerpiece of
his campaign, was new to politics in <DATE>1988</DATE> when he finished last in
a six-man Democratic gubernatorial primary.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901005-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-05-90 0014EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Montana-Senate     10-05 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Montana-Senate,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Looks for Repeat of 1988 Senate Upset in Montana</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> candidate <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON>
has the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> on his side, but <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON> has the money,
the lead and widespread appeal among rural <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> voters.
   Kolstad, the state's lieutenant governor, is a wealthy rancher
and grain farmer who is trying to tar <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> as a liberal in favor
of big government. Kolstad's conservative pitch even includes a
reminder that he ``opposes <PERSON>Ted Kennedy</PERSON> on most national issues.''
   But <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> pays close attention to rural and economic concerns.
Pet issues include aid to rural hospitals, <ORGANIZATION>Essential Air Service</ORGANIZATION>
subsidies for rural airline routes and agricultural trade. He voted
against the <DATE>1990</DATE> farm bill, saying it didn't do enough for farmers.
   Kolstad was at least 20 points behind <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> in an independent
mid-September poll. In addition, the Republican is up against the
largest campaign bankroll in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> history.
   Baucus raised <MONEY>$1.9 million</MONEY> in the 18 months ending in <DATE>June</DATE>, a
princely sum in a state with only 800,000 people. Aggressive
fund-raising efforts continue.
   Baucus says he's just taking precautions.
   Kolstad had only <MONEY>$267,000</MONEY> in campaign funds on <DATE>June 30</DATE>, but if
the race gets closer, he may look to national GOP groups for
eleventh-hour fund-raising help.
   That approach worked in <DATE>1988</DATE>, when political newcomer <PERSON>Conrad
Burns</PERSON> narrowly upset two-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to become the first Republican <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator from this state
in 36 years. The huge infusions of cash used to help <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> are
being challenged in a lawsuit and in a complaint before the <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Election Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``If someone unfairly attacks me, I'm going to respond,'' says
<PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>. ``I just have be to prepared for the possibility that I'll
face the same deluge of dollars.''
   In the <DATE>1988</DATE> race, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>, a former farm-and-ranch broadcaster,
attacked <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> as a liberal out of touch with conservative, rural
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   Kolstad has adopted the same strategy.
   ``More federal bureaucracy, more federal control, the higher
deficits - there are the things I'm going to be fighting against in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,'' says <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON>.
   Like <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> was recruited by national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> heavyweights,
including President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> raised
more than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> for <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> when the president traveled to
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>.
   Kolstad cannot claim the mantle of political outsider. He spent
20 years in the <LOCATION>Montana Legislature</LOCATION> before winning the lieutenant
governorship on the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> ticket with Gov. <PERSON>Stan Stephens</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   The Stephens-Kolstad adminstration has not been universally
popular in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, struggling with tax and budget issues and
controversial appointees. Recent polls show his ``negatives''
nearly doubled since a similar poll in mid-June.
   Kolstad, 58, says he is saving his money for a last-minute
barrage of media advertising attacking <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> on his votes against
defense spending, tax cuts and budget-balancing measures.
   The 48-year-old <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, running for a third term, has been
working hard to dispel whatever liberal image he may have had.
   He earns relatively high marks from most liberal interest groups
but insists he doesn't care about ratings.
   ``I don't look left, I don't look right, I look forward - to
what is the best solution for <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' says <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>. ``Most people
are more concerned with producing results for <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> than with
labels.''
   <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> has barely mentioned <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> in campaign materials,
preferring instead to emphasize efforts he says have created or
protected jobs in economically depressed <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   While differences between the candidates exist - <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> is
pro-choice on abortion, <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> is not, for example - the race has
generated few fireworks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881102-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-02-88 0037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-MontanaSenate     11-02 0654</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Montana Senate,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pastoral Politics Marks Montana Senate Campaign</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Political Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Montanan <PERSON>John Melcher</PERSON> is using pastoral
politics in his fight to retain his <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> seat and prevent
<PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> from becoming the state's first Republican senator
since <DATE>1952</DATE>.
   ``Every election some greenhorn runs against <PERSON>Doc Melcher</PERSON>,'' says
a talking cow in one <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> campaign ad. ``They come in thinking
they can put Doc out to pasture.''
   ``But they leave with egg on their faces, and even worse on their
shoes,'' chuckles another cud-chewing bovine.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, a veterinarian and two-term senator, holds a
double-digit lead over <LOCATION>Burns</LOCATION> in recent state polls, but the
Republican county commissioner from Billings is waging a spirited
challenge.
   ``I just think <PERSON>John Melcher</PERSON> is completely out of step with the
majority of Montanans,'' says <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>, who has been hammering away at
his opponent as ``too liberal'' and an ineffective member of the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   The liberal accusation is nothing new for <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, who was
targeted for defeat by the <ORGANIZATION>National Conservative Political Action
Committee</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   He responded with TV ads that featured talking cows ridiculing
NCPAC as a herd of city-slickers trying to fool Montanans about
``old <PERSON>Doc Melcher</PERSON>.''
   Earlier this year, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> picked up on the theme, warning voters
that <PERSON>Doc Melcher</PERSON>'s cows would be ``spreading real bull'' this
election. In response, the incumbent senator again trotted out his
campaign cows.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, 64, a senior member of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Agriculture Committee</ORGANIZATION>,
portrays himself as a fighter who stands up for family farmers,
workers and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s basic industries _ timber, mining and
agriculture.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, he fought <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration attempts to reduce price
supports for grain, cotton and rice.
   ``If what I get done is beneficial, then that's how I should be
judged,'' he says. ``There are very few people in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> who
understand what the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> is all about.''
   Melcher is also considered something of a maverick. He was one of
only two senators who voted against the Omnibus Drug Bill of <DATE>1986</DATE>,
one of only three who opposed the <DATE>1986</DATE> tax overhaul bill, and one of
only three who voted against the U.S.-Canadian trade agreement this
year.
   Melcher received high ratings from many liberal groups, but he
has voted with conservatives on several key issues.
   He opposed the <ORGANIZATION>Panama Canal</ORGANIZATION> treaty in <DATE>1978</DATE>, supported <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s
<DATE>1981</DATE> tax cuts and the balanced-budget law and is a staunch opponent
of abortion.
   Burns, 53, operated a farm-and-ranch broadcasting service until
he ran for commissioner in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s largest county in <DATE>1986</DATE>. He
upset the Democratic incumbent, and announced earlier this year he
would take on <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>.
   ``There's quite a bit of dissatisfaction here in the state of
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' he says. ``I don't think we can stand six more years of
the same.''
   folksy, personable campaigner, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> has been barnstorming the
state, meeting voters door-to-door. He says his outgoing, friendly
style will be more effective in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> than <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>'s
``obstructionist'' tactics.
   But <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>' media campaign carries a strident tone, labeling
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> as soft on drugs, crime, and defense, and describing him as
a big-spending liberal who likes to raise taxes.
   Some of <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>' advertising was prepared with help from the
<ORGANIZATION>Republican Senatorial Campaign Committee</ORGANIZATION>, which helped recruit him
as a candidate and considers him one of the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s best shots at
knocking off an incumbent <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Democrat in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>' <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> managers have denied suggestions that the national
committee is calling the shots for the campaign, but say the
assistance is welcome and needed to offset <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>'s 2-to-1
advantage in campaign funds.
   Despite polls showing him behind, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> is convinced he has a
chance. He says his agricultural background will help him cut into
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>'s power base in eastern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, which <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> represented
in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for 7{ years.
   ``I think it's going to be tighter than a new pair of shoes,''
<PERSON>Burns</PERSON> says of the election.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900606-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-90 0537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-MontanaPrimary     06-06 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Montana Primary,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veteran GOP Politician Prepares To Take On Baucus</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Montana Republicans tapped Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen
Kolstad</PERSON> to challenge Democratic <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON>, who brushed
aside his primary opposition but said he's taking nothing for
granted in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Baucus, raised more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> in campaign money even before
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s primary victory, but recalled the <DATE>1988</DATE> upset of Democratic
<PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> by upstart Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>.
   ``One never takes anything for granted _ ever,'' said <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, 48.
   Kolstad, a 58-year-old farmer-rancher and 20-year veteran of
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> politics, bested three rivals in a hotly contested <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>
primary.
   With <PERCENT>98 percent</PERCENT> of 967 precincts reporting early today, <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON>
had 36,897 votes, or <PERCENT>43 percent</PERCENT>; to 30,451 votes, or <PERCENT>36 percent</PERCENT>, for
scientist-businessman <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>; 11,484, or <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT>, for
state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Farrell</PERSON>; and 6,525, or <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>, for businessman
<PERSON>John Domenech</PERSON>.
   Kolstad promised a campaign that would ``keep Senator Baucus up
against the ropes right from the beginning.''
   ``We're just going to have to outwork him,'' he said. ``We're
used to putting in a lot of 16- and 18-hour days on the ranch. We're
going to convert that energy into the campaign.''
   Baucus had 79,131 votes, or <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT>, to 12,444 votes, or <PERCENT>13
percent</PERCENT> for state <ORGANIZATION>Public Service</ORGANIZATION> Commissioner <PERSON>John Driscoll</PERSON>; and
4,321 votes, or <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT>, for evangelist Curly <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>.
   Kolstad was recruited by national Republicans, including
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>. Baucus, pointing to the
national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> involvement, predicted that <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON>'s campaign would be
run from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Kolstad, emphasized his farming background and his lifelong ties
to <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. The emphasis also was a slap at Vorhauer, who moved his
legal residence to <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> only <DATE>last fall</DATE>.
   Vorhauer, 48, is best known as the inventor of the Today
contraceptive sponge. His campaign stressed his engineering and
science background as qualifying him to bring high-tech businesses
to the state.
   <PERSON>Farrell</PERSON>, 41, who operates a small independent trucking firm,
touted his working-man image. <PERSON>Domenech</PERSON>, 36, campaigned for a
national health plan.
   Baucus ran a quiet primary campaign, with neither of his
challengrs having much in the way of money or organizations.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900606-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-90 2011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-MontanaPrimary     06-06 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Montana Primary,0267</SECOND>
<HEAD>Montana Candidates Brace for Expensive Fall Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON> and his Democratic
supporters say they're bracing for an avalanche of Republican cash
in this <DATE>fall</DATE>'s general election battle with Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON>.
   But <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, a two-term Democrat who was nominated for re-election
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, has his own pile of campaign cash, which Republicans are
trying to turn into a liability rather than an asset.
   ``Senator <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> will learn the hard way that <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> cannot be
bought with an out-of-state war chest,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Montana GOP</ORGANIZATION> Chairman
<PERSON>Barbara Campbell</PERSON>. ``Does he need <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to get re-elected to a
job he's held for 12 years? That says he's very weak.''
   Baucus coasted past two primary opponents <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT>
of the Democratic vote, while <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> won a four-man race with <PERCENT>43
percent</PERCENT> of the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> vote.
   Kolstad and the Republicans are hoping for a repeat of <DATE>1988</DATE>, when
upstart Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> pulled off an upset victory over
two-term incumbent Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>.
   Kolstad promised <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to run an above-board campaign
focusing on economic issues and refraining from personal attacks.
But Democratic Party Chairman <PERSON>Bruce Nelson</PERSON> said he expects <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON>
to go on the offensive against <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>.
   ``The pattern that Republicans set two years ago of a relentless
negative attack is the same thing that they will do this year,'' he
predicted.
   Baucus already has raised more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> in campaign funds,
smashing the state campaign-spending record of <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY> set by
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881109-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-88 1353EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-ELN--BurnsProfile     11-09 0303</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ELN--Burns Profile,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Farm Broadcaster Waged Folksy But Hard-Hitting Campaign</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> only has two years
of political experience but the folksy former broadcaster is not
intimidated by the transition from county commissioner to the
powerful <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``There's really no difference. We're just dealing in more zeros.
The responsibility's the same,'' said <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> after writing himself
into <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> history with an upset victory over two-term Democratic
<PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>.
   On a day that saw Republicans capture the presidency, the
governorship and the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> became the first Republican
senator from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> in 36 years and only the second man ever to
defeat an incumbent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   ``It's nice to have a personal friend in the statehouse and it's
nice to have a personal friend in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> said
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   The 53-year-old <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> is a <LOCATION>Yellowstone County</LOCATION> commissioner from
Billings, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s largest city. He entered politics only two years
ago after a career as a broadcaster, livestock show manager and
field representative for a ranching publication.
   Burns barnstormed the state, meeting voters door-to-door and
telling them his outgoing, friendly style will be more effective in
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> than <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>'s ``obstructionist'' tactics.
   Burns campaigned as a conservative, saying <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> was ``too
liberal'' for <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and not an effective senator. He also labeled
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> a supporter of higher taxes and promised to vote against any
tax increasing, saying the federal deficit can be balanced by
restraining spending.
   ``I always like to win, but I enter all these things realizing
that voters may not approve,'' <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said <DATE>early Wednesday</DATE>. ``And
if they don't, you have to accept that.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Senatorial Committee</ORGANIZATION> helped recruit <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>
as a candidate and assisted his campaign with money and advice.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880608-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-08-88 1423EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-StatePrimariesRdp Bjt   06-08 0760</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-State Primaries Rdp, Bjt,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>GOP Launches Drive for 3 Senate Seats</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Primaries in seven states cleared the way for
multimillion-dollar <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> battles in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
and Republicans said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the results also bolstered their
hopes of ousting Sens. <PERSON>Jeff Bingaman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <PERSON>John Melcher</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, voters rejected propositions authorizing an AIDS
quarantine, closing the Rancho Seco nuclear plant, dividing mammoth
<LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION> in two and relaxing state spending limits
imposed after tax-slashing Proposition 13 was passed a decade ago.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s ballots also included one race for governor and one
for mayor. In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, former Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON> captured
the nomination to succeed retiring Democrat <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>, scoring
<PERCENT>39 percent</PERCENT> of the vote in a six-man race. He will face Republican
former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON>. In <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>Maureen
O'Connor</PERSON> was elected to a full four-year term with <PERCENT>58 percent</PERCENT> of
the vote.
   In congressional races, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Ernest Konnyu</PERSON>, a
freshman Republican from the <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> suburb of <LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION>, became
the first incumbent to lose a primary this year, falling by a <PERCENT>58
percent-to-42 percent</PERCENT> margin to <PERSON>Tom Campbell</PERSON>, a politically
moderate <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> professor.
   <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Councilman Donald Payne</PERSON> won the Democratic
nomination in the 10th District with <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> of the vote for a
chance to succeed retiring <PERSON>Peter Rodino</PERSON> and become the state's
first black in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. Victory in the primary is tantamount to
election in the overwhelmingly Democratic district.
   <PERSON>Oliver North</PERSON>, the fired <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> national security aide
indicted in the Iran-Contra affair, scored a personal success as a
campaigner when two Republicans for whom he stumped in <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION> won congressional primaries. Former deputy <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
counsel <PERSON>Christopher Cox</PERSON> was the victor over 12 rivals in the 40th
District and former <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration speechwriter <PERSON>Dana
Rohrabacher</PERSON> topped an eight-candidate field in the 42nd District.
   In <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> races, first-term New Jersey Democrat <PERSON>Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>
polled <PERCENT>77 percent</PERCENT> of the vote against two challengers and will
defend his seat against <PERSON>Pete Dawkins</PERSON>, a former star athlete, <PERSON>Rhodes</PERSON>
scholar and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War hero who moved from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
to make his first bid for office.
   The two expect to spend a total of <MONEY>$14 million</MONEY> on the race,
which the national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> has targeted as vital to its hopes of
recapturing the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. Democrats now control it 54-46.
   In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, Democratic Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> shrugged off
three primary opponents for the right to challenge first-term
Republican <PERSON>Sen. Pete Wilson</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> has spent <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> already on his re-election, and
his numbers are exactly where they were 18 months ago, at <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT>, which is the definition of a very vulnerable incumbent,''
said <PERSON>Anita Dunn</PERSON>, communications director for the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic
Senatorial Campaign Committee</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Her counterpart in the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Tom Mason</PERSON>, saw vulnerability on the
Democratic side in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> won nomination
to a third term with <PERCENT>76 percent</PERCENT> of the vote against a political
newcomer.
   ``The good news for us is that <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>'s <PERCENT>76 percent</PERCENT> against a
nobody tells us a good manifestation of voter dissatisfaction,''
<PERSON>Mason</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, not surprisingly, took exception to that analysis.
   ``I think the <ORGANIZATION>Republican Senatorial Committee</ORGANIZATION> would like to
capture this seat,'' he said. ``I'm going to make sure that doesn't
happen.''
   The Republican candidate, county commissioner <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, said
he expected <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> to attack him as inexperienced, but added,
``When you're green, you're growing, and when you're ripe, you're
rotten.... That's how we'll counter.''
   Mason also said the victory by state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION>'s four-man <ORGANIZATION>GOP Senate</ORGANIZATION> primary put him in good shape for a
run at first-term Democrat <PERSON>Bingaman</PERSON>.
   ``It was a clean campaign, and there are no scars left, so we
can focus on <PERSON>Bingaman</PERSON>'s lack of name ID and lack of depth of
support,'' <PERSON>Mason</PERSON> said.
   Valentine immediately attacked his rival as too liberal for <LOCATION>New
Mexico</LOCATION>, saying <PERSON>Bingaman</PERSON> supported ``big labor, big government and
big spending on the part of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.''
   With <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> of the vote counted, <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION> had 33,698 votes
or <PERCENT>43 percent</PERCENT>, and his closest challenger, former <ORGANIZATION>Interior
Department</ORGANIZATION> official <PERSON>Rick Montoya</PERSON>, had 22,392 votes or <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT>.
   In other voting <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, Circuit <PERSON>Judge Mark Kennedy</PERSON>, a
son-in-law of former Gov. <PERSON>George C. Wallace</PERSON>, won the Democratic
nomination to the <ORGANIZATION>Alabama Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>; five supporters of <PERSON>Lyndon
LaRouche</PERSON> all lost congressional primaries in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>; and in <LOCATION>South
Dakota</LOCATION>, there were no statewide races and only 26 primaries for the
105 state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900719-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-90 1842EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-GOPLawsuit     07-19 0580</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-GOP Lawsuit,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Allegations in Lawsuit Against Montana GOP, National
Republican Committee</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB ANEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The former executive director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Montana Republican Party</ORGANIZATION> has accused the organization, its
chairwoman and a national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> committee of breaking federal
racketeering laws.
   The allegations involved the handling of political money during
the <DATE>1988</DATE> campaigns.
   <PERSON>Terry Merica</PERSON> made the allegations in a complaint filed in <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
District Court</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. It amends a lawsuit he and his wife,
<PERSON>Neida</PERSON>, filed in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   The complaint alleges that the state GOP, Chairwoman <PERSON>Barbara
wire and mail fraud by illegally funneling money into the campaigns
of <PERSON>Sen. Conrad Burns</PERSON> and Gov. <PERSON>Stan Stephens</PERSON>.
   Burns, at the time a county commissioner in Billings, upset
Democratic incumbent <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> in the <DATE>November</DATE> election.
<PERSON>Stephens</PERSON> defeated former Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Tom Judge</PERSON> in the race for
governor.
   The complaint says the defendants used a series of letters and
money transfers in the <DATE>spring</DATE> and <DATE>summer of 1988</DATE> to defraud the
citizens of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The original lawsuit alleged the Mericas were fired in late <DATE>1988</DATE>
for questioning whether financial dealings between the state
<ORGANIZATION>Republican Party</ORGANIZATION> and the national committee violated state and
federal election laws.
   Neida Merica was an administrative secretary for the state <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s complaint contends there were additional violations
of the federal Racketeer Influenced, Corrupt Organizations Act.
   <PERSON>Charles Erdmann</PERSON>, attorney for the <ORGANIZATION>Montana GOP</ORGANIZATION>, said the new
contentions may reflect <LOCATION>Merica</LOCATION>'s concern that the original suit
will be dismissed.
   ``This may be nothing more than an attempt to bolster their
complaint,'' he said.
   He would not comment on specifics, saying he had not seen the
new complaint, but he questioned the timing of its filing. The
state <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> convention began <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in Billings, with President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> scheduled to appear in the <TIME>evening</TIME> on behalf of Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen
Kolstad</PERSON>, who is challenging Democratic incumbent <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON>.
   ``The timing of this would make you think this is politically
motivated,'' <PERSON>Campbell</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>James Goetz</PERSON>, the Mericas' attorney, said the timing was
coincidence.
organize campaigns of <ORGANIZATION>GOP Senate</ORGANIZATION> candidates, had no immediate
comment on the new allegations.
   The complaint alleges the defendants committed mail and wire
fraud by not legally reporting as much as <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> in campaign
contributions in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   It cites several instances of questionable handling of campaign
financing. It alleges that:
   _The national committee conducted a voter identification project
in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, but gave results only to the <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON>
campaigns. The cost of the project was never reported as a
contribution to the campaigns and the expense exceeded the federal
limit on what such committees can give to a candidate.
   _The national committee transferred thousands of dollars through
the <ORGANIZATION>Montana GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s accounts to help pay for a direct mailing by a
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> company for the <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> campaign in violation of federal
election laws.
   _Between <DATE>Aug. 8, 1988</DATE>, and <DATE>Nov. 16, 1988</DATE>, the national committee
shifted <MONEY>$178,145</MONEY> into the <ORGANIZATION>Montana GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s account. The money
transfers prompted a <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE> memo from <PERSON>Ward Shanahan</PERSON>, the state
party's lawyer, to <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> headquarters warning that the national
committee was using the <ORGANIZATION>Montana Republican Party</ORGANIZATION> for ``financial
shenanigans.''
   _In <DATE>October 1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Republican Governors' Association</ORGANIZATION> gave
<MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> to the <ORGANIZATION>Montana GOP</ORGANIZATION> with a letter from Executive Director
<PERSON>Michele Davis</PERSON> saying the money should be reported as coming from
the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900606-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-90 0131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-MontanaPrimary 3rdLd-Writethru a0431 06-06 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Montana Primary, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0431,0376</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Baucus Wins Renomination; Republicans Vie To Challenge Him</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with Kolstad winning, results;
picks up after dash. Matter below dash will stand.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BOB ANEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> defeated
three fellow Republicans for the right to challenge <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON>
in a bid to repeat the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1988</DATE> feat of knocking off a Democratic
incumbent.
   <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, seeking his third term, had no trouble turning back a
challenge for the Democratic nomination from <PERSON>John Driscoll</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Public
Service Commission</ORGANIZATION> member, and evangelist Curly <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>.
   With 694 of 967 precincts reporting, <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> had 27,250 votes, or
<PERCENT>42 percent</PERCENT>, to 23,352 votes, or <PERCENT>36 percent</PERCENT>, for businessman and
scientist <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>; 8,569 votes, or <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> for state <PERSON>Sen.
Bill Farrell</PERSON>; and 4,981 votes, or <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>, for former business
executive <PERSON>John Domenech</PERSON>.
   In the Democratic race, <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> had 61,054 votes, or <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT>,
to 9,538 votes for <PERSON>Driscoll</PERSON>, or <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT>, and 3,192 votes for
<PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>, or <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> defeated
three fellow Republicans for the right to challenge <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON>
in a bid to repeat the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1988</DATE> feat of knocking off a Democratic
incumbent.
   <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>, seeking his third term, had no trouble turning back a
challenge for the Democratic nomination from <PERSON>John Driscoll</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Public
Service Commission</ORGANIZATION> member, and evangelist Curly <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>.
   With 694 of 967 precincts reporting, <PERSON>Kolstad</PERSON> had 27,250 votes, or
<PERCENT>42 percent</PERCENT>, to 23,352 votes, or <PERCENT>36 percent</PERCENT>, for businessman and
scientist <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>; 8,569 votes, or <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> for state <PERSON>Sen.
Bill Farrell</PERSON>; and 4,981 votes, or <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>, for former business
executive <PERSON>John Domenech</PERSON>.
   In the Democratic race, <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> had 61,054 votes, or <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT>,
to 9,538 votes for <PERSON>Driscoll</PERSON>, or <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT>, and 3,192 votes for
<PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>, or <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880607-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-07-88 1458EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-StatePrimariesRdp Bjt   06-07 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-State Primaries Rdp, Bjt,0817</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven States Hold Primaries, With Four Senate Races on Ballot</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Polls close at 8 p.m. EDT in New Jersey, 10 in Montana and New
Mexico and 11 in California; material below the dash will stand.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> voters <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> decided whether to shut down a nuclear
plant and permit the quarantining of AIDS victims, while two <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>
councilmen vied for a chance to become <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s first black
congressman.
   Four <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> races also were on the ballots as seven states
held primaries, and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> had a wide-open race for governor,
highlighted by former Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON>'s comeback bid.
   The liveliest <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primary was in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, where polls
showed state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> leading three fellow Republicans
for the nomination to oppose first-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen. Jeff
Bingaman</PERSON>.
   Three other <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primaries were all Democratic skirmishes
leading to the main event in <DATE>November</DATE>. First-term <PERSON>Sen. Frank
Lautenberg</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> had two little-known opponents as he sought
to defend his seat against Republican <PERSON>Peter Dawkins</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> Sen.
<PERSON>John Melcher</PERSON> had one challenger in his bid for a third term against
Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> was
favored over three rivals to win a chance to face Republican <PERSON>Sen.
Pete Wilson</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>'s heavily Democratic 10th district, where Rep. <PERSON>Peter
Rodino</PERSON> was retiring after 40 years, black City Councilmen <PERSON>Donald
Payne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ralph Grant</PERSON> competed in the Democratic primary. The winner
was expected to defeat the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> nominee, political newcomer <PERSON>Michael
Webb</PERSON>, who also is black.
   In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> was one of six Democrats who entered the race
for governor after Democrat <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON> decided not to seek a
third term. Former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON> and state Rep. <PERSON>Cal
Winslow</PERSON> were the only Republican candidates left after the early
favorite, Secretary of State <PERSON>Jim Waltermire</PERSON>, was killed in a plane
crash in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Maureen O'Connor</PERSON> was seeking a full four-year
term and needed a majority in the non-partisan primary to avoid a
runoff in the nation's seventh-largest city.
   Californians confronted their usual slew of ballot measures,
including proposals to ease state spending limits, curb campaign
spending, slow growth and declare AIDS a communicable disease,
subjecting victims to potential quarantine.
   In <LOCATION>Sacramento County</LOCATION>, a measure seeking closure of the Rancho
Seco nuclear power plant could mark the first time in history that
voters have directly ordered the shutdown of such a facility.
   And in <LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION>, geographically the nation's
largest, voters were asked to carve away the eastern, desert portion
to create a new jurisdiction called <ORGANIZATION>Mojave County</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here are highlights of voting in the other states:
   <LOCATION>ALABAMA</LOCATION> _ Circuit <PERSON>Judge Mark Kennedy</PERSON>, a son-in-law of former Gov.
<PERSON>George C. Wallace</PERSON>, was running for the Democratic nomination to
state <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> on a slate supported by trial lawyers and
opposed by big business and insurance companies.
   IOWA _ Sixteen supporters of extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON> were
running in Democratic primaries, five for congressional nominations
and the rest in state legislative districts.
   SOUTH DAKOTA _ No statewide races were on the ballot and there
were only 26 primary races for the 105 state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> voters <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> decided whether to shut down a nuclear
plant and permit the quarantining of AIDS victims, while two <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>
councilmen vied for a chance to become <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s first black
congressman.
   Four <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> races also were on the ballots as seven states
held primaries, and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> had a wide-open race for governor,
highlighted by former Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON>'s comeback bid.
   The liveliest <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primary was in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, where polls
showed state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> leading three fellow Republicans
for the nomination to oppose first-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen. Jeff
Bingaman</PERSON>.
   Three other <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primaries were all Democratic skirmishes
leading to the main event in <DATE>November</DATE>. First-term <PERSON>Sen. Frank
Lautenberg</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> had two little-known opponents as he sought
to defend his seat against Republican <PERSON>Peter Dawkins</PERSON>; <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> Sen.
<PERSON>John Melcher</PERSON> had one challenger in his bid for a third term against
Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> was
favored over three rivals to win a chance to face Republican <PERSON>Sen.
Pete Wilson</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>'s heavily Democratic 10th district, where Rep. <PERSON>Peter
Rodino</PERSON> was retiring after 40 years, black City Councilmen <PERSON>Donald
Payne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ralph Grant</PERSON> competed in the Democratic primary. The winner
was expected to defeat the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> nominee, political newcomer <PERSON>Michael
Webb</PERSON>, who also is black.
   In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> was one of six Democrats who entered the race
for governor after Democrat <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON> decided not to seek a
third term. Former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON> and state Rep. <PERSON>Cal
Winslow</PERSON> were the only Republican candidates left after the early
favorite, Secretary of State <PERSON>Jim Waltermire</PERSON>, was killed in a plane
crash in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Maureen O'Connor</PERSON> was seeking a full four-year
term and needed a majority in the non-partisan primary to avoid a
runoff in the nation's seventh-largest city.
   Californians confronted their usual slew of ballot measures,
including proposals to ease state spending limits, curb campaign
spending, slow growth and declare AIDS a communicable disease,
subjecting victims to potential quarantine.
   In <LOCATION>Sacramento County</LOCATION>, a measure seeking closure of the Rancho
Seco nuclear power plant could mark the first time in history that
voters have directly ordered the shutdown of such a facility.
   And in <LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION>, geographically the nation's
largest, voters were asked to carve away the eastern, desert portion
to create a new jurisdiction called <ORGANIZATION>Mojave County</ORGANIZATION>.
   Here are highlights of voting in the other states:
   <LOCATION>ALABAMA</LOCATION> _ Circuit <PERSON>Judge Mark Kennedy</PERSON>, a son-in-law of former Gov.
<PERSON>George C. Wallace</PERSON>, was running for the Democratic nomination to
state <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> on a slate supported by trial lawyers and
opposed by big business and insurance companies.
   IOWA _ Sixteen supporters of extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON> were
running in Democratic primaries, five for congressional nominations
and the rest in state legislative districts.
   SOUTH DAKOTA _ No statewide races were on the ballot and there
were only 26 primary races for the 105 state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881109-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-88 1941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-ELN--Montana 1stLd-Writethru a1162 11-09 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-ELN--Montana, 1st Ld-Writethru, a1162,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Political Neophyte Goes From County Commissioner to U.S. Senate</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RECASTS lede to refocus; picks up 3rd graf pvs, `Burns, a...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KRONHOLM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   County Commissioner <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> may not
know it yet, but his defeat of two-term <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> put
him in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s history books.
   <PERSON>Burns</PERSON>' win <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> made him only the second man to defeat an
incumbent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. It also made him the first
Republican senator from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> in 36 years.
   Burns, a farm-and-ranch broadcaster and a county commissioner in
Billings who was making his second try for elective office, defeated
Melcher <PERCENT>52 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>48 percent</PERCENT>.
   Republican <PERSON>Stan Stephens</PERSON> won the <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> gubernatorial race,
defeating former Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON> by 189,630 votes to
168,537 votes, a margin of <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>47 percent</PERCENT>. <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON> will
be the first Republican governor in 20 years.
   <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> captured <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s four electoral votes, defeating
<ORGANIZATION>Michael Dukakis</ORGANIZATION> <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>47 percent</PERCENT>. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> had 189,598 votes to
168,120 cast for <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>.
   Melcher had been targeted for defeat by the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National
Senatorial Committee</ORGANIZATION>, which helped recruit <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> and funneled almost
<MONEY>$400,000</MONEY> into his campaign.
   ``I was hoping to campaign for a month solid,'' <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said.
``I've only been out here just about 17 or 18 days. I never really
had a good feel for the race.''
   <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON>, a former radio broadcaster and cable television company
owner from <LOCATION>Havre</LOCATION>, said his victory reflected <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s desire ``to
put someone with business experience in the executive position of
the state.''
   Both <ORGANIZATION>Montana U.S. House</ORGANIZATION> seats went to the incumbents, Democrat
<PERSON>Pat Williams</PERSON> and Republican <PERSON>Ron Marlenee</PERSON>.
   Montana voters refused to repeal the state's mandatory seat-belt
law; approved repeal of the constitutional right of the needy to
welfare benefits; and defeated a mandatory deposit on beverage
containers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881109-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-88 1056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d p PM-ELN--Montana     11-09 0264</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-ELN--Montana,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Melcher Ousted From Senate, GOP's Stephens Wins Governor Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE DENNISON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two-term Democratic <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>
lost to a Republican county commissioner and Republicans captured
the <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> governor's mansion after 20 years of Democratic control.
   Republican <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> won the state's four electoral votes.
   <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, a commissioner from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s most populous county
which includes Billings, became the first GOP senator from <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>
in 36 years.
   <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> said taxes and the <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> wilderness bill sponsored by
<PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> but vetoed last week by President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> were keys to his
victory <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``The 101st <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is really going to have to knuckle down and
go to work on this deficit,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said he'd only been campaigning for about 18 days and ``I
never really had a good feel for the race.''
   With <PERCENT>98 percent</PERCENT> of the precincts reporting, <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> had 184,789, or
<PERCENT>52 percent</PERCENT>, and <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, 170,149, or <PERCENT>48 percent</PERCENT>.
   In the governor's race, Republican <PERSON>Stan Stephens</PERSON>, a former state
senator, defeated former Democrat Gov. <PERSON>Tom Judge</PERSON>, who was seeking
his third term after losing in his party's primary eight years ago
to retiring Gov. <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>.
   ``I'd like to think we won the contest because people realize we
represent change,'' said <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON>, a Canadian immigrant who came to
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to harvest wheat 39 years ago.
   <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON> had 185,256 votes, <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT>, to <PERSON>Judge</PERSON>'s 164,111 votes,
<PERCENT>47 percent</PERCENT>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> collected 185,688 for <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT>, Democrat <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
had 163,507 for <PERCENT>47 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s two congressmen, a Republican and a Democrat, were
re-elected.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900531-0202 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-31-90 1624EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s p BC-PrimariesRdp Adv03   05-31 1185</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Primaries Rdp, Adv03,1212</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv 03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, June 3, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>California, North Carolina Races Top Primary Lineup</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A bitter primary campaign for governor of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is winding
down in a flurry of television commercials while <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>
Democrats are choosing a challenger to Republican <PERSON>Sen. Jesse Helms</PERSON>.
All told, candidates in nine states are vying for support <DATE>Tuesday,
1990</DATE>'s busiest primary election day so far.
   Democrats <PERSON>Dianne Feinstein</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>John Van de Kamp</ORGANIZATION> have spent months
attacking each other's positions on abortion, the death penalty and
how to deal with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <MONEY>$3.6 billion</MONEY> budget deficit.
   Polls suggested their race was a dead heat as they entered the
<DATE>last weekend</DATE> of the primary campaign.
   On the Republican side, <PERSON>Sen. Pete Wilson</PERSON> faced only token primary
opposition and sat on a huge campaign war chest as he waited to
learn which Democrat would be his opponent in the race to succeed
retiring Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON>, a Republican.
   In <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Harvey Gantt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mike Easley</PERSON> were in a runoff
for the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Senate</ORGANIZATION> nomination. <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON>, the former mayor of
<LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, finished first in a six-way primary <DATE>May 8</DATE>, but failed to
get the <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> necessary to avoid a runoff with the second-place
finisher.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Helms</PERSON> has started running television ads accusing the
Democrats of throwing mud at him.
   Voters also will go to the polls <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, five Democrats were battling for the right to
challenge Gov. Guy Hunt, the first Republican elected governor of
the state since Reconstruction. The contenders were state Attorney
General <PERSON>Don Siegelman</PERSON>, former Gov. <LOCATION>Fob James</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Ronnie
Flippo</PERSON>, state <PERSON>Sen. Charles Bishop</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Paul Hubbert</PERSON>, executive
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Alabama Education Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Sen. Howell Heflin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ala.</LOCATION>, and Republican state <PERSON>Sen. Bill
Cabannis</PERSON> were assured of their party nominations, setting up a
face-off in <DATE>November</DATE>.
   Abortion was the big issue in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, where three Democrats were
vying to take on GOP Gov. <PERSON>Terry Branstad</PERSON>, an opponent of legalized
abortion. The <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>National Abortion Rights Action
League</ORGANIZATION> endorsed <PERSON>Don Avenson</PERSON>, speaker of the <ORGANIZATION>Iowa House</ORGANIZATION>, a move that
provoked an angry response from banker <PERSON>John Chrystal</PERSON>, who, like
<PERSON>Avenson</PERSON>, supports legal abortion.
   NARAL's decision to weigh in on the race was believed aimed at
the third Democrat, Attorney General <PERSON>Tom Miller</PERSON>, an opponent of
abortion. <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> was an early favorite in the race and NARAL leaders
were concerned the fall election would be between two opponents of
abortion.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primary in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, incumbent Democrat <PERSON>Tom Harkin</PERSON> and
his <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> challenger, Rep. <PERSON>Tom Tauke</PERSON>, were assured of their party
nominations.
   Another crowded field was battling in Democratic and Republican
gubernatorial primaries in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, where incumbent <PERSON>Garrey
Carruthers</PERSON>, a Republican, was ineligible to seek a second term.
   For the first time in the state's history, the governor elected
in <DATE>1990</DATE> will be allowed to serve two consecutive four-year terms.
   The leading contenders on the Democratic side were <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>
lawyer <PERSON>Paul Bardacke</PERSON> and rancher <PERSON>Bruce King</PERSON>, who already has served
eight years as governor, elected first in <DATE>1970</DATE> and again in <DATE>1978</DATE>.
   Regarded as the top <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> contenders were <ORGANIZATION>Frank Bond</ORGANIZATION>, a former
legislator and education commissioner, and <LOCATION>Les Houston</LOCATION>, the
Republican leader of the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   Four Republicans were competing in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> to challenge
Democratic <PERSON>Sen. Max Baucus</PERSON>. Two years ago, underdog <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> challenger
<PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> toppled Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>, and the
Republicans are hoping to repeat that success this year. Vying to
take on <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON> were Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON>, state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Farrell</PERSON>,
and businessmen <PERSON>John Domenech</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>.
   Abortion was an issue in a three-way congressional primary in <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>. state Assemblyman <PERSON>Rodney Frelinghuysen</PERSON> and state <PERSON>Sen.
Richard A. Zimmer</PERSON>, supporters of the pro-choice position, were
competing with professional football player <PERSON>Phil McConkey</PERSON>, an
abortion opponent, for the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> nomination. The winner will face
Democrat <PERSON>Marguerite Chandler</PERSON> in <DATE>November</DATE> for the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat held by
<PERSON>James Courter</PERSON>, the defeated <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> candidate for governor in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   The leading candidates in the Democratic primary to fill the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat formerly held by Democrat <PERSON>James Florio</PERSON>, the winner of
last year's campaign for governor of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, were <PERSON>Linda Bowker</PERSON>,
president of the state chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>National Organization for
Women</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Camden County</LOCATION> official <PERSON>Robert E. Andrews</PERSON>. <LOCATION>Gloucester
County</LOCATION> official <PERSON>Daniel Mangini</PERSON> had no opposition in the Republican
primary.
   The <DATE>November</DATE> lineups were virtually assured for <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> races in
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, where Democrat <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON> and
Republican <PERSON>Pete Domenici</PERSON> were heavily favored for re-election. In
<LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, Republican <PERSON>Larry Pressler</PERSON> will be challenged in
<DATE>November</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>Democrat Ted Muenster</ORGANIZATION>. In <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, no Democrat filed
to oppose Republican <PERSON>Sen. Thad Cochran</PERSON>.
   Abortion was just one of the issues raised in the heated
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gubernatorial primary.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> governor's office was the biggest prize in the
<DATE>1990</DATE> elections. The Democrats control the legislature and if they
can recapture the governor's office, the party will have the
political advantage next year when lines are redrawn for the state's
congressional districts. With 45 seats, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> already has the
largest <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> delegation and the state is expected to gain six more
as a result of the <DATE>1990</DATE> Census.
   The Republicans recruited <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, re-elected to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1988</DATE>, to run for governor. Van de Kamp, the state attorney general,
was the early favorite for the Democratic nomination. But <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON>,
the former mayor of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, surprised many observers with the
strength of her campaign.
   A supporter of the death penalty, <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON> contrasted her
position with <ORGANIZATION>Van de Kamp</ORGANIZATION>'s opposition to capital punishment. She
also suggested that as a woman, her pro-choice credentials were
stronger than <ORGANIZATION>Van de Kamp's</ORGANIZATION>.
   Van de <PERSON>Kamp</PERSON> said he personally opposes capital punishment but
would uphold <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s death penalty, and countered with a
commercial saying he had put or kept 277 murderers on death row. His
most recent ad features an endorsement from consumer advocate <PERSON>Ralph
Nader</PERSON>, who labels <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON> ``a Republican in Democratic clothing.''
   While the Democratic contenders were spending millions on
commercials in the primary, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> has raised close to <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY>
while facing only token primary opposition.
   Also on the ballot in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> were two Republican-backed
propositions designed to dilute the legislature's power of
redistricting. One would require any plan to pass by a two-thirds
vote of both chambers, the other would remove it entirely and place
it in the hands of a non-partisan commission. Democrats oppose both
proposals.
   In <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON>, bidding to become the first black
Democrat ever elected to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Easley</PERSON> have spent more time
attacking <PERSON>Helms</PERSON> than each other.
   And now the Republican senator has responded with an animated
television ad that shows a wooded scene with flowers blooming and
birds chirping. It then shifts to a bullet-riddled photo of <PERSON>Helms</PERSON>
nailed to a tree and closes with a blob of mud hitting the picture.
A voice then says, ``Isn't it nice that <PERSON>Mike Easley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harvey Gantt</PERSON>
aren't running negative campaigns?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, June 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880608-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-08-88 0708EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-StatePrimariesRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0590 06-08 0843</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-State Primaries Rdp, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0590 ,0857</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Says No to AIDS Measure; Democrats to Defend 3 Senate
Seats</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 8-10 to UPDATE with results on California
propositions, new vote totals</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Voters rejected a possible AIDS quarantine in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
nominated a councilman to become the first black congressman in <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>, and launched a comeback by former Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.
   In other results from seven state primaries <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, voters set
the stage for four <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> races:
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> _ Democratic Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> piled up <PERCENT>81
percent</PERCENT> of the vote against three challengers and will oppose
moderate Republican <PERSON>Sen. Pete Wilson</PERSON>. <PERSON>McCarthy</PERSON> said he would attack
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> for a lack of leadership, adding, ``you must speak from your
convictions to people. You don't jump on winning sides.''
   New Jersey _ First-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen. Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>
trounced two opponents with <PERCENT>77 percent</PERCENT> of the vote and will face
<ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> newcomer <PERSON>Peter Dawkins</PERSON>, a former star athlete, <PERSON>Rhodes</PERSON> scholar
and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> war hero. <PERSON>Dawkins</PERSON> criticized <PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON>'s opposition to
the death penalty and willingness to support tax increases.
<PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON> said <PERSON>Dawkins</PERSON>, who recently moved to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, ``has
demonstrated a lack of knowledge'' about environmental and other
issues of concern to the state's voters.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> _ Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON> won <PERCENT>74 percent</PERCENT> of the
vote against a political unknown in his bid for a third term and
will run against Republican <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Yellowstone County</LOCATION>
commissioner. ``I think it's pretty obvious I've been here
awhile,'' <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. ``The longer you're here,
the more chances you have to get bills passed ... that will benefit
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>.''
   New <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> _ State <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> outpolled three
Republicans for the right to take on first-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen.
Jeff Bingaman</PERSON>. Valentine said <PERSON>Bingaman</PERSON> supported ``big labor, big
government and big spending on the part of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'' and had
fallen in line ``with the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> liberals.''
   With <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> of the vote counted, <ORGANIZATION>Valentine</ORGANIZATION> had 33,620 votes
or <PERCENT>43 percent</PERCENT>, and his closest challenger, former <ORGANIZATION>Interior
Department</ORGANIZATION> official <PERSON>Rick Montoya</PERSON>, had 22,314 votes or <PERCENT>28.5 percent</PERCENT>.
   The AIDS measure, backed by extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON>, was one
of a slew of propositions in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. With <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> of the
precincts in, it was soundly defeated by 3,604,180 votes or <PERCENT>68
percent</PERCENT> to 1,690,973 votes or <PERCENT>32 percent</PERCENT>.
   Also rejected were proposals to relax limits on government
spending, and local measures to shut down the Rancho Seco nuclear
power plant and split mammoth <LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION> in two.
However, voters approved two state measures to cap campaign
spending.
   In <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>Maureen O'Connor</PERSON> won a full four-year term.
With <PERCENT>38.1 percent</PERCENT> of the vote counted, she had 36,179 votes or <PERCENT>58.3
percent</PERCENT>, and her closest rival, former Councilman <PERSON>Floyd Morrow</PERSON>, had
21,334 votes or <PERCENT>34.4 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> Councilman <PERSON>Donald Payne</PERSON> defeated a fellow
black councilman, <PERSON>Ralph Grant</PERSON>, to capture the Democratic nomination
for the seat held by Rep. <PERSON>Peter Rodino</PERSON> for 40 years. Payne will be
an overwhelming favorite against Republican <PERSON>Michael Webb</PERSON>, who also
is black.
   ``It gives our delegation the fairness it's been lacking for
many years,'' <PERSON>Payne</PERSON> said of the fact that he stands to become the
state's first black congressman. ``I can speak from a true urban
perspective.''
   With <PERCENT>98 percent</PERCENT> of the vote counted, <PERSON>Payne</PERSON> had 39,681 votes or
<PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> and Grant had 14,576 votes or <PERCENT>27 percent</PERCENT>.
   In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> defeated five other Democrats who were enticed
into the race by the retirement of two-term Gov. <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>.
   ``People remember we had eight good years,'' said <PERSON>Judge</PERSON>, who
served from 1973-1981 and was beaten by Schwinden in the <DATE>1980</DATE>
primary. He said he also had ``put forth a program that the people
of this state have been waiting for.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> primary victor, former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON>, said
<PERSON>Judge</PERSON> ``represents an administration from yesteryear.''
   With <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of precincts reporting, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> had 45,826 votes
or <PERCENT>39.3 percent</PERCENT>, former <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court Justice Frank Morrison</ORGANIZATION> had
31,718 votes or <PERCENT>27.2 percent</PERCENT> and Attorney General <PERSON>Mike Greely</PERSON> had
26,497 votes or <PERCENT>22.7 percent</PERCENT>.
   <PERSON>Stephens</PERSON> had 43,279 votes or <PERCENT>49.9 percent</PERCENT> and state Rep. <LOCATION>Cal
Winslow</LOCATION> had 37,451 votes or <PERCENT>43.2 percent</PERCENT>. The early favorite,
Secretary of State <PERSON>Jim Waltermire</PERSON>, was killed in a plane crash in
<DATE>April</DATE>, but his name was on the ballot and he had 6,045 votes or <PERCENT>7
percent</PERCENT>.
   Here are highlights from the other states that voted:
   <LOCATION>ALABAMA</LOCATION> _ Circuit <PERSON>Judge Mark Kennedy</PERSON>, a son-in-law of former
Gov. <PERSON>George C. Wallace</PERSON>, won the Democratic nomination to state
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> on a slate supported by trial lawyers and opposed by
big business and insurance companies.
   IOWA _ Sixteen LaRouche supporters ran in Democratic primaries,
losing all five congressional nominations they sought and nine of
11 state legislative nominations. They won only in two districts
where they were unopposed.
   SOUTH DAKOTA _ No statewide races were on the ballot and there
were only 26 primary races for the 105 state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880608-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-08-88 0201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-MontanaPrimary 3rdLd-Writethru a0461 06-08 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Montana Primary, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0461,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>Judge, Stephens Win Gubernatorial Primaries</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs to UPDATE with Melcher quotes; Stephen
winner in GOP gubernatorial primary; UPDATES vote totals in all
races; SUBS 5th graf to CORRECT Faranda's first name to Thomas, sted
Michael; picks up at dash; should stand for AMs.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM KRONHOLM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HELENA, Mont. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s Republicans on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> chose
<PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, a county commissioner from Billings, to challenge
Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>, who smothered an obscure challenge in
his party's primary.
   Former Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON> won the Democratic primary to vie for
the succession of retiring two-term Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>,
and former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON> won the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s gubernatorial
primary to oppose him.
   In the presidential primaries, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
easily outdistanced <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> in the Democratic contest for
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s 19 delegates, while Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> walked away
in <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> voting.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, 64, seeking a third <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> term, put down an
underfinanced and barely visible challenge from <PERSON>Robert Kelleher</PERSON>, a
Billings lawyer.
   Burns beat <PERSON>Thomas Faranda</PERSON>, a Minnesotan who filed for the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>
nomination but gave up his absentee bid weeks ago, though his name
remained on the ballot.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said the difference between him and <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> was experience.
``I think it's pretty obvious I've been here awhile,'' he said.
``He's going to try and say that's a disadvantage, but I don't
really think it is.
   ``The longer you're here, the more chances you have to get bills
passed ... that will benefit <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' he said in a telephone
interview from his suburban outside <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   With 641 of 982 precincts, or <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT>, reporting, <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> had
55,011 votes or <PERCENT>74.7 percent</PERCENT> compared to 18,609 or <PERCENT>25.3 percent</PERCENT> for
<PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON>; <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> had 38,026 votes or <PERCENT>84.0 percent</PERCENT> to 7,270 votes or
<PERCENT>16.0 percent</PERCENT> for Faranda.
   In the Democrats' six-candidate governor's primary, with 626
precincts reporting, or <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT>, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> won with 27,251 votes, or
<PERCENT>39.5 percent</PERCENT>; former <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court Justice Frank Morrison</ORGANIZATION> had 18,806
votes or <PERCENT>27.2 percent</PERCENT> and Attorney General <PERSON>Mike Greeley</PERSON> had 15,607
votes or <PERCENT>22.6 percent</PERCENT>.
   The other three candidates combined for nearly <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of the
vote.
   In the Republican gubernatorial primary, former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan
Stephens</PERSON> won with 25,674 votes, or <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT> to state Rep. <LOCATION>Cal
Winslow</LOCATION>'s 23,168 votes, or <PERCENT>44.2 percent</PERCENT>.
   Also seeking the Democratic gubernatorial nomination were State
<PERSON>Sen. Ted Neuman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Emmett</PERSON> ``Curly'' <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>, an ex-drug addict turned
evangelist, and <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> ``Red'' <PERSON>Beckman</PERSON>, a tax protester.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s Republicans on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> chose
<PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON>, a county commissioner from Billings, to challenge
Democratic <PERSON>Sen. John Melcher</PERSON>, who smothered an obscure challenge in
his party's primary.
   Former Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON> won the Democratic primary to vie for
the succession of retiring two-term Democratic Gov. <PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>,
and former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON> won the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>'s gubernatorial
primary to oppose him.
   In the presidential primaries, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
easily outdistanced <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> in the Democratic contest for
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s 19 delegates, while Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> walked away
in <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> voting.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON>, 64, seeking a third <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> term, put down an
underfinanced and barely visible challenge from <PERSON>Robert Kelleher</PERSON>, a
Billings lawyer.
   Burns beat <PERSON>Thomas Faranda</PERSON>, a Minnesotan who filed for the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>
nomination but gave up his absentee bid weeks ago, though his name
remained on the ballot.
   <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> said the difference between him and <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> was experience.
``I think it's pretty obvious I've been here awhile,'' he said.
``He's going to try and say that's a disadvantage, but I don't
really think it is.
   ``The longer you're here, the more chances you have to get bills
passed ... that will benefit <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>,'' he said in a telephone
interview from his suburban outside <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   With 641 of 982 precincts, or <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT>, reporting, <PERSON>Melcher</PERSON> had
55,011 votes or <PERCENT>74.7 percent</PERCENT> compared to 18,609 or <PERCENT>25.3 percent</PERCENT> for
<PERSON>Kelleher</PERSON>; <PERSON>Burns</PERSON> had 38,026 votes or <PERCENT>84.0 percent</PERCENT> to 7,270 votes or
<PERCENT>16.0 percent</PERCENT> for Faranda.
   In the Democrats' six-candidate governor's primary, with 626
precincts reporting, or <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT>, <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> won with 27,251 votes, or
<PERCENT>39.5 percent</PERCENT>; former <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court Justice Frank Morrison</ORGANIZATION> had 18,806
votes or <PERCENT>27.2 percent</PERCENT> and Attorney General <PERSON>Mike Greeley</PERSON> had 15,607
votes or <PERCENT>22.6 percent</PERCENT>.
   The other three candidates combined for nearly <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of the
vote.
   In the Republican gubernatorial primary, former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan
Stephens</PERSON> won with 25,674 votes, or <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT> to state Rep. <LOCATION>Cal
Winslow</LOCATION>'s 23,168 votes, or <PERCENT>44.2 percent</PERCENT>.
   Also seeking the Democratic gubernatorial nomination were State
<PERSON>Sen. Ted Neuman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Emmett</PERSON> ``Curly'' <PERSON>Thornton</PERSON>, an ex-drug addict turned
evangelist, and <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> ``Red'' <PERSON>Beckman</PERSON>, a tax protester.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880607-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-07-88 1146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-StatePrimariesRdp 1stLd-Writethru a0458 06-07 0820</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-State Primaries Rdp, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0458,0832</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven States Vote In Year's Biggest State Primary Day So Far</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts 1 graf after 5th graf, `New Jersey ...,' to UPDATE
with light turnout today in New Jersey.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Primary voters today narrow the fields in four <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Senate races,
choose nominees for governor of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and pick a black Democratic
candidate for the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> congressional seat occupied by <PERSON>Peter
Rodino</PERSON> for 40 years.
   In other highlights of voting in seven states, Californians
decide a large crop of propositions, including a measure sponsored
by supporters of extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON> that would permit the
state to quarantine AIDS victims. Sacramento voters could become the
first in the nation to close a nuclear power plant, the troubled
Rancho Seco; and voters in <LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION> _ the nation's
largest _ will decide whether to carve away the eastern, desert
portion to create a new county called Mojave.
   In <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, the nation's seventh-largest city, Mayor <PERSON>Maureen
O'Connor</PERSON> is expected to win a four-year term by gaining a majority
in the nonpartisan primary. She was first elected two years ago
after Mayor <PERSON>Roger Hedgecock</PERSON> was convicted of a felony and forced to
resign.
   Both of the nation's first-term Democrats are among the senators
with a stake in today's races, and both have been targeted as
vulnerable by the national <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Frank Lautenberg</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> has
two little-known primary opponents, and <PERSON>Jeff Bingaman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>
has none.
   New Jersey Republicans have united behind a single nominee, <PERSON>Peter
Dawkins</PERSON>, a former Heisman trophy winner, <PERSON>Rhodes</PERSON> scholar and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
war hero who moved to the state to enter the race.
   Voting officials in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> reported a light turnout <TIME>this
morning</TIME> for the primary races.
   In <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, four Republicans are competing for the chance to
face <PERSON>Bingaman</PERSON>. A poll taken last week for the <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION> Journal
showed state <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> leading the field with support of
<PERCENT>29.5 percent</PERCENT> of Republicans, but <PERCENT>38.9 percent</PERCENT> were undecided.
   A third first-term senator seeking re-election is Republican <PERSON>Pete
Wilson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. He has no primary competition, but does have a
jinx to worry about _ for 30 years, no one holding his <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> seat
has been elected more than once. On the Democratic side, Lt. Gov.
<PERSON>Leo McCarthy</PERSON> is expected to dispatch three little-known opponents.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> also has a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> race, with two-term Democrat <PERSON>John
Melcher</PERSON> opposed in the primary by attorney <PERSON>Robert Kelleher</PERSON>, who
advocates a parliamentary form of government. Yellowstone County
Commissioner <PERSON>Conrad Burns</PERSON> is the only <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> entrant.
   But the liveliest race in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> is for governor, since Democrat
<PERSON>Ted Schwinden</PERSON>'s decision to retire after two terms has left the
ballot without an incumbent for the first time in 20 years.
   The six-way Democratic field features a comeback bid by former
Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Judge</PERSON>, who served two terms before losing to Schwinden
in the <DATE>primary eight years ago</DATE>. A <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> Poll taken last week
showed <PERSON>Judge</PERSON> was the choice of <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT> of Democratic voters, but
<PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> were undecided.
   In the two-way Republican race, the poll showed a dead heat
between former state <PERSON>Sen. Stan Stephens</PERSON> and state Rep. <LOCATION>Cal Winslow</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> favorite, Secretary of State <PERSON>Jim Waltermire</PERSON>, was killed in a
plane crash in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   The retirement of <PERSON>Rodino</PERSON>, whose 79th birthday is today, comes
amid growing sentiment that his predominantly black district should
be represented by the state's first black congressman. Two black
<LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION> city councilmen, <PERSON>Donald Payne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ralph Grant</PERSON>, are competing
in the Democratic primary, with the winner expected to defeat the
<ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> nominee, political newcomer <PERSON>Michael Webb</PERSON>, who also is black.
   Here is a look at the other states voting today:
   <LOCATION>ALABAMA</LOCATION> _ Democratic Reps. <PERSON>Claude Harris</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Tuscaloosa</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bill
Nichols</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Sylacauga</LOCATION> are favored to turn back primary challenges.
   Races for three <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> seats have turned into unusually
rough-and-tumble scraps in which big business and insurance
companies are backing one slate of Democrats, while trial lawyers
and less conservative interests are backing another. One of the
candidates with trial lawyer support is Circuit <PERSON>Judge Mark Kennedy</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, a son-in-law of former Gov. <PERSON>George C. Wallace</PERSON>. He is
running against <LOCATION>Anniston</LOCATION> lawyer <PERSON>A.W. Bolt</PERSON>, who is supported by
business lobbies, for an associate justice post.
   IOWA _ Sixteen LaRouche supporters are running in Democratic
primaries, five for congressional nominations and the rest in state
legislative districts. Four Democrats are seeking the nomination to
oppose first-term GOP Rep. <PERSON>Fred Grandy</PERSON>, who for years played Gopher
on television's ``The Love Boat.''
   SOUTH <LOCATION>DAKOTA</LOCATION> _ The state is having one of its quietest elections
in memory, with no statewide races on the ballot. And there are only
26 primary races for the 105 state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats. The
state's lone congressman, Democratic Rep. <PERSON>Tim Johnson</PERSON>, is unopposed
in the primary as is his Republican challenger, state Treasurer
<PERSON>David Volk</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900605-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-05-90 1603EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-PrimariesRdp 3rdLd-Writethru a0625 06-05 1106</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Primaries Rdp, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0625,1135</SECOND>
<HEAD>California, 8 Other States Vote in Busiest Spring Primary Day</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS in 3rd graf that Gantt would be first black nominated
for Senate in NC, not any statewide office; Polls close beginning at
7:30 p.m. EDT in North Carolina; matter below the dash should stand.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Covering</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dianne Feinstein</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Van de Kamp</PERSON> brawled to the wire for one
of <DATE>1990</DATE>'s biggest political prizes, the Democratic nomination for
governor of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and voters set lineups <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for fall
contests in eight other states.
   The busiest primary night so far this campaign year saw <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> Democrats deciding whether former <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Harvey
Gantt</PERSON> or county prosecutor <PERSON>Mike Easley</PERSON> would get the formidable task
of challenging Republican <PERSON>Sen. Jesse Helms</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON> was bidding to become the first black nominated for <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> <DATE>this century</DATE>.
   ``I'm ready to get into this fight'' with <PERSON>Helms</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON> said as he
cast his own ballot. ``I'm ready to get it on with him.''
   <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON>, the former mayor of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, and Van de Kamp,
the state attorney general, have spent <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> battling
each other and now the winner will plunge into an even more costly
and just as nasty general election race against Republican <PERSON>Sen. Pete
Wilson</PERSON>. He is trying to keep the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> governor's office in <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>
control.
   Voters also were choosing nominees in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   As usual, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> voters also were making decisions on ballot
propositions, including two that would strip the legislature of most
of its power to redraw legislative, including congressional,
district lines. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is likely to gain six <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House</ORGANIZATION> seats as
a result of the <DATE>1990</DATE> Census.
   Another <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> ballot proposal would double the gasoline tax
over the next five years and was being watched as a signal of a
shift in sentiment in the state where the anti-tax revolt began in
the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   Seven senators and three governors were on ballots, none with
serious primary opposition.
   The senators were Democrats <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Howell
Heflin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Max Baucus</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Tom Harkin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. The
Republicans were <PERSON>Larry Pressler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pete Domenici</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Thad Cochran</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   Long in advance of their formal nomination in the primary, <PERSON>Harkin</PERSON>
and Republican Rep. <PERSON>Tom Tauke</PERSON> began campaigning against each other
in what looks like one of the tightest <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> races of the year.
   Alabama Republican <PERSON>Bill Cabannis</PERSON> was geared to challenge <PERSON>Heflin</PERSON>
and Democrat <PERSON>Ted Muenster</PERSON> was taking on Pressler in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON> and businessman <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>
were the leading contenders for the Republican nomination to
challenge <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>.
   Scores of primaries also were deciding the lineups for elections
to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. One incumbent who faced a strong challenge was
Democratic Rep. <PERSON>Jim Bates</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, who was rebuked by the <ORGANIZATION>House
Ethics Committee</ORGANIZATION> for sexual harassment of women employees.
   One of the hottest primaries for a congressional seat was in the
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> district represented by <PERSON>James Courter</PERSON>, the unsuccessful
GOP candidate for governor in <DATE>1989</DATE>. Courter is not seeking
re-election to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and the Republican contenders to succeed
him include Assemblyman <PERSON>Rodney Frelinghuysen</PERSON>, state <PERSON>Sen. Richard A.
Zimmer</PERSON> and professional football player <PERSON>Phil McConkey</PERSON>.
   Gov. Guy Hunt of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, the first Republican elected to that
office this century, was bidding for a second term and a crowded
field of Democrats was vying to challenge him.
   Former Gov. <PERSON>Fob James</PERSON>, educator-lobbyist <PERSON>Paul Hubbert</PERSON>, Rep.
<PERSON>Ronnie Flippo</PERSON>, and Attorney General <PERSON>Don Siegelman</PERSON> were the leading
contenders. No one was expected to get the clear majority needed to
avoid a <DATE>June 26</DATE> runoff.
   In a race in which abortion was a major issue, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> Democrats
were choosing among Attorney General <PERSON>Tom Miller</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Speaker <PERSON>Don
Avenson</PERSON> and banker <PERSON>John Chrystal</PERSON> for the nomination to challenge
Republican Gov. <PERSON>Terry Branstad</PERSON>.
   Avenson and <PERSON>Chrystal</PERSON> support the pro-choice position, while
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Branstad</PERSON> are abortion opponents.
   Republican Gov. <PERSON>Garrey Carruthers</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> was ineligible to
seek re-election. Four Democrats, including former Gov. <PERSON>Bruce King</PERSON>,
and four Republicans were competing to succeed him. The next
governor will be the first allowed to serve two consecutive
four-year terms.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Dianne Feinstein</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Van de Kamp</PERSON> brawled to the wire for one
of <DATE>1990</DATE>'s biggest political prizes, the Democratic nomination for
governor of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and voters set lineups <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for fall
contests in eight other states.
   The busiest primary night so far this campaign year saw <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> Democrats deciding whether former <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Harvey
Gantt</PERSON> or county prosecutor <PERSON>Mike Easley</PERSON> would get the formidable task
of challenging Republican <PERSON>Sen. Jesse Helms</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON> was bidding to become the first black nominated for <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> <DATE>this century</DATE>.
   ``I'm ready to get into this fight'' with <PERSON>Helms</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gantt</PERSON> said as he
cast his own ballot. ``I'm ready to get it on with him.''
   <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON>, the former mayor of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, and Van de Kamp,
the state attorney general, have spent <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> battling
each other and now the winner will plunge into an even more costly
and just as nasty general election race against Republican <PERSON>Sen. Pete
Wilson</PERSON>. He is trying to keep the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> governor's office in <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION>
control.
   Voters also were choosing nominees in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   As usual, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> voters also were making decisions on ballot
propositions, including two that would strip the legislature of most
of its power to redraw legislative, including congressional,
district lines. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is likely to gain six <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House</ORGANIZATION> seats as
a result of the <DATE>1990</DATE> Census.
   Another <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> ballot proposal would double the gasoline tax
over the next five years and was being watched as a signal of a
shift in sentiment in the state where the anti-tax revolt began in
the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   Seven senators and three governors were on ballots, none with
serious primary opposition.
   The senators were Democrats <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Howell
Heflin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Max Baucus</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Tom Harkin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. The
Republicans were <PERSON>Larry Pressler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pete Domenici</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Thad Cochran</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>.
   Long in advance of their formal nomination in the primary, <PERSON>Harkin</PERSON>
and Republican Rep. <PERSON>Tom Tauke</PERSON> began campaigning against each other
in what looks like one of the tightest <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> races of the year.
   Alabama Republican <PERSON>Bill Cabannis</PERSON> was geared to challenge <PERSON>Heflin</PERSON>
and Democrat <PERSON>Ted Muenster</PERSON> was taking on Pressler in <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Allen Kolstad</PERSON> and businessman <PERSON>Bruce Vorhauer</PERSON>
were the leading contenders for the Republican nomination to
challenge <PERSON>Baucus</PERSON>.
   Scores of primaries also were deciding the lineups for elections
to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. One incumbent who faced a strong challenge was
Democratic Rep. <PERSON>Jim Bates</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, who was rebuked by the <ORGANIZATION>House
Ethics Committee</ORGANIZATION> for sexual harassment of women employees.
   One of the hottest primaries for a congressional seat was in the
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> district represented by <PERSON>James Courter</PERSON>, the unsuccessful
GOP candidate for governor in <DATE>1989</DATE>. Courter is not seeking
re-election to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and the Republican contenders to succeed
him include Assemblyman <PERSON>Rodney Frelinghuysen</PERSON>, state <PERSON>Sen. Richard A.
Zimmer</PERSON> and professional football player <PERSON>Phil McConkey</PERSON>.
   Gov. Guy Hunt of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, the first Republican elected to that
office this century, was bidding for a second term and a crowded
field of Democrats was vying to challenge him.
   Former Gov. <PERSON>Fob James</PERSON>, educator-lobbyist <PERSON>Paul Hubbert</PERSON>, Rep.
<PERSON>Ronnie Flippo</PERSON>, and Attorney General <PERSON>Don Siegelman</PERSON> were the leading
contenders. No one was expected to get the clear majority needed to
avoid a <DATE>June 26</DATE> runoff.
   In a race in which abortion was a major issue, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> Democrats
were choosing among Attorney General <PERSON>Tom Miller</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Speaker <PERSON>Don
Avenson</PERSON> and banker <PERSON>John Chrystal</PERSON> for the nomination to challenge
Republican Gov. <PERSON>Terry Branstad</PERSON>.
   Avenson and <PERSON>Chrystal</PERSON> support the pro-choice position, while
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> and <PERSON>Branstad</PERSON> are abortion opponents.
   Republican Gov. <PERSON>Garrey Carruthers</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> was ineligible to
seek re-election. Four Democrats, including former Gov. <PERSON>Bruce King</PERSON>,
and four Republicans were competing to succeed him. The next
governor will be the first allowed to serve two consecutive
four-year terms.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880604-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-04-88 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-StatePrimariesRdp Bjt   06-04 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-State Primaries Rdp, Bjt,0784</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seven States Vote In Year's Biggest State Primary Day So Far</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE SILVERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Skirmishes over four <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Senate seats, a wide-open race for
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> governor and a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> potpourri of propositions
highlight the ballots in seven states <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the busiest state
primary day so far in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, two black Democrats are competing for their
party's nomination to the congressional seat being vacated by <PERSON>Peter
Rodino</PERSON> after 40 years. In <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>Maureen O'Connor</PERSON> is
overwhelmingly favored to win election in a nonpartisan race to a
full four-year term.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> propositions include statewide measures that would
permit the quarantining of AIDS victims, ease the government
spending limits imposed by Proposition 13 a decade ago, and cap
runaway spending on political campaigns.
   In local measures of note, <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> voters could become the
first in the nation to close a nuclear power plant, the troubled
Rancho Seco facility; and voters in <LOCATION>San Bernardino County</LOCATION> _ the
nation's largest county _ will decide whether to carve away the
eastern, desert portion to create a new county called Mojave.
   The most hotly contested <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> primary is in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, where
four Republicans think first-term Democratic <PERSON>Sen. Jeff Bingaman</PERSON> is
vulnerable because of his liberal voting record in a state that
strongly supports defense spending. State <PERSON>Sen. Bill Valentine</PERSON> and
longtime party activist <PERSON>Corky Morris</PERSON> have held the lead in polls for
