<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061189-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 68653 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 11, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part 7; Page 18; Column 3; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
669 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
YOUTH BEAT: AUSTRALIA OPENS THREE NEW LOW-COST HOSTELS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LUCY IZON, Izon is a Canadian travel journalist covering youth budget 
routes. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Three key Australian cities -- <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and Cairns -- have new hostels 
for budget travelers. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, it's not just the youth hostel that's appealing. One of the city's 
charms is that it offers visitors the opportunity to take in city sights and 
enjoy the beach life as well. 
</P>
<P>
You can start your day in the central city area with a visit to the Australian 
Museum and a walking tour through the 200-year-old historic district known as 
"The Rocks." 
</P>
<P>
Then you can take a 10-minute ferry trip across the harbor to <LOCATION>Manly Beach</LOCATION>, or 
grab a bus to the popular surfing suburb of <LOCATION>Bondi Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>'s new flagship youth hostel, <ORGANIZATION>Hereford Lodge</ORGANIZATION>, has a pool, sauna, rooftop 
recreation area, TV and video lounge, plus a low-cost cafeteria. It's at 51 
<ORGANIZATION>Hereford St.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Glebe</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The hostel has 92 rooms. The price per person in a twin room is about <MONEY>$14</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> Cup 
</P>
<P>
If you want to experience the exciting atmosphere of one of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s premier 
sports events, plan to be in the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> area on the first <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in 
<DATE>November</DATE>. The city comes to a halt as everyone focuses attention on <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s 
most important horse race, the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> Cup. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> area is also one of the most popular spots to enjoy another 
Australian custom -- the BYO (bring your own) restaurants. These are 
establishments that allow you to furnish your own wine or beer to enjoy with 
your meal. The minimum drinking age in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is 18. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>'s new youth hostel is at 118 <ORGANIZATION>Lonsdale St.</ORGANIZATION> It can accommodate up to 
140 people, who are charged <MONEY>$13</MONEY> each night. 
</P>
<P>
Cairns, on <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s northeastern coast, draws travelers to investigate the 
Great Barrier Reef. The town has several hostels that compete for business from 
young visitors. In addition to accommodations, they offer opportunities for 
economical trips to the rain forest, plus river rafting and sailing adventures. 
</P>
<P>
The new Cairns youth hostel is at 20-24 McLeon St. just opposite the railway 
station. The single-room rate is <MONEY>$12</MONEY> a night. A bed in a twin room costs <MONEY>$9</MONEY>, 
while a bed in a dormitory room is <MONEY>$7</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
All three youth hostels are members of a network of 130 Australian hostels 
affiliated with the <ORGANIZATION>International Youth Hostel Federation</ORGANIZATION>. If you are not a 
member of your own national youth hostel association, they may request that you 
buy a guest membership, or pay a few dollars extra per night. There are no age 
restrictions. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> also has many independent budget-priced hostels. They tend to supply 
information about each other, so once you start using them you can find out 
about others. 
</P>
<P>
The youth hostels offer young travelers a good place to exchange information 
and develop friendships. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
On-Site Vans 
</P>
<P>
When several people begin to travel together, the variety of opportunities 
expand. You can begin to consider new options such as buying a cheap car and 
making more use of campgrounds, where you'll discover another Australian 
novelty, the on-site van. 
</P>
<P>
These are recreational vehicles parked in permanent positions in campgrounds; 
you can rent them by the night or week. 
</P>
<P>
One free source of information about budget accommodations, including some 
youth hostels, budget hotels, tourist homes and campgrounds, is a publication 
called "Destination <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
The guide also covers basic information on what to see and do in key tourism 
areas, and offers advice on a variety of services such as bus passes and tour 
operators. Copies are available from the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Tourist Commission</ORGANIZATION>, 2121 
Avenue of the Stars, Suite 1200, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 90067, (213) 552-1988. 
</P>
<P>
If you need to make transportation arrangements after you arrive in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 
keep in mind that <ORGANIZATION>STA Travel</ORGANIZATION> (formerly Student Travel <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>) has offices in 
<LOCATION>Hobart</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Townsville</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The company specializes in services for all young travelers. They also have a 
network of offices in other countries, including <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, so they can help 
with arrangements and information when you want to move on from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-28236 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas111_q_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-111 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> AUSTRALASIA </F>
<F P=101> Australia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Qantas To Increase Flights From Melbourne </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Qantas To Increase Flights From Melbourne </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0606072494 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0500 GMT 6 
Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0606072494 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Direct air links between <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> are 
set to be restored. State political reporter <PERSON>Tony Allen</PERSON> says it 
follows meetings between Victorian Premier <PERSON>Jeff Kennett</PERSON> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s international airline, <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION>. 
  [Begin recording] [<PERSON>Allen</PERSON>] <PERSON>Mr. Kennett</PERSON> declared a personal 
black ban on <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ansett</ORGANIZATION> international services to 
illustrate his concern at the airlines using <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> as their 
base. Now, after talks with <PERSON>Mr. Kennett</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> has announced a 
plan for a weekly direct flight to <LOCATION>Osaka</LOCATION>'s new <LOCATION>Kansai Airport</LOCATION>. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Kennett</PERSON> said it takes up an unused <ORGANIZATION>Ansett</ORGANIZATION> right that 
expires in <DATE>November</DATE>. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Kennett</ORGANIZATION>] And we will support <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> to get that flight 
awarded to <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION>. If that is the case, then we are able then 
to establish ourselves and to (?prove) up the value of that 
flight. [end recording] 
  As well, <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> will add three new flights from <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> via <LOCATION>Auckland</LOCATION> from the end of <DATE>October</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> says 
it is more expensive to fly from <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> than from the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> tourist markets, but if the new flights prove a 
success, there will be more. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100390-0131 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 287151 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 3, 1990, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part P; Page 3; Column 3; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
335 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MURDOCH MERGES 4 NEWSPAPERS INTO 2 IN RESCUE EFFORT; 
</P>
<P>
AUSTRALIA: FIRM'S STOCK TUMBLES 40% IN A MONTH AMID CONCERN OVER ITS MASSIVE 
$8.7-BILLION DEBT. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MELBOURNE, Australia 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's debt-laden News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> it will merge its four <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> newspapers into two 24-hour publications to avoid shutting down 
its struggling afternoon dailies. 
</P>
<P>
Industry analysts said the move, effective <DATE>Monday</DATE>, will likely ease pressure on 
<ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, whose stock price has tumbled about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> in the last month on 
investor concern about its massive <MONEY>$8.7-billion</MONEY> debt. 
</P>
<P>
The merger of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s best-selling newspaper, the <ORGANIZATION>Melbourne Sun</ORGANIZATION>, with the 
city's struggling afternoon broadsheet the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>'s tabloids, the 
morning Daily Telegraph and ailing afternoon Daily Mirror, will mean the loss 
of about 180 jobs. 
</P>
<P>
"As an alternative to closing either (afternoon) paper, it will save well over 
800, probably 1,000 jobs as well as giving the public continuing afternoon 
newspaper service," <PERSON>Murdoch</PERSON> said at a news conference in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I expect the savings to be quite considerable," he said. "I think it is a 
business benefit in that it should improve the overall profit of the company." 
</P>
<P>
Murdoch declined to comment either about the recent plunge in <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s 
stock price, which has wiped about <MONEY>$515 million</MONEY> off its market value, or a 
sharp rise in the group's short-term debt. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Murdoch</PERSON> said the changes are linked with News' <MONEY>$830-million</MONEY> investment in 
high-technology color printing plants in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Murdoch, now an American citizen who spends little time in his native 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, is on an extended visit that will include the company's <DATE>Oct. 23</DATE> 
annual meeting in <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> said he welcomes the merger. "It will probably mean a 
loss of jobs for some people, but as far as the community in general is 
concerned, they probably will get a better service," he told reporters in 
<LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The merger of the <ORGANIZATION>Melbourne Sun</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> will create the <ORGANIZATION>Herald-Sun</ORGANIZATION> with 
circulation estimated to reach 600,000, he said. Currently, the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> sells 
175,634 copies a day and the morning Sun 560,444. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Rupert Murdoch Reuters 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-13811</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJZDWAC2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941026
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 OCT 94 / Business and the Environment: A rumbling in the waterworks -
Jane Martinson on attracting tourists to a sewage plant
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JANE MARTINSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Managers of a sewage treatment plant in south-east <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> are considering
plans to turn it into a tourist attraction.
The 10,851 ha plant - which produces more beef than any farm in the region -
treats 55 per cent of the wastewater generated by the city of <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
Natural purification methods rather than chemical treatment are used to
produce effluent, which is deposited in <LOCATION>Port Phillip Bay</LOCATION>. Some 16,000 cattle
graze the grass fertilised by raw sewage; livestock generated just over
ADollars 3m (Pounds 1.4m) in income last year.
Much of the sewage is treated in lagoons, which cover 1,667 ha at the
Werribee site, 35 km south-west of <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. Three large lagoons built in
the past six years have been designed to control odour and produce biogas.
Mechanical aerators speed up the process of digestion and reduce odour,
while covers are being installed to capture methane and other odorous gases.
The methane will eventually be burnt off to generate power.
The plan to create an 'eco-tourist park' focuses on 600 ha of older lagoons.
Over 250 species of birds are found around them. Many rare species have been
recorded, including up to 50 per cent of the world's total of the
orange-bellied parrot.
as a wetland of international importance.
A study conducted this <DATE>summer</DATE> by <LOCATION>Melbourne Parks</LOCATION> and Waterways claimed the
sewage plant could attract up to 160,000 tourists a year if developed as an
eco-tourist park. The organisation manages a funding programme which aims to
encourage community use of open spaces and the preservation of wildlife.
Last year it allocated ADollars 6.2m to such schemes.
Melbourne Water, the state-owned authority which manages Werribee, says
there is 'definite commercial potential there' and has commissioned a full
economic analysis of the project.
There are a number of advantages to the plan, not least enhanced public
relations. <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>'s sewers, with their network of old brick tunnels,
suffered three serious collapses two years ago. Sewage spilled into a local
river and it took more than three months to stem the flow.
has decreed that checks on effluent discharges into <LOCATION>Port Phillip Bay</LOCATION> are to
be made much more stringent by <DATE>2004</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Melbourne Water</ORGANIZATION> has committed itself to
complying with the regulations by <DATE>1997</DATE>. It has also earmarked ADollars 32m
for upgrading its two major treatment plants.
The impact on wildlife of a significant increase in visitor numbers is
causing some concern, however. <PERSON>Alex Sandles</PERSON>, the wastewater treatment
manager at <LOCATION>Werribee</LOCATION>, says birds are attracted by the food, security and calm
of the plant. 'The lakes near here tend to be full of waterskiers and other
noise.'
The plan has some support among environment groups. <PERSON>Karri Giles</PERSON>, water
catchment manager for Friends of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, says: 'We are
positive as long as it is done sensitively.'
However, the proposal may be delayed by the shake-up planned for <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>
Water by a state government keen on privatisation. It was to appear before
the authority's board in <DATE>November</DATE>.
Nonetheless, Sandles feels the plan will be implemented. Werribee treatment
plant could become part of a 'complete weekend package' for <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>'s
tourists, he says.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P4952 Sewerage Systems.
    P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Services &amp; Services use.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-10538</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EBIDBACVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940209
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  09 FEB 94 / People: Melbourn promoted at NatWest
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
A chain of moves in the top management of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster Bank</ORGANIZATION> was
disclosed yesterday, led by the appointment of <PERSON>John Melbourn</PERSON>, the bank's
head of group risk, to succeed <PERSON>Bert Morris</PERSON> as the bank's deputy chief
executive.
The reshuffle is one of the most significant changes to the bank's senior
roster since <PERSON>Derek Wanless</PERSON> was appointed chief executive in <DATE>1992</DATE>. The
changes, which all involve bank insiders, will take place from <DATE>March 1</DATE>.
Melbourn, a 56-year-old who was thought to be a contender for the chief
executive's job when <PERSON>Derek Wanless</PERSON> was appointed, is one of the bank's most
experienced hands, having headed international operations and its
relationships with large companies.
<PERSON>Wanless</PERSON> says that <PERSON>Melbourn</PERSON> is 'a tremendous banker' who would bring a wide
range of experience to the post. Melbourn will work alongside <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> until
<DATE>September</DATE>, when the latter is due to retire.
Melbourn will retain board responsibility for credit risk, and the handling
of large corporate restructurings. But his current deputy, <PERSON>Fred Pointon</PERSON>, has
been appointed to the post of general manager of group risk in his place.
A second significant change announced yesterday is the appointment of <PERSON>Phil
Wise</PERSON>, the current chief executive of group services, as chief operating
officer at <ORGANIZATION>NatWest Markets</ORGANIZATION>, the bank's corporate and investment banking arm.
Wise, 45, has worked with <PERSON>Martin Owen</PERSON>, the chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>NatWest
Markets</ORGANIZATION>, before when the men brought together the bank's treasury
operations.
Like other securities houses, <ORGANIZATION>NatWest Markets</ORGANIZATION> had a good year amid buoyant
bond and equity markets. Wanless has signalled that the bank is considering
ways of building on its investment banking business to help raise revenues.
<ORGANIZATION>NatWest Markets</ORGANIZATION>' two senior managing directors, <PERSON>Roger Byatt</PERSON> and <PERSON>John
Howland-Jackson</PERSON>, have been appointed deputy chief executives. Wise will be
succeeded at group services by <PERSON>Trevor Blackler</PERSON>, general manager of UK branch
business. <PERSON>Stuart Chandler</PERSON>, general manager for human resources and strategic
development, has been appointed to the new post of deputy chief executive
for UK branch business with responsibility for technology and human
resources.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6021 National Commercial Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  Appointments.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 18
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-835</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EI0DNAFVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940927
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 SEP 94 / International Company News: Media groups to merge networks
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION>, the Australian radio group, and the entertainment group <ORGANIZATION>Village
Roadshow</ORGANIZATION>, which were involved in a hostile takeover bid last week, have
agreed to merge their radio networks, <ORGANIZATION>Reuter</ORGANIZATION> reports from <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
In place of its hostile bid, Village will acquire at least 50.1 per cent of
<ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> in two stages via a placement and a partial bid at ADollars 0.55
(USDollars 0.40) a share higher than <ORGANIZATION>Village</ORGANIZATION>'s first offer.
<ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> will issue 52.5m shares to Village and Village will offer ADollars
1.75 a share for 20 per cent of each <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION>'s shareholder's existing
stake.
Village Roadshow's original takeover offer for <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> was ADollars 1.20 a
share, but the market soon moved above this level and on <DATE>Friday</DATE> the shares
closed at ADollars 1.35.
Austereo shares were suspended yesterday at the company's request.
The <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> share issue, together with <ORGANIZATION>Village Roadshow</ORGANIZATION>'s current 12.8 per
cent stake, will take <ORGANIZATION>Village</ORGANIZATION>'s shareholding to 40.8 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION>'s
enlarged capital.
Under the deal, <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> will purchase Village's Triple M radio stations in
<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, and may acquire Triple M in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>
by means of the share issue.
The Triple M stations will join the current <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> network comprising
seven stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>.
The merger is subject to clearance by the anti-monopoly <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices
Commission</ORGANIZATION> and approval by <ORGANIZATION>Austereo</ORGANIZATION> shareholders.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Austereo.
    Village Roadshow.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P4832 Radio Broadcasting Stations.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
    FIN  Share issues.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-13439</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CAUBNAF7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920121
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 JAN 92 / International Company News: Melbourne bank plunges into red
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BRUCE JACQUES
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
BANK OF <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, one of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s newest licensed banks, plunged into
the red in the <DATE>December half</DATE>, reflecting its exposure to the
Occidental/Regal life insurance crash, writes <PERSON>Bruce Jacques</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
The bank yesterday disclosed it had suffered a loss of ADollars 21.1m
(USDollars 15.5m) in the half, against a ADollars 13.1m profit last time.
The loss followed a ADollars 65m pay-out to the judicial manager of the two
life companies after the bank settled a prolonged legal action.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 24
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-14305</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJXDSACKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941024
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  24 OCT 94 / This Week: Cricket
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN WRAIGHT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Bouncers were bowled at <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> cricket captain <PERSON>Mike Atherton</PERSON> as soon as the
team landed in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>, where the first match of the tour will be played
tomorrow. This time the fast balls came from the Australian press and the
hot topic was sledging - players verbally abusing opponents at the crease.
Atherton was questioned fiercely about a statement he is alleged to have
made after the last Ashes series in <DATE>1993</DATE>. 'The one who really got up my nose
was <PERSON>Steve Waugh</PERSON>,' <PERSON>Atherton</PERSON> is said to have said. 'He spent the entire series
giving out verbals - a bit of a joke really as he was the one bloke on
either side who was wetting himself against the quick bowlers.'
Atherton now claims he cannot remember making the comments, but the issue
highlights two things that will determine <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s success in the coming
Ashes battle: team spirit (sledging or no sledging) and fast bowling.
'Ashes to Ashes, dust to dust, if <PERSON>Lillee</PERSON> doesn't get you, <ORGANIZATION>Thomson</ORGANIZATION> must.'
That was a chant that turned many an <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> supporter's blood to ice, and
it has been traditional that the side with the best fast bowlers wins Test
series in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
Atherton will be hoping that the tradition is maintained, because this time
round it is <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> that have the stronger pace attack. However, <PERSON>Devon
Malcolm</PERSON>, <PERSON>Phillip DeFreitas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Darren Gough</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Martin McCague</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Joey Benjamin</PERSON>
will need to be at their best, for <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> seem to be stronger in every
other department, including team character.
Firing up the troops to take on the ancient enemy has never been an
Australian problem. As <PERSON>Graham Gooch</PERSON> lamented last year: 'Our spirit is
nothing like their's' <PERSON>Atherton</PERSON> will be aware that developing the team's
character will be as important as his other duties if he is to interrupt one
of the worst spells - for <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> - since <PERSON>James Lilleywhite</PERSON> first led an
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> touring side to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1877</DATE>. The last three Ashes series have
finished 4-0, 3-0 and 4-1 in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s favour.
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
                     ENGLAND'S TOUR OF <LOCATION>AUSTRALIA</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
OCTOBER
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Date              Match                          Venue
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Tue 25            England     v Chairman's XI    Lilac Hill. <LOCATION>Perth
Thu 27            England</LOCATION>     v W. <LOCATION>Australia                 Perth</LOCATION>**
Sat 29-Tue 1      <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v W. <LOCATION>Australia                 Perth</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
NOVEMBER
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Fri 4-Mon 7       <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v <ORGANIZATION>S. Australia              Adelaide
Wed 9             England</ORGANIZATION>     v Prime Minister's XI       <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>
Sat 12-Tue 15     England     v <ORGANIZATION>New South Wales          Newcastle
Fri</ORGANIZATION> 18-Mon 21     England     v Australian XI              Holbart
Fri 25-Tue 29     <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v 1st TEST                  <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
DECEMBER
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Fri 2             <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                    <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>**
Fri 2             <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v <ORGANIZATION>Bradman XI                  Bowral
Sun</ORGANIZATION> 4             <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                    <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>
Sun 4             England     v ACT                       <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>
Tue 6             <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>*                    <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>**
Tue 6             <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                  Holbart
Fri 9-Sun 11      <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v Cricket <PERSON>Academy          N. Sydney</PERSON>
Sat 10            <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> A v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                 <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>
Sun 11            <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> A*              <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>
Tue 13            <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> A v <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>*                 <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>**
Thu 15            <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                   <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>**
Sat 17-Tue 20     England     v <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>                Toowooba
Sat 24-Thu 29     2nd TEST                               <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
JANUARY
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Sun 1-Thu 5       3rd TEST                                  <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>
Sat 7             <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>*                 <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>
Sun 8             <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> A*              <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>
Tue 10            <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>   v <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>*                 <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>**
Thu 12            <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> A v ENgland*                    <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>**
Sun 15            1st FINAL*                                <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>**
Tue 17            2nd FINAL*                             <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>**
Thu 19            3rd FINAL*                             <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>**
Sat 21-Mon 23     <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>     v <ORGANIZATION>Victoria                   Bendigo
Thu</ORGANIZATION> 26-Mon 30     4th TEST                                <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
FEBRUARY
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
Fri 3-Tue 7       5th TEST                                   <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>
 -------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7941 Sports Clubs, Managers, and Promoters.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-10214</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBGA3ACIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920207
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 FEB 92 / International Company News: Bank of Melbourne changes share
issue
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
BANK of <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> said it will make a one-for-four rights issue instead of
the convertible preference share issue it announced on <DATE>January 20</DATE>, Reuter
reports from <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
The bank said it believed a rights issue would be in the better interests of
shareholders after the Australian Tax Office cast doubts on the franking of
preference share dividends.
The bank said a prospectus was expected to be released in early <DATE>March</DATE>.
<ORGANIZATION>Bank of Melbourne</ORGANIZATION> shares closed <MONEY>4 cents</MONEY> firmer at ADollars 4.35. The bank
has 79.27m shares on issue.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-7610</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EKXDRABFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941124
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  24 NOV 94 / Oil groups sued in Australia
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
Shell <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, both part of the larger international oil
groups, are being sued by the <ORGANIZATION>Trade Practices Commission</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
competition watchdog, over alleged price collusion in the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> retail petrol markets. Shell issued a statement yesterday stating
that it would 'mount a vigorous defence' against allegations that it
colluded with other oil companies to increase retail petroleum prices in
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> between <DATE>1988</DATE> and <DATE>1991</DATE>. BP <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> confirmed that it,
too, was served with legal proceedings by the <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> yesterday. These,
it said, alleged certain anti-competitive practices in the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> motor spirit markets between <DATE>May 1991</DATE> and <DATE>June 1992</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Shell Australia.
    BP Australia.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9651 Regulation of Miscellaneous Commercial Sectors.
    P2911 Petroleum Refining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COSTS  Product costs &amp; Product prices.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-3083 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi051_v_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-051 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> TAIWAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Taipei, Australia To Hold Talks on Expanding Air Links </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW1603082294 Taipei CNA in English 0656 GMT 16 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1603082294 </F>
<F P=104>  Taipei CNA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <PERSON>Peter Chen</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 16</DATE> (CNA) -- <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and the 
Republic of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> [ROC] are scheduled to hold talks in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> 
later this month to discuss expansion of the current air links 
between the two countries, the <ORGANIZATION>Taipei Economic and Cultural 
Office</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>TECO</ORGANIZATION>) in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [16 <DATE>March</DATE>]. 
  TECO Representative <PERSON>Francias Li</PERSON> said the ROC delegation 
would 
be led by Sun Chao-liang, director-general of the <ORGANIZATION>Civil 
Aeronautics Administration</ORGANIZATION>, and his Australian counterpart would 
be <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s representative in <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>. 
  Officials from the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Transport Department</ORGANIZATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Asia Airlines</ORGANIZATION> (AAA), <LOCATION>Eva Air</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mandarin Airways</ORGANIZATION> 
will take part in the two-day meetings on <DATE>March 24</DATE> and 25. 
  Li said the <ORGANIZATION>ROC</ORGANIZATION> delegates are expected to arrive in 
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> 
on <DATE>March 23</DATE>. 
  "The purpose of the meeting is to discuss bilateral 
expansion 
of the current air links between our two countries," he said. 
  He said the issue was first raised by the officials of <ORGANIZATION>AAA</ORGANIZATION>, 
a 
subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>Qantas Airways</ORGANIZATION>, last year. 
  Australia signed an aviation agreement with the ROC in early 
<DATE>1991</DATE>. 
  AAA inaugurated its flights to <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> on <DATE>October 11</DATE> the same year. 
  <ORGANIZATION>Mandarin Airways</ORGANIZATION> followed suit a week later with direct 
flights between <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. Eva air started flying to 
<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> in <DATE>September 1993</DATE>. 
  Under the <DATE>1991</DATE> agreement, airlines from the two countries 
are 
allowed to provide four weekly flight between <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>. Additional flights on this route have to be 
approved first by either <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>. 
  AAA has maximized its services with four weekly flights 
while 
<PERSON>Mandarin</PERSON> and Eva provide two weekly flights each. 
  But a faster-than-expected tourist flow from <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> to 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> has called for more flights and the airlines 
operating the route are very profitable, airlines officials said. 
  <ORGANIZATION>Eva Air</ORGANIZATION> has been forced to offer an extra flight to meet 
growing demand, company representative in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> <PERSON>Peter Kwoh</PERSON> said 
in an interview. 
  "All airlines operating between <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> are making profits thanks to a surge in the number of 
tourists from <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>," he said. 
  The number of tourist arrivals from <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> going to 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
hit a record high of nearly 109,000 last year, up from 63,500 in 
<DATE>1992</DATE>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Tourist Commission</ORGANIZATION> (ATC). 
  Tourists from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> going to <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> totalled more than 
20,000, up only slightly from a year earlier. 
  "The <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION> route has been known as the golden route for 
many 
years," <PERSON>Kwoh</PERSON> said, adding "because more and more affluent <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> 
residents like to travel overseas." 
  "They are big spenders in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>," an <ORGANIZATION>ATC</ORGANIZATION> official said. 
  <ORGANIZATION>China Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, a parent company of <LOCATION>Mandarin</LOCATION>, said this 
month 
that its subsidiary would expand its current Taipei-Sydney 
flights to <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> later this year. 
  "I believe all the airlines operating between the <ORGANIZATION>ROC</ORGANIZATION> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will cash in on the growing tourist flow to share a 
bigger market pie," <ORGANIZATION>TECO</ORGANIZATION>'s Li said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110489-0126 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 130072 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 4, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 15A; Column 6; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
197 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO SPORTS ET CETERA: USD BEATS AUSTRALIANS IN OPENER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JIM LINDGREN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> men's basketball team began its season with a 91-81 
exhibition victory over <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Eastside Melbourne Spectres</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the 
<ORGANIZATION>USD Sports Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Senior <PERSON>John Jerome</PERSON>, who red-shirted last season, led USD with 21 points. Senior 
<PERSON>Craig Cottrell</PERSON> added 10 points. <PERSON>Shawn Hamilton</PERSON>, a community college transfer 
from <LOCATION>Mesa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, had seven rebounds, and freshman <PERSON>Pat Holbert</PERSON> had eight 
assists. 
</P>
<P>
USD took an 8-2 lead and never trailed. It took its biggest lead of the half, 
42-26, with a 10-0 run with four minutes remaining. The Toreros, who 
substituted freely, had a 27-point lead five minutes into the <DATE>second half</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In the first 7:35, <PERSON>Jerome</PERSON> (6-feet-8) scored 14 of the Toreros' first 23 points, 
including two three-pointers. 
</P>
<P>
USD shot well from the floor -- <PERCENT>58%</PERCENT> (38 of 66) -- but converted on just 10 of 
17 free throws, three of seven in the first half. 
</P>
<P>
Eastside <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> was led by <PERSON>Steve deLaveaga</PERSON>'s 22 points. DeLaveaga normally 
plays for <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>'s High Five <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, but <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> was permitted to use two 
American players. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> International opens its season tonight (7:30) at Serra High against the 
same <ORGANIZATION>Eastside Melbourne</ORGANIZATION> team. JIM <PERSON>LINDGREN</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-12442</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EKAEZAHNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941101
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 NOV 94 / Survey of Australia (6): Wheel of misfortune - Nikki Tait
studies the rise of the gambling dens
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
If the growth in visitors to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is a pretty sight, the development of
the country's casino industry - a key factor in the tourism equation - looks
increasingly ugly.
It has been estimated that revenues from Australian casinos could double
over the next five years, to around ADollars 1.25bn per annum, as new
properties in <LOCATION>Cairns</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> come on stream.
This will be the third phase of the industry's development. While casinos
have been operating in <LOCATION>Tasmania</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> for several
decades, these have always been small-scale operations, with aggregate
annual revenues of less than ADollars 50m.
It was only when the <LOCATION>Burswood</LOCATION> casino got going outside <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>,
followed by <ORGANIZATION>Jupiters</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Gold Coast</ORGANIZATION>, that the dollar signs
started to clock up. Burswood has around 116 tables, and <ORGANIZATION>Jupiters</ORGANIZATION> almost as
many. The other seven casinos sprinkled across <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> are only in
double-digits, and <PERSON>Alice Springs</PERSON>' has fewer than 20 tables. Burswood alone
accounted for 40 per cent of the industry's ADollars 657m revenues in
<DATE>1992-3</DATE>.
Today, there are two principal reasons why other big states, such as
<LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, are clambering on to the same bandwagon. The
first is an acute desire to attract the Asian tourist dollar - or, at the
very least, not to lose out to competing cities and states. According to
projections from the <ORGANIZATION>NSW Casino Control Authority</ORGANIZATION>, the number of
international visitors to the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> property could top the million-mark by
the year <DATE>2000</DATE>, compared with 1.1-2.2m domestic visitors and 6-7.5m local
visitors or day-trippers.
Secondly, state treasurers, eager to relieve their budgetary pressures, see
tax revenues from gaming dollars as a fairly efficient means of raising new
funds. Consultants say that the substitution effect - the drop in
racing-related revenues, for example, as punters adjust their activities -
is relatively modest.
But as the stakes are raised, the disquiet is growing. In <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, where a
temporary casino opened early this year, there have been reports of a
proliferation of 'gambling problems'. Pawnshops are said to be seeing a
surge in business, and financial difficulties, notably within the city's
large Asian community, are rife.
Meanwhile, the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> casino development has degenerated into a dirty brawl
between the business interests of <PERSON>Mr Kerry Packer</PERSON>, the Australian
businessman who already has a significant stake in the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> operation,
and a consortium of Showboat, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> casino group, and <ORGANIZATION>Leighton Holdings</ORGANIZATION>,
the Australian building company.
Leighton-Showboat appeared to win the right to build and operate the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>
property earlier this year, outbidding the <ORGANIZATION>Packer</ORGANIZATION> consortium, which also
included the <ORGANIZATION>US</ORGANIZATION>'s Circus Circus, by offering an upfront payment of ADollars
376m.
But since then, the <PERSON>Packer</PERSON> camp has unleased a barrage of accusations about
Showboat's probity. <PERSON>Mr Bob Carr</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>NSW Labor</ORGANIZATION> opposition leader, has
levelled some of the more detailed allegations, which hang on fairly tenuous
links between Showboat and a <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> mob figure and seem to baffle US
analysts. Confidential US police reports have been leaked; public relations
advisers and lawyers spurred into action.
The CCC, having assured everyone that extensive probity checks had been
carried out before the Leighton-Showboat choice was made, has set up an
inquiry to look into the allegations.
Sydney residents, meanwhile, tend to view the whole business with a mixture
of contempt and cynicism. Two previous attempts to award a <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> casino
licence - in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE> - went awry when individuals or companies
involved in the winning bids ran into controversy. It is now a question of
whether the third time is any more lucky.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    RES  Facilities.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page III
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870210-0006 </DOCNO>
<HL> International Corporate Report:
Murdoch's News Corp. Sells
Its Australian TV Stations</HL>
<DD> 02/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> NWS FREST
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL)
PUBLISHING (PUB) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's NEWS CORP.</ORGANIZATION> sold its two Australian television stations to <ORGANIZATION>WESTFIELD CAPITAL CORP.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Westfield</ORGANIZATION> paid <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> the equivalent of <MONEY>$555 million</MONEY> for the stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, as well as some small newspapers, radio stations and a recording business. 

   <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> had said it would sell the television stations and concentrate in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> on the print media. 
The sale partially offsets the cost of <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s acquisition of <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which leaves <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s company with about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the total newspaper circulation in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s major cities. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Westfield Capital</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, enters the scramble among Australian companies to set up television networks. 
<ORGANIZATION>Westfield</ORGANIZATION> will hold its newly acquired media interests through its <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT>-owned <ORGANIZATION>Northern Star Holdings Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which already owns newspapers, radio stations and two television stations in smaller cities. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Westfield</ORGANIZATION>'s managing director, <PERSON>David Gonski</PERSON>, said: "Our No. 1 priority will be to go nationwide, either by linking with other networks or by acquisition." 
Analysts said one possibility would be a link with businessman <PERSON>Kerry Stokes</PERSON>, who bought <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s television station in <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> and also owns a station in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> and a license for a station in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> last month became the first company to set up a television network covering most major Australian cities, and <ORGANIZATION>John Fairfax Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> is in position to establish a second network after adding <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> station to its television operations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881209-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-09-88 1205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Australia-Stowaway 1stLd-Writethru a0522 12-09 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Stowaway, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0522,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Sydney</HEAD>
<HEAD>Stowaway, 12, Flies Around The World In Search For America</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 4 grafs to UPDATE with boy's arrival in Vienna,
details. Pickup 3rd graf pvs, ``He is ...''</NOTE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Austria (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 12-year-old stowaway who wanted to go to
American but ended up in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by mistake arrived back in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>
today at the end of a 19,000-mile airborne adventure.
   <PERSON>Kristofer Dobrowski</PERSON> was questioned by police and then handed back
to his Polish-born mother, officials at <LOCATION>Schwechat</LOCATION> airport told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. His home address was not released.
   Airline officials were at a loss to explain the incident but said
they were checking security systems.
   Dobrowski was put on a Vienna-bound plane in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> late
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> after he was discovered in the transit lounge of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>'s
airport without a ticket, travel papers or identity documents.
   ``He is knee-high to a grasshopper,'' said one Australian
immigration officer. ``It seems he wanted to go to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and
mistook the <ORGANIZATION>Qantas</ORGANIZATION> flight destination of <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.''
   With the help of an interpreter, officials found that <PERSON>Dobrowski</PERSON>
had flown undetected from <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION>, and on to <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> before being picked up in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>.
   Immigration spokesman <PERSON>Geoff Smith</PERSON> said officials became
suspicious when they realized the boy spoke no English, was
traveling alone and had no travel documents.
   <PERSON>Dobrowski</PERSON>, who is Polish but lives with his mother in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>,
said he was unhappy at his mother's recent remarriage. He said he
did not like his stepfather, so he decided to run away.
   ``He left home <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and went to <LOCATION>Vienna Airport</LOCATION> where he
somehow boarded an <ORGANIZATION>Air Lauda</ORGANIZATION> jet for <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>,'' said
the spokesman. ``He stayed in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> for two days in the transit
area, mostly sleeping while he recovered from his flight from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
to <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>.''
   When he overcame his jetlag, <PERSON>Dobrowski</PERSON> tagged along with a family
that was flying to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, apparently managing to pick up a
boarding pass he found on the ground and use it to join a flight to
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>.
   ``But <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> wasn't <PERSON>Kristofer</PERSON>'s chosen destination. With his
poor understanding of English, he mistook <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, which
is where he really wanted to go _ <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>,'' said the official
demanded anonymity.
   Qantas paid for him to stay the night at the <ORGANIZATION>Airport Hilton Hotel</ORGANIZATION>
before putting him on a plane home _ as a first-class passenger.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-28320 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas111_q_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-111 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> AUSTRALASIA </F>
<F P=101> Australia </F>
<H3> <TI>   PRC Delegation Signs Deals With Local Firms </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    PRC Delegation Signs Deals With Local Firms </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0706080994 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0500 GMT 7 
Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0706080994 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s biggest trade and investment delegation to 
ever visit <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is continuing to generate multimillion 
dollar deals for local companies. About 500 business people, 
including 119 Chinese representatives, are today meeting at an 
investment forum in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. Last week's first session of the 
forum in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> resulted in 147 letters of intent worth a 
potential <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> [Australian]. Managing Director of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Trade Commission Ralph Evans</ORGANIZATION> says the Chinese 
delegation has an extensive shopping list. 
  [Begin <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> recording] There were up to <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY> worth 
of projects and that <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> on which there have been 
companies that have signed initial letters of intent represents 
<PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of that. So, they have come with a very extensive 
shopping list and we would hope that more of it can be tapped 
into during the session here in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> today. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-28060 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas110_q_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-110 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> AUSTRALASIA </F>
<F P=101> Australia </F>
<H3> <TI>   PRC Delegation Signs Deals With Local Companies </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    PRC Delegation Signs Deals With Local Companies </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0706080994 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0500 GMT 7 
Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0706080994 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s biggest trade and investment delegation to 
ever visit <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is continuing to generate multimillion 
dollar deals for local companies. About 500 business people, 
including 119 Chinese representatives, are today meeting at an 
investment forum in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. Last week's first session of the 
forum in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> resulted in 147 letters of intent worth a 
potential <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> [Australian]. Managing Director of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Trade Commission Ralph Evans</ORGANIZATION> says the Chinese 
delegation has an extensive shopping list. 
  [Begin <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> recording] There were up to <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY> worth 
of projects and that <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> on which there have been 
companies that have signed initial letters of intent represents 
<PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of that. So, they have come with a very extensive 
shopping list and we would hope that more of it can be tapped 
into during the session here in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> today. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870209-0054 </DOCNO>
<HL> Herald Apparently Is Won by Murdoch;
Other Firms Scramble for TV Networks
---
By Tony Patrick
<DD> 02/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> FREST NWS
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PUBLISHING (PUB)
TELECOMMUNICATIONS, BROADCASTING, TELEPHONE, TELEGRAPH (TEL) </IN>
<DATELINE> SYDNEY, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> apparently won the battle for <ORGANIZATION>Herald &amp; Weekly Times Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest media group. 
But the reshaping of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s media industry will continue, as the scramble to set up television networks intensifies with the sale of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s stations and the impending sale of those owned by <ORGANIZATION>News Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>John Fairfax Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> reached an agreement <DATE>Friday</DATE> under which <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> purchased <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> television station for the equivalent of <MONEY>$214.3 million</MONEY>. 
Fairfax also acquired most of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s smaller newspapers in the state of <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, as well as <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Tamworth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, paper, for a total of <MONEY>$30.1 million</MONEY>. 
In return, <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> withdrew its bid for <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> and dropped all legal action against <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s competing <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> offer. 

   The agreement paves the way for <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to take control of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s company has acquired nearly <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s shares, and the end of legal actions means he can step in to control the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> board. 

   Fairfax also will ask the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Broadcasting Tribunal</ORGANIZATION> to stop an investigation into <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s takeover of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>. 
The tribunal still might continue its investigation, which is based on <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizenship and Australian regulations prohibiting control of television stations here by foreigners. 
But analysts believe such a move isn't likely now that <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> has sold its television operations and <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> has said <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> will sell its two television stations as well. 

   <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> emerged from the transactions as the biggest newspaper publisher in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, with about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the total newspaper circulation in the major cities. 
In addition to its own publications, which already cover most of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON>'s company will retain <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> newspapers in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hobart</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, as well as a string of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> suburban newspapers, several magazines and printing and distribution operations. 

   Analysts said the price paid by <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, while difficult to determine exactly, makes the complicated transactions a bargain for the Murdoch-controlled company. 
After selling the television operations of <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Murdoch</PERSON> might end up paying about <MONEY>$536 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$670 million</MONEY> to greatly expand his newspaper-publishing empire. 

   The active bidding for the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> broadcasting operations pushed their prices well above earlier offers for the stations. 
That effectively reduces the cost to <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of acquiring <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>, because it gives <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> additional cash that will go to <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> when it takes control of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>, meanwhile, is in position to lead <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s second television network with its acquisition of the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> station. 
It already owns television stations in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>. 
Last month, <ORGANIZATION>Bond Corp.</ORGANIZATION> became the first company to set up a television network covering most major Australian cities, when it acquired the television operations of privately owned <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Press Holdings Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Robert Holmes</PERSON> a Court, a businessman with television stations in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, might join with <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> to establish a national network, analysts speculate. 
<PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, under a previous agreement, is to get the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> newspaper business in his home state of <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>, but failed in his bid for <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> television station. 

   But the carving-up of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> also strengthened a competitor of <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION> in the race to establish television networks. 
Herald will sell its other television station, in <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, plus radio stations in the states of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Australia</LOCATION>, to businessman <PERSON>Kerry Stokes</PERSON> for <MONEY>$87.1 million</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Stokes</PERSON> owns a television station in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> and a license for a station in <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>. 
He also is expected to be a bidder for <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s two television stations, which could make him the leader in a third national network. 

   The buyer of the <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stations is likely to be announced today. 
If another company wins the race for <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s television stations, that bidder is expected to team with <PERSON>Mr. Stokes</PERSON> to form the third network. 
The two <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stations are expected to be sold for a total of about <MONEY>$502.4 million</MONEY>. 

   The carving up of <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> was sparked in part by a government proposal to liberalize laws that currently limit a company to owning only two television stations. 
That liberalization, if approved by parliament, would encourage creation of national networks, which would boost profitability for station owners. 

   The government also proposes to reduce the ability of one company to own both a television station and a major newspaper in any city. 
Such a change could present problems for <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>, which now will own a television station and a newspaper in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. 

   Some further redistribution of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s media business therefore is likely as the television networks are established and rulings are made on newspaper-television cross ownership. 
Owners of the few independent television stations that remain might sell those businesses if they bid for the <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stations but fail in those offers. 
And <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> a Court, who comes out of the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> carve-up with few of the spoils, still might fight to improve his position, analysts say. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-11005</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EEHA5ACJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940507
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 MAY 94 / International Company News: Packer team loses bid for Sydney
casino
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr Kerry Packer</PERSON>, the Australian businessman, and Circus Circus, the large <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
gaming group, yesterday lost their joint bid to build the USDollars 1bn-plus
<LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> casino complex, which is forecast to have annual gaming revenues of
around ADollars 500m (USDollars 357.1m) when it comes on stream in <DATE>1997</DATE>.
Instead, the <ORGANIZATION>New South Wales Casino Control Authority</ORGANIZATION> announced yesterday
the winning development proposal had been submitted by <ORGANIZATION>Leighton Holdings</ORGANIZATION>,
the stock market-listed Australian engineering and construction group in
which <ORGANIZATION>Hochtief</ORGANIZATION>, the German construction group, has a 48 per cent
shareholding.
Although the <ORGANIZATION>CCA</ORGANIZATION> stressed no one factor had influenced its decision, the
Leighton bid - made in conjunction with Showboat, a <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> casino group -
offered a much higher upfront payment to the <ORGANIZATION>NSW</ORGANIZATION> state in return for the
casino licence.
The consortium has promised to pay ADollars 441m over three years, or
ADollars 376m as a single upfront sum - a figure which even <PERSON>Mr Chris Cullen</PERSON>,
the <ORGANIZATION>CCA</ORGANIZATION> chairman, described as 'exceptional'.
<PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> - whose involvement in the rival consortium was through his Nine
Network and <ORGANIZATION>Consolidated Press</ORGANIZATION> companies - said his group had 'bid our
maximum price and came up over ADollars 80m short'. 'On that basis,
(Leighton/Showboat) deserved to win and good luck to them,' said the
businessman, known to be a keen gambler himself.
The <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> casino is the last, and largest, in a string of such development
announcements in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. Growth in the industry is expected to explode
over the next three years. Casinos are due to come on stream in <LOCATION>Cairns</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> during that time and - with <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> included - the
country's total annual gross casino revenues could top ADollars 2bn by the
late-1990s. <PERSON>Mr Packer</PERSON> already has connections with - and a potential direct
interest in - the <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> property.
The <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> casino has always been seen as a 'prize' because of the city's
strong Asian tourist trade. In addition to the upfront licence payment, the
state expects to get annual tax revenues of around ADollars 100m once it
starts operating.
The Leighton/Showboat proposal includes a five-star hotel, serviced
apartments, a floorshow theatre and a 2,000-seat lyric theatre, as well as
the 'themed' casino with its 170 gaming tables and 1,480 gaming machines.
<PERSON>Leighton</PERSON> said the consortium company, called <ORGANIZATION>Sydney Harbour Casino</ORGANIZATION>, would be
floated by <DATE>1995</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Circus Circus Enterprises Inc.
    Leighton Holdings.
    Showboat Inc.
    Nine Network Australia.
    Consolidated Press Holdings.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
    USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
    COMP  Strategic links &amp; Joint venture.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 11
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890428-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-89 0609EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Quayle     04-28 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quayle,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Beer, Tennis and Impromptu Walks Down Under for Quayle</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Tops prospects uncertain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN MOWER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, acting like
a political candidate on a whistlestop tour of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, quaffed
beer at a local pub, hit tennis balls with underprivileged children
and mingled with crowds in two cities today.
   Obviously enjoying himself on the third day of his trip, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>
paid a surprise visit to the wood-paneled pub at the <ORGANIZATION>Lord Nelson
Brewery Hotel</ORGANIZATION> where his brief stop stunned the clientele.
   ``I couldn't believe it,'' said <PERSON>Kim Ivey</PERSON>, a banker who was
drinking at the bar with friends in mid-afternoon. ``We were
standing here and he walked up and said, `Hi. I'm <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>.'''
   Quayle, sipping a glass of <PERSON>Hahn</PERSON> beer, chatted with the young
women behind the bar, joked with proprietor <PERSON>Blair Hayden</PERSON> about his
golfing tie and suggested two patrons attend a black-tie dinner at
which he's the guest of honor.
   He called the beer _ which is <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s national drink _ good,
but added, ``It has a bite.''
   <PERSON>Ann Larson</PERSON>, 25, an administrator at <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> who chatted with <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>
said, ``It was great. He is really nice.'' She said her friends
``will be spewing. They'll be so jealous.''
   The pub stop capped a day in which <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> spent much of his time
shaking hands and posing for pictures, including several on a boat
tour of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>'s breathtaking harbor.
   The good-natured touring was in contrast to the first days of
<PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>'s first trip to the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> region. The vice president has
highlighted the U.S.-Australia defense alliance, but Australian
officials have protested export subsidies the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> places
on wheat, subsidies the Australians say hurt their exports abroad.
   Australian officials who hoped <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> would say the subsidies
were ending were angered at his public comments. <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> said at a
news conference on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, ``We do not believe that it (the
subsidy program) is injuring <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.''
   Senior government sources, speaking on condition of anonymity,
said Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> was exasperated at <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>'s stance in
a private meeting. <PERSON>Hawke</PERSON> said on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the losses ``are not
figments of our imagination. They are cold, hard and brutally
hurtful economic statistics which have adversely affected our
farmers, our wheat farmers.''
   The country's major national newspaper, The Australian, was more
blunt in an editorial, saying, ``Who do you think you are kidding,
<PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>? Read our lips, <PERSON>Mr. Quayle</PERSON>. Australians are not happy.''
   The vice president and his wife, <PERSON>Marilyn</PERSON>, flew here from
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, their second stop on their five-day trip to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   Taking a cue from President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, who sometimes spontaneously
stops his motorcade to mix with the crowds, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> jumped out of
his limousine in downtown <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> to shake hands outside one of
the city's landmarks, the clocks at the <ORGANIZATION>Flinders Street</ORGANIZATION> train
station.
   Quayle, trailed by local reporters, also insisted on walking
near the waterfront in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, much to the consternation of his
<ORGANIZATION>Secret Service</ORGANIZATION> agents. ``I wish he would get in the car,'' one
agent said in an exasperated tone.
   Before he left <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> laid a wreath at a war memorial
where a brass plaque honors <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Marines who fought at <LOCATION>Guadalcanal</LOCATION>
in World War II.
   He also stopped by the <ORGANIZATION>National Tennis Center</ORGANIZATION>, home of the
Australian Open, to honor Oz Tennis, a charity that gives poor
children the chance to learn the game. The vice president hit
tennis balls there with former <ORGANIZATION>Wimbledon</ORGANIZATION> doubles champion <PERSON>Paul
McNamee</PERSON> and 11-year-old <PERSON>Michael Memedev</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901210-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-10-90 0849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Australia-Fairfax     12-10 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Australia-Fairfax,0387</SECOND>
<HEAD>Media Comapny Placed in Receivership</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS PASSA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>John Fairfax Group Proprietary Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>,
which owns the <ORGANIZATION>Sydney Morning Herald</ORGANIZATION> and three other major
Australian publications, was placed into receivership <DATE>Monday</DATE> after
banks called in outstanding debts.
   <PERSON>John Fairfax</PERSON>, one of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s two major newspaper groups
along with <ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Ltd., owes about <MONEY>1.7 billion
Australian dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.31 billion</MONEY>, to its creditors.
   Company officials said directors asked for the appointment of a
provisional liquidator for the group's finance division after banks
refused to agree to a rollover of a debt of <MONEY>850 million Australian
dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$654 million</MONEY>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Deloitte Ross Tohmatsu</ORGANIZATION> accountancy firm was then appointed
receiver and manager at the request of <ORGANIZATION>John Fairfax Group</ORGANIZATION>'s banking
syndicate.
   The <ORGANIZATION>ANZ Bank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> are owed about <MONEY>1.2 billion Australian
dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$850 million</MONEY>. The remaining debt is in the form of
high-yield, high-risk bonds.
   John <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s oldest media organization, also owns
the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Financial Review</ORGANIZATION>, Business Review Weekly and The
(<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>) Age as well as the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> is the
oldest English-language newspaper in the world continuously owned
by the same family.
   In early <DATE>October</DATE>, the company reported a net loss of <MONEY>59.08
million Australian dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$45.49 million</MONEY>, for the year ending
<DATE>June 30</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE>, three top <PERSON>John Fairfax</PERSON> officials - Chief Executive
<PERSON>Chris Anderson</PERSON>, Chairman <PERSON>Brian Kelman</PERSON> and director <PERSON>Bob Johnston</PERSON> -
resigned amid continuing disputes on renegotiations of the debt.
   John <LOCATION>Fairfax</LOCATION>'s problems have been mirrored at <ORGANIZATION>Murdoch's News
Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Ltd.
   In early <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Murdoch</PERSON> merged four of his newspapers into two
round-the-clock productions in <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. The moves came
amidst a plunge in the value of <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stock that wiped out
more than <MONEY>2 billion Australian dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.66 billion</MONEY>, of the
company's market capitalization.
   Murdoch has been talking in recent weeks with bank lenders about
restructuring <ORGANIZATION>News Corp.</ORGANIZATION> debt and hopes to have a deal by early
next year.
   Other media outlets in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have fared poorly as well. Two
of the major private television stations are in receivership and
have fired hundreds of staff. The third recently reported a loss of
<MONEY>618 million Australian dollars</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$511 million</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900521-0134
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900521-0134.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Carlson Cos. Buys
   51% Stake in Forum,
   An Australian Firm
</HL>
<DATE>
05/21/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B6D
</SO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   MELBOURNE, Australia -- Carlson Cos., a U.S. marketing
group, said it has bought 51% of Forum Organization Pty.
Ltd., an Australian marketing firm.
   The price of the acquisition wasn't disclosed, but the
companies said in a statement that Forum has annual revenue
of around 20 million Australian dollars.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>E.C. Gage</ORGANIZATION>, chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Carlson</ORGANIZATION>, said the purchase
allows the company to "rapidly expand its global network of
full service marketing facilities to its many international
has offices in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082889-0078 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 100382 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 28, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 3; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
663 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MARKETING THE LAND DOWN UNDER; 
</P>
<P>
JOHN CAIN, PREMIER OF VICTORIA, AUSTRALIA, IS MAKING THE ROUNDS TO SELL 
MELBOURNE AS THE GATEWAY TO THE PACIFIC. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By NANCY YOSHIHARA, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When the <PERSON>Honorable John Cain</PERSON>, premier of the state of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 
passed through town the other day, he made a pitch to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' chief 
executives to come invest Down Under. 
</P>
<P>
"They see the place as vibrant but expensive," <PERSON>Cain</PERSON> said in an interview after 
lunching with 10 chief executives at the <ORGANIZATION>California Club</ORGANIZATION>. He was en route to 
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> to sell <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> as the site for the <DATE>1996</DATE> Olympics. 
</P>
<P>
The city is up against <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Belgrade</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>; 
<LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. If <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> wins, the Games are expected to help channel 
tourism and investment into <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> -- specifically <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>, which is on the 
southeastern coast. 
</P>
<P>
Cain is selling <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> as a gateway to the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> with its 24-hour port, 
the largest in the <LOCATION>Southern Hemisphere</LOCATION> and the 10th-largest container port in 
the world. With <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> increasingly aligning itself with its Asia-Pacific 
neighbors, <PERSON>Cain</PERSON> said his state is part of the "most dynamic market at the 
moment." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Diversifying Exports 
</P>
<P>
Since <DATE>January</DATE>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has attempted to interest other Asia-Pacific countries 
in uniting to promote regional economic cooperation through a so-called Pacific 
Rim Initiative. Earlier this month, Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> invited 11 
countries, including the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, to an initial meeting in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>November</DATE> to discuss the international economic and trade environment. 
</P>
<P>
During the past few years, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has been restructuring its economy to be 
less dependent on commodity exports by diversifying into export-oriented 
manufacturing businesses. As part of the change, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has cut its 
effective corporate tax rate to <PERCENT>39%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> and liberalized some of the work 
practices of unions. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has aggressively hit the road to lure foreign investors from abroad. 
The states of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> have sent their own investment missions 
abroad, and each has a trade office in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. The Victoria Investment 
Program, for example, is targeting the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West 
Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> as primary sources of potential investment. 
</P>
<P>
In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the target industries are biotechnology, tourism 
facilities, advanced manufacturing and materials, and medical and scientific 
instruments. 
</P>
<P>
"We are seeking business that capitalizes on our strengths," such as cheap 
energy and tax advantages for research and development, <PERSON>Cain</PERSON> said in an 
interview. 
</P>
<P>
Major <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies, he said, have discovered <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> as a strategic base 
for Asia-Pacific operations. They include <ORGANIZATION>Eastman Kodak Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>B. F. Goodrich 
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Control Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>McDonnell 
Douglas Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Philip Morris Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Investment Applications 
</P>
<P>
One-third of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> investment in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is concentrated in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, which 
is home for <PERCENT>34%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s manufacturing industries and <PERCENT>26%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s 
population. Victoria's rate of growth of non-farm gross domestic product 
averaged <PERCENT>4.6%</PERCENT> during the past five years compared to <PERCENT>4.3%</PERCENT> for all of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
during the same period. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> was the biggest foreign investor in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> at the end of 
<DATE>1988</DATE>, with investments totaling <MONEY>$32.1 billion</MONEY>, followed by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
with <MONEY>$28.6 billion</MONEY> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> with <MONEY>$19.3 billion</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Australian Foreign Investment Review Board</ORGANIZATION> reported that in <DATE>1987-1988</DATE>, 
applications for investment from <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies totaled <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>, divided 
evenly among manufacturing, tourism, minerals and exploration. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is also nurturing business with its Asia-Pacific neighbors. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Portland Aluminum Smelter</ORGANIZATION>, the largest industrial project with <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to date, 
is a partnership involving <ORGANIZATION>Alcoa</ORGANIZATION>, the state of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>First National Trust 
and China International Trust and Investment Corp</ORGANIZATION>. The smelter's first 
production in <DATE>1987</DATE> brought <MONEY>$583.2 million</MONEY> in export income for <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Similarly, Australian firms last year completed a light rail system in <LOCATION>Hong 
Kong</LOCATION> for the <ORGANIZATION>Kowloon Canton Railway Corp.</ORGANIZATION> worth about <MONEY>$216.4 million</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, John Cain discusses '84 Olympics logistics with Margaret Farnum, acting 
chief administrator for the Coliseum commission. MEL MELCON / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN INVESTMENTS -- AUSTRALIA; MELBOURNE (AUSTRALIA); 
PACIFIC RIM NATIONS; AUSTRALIA -- ECONOMY; UNITED STATES -- TRADE -- AUSTRALIA 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-24595 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi105_e_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-105 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Southeast Asia &amp; Pacific </F>
<H3> <TI>   Trade-Investment Forum Held in Australia </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Trade-Investment Forum Held in Australia </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0106081594 Beijing XINHUA in English 0728 GMT 1 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0106081594 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 1</DATE> (XINHUA) -- <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> Trade and 
Investment Forum <DATE>'94</DATE>, the largest ever held in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, opened 
in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, the second largest city in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, today. 
  The Chinese delegation, consisting of more than 100 
businessmen from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s 20 provinces and cities, was led by <PERSON>Gu 
Yongjiang</PERSON>, vice-minister of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ministry for Foreign Trade 
and Economic Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The Chinese businessmen have brought with them over 500 
projects, valued at <MONEY>7 billion U.S. dollars</MONEY>. 
  The projects cover the fields of communications, energy, 
<LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION>- chemical industry, electronic industry, textile industry, 
building materials, agriculture, and service industry. 
  The aim of the forum is to brief the Australian counterpart 
on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s investment environment, its investment policy and 
laws with a view to increasing their understanding of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and 
furthering the development of bilateral economic and trade links. 
  The two-way trade between the two countries stood at <MONEY>3 
billion</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars last year, representing an increase of <PERCENT>29 
percent</PERCENT> over the previous year, according to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s official 
figures. 
  The forum will last for two days in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> and will then 
be moved to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest city of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> next week. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910507-0103
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910507-0103.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Stelco Inc.
</HL>
<DATE>
05/07/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C12
</SO>
<CO>
   STE.A WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
STEEL MANUFACTURERS (STL)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
CANADA (CN)
</RE>
<LP>
   STELCO Inc. (Toronto) -- Robert J. Melbourne was named
concern. Mr. Melbourne's move into the newly created
positions coincides with Stelco's plan to eliminate its
Stelco Steel and Stelco Enterprises divisions as separate
organizations. The units will be integrated into the parent
company. Mr. Melbourne had been president of Stelco Steel. T.
Raymond Meadowcroft, formerly president of Stelco
Enterprises, will continue as an executive vice president of
the parent with responsibility for its technology-marketing
arm.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-7910</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBVBWADKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 FEB 93 / Banks given assurance by Daily Mirror
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROBERT PESTON, Banking Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE FOUR banks which are majority shareholders in <ORGANIZATION>Mirror Group Newspapers</ORGANIZATION>
received an assurance on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> from <PERSON>Mr David Montgomery</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s
chief executive, that the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Mirror</ORGANIZATION> will remain a left-of-centre
newspaper.
'As a result of conversations which took place last week, I have no doubt
that the Daily Mirror's left-of-centre position will continue,' said <PERSON>Mr John
Melbourn</PERSON>, a senior executive director of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster Bank</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr
Melbourn</PERSON> added that 'left-of-centre' is synonymous with backing the <ORGANIZATION>Labour
Party</ORGANIZATION> in general elections. The banks believe a rightward shift would damage
MGN as a business.
Separately it also emerged yesterday that <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s board is likely to issue a
statement this week, reaffirming both the left-of-centre stance of the Daily
Mirror and stating the board's support for <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON>'s management.
<ORGANIZATION>NatWest</ORGANIZATION> is <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest shareholder and <PERSON>Mr Melbourn</PERSON> has been playing a
leading role in attempts by the bank to restore stability to <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>, after its
employees and the <ORGANIZATION>Labour Party</ORGANIZATION> accused <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> of attempting to break
the Mirror's traditional Labour allegiance.
Representatives of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds</ORGANIZATION>,
which between them control 54 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s shares as collateral on
loans to the late <PERSON>Mr Robert Maxwell</PERSON>, saw <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> for a
briefing on the performance of the businesses. A banker at the meeting said:
'After all <DATE>last week</DATE>'s speculation, we asked him for an assurance that the
newspaper would stay left of centre.' <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> gave that assurance.
Earlier in the week, <PERSON>Mr Melbourn</PERSON> sought and received a similar commitment on
the Mirror's political stance from Sir <PERSON>Robert Clarke</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman. He
also asked Sir <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> to stay on as chairman for another year, but suggested
that the board should be slightly reconstituted so that non-executives make
up 60 per cent of all directors. One or two other non-executives are
therefore likely to be appointed.
A banks' representative also had a meeting last week with <PERSON>Lord Hollick</PERSON>, the
Labour businessman who is a non-executive director of <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>. The banker asked
<PERSON>Lord Hollick</PERSON> whether he had a hidden agenda as a director of MGN, following
reports that he plans to make a bid for <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>. Lord <PERSON>Hollick</PERSON> told the banks
that he had no hidden agenda and that no bid was planned.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>National Westminster Bank.
    Midland Bank.
    Goldman Sachs.
    Lloyds Bank.
    Mirror Group Newspapers.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2711 Newspapers.
    P602  Commercial Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Company News.
    MGMT  Management.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-7842</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBVBWADKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 FEB 93 / Banks given assurance by Daily Mirror
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROBERT PESTON, Banking Editor
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE FOUR banks which are majority shareholders in <ORGANIZATION>Mirror Group Newspapers</ORGANIZATION>
received an assurance on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> from <PERSON>Mr David Montgomery</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s
chief executive, that the <ORGANIZATION>Daily Mirror</ORGANIZATION> will remain a left-of-centre
newspaper.
'As a result of conversations which took place last week, I have no doubt
that the Daily Mirror's left-of-centre position will continue,' said <PERSON>Mr John
Melbourn</PERSON>, a senior executive director of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster Bank</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr
Melbourn</PERSON> added that 'left-of-centre' is synonymous with backing the <ORGANIZATION>Labour
Party</ORGANIZATION> in general elections. The banks believe a rightward shift would damage
MGN as a business.
Separately it also emerged yesterday that <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s board is likely to issue a
statement this week, reaffirming both the left-of-centre stance of the Daily
Mirror and stating the board's support for <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON>'s management.
<ORGANIZATION>NatWest</ORGANIZATION> is <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest shareholder and <PERSON>Mr Melbourn</PERSON> has been playing a
leading role in attempts by the bank to restore stability to <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>, after its
employees and the <ORGANIZATION>Labour Party</ORGANIZATION> accused <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> of attempting to break
the Mirror's traditional Labour allegiance.
Representatives of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds</ORGANIZATION>,
which between them control 54 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s shares as collateral on
loans to the late <PERSON>Mr Robert Maxwell</PERSON>, saw <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> for a
briefing on the performance of the businesses. A banker at the meeting said:
'After all <DATE>last week</DATE>'s speculation, we asked him for an assurance that the
newspaper would stay left of centre.' <PERSON>Mr Montgomery</PERSON> gave that assurance.
Earlier in the week, <PERSON>Mr Melbourn</PERSON> sought and received a similar commitment on
the Mirror's political stance from Sir <PERSON>Robert Clarke</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman. He
also asked Sir <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> to stay on as chairman for another year, but suggested
that the board should be slightly reconstituted so that non-executives make
up 60 per cent of all directors. One or two other non-executives are
therefore likely to be appointed.
A banks' representative also had a meeting last week with <PERSON>Lord Hollick</PERSON>, the
Labour businessman who is a non-executive director of <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>. The banker asked
<PERSON>Lord Hollick</PERSON> whether he had a hidden agenda as a director of MGN, following
reports that he plans to make a bid for <ORGANIZATION>MGN</ORGANIZATION>. Lord <PERSON>Hollick</PERSON> told the banks
that he had no hidden agenda and that no bid was planned.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>National Westminster Bank.
    Midland Bank.
    Goldman Sachs.
    Lloyds Bank.
    Mirror Group Newspapers.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2711 Newspapers.
    P602  Commercial Banks.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Company News.
    MGMT  Management.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-12827</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJ4DUABXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941031
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 OCT 94 / This Week: Sport
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN WRAIGHT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
HORSE RACING. <DATE>November 1</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Melbourne Cup</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Flemington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. <DATE>November 5</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Breeders</ORGANIZATION>' Cup meeting, <LOCATION>Churchill Downs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>.
Increasingly, star racehorses are jetting the globe for cash and kudos.
Long-haul travel does not suit all racehorses, but the success of the
Irish-based Vintage Crop in last year's <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> Cup proved an eye-opener
for top owners. Vintage Crop has again been flown to <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>, though a leg
injury last week was a worry. A better prospect in a tricksy race (the
<LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> Cup is a handicap) may be fellow long-haul traveller Quick Ransom
from <PERSON>Mark Johnston</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Yorkshire</LOCATION> stable, who receives weight from Vintage
Crop. Quick Ransom shed 18 kilos on the flight to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> but regained
most of them swiftly and is said to be spot on. In <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, the 11th
staging of the lucrative Breeders' Cup races - seven in total, five on dirt,
two on grass, with prize money of Dollars 10m - sees the biggest overseas
challenge yet. A record 26 European horses are due to appear in different
races, half of them from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s raid is strongest in the Classic,
Turf and Mile events (the latter two on grass), while <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s brightest
chance lies with flying mare Lochsong, who faces 13 US rivals in the <ORGANIZATION>Sprint</ORGANIZATION>.
Only Pebbles (<DATE>1985</DATE>) and <PERSON>Sheikh Albadou</PERSON> (<DATE>1991</DATE>) have won for <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in 77
Breeders' Cup races. The odds against a British win of any sort are quoted
at a sobering 2-1.
FOOTBALL. <DATE>November 1</DATE>, Uefa Cup, 2nd round, 2nd leg, <PERSON>Athletico Bilbao</PERSON> v
<LOCATION>Newcastle</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Aston Villa v Trabzonspor</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>November 2</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>European Champions' League
Group</ORGANIZATION> A, <ORGANIZATION>FC Barcelona v Manchester United</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>November 3</DATE>, European Cup Winners'
Cup, <LOCATION>Austria Vienna</LOCATION> v <LOCATION>Chelsea</LOCATION>, Arsenal v <LOCATION>Brondby</LOCATION>.
Five English clubs compete in European this week, with the hardest task
appearing to face <PERSON>Chelsea</PERSON> who are away to FK <LOCATION>Austria Vienna</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Austria
Memphis</LOCATION> as they now prefer to be called. No English club has ever lost to an
Austrian club in a European competition, but <ORGANIZATION>Chelsea</ORGANIZATION>'s walking wounded could
put that right on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. They drew the first leg 0-0 at <ORGANIZATION>Stamford Bridge</ORGANIZATION>,
and it really will be a funny old game if <PERSON>Glenn Hoddle</PERSON>'s men can produce
those 'Goodnight <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>' headlines come <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Also in the Cup Winners'
Cup, holders Arsenal take a 2-1 lead over <LOCATION>Brondby</LOCATION> into the game at <LOCATION>Highbury</LOCATION>.
In the <ORGANIZATION>Uefa Cup</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Aston Villa</ORGANIZATION> entertain <ORGANIZATION>Trabzonspor</ORGANIZATION> after losing 1-0 in
<LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>, and Premiership leaders <ORGANIZATION>Newcastle</ORGANIZATION> are away to <ORGANIZATION>Athletico Bilbao</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Kevin Keegan</PERSON>'s side nodded off for a while in the first leg. After leading
3-0 they finished the game 3-2 up, and take that advantage to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
Meanwhile, in the big one - the <ORGANIZATION>European Champions League</ORGANIZATION> - <ORGANIZATION>Manchester
United</ORGANIZATION> go to <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>. Over 100,000 Catalans have booked their seats in the
Nou Camp, and <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> will be hoping for the kind of refereeing they enjoyed
in the Premier League this month against <ORGANIZATION>Blackburn</ORGANIZATION>.
RUGBY LEAGUE. <DATE>November 5</DATE>, <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> v <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 2nd <PERSON>John Smith</PERSON>'s Test,
Old Trafford.
What happened to the invincible Kangaroos at <LOCATION>Wembley</LOCATION>? Great <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s 8-4
victory over the Australians in the first <PERSON>John Smith</PERSON>'s Test has had the
Tourists checking video evidence to see how they managed to lose 'the match
<ORGANIZATION>Great Britain</ORGANIZATION> couldn't win'. The Australians, however, will take heart from
the fact that in <DATE>1990</DATE> they came back from a surprise <ORGANIZATION>Wembley</ORGANIZATION> defeat to take
the series 2-1, and that it is nearly 30 years since they lost a series to
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>.
MOTOR RACING. <DATE>November 6</DATE>, Japanese Grand Prix, <LOCATION>Suzuka</LOCATION>.
Formula One title chase has been superb unscripted drama - strong
characterisation and a thrilling, if sometimes unbelievable, plot. With two
races to go and only five points between them, the pressure has even got to
two of the sport's <PERSON>Mr Nice Guys</PERSON>, with <PERSON>Michael Schumacher</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Benetton</ORGANIZATION>) and
<PERSON>Damon Hill</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>) hurling ever more vicious insults at each other in the
press. Schumacher could clinch the title at <LOCATION>Suzuka</LOCATION>, but admits it is a
circuit where <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> may have a power advantage. Off the track in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
all talk will be of who will be racing for whom next season, and which
engines will power which cars. <ORGANIZATION>Peugeot</ORGANIZATION> announced last <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that it is
switching its engines from <ORGANIZATION>McLaren</ORGANIZATION> to <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> for <DATE>1995</DATE>. This was brought
about by one of the biggest motor racing alliances for many a year, in which
