<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880308-0033 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Pound Exceeds 3 Marks as U.K. Changes Tack --- Bank of England Halts Bid To Keep It at Key Level; Trend Depresses Dollar </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens and Peter Torday (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP FREST CANDA JAPAN </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   The British pound surged in a powerful rally yesterday, as the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> abandoned a long struggle to contain the currency's value in favor of a more anti-inflationary strategy. 

   The pound was quoted at <MONEY>$1.8182</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading yesterday, up <PERCENT>2.5%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$1.7745</MONEY> <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 

   Traders attached more significance, however, to sterling's breakthrough above the 3.00-West German mark level. 
For more than a year, traders said, the British central bank had sought to keep the pound under <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY> through interest rate policies and foreign exchange market intervention. 

   Yesterday, the pound climbed <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>3.0488 marks</MONEY> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, compared with 2.9987 <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
Traders said the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> intervened in early European trading by selling sterling to depress its price but quickly dropped the effort. 
"It was a situation where the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> finally threw in the towel. 
The pressure to push sterling through <MONEY>3 marks</MONEY> was irresistable," said <PERSON>Robert Hatcher</PERSON>, vice president and corporate foreign exchange dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Barclays Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   In midmorning trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>127.93 yen</MONEY>, down from <MONEY>128.87 yen</MONEY> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 

   Economists interpreted the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s willingness to let the pound rise above <MONEY>3 marks</MONEY> as signaling the higher priority the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> government places on fighting inflation over stimulating export growth. 
By keeping sterling's value down, the government encourages exports by making British goods less expensive for foreigners, particularly in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, to buy. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s sales of sterling through intervention to contain the pound's value tended to be inflationary as they expanded the British money supply and put downward pressure on interest rates. 

   Moreover, containing sterling's value has become an increasingly difficult battle. 
Because of recent stability in dollar exchange rates and interest rate differentials favoring British investments, currency traders have been moving heavily into sterling. 

   "If you feel that exchange rates are going to be fairly stagnant, then you're going to go where you can earn high interest rates," <PERSON>James H. Hohorst</PERSON>, managing director of foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said. 

   For more than a year the British government corraled the pound in a range between 2.93 and <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY>. 
Last week the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> sold as much as <MONEY>3 billion pounds</MONEY> in currency market intervention to offset upward pressure. 
Market economists speculated yesterday that British monetary authorities may now try to keep the pound between 2.95 and <MONEY>3.10 marks</MONEY>. 
In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> officials declined to discuss limits it may have for sterling exchange rates. 

   U.K. officials stressed, however, that they haven't abandoned their goal of keeping the pound within a relatively narrow range. 

   The ease with which <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> appeared to raise its sterling target range yesterday is bound to strengthen the hand of Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> in resisting calls to join the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary System</ORGANIZATION>, the eight-currency exchange rate mechanism. 
An <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> currency realignment, by contrast, usually involves complicated and time-consuming negotiations. 
<PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> contends the <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> is too inflexible. 

   The policy shift may lead to renewed dollar weakness, analysts predicted. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> has amassed <MONEY>$42.93 billion</MONEY> in foreign-currency reserves, almost half of it from buying dollars and selling sterling during the past year to support the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency and keep the pound stable. 
"One of the big (buyers) in dollars is out of the market now," said <PERSON>Brendan Brown</PERSON>, an economist with <ORGANIZATION>County Natwest</ORGANIZATION>, the investment banking arm of <ORGANIZATION>National Westminster Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>. 

The estimated volume was 2.5 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$437.10</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                    Late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Trading
                   <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>March 7, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                         <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <LOCATION>New York
                            Mon</LOCATION>.        Mon.         Fri.
                      (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.8182      1.8180      1.7745
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.7970      0.7970      0.7977
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 5.6750      5.7045      5.7100
    Japanese yen ....... 127.79      128.88      128.80
    Swiss franc .......... 1.3830      1.3845      1.4002
    West German mark ..... 1.6768      1.6860      1.6899
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                         GOLD PRICES
              (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
    <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
     Mon</ORGANIZATION>.          Mon.            Mon.          Fri.
    437.30       435.90           436.00        437.40
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880302-0030 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Pound Extends Its Rise, Fueled By High Rates --- Dollar Is Mixed in Light Day As British Investments Offer Alluring Returns </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   Relatively high interest rates continued to bolster the British pound in an otherwise sleepy foreign exchange market yesterday. 
The dollar was narrowly mixed against most major currencies. 

   "Sterling was the only mover in the Street," said <PERSON>Cynthia H. Johnson</PERSON>, vice president and corporate foreign exchange manager at <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
Interest rate differentials favoring British investments over those of other major industrial countries provided "a big incentive" to buy sterling, she said. 

   The pound was quoted at <MONEY>$1.7760</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, up from <MONEY>$1.7740</MONEY> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, marking its ninth advance against the dollar in the past 11 trading days. 
The pound also strengthened against its European counterparts, climbing, for example, to 2.9970 West German marks from 2.9936. 

   If sterling's current trend continues, traders said a possible showdown looms between market forces and the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> when the pound reaches the 3.00-mark level. 
Over the past year, the British central bank has consistently intervened in trading to prevent the pound from overtaking the 3.00-mark level by selling sterling in the market, depressing its price. 

   The British government is believed to be concerned that if sterling strengthened beyond that point, it would hurt exports to continental <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
That would affect trade with <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s primary trading partners, many of which have currencies pegged to the mark. 
These concerns were underscored <DATE>Monday</DATE> when the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> government disclosed a record trade deficit for <DATE>January</DATE>. 

   "The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> has a lot of reserves, and they can, if they wish, hold (sterling) below 3.00" marks, <PERSON>Ms. Johnson</PERSON> said. 

   Traders believe <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is less concerned about sterling's dollar value because the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is a less significant trading partner. 

   Despite the threat of central bank resistance, many dealers find yields on sterling investments irresistible, especially while relatively stable exchange rates overall lessen opportunities for trading profits. 
"When you see the market quiet like this, money moves to high-interest rate currencies. 
If things are quiet, people are going to put money where they can earn interest," said <PERSON>Paul R. Loffredo</PERSON>, vice president and chief dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Security Pacific National Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   Yields on closely watched, three-month Eurodeposits were <PERCENT>9.125%</PERCENT> for sterling investments, in contrast to <PERCENT>3.375%</PERCENT> for mark instruments and <PERCENT>6.75%</PERCENT> for dollar investments. 

   In other trading yesterday, the dollar was little changed. 
The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency firmed to <MONEY>128.40 yen</MONEY>, from 128.25, and was unchanged at <MONEY>1.6875 marks</MONEY>. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>128.45 yen</MONEY>. 

   Statements by <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Treasury</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>James Baker</PERSON> that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and other nations will work toward stable exchange rates and that the federal budget deficit is under control failed to impress the currency market yesterday, traders said. 

   "Looking at rates now, they're not going to have to work very hard to achieve stability," one trader said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Appropriations Committee</ORGANIZATION> that a further decline in the dollar could be counterproductive and as a result, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and its major trading partners will work closely to foster exchange rate stability. 
"I want to assure you that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> will do its part in this effort," he said. 

The estimated volume was 5.8 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$431.50</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                     LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                    <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 1, 1988</DATE>
    Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                          <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <ORGANIZATION>New York
                            Tue</ORGANIZATION>.        Tue.         Mon.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.7760      1.7770       1.7740
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.7948      0.7949       0.7946
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 5.7095      5.71925      5.7175
    Japanese yen ....... 128.40      128.63       128.25
    Swiss franc .......... 1.3925      1.3920       1.3910
    West German mark ..... 1.6875      1.6895       1.6875
    Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
        Tue</ORGANIZATION>.          Tue.            Tue.          Mon.
       431.00        429.30          429.15        430.50
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880314-0033 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Dealers to Focus on U.K. to Determine If It Will Attempt to Stem Pound's Rise </HL>
<AUTHOR> Michael R. Sesit and Peter Torday (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP FREST JAPAN CANDA </CO>
<IN> PCS CMD MON FRX </IN>
<TEXT>
   Profit-hungry currency traders this week will be focusing on the British government to see if it finally acts to keep a lid on its fast-rising currency. 

   The British pound already has climbed <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> against the dollar and <PERCENT>2.8%</PERCENT> against the West German mark in the past seven trading days. 
So dealers and analysts are trying to guess at what point the British government will do something to stem the rise -- if, indeed, it does anything at all. 

   Meanwhile, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s economy is robust, its interest rates high, and the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> appears to have abandoned intervention to hold sterling down. 
But last week also was marked by what appears to be a public conflict between Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> and her most senior <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> official over exchange-rate policy. 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the pound advanced to <MONEY>$1.8565</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.8460</MONEY> late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 

   Right now, the betting is that the British currency will get another shot in the arm tomorrow when Chancellor of the Exchequer <PERSON>Nigel Lawson</PERSON> delivers to parliament the government's budget for the fiscal year beginning in <DATE>April</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Peter Fellner</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> economist at <ORGANIZATION>James Capel &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, expects <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>'s budget to show a surplus for the year in addition to as much as <MONEY>#4 billion</MONEY> (<MONEY>$7.4 billion</MONEY>) in tax cuts, particularly to the wealthy. 

   "The budget is likely to be very positive for the pound," says <PERSON>Gavyn Davies</PERSON>, chief <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> economist for <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs International Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 
Noting that <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> has the opportunity to combine a fairly tight fiscal program with "supply-side cuts in marginal income-tax rates," he adds: "You can get the best bits of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s tax package without the worst bits of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s tax package." 

   As long as the tax cuts are modest and don't threaten the anticipated surplus, "there'll be no downside for sterling," predicts <PERSON>Paul Chertkow</PERSON>, director of economics at <ORGANIZATION>Security Pacific Hoare Govett</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 

   For more than a year, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> maintained an unofficial policy of trying to hold the pound between 2.93 West German marks and <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY>. 
When the currency threatened to break above <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> resorted to intervention -- at times massively -- to keep the pound from rising. 

   The pound-mark rate -- and, thus, the other European currencies that effectively or actually are pegged to it -- are more important to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> than the pound-dollar rate. 
That's because about <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION>'s exports go to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> vs. <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   But <DATE>last week</DATE>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Thatcher</PERSON>'s opposition to any more large-scale currency intervention enabled the pound to break through the 3-mark ceiling. 
Having risen as high as <MONEY>3.0850 marks</MONEY> during the week, sterling stood at <MONEY>3.0818 marks</MONEY> late <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   Twice last week, <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> wouldn't use either "excessive" intervention or lower interest rates to weaken its currency. 
She also argued that "there is no way to buck the market." 
<PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>'s prime motive is to battle inflationary pressures in the British economy, which economists say is expanding at <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> a year in real terms with inflation currently at <PERCENT>3.3%</PERCENT> and expected to rise to <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> at year end. 
Meanwhile, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s economy is growing at about half that pace with inflation at only <PERCENT>0.9%</PERCENT> a year. 

   <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>'s stance has put her at odds with <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>, who has advocated maintaining a tightly controlled course for sterling and <DATE>last week</DATE> contended that its advance was "unsustainable." 

   Moreover, senior <ORGANIZATION>British Treasury</ORGANIZATION> officials continue to insist that exchange-rate policy hadn't changed, and have asserted the government would use selective currency intervention and interest-rate changes to keep the pound stable. 

   So far, the market is skeptical. 
"<PERSON>Mr. 
Lawson</PERSON> can hardly stand up now and say we need fixity of exchange rates, <PERSON>Bretton Woods</PERSON> style," says <PERSON>Stephen Lewis</PERSON>, director of economic research at <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> stockbrokers <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Drew</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of the <ORGANIZATION>Union Bank of Switzerland</ORGANIZATION>. 

   "At the moment we are in a sort of limbo period. 
No one knows what actually the policy is," adds <PERSON>Mr. Fellner</PERSON> of <PERSON>James Capel</PERSON>. 

   Nonetheless, many analysts suspect that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> has an upper limit in mind and predict that the market will force the issue by trying to push sterling still higher. 

   Many traders believe the first test of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s intentions will be <MONEY>3.10 marks</MONEY> and come soon after the release of the budget. 
Currency dealers "will be tapping lightly at 3.10 to see if they can bring the <ORGANIZATION>Bank</ORGANIZATION> (of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>) out," predicts <PERSON>Jeff Mondschein</PERSON>, a vice president at <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Davies</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs</ORGANIZATION> puts the threshhold a little higher. 
"They won't make much of an effort to stop a rise to <MONEY>3.15 marks</MONEY>; anything much above that and they will intervene," he says. 
Meanwhile, he sees sterling rising to at least <MONEY>$1.90</MONEY> to <MONEY>$2</MONEY> "quite soon." 

   Regardless, traders are nervous. 
Noting that the pound didn't climb to <MONEY>3.20 marks</MONEY> last week as some people had predicted, <PERSON>James Capel</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Mr. Fellner</PERSON> says: "Foreign exchange operators are sitting cautious; they don't know if the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> is lurking around the corner to pounce." 

   ---
   <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s Currency Activity
   The dollar fell against most major foreign currencies <DATE>Friday</DATE> in what dealers said were quiet, nervous markets. 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> activity, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency stood at <MONEY>1.6600 marks</MONEY> and <MONEY>127.36 yen</MONEY>, down from <MONEY>1.6640 marks</MONEY> and <MONEY>128 yen</MONEY> late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
Dealers said they were apprehensive that <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s release of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trade data for <DATE>January</DATE> could be negative for the dollar. 

   In midmorning trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>127.20 yen</MONEY>. 

Estimated volume was 3.5 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$442.30</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                Late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Trading
               <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>March 11, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                          <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <ORGANIZATION>New York
                            Fri</ORGANIZATION>.        Fri.         Thu.
                 (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
   British pound ........ 1.8565      1.8535       1.8460
   Canadian dollar ...... 0.7956      0.7954       0.7956
              (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
   French franc ......... 5.6475      5.6580       5.6684
   Japanese yen ....... 127.36      127.78       128.00
   Swiss franc .......... 1.3705      1.3670       1.3785
   West German mark ..... 1.6600      1.6586       1.6640
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                        GOLD PRICES
              (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
      <ORGANIZATION>Comex      London PM      London AM      Comex
       Fri</ORGANIZATION>.         Fri.           Fri.         Thu.
      441.30      441.80          444.10       443.20
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870305-0031 </DOCNO>
<HL> Pound Rises,
U.S. Unit Gains
Against Others
---
By Charles W. Stevens
<DD> 03/05/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP CANDA FREST JAPAN
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The British pound resumed its rise yesterday, after having fallen the previous day on rumored intervention by the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar, meanwhile, gained against most other major currencies, despite its decline against sterling. 

   Despite the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s apparent attempt <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to thwart the recent rush of speculative money into the pound, dealers said sterling remains an attractive alternative to the usually more dominant market involving the dollar and the West German mark, which has shown little movement lately. 

   "With no action in the dollar-mark, the sterling cross is commanding attention," said a New York-based trader for a West German bank. 

   In the so-called cross rate between the pound and the mark, sterling yesterday climbed <PERCENT>0.9%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>2.8818 marks</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading from 2.8558 <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
Against the dollar, the pound firmed to <MONEY>$1.5644</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.5610</MONEY>. 

   The relatively stable dollar-mark rate has decreased opportunities for making profits from trading those units, dealers said. 
That, in turn, has increased interest in sterling. 

   The relatively higher yields on sterling-denominated investments make the pound an attractive alternative. 
Optimism about a budget proposal due from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s government on <DATE>March 17</DATE> also continues to fuel sterling purchases. 
The budget is expected to include a tax cut and reduced government borrowing needs. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>William G. Orsini</PERSON>, corporate foreign-exchange manager for <ORGANIZATION>Bank of Montreal</ORGANIZATION>, said traders also believe that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s economic outlook justifies the pound's gains. 
He cited this year's surge on <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s stock exchange, in contrast to the decline in West German stock prices. 

   In other foreign-exchange activity yesterday, the dollar rose to <MONEY>1.8421 marks</MONEY> from 1.8295 and firmed to 153.76 Japanese yen from 153.56. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the dollar fell against the Japanese currency to <MONEY>153.70 yen</MONEY> from 153.76 in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <TIME>yesterday afternoon</TIME>. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, gold for <DATE>March</DATE> delivery climbed <MONEY>$3.20</MONEY> an ounce to <MONEY>$410.40</MONEY> in moderate trading. 
Volume was estimated at 3.5 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$409.25</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                     CURRENCY RATES
                         <LOCATION>New York   Home Mkt</LOCATION>.  <LOCATION>New York
                           Wed</LOCATION>.       Wed.       Tues.
                    (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
 British pound .......... 1.5644     1.5650     1.5610
 Canadian dollar ........ 0.7496     0.7497     0.7504
             (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
 French franc ........... 6.1248     6.0920     6.0925
 Japanese yen ......... 153.76     153.48     153.56
 Swiss franc ............ 1.5523     1.5440     1.5410
 West German mark ....... 1.8421     1.8304     1.8295
   Based on average of late buying and selling rates.
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                       GOLD PRICES
            (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
         <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM     London AM       Comex
          Wed</ORGANIZATION>.          Wed.          Wed.          Tues.
         410.40        406.55        407.65        407.20
   Comex based on settlement price for gold delivery in the
nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of
five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870312-0005 </DOCNO>
<HL> U.S. Currency Is Mixed, Sterling Gains;
Interbank Trading Spurs Wide Swings
---
By Charles W. Stevens
<DD> 03/12/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar was narrowly mixed and the British pound stronger as both currencies seesawed in foreign-exchange trading yesterday. 

   Dealers attributed the wide swings to short-term speculative moves -- generated by interbank trading -- that didn't represent any change in the long-term outlook for either currency. 

   "It's basically the exchange market trading with itself," said <PERSON>James M. Pugh</PERSON>, vice president of corporate foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Manufacturers Hanover Trust Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"Corporate demand isn't there on either side." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> was also rumored to have intervened in yesterday's trading, selling sterling at levels near the top of the currency's rise. 
Officials at the central bank and <ORGANIZATION>British Treasury</ORGANIZATION> declined to confirm the intervention rumors but reiterated that the government doesn't have specific exchange-rate targets for the pound. 

   The dollar's movement against the bellwether West German mark was the widest swing between those currencies in three weeks, traders said. 
The dollar traded as low as <MONEY>1.8538 marks</MONEY> in early European dealings and climbed to an intraday high of 1.8733 during brisk, midday trading in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   Expectations for the release of bullish <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economic indicators, beginning with today's retail sales report, were partly responsible for the dollar's rise against the mark, traders said. 
But much of the move was purely on speculation, they added. 
"Buyers came out of the woodwork," <PERSON>Mr. Pugh</PERSON> said. 

   Then sellers followed, as speculators took profits on the dollar's rise, driving the currency back to <MONEY>1.8600 marks</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, up slightly from 1.8565 <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   Trading in sterling followed a similar pattern. 
After trading as low as <MONEY>$1.5840</MONEY> early in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, the pound climbed to an intraday high of <MONEY>$1.6000</MONEY>, and then fell back. 
"It just got hammered," said <PERSON>Anthony J. Murphy</PERSON>, senior dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank of Canada</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"I don't think it was a change in philosophy, just profit-taking." 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, the pound stood at <MONEY>$1.5933</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$1.5865</MONEY>. 

   A trader for a British bank maintained that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> sold sterling yesterday to slow the momentum of the currency's rise. 
The pound has drawn attention recently as <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s high interest rates have siphoned speculative capital from the comparatively stable market between dollars and marks. 

   Against the Japanese yen, the dollar eased to <MONEY>153.69 yen</MONEY> from 153.73. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, gold for <DATE>March</DATE> delivery rose <MONEY>10 cents</MONEY> an ounce, to <MONEY>$406.90</MONEY>, in moderate trading. 
The estimated volume was 2.2 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$407</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                        CURRENCY RATES
                          <LOCATION>New York    Home Mkt</LOCATION>.    <LOCATION>New York
                            Wed</LOCATION>.         Wed.        Tues.
                      (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.5933      1.5905       1.5865
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.7564      0.7567       0.7492
              (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 6.1895      6.1825       6.1760
    Japanese yen ....... 153.69      153.53       153.73
    Swiss franc .......... 1.5618      1.5695       1.5645
    West German mark ..... 1.8600      1.8580       1.8565
   Based on average of late buying and selling rates.
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
        Wed</ORGANIZATION>.          Wed.            Wed.         Tues.
       406.90        407.20          406.85        406.80
   Comex based on settlement price for gold delivery in the
nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of
five major dealers.
   ---
   <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> to Reduce 2 Rates
   Special to The Wall Street Journal
   <LOCATION>BRUSSELS</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> -- <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>'s central bank said it is
cutting two interest rates one-half percentage point each,
effective today.
   The reductions will lower the discount rate to <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> from
<PERCENT>8.5%</PERCENT> and the Lombard rate to <PERCENT>8.25%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>8.75%</PERCENT>.
   The central bank said it is reducing the rates in reaction
to recent rate cuts in other European nations and to reflect
the "better position" of the Belgian franc in the <ORGANIZATION>European
Monetary System</ORGANIZATION>.
   The discount rate is the lending fee charged by central
banks to financial institutions, while the Lombard rate is a
rate under which banks borrow from the central bank using
certain securities as collateral. The Lombard is
traditionally meant only for last-resort financing.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870313-0023 </DOCNO>
<HL> Dollar, Sterling
Ease on Rumors
Of Intervention
---
By Charles W. Stevens
<DD> 03/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP FREST JAPAN CANDA
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar eased against most other major currencies and sterling also weakened yesterday as rumors of central-bank intervention earlier this week tempered bullishness for both currencies. 

   The rumored intervention "took the steam out of the market . . . it just died," said <PERSON>Robert K. Ryan</PERSON>, vice president, foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Irving Trust Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   Meanwhile, the effect of yesterday's better-than-expected report that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> retail sales climbed <PERCENT>4.1%</PERCENT> last month was offset by a downward revision of the <DATE>January</DATE> figure, to a <PERCENT>7.4%</PERCENT> decline from the <PERCENT>5.8%</PERCENT> drop originally reported. 
"The <DATE>February</DATE> number was great, but the revision was horrendous," <PERSON>Mr. Ryan</PERSON> said. 

   As previously reported, the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> is believed to have sold sterling on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to slow the pound's recent surge. 
The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> was also rumored to have sold dollars <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and yesterday in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> to damp the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency's rise. 

   The rumors, though unsubstantiated, prevented many market participants from acting on their generally bullish near-term view of both currencies. 

   Traders have been cautious about opening or maintaining large currency positions in the wake of a <DATE>Feb. 22</DATE> agreement meant to stabilize exchange rates between the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and five top economic allies. 

   "They really don't want the market to run away with the currency," said <PERSON>J. Steven Stekly</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Bank of Boston</ORGANIZATION> trader, referring to the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s rumored sterling intervention. 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, the dollar stood at <MONEY>1.8590 West German marks</MONEY>, off from 1.8600 the day before. 
The dollar slipped to 153.38 Japanese yen from 153.69. 
The British pound eased to <MONEY>$1.5875</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.5933</MONEY>, and dipped to <MONEY>2.9512 marks</MONEY> from 2.9635. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> the dollar rose against the Japanese currency to <MONEY>153.45 yen</MONEY> from 153.38 in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <TIME>yesterday afternoon</TIME>. 

   Despite the downward revision of <DATE>January</DATE> retail sales, traders said the <DATE>February</DATE> figure supports the market's more positive attitude toward the dollar that has stemmed from earlier economic reports. 
And so-called technical analysis of charts illustrating the dollar's recent trading pattern -- which many dealers study -- indicates continued gains by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency. 

   "Technically and fundamentally, the dollar is in a bullish trend for the near term," said <PERSON>John W. Baker</PERSON>, chief foreign-exchange trader at <ORGANIZATION>Bank Julius Baer &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"We've been having higher highs and high lows each day. 
The dollar is trading beautifully in an up channel." 

   "Sterling is also following a perfectly bullish trend line" on charts, <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON> said. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, gold for <DATE>March</DATE> delivery rose <MONEY>$1.80</MONEY> an ounce, to <MONEY>$408.70</MONEY>, in moderate trading. 
The estimated volume was 3.1 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$409.20</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                       CURRENCY RATES
                          <LOCATION>New York    Home Mkt</LOCATION>.    <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
                            Thurs.      Thurs.       Wed.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.5875       1.5882      1.5933
   Canadian dollar ...... 0.7583       0.7583      0.7564
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 6.1875       6.1880      6.1895
    Japanese yen ....... 153.38       153.68      153.69
    Swiss franc .......... 1.5593       1.5590      1.5618
    West German mark ..... 1.8590       1.8567      1.8600
   Based on average of late buying and selling rates.
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
       Thurs</ORGANIZATION>.        Thurs.          Thurs.         Wed.
       408.70        409.90          408.00        406.90
   Comex based on settlement price for gold delivery in the
nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of
five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880210-0048 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Dollar Drops a Bit; U.K. Isn't Boosting Rates, Official Says </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   The dollar eased in quiet foreign-exchange dealings yesterday as market participants awaited <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s report on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> merchandise trade. 

   Traders' expectations that the report covering <DATE>December</DATE> will show a continued shrinkage of the trade deficit supported the dollar in a stable but narrow trading range. 
Despite such optimism, uncertainty about the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION>'s trade data discouraged many dealers from taking large positions. 

   "People are perfectly content to stay inactive until the trade number," <PERSON>Robert Hatcher</PERSON>, vice president and corporate foreign-exchange dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Barclays Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said. 

   With activity in the dollar stymied by anticipation of the trade data, "cross-trading" increased among the British pound, West German mark and Japanese yen. 
"That's typical of a market that isn't confident on where the dollar's heading," <PERSON>Mr. Hatcher</PERSON> said. 

   In cross-trading, the pound eased against the mark yesterday after British Chancellor of the Exchequer <PERSON>Nigel Lawson</PERSON> said he doesn't see any "great pressure" for higher British interest rates. 
The comment, made in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION> after a meeting of the finance ministers of the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION>, contradicted market speculation that an official rate increase is in the works. 

   Higher British interest rates would increase the appeal of sterling-denominated investments and, in turn, demand for sterling. 
In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading yesterday, the pound stood at <MONEY>2.9679 marks</MONEY>, off from 2.9738 <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 

   When asked by reporters whether he saw a need to increase interest rates in the near term, <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> said he would act "when necessary." 

Asked whether <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> would join the <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> mechanism, <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> said, "We hope to continue with a policy that encourages exchange-rate stability." 
He declined to be more specific. 

   His comment concerning sterling's relationship to the <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> didn't immediately affect the market, but it confirmed speculation. 
From watching the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s pattern of foreign-exchange-market intervention over most of last year, dealers have assumed that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is enforcing a trading range for sterling between 2.95 and <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> is centered around the West German currency. 
"Sterling has been a shadow member of the <ORGANIZATION>EMS</ORGANIZATION> for several months," said <ORGANIZATION>Barclays</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Hatcher</PERSON>. 

   The pound inched higher against the dollar, as did most other major currencies yesterday. 
The pound firmed to <MONEY>$1.7510</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.7495</MONEY>, while the dollar eased to <MONEY>1.6950 marks</MONEY>, from 1.6998. 
The dollar was unchanged at <MONEY>128.83 yen</MONEY>. 

   In midmorning <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>129.05 yen</MONEY>. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, gold for current delivery rose <MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> an ounce to <MONEY>$441.60</MONEY> in moderate trading. 
The estimated volume was 3.4 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$442.35</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                     LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                     <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Feb. 9, 1988</DATE>
    Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                          <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <ORGANIZATION>New York
                            Tue</ORGANIZATION>.         Tue.        Mon.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.7510      1.7465       1.7495
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.7878      0.7882       0.7896
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 5.7195      5.7480       5.7365
    Japanese yen ....... 128.83      129.08       128.83
    Swiss franc .......... 1.3875      1.3955       1.3905
    West German mark ..... 1.6950      1.7029       1.6998
    Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM      Comex
        Tue</ORGANIZATION>.          Tue.            Tue.         Mon.
       441.60        438.60          439.25       440.40
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870304-0085 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sterling's Surge
Halts; Intervention
By U.K. Rumored
---
By Charles W. Stevens
<DD> 03/04/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP JAPAN CANDA FREST
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The British pound's surge halted yesterday as the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> was widely rumored to have intervened in currency markets to cool speculative interest in the currency. 

   Although the central bank's rumored selling of pounds for West German marks appeared to be effective, sending sterling lower, dealers said that the British currency still holds considerable investor interest and could rebound. 

   Meanwhile, against a backdrop of bad economic news, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar fell against most other major currencies as it continued its lethargic trading in a narrow band. 

   Sterling's sharp gains prior to yesterday's rumored intervention were partly caused by inaction in trading of dollars for West German marks in recent weeks, dealers said. 
The situation directed speculators' attention to higher-yielding currencies, such as the pound. 
The Australian and <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> currencies also have attracted new investor interest, dealers said. 

   Traders said the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s action was aimed at "smoothing out" sterling's latest exchange-rate swing. 
"They fired a warning shot across the bow, and it was effective. 
The market took heed," said <PERSON>Robert Hatcher</PERSON>, vice president and corporate foreign exchange dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Barclays Bank Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hatcher</PERSON> said the rush of speculative interest in the pound may have worried the British government, which would prefer more stable exchange rates as it prepares to release its federal budget later this month. 
"The problem is, when you have a lot of hot money moving into the sterling market like that, it can slide out of the country just as fast," he said. 
"The last thing they want right now are currency gyrations." 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, the pound stood at <MONEY>2.8558 marks</MONEY>, down <PERCENT>0.6%</PERCENT> from 2.8741 <DATE>Monday</DATE>, when the pound rose <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT>. 
Sterling had climbed to more than <MONEY>2.88 marks</MONEY> yesterday before the rumored intervention. 
Against the dollar, the pound slipped to <MONEY>$1.5610</MONEY> from <MONEY>$1.5643</MONEY>. 

   Relatively higher British interest rates have attracted speculators to sterling during the recent dollar-mark doldrums. 

   Yields on three-month sterling Eurodeposits are almost five percentage points above similar dollar investments and more than six points higher than for three-month mark Eurodeposits. 

   Traders expect additional developments to benefit sterling. 
The British government's new budget is expected to be released <DATE>March 17</DATE> and to call for tax cuts and lower public borrowing needs. 
The budget is seen as possibly enhancing the reelection chances of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Conservative government, which would also help the pound. 

   "Prospects for sterling still look better than on anything else," said <PERSON>Frank Pusateri</PERSON>, senior corporate trader at <ORGANIZATION>Bank of Boston</ORGANIZATION>. 
"If they {the government} push the right buttons at the right time, that could make sterling look even more attractive." 

   Speculation that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> may also soon decrease its lending fee to financial institutions is also helping the pound indirectly, traders said. 
They said some investors are buying sterling to purchase British government bonds in the expectation that the value of those securities will rise following any interest-rate cut. 

   In other foreign-exchange trading yesterday, the dollar fell to <MONEY>1.8295 marks</MONEY> from 1.8373 and to 153.56 Japanese yen from 153.70. 

   The dollar's decline came amid more weak economic statistics that confirmed the generally bearish climate for the currency but failed to shake it out of its narrow trading range. 
The government reported that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> leading economic indicators fell <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> and that single-family home sales dropped <PERCENT>6.8%</PERCENT> in <DATE>January</DATE>. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the dollar fell against the Japanese currency to <MONEY>153.48 yen</MONEY> from 153.56 in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <TIME>yesterday afternoon</TIME>. 

   On the <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, gold for <DATE>March</DATE> delivery climbed <MONEY>$3.60</MONEY> an ounce, to <MONEY>$407.20</MONEY>, in moderate trading. 
The estimated volume was 2.8 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$406.45</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                       CURRENCY RATES
                         <LOCATION>New York    Home Mkt</LOCATION>.    <LOCATION>New York
                           Tues</LOCATION>.       Tues.        Mon.
                      (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ...... 1.5610       1.5600       1.5643
    Canadian dollar .... 0.7504       0.7505       0.7509
               (n foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ....... 6.0925       6.1020       6.1045
    Japanese yen ..... 153.56       153.58       153.70
    Swiss franc ........ 1.5410       1.5440       1.5455
    West German mark ... 1.8295       1.8340       1.8373
   Based on average of late buying and selling rates.
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                         GOLD PRICES
             (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
        <ORGANIZATION>Comex      London PM      London AM      Comex
        Tues</ORGANIZATION>.        Tues.          Tues.         Mon.
        407.20      403.80         403.70        403.60
   Comex based on settlement price for gold delivery in the
nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of
five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880516-0017 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Continued Climb Seen for British Pound; Interest Rates and Policy Debate Cited --- A Wall Street Journal News Roundup </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   Currency analysts in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> expect the pound to continue its upward move this week, buoyed by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s high interest rates and differences over exchange rate policy inside its government. 

   The pound could be poised to breach the 3.20 West German marks level, analysts say. 
In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the pound stood at <MONEY>$1.8915</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$1.8832</MONEY> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. 
It climbed to <MONEY>3.1853 marks</MONEY> from 3.1681. 
For the week, the pound rose <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT> against the dollar and <PERCENT>1.9%</PERCENT> against the mark. 
Traders say the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> intervened in <DATE>Friday</DATE> dealings, selling sterling against dollars and marks, but the intervention appeared to be aimed at smoothing market conditions. 


   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey Howe</PERSON>, the foreign secretary and a longtime <PERSON>Thatcher</PERSON> loyalist, appeared to support the chancellor's quest for more stable exchange rates, against the prime minister, who says governments shouldn't "buck" the currency market. 
But he departed from his text to say: "We cannot forever go on adding that qualification to the underlying commitment." 

   Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey</PERSON>'s remarks were construed as evidence that government policy is in disarray. 
Weekend press speculation cast doubt on Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey</PERSON>'s political future and suggested that <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> may want to leave office later this year, adding to concern about exchange rate policy among Conservative members of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. 

   In a radio interview yesterday, Sir <PERSON>William Clark</PERSON>, chairman of the Conservative parliamentarians' finance committee, called on <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> to issue a statement saying that agreement exists on exchange rate policy. 

   Aides to the prime minister's office said yesterday that there isn't a rift between <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>; that she isn't planning a cabinet reshuffle; that Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey</PERSON> has made remarks about the monetary system before, and that more explicit remarks by <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> about the pound would only play into the hands of speculators. 
"There are no plans at all for a statement" about the pound, a spokesman for <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> said. 

   Normally such political uncertainty is poison for a currency, but <PERSON>Geoffrey Dennis</PERSON>, international currency economist at <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> stock brokerage <ORGANIZATION>James Capel &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, said the turmoil is contributing to upward pressure on the pound. 
<PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> has so far failed to sway <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON> to more stable exchange rates, <PERSON>Mr. Dennis</PERSON> noted. 
If the chancellor or Sir <PERSON>Geoffrey</PERSON> were to quit, there would be even less resistance to the prime minister's free market views, he said. 

   Traders said <DATE>Friday</DATE> interest in the pound was sparked by a <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> report that was widely interpreted to mean that the central bank favors higher interest rates to combat domestic inflation. 
The bank said in its quarterly report, issued late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, that it would prefer a different monetary policy mix from its current one, saying: "a combination of a stronger currency and lower interest rates doesn't represent an ideal response to current (inflationary) concerns and a different balance would be desirable." 

   The pound also received a boost when <PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>, during parliamentary question time <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, declined to say if she agreed with <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>'s view that the pound shouldn't appreciate further. 

   These factors helped convince market participants that the government's ability to control the pound's ascent is limited. 
<PERSON>J. Thomas Stanley</PERSON>, vice president of foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch Capital Markets</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said, "I think we're on our way to 3.20 (marks)." 

   Away from day-to-day concerns, economic factors have bolstered the pound. 
Later this week, the British government will publish data on employment, average earnings, money supply, bank lending and retail prices, which are expected to underline the present robust economic growth but also the persistence of underlying inflationary pressures. 

   Although some economists in the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s financial district, fear that strong domestic demand could lead <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> into a damaging balance of payments crisis later this year, foreign investors are more impressed by evidence of the country's economic dynamism. 
Another reason for currency dealers to flock into sterling is the lack of movement in dollar exchange rates against other major currencies. 
This limits opportunities for trading profits. 

   "The quieter the (dollar) market is in general, the more we're looking for currencies with a discernible trend to them," <PERSON>Trevor W. Woodland</PERSON>, vice president of foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Harris Trust &amp; Savings Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, said. 
"Since there isn't a lot of activity in other currencies, it's very easy to zero in on sterling." 

   In other trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the dollar firmed but was little changed against other major currencies as dealers squared positions ahead of tomorrow's release of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trade data for <DATE>March</DATE>. 
Economists figure that a robust rise in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> exports probably pared the trade deficit from <DATE>February</DATE>'s <MONEY>$13.83 billion</MONEY>. 

   In midmorning trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>124.70 yen</MONEY>. 

   On <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, current-delivery gold rose <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> an ounce, to <MONEY>$452.20</MONEY>, in moderate trading <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
The estimated volume was 3.4 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$452.50</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                   LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                    <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <DATE>May 13, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                          <ORGANIZATION>New York   Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.  <ORGANIZATION>New York
                            Fri</ORGANIZATION>.       Fri.       Thu.
                        (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
 British pound ........... 1.8915     1.8905     1.8832
 Canadian dollar ......... 0.8112     0.8112     0.8113
                (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
 French franc ............ 5.7085     5.6970     5.6985
 Japanese yen .......... 124.76     124.68     124.54
 Swiss franc ............. 1.4010     1.3995     1.3990
 West German mark ........ 1.6840     1.6805     1.6823
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
         <ORGANIZATION>Comex      London PM    London AM      Comex
          Fri</ORGANIZATION>.         Fri.         Fri.         Thu.
         452.20       449.50       451.05       451.90
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880310-0041 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Baker Remarks Help Sterling Continue Rally --- U.S. Treasury Chief Seeks To Allay Fears of Shift In U.K. Monetary Policy </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST JAPAN EUROP CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   Sterling's rally stretched into its fifth day yesterday, encouraged by remarks of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Treasury</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>James Baker</PERSON> endorsing the recent shift in British monetary policy. 

   Trading again focused on the pound's exchange rate with the West German currency, which rose <PERCENT>0.3%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>3.0822 marks</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading yesterday, from 3.0720 <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
Meanwhile, the dollar firmed against most major currencies. 

   Sterling gave up some of its gains from earlier in the day, following selling to take profits on its rise over the past week. 
The pound finished the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading day at <MONEY>$1.8445</MONEY>, up slightly from <MONEY>$1.8424</MONEY> the day before. 

   Sterling's so-called "cross rate" with the West German currency has been playing center stage in the foreign exchange market since the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>, for the first time in more than a year, let the pound rise above <MONEY>3.00 marks</MONEY> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 

   Previously, the British central bank maintained a tight cap on the pound's value by intervening in currency markets to sell sterling, thus reducing its exchange rate and thereby helping British exporters. 
But British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> wouldn't intervene or cut interest rates to weaken sterling because of concerns about inflation heating up in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s buoyant economy. 

   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> voiced support for the shift in British monetary policy, saying that the change reflected monetary policy considerations within <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and in relation to other currencies in the <ORGANIZATION>European Monetary System</ORGANIZATION>, an eight-currency exchange rate mechanism centered on the mark. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON>'s remarks to the congressional <ORGANIZATION>Joint Economic Committee</ORGANIZATION> removed some speculation about British monetary policy. 
<PERSON>Mrs. Thatcher</PERSON>'s statement <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> had prompted speculation that the monetary policy was shifting from the <ORGANIZATION>Group of Seven</ORGANIZATION>'s agreement on exchange-rate stability. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Group of Seven</ORGANIZATION> nations -- <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> -- reaffirmed the agreement last <DATE>December</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON> said the <PERSON>Thatcher</PERSON> statement isn't "in any way" contrary to the <ORGANIZATION>Group of Seven</ORGANIZATION> agreement and that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> remains "fully committed" to the accord. 

   With relatively high interest rates and a booming economy in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, traders predicted the pound's rally will carry sterling still higher against the West German currency, to <MONEY>3.10 marks</MONEY>. 
"This is not over. 
We have to try 3.10 (marks) to see if the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> is there" to stem sterling's rise, said <PERSON>Francoise Soares-Kemp</PERSON>, treasury vice president at <ORGANIZATION>Credit Suisse</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   But some market participants began expressing wariness about sterling's outlook. 
"It has the potential to disappoint people very quickly. 
There's a lot of speculative buying," said <PERSON>Jeff Mondschein</PERSON>, vice president and foreign exchange manager at <ORGANIZATION>Merrill Lynch Capital Markets</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
Speculators could rush out of the currency just as quickly as they came in it, he said. 
"There are also a lot of positions looking to take profits. 
Some people have been playing it since (sterling was) 2.96" marks, <PERSON>Mr. Mondschein</PERSON> added. 

   In other dealings, the dollar firmed to <MONEY>1.6710 marks</MONEY>, from 1.6674, and to <MONEY>128.15 yen</MONEY>, from 127.85. 
In early <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, it opened at <MONEY>128.25 yen</MONEY>. 

   Traders said the dollar avoided a possible pitfall from the Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> voting results. 
A strong showing by Rep. <PERSON>Richard Gephardt</PERSON>, which didn't occur, could have put the dollar under heavy pressure because his views were considered protectionist and harmful to the economy. 

The estimated volume was 2.8 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$435.70</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                   Late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Trading
                 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 9, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                         <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <LOCATION>New York
                           Wed</LOCATION>.        Wed.         Tue.
                      (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ....... 1.8445       1.8475       1.8424
    Canadian dollar ..... 0.7974       0.7973       0.7974 -
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ........ 5.6615       5.6550       5.6475
    Japanese yen ...... 128.15       128.08       127.85
    Swiss franc ......... 1.3805       1.3785       1.3770
    West German mark .... 1.6710       1.6692       1.6674
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                        GOLD PRICES
             (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
    <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
     Wed</ORGANIZATION>.          Wed.           Wed.           Tue.
    436.20        436.35          436.10        435.30
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880510-0024 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Sterling Surges, Causing Action By Central Bank --- Bullish Report in London Is Cited in Sharp Rally; Dollar Climbs Slightly </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST JAPAN EUROP CANDA </CO>
<IN> PCS CMD MON FRX </IN>
<TEXT>
   A bullish article on sterling by a <ORGANIZATION>Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> economist in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> was cited in yesterday's sharp rally by the British currency. 

   The pound surged <PERCENT>1.1%</PERCENT> to stand at <MONEY>$1.8815</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, from <MONEY>$1.8605</MONEY> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and climbed <PERCENT>1.3%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>3.16 marks</MONEY>, from 3.12 in heavy trading. 

   The pound's sudden rally prompted the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> to intervene in foreign exchange trading by selling sterling for dollars, and thus capping the British currency's rise for the time being. 
But traders and economists continued to voice optimism for the pound. 

   In other trading, the dollar firmed slightly. 

   The article cited by many traders for kicking off <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s rally appeared in the <DATE>Sunday</DATE> Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and was written by <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs</ORGANIZATION>'s London-based chief international economist, <PERSON>David Morrison</PERSON>, an influential exchange-rate forecaster. 
In a recent report, <PERSON>Mr. Morrison</PERSON> said the pound could rise to <MONEY>$2</MONEY> within six months and reach the 3.2-mark level in the same period. 

   According to traders, the market reacted to a reassertion of that forecast in the <DATE>Sunday</DATE> article and a statement that British exporters could tolerate even higher sterling exchange rates. 
A stronger currency makes British exports more costly for foreign consumers. 

   The article reinforced strong bullish sentiment toward sterling already established in the market. 
Because of a strong economy and relatively high interest rates, the pound has been a darling among currency traders this year. 
"A lot of (economic) fundamentals are in favor of the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> 
This trend could possibly continue," <PERSON>Cynthia H. Johnson</PERSON>, vice president of foreign exchange at <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> unit. 

   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s high interest rates have become particularly attractive to traders recently because of the dollar's stability in the market. 
Unable to profit from the dollar's volatility, traders have bought sterling to earn its higher yields. 
Yesterday, three-month Eurosterling deposits yielded <PERCENT>8 5/16%</PERCENT>, in contrast to 7 3/8 for similar dollar investments, and <PERCENT>3 9/16%</PERCENT> for three-month Euromark deposits. 

   "Investors still like to buy sterling and hold it," said <PERSON>Antonio Bustamante</PERSON>, global foreign exchange manager at <ORGANIZATION>Marine Midland Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   In <PERSON>Mr. Morrison</PERSON>'s most recent monthly economic report for <ORGANIZATION>Goldman Sachs</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> economic growth for this year is estimated at <PERCENT>3.6%</PERCENT>, in contrast to a <PERCENT>1.8%</PERCENT> forecast for West German economic expansion, and <PERCENT>2.2%</PERCENT> for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

The estimated volume was 1.2 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$447.40</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>124.75 yen</MONEY>. 

   ---

                    LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                     <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>May 9, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                         <ORGANIZATION>New York   Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.   <LOCATION>New York
                           Mon</LOCATION>.       Mon.        Fri.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ....... 1.8815      1.8805     1.8605
    Canadian dollar ..... 0.8074      0.8072     0.8076
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ........ 5.7040      5.7075     5.7085
    Japanese yen ...... 124.85      124.88     124.75
    Swiss franc ......... 1.4000      1.4000     1.3995
    West German mark .... 1.6817      1.6803     1.6796
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
            <ORGANIZATION>Comex    London PM    London AM    Comex
             Mon</ORGANIZATION>.       Mon.         Mon.       Fri. -
            447.30     444.40       443.60     443.70
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880324-0016 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: High-Yielding Currencies Rise As Dollar Drops --- Australia, Britain Intervene To Try to Stem Increases In Their Monetary Units </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   High-yielding currencies continued surging yesterday, prompting the British and Australian central banks to intervene in foreign exchange markets to restrain the rise of their currencies, dealers said. 

   The dollar was slightly weaker against most other major currencies. 
However, according to some dealers, the dollar is benefiting indirectly from so-called cross-trading between non-dollar currencies. 
Cross-trading has increased recently as part of the general movement into such high-interest rate currencies as the British pound and the Australian dollar, from such relatively low-yielding currencies as the West German mark and yen. 

   The dollar lost the most ground to the pound, as the British currency climbed <PERCENT>0.3%</PERCENT> to stand at <MONEY>$1.8375</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, from <MONEY>$1.8315</MONEY> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
Of more concern to British monetary authorities, however, was sterling's rise against the mark following sharp gains over the past two weeks. 
The stronger pound hurts British exporters by making <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> goods more expensive abroad. 

   In early <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> trading the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> sold sterling, according to traders, as the pound climbed to <MONEY>3.11 marks</MONEY>. 
By late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, sterling was quoted at <MONEY>3.1063 marks</MONEY>. 
That was still up <PERCENT>0.2%</PERCENT> from 3.0987 <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, traders said the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION>, acting on behalf of the <ORGANIZATION>Reserve Bank of Australia</ORGANIZATION>, sold Australian dollars in the market to turn back the currency's advance. 
The Australian dollar stood at <MONEY>73.96 U.S. cents</MONEY> in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading yesterday, down from 74.18 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cents <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   The Canadian dollar, another currency offering high yields, continued to rally, climbing to <MONEY>80.43 U.S. cents</MONEY>, from <MONEY>80.25 U.S. cents</MONEY>. 

   Higher interest rates for deposits of these currencies make them more attractive to hold than other currencies, and increase the demand for them. 
The yields on three-month Eurocurrency deposits are <PERCENT>8.63%</PERCENT> for sterling, <PERCENT>10.31%</PERCENT> for Australian dollars, and <PERCENT>8.5%</PERCENT> for Canadian dollars. 
These rates stand in sharp contrast to yields for similar deposits of <PERCENT>6.84%</PERCENT> for dollars and <PERCENT>3.38%</PERCENT> for marks. 

   "There's a great deal of demand for these currencies and that (upward) pressure will probably continue," said <PERSON>Albert Soria</PERSON>, vice president and foreign exchange manager at <ORGANIZATION>Swiss Bank Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   In other trading, the dollar eased slightly to <MONEY>1.6905 marks</MONEY>, from 1.6919, and to <MONEY>126.75 yen</MONEY>, from 127.05. 

   In <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, the dollar opened <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at 126.75, below its quote of <MONEY>127.15 yen</MONEY> at the end of <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> session. 

The estimated volume was six million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$451.80</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                     LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 23, 1988</DATE>
    Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                          <ORGANIZATION>New York    Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.    <LOCATION>New York
                            Wed</LOCATION>.        Wed.         Tue.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.8375      1.8355       1.8315
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.8043      0.8025       0.8025
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 5.7435      5.7555       5.7490
    Japanese yen ....... 126.75      127.13       127.05
    Swiss franc .......... 1.3985      1.4000       1.3990
    West German mark ..... 1.6905      1.6945       1.6919
    Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
        Wed</ORGANIZATION>.          Wed.            Wed.          Tue.
       451.10        449.50          450.00        448.70 -
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880316-0047 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Sterling Gains Erased by Talk Of Intervention --- Profit-Taking Also Stalls Rally Linked to Budget; Dollar Posts Increases </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP CANDA FREST JAPAN </CO>
<IN> MON PCS CMD FRX </IN>
<TEXT>
   Profit-taking and rumored central bank intervention reversed a brief but sharp rally in sterling yesterday immediately after the British government released its budget proposal. 

   The pound began soaring around midday <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> time as British Chancellor of the Exchequer <PERSON>Nigel Lawson</PERSON> presented the <LOCATION>U.K.</LOCATION> government's proposed budget for the fiscal year beginning in <DATE>April</DATE>. 
As <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> concluded his remarks, the pound was already under selling pressure from traders taking profits on the currency's quick runup. 

   "It wasn't exactly a quiet day," said <PERSON>John I. Shupe</PERSON>, the sterling trader at <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank of Canada</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading the pound stood at <MONEY>$1.8455</MONEY>, off <PERCENT>0.3%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$1.8515</MONEY> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
But the day's overall movement in exchange rates masked a hectic trading period during <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>'s budget speech in which the pound soared <PERCENT>0.5%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$1.86</MONEY>, from <MONEY>$1.8505</MONEY> during the first 30 minutes of the chancellor's remarks. 

   Many <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> banks stopped quoting prices for sterling while they watched the speech on television, and many other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> banks withdrew from the market to await news service stories on the budget plan, which channeled most trading through the broker market. 

   Against the mark, the pound climbed to an intraday high of <MONEY>3.0930 marks</MONEY>, from 3.0827 <DATE>Monday</DATE>, before falling back to 3.0838 late in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   A bullish British budget for fiscal <DATE>1989</DATE> was generally expected by market participants, who had been bidding sterling higher over most of the past two weeks partly in anticipation of the news. 
The actual budget proposal, however, was interpreted by many traders as being more positive for sterling than earlier speculation. 

   <PERSON>Michael D. Andrews</PERSON>, vice president and foreign exchange economist at <ORGANIZATION>Irving Trust Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said the projection of a larger-than-expected budget surplus "is an indication of the economy's overall health." 
He added that the absence of government borrowings will increase the demand and prices for existing British government bonds, or gilts, attracting foreigners seeking capital gains potential. 
"Foreigners will have to buy sterling to buy gilts," <PERSON>Mr. Andrews</PERSON> said, explaining the bullish impact on the pound. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>'s forecast of a government surplus of <MONEY>#3 billion</MONEY> (<MONEY>$5.54 billion</MONEY>) for fiscal <DATE>1989</DATE> exceeded market expectations of a <MONEY>#2 billion</MONEY> surplus. 

   Sterling's slide yesterday came almost as quickly as its rise. 
"What we saw was profit-taking. 
People had some very nice profits in the cross positions," said <PERSON>Cynthia H. Johnson</PERSON>, vice president and corporate foreign exchange manager at <ORGANIZATION>Lloyds Bank PLC</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, referring to trades between sterling and marks. 

   The wave of selling also prompted rumors that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> intervened in the market to stem sterling's rise. 
A spokesman at the British central bank declined to comment on the rumors. 
The lack of confirmation of intervention did little to discourage selling on the fear that the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> was blocking further appreciation of sterling. 
"I'd rather trade off of rumors than facts. 
By the time it's confirmed it doesn't matter anymore," said <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mr. Shupe</PERSON>. 

The <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>'s intervention against the pound tends to be inflationary because by selling sterling in the foreign exchange market, it increases the money supply. 
Despite the policy announcement, many traders are wary of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION> attempting to thwart the pound's rise if the currency nears <MONEY>3.10 marks</MONEY>. 

   In other dealings, the dollar firmed against the major currencies. 
Traders attributed the rise to position-squaring ahead of tomorrow's report on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> merchandise trade. 
The dollar climbed yesterday to <MONEY>1.6710 marks</MONEY>, from 1.6650, and to <MONEY>127.45 yen</MONEY>, from 126.90. 

   The dollar opened <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> at <MONEY>127.38 yen</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>127.25 yen</MONEY> in closing trading <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

The estimated volume was 3.2 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$446.20</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                    LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 15, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                           <ORGANIZATION>New York   Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.   <ORGANIZATION>New York
                             Tue</ORGANIZATION>.        Tue.       Mon.
                       (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ......... 1.8455      1.8555     1.8515
    Canadian dollar ....... 0.7974      0.7976     0.7954
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc .......... 5.6770      5.65525    5.6560
    Japanese yen ........ 127.45      127.23     126.90
    Swiss franc ........... 1.3810      1.3745     1.3735
    West German mark ...... 1.6710      1.6649     1.6650
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
                (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
          <ORGANIZATION>Comex     London PM     London AM     Comex
           Tue</ORGANIZATION>.        Tue.          Tue.        Mon.
          446.30      442.20        442.15      441.90
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870218-0012 </DOCNO>
<HL> U.S. Currency Mixed as Traders Await
Economic Data, Testimony by Officials
---
By Charles W.                                                 
<DD> 02/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP JAPAN CANDA FREST
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The dollar was mixed against most major currencies in light trading yesterday as dealers awaited the latest word on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economy and monetary policy, scheduled for tomorrow. 

   Treasury Secretary <PERSON>James Baker</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Federal Reserve Board</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Paul Volcker</PERSON> are scheduled to testify before separate <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> panels tomorrow, and comments by either official could move currency rates, traders said. 
"People want to see whether <PERSON>Volcker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> are dancing to the same tune," said <PERSON>Peter Rogers</PERSON>, vice president and chief foreign-exchange dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Banca Nazionale Dell</ORGANIZATION>'Agricoltura, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON> recently has maintained that "the market" should determine proper exchange rates between major world currencies. 
Previously, <PERSON>Mr. Baker</PERSON> led the effort to weaken the dollar to increase the competitiveness of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> goods in international markets, and many speculators believe he still seeks a lower dollar. 
<PERSON>Mr. Volcker</PERSON>, meanwhile, frequently has voiced concern about a sharp decline in the dollar and its potential inflationary impact as imports become more expensive for Americans to buy. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> is scheduled to release tomorrow revised gross national product figures for the <DATE>final quarter of 1986</DATE>. 
Traders and analysts generally are looking for a modest upward revision of the <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT> growth rate originally reported. 
"A slight upward revision will have no effect, but a large downward revision would be detrimental for the dollar," <PERSON>Mr. Rogers</PERSON> said. 

<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading was idle <DATE>Monday</DATE> for the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s birthday holiday. 
The dollar also eased yesterday to 153.40 Japanese yen, from 153.55, but firmed to 1.5368 Swiss francs, from 1.5355. 
The British pound climbed to <MONEY>$1.5290</MONEY>, from <MONEY>$1.5213</MONEY>. 

   In early trading in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the dollar rose against the Japanese currency to <MONEY>153.43 yen</MONEY> from 153.40 in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> <TIME>yesterday afternoon</TIME>. 

The estimated volume was 3.8 million ounces. 

   Gold was quoted at <MONEY>$393.15</MONEY> an ounce in early trading <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. 

   ---

                       CURRENCY RATES
                          <LOCATION>New York    Home Mkt</LOCATION>.    <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
                            Tues.       Tues.       Mon.
                      (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
    British pound ........ 1.5290      1.5310       1.5213
    Canadian dollar ...... 0.7521      0.7522       0.7483
               (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
    French franc ......... 6.0703      6.0345       6.0645
    Japanese yen ....... 153.40      153.43       153.55
    Swiss franc .......... 1.5368      1.5315       1.5355
    West German mark ..... 1.8178      1.8118       1.8210
   Based on average of late buying and selling rates.
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
   Note: The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> market was closed <DATE>Monday</DATE> for the
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s birthday holiday.
                         GOLD PRICES
             (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
       <ORGANIZATION>Comex       London PM       London AM       Comex
       Tues</ORGANIZATION>.          Tues.          Tues.          Mon.
      392.10         397.25          396.85          z
   Comex based on settlement price for gold delivery in the
nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of
five major dealers.
   z-Holiday.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880331-0003 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets: Pound Surges, Despite Fed's Move to Curb It --- Britain, Clarifying Policy, Says Rein on Currency Is Looser; Dollar Falls </HL>
<AUTHOR> Charles W. Stevens and Peter Torday (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP JAPAN FREST CANDA </CO>
<IN> MON FRX PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   The British pound continued its surge in foreign-exchange trading yesterday but ran into resistance from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Federal Reserve</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The dollar, meanwhile, fell in moderately active <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading despite the <ORGANIZATION>Fed</ORGANIZATION>'s attempts to prop it up and limit the pound's gains. 

   According to dealers at several <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> banks, the <ORGANIZATION>Fed</ORGANIZATION> sold <MONEY>#70 million</MONEY> (<MONEY>$131.8 million</MONEY>) of the British currency in afternoon trading after sterling climbed to its intraday highs of <MONEY>$1.8825</MONEY> and 3.1250 West German marks. 
The intervention against the pound was probably done on behalf of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>, which was concerned with the market's new rush to the British currency, traders said. 

   In late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading, the pound stood at <MONEY>$1.8755</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>0.5%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$1.8660</MONEY> late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
Over the past two weeks, the pound has gained <PERCENT>2.8%</PERCENT> against the dollar after an announced shift in British monetary policy made the fight against inflation the top priority. 

   The pound's latest gains followed remarks made in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s top financial official. 

   Speaking to a parliamentary panel, Chancellor of the Exchequer <PERSON>Nigel Lawson</PERSON> confirmed that <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had abandoned tight management of the pound's value and indicated that the currency might be allowed to rise further. 
His comments appeared to end a period of confusion over British exchange-rate policy that had disturbed the currency markets. 

   The pound soared after <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>'s remarks. 
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had been striving for about a year to keep the currency below 3.00 West German marks to try to keep British exports competitive in European markets. 
It stopped defending that level early this month, but <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s new stance hadn't been clear to foreign-exchange traders before yesterday. 

   The pound closed yesterday in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> at <MONEY>3.1227 marks</MONEY>, compared with <MONEY>3.1077 marks</MONEY> a day earlier. 

   The new British strategy apparently means British interest rates will remain relatively high. 
That is attracting a huge flow of capital into sterling as investors seek higher yields than are available in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON>, whose job is analogous to that of <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> secretary in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, said sterling's stabilization over the past year ended a six-year decline in the currency that had threatened to undermine <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s fight against inflation. 
The pound's value averaged <MONEY>2.94 marks</MONEY> last year, compared with <MONEY>4.56 marks</MONEY> in <DATE>1981</DATE>. 

   Today's stable to slightly firmer pound helps British exporters keep their prices steady and indirectly holds down costs throughout the entire domestic economy, <PERSON>Mr. Lawson</PERSON> said. 

   He suggested that sterling might be allowed to rise still further, saying, "It may be that we become so successful that we can have a gradually appreciating exchange rate." 

   Traders in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> said yesterday's <ORGANIZATION>Fed</ORGANIZATION> intervention didn't seem aimed at stopping the pound's rise completely. 

   "It's just slowing down any movements, keeping the rise in an orderly fashion and from getting out of hand," <PERSON>John I. Shupe</PERSON>, the sterling dealer at <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank of Canada</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said. 

   Meanwhile, despite the reported <ORGANIZATION>Fed</ORGANIZATION> activity, the dollar stood in late <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> trading yesterday at <MONEY>1.6635 marks</MONEY>, down from <MONEY>1.6690 marks</MONEY> late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, and at 125.10 Japanese yen, off from 125.25 late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   In midmorning <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> trading <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the dollar was quoted at <MONEY>125.25 yen</MONEY>. 

   One dealer at a major bank said the dollar eased in part because of a large order to buy currency futures placed on <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>International Monetary Market</ORGANIZATION> by a major Chicago-based commodities house. 

Estimated volume was 7.5 million ounces. 

   ---

                   LATE <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> TRADING
                 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>March 30, 1988</DATE>
   Based on average of late afternoon buying and selling rates.
                         <ORGANIZATION>New York   Home Mkt</ORGANIZATION>.   <LOCATION>New York
                            Wed</LOCATION>.       Wed.       Tue.
                     (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars)
 British pound ........... 1.8755     1.8700     1.8660
 Canadian dollar ......... 0.8088     0.8088     0.8045 -
             (In foreign units to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar)
 French franc ............ 5.6390     5.6565     5.6555
 Japanese yen .......... 125.10     125.39     125.25
 Swiss franc ............. 1.3725     1.3780     1.3787
 West German mark ........ 1.6635     1.6689     1.6690
   Home markets: <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>.
                          GOLD PRICES
               (In <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars per troy ounce)
         <ORGANIZATION>Comex      London PM     London AM     Comex
          Wed</ORGANIZATION>.         Wed.         Wed.         Tue.
         457.80       453.75       454.00       455.40
   Comex based on settlement price for gold for delivery in the nearest month on <ORGANIZATION>Commodity Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> based on morning and afternoon price fixings of five major dealers.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870318-0071 </DOCNO>
<HL> Currency Markets:
Pound Surges
In Endorsement
Of U.K. Budget
---
Advance Exceeds 1% Despite
Decline in Interest Rates;
Dollar Is Narrowly Mixed
---
By Charles W. Stevens
<DD> 03/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> EUROP JAPAN CANDA FREST
MONETARY NEWS, FOREIGN EXCHANGE, TRADE (MON)
FOREIGN-EXCHANGE MARKETS (FRX)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The British pound surged more than <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> against major currencies in response to the British government's new budget. 

   Sterling's advance was especially significant, traders said, because it coincided with a drop in British interest rates following yesterday's formal proposal of the fiscal <DATE>1988</DATE> budget. 
Lower interest rates tend to reduce demand for the currency. 
