<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900227-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-90 0901EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ZebraMussels     02-27 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zebra Mussels,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shellfish Expected To Reach Rivers</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PITTSBURGH (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A striped shellfish now clogging water system
pipelines and threatening the ecological balance of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION>
could make its way to rivers around the country in as little as
five years, scientists say.
   The rapidly producing zebra mussels could pose a significant
problem for manufacturing plants, many of which have miles of pipes
that draw cooling water, the experts warn.
   The mussels eventually will attach themselves to the insides of
pipes supplying factories and municipal water plants, in some cases
restricting flow, in the <LOCATION>Allegheny</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and Monongahela rivers,
said <PERSON>Thomas Nalepa</PERSON>, a biologist with the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> basin also is vulnerable because <LOCATION>Lake
Michigan</LOCATION>, where the mussels are expected to arrive soon, is
connected to the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Canal</ORGANIZATION>.
   However, there is no reliable way to determine exactly when the
1{-inch mollusk will arrive in these or other rivers around the
country, scientists said.
   Zebra mussels, so named because of their brown and white zigzag
stripes, have been found in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lake Ontario</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lake St.
Clair</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>.
   They are growing on spawning reefs favored by walleye,
smallmouth bass and other fish in western <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, raising
concern about the future of a valuable fishery.
   Like barnacles, zebra mussels can travel by clinging to boat
hulls. They can survive out of water for perhaps up to 14 days by
living on internal moisture.
   ``Let's say someone from <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> were to trailer their boat
up to fish on <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> and ended up with zebra mussels that
attached to their hull,'' said <PERSON>David Kelch</PERSON>, a specialist with <ORGANIZATION>Ohio
State University</ORGANIZATION>'s sea grant program.
   ``They take their boat back to <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> and in a day or two
put the boat into a river or lake in that area. You've got them.''
   What's more, the larvae, or young, which are microscopic in
size, easily can attach themselves to an angler's minnow bucket, a
water nook in a boat trailer or the feathers of a duck.
   The zebra mussel originated in the Black and Caspian seas
between <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. In 200 years, it has spread through much
of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Two years ago, it was discovered in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> and
has infested water intakes for <ORGANIZATION>Erie</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
   The mussel reproduces at an astonishing rate. A single female
produces as many as 40,000 eggs each breeding season.
   The mollusk also has a voracious appetite for phytoplankton,
which are microscopic floating plants that form the bottom of the
food chain. Mussels could reduce the supply of phytoplankton for
microscopic animals called zooplankton. The zooplankton, in turn,
are eaten by smaller fish, which are eaten for food by larger fish.
   ``Anytime you impact the basic bottom building block of the food
chain, you're going to see an impact on the top predators _
walleye, smallmouth bass, yellow perch,'' <PERSON>Kelch</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--ZebraMussels ADV28-2Takes   10-15 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Zebra Mussels, ADV 28-2 Takes,0906</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv28</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Oct. 28</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w
photos, 1 graphic. ColorFoto subscribers get 2 35mm slides.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - They are alien creatures of the deep, unknown in
the waters of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> until a few years ago. They can cut
off the water supply of cities, ruin boat engines, and scientists
worry that they will upset the aquatic food chain. The invasion of
the zebra mussels, which began in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>, is expected to
spread to waterways across the land.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - They are alien creatures of the deep, unknown in
the waters of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> until a few years ago. They can cut
off the water supply of cities, ruin boat engines, and scientists
worry that they will upset the aquatic food chain. The invasion of
the zebra mussels, which began in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>, is expected to
spread to waterways across the land.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By GEOFFREY HAYNES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MONROE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - They are alien creatures of the deep, unknown in
the waters of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> until a few years ago. They can cut
off the water supply of cities, ruin boat engines, and scientists
worry that they will upset the aquatic food chain. The invasion of
the zebra mussels, which began in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>, is expected to
spread to waterways across the land.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - They are alien creatures of the deep, unknown in
the waters of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> until a few years ago. They can cut
off the water supply of cities, ruin boat engines, and scientists
worry that they will upset the aquatic food chain. The invasion of
the zebra mussels, which began in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>, is expected to
spread to waterways across the land.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901015-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-15-90 1425EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--ZebraMussles ADV28-1stAdd   10-15 0657</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Zebra Mussles, ADV 28-1st Add,0839</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv28</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release Sun., Oct. 28</NOTE>
<HEAD>MONROE, Mich.: St. Louis.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> has the greatest infestation, but scientists hold out
hope that the other Great Lakes will experience only small
invasions because they don't have the rocky bottom structure <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION> has.
   The zebra mussel is so dangerous because it can reproduce so
quickly. A fully mature female can produce more than 30,000 eggs
per season. The eggs are fertilized outside the shell and hatch
into free-swimming larvae called veligers.
   The veligers can remain suspended in the water for one to three
weeks, allowing currents to scatter them. If they don't settle on
firm objects in that time period, they die. Those that find a hard
surface attach to it with extremely strong tentacle-like threads.
The zebra mussel is mature at one year and can live to about 4
years old and grow to about 1{ inches long.
   ``The older they get, the tougher they are to remove,'' says
<PERSON>Gerry Mackie</PERSON>, a researcher at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Guelph</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>.
``Nothing or very few things can pry it off the rock. That makes it
tough for predators.''
   And the zebra mussel has few natural predators outside of the
diving duck and sheepshead fish.
   The zebra mussel has flourished in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, where it filters
plankton from the water. An adult can filter about a quart of water
per day, and that's what concerns scientists about the impact on
the food chain.
   ``The current situation is the plankton is out in the open
water,'' <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> says. ``With the zebra mussel, which settles on the
bottom, they will be removing particles from the open water. More
of this food is going to be channeled to the bottom. Getting this
food to a salmon is going to be less efficient.''
   Researchers say it's too early to tell how the zeb mussel will
affect sport fishing. They say there could be an increase in mussel
predators such as the bottom-feeding sheepshead, but it's unknown
how they will affect more sought-after fish in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>,
such as walleye and lake trout.
   <PERSON>Mackie</PERSON> says, however, there are some positive aspects to the
zebra mussel invasion. The zebra mussel's filtering ability is
making <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> clearer.
   ``I've never seen <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> look so nice as it has,'' <PERSON>LePage</PERSON>
says. ``I've seen the bottom of the lake in places that I've never
seen before.''
   In the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, researchers put the zebra
mussel's filtering ability to use in clarifying lakes. They also
use it as a biological monitor to detect what chemicals are in the
water.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, a new industry has sprouted
around the zebra mussel. <ORGANIZATION>Dow Chemical Company</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>,
and many others are developing anti-fouling boat coatings to keep
zebra mussels from attaching. The <ORGANIZATION>King Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, has
developed a bullet-shaped squeegee to scrape and remove zebra
mussels from water intake pipes.
   Researchers from around the country are watching <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to see
whether it appropriates <MONEY>$37.5 million</MONEY> for research and control of
the zebra mussel. Others are refining methods to control the pest.
Most of those solutions are based on chlorine, which is fatal to
the zebra mussel. It's been used for the past 200 years in the
mollusk's native <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   In <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, a chlorine spray jet has been installed at the mouth
of the water intake to treat the water as it enters the pipe.
   ``So far we are keeping them down,'' <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> says. ``Our intake
is as clean as a whistle.''
   <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON> used the <ORGANIZATION>King Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s squeegee to clean its intake pipe
after last year's invasion. The high-tech RotoRooter removed enough
mussels to fill six dump trucks. It cost the city <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to get
the system back to pre-mussel operating levels.
   The water plant sends divers down regularly to inspect the
intake for zebra mussel buildup. The city also is building a second
water intake designed to prevent another zebra mussel takeover. The
modifications will cost the city an extra <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> says.
   To control the zebra mussel, Great Lakes researchers are trying
to learn all they can about the mussel's habits - its reproduction,
its predators and parasites, and its favorite nesting spots.
   At a recent meeting of zebra mussel experts from around the
world in <LOCATION>Saginaw</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, some said the best approach may be to find
ways to control and even anticipate all introduced species, not
just the zebra mussel. Other species recently introduced in the
Great Lakes are upsetting the food chain. They include the spiny
water flea and the ruffe, a fish limited mainly to the <LOCATION>Duluth</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, area.
   The scientists proposed forming a center for the study of
introduced species, possibly to be established at a university in
the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>.
   ``It's going to take years of research before we get a
definitive answer,'' <PERSON>Mackie</PERSON> says.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> has the greatest infestation, but scientists hold out
hope that the other Great Lakes will experience only small
invasions because they don't have the rocky bottom structure <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION> has.
   The zebra mussel is so dangerous because it can reproduce so
quickly. A fully mature female can produce more than 30,000 eggs
per season. The eggs are fertilized outside the shell and hatch
into free-swimming larvae called veligers.
   The veligers can remain suspended in the water for one to three
weeks, allowing currents to scatter them. If they don't settle on
firm objects in that time period, they die. Those that find a hard
surface attach to it with extremely strong tentacle-like threads.
The zebra mussel is mature at one year and can live to about 4
years old and grow to about 1{ inches long.
   ``The older they get, the tougher they are to remove,'' says
<PERSON>Gerry Mackie</PERSON>, a researcher at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Guelph</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>.
``Nothing or very few things can pry it off the rock. That makes it
tough for predators.''
   And the zebra mussel has few natural predators outside of the
diving duck and sheepshead fish.
   The zebra mussel has flourished in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, where it filters
plankton from the water. An adult can filter about a quart of water
per day, and that's what concerns scientists about the impact on
the food chain.
   ``The current situation is the plankton is out in the open
water,'' <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> says. ``With the zebra mussel, which settles on the
bottom, they will be removing particles from the open water. More
of this food is going to be channeled to the bottom. Getting this
food to a salmon is going to be less efficient.''
   Researchers say it's too early to tell how the zeb mussel will
affect sport fishing. They say there could be an increase in mussel
predators such as the bottom-feeding sheepshead, but it's unknown
how they will affect more sought-after fish in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>,
such as walleye and lake trout.
   <PERSON>Mackie</PERSON> says, however, there are some positive aspects to the
zebra mussel invasion. The zebra mussel's filtering ability is
making <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> clearer.
   ``I've never seen <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> look so nice as it has,'' <PERSON>LePage</PERSON>
says. ``I've seen the bottom of the lake in places that I've never
seen before.''
   In the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, researchers put the zebra
mussel's filtering ability to use in clarifying lakes. They also
use it as a biological monitor to detect what chemicals are in the
water.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, a new industry has sprouted
around the zebra mussel. <ORGANIZATION>Dow Chemical Company</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>,
and many others are developing anti-fouling boat coatings to keep
zebra mussels from attaching. The <ORGANIZATION>King Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Holland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, has
developed a bullet-shaped squeegee to scrape and remove zebra
mussels from water intake pipes.
   Researchers from around the country are watching <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to see
whether it appropriates <MONEY>$37.5 million</MONEY> for research and control of
the zebra mussel. Others are refining methods to control the pest.
Most of those solutions are based on chlorine, which is fatal to
the zebra mussel. It's been used for the past 200 years in the
mollusk's native <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   In <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, a chlorine spray jet has been installed at the mouth
of the water intake to treat the water as it enters the pipe.
   ``So far we are keeping them down,'' <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> says. ``Our intake
is as clean as a whistle.''
   <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON> used the <ORGANIZATION>King Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s squeegee to clean its intake pipe
after last year's invasion. The high-tech RotoRooter removed enough
mussels to fill six dump trucks. It cost the city <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to get
the system back to pre-mussel operating levels.
   The water plant sends divers down regularly to inspect the
intake for zebra mussel buildup. The city also is building a second
water intake designed to prevent another zebra mussel takeover. The
modifications will cost the city an extra <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> says.
   To control the zebra mussel, Great Lakes researchers are trying
to learn all they can about the mussel's habits - its reproduction,
its predators and parasites, and its favorite nesting spots.
   At a recent meeting of zebra mussel experts from around the
world in <LOCATION>Saginaw</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, some said the best approach may be to find
ways to control and even anticipate all introduced species, not
just the zebra mussel. Other species recently introduced in the
Great Lakes are upsetting the food chain. They include the spiny
water flea and the ruffe, a fish limited mainly to the <LOCATION>Duluth</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, area.
   The scientists proposed forming a center for the study of
introduced species, possibly to be established at a university in
the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>.
   ``It's going to take years of research before we get a
definitive answer,'' <PERSON>Mackie</PERSON> says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030890-0164 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 186572 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 8, 1990, Thursday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 16; Column 2; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
328 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BILL OFFERED TO CURB TINY MUSSEL THREATENING GREAT LAKES, RIVERS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION> states <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> introduced legislation to 
curb or eradicate the zebra mussel, a tiny shellfish that has infested <LOCATION>Lake 
Erie</LOCATION> and threatens to cause damage in other lakes and rivers. 
</P>
<P>
"The experts seem to think that this can spread very rapidly, just as it has in 
<LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Sen. John Glenn</PERSON> (D-Ohio), a co-sponsor of the measure, which 
would authorize spending <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> a year for five years for prevention 
programs and the same amount on eradication. 
</P>
<P>
The legislation would require freighters to dump their ballast water in the 
ocean at least 200 miles from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> coast. 
</P>
<P>
The striped zebra mussel, usually no more than 1 1/2 inches long, is believed 
to have arrived in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, when a freighter from eastern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> 
flushed its ballast water into <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> or in the <LOCATION>St. Clair River</LOCATION> near 
<LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>. The mussels have since spread down the length of the <LOCATION>Detroit River</LOCATION> and 
into <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, moving at about 160 miles a year. 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>Carl Levin</PERSON> (D-Mich.) said that the mussels forced <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, to ration 
water for several days because they had clogged drinking water intake pipes. 
</P>
<P>
"Over 50 other major municipal intake pipes in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, not to mention 
industry users, are at risk from this same type of fouling," <PERSON>Levin</PERSON> said. "They 
threaten the Great Lakes' <MONEY>$4-billion</MONEY> sports fish industry by robbing the fish 
and other aquatic species of essential food sources such as algae and 
plankton." 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>John Heinz</PERSON> (R-Pa.) warned that the inedible shellfish can easily migrate 
into the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> river systems, which "could become 
literally mussel-bound." 
</P>
<P>
A female zebra mussel lays up to 40,000 microscopic eggs in a year. 
</P>
<P>
An expert who investigated the problem for the <ORGANIZATION>Congressional Research Service</ORGANIZATION> 
found evidence that diving ducks and crawfish eat zebra mussels, but he warned 
that there may not be enough intact wetlands to provide habitat for more of the 
natural predators. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900613-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-90 2234EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r u AM-ZebraMussels     06-13 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zebra Mussels,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Believe Mussels Clean Polluted Water, Official Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN FLESHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Could it be that the hated zebra mussel isn't
all bad?
   Soviet scientists apparently think so, says an <ORGANIZATION>Environmental
Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> official who is planning to visit <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> next
month in search of ideas for battling the tiny mollusks.
   Officials are frantically searching for a way to prevent
infestation of the Great Lakes by the pesky mussels, with their
zebra-like stripes.
   <PERSON>Valdas V. Adamkus</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION>'s national program manager for the
<ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> he had received some papers from Soviet
scientists who earlier notified him they had developed a biological
method of attacking the pest.
   Zebra mussels breed rapidly and attach themselves to municipal
water intake pipes.
   Much to his surprise, however, the papers said nothing about
ways to eradicate the mussel, <PERSON>Adamkus</PERSON> said. Instead, they described
the creature as useful because it can help control water pollution.
   ``They proved through their scientific work that zebra mussels
can be a cleansing agent,'' he said. ``So instead of trying to
reduce them, they are actually trying to ... increase their
population.
   ``We were surprised,'' he said. ``We're trying to eliminate the
zebra mussels and they are actually using them as an agent for
purification of water.''
   How the mussels could clean dirty water isn't clear, <PERSON>Adamkus</PERSON>
said. But the report has made him all the more eager to visit the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   ``I'm going to call on all the available scientists over there,
meet with them, get any information or whatever scientific work or
literature is available,'' he said.
   Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, the mussels clogged the water intake pipe of
<LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, restricting the flow through the 6,000-foot pipe by
nearly <PERCENT>24 percent</PERCENT>.
   Zebra mussels originated in <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION>'s freshwater seas and
are believed to have entered the Great Lakes in the ballast water
of oceangoing vessels.
   They showed up in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE> and rapidly infested
<LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>. They have been spotted from <LOCATION>Duluth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
voted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to spend <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for zebra mussel research at
the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes Research Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> at <PERSON>Ann Arbor</PERSON>.
   Another <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> for zebra mussel study was reserved, pending
completion of legislation to authorize the Sea Grant program, said
Rep. <PERSON>Bob Carr</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mich.</LOCATION>, a committee member.
   The panel also set aside <MONEY>$1.4 million</MONEY> to combat the sea lamprey,
another Great Lakes pest.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900308-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-90 0320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MusselMenace     03-08 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mussel Menace,640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Marauding Mollusks Threaten to Turn Great Lakes Into Mussel
Beaches</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHERINE RIZZO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Small, striped aliens that stowed away on
European freighters are threatening the security of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s
waterways, warn lawmakers who fear the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION> will become
mussel beaches.
   The rapid spread of the marauding mollusks led legislators
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to introduce bills aimed at preventing further aquatic
invasions and battling the one underway by the dread zebra mussel.
   Unchecked, the exotic, inedible shellfish could cause <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY>
in damage by the turn of the century and spread to two-thirds of
the nation's waterways, said <PERSON>Sen. John Glenn</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>.
   ``I can tell you it's no joke,'' said <PERSON>Glenn</PERSON>, who was joined at a
news conference by seven lawmakers who want the federal government
to spend <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> to research and control the barnacle-like
creature.
   ``We don't want to look a few years from now on what we should
have spent this year,'' said Rep. <PERSON>Fred Upton</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Mich.</LOCATION>, whose
district is bound by <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>. That lake so far is mussel-free
except for the bottom of one boat in <LOCATION>Green Bay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis</LOCATION>.
   The mussels, usually no more than 1{ inches long, are believed
to have been carried here from <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> three years ago in
the ballast water of freighters.
   They've multiplied dramatically because they spawn almost
continuously _ an adult female can produce upwards of 30,000 eggs
in a year _ and because there has been nothing to control the
spread of the alien mussels.
   An expert who investigated the problem for the <ORGANIZATION>Congressional
Research Service</ORGANIZATION> found evidence that diving ducks and crawfish eat
zebra mussels but warned that there may not be enough intact
wetlands to provide a habitat for more of the natural predators.
   There weren't enough predators to prevent 30 tons of mussels
from clogging a 2{-mile intake pipe at an <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> water plant or
prevent mussels from accumulating up to two inches thick on screens
of the water intakes at five <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Electric Illumination Co.</ORGANIZATION>
power plants.
   <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, was forced to close its water plant for three
days after zebra mussels restricted water flow. <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Edison Co.</ORGANIZATION>
had to reduce the output of its <LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION> plant by <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT>
because one of its pipes became coated with the mussels.
   <PERSON>Sen. Arlen Specter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>, said a <MONEY>$29 million</MONEY> breakwall that
took a decade to get for <LOCATION>Presque Isle</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> is being
jeopardized by zebra mussels.
   And <PERSON>Sen. John Heinz</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>, warned that the shellfish can easily
migrate into the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> river systems,
which ``could become literally mussel-bound.''
   And there's more. Dead zebra mussels can produce ``offensive
quantities of methane gas,'' according to the congressional
research report. When they die in the pipes of water treatment
systems they can give the water a foul taste and smell. Once they
wash ashore, the mussels' sharp shells can rip up the bare feet of
beach walkers.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dennis Eckart</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ohio</LOCATION>, said the mussels already endanger
the fisheries of <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> by stripping the lake of microscopic
feeder plants.
   When the bottom of the aquatic food chain collapses, ``the net
result is there will be no little baby fish left in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> to
grow up to be big fish,'' said <PERSON>Eckart</PERSON>, who added he's worried about
the impact on a newly revived sportfishing and recreation economy.
   ``It's another one of those unwanted foreign imports that's
costing us jobs,'' he said.
   The bills introduced by <PERSON>Glenn</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and Rep. <PERSON>Henry
Nowak</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> would authorize spending <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> a
year for five years to control the mussels and the same amount on
prevention programs to protect <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> waters from other foreign
invaders.
   In addition, the bills require freighters to dump their ballast
water in the ocean, at least 200 miles from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> coast.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ZebraMussels     11-29 0262</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Zebra Mussels,0310</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report: Pesky Zebra Mussels Found in Hudson</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The zebra mussel, a fast-breeding type of
shellfish that clogs the intake pipes of power plants, has been
found in the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> for the first time, scientists said.
   The mussels, which had not been seen east of the central section
of the <ORGANIZATION>Erie Canal</ORGANIZATION>, were found off <LOCATION>Croton Point</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Westchester
County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s northern suburbs. It was identified
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by experts at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zebra Mussel Information
Clearinghouse</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>State University of New York</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Brockport</LOCATION>.
   ``It is the first confirmed North American sighting of the
mussel outside of the Great Lakes drainage basin,'' <PERSON>Charles O'Neill
Jr.</PERSON>, a supervisor at the clearinghouse, told <ORGANIZATION>The New York Times</ORGANIZATION> in
a story published today.
   O'Neill noted that the zebra mussel, classified as a freshwater
animal, is not usually found in saltwater like the lower Hudson.
   ``It raises a lot of questions that we don't have answers for,''
he said.
   The zebra mussel, a native of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, was first found in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE> in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION>, east of <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>.
   Named for its dark brown stripes on a tan shell, the mussel
breeds quickly and can clog the intake pipes of power plants and
eats microscopic plants at the base of the food chain for
freshwater fish.
   In areas where the mussels have taken hold, utilities have
fought back by flushing pipes with treated water, cleaning intake
screens by hand and using chlorine and other chemicals to kill
them.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> has estimated that the
expanding population of the mussels could add <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> a year
in added costs for utilities, water companies and factories and
loss of business in sports fishing, marinas and motels along inland
waterways.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900219-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-19-90 0030EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EXP--ZebraMussels     02-19 1041</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EXP--Zebra Mussels,1063</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tiny Molluscs Imperil Water Supplies, Power Plants, Fishing</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Wilfred LePage</PERSON> saw his first zebra mussel <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE>. By <DATE>September</DATE>,
thousands of the tiny molluscs jammed the intake of the water
treatment plant he manages, cutting the flow <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> and nearly
sparking a water emergency.
   ``There is no cheap solution to it and there's no real cure to
the problem,'' said <PERSON>LePage</PERSON>, water treatment superintendent in
<LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>'s western edge.
   At the eastern end of the lake, in <LOCATION>Dunkirk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, the
green-and-yellow striped shellfish first appeared <DATE>Oct. 3</DATE>, and now
infest a <ORGANIZATION>Niagara Mohawk Power Corp.</ORGANIZATION> generating plant. <DATE>December</DATE>'s
deep freeze stopped them from clogging water intakes but they
quickly settled inside the plant.
   ``They like it where it's dimly lit, they like it where it's
warm, and they don't like a lot of turbulence. This place is ideal
for them,'' said <PERSON>Robert C. Henderson</PERSON>, a chemical lab supervisor at
the plant. ``By <DATE>July</DATE>, we're going to have a massive problem with
them.''
   Three years after they were introduced to <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> and
after only one year in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, zebra mussels have spread
throughout the lake and have been spotted at the entrance to <LOCATION>Lake
Ontario</LOCATION> and along the <LOCATION>St. Lawrence River</LOCATION>. It's an invasion
scientists say could affect farming, fishing and daily life along
virtually every body of fresh water in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> in the next
few years.
   The mussels are mostly about a half-inch long, although they can
reach 2 inches during their five-year lifespans. They eat by
filtering microscopic food particles from the water, and love
intake pipes of water and power plants because the current brings
them a steady supply of fresh food.
   A mussel can filter more than a gallon of water an hour, said <PERSON>R.
Warren Flint</PERSON>, a scientist with the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes Program</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>State
University of New York-Buffalo</ORGANIZATION>. As a result, they will leave water
cleaner than before. ``From an aesthetic perspective, that would
certainly be a benefit, I guess,'' he said.
   Europeans have used zebra mussels to clean algae-choked ponds,
and the shells can be used to add calcium to livestock feed, said
<PERSON>Charles O'Neill</PERSON>, with the Sea Grant program at the <ORGANIZATION>State University
College</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Brockport</LOCATION>.
   The mussels also are a good source of food for diving ducks and
some kinds of fish, including sturgeons and eels, <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said. But
with millions of them at work filtering microscopic food, they
could deplete the supply for the small fish that support the
billion-dollar walleye- and bass-fishing industry.
   And the bad news could spread beyond the lake and its shoreline.
Farmers and golf courses that draw irrigation water from the lakes
can expect problems, and beachgoers will have to wear shoes because
of the shells, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said.
   ``It can affect everything from the electricity at your outlet
to the water at your tap,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``It's not just an
environmental problem.''
   Like their distant cousins, the blue mussels, zebras ought, in
theory, to be edible by humans, <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said. But when Canadian
researchers tried steaming a bunch, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said, ``What they got
was a stench that cleared the lab.''
   The mussels have plagued <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for more than a century and are
believed to have arrived in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> on a freighter that
emptied its ballast tanks in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION>, upstream from <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Scientists are studying the possibility that the <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>
infestations came from several ships rather than that single <DATE>1986</DATE>
event, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. But <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said one colony could have infested
the lake because one mussel can lay 30,000 to 50,000 eggs a year
and the larvae can swim for up to two weeks before growing shells.
``They could easily get across <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Lake Ontario</LOCATION> in that
period of time,'' he said.
   For public water systems, controlling the mussels is a matter of
applying chlorine, ozone or other disinfectants at the mouth of the
intake pipe rather than waiting until the water is inside the
plant, say scientists and plant operators like <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> who have
already faced the problem.
   Power plants have a different problem, because officials are
reluctant to let them put chlorine or other disinfectants in
cooling water discharged back to the lake, <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> said. Niagara
Mohawk and the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental Conservation</ORGANIZATION> are
negotiating a solution.
   <PERSON>James Sell</PERSON>, chief operator of the <LOCATION>Dunkirk</LOCATION> water plant, is
studying ways of getting chlorine to the pipe's mouth, like
building a platform over the intake or running a smaller chlorine
pipe out through the intake. ``We're better off than the people in
the western end of the lake,'' <PERSON>Sell</PERSON> said.
   ``At least we have some time to do something by <DATE>spring</DATE>.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> hasn't been persuaded to pay up to <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> for
the plans, but Sell, who keeps three living mussels in a jar to
show visitors, said, ``I don't see much option for them if they
want a water supply.''
   Farther inland, many water officials are unaware of the problem
or not prepared to do anything about it. <PERSON>Michael Burke</PERSON>, director of
the state <ORGANIZATION>Health Department</ORGANIZATION>'s bureau of public water supply
protection, said the department was studying the problem but
doesn't see the need to issue warnings. ``I think the word's
getting to them, particularly those with large surface intakes in
the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>. It is coming out in industry papers and things of
that sort.''
   O'Neill and other scientists said the state should do more to
get the word out, because it is only a matter of time _ and not
necessarily very much time.
   ``The chances of them getting into the western reach of the <ORGANIZATION>Erie
Canal</ORGANIZATION> is good,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``The canal is an ideal place for
them to live. It's warm. It's shallow. Most of it has rock riprap
to attach to.''
   Pleasure boats can also carry mussels and their larvae in their
engine housings and other places where water collects.
   Once the mussels get into <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>, they will almost
certainly spread through the <LOCATION>Chicago River</LOCATION> and into the <LOCATION>Mississippi
River</LOCATION> basin, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``Any area in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> that is
utilizing surface water should be concerned.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911206-0049
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911206-0049.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Pesky Zebra Mussel
   Spawns Creativity
   In Plastics Company
   ---
   Coltec Industries Unit Touts
   Chemically Treated Pipes;
   `Silver Bullets' Multiply
   ----
   By Robert J. Brennan
</HL>
<DATE>
12/06/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A9E
</SO>
<CO>
   COT
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
</MS>
<IN>
BUILDING MATERIALS, CONCRETE, GLASS, PAINT (BLD)
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
</IN>
<NS>
NEW PRODUCTS &amp; SERVICES (PDT)
</NS>
<RE>
MICHIGAN (MI)
NEW JERSEY (NJ)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
OHIO (OH)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- A subsidiary of Coltec Industries Inc. says it
has a better way to combat the zebra mussel, the
fast-breeding mollusk pest that is clogging up America's
water pipes.
   Garlick Valves &amp; Industrial Plastics, a Camden, N.J., unit
of New York-based Coltec, said it has produced a plastic pipe
material in which a mollusk-killing chemical is embedded. The
chemically treated pipe keeps the mussels out of their
favorite breeding places -- water intake pipes, valves and
debris gates -- where they create problems for water
authorities and power generation plants.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Utility officials pointed out that many companies have
been touting products and services with varying degrees of
effectiveness against the persistent pest.
   The zebra mussel, native to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, was discovered in the
<LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>; biologists believe they arrived in
the ballast of European freighters that moved in the lakes.
The mussel grows to about thumbnail-size, and breeds
profusely, up to concentrations of nearly a million per
square meter of surface. It causes havoc by clogging water
intake pipes of boats, factories, public water facilities and
irrigation systems. Various estimates of the cost of cleanup
and control of the zebra mussel over the next several years
run in the <MONEY>billions of dollars</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Adam Patarcity</PERSON>, operations manager for <ORGANIZATION>Garlick Valves</ORGANIZATION>,
said the product, called Z-Gard, is a version of its
ultra-high molecular weight polyethylene to which a
molluscicide is added. The current slick-surfaced
polyethylene hasn't prevented the zebra mussels from
attaching, but the new plastic has been very effective, after
tests at 11 sites in <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>, he said.
   The worst areas of infestation in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> are <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>,
particularly the southern shore around <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Lake
Huron</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> area. Removal of the mussels currently
must be done mechanically, by scraping or blasting with
high-pressure water, or by chemical treatment of the water.
<PERSON>Mr. Patarcity</PERSON> said that unlike previous efforts to control
the mussels, the chemical in its new pipe material won't
leach out into the water and threaten the environment.
   Z-Gard joins a growing list of ostensible mussel-stoppers,
and its potential market has a wait-and-see attitude. "Every
day we have people calling to offer a silver bullet" for the
problem, said <PERSON>William Kovalak</PERSON>, a biologist for <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Edison
Co.</ORGANIZATION> "So we take more of a passive stance. We let them come in
and put their product in the water, and if it works, we can
use it without having invested much." He said some
silicone-based chemical coatings for intake areas seem to
work well, adding that <ORGANIZATION>Detroit Edison</ORGANIZATION> facilities on lakes
Erie and Huron have some of the worst mussel concentrations
in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900215-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-90 1141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--ZebraMussels Adv19   02-15 1052</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Zebra Mussels, Adv 19,1077</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv19</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Feb. 19, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Tiny Molluscs Imperil Water Supplies, Power Plants, Fishing</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Wilfred LePage</PERSON> saw his first zebra mussel <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE>. By <DATE>September</DATE>,
thousands of the tiny molluscs jammed the intake of the water
treatment plant he manages, cutting the flow <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> and nearly
sparking a water emergency.
   ``There is no cheap solution to it and there's no real cure to
the problem,'' said <PERSON>LePage</PERSON>, water treatment superintendent in
<LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>'s western edge.
   At the eastern end of the lake, in <LOCATION>Dunkirk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, the
green-and-yellow striped shellfish first appeared <DATE>Oct. 3</DATE>, and now
infest a <ORGANIZATION>Niagara Mohawk Power Corp.</ORGANIZATION> generating plant. <DATE>December</DATE>'s
deep freeze stopped them from clogging water intakes but they
quickly settled inside the plant.
   ``They like it where it's dimly lit, they like it where it's
warm, and they don't like a lot of turbulence. This place is ideal
for them,'' said <PERSON>Robert C. Henderson</PERSON>, a chemical lab supervisor at
the plant. ``By <DATE>July</DATE>, we're going to have a massive problem with
them.''
   Three years after they were introduced to <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> and
after only one year in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, zebra mussels have spread
throughout the lake and have been spotted at the entrance to <LOCATION>Lake
Ontario</LOCATION> and along the <LOCATION>St. Lawrence River</LOCATION>. It's an invasion
scientists say could affect farming, fishing and daily life along
virtually every body of fresh water in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> in the next
few years.
   The mussels are mostly about a half-inch long, although they can
reach 2 inches during their five-year lifespans. They eat by
filtering microscopic food particles from the water, and love
intake pipes of water and power plants because the current brings
them a steady supply of fresh food.
   A mussel can filter more than a gallon of water an hour, said <PERSON>R.
Warren Flint</PERSON>, a scientist with the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes Program</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>State
University of New York-Buffalo</ORGANIZATION>. As a result, they will leave water
cleaner than before. ``From an aesthetic perspective, that would
certainly be a benefit, I guess,'' he said.
   Europeans have used zebra mussels to clean algae-choked ponds,
and the shells can be used to add calcium to livestock feed, said
<PERSON>Charles O'Neill</PERSON>, with the Sea Grant program at the <ORGANIZATION>State University
College</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Brockport</LOCATION>.
   The mussels also are a good source of food for diving ducks and
some kinds of fish, including sturgeons and eels, <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said. But
with millions of them at work filtering microscopic food, they
could deplete the supply for the small fish that support the
billion-dollar walleye- and bass-fishing industry.
   And the bad news could spread beyond the lake and its shoreline.
Farmers and golf courses that draw irrigation water from the lakes
can expect problems, and beachgoers will have to wear shoes because
of the shells, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said.
   ``It can affect everything from the electricity at your outlet
to the water at your tap,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``It's not just an
environmental problem.''
   Like their distant cousins, the blue mussels, zebras ought, in
theory, to be edible by humans, <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said. But when Canadian
researchers tried steaming a bunch, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said, ``What they got
was a stench that cleared the lab.''
   The mussels have plagued <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for more than a century and are
believed to have arrived in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> on a freighter that
emptied its ballast tanks in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION>, upstream from <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Scientists are studying the possibility that the <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>
infestations came from several ships rather than that single <DATE>1986</DATE>
event, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. But <LOCATION>Flint</LOCATION> said one colony could have infested
the lake because one mussel can lay 30,000 to 50,000 eggs a year
and the larvae can swim for up to two weeks before growing shells.
``They could easily get across <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Lake Ontario</LOCATION> in that
period of time,'' he said.
   For public water systems, controlling the mussels is a matter of
applying chlorine, ozone or other disinfectants at the mouth of the
intake pipe rather than waiting until the water is inside the
plant, say scientists and plant operators like <PERSON>LePage</PERSON> who have
already faced the problem.
   Power plants have a different problem, because officials are
reluctant to let them put chlorine or other disinfectants in
cooling water discharged back to the lake, <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> said. Niagara
Mohawk and the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental Conservation</ORGANIZATION> are
negotiating a solution.
   <PERSON>James Sell</PERSON>, chief operator of the <LOCATION>Dunkirk</LOCATION> water plant, is
studying ways of getting chlorine to the pipe's mouth, like
building a platform over the intake or running a smaller chlorine
pipe out through the intake. ``We're better off than the people in
the western end of the lake,'' <PERSON>Sell</PERSON> said.
   ``At least we have some time to do something by <DATE>spring</DATE>.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> hasn't been persuaded to pay up to <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> for
the plans, but Sell, who keeps three living mussels in a jar to
show visitors, said, ``I don't see much option for them if they
want a water supply.''
   Farther inland, many water officials are unaware of the problem
or not prepared to do anything about it. <PERSON>Michael Burke</PERSON>, director of
the state <ORGANIZATION>Health Department</ORGANIZATION>'s bureau of public water supply
protection, said the department was studying the problem but
doesn't see the need to issue warnings. ``I think the word's
getting to them, particularly those with large surface intakes in
the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>. It is coming out in industry papers and things of
that sort.''
   O'Neill and other scientists said the state should do more to
get the word out, because it is only a matter of time _ and not
necessarily very much time.
   ``The chances of them getting into the western reach of the <ORGANIZATION>Erie
Canal</ORGANIZATION> is good,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``The canal is an ideal place for
them to live. It's warm. It's shallow. Most of it has rock riprap
to attach to.''
   Pleasure boats can also carry mussels and their larvae in their
engine housings and other places where water collects.
   Once the mussels get into <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>, they will almost
certainly spread through the <LOCATION>Chicago River</LOCATION> and into the <LOCATION>Mississippi
River</LOCATION> basin, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``Any area in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> that is
utilizing surface water should be concerned.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Feb. 19</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891122-0237 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-89 1200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Briefs Adv27   11-22 0613</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Briefs, Adv 27,0628</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, Nov. 27, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Zebra Mussel Infestation of Great Lakes Could Be Costly</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANN ARBOR, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zebra mussels accidentally imported to
the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>last four years</DATE> are threatening commercial
and sport fishing and forcing cities and industries into costly
measures to protect water supplies.
   The 2-inch-long mollusk, first dropped off an ocean-going
freighter in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> outside <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, has spread through
<LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> and a colony was found in <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Green Bay</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Donahue</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes
Commission</ORGANIZATION>, headquartered in <LOCATION>Ann Arbor</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
   Intake pipes for industrial plants and municipal water systems
are among favorite breeding grounds for the greenish-striped
mussel. Monroe, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, just south of <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, is designing a system
to bathe the mouth of its intake system with ozone-infused water in
hopes of killing the mussels' larvae, but there is very little that
apparently can be done to stem the surge of the mussels.
   Cleveland is also facing heavy bills to rid itself of an
infestation, and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> has been forced to partially close its
water plant.
   ``I will guarantee you that it may be <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s
problem today, but it is going to be <PERSON>Gary</PERSON>'s and <LOCATION>Michigan City</LOCATION>'s
problem in the near future,'' <PERSON>Donahue</PERSON> said. ``There's just no way
to stop it.''
   In addition, the mussels feed voraciously on algae that other
fish and mollusks need, and could devastate <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>'s walleye
pike _ one of the lake's most important commercial fish, by
covering spawning grounds, said <PERSON>Jon Stanley</PERSON>, of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ann Arbor</LOCATION>.
   ``Those actions in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, we expect, will reduce the walleye
population by about half,'' <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> said. A ``good portion'' of the
estimated <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> a year in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> fisheries comes from
walleye.
   Beaches also could become fouled by the sharp-edged mussel
shells, <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> said. ``You can notice the difference on some
beaches already. They used to be nice soft sand, but now they
crunch underfoot as you walk.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Researchers Use Dogs to Test Radon Exposure</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST LAFAYETTE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zebra mussels accidentally imported to
the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>last four years</DATE> are threatening commercial
and sport fishing and forcing cities and industries into costly
measures to protect water supplies.
   The 2-inch-long mollusk, first dropped off an ocean-going
freighter in <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> outside <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, has spread through
<LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> and a colony was found in <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Green Bay</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Donahue</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes
Commission</ORGANIZATION>, headquartered in <LOCATION>Ann Arbor</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich</LOCATION>.
   Intake pipes for industrial plants and municipal water systems
are among favorite breeding grounds for the greenish-striped
mussel. Monroe, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, just south of <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, is designing a system
to bathe the mouth of its intake system with ozone-infused water in
hopes of killing the mussels' larvae, but there is very little that
apparently can be done to stem the surge of the mussels.
   Cleveland is also facing heavy bills to rid itself of an
infestation, and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> has been forced to partially close its
water plant.
   ``I will guarantee you that it may be <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s
problem today, but it is going to be <PERSON>Gary</PERSON>'s and <LOCATION>Michigan City</LOCATION>'s
problem in the near future,'' <PERSON>Donahue</PERSON> said. ``There's just no way
to stop it.''
   In addition, the mussels feed voraciously on algae that other
fish and mollusks need, and could devastate <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>'s walleye
pike _ one of the lake's most important commercial fish, by
covering spawning grounds, said <PERSON>Jon Stanley</PERSON>, of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ann Arbor</LOCATION>.
   ``Those actions in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>, we expect, will reduce the walleye
population by about half,'' <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> said. A ``good portion'' of the
estimated <MONEY>$600 million</MONEY> a year in <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION> fisheries comes from
walleye.
   Beaches also could become fouled by the sharp-edged mussel
shells, <ORGANIZATION>Stanley</ORGANIZATION> said. ``You can notice the difference on some
beaches already. They used to be nice soft sand, but now they
crunch underfoot as you walk.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Nov. 27</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900503-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-90 1242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Briefs Adv07   05-03 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Briefs, Adv 07,0804</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv07</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, May 7, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Spread of Zebra Mussels Inland Feared After Lake Superior
Discovery</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DULUTH, Minn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists say the zebra mussel will spread
to inland waters following the first confirmed sightings in Lake
Superior.
   ``This isn't going to just affect anglers,'' said <PERSON>Dennis Pratt</PERSON>,
western Lake Superior fisheries manager for the <ORGANIZATION>Wisconsin
Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>. ``This one's going to affect
industry, boaters ... and the ecosystem is going to take it on the
chin.''
   Discovery in <DATE>March</DATE> of the mussel in the Twin Ports of <LOCATION>Duluth</LOCATION> and
Superior, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, proves the pest is established in all the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION>, scientists say.
   The invader brought via the <PERSON>St. Lawrence Seaway</PERSON> in the ballast
of European freighters was found last month on eight of 26 <LOCATION>St.
Louis River</LOCATION> buoys inspected.
   Experts say the half-inch, barnacle-like shellfish multiply so
fast that colonies of millions may turn up soon. They can clog
water valves, foul city water systems and pollute beaches.
   ``They have a two-year reproductive cycle. I think you'll start
seeing them next year in big numbers,'' <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> said. And once
they're here, there's almost nothing that can be done to stop them,
<PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> said.
   Zebra mussels have caused <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damage in <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION>. Great Lakes environmental officials say
virtually all the hard surfaces in the two lakes are covered with
zebra mussel beds at least an inch thick.
   The creatures also have accumulated two inches thick and clogged
water intakes at five <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Electric Illumination Co.</ORGANIZATION> power
plants. <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, was forced to close its water plant for
three days when zebra mussels were so thick on intake pipes they
slowed water flow.
   Dead zebra mussels can give off offensive quantities of methane
gas and foul city water supplies.
   Environmentally, it's feared huge colonies of zebra mussels on
rocks and shoals will disrupt fish spawning, especially walleye and
lake trout. They also are believed to increase the spread of
parasites damaging to fish and waterfowl.
   A bill moving through <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> asks for <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> to help
combat the mussels. The mussels' total economic damage in the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION> could hit <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> by the turn of the century, a
congressional study said.
   The mussels apparently have few natural enemies, and it is
unlikely they'll be food for humans because they're so small and
carry parasites.
   Scientists on the lower Great Lakes are experimenting with
ultrasound vibrations to keep the mussels away. Chlorination also
seems to help, as does electric shock and speeding the water flow.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Chemists' Laboratory-Created Molecule Makes, Stores Energy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TEMPE, Ariz. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists say the zebra mussel will spread
to inland waters following the first confirmed sightings in Lake
Superior.
   ``This isn't going to just affect anglers,'' said <PERSON>Dennis Pratt</PERSON>,
western Lake Superior fisheries manager for the <ORGANIZATION>Wisconsin
Department of Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION>. ``This one's going to affect
industry, boaters ... and the ecosystem is going to take it on the
chin.''
   Discovery in <DATE>March</DATE> of the mussel in the Twin Ports of <LOCATION>Duluth</LOCATION> and
Superior, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, proves the pest is established in all the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION>, scientists say.
   The invader brought via the <PERSON>St. Lawrence Seaway</PERSON> in the ballast
of European freighters was found last month on eight of 26 <LOCATION>St.
Louis River</LOCATION> buoys inspected.
   Experts say the half-inch, barnacle-like shellfish multiply so
fast that colonies of millions may turn up soon. They can clog
water valves, foul city water systems and pollute beaches.
   ``They have a two-year reproductive cycle. I think you'll start
seeing them next year in big numbers,'' <PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> said. And once
they're here, there's almost nothing that can be done to stop them,
<PERSON>Pratt</PERSON> said.
   Zebra mussels have caused <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damage in <LOCATION>Lake
Erie</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION>. Great Lakes environmental officials say
virtually all the hard surfaces in the two lakes are covered with
zebra mussel beds at least an inch thick.
   The creatures also have accumulated two inches thick and clogged
water intakes at five <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Electric Illumination Co.</ORGANIZATION> power
plants. <PERSON>Monroe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, was forced to close its water plant for
three days when zebra mussels were so thick on intake pipes they
slowed water flow.
   Dead zebra mussels can give off offensive quantities of methane
gas and foul city water supplies.
   Environmentally, it's feared huge colonies of zebra mussels on
rocks and shoals will disrupt fish spawning, especially walleye and
lake trout. They also are believed to increase the spread of
parasites damaging to fish and waterfowl.
   A bill moving through <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> asks for <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> to help
combat the mussels. The mussels' total economic damage in the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION> could hit <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> by the turn of the century, a
congressional study said.
   The mussels apparently have few natural enemies, and it is
unlikely they'll be food for humans because they're so small and
carry parasites.
   Scientists on the lower Great Lakes are experimenting with
ultrasound vibrations to keep the mussels away. Chlorination also
seems to help, as does electric shock and speeding the water flow.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End advance for May 7</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900717-0169 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-17-90 1134EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-MenacingMollusks Adv23   07-17 0946</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Menacing Mollusks, Adv 23,0978</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv23</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Monday July 23 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>European Mollusks Invading Great Lakes Are Here To Stay</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   By <ORGANIZATION>JEFFREY ULBRICH&equals;
Associated Press Writer&</ORGANIZATION>equals;
   <LOCATION>TORONTO</LOCATION> (AP) _ A small European freshwater mollusk called the
zebra mussel has spread at an alarming rate since it was found in
the Great Lakes in <DATE>1988</DATE>, threatening the ecosystem and clogging up
industry.
   Experts say there is no way to wipe the mussels out.
   ``In the <ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION>, all we can do is accept the fact that they
are here and learn to live with it,'' said <PERSON>Gerry Mackie</PERSON>, a biology
professor at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Guelph</ORGANIZATION> who specializes in freshwater
bivalves.
   Criticism in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> focuses on the government's slowness in
attacking the problem.
   ``The invasion of the zebra mussels was preventable,'' the
<ORGANIZATION>Toronto Globe</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Mail</PERSON> said in an editorial. ``<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s complacency
let it happen, and may enable similar invasions unless the country
takes strong preventive measures.''
   <PERSON>Joe Comuzzi</PERSON>, a Liberal member of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, complained recently
that <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> had committed only <MONEY>$230,000</MONEY> (<MONEY>$195,500</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>) to the
problem. He said that ``doesn't even pay for the paper to write a
report.''
   The mussel invasion has been expensive for <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Hydro</ORGANIZATION>, which
has power plants along the lake shore.
   Zebra mussels produce a sticky thread that attaches them to
solid objects _ water pipes in <LOCATION>Ontario Hydro</LOCATION>'s case. The mussels
are capable of sticking in such numbers that they stop or greatly
reduce the flow of water.
   Large intake pipes are not affected, but the mussels swim up
into the small-diameter service piping inside the plants.
   Their presence also leads to corrosion.
   ``It has cost us well over <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> to retrofit all of the
stations for this year, and it's costing us lots in research,''
said <PERSON>Renata Claudi</PERSON>, a senior scientist with the utility company.
   Representatives of 13 companies in the <ORGANIZATION>Chemical Valley</ORGANIZATION> of
<LOCATION>Sarnia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>, got together this month to work out a common
strategy against the mollusks.
   The zebra mussel, about 1{ inches in diameter, is a
dark-colored, clam-like creature with white stripes.
   It has a larval stage of about a month when it swims with the
currents. That accounts for much of its rapid spread throug the
Great Lakes.
   Some of the mollusks hitch rides on ships up the lakes through
<LOCATION>Huron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and Superior and others swim down the current into
the St. <PERSON>Lawrence Seaway</PERSON>.
   A female produces 30,000 to 40,000 eggs in each of its two or
three years of life.
   Experts agree zebra mussels entered the Great Lakes system in
<LOCATION>Lake St. Clair</LOCATION> in the <DATE>summer of 1985</DATE> or <DATE>1986</DATE>. They probably were
flushed from the ballast of a ship that came from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   All the Great Lakes now are infested and scientists say their
passage into the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> system is inevitable.
   ``They have gone through the <LOCATION>Niagara River</LOCATION> and into <LOCATION>Lake
Ontario</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Ms. Claudi</PERSON> said. ``Now they are swimming their way
toward <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>.''
   Scientists are not sure what the ecological impact will be, but
are fearful of it.
   ``You have to keep it in perspective,'' said <PERSON>Joe Leach</PERSON>, a
research scientist with the <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Natural Resources Ministry</ORGANIZATION>.
``The major impacts right now are with the technical devices, pipes
and so on. We ... are looking at potention impacts on ... fishes,
but at the present time there is no indication of major ecological
impact.''
   <PERSON>Leach</PERSON> said the main fears were disruption of spawning for fish
like walleye, which lay their eggs on hard, rocky areas, and that
the food chain would be altered.
   ``These things are filter feeders,'' he said. ``They filter an
enormous amount of water and take everything out of it. What they
don't use, they put mucus around and drop it down to the bottom.''
   That shifts a lot of organic matter from the water to the bottom
of the lake. <PERSON>Leach</PERSON> said it eventually could change fish populations
by reducing the number of water column feeders, such as walleye and
trout, and increasing catfish, sturgeon and other bottom feeders.
   There also is increasing evidence of zebra mussels attaching to
other bivalves and smothering them.
   ``As it stands now, there isn't anything you can do,'' <PERSON>Leach</PERSON>
said. ``There is no way you can control them. If you use poison,
you are going to poison the system.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Hydro</ORGANIZATION> uses chlorine, the most effective molluscicide
found so far.
   In one affected plant, <PERSON>Ms. Claudi</PERSON> said, the company ``applied
sodium hypochlorite in relatively small doses for about two weeks.
That basically did them in and all we had to worry about was
cleaning out the shells.''
   She added that the amount used, in an agreement with the
<ORGANIZATION>Environment Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, ``is never more than 10 parts per billion.
Compare that with the five parts per million of the same stuff in
the drinking water we happily drink every day.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Claudi</PERSON> says <PERSON>Ontario Hydro</PERSON> was talking to other utilities
across the lakes, the <ORGANIZATION>American Waterworks Association and Electric
Power Research Association</ORGANIZATION>, ``but we're finding that we are way
ahead or at the same level as these guys'' in research.
   Most experts believe the zebra mussel population eventually will
level off and perhaps even decline, but <PERSON>Mackie</PERSON> said the problem was
``trying to determine at what point they will level off or if they
will crash.''
   <PERSON>Geoff Holland</PERSON> of the federal fisheries and oceans department
said Canadian officials probably would meet with provincial and
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> representatives this fall to work out a budget for fighting
the zebra mussel.
   As for <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Hydro</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Claudi</PERSON> said: ``Prevention is really
what we're looking at. We just don't want those guys in our pipe.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Monday July 23</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1936EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ZebraMussel     11-29 0397</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zebra Mussel,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discovery Of Zebra Mussels In Hudson River Startles Scientists</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   CROTON-ON-HUDSON, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> (AP) - The discovery of zebra mussels in
the brackish waters of the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> startled scientists, who
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the pests weren't supposed to get this far south this
soon.
   ``We've just thrown the book out now,'' <PERSON>Avery Klauber</PERSON>, a
spokesman for <LOCATION>New York Sea Grant</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>State University of New
York</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Stony Brook</LOCATION>. ``There's no way of knowing how far and how
fast they're going to travel.''
   Experts didn't expect the tiny mussel, named for its striped
shell, to appear in the Hudson until next year or the year after.
Scientists also had hoped the waters of the lower <PERSON>Hudson</PERSON>, with a
salinity of eight parts per thousand, would be too salty for the
mussels.
   They have been spreading through the Great Lakes since <DATE>1988</DATE>,
when scientists think European ships released them with ballast
water.
   The mussels have few natural predators and breed rapidly,
causing problems for industries, power plants, public water systems
and boaters by clogging water intakes. They can also wreak havoc on
aquatic food chains.
   Federal officials have estimated that control of the mussels
could cost as much as <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> over the next decade in the <LOCATION>Great
Lakes</LOCATION> region.
   The <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> discovery is the first North American sighting
of the pest outside the Great Lakes drainage basin, said <PERSON>Charles
O'Neill</PERSON>, supervisor of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Zebra Mussel Information
Clearinghouse</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>State University of New York</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Brockport</LOCATION>.
   ``Everybody was watching to see where they'd turn up out of the
<LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said. ``This one being such a jump opens up
the possibility that the mussels can be really widely scattered.''
   The animals were discovered by accident on a piece of wood
collected for an museum exhibit from <LOCATION>Haverstraw Bay</LOCATION>, about 25 miles
north of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said, adding it was too early to
tell the extent of the infestation.
   He said the mussels may have been brought to the river by a
Great Lakes pleasure boat or a European ship, or even by a piece of
wood floating from the <ORGANIZATION>Erie Canal</ORGANIZATION> to the <LOCATION>Mohawk River</LOCATION> and on into
the <LOCATION>Hudson</LOCATION>.
   The discovery of the mussels is particularly worrisome to
officials of four major power plants near the discovery site,
<PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said.
   Experts expect zebra mussels eventually to find their way into
the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> through canals connecting it to the Great
Lakes. From there, they could spread across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``We're looking at a critter that within the next couple
generations could very possibly be found throughout <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> said.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sen. Daniel P. Moynihan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, issued a plea to
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to sign legislation authorizing <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY>
for project grants and research funding to control the mussels.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900619-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-19-90 1450EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WaterInvaders     06-19 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Water Invaders,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Species Invading U.S. Waters, Experts Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN FLESHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The zebra mussel is one of many exotic species
invading <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> waters, and a broad strategy is needed to keep them
from wreaking economic and environmental havoc, experts said
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The river ruffe, spiny water flea and tube-nosed goby soon may
become as familiar to the Great Lakes as the zebra mussel,
witnesses said at a hearing of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Subcommittee on
Environmental Protection</ORGANIZATION>.
   Meanwhile, the asiatic clam, Japanese seaweed and the red tide
are damaging shellfish and marine industries along the ocean coasts.
   The newcomers threaten many native species, interrupt the food
chain and pose a danger to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fishing industry and other
segments of the economy, said <PERSON>Gillman D. Veith</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection Agency's Office of Research and
Development</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Given the rate of technological change and movement of people,
it is likely that the problems resulting from invasions of
non-native species will increase,'' said <PERSON>Veith</PERSON>.
   The city of <LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, was forced to ration water for
several days and spend <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> removing zebra mussels from its
water intake pipe last year, said <PERSON>Sen. Herb Kohl</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis</LOCATION>. Shipping,
tourism, paper production and other industries could be affected if
such problems become widespread, he said.
   ``There is growing concern that the introduction of
non-indigenous species by ships, particularly through their ballast
water, has affected the ecosystems and economies of countries
around the world,'' said Capt. <PERSON>Thomas E. Thompson</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast
Guard</ORGANIZATION>.
   Bills pending in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> would order the <ORGANIZATION>Coast
Guard</ORGANIZATION> to develop and enforce regulations on dumping of ships'
ballast water _ the suspected source of zebra mussels, which are
native to fresh-water bodies of <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   The tiny bivalves with zebra-like stripes have spread with
lightning speed through the Great Lakes since their arrival in
<DATE>1986</DATE>. They fasten themselves to hard surfaces, such as pipes and
boat hulls, and ingest plankton essential to the aquatic food chain.
   Senators from the region urged quick action and braodening the
scopes of the bills to deal with other natural invaders.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900726-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-26-90 1525EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-ZebraMussels     07-26 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zebra Mussels,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Adds $20 Million to Farm Bill to Stop Zebra Mussel Spread</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIM I. MILLS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has approved a <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> research
and prevention program to keep zebra mussels from invading farm
irrigation systems.
   The striped mollusk, which is not native to <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, has
caused problems at water and power plants throughout the Great
Lakes. They attach to water intake pipes and clog them.
   An amendment authorizing the <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> over five years was
added to the <DATE>1990</DATE> farm bill by <PERSON>Sen. Daniel P. Moynihan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>
   ``Unlike other infestations, this one is irreversible,''
<PERSON>Moynihan</PERSON> said in a statement <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. ``The zebra mussel is here
to stay ... Within 20 years' time it will have spread through the
entire surface water system of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.''
   The amendment, which the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passed <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE>, directs
the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army Corps of Engineers</ORGANIZATION>
to develop a program of research, prevention and design criteria
for irrigation systems with an emphasis on keeping the mussels out.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, scientists expressed surprise that the tiny
mollusks are spreading through the <ORGANIZATION>Erie Canal</ORGANIZATION> system from <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, and now threaten <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> and the Finger Lakes region.
   ``Frankly, I did not think their advance would be this fast,''
said <PERSON>Cameron Lange</PERSON>, a biologist studying the mussels' movement for
a consortium of power companies.
   ``I thought we might find a few at <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION> during our <DATE>late July</DATE>
sample but I did not think they'd reach Rochester by now.''
   Rochester is about 60 miles east of <LOCATION>Lockport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   In <DATE>May</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Committee on Environment and Public Works</ORGANIZATION>
authorized <MONEY>$37.5 million</MONEY> in grants and research funding for control
of the mussel. The provision is part of the pending Water Resources
Development Act of <DATE>1990</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900705-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-90 2145EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brite-SovietGoby     07-05 0178</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brite-Soviet Goby,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tiny Foreigner Invades Great Lakes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Yet another foreign invader has ignored the
border and taken up residence in the <LOCATION>Great Lakes</LOCATION>.
   A tube-nosed goby, a 3-inch-long fish from the Black Sea region
of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, was recently found on an intake screen at the
<ORGANIZATION>Detroit Edison Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Belle River</LOCATION> plant on the <LOCATION>St. Clair River</LOCATION>.
   But the goby doesn't appear threatening, unlike a host of other
invaders, including the water pipe-clogging zebra mussel, the
trout-killing sea lamprey, and the beach-befouling alewife.
   Like other non-native critters, the goby probably got to the
Great Lakes by hitching a ride on ocean freighters which take on
water _ and any small free-swimming animals that happen to be in
the way _ for ballast. When the ship reaches port on the Great
Lakes to take on cargo, the ballast gets dumped.
   Threatening or no, the goby isn't welcome.
   Biologists ``don't like to see foreign species end up in our
bodies of water,'' said <PERSON>Dave Jude</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION>
scientist who found the fish.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06034023 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06034023 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Kenneth Love -- National Geographic Society; A Chippewa boy
celebrates the wild rice harvest along the Great Lakes.; PHOTO: James L. Amos
-- National Geographic Society; Two sea lampreys, a Great Lakes invader
species, feast on fish's body fluids  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; CANADA; MULTIPLE; LAKE; ENVIRONMENT; TELEVISION; PROGRAM  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  MOST everybody must know that Lake Superior is the largest body of fresh water
in the world and that Lake Erie was so polluted that it once caught on fire.; 
  But, unless we've lived on or near the Great Lakes, that may be the extent
of what most of us know about that enormous system of lakes and waterways
along the U.S.-Canadian border.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  TV Magazine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SPECIAL TAKES FRESH LOOK AT GREAT LAKES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cable  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Now, thanks to the latest National Geographic TV special, "Great Lakes,
Fragile Seas" (<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>, <LOCATION>Ch</LOCATION>. 9), we can learn a lot more about the
lakes and the imposing challenges that threaten their long-term survival.;   
This excellent hour documentary, written, produced and photographed by <PERSON>Joe
Seamans</PERSON>, contains some facts that may amaze most of us, including:;    (box) 
The five lakes -- <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Erie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Huron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and Superior -- hold at least
six quadrillion gallons of water, enough to flood all 48 contiguous states to
a depth of 10 feet.;    (box)  The largest lakes are so huge that they
frequently have stormy "seas" that rival those found in the world's oceans.;  
 (box)  More than 10,000 vessels have sunk while crossing the Great Lakes.;   
(box)  The flow in the lakes is so complex that it may take nearly 100 years
for toxic chemicals to completely wash out of their waters.;    (box)  The
lakes contain about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of all the fresh water on the planet.;   
Scooped out by glacial action about 20,000 years ago, the Great Lakes face
several simultaneous ecological crises brought about by humans' intense use of
their waters in just the past 200 years.;    <PERSON>Seamans</PERSON>' camera shows us deformed
fish and birds, genetically damaged by toxic chemicals still present in the
waters despite heroic efforts to clean them up after a <DATE>1972</DATE> pact between the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Canadian governments.;    We also see what amounts to "biological
pollution" from the destructive Zebra mussels, now multiplying rapidly in the
lakes and destroying the natural food chain by siphoning off up to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT>
of all nutrients needed by native lake species.;    Experts studying the
problem believe that the mussels, native to the Caspian and Black seas, were
carried into the lakes by seagoing foreign vessels. If Americans and Canadians
hadn't built a complex system of locks and waterways, linking the lakes to the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, these marauders never would have turned up.;     Diversity of life; 
Originally, lakes <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> and Erie were linked only by the <LOCATION>Niagara River</LOCATION>. The
spectacular <ORGANIZATION>Niagara Falls</ORGANIZATION> served as a natural barrier to invasion of outside
species. But the human-made bypass of the falls opened the doorway to what may
be ecological disaster.;    <PERSON>Seamans</PERSON>' far-ranging film aptly demonstrates the
diversity of life on the lakes, beyond the skyscraper-lined cities along their
shores. For example, we visit remote <LOCATION>Madeline Island</LOCATION> on Lake Superior, which
is reached only by "wind sleds" during the icy winters, and a Chippewa Indian
community, where wild rice is harvested in preserved wetlands the same way it
was 200 years ago.;    Wreckage explored; In what may be the film's most
bizarre excursion, we probe the depths of Lake Superior by robot mini-sub to
explore the wreckage of the 729-foot steel freighter <PERSON>Edmund Fitzgerald</PERSON>, which
split in half and sank during a tremendous storm in <DATE>1975.</DATE>;    Though "Great
Lakes, Fragile Seas" does include some sobering information, it's not a
downer. Progress is being made in halting the environmental threats to the
lakes. They're even pulling big, beautiful, edible fish from the same waters
that once caught fire; so it seems there is cause for cautious optimism after
all. (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  RON MILLER, Mercury News Television Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910203  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  632  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday February 3, 1991
00034023,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900509-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-90 0547EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     05-09 0411</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BATTLE CREEK, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some people never throw anything
away, according to <PERSON>Scott Bruce</PERSON>, who came to this breakfast food
mecca looking for old cereal boxes to add to his collection.
   Sound flaky?
   ``Cereal boxes represent heroes of popular culture _ the grain
gods, I call them,'' said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, collector who
once started a lunch-box collecting craze.
   ``When a kid sits down with a bowl of his favorite cereal, he
becomes one with his hero. It's like a secular communion rite.''
   Bruce, 34, is talking this week with cereal company executives
as well as ordinary people who hoard cereal boxes, if there is such
a thing.
   Rare boxes can fetch up to <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>, said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>, who began his
collection in <DATE>1988</DATE> and recently published a collector's magazine
called <ORGANIZATION>Flake</ORGANIZATION>.
   Battle Creek is the home of <ORGANIZATION>Kellogg Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the world's largest
cereal maker, as well as Post and <ORGANIZATION>Ralston-Purina</ORGANIZATION> plants.
   ``The people here have cereal in their bloodstream,'' said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>.
   Old cereal boxes are all the more valuable because of the
scarcity of people who allow them to hang around.
   ``The militant mom was the death to many collections,'' he said
mournfully. ``But maybe I'll find that that odd citizen who has a
Corn Flakes box with <PERSON>Vanessa Williams</PERSON>.'' Miss <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Miss
America</LOCATION> <DATE>1984</DATE>, lost the crown when it was disclosed she had posed
nude for Playboy.
   <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON> said he generally hunts for vintage boxes in good
condition from the <DATE>1930s</DATE> through <DATE>1970s</DATE>. But he's even squirreling
away some of today's boxes.
   ``The <DATE>1990</DATE> Batman cereal box from <ORGANIZATION>Ralston</ORGANIZATION> is an instant
classic,'' he said. ``Just you wait.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OAK HARBOR, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some people never throw anything
away, according to <PERSON>Scott Bruce</PERSON>, who came to this breakfast food
mecca looking for old cereal boxes to add to his collection.
   Sound flaky?
   ``Cereal boxes represent heroes of popular culture _ the grain
gods, I call them,'' said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, collector who
once started a lunch-box collecting craze.
   ``When a kid sits down with a bowl of his favorite cereal, he
becomes one with his hero. It's like a secular communion rite.''
   Bruce, 34, is talking this week with cereal company executives
as well as ordinary people who hoard cereal boxes, if there is such
a thing.
   Rare boxes can fetch up to <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>, said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>, who began his
collection in <DATE>1988</DATE> and recently published a collector's magazine
called <ORGANIZATION>Flake</ORGANIZATION>.
   Battle Creek is the home of <ORGANIZATION>Kellogg Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the world's largest
cereal maker, as well as Post and <ORGANIZATION>Ralston-Purina</ORGANIZATION> plants.
   ``The people here have cereal in their bloodstream,'' said <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON>.
   Old cereal boxes are all the more valuable because of the
scarcity of people who allow them to hang around.
   ``The militant mom was the death to many collections,'' he said
mournfully. ``But maybe I'll find that that odd citizen who has a
Corn Flakes box with <PERSON>Vanessa Williams</PERSON>.'' Miss <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Miss
America</LOCATION> <DATE>1984</DATE>, lost the crown when it was disclosed she had posed
nude for Playboy.
   <PERSON>Bruce</PERSON> said he generally hunts for vintage boxes in good
condition from the <DATE>1930s</DATE> through <DATE>1970s</DATE>. But he's even squirreling
away some of today's boxes.
   ``The <DATE>1990</DATE> Batman cereal box from <ORGANIZATION>Ralston</ORGANIZATION> is an instant
classic,'' he said. ``Just you wait.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891218-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-18-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Storms-ColdRdp 2ndLd-Writethru a0692 12-18 0901</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Storms-Cold Rdp, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0692,0918</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arctic Air Brings Winter to Dixie, Shatters Records in North</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 7th graf, `At least ..., with 2 grafs to UPDATE deaths
total and total exposure deaths in Chicago.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A Canadian delivery of sleet and ice sledded into the deep South
on <DATE>Monday</DATE> in a winter preview that cracked century-old temperature
records across the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and clogged the <LOCATION>Missouri River</LOCATION> with a
75-mile ice jam.
   The bitter weather closed schools from <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>,
and forecasters said no change was in sight. The cold is being
caused by a horseshoe-shaped flow of air that follows the <LOCATION>West
Coast</LOCATION> up to <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, chills out and plunges down through <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> into
the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>.
   ``It's simply a pipeline that carries ... the cold air
southward,'' said <PERSON>Ed Ferguson</PERSON>, deputy director of the federal
government's <ORGANIZATION>Severe Storms Forecast Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>. ``And by
southward, I mean all the way to the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>.''
   Southerners from central <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION> awoke
<DATE>Monday</DATE> to a <ORGANIZATION>Yankee</ORGANIZATION>'s vista of freezing rain and sleet that made
driving hazardous and was blamed for at least one traffic death.
Hundreds of schools were closed.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said as much as an inch of sleet
and freezing rain covered north and central <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> before dawn,
and freezing rain extended as far south as <LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION>.
   Ice on <LOCATION>Interstate 85</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> apparently contributed to a
crash that killed <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Falcons tight end <PERSON>Brad Beckman</PERSON>,
authorities said.
   At least 19 deaths around the nation were blamed on the cold
during the weekend, including the deaths of two young <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>,
girls who apparently were playing with a makeshift sled <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when
they plunged through thin ice on a lake. Two homeless people died
of hypothermia while sleeping in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> subway stations.
   One weekend hypothermia death in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> brought to 10 the
number of people who have died from exposure in the municipal area
so far this <DATE>winter</DATE>, said a spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>Cook County Medical
Examiner</ORGANIZATION>'s office.
   A school bus carrying 43 children crashed into a station wagon
on a slippery highway <DATE>Monday</DATE> near <LOCATION>Shapleighl</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, but none of
the children were seriously hurt, officials said.
   <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s cold broke <DATE>Dec. 18</DATE> records that had held for more than
a century in <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, where it was minus 7; in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>,
where it also was 7 below, and in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, where it was minus 3.
   Other records included <LOCATION>Parkersburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va.</LOCATION>, at 4 above,
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> at 3 below, <LOCATION>Fort Wayne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> at minus 5,
and <LOCATION>Youngstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, at minus 8.
   ``Good night, it's been unreal,'' said <PERSON>Pam Decker</PERSON>, co-owner of
<ORGANIZATION>Decker's Wrecker Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, which was besieged
with calls about stalled and wrecked cars and the need to
jump-start dead or dying car batteries.
   The <LOCATION>Missouri River</LOCATION> turned to ice for about a 75-mile stretch
between <PERSON>Blair</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, just north of <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Sioux City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
   The ice jam had begun late <DATE>Friday</DATE> and grew over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>.
Officials feared that the ice floe could cause problems for
communities that pump their water from the river, and <ORGANIZATION>Weather
Service</ORGANIZATION> hydrologist <PERSON>Roy Osugi</PERSON> didn't hold out hope for an early
thaw.
   ``Nothing is going to bust it up except warmer weather,'' <PERSON>Osugi</PERSON>
said. ``We think it's going to stay in place at least <DATE>this week</DATE>
because it's going to stay very cold.''
   In <LOCATION>St. Joseph</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, officials activated a new emergency pump as
a precautionary measure to keep water flowing to the city.
   There were similar problems in the town of <LOCATION>Monroe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, where
55,000 water customers were asked to conserve while workers <DATE>Monday</DATE>
cleared a frozen intake valve that also was clogged with <LOCATION>Lake Erie</LOCATION>
zebra mussels, a non-native species which has no natural predators
and is proliferating in the lake.
   In <LOCATION>Crooksville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, officials declared a water emergency after
a series of water main breaks over the weekend. Parts of the small
town had been without service for three days.
   The cold also was the likely cause of a break in a 4-inch pipe
that let water surge through all 12 floors of a new hospital at
<ORGANIZATION>Ohio State University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, causing at least <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>
damage and delaying its scheduled <DATE>Jan. 16</DATE> opening, said <ORGANIZATION>OSU</ORGANIZATION> vice
president <PERSON>Richard Jackson</PERSON>.
   Farther west, the arctic weather system carried welcome snow to
<ORGANIZATION>Rocky Mountain</ORGANIZATION> ski resorts and wind chills of 35 below zero to
parts of <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. It was 26 below at <LOCATION>Jordan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, and high
temperatures in some parts of <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> were expected to be below
zero.
   In <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, snowfall in the 24 hours that ended <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>
included 4 inches at <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 16 inches at <LOCATION>Vail</LOCATION> and 9\ inches at
<LOCATION>Steamboat Springs</LOCATION> _ which has gotten 99 inches in nine days, said
spokeswoman <PERSON>Barb Jennings</PERSON>.
   At <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Stapleton International Airport</LOCATION>, spokesman <PERSON>Norm
Avery</PERSON> said crews were out before daybreak, clearing 10 runways.
However, he said flights were delayed up to an hour because of the
snow.
   Ferguson, of the <ORGANIZATION>Severe Storms Forecast Center</ORGANIZATION>, said the outlook
for most of the country is for below-average temperatures for the
next month or so.
   ``There's no promise that we can see in any of our projections
that we're going to have balmy weather in the middle of <DATE>winter</DATE>,''
he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890608-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-08-89 1256EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-GreatLakes     06-08 0407</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Great Lakes,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Commission Urges U.S. and Canada to Bar New Species</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM BOVEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international commission urged the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to bar new species of animals from the
<ORGANIZATION>Great Lakes</ORGANIZATION> in an effort to prevent additional harm to the region's
delicate ecology.
   ``The integrity of the Great Lakes ecosystem requires the
maintenance of a balanced yet dynamic natural system,'' the
<ORGANIZATION>International Joint Commission</ORGANIZATION>, a U.S.-Canadian agency, said in a
report on the lakes' environment.
   ``Introduced species can seriously affect the balance and
distribution of native species by altering the structure and
developmental patterns of their biological communities,'' it added.
   The report by the commission noted that there have been
continuing concerns about outside species in the lakes, the sea
lamprey and smelt in particular.
   However, in recent years, the number of alien species introduced
into the lakes has shown a significant increase.
   Among the outside species that now threaten the lakes' native
life forms are the alewife, the coho salmon, the Asiatic clam, the
zebra mussel and the river ruffe.
   The commission encouraged involvement by the coast guards of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> in controlling the problem, and recommended
that the nations ``take steps to prevent the further introduction,
particularly the unplanned introduction, of exotic life forms into
the Great Lakes ecosystem.''
   It was the first time the commission had made such a
recommendation, said <PERSON>Frank Bevacqua</PERSON> of the commission's <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
office.
   Some of the outside species were introduced for sport fishing.
Others made their way into the lakes as hitchhikers on ships or
