<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871124-0142 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- The Gallery:
One Poet's Wide World: In Word and Picture
---
By Manuela Hoelterhoff</HL>
<DD> 11/24/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> New York  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1792</DATE>, young <PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and all heated up with revolutionary ardor, was ready to offer his words, his self, his very life to the Girondist party. 
His appalled family threatened to cut off his allowance, and so he went home, his saved head soon reverberating with "Tintern Abbey." 
The Girondists in the meanwhile mostly headed up the long steps to the guillotine, dispatched there by <LOCATION>Robespierre</LOCATION> and the Jacobins. 

   Now this near-martyr who is more often remembered as the fuddy-duddy who lived in cozy comfort at <ORGANIZATION>Dove Cottage</ORGANIZATION> with his doting sister <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>, is the hero of a new show at the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION>: "<PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON> and the Age of English Romanticism." 
His long poems and long life (1770-1850) thread together some 300 manuscripts, books, paintings, drawings and prints from 70 libraries, museums and private lenders. 

   It is a superbly interesting show, a model even, in its tasteful design and the intelligent way it links words and images to show all aspects of Romantic thought and sensibility. 
Gallery walls do not glow with a fashionable, lurid pastel color; the catalog can be lifted by an able-bodied person; the wall labels aren't written in the impenetrable artspeak typical of the genre. 
<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, who thought poetry should be accessible to clodhoppers and to academics, would like this show. 

   The discovery of nature as a theme, the role of memory and the sublime, are probed skillfully in a display that begins with the French Revolution -- "The master theme of the epoch in which we live," as <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON> called it. 
He penned his own Declaration of Rights for the oppressed of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, but, always a bit impractical, disseminated the list in toy boats and homemade hot-air balloons. 
Then he untethered himself from British soil, moving to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> like so many of the Romantic-era poets -- think of <PERSON>Keats</PERSON>, who expired in a house by <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>'s Spanish Steps, or <PERSON>Lord Byron</PERSON>, whom we see in the famous portrait showing him in his resplendent Albanian fighting regalia. 

   Perhaps the rarest autograph in the show is a hastily scrawled page from <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON>'s "The Triumph of Life," lent by the <ORGANIZATION>Bodleian Library</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Oxford</ORGANIZATION>. 
It shows how, having framed the question "And what is life, I cried?" 
Shelley changed "And" to "Then" and "cried" to the more moderate "said." 
He never composed the answer. 
We are looking at his last poem. 
Not much later, at age 29, he drowned in his skiff, the <PERSON>Don Juan</PERSON>, off the coast of Viareggio. 

   You can read also from a first edition of "Frankenstein," the horror tale penned earlier by <PERSON>Mary Shelley</PERSON>, the wife left behind on the shore. 
Her maudlin monster also questioned life's meaning. 
"Was I, then, a monster, a blot upon the earth from which all men fled . . ." the blob sobs in chapter 31. (Yes! he discovers soon enough.) 
Her mother, <PERSON>Mary Wollstonecraft</PERSON>, gazes glumly out of a portrait. 
An early feminist, she died in <DATE>1797</DATE> depressed by the Revolution's failure to amplify the rights of women. 

   But to hear with what boundless joy revolutionary <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was regarded just a few years earlier you can count on <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>. 
"<PERSON>Bliss</PERSON> was it in that dawn to be alive. 
But to be young was very heaven!" he wrote in his autobiographical poem "The Prelude" without giving any of the juicy details of his doubtless heavenly youthful affair with <PERSON>Annette Vallon</PERSON>. 

   She was the mademoiselle he left behind in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, pregnant with Anne-Caroline. 
She crops up in two letters that have never before been exhibited because they were intercepted by a revolutionary watchdog committee and filed away in a provincial archive. 
In the primmest of scripts, she begs her hotly missed <PERSON>William</PERSON> not to forget "Your Annette who kisses you a thousand times on the mouth." 
Good lord. 
How hard it is to associate such ardor with the bland gent who looks like he has earthworms on his head in the odd portrait bust at the show's entrance. 

   At least <PERSON>Annette</PERSON> survived. 
An exquisite little painting by <PERSON>Jean-Jacques Hauer</PERSON> shows another French lady friend of <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> who did not: <PERSON>Madame Rolland</PERSON> sits in her drawing room with her harp, pet dog and <LOCATION>Lafayette</LOCATION>. 
Plucky to the last, she managed a much-quoted line before tied down to the plank: "Ah, Liberty! 
How hast thou been sported with!" she said, prompted by a statue of Liberty erected near the guillotine. 
<PERSON>Louis XVI</PERSON>, in contrast, got off no bon mots at all. 
A drum corps had been ordered to drown him out as he reached the top of the scaffold depicted in another painting. 

   Such bloody spectacles did not give a boost to fashionable theories about the perfectibility of man. 
Many sensible poets and painters turned away from politics and took stock of nature, which needed no further perfection in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> then. 
Proof is all around you in this show, with its splendid landscapes by <PERSON>John Sell Cotman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Samuel Palmer</PERSON> and most of all, <PERSON>John Constable</PERSON>, who shared <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>'s feelings for the simple felicities of the countryside. 

   "For I have learned," wrote <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, "To look on Nature not as in the hour/Of thoughtless youth, but hearing often times/The still, sad music of humanity." 
The passage is from "Tintern Abbey," and the bare, ruined choirs of the place itself can be seen, gorgeously dilapidated, in an early watercolor by <PERSON>J.M.W. Turner</PERSON>, one of the show's many superb works by this poet of light and color. 

   More often, as he got older, <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> explored a more private landscape -- the topography of his mind, searching "memory's cells" for inspirational scenes that would billow his sails. 
He worried that his powers were failing, and anyone who has ever read "Is this, <PERSON>Ye Gods</PERSON>, the Capitoline Hill?" written in the <DATE>1830s</DATE> and my favorite worst <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> passage, will know why he did. 
But, paradoxically, his fear of dimming down more often produced stunning rhymes. 
Consider these lines from his "Intimations of Immortality": 

   "What though the radiance which was once so bright/Be now for ever taken from my sight,/Though nothing can bring back the hour/of splendour in the grass, of glory in the flower. . . ." 

   "<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> and the Age of English Romanticism" was organized by <PERSON>Jonathan Wordsworth</PERSON>, a descendant of the poet, <PERSON>Michael C. Jaye</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Woof</PERSON>. 
The Economist magazine and the <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the Humanities are the main sponsors; the show stays here through <DATE>Jan. 2</DATE>, then heads for the <ORGANIZATION>Indiana University Art Museum</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Bloomington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION> (Jan. 27-March 6) and the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Historical Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>April</DATE> 6-June 5). 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06189023 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06189023 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Wordsworth  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  UK; WRITING; COMPUTER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The ultimate English poetry anthology, containing every inspired or wretched
line published by 1,350 poets from early Anglo-Saxon times to 1900, will soon
be available on computer.;    "English Poetry," the entire output from 1,300
years, will be contained on four computer discs or one magnetic tape, 2,400
feet long, and available for $35,200.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BRITISH POETRY OF 1,300 YEARS COMPUTERIZED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "It may sound expensive, but it will be cheaper than trying to acquire
nearly 5,000 volumes," said <PERSON>Stephen Pocock</PERSON>, the senior project editor at
publishers <ORGANIZATION>Chadwyck-Healey Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>. The discs will become available
between <DATE>March 1992</DATE> and <DATE>March 1994.</DATE>;    "Some of these poets have not been
reprinted since their work was originally published in the 17th and 18th
centuries. The poetry will be indexed by author, title, part-title and key
words so that anyone searching it will be able to see if some poets borrowed
anything from their predecessors," <PERSON>Pocock</PERSON> said in an interview Friday.;    He
said the work stopped at <DATE>1900</DATE> because of copyright difficulties with 20th
century poetry.;    Publication is scheduled for three installments, one disc
each for the periods 600 to <DATE>1660</DATE> and <DATE>1661</DATE> to <DATE>1800</DATE> and the last two for the
<DATE>19th century</DATE>, which contains as much verse as the other two periods together,
<PERSON>Pocock</PERSON> said.;    "All the published work of these poets will be included, the
famous and the completely obscure, whether it was poetry of genius or just
plain awful. Even famous poets like (<LOCATION>William</LOCATION>) <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> wrote some dire stuff
at times," he said.;    Even one of <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>'s worst lines will be included:
"This piteous news so much it shocked her, She quite forgot to send the
doctor.";    Besides the great masters like <PERSON>William Shakespeare</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Milton</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Lord Byron</PERSON>, the project will include little-known versifiers.;    One is
<PERSON>William Tennant</PERSON>, whose epic 1822 poem "The Thane of Fife" has some memorable
imagery like, "Now, in the very navel of the sky" and "Morning's
golden-tassell'd shoes, Had leapt from sea and now in heaven walk dry.";   
"It's taken 15 people all <DATE>summer</DATE> just to count the words involved and there
are more than 1 billion characters," said <PERSON>John Russell</PERSON>, the publisher's sales
director.;    <PERSON>Pocock</PERSON> said the poets are those listed in "The New Cambridge
Bibliography of English Literature," issued by <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University Press</ORGANIZATION> from
<DATE>1969</DATE> to <DATE>1972</DATE>, and which includes English translations of <ORGANIZATION>Welsh</ORGANIZATION>, Scottish and
Irish poets who wrote in other languages.;    "We expect university libraries
around the world, English faculties and some public libraries to buy it. Much
of the material is hard to come by and isn't available in some British
libraries," <PERSON>Pocock</PERSON> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  London  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910707  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  19A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  434  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 7, 1991
00189023,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052989-0088 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 63444 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 29, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 3; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
542 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ART REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
HUNTINGTON ASSEMBLES DRAWINGS OF HISTORIC BRITISH FIGURES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUVAN GEER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Huntington Art Gallery</ORGANIZATION>'s current exhibition, "British Portrait Drawings of 
Notables," takes as its central theme the famous historic individuals in 
European literature, the arts and politics. It offers a modest but often 
delightful look at writers and poets such as <PERSON>Charles Dickens</PERSON> and <PERSON>Elizabeth 
Barrett Browning</PERSON> and such memorable figures as politician <PERSON>William Gladstone</PERSON> and 
adventurer Captain Blood. 
</P>
<P>
Culled by curator <PERSON>Shelley M. Bennett</PERSON> from the <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION>'s collection of more 
than 13,000 drawings and watercolors, the exhibit features some of the most 
famous countenances in European history, from <LOCATION>Napoleon</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Johann Sebastian 
Bach</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Any exhibit of historical portraiture must unfortunately deal with a 
contemporary ignorance of history. Thankfully, this show's descriptive labels 
are more than just title and artist. They are mercifully brief but give a touch 
of history, a hint of social implication and occasionally even a whiff of 
gossip. This kind of concise information adds immeasurably to an appreciation 
of images such as illustrator <PERSON>James Smetham</PERSON>'s gaunt and intense pencil 
self-portrait and comic artist <PERSON>Thomas Rowlandson</PERSON>'s stinging watercolor of the 
theatrics of actress <PERSON>Sarah Siddons</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The show isn't large, but the history it covers gets further clarification by 
being broken into three small rooms, which feature heads of state, the arts and 
finally notables in politics, the military and the church. Interestingly 
enough, the distinction of social position also shows some of the artistic 
conventions that artists used to express the personality of their subject. 
Poets and artists like <PERSON>Lord Byron</PERSON> appear to glow with an inner fire. 
</P>
<P>
Creativity frequently lights their the faces with near-mystic inspiration as 
they gaze off into infinity with romantic melancholy. But heads of state such 
as <PERSON>King George IV</PERSON> are ripe for lampooning and wily politicians such as <PERSON>William 
Gladstone</PERSON> are engagingly exaggerated into a kind of physical comedy of 
political blunders. 
</P>
<P>
Explanations and commentary aside, the seduction in these portraits lies in the 
fact that these were memorable individuals. After being duly impressed by their 
credentials and the artistic trappings of their positions, we want to feel we 
can know what they were like as people. We try to read their faces, looking 
deeply into their eyes for humor or cruelty. We see in the scholar <PERSON>Johann 
Bodmer</PERSON>'s hawklike profile a keen intellect and summon up <PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON>'s 
mellowness from his relaxed and open gaze. Portraits provide a way to search 
for character and personality. It's a rewarding and timeless venture that makes 
history seem more about people than events. 
</P>
<P>
Yet for all the glamour of famous personalities, this exhibit is remarkably 
restrained, tucked away in an upstairs corner of the <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION> mansion like a 
bright, shy child. The images are small and sometimes so pale the viewer must 
look closely to catch the nuances in color and line. But the subtle charms of 
the doe-eyed illustrator <PERSON>Kate Greenaway</PERSON> and the impishness of artist <PERSON>John 
Linnell</PERSON> are worth looking for. 
</P>
<P>
The exhibition will be on view until <DATE>June 25</DATE> in the Changing Exhibitions Rooms. 
The <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION> is open Tuesdays through <DATE>Saturdays</DATE>, 1 to <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> and on 
<DATE>Sundays</DATE> by reservation. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, "William Wordsworth," by William Haines, from "British Portrait 
Drawings" exhibition. ; Photo, "Joseph Priestley," pencil and pastel by Hugh 
Douglas Hamilton, at Huntington Art Gallery. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Art Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880119-0064 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf: The Fabulous Faker </HL>
<AUTHOR> Lee Lescaze </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   It is one of romantic literature's most flamboyant images. 
The young poet, so beautiful and so talented, driven to swallow arsenic by a callous world, lies dead across his garret bed, his luxurious red hair hanging above a pile of torn manuscript scraps. 
Beauty, death and art! 
Hollywood would call it a socko finish. 

   As <PERSON>Helen</PERSON>'s face launched a thousand ships, so <PERSON>Thomas Chatterton</PERSON>'s death at 17 launched a thousand elegies. 
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keats</PERSON> and <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> sang his praises. 
French romantics joined in. 
Who else, after all, had so starved, suffered and died for art? 
And so young. 
<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> called him the "marvellous boy" and the phrase stuck in literary memory like a Homeric tag line. 

   Of course, <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON> was not only a poet, but also a literary counterfeiter who passed off a series of medieval-style poems as the just-discovered work of a 15th-century monk. 
In <PERSON>Peter Ackroyd</PERSON>'s brilliant, witty novel, the Chatterton forgeries and tragic death are at the core of a story that cuts back and forth across two centuries. 

   Suppose <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON>'s most audacious deception was not his fake poems, but his <DATE>1770</DATE> suicide? 
What if instead of dying on his garret bed, <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON> was a precursor of our century's tribe of disappearing men who, for more mundane reasons such as embezzlement, seemingly drop dead in one life only to surface sipping champagne in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>? 

   Suppose Chatterton lived on, not in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, but in an ever-widening world of forgery until he had created hundreds of poems under the names of recently deceased contemporaries? 
Names like Gray, <LOCATION>Akenside</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Churchill</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Blake</PERSON>? 
It would put scholars to work for decades reevaluating 18th-century literature. 
For the discoverer of the great hoax it would bring a measure of literary-world fame. 

   From such questions, <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> spins a fascinating web of questions, comic and otherwise, about literature and life. 
What is real and what is made up? 
What is original and what is imitation? 
What is valuable? 
What endures? 

   "Chatterton" (<ORGANIZATION>Grove</ORGANIZATION>, 240 pages, <MONEY>$17.95</MONEY>), which was a No. 1 best seller in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> last year, is so packed with lively characters, so gracefully written and so adept at mixing wit with learning that no potential reader should be intimidated by its literary source. 
In a page, <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> supplies all the background needed about <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON>'s short, desperate life and about <PERSON>Henry Wallis</PERSON>'s painting of the dead poet, using novelist and poet <PERSON>George Meredith</PERSON> as his model. 
The painting, in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Tate Gallery</LOCATION>, was made some 100 years after <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON>'s death, but it has set the image of <ORGANIZATION>Chatterton</ORGANIZATION>'s deathbed in the minds of generations. 

   Then, <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> sails into his lively tri-level invention, part exploration of <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON>'s 18th-century life, part 19th-century byplay among egotistical <PERSON>Meredith</PERSON>, romantic <PERSON>Wallis</PERSON> and adulterous <PERSON>Mrs. Meredith</PERSON>, and part contemporary comedy of failed poet <PERSON>Charles Wychwood</PERSON>, well-known novelist <PERSON>Harriet Scrope</PERSON> and their supporting cast caught up in efforts to track down what happened to <LOCATION>Chatterton</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> is an arch observer of his squalid contemporary scene, a world in which <PERSON>Vivaldi</PERSON>'s "Four Seasons" is background music equally at cremations and porn movies. 
Our century is no romantic age. 
Poets don't die pale and beautiful garret deaths. 
They collapse amid the chicken tikka, tandoori mutton and vegetable biryanis in a cheap Pakistani restaurant. 
And, when they rise to the defense of poetry, it is to carping wits eager to mock their eloquence with joking asides. 

   For <PERSON>Harriet</PERSON>, the novelist, old age and a degree of fame have brought her only a jaundiced view of the world. 
Gin-soaked, waspish quips (she mocks friend, foe and stranger alike) dominate her conversation; a desire to buttress her renown at any cost to others dominates her life. 
Characters are as stained as her sofa, but the sofa has an excuse. 
"You'd be stained, too, if you'd been sitting upright for two centuries," <PERSON>Harriet</PERSON> explains. 
Kindness is in short supply. 
"I've given my life to English literature," <PERSON>Harriet</PERSON> remarks. 
Her closest friend quickly jabs: "It's a pity, then, that you didn't get anything in return." 

   It is a world in which everyone plagiarizes, but some prosper while others stumble. 
Some live in fear of being discovered. 
Others blackmail their way to safety. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> keeps shifting the angle of vision, however, so that all is not despair. 
So what if life is full of imitation? 
If illusion triumphs over reality, what is wrong with that? 
Imagination can conquer grim surroundings. 
Memories can endure. 
Just as <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON>'s fame has long survived his squalid death. 

   Over everyone hovers the spirit of the poet who wrote in his diary: "The truest plagiarism is the truest poetry." 
Or did he? 
Is that his sentence, or another hoax? 
"Without words, there is nothing," <PERSON>Chatterton</PERSON> muses. 
True or false? 

   "Chatterton" is amusing and provocative. 
Only one warning label should be attached lest this novel prompt readers to seek out Chatterton's poems. 
He may have been a "marvellous boy," but the poetry is far from marvelous. 
Let <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON> speak for Chatterton. 
Remember Chatterton the way <PERSON>Mr. Ackroyd</PERSON>, whose inventiveness seems inexhaustible, reinvents him. 

   He saves a wonderful twist for last, one that suggests that in a world where events seem random, romantic legends may <DATE>spring</DATE> from anywhere, even from clumsy mistakes. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Lescaze</PERSON> is the Journal's deputy foreign editor. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900720-0097
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900720-0097.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   The Quintessential English Romantic
   ----
   By Roger Kimball
</HL>
<DATE>
07/20/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   To his lifelong friend Charles Lamb, he was "an archangel
slightly damaged." To his early disciple turned vociferous
critic William Hazlitt, he was a man "sunk into torpid,
uneasy repose, tantalized by useless resources, haunted by
vain imaginings, his lips idly moving." To almost everyone
who encountered him, Samuel Taylor Coleridge (1772-1834) was
a dazzling force of nature. Part poet, part orator, part
metaphysical seer, he was a wordsmith who invariably beguiled
his auditors with an unstoppable stream of brilliant,
intoxicating talk.
   The cataract of talk even reached into posterity. "He
seems not a man," wrote Virginia Woolf, "but a swarm, a
cloud, a buzz of words, darting this way and that,
clustering, quivering, and hanging suspended." Yet Coleridge
was much more than a fountain of words. As his biographer,
Richard Holmes, shows in his superlative account of
Coleridge's early life, "Coleridge: Early Vision" (Viking,
409 pages, $22.95), he was in many ways the quintessential
English Romantic.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   More than the grim and prosey <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, perhaps even
more than the flamboyant <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> or the ethereal <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> incarnated the spiritual aspirations of his age.
That he also incarnated its excesses and liabilities is only
too familiar. Coleridge the stalled writer, the irresponsible
dreamer, the shameless plagiarizer; <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> the opium
addict and burnt-out case: All that is as much a part of our
literary folklore as <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> the author of "Kubla Khan" and
"The Rime of the Ancient Mariner."
   In this first of two projected volumes, <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> takes
us from <ORGANIZATION>Coleridge</ORGANIZATION>'s birth at <LOCATION>Devon</LOCATION> to the eve of his
departure for <LOCATION>Malta</LOCATION> in <DATE>1804</DATE>. He chronicles, in other words,
the career of the visionary <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>: the radical utopian
schemer and poetic innovator who dreamed of a commune by the
<LOCATION>Susquehanna River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and who collaborated with
<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> on "Lyrical Ballads."
   He also writes of <ORGANIZATION>Coleridge</ORGANIZATION> the unhappy and perpetually
absent husband, the unrequited lover, the increasingly
despondent and drug-sodden waster. Still to come are
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> the great literary critic, the religious thinker,
the public philosopher.
   The youngest of 10 children, <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> found his bucolic
home life shattered when his father -- a learned minister and
schoolmaster -- died in <DATE>1781</DATE>. The young boy was promptly
packed off to school at <ORGANIZATION>Christ's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, a
brutalizing place that nonetheless provided him with a good
grounding in classics and, eventually, a scholarship to <ORGANIZATION>Jesus
College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> was ferociously precocious, able to read a
chapter of the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> when only three and blessed with an
extraordinary memory. But he proved to be a dilatory student
at best. Already at <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> his vacillating and irresolute
character was on full display. <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> duly reports the
"wild expenditure on books, drinking, violin lessons, theater
and whoring . . . alternating with fits of suicidal gloom and
remorse." "<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> was," he notes, "a man who could confess
spiritual despair at <TIME>midday</TIME>; and dine out brilliantly at
<TIME>midnight</TIME>."
   But in truth it was restlessness, not sloth, that was
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>'s besetting vice. Would that more of us were as
productive as he] Always a prodigious walker, he once covered
263 miles in eight days. He was capable of writing 76
newspaper articles in five months or composing 50 blank verse
lines of a translation of <PERSON>Schiller</PERSON>'s "Wallenstein" in a
single day.
   Yet he could not stay put. A planned three-month trip in
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> with the Wordsworths stretched on for 10 months. As
usual, his wife, <PERSON>Sara</PERSON>, remained impatiently behind with the
children, one of whom died while his father was away.
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> was as addicted to drawing up lists of impossible
works and projects as he was to opium. "He dreamed more than
he planned," writes <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON>, "he planned more than he
could execute {and he was} never still or concentrated for
more than a few weeks at a time."
   <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> does not attempt to excuse <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>'s
failings. But his enthusiasm for this damaged archangel
remains undiminished. Rather, like <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> himself, he
understands -- and lets us understand -- that "the hope of
recreating himself imaginatively out of the sense of failure
itself" early on became one of <ORGANIZATION>Coleridge</ORGANIZATION>'s chief spurs to
creativity and reflection.
   In this, <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> could not have been more different from
<LOCATION>Wordsworth</LOCATION>. While <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> was composing his great
Immortality Ode, with its vision of the past as a "perpetual
benediction," <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> wrote "Dejection: An Ode," meditating
on "A stifled, drowsy, unimpassioned grief,/ Which finds no
natural outlet, no relief."
   This account of the young <ORGANIZATION>Coleridge</ORGANIZATION> is a fit sequel to <PERSON>Mr.
Holmes</PERSON>'s magisterial biography of Shelley (<DATE>1974</DATE>). Perhaps its
greatest achievement is to have reminded us of how complex
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> was, how he managed to salvage an enlivening
passion even from disappointment and dissipation. "If he does
not leap out of these pages -- brilliant, animated, endlessly
provoking -- and invade your imagination," <PERSON>Mr. Holmes</PERSON> writes
in his preface, "then I have failed to do him justice." Few
readers, perhaps, will close this book unexasperated by
<ORGANIZATION>Coleridge</ORGANIZATION>'s foibles; I think none will come to the end
unmoved by his painfully expansive genius.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-8358</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EBTAMAFDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940219
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 FEB 94 / Books: Poet hobbled by passion - The work of Stephen
Spender, 85 this year
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL GLOVER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
DOLPHINS by <PERSON>Stephen Spender Faber</PERSON> and <PERSON>Faber</PERSON> Pounds 12.99 (Pounds 5.99
paperback) 46 pages
This month, the great cultural monument that is Sir <PERSON>Stephen Spender</PERSON> will be
85 years of age. It is now more than 30 years since the death of <ORGANIZATION>Louis
MacNeice</ORGANIZATION>, 20 since the deaths of <PERSON>WH Auden</PERSON> and C. Day <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> and 10 since that
of <PERSON>Christopher Isherwood</PERSON>. Spender, the last surviving member of that
much-memorialised generation of the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, has survived them all - and he
continues to write and review regularly to this day.
The poetry, however, has come very slowly. His last full collection, The
Generous Days, was published in <DATE>1971</DATE>; his Collected Poems of <DATE>1985</DATE>, though
containing some new works (including notable elegies to <ORGANIZATION>MacNeice</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Auden</PERSON>)
was largely a re-presentation - often drastically re-worked  - of older
material.
In 'Worldsworth', the best poem of his new collection, <LOCATION>Dolphins</LOCATION>, he records
his first brush with poetry. In <DATE>1916</DATE> the Spenders were obliged to leave
their home on the cliffs near <LOCATION>Sheringham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION> after two stray German
bombs fell nearby. The family decamped to a farmhouse near <LOCATION>Lake Derwentwater</LOCATION>
and it was there that Spender, then seven years old, heard his father
reading <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> in the garden. The vocabulary and the cadences of
romanticism became a life-long passion and it is a passion that has both
enriched and hobbled his poetry.
'Worldsworth' is just one of several autobiographical poems in this short
collection. Another, '<ORGANIZATION>Air Raid</ORGANIZATION>', captures a moment in <DATE>1941</DATE> when a bomb, that
'unreasoning fury from an enemy's vision of life', destroys the outer walls
of a house, turning what had once been private and inside - a bath, a
wardrobe, books, the telephone - into a public spectacle. All that "tender
sensitive life" has been thrown away.
Variants upon this observation are the over-riding theme of the collection,
no matter how widely it may seem to range in subject matter  - from memories
of the first and second world wars, through elegies for dead friends, to a
long poem which examines the explosive relationship between <PERSON>Rimbaud</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Verlaine</PERSON>. What can be preserved of the intensities of the inner life in a
world that seems hell bent on its own annihilation? The poet, according to
Spender, acts as a mediator between the uniquely private self and the world
outside us. There is a lived, shared reality which is both general to
everyone and unique to each person, and it is poetry's task to describe it.
Unfortunately Spender's abilities in this book are rarely equal to his
vision. '<ORGANIZATION>Air Raid</ORGANIZATION>' collapses at the end into cliche and verbal redundancy;
many of the other poems seem too casually written, as if they are little
more than notebook jottings. Only in the Wordsworthian blank verse of
'Worldsworth' do we find a sustained and excellent piece of writing from
beginning to end.
Sir <PERSON>Stephen Spender</PERSON>, cultural ambassador plenipotentiary, the memorialiser
of himself and his famous generation, journalist, editor, essayist,
university teacher and literary critic seems to have spent so much time
clinking glasses across tables and lurching from glittering lunch to equally
glittering dinner (anyone who doubts this should read his Journals
1939-1983) that it is a wonder he has had the time - or the powers of
concentration - to write any good poetry at all. The fact is, of course,
that he has written a little. But most critics would agree that he has not
achieved his life-long ambition to be a great poet. His more enduring
achievements have been elsewhere: as a writer of prose, for example, (an
autobiography, World within World, is his masterpiece). Here he has found a
way with words that is much more subtle, flexible and assured than most of
his poetry ever manages to be, marred as it so often is by a peculiar
stiffness and Shelleyan rhetoric. As a spokesman for liberal values, no
matter how hopelessly privileged the spokesman may at times seem to be,
<PERSON>Spender</PERSON> has also made his mark: to argue for the sacredness of the
individual and his impulses is, after all, one of the finest fruits of the
romantic movement.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890719-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-19-89 1231EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Olivier     07-19 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Olivier,0205</SECOND>
<HEAD>Actor's Ashes to be Entombed in Westminster Abbey</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The ashes of <PERSON>Laurence Olivier</PERSON> will be buried in
<LOCATION>Westminster Abbey</LOCATION> among monarchs, prime ministers and great artists
of past centuries.
   The Very Rev. <PERSON>Michael Mayne</PERSON>, dean of the church where <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s
kings and queens are crowned, said a public memorial service for the
actor would also be held in the abbey this <DATE>autumn</DATE>.
   No date for either event was announced, but <ORGANIZATION>Mayne</ORGANIZATION> said the burial
and placement of a memorial plaque would be some time after the
memorial service.
   Olivier, 82, died <DATE>July 11</DATE>.
   Two of the great actors with whom he was frequently compared,
<PERSON>David Garrick</PERSON> and <PERSON>Henry Irving</PERSON>, are buried in the abbey.
   Among other famous tombs in the former monastic church are
<PERSON>Geoffrey Chaucer</PERSON>, author of the ``Canterbury Tales''; the
lexicographer <PERSON>Samuel Johnson</PERSON>; the playwrights <PERSON>Ben Jonson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard
Brinsley Sheridan</PERSON>; and poets <PERSON>Robert Browning</PERSON> and <PERSON>Alfred</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lord
Tennyson</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>William Shakespeare</PERSON> is among the artists honored by a monument in
``Poet's Corner,'' but is not buried in the church. Others so
honored include <PERSON>John Milton</PERSON>, <PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Charles Dickens</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Thomas Hardy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jane Austen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>T.S. Eliot</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Emily</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Anne</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Charlotte
Bronte</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-5146</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIEAAAEBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930904
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 SEP 93 / Travel: Romantic inspiration in Somerset - Christian Tyler
heads west and discovers what influenced Wordsworth and Coleridge
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHRISTIAN TYLER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
TRY, YOU tireless travellers, to define what is meant by 'a sense of place.'
Is it a view, a sound, a smell, a state of mind? Poets describe it,
musicians too - and, of course, painters who work out of doors.
In a walled garden in the west of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, with a wooded slope of the
<PERSON>Quantock</PERSON> hills behind him and the <LOCATION>Bristol</LOCATION> Channel invisible below, the
painter <PERSON>David Imms</PERSON> is as attached to bits of the English terrain as any
Aborigine to his song-line.
He was born in the near north and lives in the east <LOCATION>Midlands</LOCATION>. But it is to
the south-west that he goes to paint: bodies in the landscape, bodies as
part of the landscape, bodies fertilising the earth. After a week on the
millstone grit of <LOCATION>Yorkshire</LOCATION> he is grinding his teeth. 'I think I am happier
on chalk soil', he said in the matter-of-fact way of one stating a
preference for, say, <LOCATION>Bournemouth</LOCATION> over <LOCATION>Bridlington</LOCATION>.
And he is right about travelling west. There is some primitive urge which is
satisfied by following the path of the sun. As you race down the motorway
the grease and smoke of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> are sloughed off, the sky expands, the light
and the air turn softer, the colours richer. The sea is perceptible long
before it becomes visible, and at sunset the clouds pile dramatically above
it to compose the mythical land across the water: Tir-na-Og.
In this walled garden in the west, part of the Alfoxton Park estate at
<ORGANIZATION>Holford</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>north Somerset</LOCATION>, the sense of place is overpowering. It is a warm
enclosure of reddish earth and brick, quartered by box hedges and planted to
bursting with vegetables, flowers and fruit. It is alive with flying and
crawling creatures not seen since the pre-chemical age. 'Organic' is the
word they use, but the word is too sterile.
The <ORGANIZATION>Mad Hatter of Alice</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wonderland</LOCATION> protested that to see what you eat is
not to eat what you see. In this instance the <LOCATION>Hatter</LOCATION>'s logic is faulty: you
may see (or paint) your cabbage in the morning and eat it that night. Around
the garden live other attendants of the dinner table: the Large Black pigs
(<ORGANIZATION>Pavarotti</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Domingo</PERSON>) behind the barn, chickens in the run, goats beside
the driveway and sheep grazing among the deer in the bracken above.
The landscape of Alfoxton Park inspired the early Romantic poets. Wordsworth
lived there in 1797-1798 with his sister <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>. At the same time <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>
occupied a cottage in <LOCATION>Nether Stowey</LOCATION>, three miles away, with his wife and
children. Their ghosts have in turn become imprinted on the place.
According to <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>, it was on one of their night walks that the Rime of
the Ancient Mariner was conceived and it was in one of the panelled rooms at
Alfoxton that <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> five months later recited the finished work to his
friends. Here, too, the poets collaborated to produce Lyrical Ballads.
Dorothy was an indefatigable diarist of <ORGANIZATION>Nature</ORGANIZATION>'s effects in this corner of
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. Her words, as well as suggesting images to the two poets, convey
their own innocently uncontrived sense of place:
'<DATE>April 2</DATE>: A very high wind', she wrote. '<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON> came to avoid the smoke
(she means, presumably, of poor <PERSON>Sara</PERSON>'s cramped kitchen); stayed all night.
We walked in the wood, and sat under the trees. The half of the wood
perfectly still while the wind was making a loud noise behind us. The still
trees only gently bowed their heads, as if listening to the wind. The
hollies in the thick wood unshaken by the blast; only, when it came with a
greater force, shaken by the rain drops falling from the bare oaks above.'
Rebuilt in <DATE>1710</DATE> on much older foundations, the house is now a hotel of
creaking floorboards, modest comfort and somewhat shambly decor; but it is
privately run, has an unfussily family feel to it - and wonderful English
cooking.
A sense of place can be learned by walking. But, as <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON> says, it has
also to be learned by sitting and looking. This seaward slope of the
Quantocks handsomely repays a <DATE>week-end</DATE>'s reflection.
Alfoxton Park Hotel, <PERSON>Holford</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bridgwater</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Somerset</LOCATION>, TA5 1SG. Tel:
0278-741211. Dinner, bed and breakfast: Pounds 48 per person (b &amp; b only
Pounds 38; two-day breaks Pounds 43 per day). Painting weekends (check
availability): Pounds 150 pp. Literary weekends: Pounds 120 pp. Closed
<DATE>December</DATE> to <DATE>March</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P79   Amusement and Recreation Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page IX
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010189-0051 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 123 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 1, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part 7; Page 3; Column 3; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1457 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ONE ENCHANTED DAY WHEN PETER RABBIT STIRRED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BOB O'SULLIVAN, O'Sullivan is a travel writer based in Canoga Park. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The names Flopsy, Mopsy and <ORGANIZATION>Cottontail</ORGANIZATION> have never figured very large in my 
adult vocabulary. Not that they weren't there. They were just too deep in 
memory for easy retrieval. 
</P>
<P>
Your average semi-macho guys, or even us everyday garden variety couch 
potatoes, just don't tend to hang onto those memories we formed before being 
checked out on two-wheel bikes. Unless we've had a refresher course. 
</P>
<P>
My wife and I recently had a refresher course. 
</P>
<P>
A few months ago, we were in the <LOCATION>Lake District of Cumbria</LOCATION> -- which is about hip 
high on the British Isles -- and having a pretty good time. There aren't a 
whole lot of places on this earth as pretty or as peaceful. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Many Lakes 
</P>
<P>
We were told there are 23 lakes. Someone else said there are 19, so I suspect 
the total number sort of depends on whether or not it rained recently. I do 
know that however many there are, they're in one of the most awe-inspiring 
settings. 
</P>
<P>
Mile after mile of rolling meadows, forests and mountains, their tops 
frequently lost in cloud. There are fields of wildflowers, waterfalls and about 
every green that nature's got. 
</P>
<P>
There are sheep -- armies of sheep, eating as fast as they can but never 
catching up with the growing landscape. And there's something else . . . a 
feeling that goes with the territory. 
</P>
<P>
Joyce and I were talking with <PERSON>Paul Carlin</PERSON>, a friend who'd come to the <LOCATION>Lake 
District</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to manage the <ORGANIZATION>Borrowdale Gates Hotel</ORGANIZATION> near <PERSON>Keswick</PERSON>. He 
grinned as we raved about the countryside, as proud as if he'd created it 
himself. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Visitors From All Over 
</P>
<P>
"It's truly unique, you know, and I know what you mean about the feeling," 
<PERSON>Carlin</PERSON> said. "People come to the <LOCATION>Lake District</LOCATION> from your <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, where lakes are common. 
</P>
<P>
"Even from <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>, whose mountains and lakes dwarf what 
we have here. And they're just as enchanted as everyone else. And I think I 
know the reason. It's not the lakes, you know." 
</P>
<P>
"What is it?" Joyce asked. 
</P>
<P>
"Well," <PERSON>Carlin</PERSON> said, "I'm almost afraid to talk about it." He leaned forward 
and lowered his voice. "It may be something left over from the Druids or 
<PERSON>Merlin</PERSON>'s time, but I think it's magic. I really believe there is a kind of 
enchantment here." 
</P>
<P>
We'd almost come to that conclusion on our own. You can't drive through the 
area without having that thought. We'd recently visited <ORGANIZATION>Dove Cottage</ORGANIZATION>, where 
<PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON> lived with his family. 
</P>
<P>
Though the cottage looks as if it's 300 years old, it's really kind of 
commonplace. The most unusual thing about it is that the children's rooms are 
wallpapered with newspapers. (The guidebook said <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> thought it would 
make the rooms warmer in the winter.) 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Setting Is Unusual 
</P>
<P>
But it's not the cottage, it's the setting that makes it unusual. When you see 
the view from the room where <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> did his writing, you begin to 
understand. 
</P>
<P>
You see <LOCATION>Lake Grasmere</LOCATION> cupped in rolling green hills, as still and reflecting as 
a mirror. The morning we were there, a few clouds were all but settling on its 
surface; you could feel a bit of the magic. 
</P>
<P>
There was no way a man of <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>'s talents could have lived in the area 
without becoming what he was -- a poet laureate, the greatest poet on nature 
that <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> has produced. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>? Yes," <PERSON>Carlin</PERSON> said. " 'Lucy,' 'The Solitary Reaper' and 'Daffodils' 
are very nice. And you'll never convince me that <PERSON>James Hilton</PERSON> didn't spend some 
time here before he wrote about Shangri-La in 'Lost Horizon,' but I was 
thinking more in terms of <PERSON>Peter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Flopsy</LOCATION>, Mopsy and Cottontail." 
</P>
<P>
"Who?" I asked. 
</P>
<P>
"Peter Rabbit!" Joyce exclaimed. "That's right! Beatrix <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> lived here in 
the <LOCATION>Lake Country</LOCATION>, didn't she?" 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Almost Missed House</ORGANIZATION> 
</P>
<P>
"That's what I meant by enchantment," <PERSON>Carlin</PERSON> said. "Her house is just down the 
way. I'll jot down some directions for you." 
</P>
<P>
It wasn't "just down the way" at all. It was a couple of lakes and a few dozen 
turns down a long road, but the trip wasn't a chore, because the country itself 
was satisfying. 
</P>
<P>
We missed the house the first time and had to backtrack. We'd have missed it 
again, except a small sign said, "Hill <ORGANIZATION>Top House</ORGANIZATION>," which my wife recognized 
from the stories. 
</P>
<P>
At first there didn't seem to be any true personality about the place. Slowly 
the lady herself, <PERSON>Beatrix Potter</PERSON>, began to take form as our guide walked us 
through the garden. 
</P>
<P>
"It's patterned after <PERSON>Mr. McGregor</PERSON>'s garden," she said. "Does that ring a 
bell?" 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Suddenly Interested 
</P>
<P>
It meant something to most of the visitors, including <PERSON>Joyce</PERSON>, whose interest in 
the garden was suddenly aroused. 
</P>
<P>
"Who's McGregor?" I asked. "Refresh my memory." 
</P>
<P>
No one answered. They were all listening as the guide led us into the house. 
She explained how Miss <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> had lived in an era that expected all proper 
young women to go from their father's house to their husband's. 
</P>
<P>
Beatrix, a very average-looking young lady who spent a good part of her 
growing-up years in the sparsely settled area, had been alone a lot. Having few 
callers and a great deal of time, she had taken to sketching and writing 
stories about the things she knew and loved, like the countryside and some of 
its inhabitants. 
</P>
<P>
One of them was a very young rabbit, whom she named <PERSON>Peter</PERSON>. It wasn't much of a 
story. It dealt with <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> leaving his siblings -- Flopsy, <PERSON>Mopsy</PERSON> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Cottontail</ORGANIZATION>, who were "good little bunnies" -- and going out and losing the new 
coat his mother had made him. 
</P>
<P>
He lost it when he was almost caught by <PERSON>Mr. McGregor</PERSON>, whose garden <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> had 
been told never to visit. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Limited Edition 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1902</DATE>, probably more on the strength of the sketches than the stories, a 
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> publisher took a chance and brought out a limited edition of "The Tale 
of Peter Rabbit." 
</P>
<P>
There were no limitations from then on. Beatrix <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> wrote and illustrated 
more than 25 children's books, which were published in dozens of languages, to 
the delight of millions of children. And then their children and their 
children's children. 
</P>
<P>
"Did <PERSON>Beatrix Potter</PERSON> have children of her own?" someone asked. 
</P>
<P>
"She eventually married a man named <PERSON>William Heelis</PERSON>," the guide answered, "but 
she was childless." 
</P>
<P>
A woman asked if Miss <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> had been able to enjoy any of her success, or 
whether fame had only come after her death. 
</P>
<P>
"She was a very canny lady who enjoyed huge success and made a great deal of 
money." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Purchased Land 
</P>
<P>
The tour group grew silent. 
</P>
<P>
"In fact," said the guide, "she loved the district so, that to have some 
control over what might happen to it, she began slowly buying up more and more 
property in the area to keep it from being destroyed by what the world calls 
'progress.' 
</P>
<P>
"In addition to her writing, she spent her time working to protect all of this 
part of <LOCATION>Cumbria</LOCATION>, to keep it pure and unspoiled for all time. Her efforts are 
largely responsible for the fact that this whole district is now under the 
protection of the <ORGANIZATION>National Trust</ORGANIZATION>. God willing, and thanks to <PERSON>Beatrix Potter</PERSON>, it 
may be protected forever." 
</P>
<P>
The tour ended and we left the house, a few feet behind a young family. As we 
entered the garden again, a bird flew out of the hedge just in front of us. The 
daughter of the family, a girl of perhaps 4 or 5, heard the rustling noise and 
turned quickly. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Thought She Saw Him 
</P>
<P>
"Oh, papa," she said excitedly. The mother and father stopped and turned. The 
little girl spoke excitedly to her parents in a language neither <PERSON>Joyce</PERSON> nor I 
could understand. Her father answered her and then smiled at us. 
</P>
<P>
"She wants to know was that <PERSON>Peter Rabbit</PERSON> who just came out of the bushes. I 
told her I didn't know because I had not seen." 
</P>
<P>
The little girl thought for a few seconds and then, nodding her head firmly, 
spoke again. Her father translated. 
</P>
<P>
"She says she thinks it was <PERSON>Peter Rabbit</PERSON>, that she thinks she caught a glimpse 
of him." The little girl ran around looking under rose bushes and behind hedges 
for another glimpse as we approached the gate cottage. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Interesting Theory 
</P>
<P>
Almost as a conspirator, the father shared a final thought with his wife and 
with us. "It probably was not really <PERSON>Peter Rabbit</PERSON>, you know. That rabbit would 
be 85 years old now." He winked. "Probably one of his children or his 
grandchildren, huh?" 
</P>
<P>
Carlin stopped by our dinner table in the hotel dining room that night and 
asked if we'd made it to <ORGANIZATION>Hill Top House</ORGANIZATION> and what we thought of his theory. 
</P>
<P>
"You didn't tell us what the lady had done for the district." 
</P>
<P>
"Or," <PERSON>Joyce</PERSON> said, "that it was <PERSON>Peter Rabbit</PERSON> that really started it all." 
</P>
<P>
"And, I'll bet," <PERSON>Carlin</PERSON> said, "that they told you <PERSON>Beatrix Potter</PERSON> never had any 
children, too." 
</P>
<P>
"You mean she did?" I asked. 
</P>
<P>
"The way I see it, she had millions of children . . . generations of millions 
of children," he said. "And didn't she leave them a lovely garden to play in?" 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Beatrix Potter at age 15, before her writing career blossomed. United 
Press International 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871103-0159 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
Time Off: Diversions and Excursions Nov. 3-16</HL>
<DD> 11/03/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
      ART
   <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION>: "<PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON> and the Age of English Romanticism" -- More than 300 Romantic works, including original manuscripts by <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keats</PERSON>, <PERSON>Byron</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON>, and paintings and drawings by Constable, <PERSON>Turner</PERSON> and <PERSON>Blake</PERSON>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Gottesman Exhibition Hall</ORGANIZATION>, Fifth Avenue and 42nd Street, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>. 
Through <DATE>Jan. 2</DATE>. 

   Tampa Museum of Art: "Dr. 
Seuss From Then to Now" -- This comprehensive retrospective exhibition traces the 60-year career of <PERSON>Theodor Seuss Geisel</PERSON>, the Pulitzer Prize winning author of such children's books as "The Cat in the Hat" and "Green Eggs and Ham." 
On view are about 300 drawings, illustrations and cartoons. 601 <ORGANIZATION>Doyle Carlton Drive</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
Through <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>. 

   Brooklyn Museum: "From the Land of Morning Calm: Korean Art at the <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> Museum" -- One hundred works from the Bronze-Iron Age (circa 350 B.C. to the birth of Christ) to the present, including painting, sculpture, ceramics, lacquer, metalwork, furniture and embroidery. 
Korean folk art, which is seldom seen outside <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, is also well represented. 200 <LOCATION>Eastern Parkway</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 
Through <DATE>Jan. 4</DATE>. 

   FESTIVAL
   Great Gulfcoast Arts Festival: The 15th edition of this community-sponsored crowd pleaser features a juried art show (in which more than 200 artists will vie for <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> in prizes), "crafts of the past" ranging from split-oak basket-making to blacksmithing, music and dance. 
And there's a separate youth festival. 
<LOCATION>Seville Square</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pensacola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>Nov. 6-8</DATE>. (904) 432-9906 or 438-8888. 

   DANCE
   Chinese Festival of Song and Dance: Twenty-eight dancers and acrobats from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in a program of traditional and contemporary folk dances and flashy acrobatics. 
Joyce Theater, 175 Eighth Ave. at 19th Street, <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> (212-242-0800). 
<DATE>Nov. 10-15</DATE>. 
The troupe's other stops are: <LOCATION>Champaign</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois Assembly Hall</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>Nov. 3</DATE>); <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Riverside Theatre</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 6-7</DATE>); <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> (<PERSON>Heinz Hall</PERSON>, <DATE>Nov. 17</DATE>); <LOCATION>Akron</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> (<PERSON>E.J. 
Thomas Hall</PERSON>, <DATE>Nov. 18</DATE>); and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Warner Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>Nov. 20-22</DATE>). 

   Tulsa Ballet Theatre: The Ballet Russe-inspired troupe presents a program including "Footage," <PERSON>Peter Anastos</PERSON>'s tip of the hat to <PERSON>Fred</PERSON> and Ginger; and "Polish Tribute to <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>," Polish-born artistic director <PERSON>Roman Jasinski</PERSON>'s salute to his adopted home. 
<ORGANIZATION>Tulsa Performing Arts Center</ORGANIZATION>, 2nd &amp; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tulsa</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>Nov. 14-15</DATE>. (918) 585-2573. 

   MUSIC
   <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> Opera opens its fall season with <ORGANIZATION>Puccini</ORGANIZATION>'s "Tosca." 
Maria Slatinaru sings the title role and Spanish tenor <PERSON>Antonio Ordonez</PERSON> makes his North American debut as <ORGANIZATION>Cavaradossi</ORGANIZATION>. 
Music Hall at <LOCATION>Fair Park</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>Nov. 5, 8</DATE>, 10 and 14. 
Also scheduled are <ORGANIZATION>Rossini</ORGANIZATION>'s "L'italiana in <LOCATION>Algeri</LOCATION>" with <PERSON>Marilyn Horne</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sesto Bruscantini</PERSON> (<DATE>Nov. 19</DATE>, 22, 24 and 28); <ORGANIZATION>Massenet</ORGANIZATION>'s "Werther" with <PERSON>Alfredo Kraus</PERSON> and <PERSON>Renata Scotto</PERSON> (<DATE>Dec. 3</DATE>, 6, 9 and 12); and <PERSON>Puccini</PERSON>'s "Turandot" with <PERSON>Johanna Meier</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ermanno Mauro</PERSON> (<DATE>Dec. 19</DATE>, 21, 23 and 27). (214) 871-0090. 

R.E.M.: The <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, guitar band's punchiest and
most commercially successful -- album thus far ("Document,"
I.R.S.) is drawing sellout crowds of both college kids and
those old enough to remember the guys who did this kind of
thing first -- the Byrds -- Madison, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Dane County
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 3</DATE>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> (UIC Pavilion), <DATE>Nov. 4</DATE>; <LOCATION>Champaign</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois Assembly Hall</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>; <LOCATION>Kansas
City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION> (Memorial Hall), <DATE>Nov. 8</DATE>; <LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Pershing
Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> (Fox Theatre), <DATE>Nov. 10</DATE>;
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 13</DATE>; <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>
(<ORGANIZATION>Bren Events Center</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE>; <LOCATION>Universal City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>
(<ORGANIZATION>Universal Amphitheatre</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>; <LOCATION>Tempe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Arizona
State University</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Gammage Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE>; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> (SMU,
<ORGANIZATION>Moody Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 18</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>College Station</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> A&amp;M),
<DATE>Nov. 19</DATE>; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Sam Houston Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 20</DATE>; <LOCATION>Oxford</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>University of Mississippi</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 22</DATE>; <LOCATION>Auburn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>
(<ORGANIZATION>Auburn University</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>Nov. 23</DATE>; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> (Fox Theater), <DATE>Nov.
24-25</DATE>, 27-28.
   Buckwheat Zydeco: Accordionist Stanley "Buckwheat" <PERSON>Dural</PERSON> and his merry band, which can be heard currently on "The Big Easy" soundtrack and a new <ORGANIZATION>Island LP</ORGANIZATION>, bring the rollicking sounds of <LOCATION>South Louisiana</LOCATION>'s dance halls to stages across the country. 
The gang will also be opening for some pretty hot acts -- U2 (at the <LOCATION>Orange Bowl</LOCATION>, <DATE>Dec. 3</DATE>, and <LOCATION>Tampa Stadium</LOCATION>, <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE>) and <LOCATION>Los Lobos</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>'s Universal Amphitheatre, <DATE>Dec. 13</DATE>) -- <LOCATION>Dearborn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Sully</ORGANIZATION>'s), <DATE>Nov. 5</DATE>; <LOCATION>Kalamazoo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION> (Club Soda), <DATE>Nov. 6</DATE>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> (<PERSON>Biddy Mulligan</PERSON>'s), <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>; <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION> (Headliner's), <DATE>Nov. 9</DATE>; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> (The Cabooze), <DATE>Nov. 10</DATE>; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> Nights), <DATE>Nov. 12</DATE>; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION> (Grand Emporium), <DATE>Nov. 13</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION> (Blue Note), <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE>; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> (Hard Rock Cafe), <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042089-0042 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 46252 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 20, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
676 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JACK SMITH: CONTRACTORS NEVER WORK SO QUICKLY FOR US 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Jack Smith 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>25th Pasadena Showcase of Design</ORGANIZATION> is supposed to open to the public <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, 
but if it does it will be a miracle. 
</P>
<P>
The house this year is a large <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> villa overlooking the <ORGANIZATION>Flintridge 
La Canada</ORGANIZATION> foothills. When I visited the site <DATE>a week ago</DATE> so many tradesmen were 
there I had to park a block and a half away. 
</P>
<P>
Landscapers swarmed over the five-acre estate, finishing pools and gardens. The 
new concrete court in front of the entrance was still wet. A plywood staircase 
was being built to handle the crowds. 
</P>
<P>
Inside, not a room was finished. Tile men were still at work in the kitchen. 
There were no seats on the dining room chairs. The grand music room with its 
20-foot vaulted ceiling was bare of furniture. Artists were still painting 
flowers on bedroom walls. A toilet sat in an upstairs hallway. 
</P>
<P>
The 9,000-square-foot house was designed by architect <PERSON>Henry Carlton Newton</PERSON> and 
built in <DATE>1924</DATE> for <PERSON>Harry G. Johansing Sr.</PERSON> and his wife, the former <PERSON>Mary Emily 
Farfsing</PERSON>, at a cost of <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Johansing was an insurance agent and sportsman. He and his wife had come here 
from <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>. They had four girls and three boys, who evidently had an 
idyllic childhood. The boys lived in one upstairs wing and the girls in the 
other, with their parents' master bedroom in between. The children used 
pull-down beds. 
</P>
<P>
The yard was their jungle. The boys had one enormous tree house and the girls 
another, with a drawbridge to keep the boys out. In the <DATE>spring</DATE>, when there was 
water in the creek, the boys followed it down to <ORGANIZATION>Devile</ORGANIZATION>'s Gate Dam and launched 
home-made rafts, much to the dismay of their mother. 
</P>
<P>
For the <ORGANIZATION>Showcase</ORGANIZATION>, a new formal Roman-style swimming pool had been built. The 
tennis court had been put in by the Johansings. They didn't have a pool, I was 
told, because their father had given the children a choice -- pool or tennis 
court, and they had chosen the court because they could use it for other 
activities. But as teen-agers and young adults they danced on a pavilion 
lighted by Chinese lanterns. 
</P>
<P>
A grand piano was yet to be placed in an alcove off the music room. It had once 
held a pipe organ that Johansing played for nightly musicals. His wife sang. 
The music room had also held a grand piano, a harp and a xylophone. Sometimes 
members of the Civic Light Opera came to sing, and a church choir used the room 
for practice while their church was being built. That's how the rich 
entertained themselves before television. 
</P>
<P>
The walls of the nursery, in which the children were kept, successively, as 
infants, were being decorated with hand-painted bluebells, delphiniums and 
Queen <PERSON>Anne</PERSON>'s lace; fairies at the top of the bedposts held a lacy canopy over 
the crib. 
</P>
<P>
I had received a letter from a landscaper, <PERSON>Leo Snider</PERSON>, saying he had installed 
an English trysting garden, and finding no suitable poem with "tryst" in it, he 
had written one himself and attributed it to <PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON>: 
</P>
<P>
 Speak soft but quick where we will tryst 
</P>
<P>
 Where arms were held and lips were kissed 
</P>
<P>
 By waters old, 'ere much he missed! 
</P>
<P>
 "My question," he said, "is whether it is illegal to so attribute a saying to 
another, and if so, is it so if the person is dead or only so if it is really 
awful poetry?" 
</P>
<P>
I found <PERSON>Snider</PERSON> at work in his garden. Beds of marigolds and white and purple 
petunias surrounded a small pool under a live oak. A nice place to tryst. I 
told him I didn't think <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> would sue, though he might turn over in his 
grave. 
</P>
<P>
The Showcase will be open to the public <DATE>Sunday</DATE> through <DATE>May 21</DATE>; 10 a.m to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> 
<DATE>Saturdays</DATE> and <DATE>Sundays</DATE>, 10 a.m. to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesdays, Thursdays</DATE> and <DATE>Fridays</DATE>. 
(<ORGANIZATION>Mornings</ORGANIZATION> are full.) Free parking and shuttle service from the <LOCATION>Rose Bowl</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Don't worry about its not being finished. The <ORGANIZATION>Pasadena Junior Philharmonic 
Committee</ORGANIZATION> and their hordes of landscapers and interior decorators somehow 
always manage to bring off this miracle. 
</P>
<P>
As for a poem with tryst in it, how about this: 
</P>
<P>
 By the petunias we will tryst 
</P>
<P>
 Under the live oak in the mist 
</P>
<P>
 I'm attributing it to <PERSON>William Shakespeare</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890811-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-89 1606EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ModularJail 1stLd-Writethru a0597 08-11 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Modular Jail, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0597,0813</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prefab Jail: Temporary Solution to Crowding</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 graf after 9th pvs, `Jim Wordsworth,...' to add detail
on size of containers, use. Picks up 10th graf pvs, `Abell, a...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA STOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LEESBURG, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The red building tucked away in the scenic
mountains of <LOCATION>northwest Virginia</LOCATION> looks more like a schoolhouse than
the nation's first prefabricated jail made from converted shipping
containers.
   New picnic tables in the back overlook a lush green field.
There's plenty of room outside the building for exercise or
picnics. But the building is being noticed for more than its looks.
   ``I think what these people are doing for prison construction is
equivalent to what <PERSON>Henry Ford</PERSON> did for automobile construction,''
said <PERSON>Richard Abell</PERSON>, assistant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney general for justice
programs. ``<PERSON>Henry Ford</PERSON> did not invent the automobile, but he made
it accessible. What these people are doing is making prisons
accessible.''
   <PERSON>Abell</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>Loudoun County</LOCATION> facility is the first of its kind
in the country. He said what makes this jail different is ``no one
has ever taken these shipping containers already made, and made
them into jails.''
   Surfside 6 Industries of <ORGANIZATION>McLean</ORGANIZATION> built the six-cell, 23-cot jail
in 13 working days for <MONEY>$96,398</MONEY>. That translates into a cost of
about <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> a bed.
   ``Ordinarily, it costs <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> per bed space, and it
generally takes two years to build a jail or a prison,'' <PERSON>Abell</PERSON>
said. ``These guys put it together in two weeks. That's beyond
revolutionary.''
   <PERSON>Abell</PERSON> said another advantage is the flexibility of the prefab
jails.
   ``Like Tinkertoys, they can be rearranged if they need to be
changed in five or 10 years,'' <PERSON>Abell</PERSON> said. ``If the needs have
decreased, they're not stuck with it on the landscape. You don't
have a problem like <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> has with <LOCATION>Alcatraz</LOCATION> _ a big massive
sore on the landscape.''
   <PERSON>Jim Wordsworth</PERSON>, secretary and treasurer of <LOCATION>Surfside</LOCATION> 6, said the
prefab building could be used as a shelter for the homeless or to
store records.
   Each steel shipping container is 8 feet tall, 8 feet wide and 20
feet long, <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> said. To convert it into a jail cell, the
container is insulated and a wall covering such as cement or
drywall is put on. The finished building uses traditional plumbing,
wiring and heating.
   <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> said the used containers are transported to <ORGANIZATION>Surfside
6 Industries</ORGANIZATION>' factory in <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and put together
there, then shipped to the location. He said they can be built on
site too.
   Abell, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Corrections
Advisory Board</ORGANIZATION>, said prison crowding has become a national problem.
   ``Between <DATE>1963</DATE> and <DATE>1981</DATE>, our crime rate soared <PERCENT>337 percent</PERCENT> in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and prison construction in the same period went
up <PERCENT>27 percent</PERCENT>,'' <PERSON>Abell</PERSON> said.
   <LOCATION>Loudoun County</LOCATION> Sheriff <PERSON>John Isom</PERSON> said there is a shortage of
about 3,000 beds in the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, area, and of about 1,900
beds in northern <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>.
   He said the maximum-security prison in <LOCATION>Leesburg</LOCATION> has 63 beds and
averages 100 people a day. He said he plans to move at least 23
people who are in work-release programs to the prefab jail when it
opens this month.
   But <PERSON>Isom</PERSON> said, ``Overcrowding will continue unless someone
figures out a way to eradicate the drug problem.''
   Crowding causes many problems, he said, including violence.
   ``We have inmate fights a couple of times a week,'' <PERSON>Isom</PERSON> said.
   While counties elsewhere have agonized over finding sites and
money to build large, future-oriented buildings equipped with
computer-controlled security and even robot food carts, <PERSON>Isom</PERSON> said
he was looking for a quick and inexpensive solution.
   He and <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> said the jail's security will be adequate.
<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> said a special welding torch would be required to cut
through the walls, made of Insulcrete, a patented concrete with
high insulation quality.
   He said officials from all over the country are calling about
the jail.
   ``It's unbelievable,'' he said. ``They're bringing the county
administrator, the director of finance, the sheriff to look at this.
   ``It's unique, it's portable, you can set it down and then move
the whole structure,'' he said. ``There is so much citizen unrest
on the location of prisons and jails ... They can assure the
citizens they're temporarily solving a problem until they go
through all of the rituals of building.''
   <PERSON>Greg Bogdan</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Bureau of Prisons</ORGANIZATION>, said
the bureau isn't opposed to the prefab idea, but says it isn't the
long-term solution to the crowding problem.
   ``They're suitable for emergency situations, but they're not an
answer to the long-term prison problem as far as the bureau is
concerned,'' <PERSON>Bogdan</PERSON> said. ``There is still a need for permanent
facilities.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-13639</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGRAKAEYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930717
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 JUL 93 / Books: Romantic whose roots reached deep into the stony soil
 -Michael Glover on the troubled life and misunderstood work of John Clare,
the 'Northamptonshire Peasant' and poet whose bicentennial falls this week
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL GLOVER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
COTTAGE TALES by <PERSON>John Clare Carcanet Pounds 9.95</PERSON>, 158 pages
JOHN CLARE: THE POET AND THE PLACE by <PERSON>Peter Moyse Crossberry Press</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Helpston
Pounds 11.95</ORGANIZATION>, 120 pages
UNLIKE many other poets of the English countryside <PERSON>John Clare</PERSON>, who was born
200 years ago this week, had a thorough-going knowledge of every aspect of
rural life and he wrote about it without sentimentality. Given his
background, this is not surprising. Born in the small village of <LOCATION>Helpston</LOCATION>,
then in <LOCATION>Northamptonshire</LOCATION> now in in <LOCATION>Cambridgeshire</LOCATION>, to parents that <PERSON>Clare</PERSON>
himself described as 'illiterate to the last degree', he worked at a whole
range of physical tasks as the occasion and the needs of the family
demanded: as corn thresher, ploughboy, gardener (at <ORGANIZATION>Burghley House</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Stamford</LOCATION>), lime-burner and pot boy at the local inn. And even when at the
height of his brief period of fame in the <DATE>1820s</DATE>, he continued to plough the
land.
His 'conversion' to poetry took place at 13. He was lent a copy of <ORGANIZATION>Thomson</ORGANIZATION>'s
Seasons, a sequence of vague pastoral encomiums that was much in vogue at
the beginning of the <DATE>19th century</DATE>. The book made <PERSON>Clare</PERSON>'s heart 'twitter with
joy'. By the time he had reached his 20s, his own verse had been brought to
the attention of <PERSON>John Keats</PERSON>' publisher, <PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON>, who released his first
collection of poetry in <DATE>1820</DATE>: Poems Descriptive of <ORGANIZATION>Rural Life</ORGANIZATION> and Scenes by
<PERSON>John Clare</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Northamptonshire Peasant</ORGANIZATION> - title fit to make a proud
provincial blench.
It was reprinted several times and <PERSON>Clare</PERSON>, on the wings of unanticipated
success, made several visits to distant <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, where he had his portrait
painted by <PERSON>William Hilton</PERSON> (RA) and was generally lionised, at the age of 26,
as the capital's newest literary celebrity. Unfortunately, the succeeding
volumes sold less and less well. Clare, it seems, was unable to meet the
general public's - and his own publisher's - incessant demands for novelty.
In fact, by the middle of the 1820s his publisher, once a helpmate, had
become a torment. Why was this so?
Clare was a poet who worked by his own lights, spelling and punctuating
exactly as he saw fit, and writing the kind of poetry that, in the opinion
of his publisher, would be less and less likely to find appeal in the
market-place. Unlike some of the other great Romantics - <PERSON>Shelley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>, for example - <PERSON>Clare</PERSON> was not a man accustomed to seeing
sermons in stones. What he saw were the stones themselves, all that hard,
flinty glitter, and he did his utmost to describe them with a particularity
unequalled by any previous poet.
The countryside that surrounds <PERSON>Helpston</PERSON>, a terrain of harsh, spare beauty
even to this day, is flat, with a great expanse of sky. It was <PERSON>Clare</PERSON>'s
ambition to preserve an honest record of it, and its customs, in the teeth
of the double despoliations of the Enclosure Acts and the advent of the
railways.
<PERSON>John Taylor</PERSON> attacked Clare repeatedly for using 'the language of common
everyday description' and for eschewing the pressing need to introduce an
element of human interest into his nature poetry. These were, after all, the
years in which the novel was coming into vogue. Poetry must be seen to
compete. Clare remained his vulgar self, obstinately inclined to write of
low rustic manners, doggedly refusing to soar into loftier regions.
Taylor cut his manuscripts ruthlessly, changed words, objected to the vivid
local usages that <PERSON>Clare</PERSON> felt most appropriate, and introduced an abundance
of punctuation so that the eyes of the middle-class country tasters from the
metropolis would glide smoothly from line to line and not be brought up
short by bewildering grammatical or orthographical idiosyncrasies. Nowadays
 -and it has taken this long for publishers to recognise that <PERSON>Clare</PERSON> was not
being deliberately wrong-headed and perverse when he chose, like <PERSON>Yeats</PERSON>, to
follow his own instincts - publishers print his poems just as he wrote them,
warts and all, and the lack of punctuation, we now see, helps to give them a
welling, teeming, gulping quality that adds to the richness of the poet's
own observations.
His later years were a protracted agony, the <DATE>last quarter</DATE> of a century being
spent in the <LOCATION>Northampton</LOCATION> asylum, where he continued to write, though now it
was poetry of a much more rootless kind. He had needed Helpston. Without the
familiarity of his home village, its sights, sounds and smells, he felt
wrenched up by the roots and tossed aside.
Two new books have been published to coincide with the bicentenary of
Clare's birth. Cottage Tales is a collection of narrative poems that <PERSON>Clare</PERSON>
intended to include in The <PERSON>Shepherd</PERSON>'s Calendar, his third book of poems;
<PERSON>John Clare</PERSON>: the Poet and the <ORGANIZATION>Place</ORGANIZATION> juxtaposes poems by <PERSON>Clare</PERSON> with
photographs of some of the places in and around Helpston with which he would
have been familiar.
The excellent <PERSON>John Clare Society</PERSON> can provide a list of bicentenary events
(sae please) upon request to: <PERSON>Peter Moyse</PERSON>, The Stables, 1a <LOCATION>West St</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Helpston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Peterborough</LOCATION> PE6 7DU.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XV
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900702-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-02-90 1556EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--AmyClampitt Adv15   07-02 1163</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Amy Clampitt, Adv15,1202</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, July 15</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ For decades she labored in obscurity, writing
the poems that no one would publish. Now at an age when most people
are considering retiring, <PERSON>Amy Clampitt</PERSON> has begun to attract
attention in the literary world.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ For decades she labored in obscurity, writing
the poems that no one would publish. Now at an age when most people
are considering retiring, <PERSON>Amy Clampitt</PERSON> has begun to attract
attention in the literary world.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL BEZDEK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ For decades she labored in obscurity, writing
the poems that no one would publish. Now at an age when most people
are considering retiring, <PERSON>Amy Clampitt</PERSON> has begun to attract
attention in the literary world.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880429-0017 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: Gilding the Lillies in Marvell's 'Garden' </HL>
<AUTHOR> Marie Winn </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Boswell</PERSON> asked <PERSON>Dr. Johnson</PERSON>, "What is poetry?" the great man answered, "It is much easier to say what it is not." 
Until a month ago one could have said with confidence that "The Garden," a difficult and beautiful poem by the 17th-century metaphysical poet <PERSON>Andrew Marvell</PERSON>, was not a poem about the interior of a fancy motor car. 
Now, however, according to fast-breaking developments in contemporary textual criticism, such a statement can no longer be made with certainty. 

   While <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON>'s most popular poem, "To His Coy Mistress," is clearly about a young man trying to persuade a reluctant beauty to go to bed with him, "The Garden" is more obscure in meaning, prompting great numbers of scholars to explore its tangled thickets in papers entitled "The Garden: <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON>'s Cartesian Ecstasy" and the like. 
Various schools of literary criticism have scratched at "The Garden" and described it as a poem exalting the powers of the imagination, a poem exploring the wellsprings of poetic inspiration -- that sort of thing. 
But they may have been hoeing the wrong row. 

   Recently, a variant text of "The Garden" has cropped up, so to speak, in a surprising new context -- a full-page advertisement appearing in millions of copies of Time, the New Yorker and the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times Magazine</ORGANIZATION>. 
The page shows the elegant interior of an expensive car. 
There, just slightly to the northeast of the leather-covered steering wheel, and west southwest of the burled walnut dashboard trim, are six lines from the second verse of the <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON> poem. 

   We know that these lines are by none other than <PERSON>Andrew Marvell</PERSON> because the name of the poet appears at the end where the author's name is customarily found in poetic quotations. 
We know that they are from "The Garden" because they are hauntingly similar to the verse we studied in school, the one beginning "Fair Quiet have I found thee here/And Innocence, thy sister dear?" 
But the text has undergone a weird metamorphosis: the word "comfort" has replaced "innocence" and the state of solitude once found "delicious" by the poet is now bluntly "luxurious"; thus a poem that once described a state of metaphysical bliss in which "a green thought in a green shade" surpasses all bodily pleasures, now seems to promote something cozy and sensuous, something that costs a lot of money, a wonderful British car, perhaps. 
But surely that isn't what the poet had in mind. 

   Well, that doesn't necessarily matter, according to <PERSON>David Greetham</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Society for Textual Scholarship</ORGANIZATION> and an English professor at the <ORGANIZATION>City University of New York</ORGANIZATION>. 
When asked how today's scholars might approach an altered version, <PERSON>Mr. Greetham</PERSON> described a form of advanced literary analysis known as Reception Theory, in which "authorial intention has no particular precedence. 
It is just one interpretation of many." 

   He goes on: "If, in the lines from <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON>'s 'The Garden,' the car manufacturers had determined that this line is imperfect in their own view of what was necessary, then they could argue that indeed they were merely perfecting the poem and that <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON> would see that this was a better version for this particular purpose than the one he had in fact written. 
It's certainly not an unprecedented condition. 
Many famous texts have been changed in the transmission in order to give more meaning to the original lines." 

   In this case, the "transmitter" of the new variant version of "The Garden" does not deny his role. 
"Yes, I am the copywriting culprit who dared to sully the works of the great English poets," cheerfully admits <PERSON>Martin Macdonald</PERSON>, creative director with the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> advertising firm of <ORGANIZATION>Hal Riney &amp; Partners</ORGANIZATION>. 
He has had his creative way not merely with <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON>, but also, in other ads, with <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert Lewis Stevenson</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Hamlin Garland</PERSON>, a poet who can hardly add a "British, upscale atmosphere" to the advertisement, (as <PERSON>Mr. Macdonald</PERSON> puts it), since he was born and raised in <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>. 
"I suppose <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON> are spinning in their graves, but in my defense I can only say that these poets are now getting a lot more visibility. 
I was actually expecting a bit of a hue and cry from the literary world," continues <PERSON>Mr. Macdonald</PERSON>, "but so far the only mild protest I've received was from a nice lady in <LOCATION>Teaneck</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, who really didn't seem too outraged at our small poetic license." 

   Not everyone in the literary world views <PERSON>Mr. Macdonald</PERSON>'s variant verses with equanimity. 
<PERSON>Cleanth Brooks</PERSON>, a pioneer of the New Criticism who is now emeritus at <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>, was less than charitable when the advertisement was pointed out to him, saying, "What they've done is really rather obscene, an appeal to the baser emotions in order to sell something." 

"Changing the word 'innocence' to 'comfort' is a dreadful comment on the trade-off between the real inspiration of <PERSON>Marvell</PERSON> and the debased standards that his lines are being twisted to uphold." 

   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Geoffrey Hartman</PERSON>, professor of comparative literature at <ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>, takes a more benign view: "I suppose they should have said 'With apologies to <PERSON>Andrew Marvell</PERSON>.' 
But I don't really consider it a very grave infringement of morality." 

   All the critics, however, seem to believe that the lines "transmitted" by <PERSON>Mr. Macdonald</PERSON> in his advertising campaign are somehow inferior to the version that appears in anthologies. 
But in defense of the Madison Avenue redaction, <PERSON>Mr. Greetham</PERSON> invokes that venerable principle of textual criticism known as "lectio difficilior," or the more difficult reading. 
Traditional editors of ancient writers used it to choose between variant readings. 
All things being equal, they chose the more difficult version on the theory that somewhere along the line of transmission, someone had simplified a text he couldn't understand. 
Lectio difficilior lives on, somewhat distorted, in the relativistic work of certain contemporary textual scholars. 
As <PERSON>Mr. Greetham</PERSON> puts it: "An author is more likely to produce an impenetrable reading than is the transmitter of that text. 
So if one has two readings, one of which makes sense and one of which does not, then the author's is the one more likely not to make sense." 

   Surely that is what <PERSON>Martin Macdonald</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Hal Riney Agency</ORGANIZATION> saw when he recast "The Garden." 
He had the wit to recognize that a green buck makes more sense than a green thought in a green shade. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Winn</PERSON> is a New York-based freelance writer. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111989-0021 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 136811 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 19, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 1; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2243 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LITERARY BRITAIN; 
</P>
<P>
EXPLORING SOUTHERN ENGLAND AND WALES, INCLUDING VISITS TO THE HOMES OF HENRY 
JAMES, WILLIAM WORDSWORTH, JANE AUSTEN AND THOMAS HARDY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By VIVIAN RINGER, Ringer is a Malibu free-lance writer. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LONDON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The chief glory of every people arises from its authors. -- <PERSON>Samuel Johnson</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> has produced more than its share of great poets and novelists, 
and it is easily possible to visit their homes, to walk the country lanes they 
trod, to stay in their towns and villages, which now abound with bed and 
breakfast signs . . . and to relive the scenes they described so vividly. 
</P>
<P>
Although guided tours are available, my husband and I found it more exciting -- 
and less expensive -- to strike off on our own, not knowing what adventures the 
day would bring, to discover the "scept'red isle" of our imagination that we 
first encountered in books. 
</P>
<P>
Last <DATE>summer</DATE>, after a rainy five days in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, we rented a car and headed 
south in search of sunshine and literary sites, staying where and when the mood 
willed. 
</P>
<P>
We agreed that our first destination should be <PERSON>Henry James</PERSON>' home, <ORGANIZATION>Lamb House</ORGANIZATION>, 
in Rye, <LOCATION>East Sussex</LOCATION>. It was a logical place to start, bridging the transition 
from <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> with the <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> expatriate who became a British 
citizen. Besides, we wanted to spend our first night with a view of the English 
Channel. 
</P>
<P>
After escaping the motorway to the quieter pace of a "single carriageway," we 
approached Rye with some dismay. This once-flourishing island town, one of the 
original Cinque Ports, was actually two miles inland, due to silting of the 
harbor in the <ORGANIZATION>16th Century</ORGANIZATION>. But the ancient hilly town, with its cobbled 
streets, was still delightful, despite the proliferation of souvenir shops. 
</P>
<P>
We stopped at a bookshop and inquired about a good place to stay and have 
dinner. The clerk suggested the <ORGANIZATION>Mermaid Inn</ORGANIZATION>, an old smugglers' haunt dating 
from <DATE>1420</DATE>. We took her advice and were charmed by the graceful decor, the many 
antiques and the mullioned windows. We ordered drinks by the huge fireplace, 
then treated ourselves to a traditional dinner of roast beef, jacket potatoes 
and <LOCATION>Yorkshire</LOCATION> pudding. 
</P>
<P>
Next we set out to explore the historic older section of town. Then, precisely 
at the opening hour of <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>, we wound our way up West Street to the top of 
the hill, where we confronted a solidly respectable, brick-fronted Georgian 
house. 
</P>
<P>
A tall door admitted us to a paneled entrance hall, where a woman at a desk 
accepted our admission fee. Her family was privileged to rent <ORGANIZATION>Lamb House</ORGANIZATION> from 
the <ORGANIZATION>National Trust</ORGANIZATION>, she told us, and it was with pride and a certain 
proprietary air that she showed the house to visitors. 
</P>
<P>
Naturally, we first wanted to see the study where <PERSON>James</PERSON> dictated his novels to 
his secretary. Alas, the <ORGANIZATION>Garden Room</ORGANIZATION> where he worked in <DATE>summer</DATE> had been 
destroyed by a German bomb in <DATE>1940</DATE>, but we were welcome to browse in the Green 
Room, his winter writing room. Adjacent to it was a bedroom known as the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s 
Room because <PERSON>George</PERSON> I occupied it in <DATE>1726</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Green Room</ORGANIZATION> was smaller than we would have thought and crowded with 
mementos, photographs and books -- reminders of <PERSON>James</PERSON>' company of literary 
friends: <PERSON>Joseph Conrad</PERSON>, <PERSON>H. G. Wells</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stephen Crane</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Ford Madox Ford</ORGANIZATION>, all of 
whom had homes nearby and were frequent visitors. 
</P>
<P>
As we wandered about the house and the walled garden with its paths and lawn, 
its flowers and fruit trees, it was easy to see why <PERSON>James</PERSON> had fallen in love 
with it. He wrote: "The quiet, essential amiability of <ORGANIZATION>Lamb House</ORGANIZATION> only deepens 
with experience . . . All the good things that I hoped of the place have, in 
fact, properly bloomed and flourished here." From <DATE>1897</DATE> until <PERSON>James</PERSON>' death in 
<DATE>1916</DATE> he wrote six novels here, among them "The Ambassadors," "The Wings of the 
Dove" and "The Golden Bowl." 
</P>
<P>
We thanked the current tenant, wishing we could trade places with her, but we 
had "promises to keep and miles to go before we sleep." The following day we 
saw <ORGANIZATION>Rudyard Kipling</ORGANIZATION>'s home, <PERSON>Bateman</PERSON>'s, another <ORGANIZATION>National Trust</ORGANIZATION> property, in 
nearby <LOCATION>Burwash</LOCATION>, another <LOCATION>East Sussex</LOCATION> village. 
</P>
<P>
The village had little to offer in the way of bed and breakfast, but we did 
find a farmhouse on the outskirts. The bed was concave, but no matter. We were 
served a rousing breakfast of bacon, bangers, fried tomatoes, toast and 
marmalade. After a hike through the countryside we drove the short distance to 
<PERSON>Bateman</PERSON>'s, arriving at the opening hour, 11 a.m. 
</P>
<P>
We were impressed by the tall-chimneyed stone mansion with its grand entryway 
and extensive grounds, where Kipling lived from <DATE>1902</DATE> until his death in <DATE>1936</DATE>. 
All this from the fruits of his pen. 
</P>
<P>
The living quarters were staid and unimaginative, unlike the man, reflecting 
solid middle-class respectability. 
</P>
<P>
Only in his upstairs study did he seem to take flight. There was his globe of 
the world, his maps, his books, his paintings, his guns, his sabers, his 
treasures from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. His view through large, leaded windows was of misty 
gardens and the countryside beyond. This was the ideal writer's workroom. 
Quiet, secluded. 
</P>
<P>
Our next destination lay to the west and promised a distinct contrast. After 
the vigor and thunder of Kipling, the international range of his writing, we 
were to visit the home of a quiet spinster who cooked and cleaned and sewed and 
rarely traveled beyond her tiny village. That such a confined life could 
produce elegant prose which ranks with the best in English literature is an 
enduring miracle. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jane Austen</PERSON> lived in a modest brick house in the <LOCATION>Hampshire</LOCATION> village of <LOCATION>Chawton</LOCATION> 
15 miles northeast of <ORGANIZATION>Winchester</ORGANIZATION>, where she wrote the final versions of her six 
novels from <DATE>1805</DATE> to <DATE>1817</DATE>. It bore little resemblance to the country manor we 
had imagined. Her bedroom was cramped, the other rooms unprepossessing. 
</P>
<P>
Standing in front of a smallish fireplace in the living room, it was impossible 
to conceive that here she had written her novels secretively on scraps of 
paper. 
</P>
<P>
She was buried in <ORGANIZATION>Winchester Cathedral</ORGANIZATION>. There, the brass tablet makes no 
mention of her novels, describing her only as the daughter of a respected local 
family. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Thomas Hardy</PERSON>'s cottage in the county of <LOCATION>Dorset</LOCATION> -- a half-day's drive west -- 
was next on our list, and we doubted that he would be recalled merely as the 
son of a respected local family. Quite the contrary. <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION>, where he lived 
and worked, and the neighboring hamlet of Higher Bockhampton where he was born, 
celebrate his genius with unabashed pride. 
</P>
<P>
There is a <LOCATION>Hardy</LOCATION> statue, a <ORGANIZATION>Hardy Room</ORGANIZATION> in the museum, guides to his imaginary 
county of <ORGANIZATION>Wessex</ORGANIZATION>. Hotels, restaurants and streets are named after the 
characters and settings in his novels. A <ORGANIZATION>National Trust</ORGANIZATION> gift shop overflows 
with his prose and poetry. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Max Gate</PERSON>, the home in <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION> where <PERSON>Hardy</PERSON> spent his mature years, is not 
open to the public, so we drove three miles northeast of the city to the 
cottage where he lived until he was 30. The approach from the car park was a 
10-minute walk through Thorncombe Wood to a picture-post card thatched cottage 
and a garden in riotous bloom. 
</P>
<P>
Hardy was born in <DATE>1840</DATE> in this house built by his grandfather, who, like his 
father, was a stonemason. Hardy walked to school in <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION>, which he called 
Casterbridge in his novels. 
</P>
<P>
At the age of 16 he was apprenticed to an architect and later pursued his 
architectural studies in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. After marrying, he moved to various towns to 
work on projects, finally returning in his 40s to <LOCATION>Dorchester</LOCATION>, where he died in 
<DATE>1928</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The interior of <LOCATION>Hardy</LOCATION>'s cottage is less attractive than the exterior. The rooms 
are small, with low ceilings. A steep staircase leads upstairs and, in a tiny 
bedroom overlooking the garden, is the deep window seat where he wrote "Under 
the Greenwood Tree" and "Far from the Madding Crowd." 
</P>
<P>
We took a different walk back to our car. Lazing along fragrant country lanes, 
passing houses with signs offering eggs, herbs and honey, we reveled in <LOCATION>Hardy</LOCATION>'s 
landscape. We were tempted to gather wildflowers, but they would wilt long 
before we arrived that evening at the elegant country hotel where, for once, we 
had made reservations. We were to be guests that night in the former home of 
<PERSON>William Wordsworth</PERSON> and his sister, <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
It was a circuitous route to <LOCATION>Alfoxton Park</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Holford</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Somerset</LOCATION>. In this 
handsome, two-story Queen <PERSON>Anne</PERSON> country house, <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON> began his great 
creative period in 1797-98. 
</P>
<P>
Amid 50 acres of woodland set in a hollow of the <LOCATION>Quantock Hills</LOCATION>, Alfoxton had 
everything. Even the modern swimming pool and tennis court did not detract from 
the tranquillity. Quince vines climbed the white walls. Herb and vegetable 
gardens flourished. Chicken, geese, pigs, sheep and cattle were raised in 
adjoining pens and fields for the hotel's kitchen. 
</P>
<P>
The bar was a wondrously inviting, dark-paneled room that had once been 
<PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>'s study. As the tables filled, a wispy elderly woman paused 
uncertainly at the empty chair beside us. We invited her to join us. 
</P>
<P>
She was a <ORGANIZATION>Bristol University</ORGANIZATION> professor researching a book on <PERSON>Wordsworth</PERSON>, and 
she regaled us with stories about <PERSON>William</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dorothy</PERSON>. They had moved to 
Alfoxton to be near <PERSON>Samuel Coleridge</PERSON>, who lived three miles away in Nether 
Stowey. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Coleridge</PERSON>'s cottage was now a museum, according to the professor. There he 
wrote "The Rime of the Ancient Mariner" and "<PERSON>Kubla Khan</PERSON>." It was a happy time 
for him, all too brief in his tormented life. 
</P>
<P>
Wales was our next stop. That mythic land of lilting voices, song and fable had 
long appealed to us and we were eager to explore the countryside described by 
its most famous poet, <PERSON>Dylan Thomas</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Caught in a twilight traffic jam in <LOCATION>Swansea</LOCATION>, we barely made it before dark to 5 
Cwmdonkin Drive, where the poet was born in <DATE>1914</DATE> and spent his first 20 years. 
