<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900218-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-18-90 2205EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AncientStatue     02-18 0163</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ancient Statue,0165</SECOND>
<HEAD>Excavators Dig Up Marble Statue in Pompeii</HEAD>
<DATELINE>POMPEII, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archaeologists unearthed a small marble
statue buried in the eruption of <LOCATION>Mount Vesuvius</LOCATION> in 79 <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION>, the
first such find in 13 years, newspapers reported <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The statue, which depicts a baby boy riding a dolphin, was found
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> of the <PERSON>Casti Amanti</PERSON>, near the center of the
abandoned city, <PERSON>Il Mattino</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> and other papers reprted.
   Archaeologists said the statue was apparently to be used to
decorate a fountain in the house, but that Vesuvius erupted before
workers had a chance to set it in place. Experts said traces of
paint coloring the hair blond and eyebrows black made the find even
more valuable.
   They believe the <ORGANIZATION>House of Casti Amanti</ORGANIZATION> was owned by a baker, who
lived on one side and kept a shop on the other.
   The last statue to be found in <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> was a bronze dug up in
<DATE>1977</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900203-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-03-90 1847EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-RobbedAntiquities     02-03 0295</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Robbed Antiquities,0301</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bandits Bind, Gag Custodians, Rob Treasures at Herculaneum</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NAPLES, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Masked gunmen bound and gagged unarmed
guards early <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, a Roman city destroyed when
Mount Vesuvius erupted in 79 <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION>, and stole hundreds of treasures,
news reports said.
   <PERSON>Baldassare Conticello</PERSON>, the superintendent of the archaeological
areas of <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> and nearby <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, said the inventory of the
stolen goods was still incomplete, the Italian news agency <ORGANIZATION>AGI</ORGANIZATION>
reported.
   The missing items included about 200 gold bracelets and
earrings, a first century bronze vase in the form of a woman's head
and a 32-inch silver-and-copper inlaid bronze statue of Bacchus, he
said.
   At least four bandits wearing ski masks surprised four night
watchmen at their station, <ORGANIZATION>AGI</ORGANIZATION> quoted investigators as saying. The
custodians were forced at gunpoint to turn over the keys to a
building that houses hundreds of artifacts, the news agency said.
   It said the custodians were tied up and their mouths taped with
bandages. After a few hours, one of the guards was able to free
himself and sounded an alarm.
   <PERSON>Conticello</PERSON> said sale of the stolen goods would be difficult
since they were cataloged. But he said it was possible someone had
commissioned the holdup to enrich a personal collection.
   <PERSON>Walter Mazzitti</PERSON>, the head of Archeoclub of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, an
organization of people interested in archaeology, decried what he
called a lack of adequate security at major ruins in the <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>
area and syggested that guards there should be armed.
   <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, along the Bay of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> and with the volcano at its
back, included the villas of wealthy ancient Romans. Its ruins,
discovered in <DATE>1709</DATE>, are considered better preserved than those at
the more extensive complex at <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, which was also destroyed by
<ORGANIZATION>Mount Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>' eruption.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06243033 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06243033 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PAST; VOLCANO; DEATH; HUMAN; BODY; FOUND; POMPEII; ITALY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Scientists have unearthed eight bodies in recent days at Pompeii, the first
human remains found at the site in at least three decades.;   Baldassare
Conticello, Pompeii's superintendent of archaeology, said Thursday that the
discoveries marked the first time that remains had been found at the rooftop
level of the ancient city.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  8 MORE VICTIMS FOUND AT POMPEII  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "These people managed to survive for several hours" after the disaster, he
said.;   <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> was buried under ash and stone after Mount Vesuvius erupted
<DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 79, killing thousands of residents of the city.;   <PERSON>Conticello</PERSON>
said one of the newly discovered victims appeared to have a basket on his or
her head. He speculated that the person had put it there for protection from
the hot ash.;   Two of the skeletons showed signs of fractures on their heads,
probably from falling objects or structures, he said.;   Some had pieces of
cloth around their mouths, apparently to keep from inhaling the suffocating
ash around them, he said.;   The victims were fleeing toward the <LOCATION>Mediterranean
Sea</LOCATION>, which reached almost as far as <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> at the time, when they apparently
succumbed to a new outburst by <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>, he said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Rome  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910830  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  20A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  188  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, August 30, 1991
00243033,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890718-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-18-89 0137EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--FireworksBlast     07-18 0106</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Fireworks Blast,0108</SECOND>
<HEAD>Explosion Rips Through Factory On Vesuvius Slope; Two Killed.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ERCOLANO, Italy (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An explosion that ripped through a
fireworks factory on the side of the Vesuvius volcano killed two
people, wounded three and produced panic in nearby towns, police
said.
   <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s explosion was heard up to a half-mile away and the
inhabitants of nearby hamlets thought the volcano was erupting,
authorities said. Several firetrucks and a helicopter arrived from
nearby <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> and doused the flames.
   Police said they did not know the cause of the blast.
   The victims were workers at the factory, which produced
skyrockets.
   Vesuvius last erupted in <DATE>1944</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900417-0096
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900417-0096.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Saving Pompeii's Rich Entombed History
   ----
   By Brigid Grauman
</HL>
<DATE>
04/17/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A20
</SO>
<LP>
   Naples, Italy -- They call it the Villa of the Chaste
Lovers because, in Pompeii, couples depicted in wall
paintings usually are engaged in more compromising activities
than the exchange of a kiss. Behind a corrugated-iron
partition, locked to keep out the curious, lies the villa,
the only building currently under excavation.
   The rooms of the large three-floor Roman house still are
filled halfway up with crumbling gray ash. On the ground lies
a rusty nail at least 1,900 years old. In what was once a
bedroom, tiny rabbits and birds are delicately painted on the
black and red backgrounds. In the center of each wall, in a
one-square-yard space, the lovers are reclining on their
beds, kissing. Their privacy has not been violated since
these frescoes were buried in 79 A.D. by lava and ash spewing
from Mount Vesuvius all over the towns and villages around
Naples.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   On that blazingly hot dawn in <DATE>August</DATE>, what sounded like a
clap of thunder filled the air and the sky seemed to shake.
Mount Vesuvius appeared to split open, and a hail of burning
stones pelted down, followed by ash that filled the eyes,
mouths and lungs of the terrified inhabitants. Within three
hours, the small trading town was completely buried under hot
ash. Very few people escaped, out of a population estimated
at 20,000. Still today, one quarter of the 27-acre site is
buried and may remain so for many years. This is not so much
a pity as a saving grace. As long as the houses stay
blanketed in ash, they are safe from the combined damage
caused by weather, weeds, wanderers and vandals.
   "<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> is dying," says <PERSON>Baldassare Conticello</PERSON>, the
Palermo-born archaeologist who has directed operations at the
site for the past five years. "I'm engaged in a battle of
wits against time and the various Italian ministries."
   Time is the more insidious foe. When the tougher surface
of the wall paintings starts to thin out, the brick-based
pigment blows away like dust.
   As for the state, <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> says between cigar puffs,
he spends his days trying to extract money from it: "The
<ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Cultural Heritage</ORGANIZATION> only gets <PERCENT>0.19%</PERCENT> of the
country's total annual budget and, out of those two billion
lira a year {<MONEY>$1.6 million</MONEY>}, <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> gets only a fraction."
<PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> estimates that, ideally, <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> would need at
least 500 billion lira {<MONEY>$406 million</MONEY>} to save it from
disaster. He may be far from that goal, but he hasn't lost
the fight, he says. "I wouldn't be here if I thought that.
I'm 57 years old and I'm not going to call myself a loser
yet."
   <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> lives with his wife and small daughter in
an apartment on the edge of the site, working a 12-hour day
to keep the city alive. He doesn't like <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>, and would
rather live in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, but he plans to stay. He recently
managed to get a <MONEY>35 billion</MONEY> lira {<MONEY>$28.4 million</MONEY>} sum out of
the government, and with it, he intends to restore the
buildings, pavements and streets from the Amphitheatre at the
east of the town to the Forum at the west.
   As the most recent in a dynasty of archaeologists
inaugurated in <DATE>1748</DATE> by an abbot from <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> who began digging
near the <ORGANIZATION>Temple of Fortune</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> wants to use the
latest scientific methods to restore the site and present the
clearest possible picture of the thriving port city as it
stood. "Most of my colleagues dream of the past in terms of
romantic ruins. I'm much more pragmatic. I like jet planes
and modern architecture. I want to rebuild the houses just
enough to save them, but no more than that. Every time you
work on an ancient site you damage it, and the gamble is to
work out how much you can damage in order to restore."
   With assistance from <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fiat</ORGANIZATION>, and a subsidy from the
<ORGANIZATION>Ministry of Labor</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> has been making a
computerized graphic database of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> over the past two
years. First 160,000 square feet of paintings were digitized.
Then, the 105 archaeologists working on the project, and
various computer experts, cartographers and architects,
turned their attention to the 8,800 papyrus scrolls
discovered in <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, now in the <ORGANIZATION>Natural History Library of
Naples</ORGANIZATION>. After photography, the gray-on-black lettering was
tinted purple and magnified to make it easier to read.
   Such computer models enable restorers to experiment
without fear of damaging the real work. On the site, however,
the workers as often as possible use stone and mortar, wood
and terra-cotta tiles, just as the ancient Romans did.
Earlier restoration techniques using reinforced concrete to
bolster walls and cement to restore paintings were "far too
brutal." The most urgent task, <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> believes, is
roofing. "You can't understand architecture if the roofs
aren't there." In the areas near the Amphitheatre and in
<LOCATION>Porta Marina</LOCATION> near the Forum the roofs are painstakingly being
rebuilt with wooden beams and, whenever possible, the
original tiles.
   The sidewalks and streets have been worn down by the feet
of the two million tourists who tramp through <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> every
year. Using another ancient method, <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> and his
team are rebuilding the sidewalks with "ciccio pisto", a
mixture of crushed terra cotta, mortar and volcanic stone.
"It acts as a sealant, protecting the houses from the
humidity that seeps up from the ground."
   <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, as <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> sees it, is not to be a
melancholy vision of ruins by <ORGANIZATION>Piranesi</ORGANIZATION>. He wants the Roman
houses to give visitors some impression of the community that
once lived here and to re-create the former border lines
between houses and gardens. With a botanist who is studying
the pollen and seeds as they were when trapped under the ash
on the day of the eruption, he can re-create the gardens
exactly as they were 19 centuries ago. They already have
replanted several gardens with vineyards and beds of violets
and roses.
   <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON>, who thinks of himself as an
archaeologist-cum-manager, has sworn that all the money gets
from the Italian state will go into restoration. But he would
love to start new digs in <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, the other
site nearby that was buried under lava, not ash. It covered
most of the ancient town under what is now many feet of hard
rock.
   <PERSON>Mr. Conticello</PERSON> is eager to create an international
foundation of businesspeople that would raise the money to
carry out the digs. "A single villa could yield more than 100
statues," he says. "Just imagine the prestige. We could build
a museum, something like the <ORGANIZATION>Peggy Guggenheim Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION>."
   Nowadays, when the night starts to fall, a wailing siren
warns visitors that it's time to leave <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>. They don't
need to be urged, says one of the 200 guards who patrols the
grounds. "For those who don't know it, <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> is scary at
night. They're afraid of ghosts."
   But the living still are very much the masters of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>.
Two men from the small modern village of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> just beyond
the walls amble in and out of the ruins, cutting tender,
edible dandelion leaves with their pen knives, stuffing them
into plastic bags, and singing a Neapolitan love song at the
top of their lungs.
   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Grauman</PERSON> is a free-lance writer based in <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-7440</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EHWDLAD0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940823
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 AUG 94 / UK Company News: Cookson in east European venture
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PAUL TAYLOR
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Cookson, the specialist industrial materials group, is forming a joint
venture with <ORGANIZATION>Thyssen</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> to manufacture and supply the central and
east European markets with special refractories and systems used in the
steel continuous casting process.
The joint venture agreement involves <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius International</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Cookson</ORGANIZATION>'s
Belgium-based subsidiary and <PERSON>Dolomitwerke Wulfrath</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Thyssen</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary.
Vesuvius will hold a 75 per cent stake in the new joint venture while
Wulfrath will hold the balance.
Both partners will inject their shares in their own existing east European
joint venture companies - <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius Czechoslovakia Trinec</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Ceramika
Wulfrath Skawina</PERSON> - into the new company. The local Czech and Polish partners
in the existing joint ventures will remain shareholders.
<PERSON>Mr Stephen Howard</PERSON>, chief executive in charge of <ORGANIZATION>Cookson</ORGANIZATION>'s group corporate
development and chief executive of the <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION> division, said the joint
venture would enable both <PERSON>Cookson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Thyssen</ORGANIZATION> to lessen the risk involved in
eastern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and to establish a closer working relationship.
The central and eastern European markets represent annual steel production
of about 170m tons with German production representing about 30 per cent of
this.
The joint venture will initially have sales of between Pounds 25m and Pounds
30m a year, but turnover and profits are expected to grow quickly as the
switch to continuously cast steel production takes place.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Vesuvius International.
    Dolomitwerke Wulfrath.
    Vesuvius Czechoslovakia Trinec.
    Ceramika Wulfrath Skawina.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
    DEZ  Germany, EC.
    BEZ  Belgium, EC.
    CZZ  Czech Republic, East Europe.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3297 Nonclay Refractories.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Strategic links &amp; Joint venture.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890118-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-18-89 0428EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Volcanoes Bjt   01-18 0650</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Volcanoes, Bjt,0676</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monitoring Of World's Killer Volcanoes Deemed Inadequate</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Embargoed for release 11 a.m. EST.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Volcanoes killed more people in the <DATE>'80s</DATE>
than during the previous 78 years, yet the deadly peaks are
inadequately monitored to protect 350 million people who live near
their slopes, a geologist says.
   ``We have to do a better job of studying the volcanoes of the
world,'' said <PERSON>Robert Tilling</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> geologist who
coordinated the agency's response to the <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens</ORGANIZATION> eruption.
   ``Existing methods of monitoring volcanoes are proving relatively
reliable. We just don't do enough of it.''
   Since A.D. 1000 more than 300,000 people died from volcanic flows
_ lava, pyroclastic or mud _ tsunamis and post-eruption starvation,
<ORGANIZATION>Tilling</ORGANIZATION> said in a summary of his remarks for today's annual meeting
   Mudflows from <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Nevado</LOCATION> del Ruiz killed at least 22,000
people in <DATE>1985</DATE>, while more than 2,000 perished in pyroclastic flows
_ blasts of hot gas, rock and ash _ from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>El Chichon</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1982</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Tilling</ORGANIZATION> said. Mount <LOCATION>St. Helens</LOCATION> left 57 people dead or missing.
   In <DATE>1902</DATE>, pyroclastic flows killed 29,000 near <LOCATION>Mount Pelee</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION>, 6,000 near <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> volcano in <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, and 1,560
in the eruption of <LOCATION>Soufriere</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Tilling</PERSON>, who is
based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   His count shows 13,080 more died during the six other deadly
eruptions this century: three volcanoes in <DATE>1951</DATE> and three others in
<DATE>1911</DATE>, <DATE>1919</DATE> and <DATE>1963</DATE>.
   An average of 50 of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s 600 volcanoes erupt each year, most
without fatalities, and the rate ``has not changed much in
historical times. But because the world population has exploded ...
to <MONEY>5 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the problem posed by volcanic and associated
hazards is greater now than ever before,'' he said.
   He said more than 350 millon people live on or within danger
range of volcanoes _ about <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
   ``We spend a lot of effort at a few volcanoes _ and we need to,''
<PERSON>Tilling</PERSON> said in an interview. ``But we're not applying existing
(monitoring) technology to more volcanoes, especially in developing
countries where the risks and hazards are the greatest.''
   And, he said, the most dangerous volcanoes are the least studied.
   Part of the problem, <ORGANIZATION>Tilling</ORGANIZATION> said, is that volcanoes erupt
infrequently compared with natural hazards such as earthquakes,
major storms, floods and landslides.
   ``However in populated areas, even very small eruptions can wreak
havoc and cause widespread devastation'' such as the Nevado del Ruiz
eruption.
   The mountain blew out only <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> as much ash as <ORGANIZATION>Mount St.
Helens</ORGANIZATION>' <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE>, explosion. But the tiny Colombian eruption
melted glacial ice, burying <LOCATION>Armero</LOCATION> and other towns under mudflows,
he said.
   Tilling urged an international effort to reduce volcano deaths.
The <ORGANIZATION>National Academy of Science</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> previously have
endorsed an international scientific effort for the <DATE>1990s</DATE> designated
the <ORGANIZATION>International Decade for Natural Hazards Reduction</ORGANIZATION>.
   To reduce volcano deaths, scientists must identify high-risk
mountains, study their geology to learn how often eruptions occur
and whether the eruptions were explosive, map the routes of killer
flows to identify danger zones, then install monitoring equipment
where necessary to listen for earthquakes, uplift and tilting, and
other signs of activity.
   Asked who should pay the bill for better volcano monitoring,
Tilling replied: ``There's the question.''
   Tilling said the 10 most deadly eruptions since <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 1000 were:
   _<LOCATION>Tambora</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <DATE>1815</DATE>, 92,000 deaths, including 80,000 from
starvation.
   _Krakatau, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <DATE>1883</DATE>, 36,420 killed by tsunamis, or
volcanic tidal waves.
   _<LOCATION>Mount Pelee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION>, <DATE>1902</DATE>, 29,000 dead.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Nevado del Ruiz</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, <DATE>1985</DATE>, at least 22,000.
   _Vesuvius, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <DATE>1631</DATE>, 18,000 killed.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Unzen</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <DATE>1792</DATE>, 15,190 tsunami deaths.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Etna</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <DATE>1169</DATE>, 15,000 fatalities.
   _Kelut, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <DATE>1586</DATE>, 10,000 killed.
   _Etna again in <DATE>1669</DATE>, 10,000 more victims.
   _Lakagigar, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>, <DATE>1783</DATE>, 9,340 lives lost.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-10184</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CG4BOAFJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920731
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 JUL 92 / Technology (Worth Watching): Taking the heat of molten steel
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PAUL TAYLOR
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
MEASURING the temperature of molten steel manually is dangerous and costly,
so <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius International</ORGANIZATION>, part of <LOCATION>Cookson</LOCATION>, the international industrial
materials group, has developed a new long-life sensor which can measure the
temperature of molten steel up to 1,8000C for more than 300 hours at a time.
'Steel companies throughout the world are trying to improve the quality of
their steel,'said <PERSON>Wolfgang Loser</PERSON>, president of the German-based Accumetrix
division of <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>.
'Our sensors will monitor the whole process, tell them second by second what
the temperature is and guarantee they produce the best quality steel.'
The new long life sensor, manufactured by the Accumetrix plant in <LOCATION>Beaver
Falls</LOCATION>,<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, is made out of platinum and rhodium and can measure the
temperature of more than 18,000 tons of molten steel being cast at the rate
of six tons a minute.
Vesuvius is also working on a new range of sensors, the size of a walking
stick, which will measure the sulphur, hydrogen,oxygen, phosphor and
nitrogen content of steel.
Vesuvius Accumetrix Division: <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,49 28 227140
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-17025</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EDGDVACUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940407
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 APR 94 / People: Grosso leaves Cookson
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Roberto Grosso</PERSON> is stepping down as an executive director of <ORGANIZATION>Cookson Group</ORGANIZATION>,
the specialist industrial materials group, and chief executive of the
ceramics division.
<PERSON>Cookson</PERSON> said in a statement that <PERSON>Grosso</PERSON> 'has decided to leave the group in
order to pursue other interests', and will do so after the annual meeting
next month.
Last month <PERSON>Cookson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Johnson Matthey</PERSON>, the precious metals group, announced
that they were planning to link some of their ceramic interests in a joint
venture to be known as <ORGANIZATION>Cookson Matthey Ceramics</ORGANIZATION>. Cookson's ceramic supplies
and minerals division, part of its ceramics operations, will be folded into
the joint venture.
Meanwhile, <PERSON>Stephen Howard</PERSON>, currently chief executive in charge of <ORGANIZATION>Cookson</ORGANIZATION>'s
group corporate development and chief executive of the engineered products
division, will also become president and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Cookson</ORGANIZATION>'s
Brussels-based Vesuvius advanced refactories group. <PERSON>Gian-Carlo Cozzani</PERSON>,
currently vice president of marketing and sales at <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>, will become
<ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>' chief operating officer.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Cookson Group.
    Vesuvius Belgium.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3339 Primary Nonferrous Metals, NEC.
    P3341 Secondary Nonferrous Metals.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
    PEOP  Appointments.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 13
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880226-0136 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-26-88 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Pompeii 1stLd-Writethru a0642 02-26 0188</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Pompeii, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0642,0188</SECOND>
<HEAD>Culture Minister Vows to Block Road Over Pompei Ruins</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to drop time element to 2nd graf.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s minister of culture says he won't approve
construction of a four-lane highway adjacent to <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>'s famous
ruins and across the ancient city's unexcavated necropolis.
   <PERSON>Carlo Vizzini</PERSON>, whose ministry protects and preserves
archaeological sites, said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that ``in no case'' will he
approve a project ``that not only edges, but minimally touches''
excavations at <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>.
   Some members of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>'s city government proposed reducing
traffic congestion in the modern city by linking two existing
highways with a new one streching a little more than a mile along
the famous tourist attraction.
   Opponents argue the exhaust and viabrations will damage the
ancient stones, and that the highway will prevent excavation of
Roman archaeological treasures in the necropolis.
<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Guiseppe Galasso</PERSON>, a member of Parliament from the town of
<LOCATION>Pozzuoli</LOCATION> in the shadow of the volcano, calls the highway proposal
``the kiss of death'' for the ruins.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-12126</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJ1C4AB5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931028
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 OCT 93 / Kaufman tells ITV chiefs of bleak future
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
ITV COMPANIES are living 'everyday life in <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> before Vesuvius erupts',
<PERSON>Mr Gerald Kaufman</PERSON>, the Labour MP, warned yesterday.
He told <ORGANIZATION>Yorkshire-Tyne Tees</ORGANIZATION> executives that the future looked bleak when the
rules governing ownership of television companies were relaxed to allow
hostile takeovers.
Chairing a Commons national heritage committee inquiry into the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>'s
future, <PERSON>Mr Kaufman</PERSON> said ITV companies needed to face reality.
'We are talking about minnows being swept away in a tidal wave,' said the
former shadow foreign secretary.
He suggested that ITV companies should merge with the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> and turn
themselves into software suppliers of programmes for the new age of
broadcasting which he said was just around the corner.
Currently, <ORGANIZATION>ITV</ORGANIZATION> chiefs are only dealing in millions of pounds when huge
multi-media foreign organisations are talking in terms of billions in
overseas sales, he added.
'And the overseas rivals will oust British companies on their own territory
unless they face reality,' he said.
'We are already seeing 11 per cent of the British TV audience belonging to
<PERSON>Mr</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Rupert</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Murdoch</PERSON> and that is before <PERSON>Mr Murdoch</PERSON> has got going and that is
before the technological revolution has arrived.'
<PERSON>Mr Kaufman</PERSON> foresaw a reasonable future for the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> and ITV only into the
early part of the next century - after that, he predicted, their audi-ence
levels would plummet.
'It is not a question of competing in the outside world, it is competing to
keep any kind of audience in this country when the new regime arrives,' he
said.
Giving evidence, <PERSON>Mr Clive Leach</PERSON>, Yorkshire-Tyne Tees chairman and chief
executive, said he refuted <PERSON>Mr Kaufman</PERSON>'s volcano analogy.
'We are aware that Vesuvius might be erupting and we want to get ourselves
organised in a planned and proper way and not be running around like scalded
cats frightened about what is going to happen,' he said.
<PERSON>Mr Leach</PERSON> asked for the moratorium, which blocks foreign takeovers of <ORGANIZATION>ITV</ORGANIZATION>
companies and which is due to end in <DATE>January</DATE>, to be extended.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7812 Motion Picture and Video Production.
    P4833 Television Broadcasting Stations.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Mergers &amp; acquisitions.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06136335 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06136335 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; EDUCATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ONE of the problems that parents face in trying to provide reinforcement and
enrichment for the lessons their children learn in school is that some of
those lessons deal with facts and theories that simply were not taught just a
few years ago.;    So parents must keep an eye out for ways to refresh their
own knowledge, and I try to make Family Learning a part of that process
whenever possible by sketching out a useful area of study and then providing
information about low-cost and no-cost learning materials that are appropriate
for use in the home.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Peninsula Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IT'S AN ERUPTION OF KNOWLEDGE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EAST6, EX4/5, WL3
Family Learning
Dr. William F. Russell's books for parents and children include Classic Myths
to Read Aloud.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     I am reminded this week of a theory in geology called "plate tectonics"
(tek-TAHN-iks), which was discussed only by scientists just a couple of
decades ago and now is taught in elementary and middle schools across the
country. This theory comes to mind right now because it helps explain an event
that happened just 11 years ago this week -- <DATE>May 18, 1980</DATE> -- the eruption of
the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> volcano known as <ORGANIZATION>Mount St. Helens.</ORGANIZATION>;    Historical value;    The
volcanoes we studied in school were consigned, for the most part, to history
classes, and, to be sure, there is a great deal of history to be learned from
them. The eruption of Mount Vesuvius (vuh-SOO-vee-us) in southern <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 79, for example, caught the people in the nearby city of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>
(pom-PAY) so much by surprise that many died where they stood, and the tons of
ash and rock that covered the city preserved it for nearly 1,700 years, giving
us our most accurate information about Roman life of that time.;    And this
Roman foundation to our knowledge of volcanoes was particularly important
because there are so many things that are associated with volcanoes that have
a Roman origin or connection. The word "volcano" itself derives from the Roman
god <ORGANIZATION>Vulcan</ORGANIZATION>, who was the blacksmith for the gods and who labored at his forge
deep inside a fiery mountain. The word "eruption" comes from the Latin word
meaning "to break out or explode," and "crater" is the Latin word for "bowl.";
   Lessons for today;    We didn't think of volcanoes and earthquakes as being
part of our time in history or our place on the planet. The Earth to us was
truly solid ground, or in the Latin phrase "terra firma." But today our
children are learning that that ground is anything but solid, and that
volcanoes and earthquakes are just the most violent outcomes of the slow,
constant and measurable drift of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> beneath our feet.;    The theory of
plate tectonics says that the surface of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, its 50-mile-thick crust,
is broken into several large, shifting slabs. Some of these slabs or plates
bump into each other, some pull away from each other, and some slide by each
other.;    It is at the edges or boundaries of these plates, then, that molten
rock from deep inside the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> can find its way to the surface. The Earth is
constantly reconstructing itself, and that is why the word "tectonics"
applies. It pertains to "building or construction" and is derived from the
Greek word for "carpenter.";    Map available;    The best visual display of
plate tectonics I have seen is a large (58- by 41-inch) map of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> that
plots all the major earthquakes and volcanic eruptions that have occurred
throughout history. These marks on the map occur all along the various plate
boundaries and form a stunning outline of the pieces in the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s fractured
crust. The map, titled "This Dynamic Planet," costs <MONEY>$3</MONEY> (plus <MONEY>$1</MONEY> for handling)
and is ideal for a classroom or bedroom wall.;    Send a check or money order
to <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>, Box 25286, Federal Center Building 41, <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>
80225. I suggest you request the rolled (rather than folded) version of the
map. There is also a free, 45-page pamphlet that the <ORGANIZATION>USGS</ORGANIZATION> has produced
explaining volcanoes and plate tectonics, which can be obtained by calling
1-(800) USA-MAPS and asking for the pamphlet titled "Volcanoes."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William F. Russell column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910515  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  701  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 15, 1991
00136335,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-14728</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CDEAFADIFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920404
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 APR 92 / Arts: Set free from its tomb of lava - Susan Moore on an
exhibition which opened in London this week
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By SUSAN MOORE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ON THE morning of <DATE>August 24</DATE> in 79 AD, <LOCATION>Mount Vesuvius</LOCATION> erupted. Pliny the
Younger, living in nearby Misenum, left a harrowing account of the awful
darkness that 'came rolling over the land after us like a torrent'.
Hit by showers of volcanic debris, earthquakes and asphyxiating gases,
<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, together with <PERSON>Oplontis</PERSON> and Stabiae to the east, were submerged
under pumice-stone and ash. To the west, <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> was engulfed by
volcanic mud that solidified to form a stone cover 10 metres thick.
These provincial coastal towns and cities of the Roman empire were
transfixed in the first century. They remained more or less undisturbed
until <DATE>1709</DATE> when a chance discovery in <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> prompted the Bourbon kings
of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> to start excavations to recover antique sculpture to adorn their
palaces.
When Goethe visited <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, the passages dug by the Bourbon
miners could be explored by lamplight, and the discoveries made there were
fuelling neo-classicism. Goethe wrote in <DATE>1787</DATE>: 'Many a calamity has happened
in the world, but never one that has caused so much entertainment to
posterity as this one.'
Archaeological research, restoration and maintenance at the Vesuvian sites
had been in decline since the <DATE>1950s</DATE>. Walls were crumbling and wall paintings
deteriorating. The sites would have deteriorated further if an earthquake in
<DATE>1980</DATE> had not jolted the Italian government into action.
In <DATE>1981</DATE>, an special archaeological administration was instituted for the
<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> area. By <DATE>1984</DATE>, it had substantial - although still insufficient -
funds and an energetic soprintendente in Professor <PERSON>Baldassare Conticello</PERSON>. He
has masterminded what he describes as a new philosophy for <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>; it
involves the collaboration of archaeologists, geologists, biologists,
botanists, geotechnicians, physicists and even a climatologist.
The bonus of computer expertise came when <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fiat Engineering</ORGANIZATION>
joined forces in <DATE>1987-89</DATE> to form the <LOCATION>Neapolis</LOCATION> consortium. It transformed the
project by setting up one of the largest ever information technology systems
for archaeology, to address the task of preserving, restoring and
interpreting <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>.
First, the whole 140 square-mile area was electronically mapped, to produce
a grid on to which other data could be added. That information included over
12,000 catalogue entries of individual finds, and over 8,700 digitised
colour images of wall paintings, mosaics and artefacts - thus preserving,
electronically at least, <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>'s most fugitive and precious treasures for
posterity. Excavation notebooks dating back to <DATE>1862</DATE> were committed to disk
and, like the <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> papyri, made more legible on the computer screen
in the process.
Imaging techniques were developed to simulate restoration of damaged wall
paintings, allowing restorers to experiment without touching the frescoes
themselves. Data on the function of each building has shed light on
<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>'s ancient social, political, religious and commercial life. At the
touch of a button, the computer reveals, for example, the existence and
whereabouts of a red light district, the distribution of shops and
workshops, or even take-aways.
On site meanwhile, <PERSON>Conticello</PERSON> inaugurated a systematic restoration of
<LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> from east to west, further excavations and a new museum. A series of
publications, exhibitions and concerts raised awareness of the area and
brought more visitors and, with them, public funding. Publishing the finds
has also protected them. The entire collection of bronze and gold stolen
from the deposit at <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in <DATE>1990</DATE> was recovered last <DATE>November</DATE>, because
thieves were unable to find a buyer.
The most ambitious and critical consciousness-raising exercise to date is
the spectacular travelling exhibition, '<ORGANIZATION>Rediscovering Pompeii</ORGANIZATION>'. It comes at
a time when digging has stopped and the computer is silent, awaiting a
second phase of funding. The show features 200 treasures and artefacts -
some only recently brought to light - and demonstrates the role of the
Neapolis technology in making the classical world more accessible. After
showing at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> (where is attracted over 350,000 visitors) and
<LOCATION>Malmo</LOCATION>, it opened in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> at the <LOCATION>Accademia Italiana</LOCATION> <DATE>this week</DATE>.
Ironically, the disaster that totally extinguished life in two days and two
nights in the first century also ensured a kind of immortality. Voices
resound in streets, houses, baths and open public spaces. Graffiti and
inscriptions record sporting triumphs and forthcoming fights, political
propaganda, and fierce expressions of love, hate and undying friendship.
Casts made from the cavities left by the fugitive Pompeiians make for
chilling death masks.
Most poignant are those of a family found sheltering in its home. Recently
excavated just outside <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>'s city walls, they show a man raised up on
his elbow to shoulder the roof timber that has fallen, cupping his hands to
cover the nose and mouth of his pregnant wife beside him.
In the exhibition, we find the highly defined contours of a lady from
Oplontis who took flight clutching a purse full of coins, rings and gems.
That little purse, and other items such as bone dice, a bronze colander,
bowls of carbonised olives, figs and prunes, speak as eloquently as any fine
marble, bronze or mosaic.
A surprising amount survives of gardens as well as houses. Botanists working
on the recent excavation of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> of the Chaste Lovers at <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> have
been able to determine the precise layout and planting (through pollens,
seeds and roots) of its formal inner garden. In time this will be
reconstructed; meanwhile a larger programme of replanting is under way. The
Pompeiian love of greenery is most vividly apparent in the enchanting
frescos of a recently excavated garden room that form the centrepiece of the
show, richly adorned with luxuriant naturalistic flora and fauna.
Pompeii was a thriving commercial city. Oplontis and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, in
contrast, were graced by the villas of the rich. The former boasts the only
surviving ancient wooden furniture (patterned by elaborate geometric
marquetry), and the fine wall painting at the supremely elegant villa
thought to have belonged to <ORGANIZATION>Nero</ORGANIZATION>'s second wife <LOCATION>Poppea</LOCATION>. A sequence of
open-air rooms, frescoed with abundant foliage and lined with flower beds,
eases the transition between garden and house.
The garden of <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>'s grand Villa of the <PERSON>Stags</PERSON> has supplied much of
the finest marble statuary in the show. Its '<ORGANIZATION>Drunken Hercules</ORGANIZATION>' is
characteristic in its robust earthiness. This Hercules is no conventional
hero. He is portrayed peeing, legs spread wide in a desperate attempt to
remain vertical.
'<ORGANIZATION>Rediscovering Pompeii</ORGANIZATION>', <LOCATION>Accademia Italiana</LOCATION>, 24 <LOCATION>Rutland Gate</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> SW7,
until <DATE>June 21</DATE>. Sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>IBM UK</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101589-0092 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 120832 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 15, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 5; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1013 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VOLCANO LOCKED MAYAN SETTLEMENT IN A TIME CAPSULE; 
</P>
<P>
ARCHEOLOGY: FOR EXCITED INVESTIGATORS, THE 1,400-YEAR-OLD CIVILIZATION IS A 
POMPEII IN EL SALVADOR. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM BOOTH, THE WASHINGTON POST 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
On a <DATE>June evening 1,400 years ago</DATE>, a volcano suddenly erupted in what is now <LOCATION>El 
Salvador</LOCATION> and sealed an entire prehistoric settlement in a time capsule, 
complete with the dirty dishes of a civilization that flourished 600 years 
before <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> arrived in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Buried beneath 15 feet of volcanic ash and extensively excavated for the first 
time <DATE>last summer</DATE>, the houses of the village of <ORGANIZATION>El Ceren</ORGANIZATION> are preserved in such 
exceptional condition that archeologists say the dwellings and their contents 
are as nearly intact as <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, the Greco-Roman city buried by the eruption of 
Mt. Vesuvius in AD 79. 
</P>
<P>
"No other site in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> has domestic architecture so well preserved," 
said <PERSON>Paul Amaroli</PERSON>, an archeologist at <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt University</ORGANIZATION> who has visited <ORGANIZATION>El 
Ceren</ORGANIZATION>. "It's hard to wear out superlatives on this site." 
</P>
<P>
The excitement over <LOCATION>El Ceren</LOCATION> stems from the fact that although monumental 
architecture such as Mayan temples and Aztec tombs are abundant in the area, 
well-preserved households of the peasants and commoners who built the 
ceremonial cities and carried out commerce and farming are rare. 
</P>
<P>
Even more precious are dwellings that have been preserved with the clutter of 
everyday life -- the garden tools, the pots and jars, even the dead ducks in 
the courtyard -- found in the same locations as they were that day 1,400 years 
ago when the volcano exploded. 
</P>
<P>
"They lived better than we had pictured them," said <ORGANIZATION>Payson Sheets</ORGANIZATION>, an 
archeologist from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Colorado</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boulder</LOCATION> who is leading the 
excavation of <ORGANIZATION>El Ceren</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We realize now that their domestic adobe architecture was much more 
sophisticated than we thought. The structures sit on big, fired platforms. 
They'd be dry even during the rainy season. The roofs were substantial. These 
were not people living crowded and huddled in a mud hut. Even their poorest 
houses were better than much of the rural houses in <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION> today. They 
really seemed to be fairly well off." 
</P>
<P>
In <ORGANIZATION>El Ceren</ORGANIZATION>, ceramic pots were found tucked into adobe niches where they were 
placed by the occupants. A digging stick leans against a doorway. A wooden 
pestle rests in a stone mortar. Enigmatic graffiti are still visible in one 
room. 
</P>
<P>
Two metates, the flat stones used for grinding flour, were discovered still 
resting on the forked wooden posts that supported them in use. Sharp obsidian 
knives, some with food residue still clinging to the blades, are wedged into 
the thatched roof, placed as if to be safely out of reach of children. 
</P>
<P>
And what may turn out to be the only book, or codex, as archeologists call 
them, to survive was found in a small cubbyhole beside three painted pots and 
an oyster shell. 
</P>
<P>
"Other codices survive from <LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION>, but they were all squirreled away 
someplace, hidden, and then ended up in collections. None of the codices are 
attached to a context. We don't know where they're from or who used them. . . . 
Here we have a book from an agricultural setting," said <PERSON>Harriet Beaubien</PERSON>, an 
expert in the conservation of antiquities at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION> Institution who is 
trying to preserve the painted codex found in a block of ash at <ORGANIZATION>El Ceren</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Mayan settlement of <ORGANIZATION>El Ceren</ORGANIZATION> was inadvertently uncovered by a bulldozer 
helping to construct grain storage silos in <DATE>1976</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Sheets was in <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION>, working at another site, and heard about the 
discovery of "recent houses" found under 15 feet of volcanic ash. Sheets said 
he expected the houses to be a hundred years old at the most. 
</P>
<P>
"I brought a trowel and went looking for <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> bottles, pieces of tin, plastic 
wrappers -- something that would date the structures," Sheets said. "Instead, I 
found a prehistoric pot. Well, I thought, these people must have had an 
interest in prehistory. I still didn't know what I was dealing with. Then I 
started finding more pots and I took some thatch samples for radiocarbon 
dating." 
</P>
<P>
Radiocarbon analysis of the thatch dated the structure about AD 600. Sheets was 
immediately intrigued, but even though he received funding from the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> to begin excavating the site, he said he did not think it 
was safe to bring colleagues and students to <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION>, which was then in the 
midst of a civil war. Sheets did not return to work in <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION> until last 
<DATE>summer</DATE>, when the first extensive excavations were begun. 
</P>
<P>
El <PERSON>Ceren</PERSON> was buried when a vein of basaltic magma from the nearby <LOCATION>Laguna 
Caldera Volcano</LOCATION> came into contact with water from <LOCATION>Rio Sucio</LOCATION>. The combination of 
super-hot magma and water created steam explosions that blasted clouds of hot 
steam and ash toward <PERSON>El Ceren</PERSON>, a village of still unknown size. The rain of hot 
ash sealed the village within a volcanic cast. 
</P>
<P>
To date, three extended households have been excavated, along with outbuildings 
and storerooms. Nearby were furrowed fields with rows of short, young corn 
stalks along each little ridge, leading Sheets to guess that the volcano 
erupted in <DATE>June</DATE>. The fact that objects like digging sticks and cooking pots 
were put away makes Sheets suspect that the eruption occurred at night. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dan Miller</PERSON>, a volcanologist with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Cascades Volcano 
Observatory</ORGANIZATION> who has studied the site, said he thinks there were several 
eruptions and ground shaking caused by volcanic earthquakes. 
</P>
<P>
"Once the eruptions began, it would be hard to get away. With the fall of ash, 
it would be pitch black. The hot surges would be very lethal. The temperatures 
of the clouds would at least be boiling," <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"There'd be hot, moist ash with larger chunks of rock sailing along or falling 
out of the sky. People would be scalded, their lungs would burn and they'd 
probably die of asphyxiation." 
</P>
<P>
Strangely, and with some disappointment, Sheets said that no human remains have 
been found in <LOCATION>El Ceren</LOCATION>. Residents who watched the bulldozer find the first 
household report seeing human bones and described shapes that might have been 
body casts. 
</P>
<P>
They have disappeared. Sheets expects further digging to reveal remains in one 
of the several structures still not fully excavated, or in a household yet to 
be found. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170130 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170130 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  VOLCANO; RELATION; WORLD; ENVIRONMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  VOLCANOES are one of the pivotal forces shaping the planet. About 80 percent
of Earth's surface is volcanic in origin, and gases escaping from volcanic
vents over hundreds of millions of years helped to create the atmosphere, said
Robert Tilling, a geologist with the U.S. Geological Survey in Menlo Park.;   
Some prehistoric eruptions were truly monstrous, said Peter Lipman, a
volcanologist at the survey. The biggest uncovered so far was an eruption in
the Rocky Mountains, about 27 million years ago, that was about 1,000 times
bigger than the current one at Pinatubo.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VOLCANOES HELPED SHAPE EARTH  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See related article on page 1E  </MEMO>
<TEXT>      The first volcanic observatory was set up on the flanks of <LOCATION>Mt. Vesuvius</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> in <DATE>1847</DATE>. But only after the turn of the century were seismometers and
other modern instruments used to keep track of volcanic activity.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Glennda Chui  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  137  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170130,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 0750EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   08-15 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0517</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wednesday, Aug. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the 237th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 79, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted,
burying the Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic
ash. An estimated 20,000 people died.
   On this date:
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and proceeded to set
fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a
non-stop flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> signed a non-aggression
pact.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was sworn in as the first
Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K. Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in
as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>. Both were from <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20
years to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John
Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic Archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: Leftist guerrillas who had seized the <ORGANIZATION>National
Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Managua</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>, released the last of their hostages
after the government freed 59 political prisoners and paid a
ransom. The guerrillas and the former prisoners were flown to
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: <PERSON>Corazon Aquino</PERSON>, widow of Philippine opposition
leader <PERSON>Benigno S. Aquino Jr.</PERSON>, returned to her homeland for her
husband's funeral, rejecting President <PERSON>Ferdinand E. Marcos</PERSON>' denial
that his government had any part in <LOCATION>Aquino</LOCATION>'s assassination.
   One year ago: A military jury in <LOCATION>Quantico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, sentenced Marine
Sgt. <PERSON>Clayton Lonetree</PERSON> to 30 years in prison for disclosing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
secrets to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 76. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 71. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 32. Actor <PERSON>Steve
Guttenberg</PERSON> is 30. All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 28.
   Thought for today: ``Nothing has really happened until it has
been recorded.'' _ <LOCATION>Virginia Woolf</LOCATION>, English author and critic
(1882-1941).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020490-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 171143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 4, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 7; Column 2; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
111 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WORLD IN BRIEF; 
</P>
<P>
ITALY; 
</P>
<P>
PRICELESS ARTIFACTS AT HERCULANEUM STOLEN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times staff and Wire reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Armed robbers stole at least 200 ancient Roman gold artifacts from a storehouse 
in the excavation site at <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, a popular tourist center. 
</P>
<P>
Police said two robbers climbed over the gates, tied up six guards and with the 
help of other robbers they let into the site, escaped with sacks full of gold 
bracelets, earrings and other trinkets dating from the <ORGANIZATION>1st Century</ORGANIZATION>. 
<LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION>, along with <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>, nine miles south of <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION>, was an ancient 
Roman city engulfed by ashes and debris from an eruption of the Vesuvius 
volcano in AD 79. Museum officials said the stolen artifacts are irreplaceable 
and therefore priceless, but would be difficult to sell. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ROBBERIES -- ITALY; ARTIFACTS; HISTORIC SITES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 1024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   08-14 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Aug. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>236th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 129
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Aug. 24, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
signed a 10-year non-aggression pact, each country pledging not to
``associate itself with any other grouping of powers which directly
or indirectly is aimed at the other party.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>A.D. 79</DATE>, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted, burying the
Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic ash. An
estimated 20,000 people died.
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and proceeded
to set fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a
non-stop flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, three days after Hawaiian statehood, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was
sworn in as the first Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K.
Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20
years to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John
Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: A 73-hour stand-off began at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kennedy
International Airport</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials prevented the takeoff of an
<ORGANIZATION>Aeroflot</ORGANIZATION> jetliner until they could determine whether Soviet
ballerina <PERSON>Lyudmila Vlasova</PERSON> was returning home voluntarily after the
defection to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of her husband, dancer <PERSON>Alexander
Godunov</PERSON>. (<PERSON>Vlasova</PERSON> was ultimately allowed to leave.)
   Five years ago: On the heels of the Republican convention,
Democrat <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON> said the proceedings had demonstrated
that President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> represented the party of the rich,
while <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> questioned <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s commitment to a strong defense.
   One year ago: Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
picked up the endorsement of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> while Republican nominee
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> campaigned in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 77. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 72. Former secretary of education <PERSON>Shirley
Hufstedler</PERSON> is 64. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 33. Actor <PERSON>Steve Guttenberg</PERSON>
is 31. All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 29.
   Thought for today: ``Posterity is as likely to be wrong as
anybody else.'' _<PERSON>Heywood Broun</PERSON>, American journalist and author
(1888-1939).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890824-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-89 0046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-History 1stLd-Writethru b0245 08-24 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, 1st Ld-Writethru, b0245, Adv24,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 3rd graf, `Fifty years ... other party,'' to clarify that
Aug. 24 was date of announcement. Original moved in advance as b0245.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>236th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 129
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Aug. 24, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
announced they had, during the night, signed a 10-year
non-aggression pact, each country pledging not to ``associate itself
with any other grouping of powers which directly or indirectly is
aimed at the other party.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>A.D. 79</DATE>, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted, burying the
Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic ash. An
estimated 20,000 people died.
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and proceeded
to set fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a non-stop
flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, three days after Hawaiian statehood, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was
sworn in as the first Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K.
Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20 years
to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: A 73-hour stand-off began at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kennedy
International Airport</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials prevented the takeoff of an
<ORGANIZATION>Aeroflot</ORGANIZATION> jetliner until they could determine whether Soviet
ballerina <PERSON>Lyudmila Vlasova</PERSON> was returning home voluntarily after the
defection to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of her husband, dancer <PERSON>Alexander
Godunov</PERSON>. (<PERSON>Vlasova</PERSON> was ultimately allowed to leave.)
   Five years ago: On the heels of the Republican convention,
Democrat <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON> said the proceedings had demonstrated
that President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> represented the party of the rich,
while <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> questioned <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s commitment to a strong defense.
   One year ago: Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
picked up the endorsement of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> while Republican nominee
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> campaigned in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 77. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 72. Former secretary of education <PERSON>Shirley Hufstedler</PERSON>
is 64. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 33. Actor <PERSON>Steve Guttenberg</PERSON> is 31.
All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 29.
   Thought for today: ``Posterity is as likely to be wrong as
anybody else.'' _ <PERSON>Heywood Broun</PERSON>, American journalist and author
(1888-1939).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-13467</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGSCZAD5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930719
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 JUL 93 / Observer: Floating asset
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
As the tall ships headed down the <DATE>Tyne this weekend</DATE> to race to <LOCATION>Bergen</LOCATION>, they
passed a send-off party thrown by a company claiming to be the only one that
plied its trade by sail from <LOCATION>Newcastle</LOCATION> which is still operating there.
Mind you, it very nearly wasn't, admitted <ORGANIZATION>Cookson Group</ORGANIZATION>'s American chief
executive <PERSON>Richard Oster</PERSON>, recalling <DATE>1990</DATE> when the industrially-diversifed
caboodle almost sank. Nor does he ascribe its recovery primarily to the new
managers who have taken the helm.
When they decided to go for a one-for-four rights issue earlier in the year,
he confided, they were a bit anxious about the outcome of an already
arranged shareholders' visit to the plant of their Vesuvius ceramics
subsidiary at Newmilns near <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>.
They became more anxious still when not only did institutional investors and
others representing more than half of the stock ownership turn up, but
<ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>'s UK chief <PERSON>Roger Brook</PERSON> blithely informed the visitors that nobody
from management would be showing them round the plant. Instead they were
divided into small groups and given a tour by shopfloor workers.
The moral was plain, <PERSON>Oster</PERSON> said. The rights issue was 96.3 per cent taken
up, and the rest of the shares readily sold. 'The workers did a better job
than the likes of me could have done,' added <LOCATION>Brook</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Cookson Group.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2819 Industrial Inorganic Chemicals, NEC.
    P3339 Primary Nonferrous Metals, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Company News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900710-0109
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900710-0109.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Timeoff: Diversions and Excursions July 10-23
</HL>
<DATE>
07/10/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A14
</SO>
<LP>
   ART
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   National Gallery of Art, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> -- "The
Sculpture of <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>" -- More than 130 objects from the
eighth through 15th centuries, the classical period of
Indonesian art. Works include Buddhist and Hindu stone
sculpture, bronzes, small figural objects of gold and silver,
and ceremonial objects. Of special interest is a life-size
<ORGANIZATION>Buddha</ORGANIZATION>, one of 504 made for the largest Buddhist temple ever
built, <LOCATION>Borobudur</LOCATION>. Fourth Street at <ORGANIZATION>Constitution Avenue NW</ORGANIZATION>,
through <DATE>Nov. 4</DATE>. The show then travels to <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s Museum of
Fine Arts (<DATE>Dec. 9</DATE>, 1990-March 17, <DATE>1991</DATE>); <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
Metropolitan Museum of Art (<DATE>April 21-Aug</DATE>. 18, <DATE>1991</DATE>); and <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>'s Asian Art Museum (<DATE>Sept. 28</DATE>, 1991-Jan. 5, <DATE>1992</DATE>).
                                                                                                       

   Art Institute of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>: "The <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Skyscraper:
Selections From the Permanent Collection" -- More than 50
drawings and models document the development of the
skyscraper in the <LOCATION>Windy City</LOCATION>. Included are drawings of
Murphy/Jahn's <ORGANIZATION>Northwestern Terminal Tower</ORGANIZATION> (1976-87); early
prints for <PERSON>Burnham</PERSON> and Root's Rookery; and fantasy drawings
from the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Architectural Club</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1983</DATE> competition to
redesign the tops of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> skyscrapers. Michigan Avenue at
<ORGANIZATION>Adams Street</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>July</DATE> 23-Dec.31.
                                                                                                       

   <ORGANIZATION>IBM Gallery of Science</ORGANIZATION> and Art, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>: "Rediscovering
Pompeii" -- More than 200 frescoes, sculptures, vessels,
games, articles of jewelry and everyday objects from
first-century <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION>. The exhibit also features more than 20
interactive computer programs enabling visitors to take an
electronic "walk" through the city's buildings, and see a
time-lapse sequence of the eruption of <LOCATION>Mount Vesuvius</LOCATION> in 79
A.D. 590 <LOCATION>Madison Ave.</LOCATION>, <DATE>July 12-Sept</DATE>. 15.
                                                                                                       

   <PERSON>Max Protetch Gallery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>: "Alan Sonfist: Art of the
Environment" is a 25-year overview of works by a
site-specific artist who does not inflict hostile piles of
rusting metal on squawking neighborhoods. The 20-some art
works include bronze castings of endangered oaks done for a
private estate outside <LOCATION>Florence</LOCATION>, and a series of collages
showing the process of his art, which often involves the
re-creation of historic landscapes. 560 Broadway, through
<DATE>July 27</DATE>.

   MUSIC/FESTIVAL
                                                                                                       

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Opera</ORGANIZATION>'s 34th season runs through <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE> and
features performances of <ORGANIZATION>Puccini</ORGANIZATION>'s "La Boheme" (<DATE>July 11</DATE>, 20,
30, <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>, 7, 14, 21 and 25); <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>'s "Cosi Fan Tutte"
(<DATE>July 13</DATE>, 31, <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>, 11, 15 and 24); <PERSON>Gluck</PERSON>'s "Orfeo ed
Euridice," with <PERSON>Marilyn Horne</PERSON> as <PERSON>Orfeo</PERSON> (<DATE>July 14</DATE>, 18, 27, <DATE>Aug.
4</DATE>, 8, 17 and 23); <PERSON>Strauss</PERSON>'s "Ariadne Auf Naxos" (<DATE>July 21</DATE>, 25,
<DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>, 9, 16 and 22); and East German composer <PERSON>Siegfried
Matthus</PERSON>'s "<PERSON>Judith</PERSON>," with <PERSON>Stephanie Sundine</PERSON> in the title role
(<DATE>July 28</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>, 10, 18). <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Opera Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION> (505) 982-3855.
                                                                                                       

   <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Chamber Music Festival</ORGANIZATION>'s 18th season runs through
<DATE>Aug. 20</DATE>. Highlights include: premiere performances of two
commissions by Pulitzer Prize-winning composers <PERSON>Ellen Taaffe
Zwilich</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ned Rorem</PERSON>; festival debut performances by the
Moscow-based <ORGANIZATION>Shostakovich String Quartet</ORGANIZATION> quartet; a piano
recital in honor of <PERSON>Aaron Copland</PERSON>'s 90th birthday; and
baroque compositions played on period instruments. <ORGANIZATION>St.
Francis Auditorium</ORGANIZATION>. (505) 982-1890.
                                                                                                       

   Festival d'Ete International de <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION>: The Italian
coloratura mezzo-soprano <PERSON>Cecilia Bartoli</PERSON> makes her North
American debut with a program of <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Rossini</ORGANIZATION> arias,
among them <PERSON>Sesto</PERSON>'s aria from "La Clemenza di Tito," and the
show-stopping "Tanti Affetti" from "La Donna del Lago." The
<ORGANIZATION>Quebec City Symphonic Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> is conducted by <PERSON>Simon
Streatfield</PERSON>. Grand Theatre de <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION>, <DATE>July 12</DATE>. (418)
692-4540.
                                                                                                       

   Mostly Mozart Festival: <PERSON>Ms. Bartoli</PERSON> then travels to
<ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Center</ORGANIZATION> to sing one of the master's concert arias, a
tune from "Cosi fan Tutte," and "Tanti Affetti." Jean <PERSON>Pierre
Rampal</PERSON> also appears on the program with a flute concerto by
<ORGANIZATION>Pleyel</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Gerard Schwarz</PERSON> conducts. <DATE>July 17</DATE>, 18.
   Mozart's comic one acter, "The Impresario," features
<PERSON>Frances Ginsberg</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sally Wolf</PERSON> slugging it out as rival
prima donnas and <PERSON>Vincent Cole</PERSON> as the frustrated producer.
This <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, with the <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> performance
telecast on <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION>. Alicia de Larrocha playing <ORGANIZATION>Mozart's Piano
Concerto</ORGANIZATION> in C major, K. 503, rounds out the program. <PERSON>Avery
Fisher Hall</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. (212) 874-2424.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-5159</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDPBVABZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910416
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 APR 91 / UK Company News: Cookson cuts borrowings by another Pounds
18m
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CLIVE COOKSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Cookson, the industrial materials group, has announced a co-ordinated series
of acquisitions and disposals affecting its business supplying the European
steel industry.
Net proceeds from the four deals will be Pounds 18m.
The announcement follows the group's successful Pounds 82.8m rights issue,
which it said on <DATE>Friday</DATE> was 96 per cent taken up by shareholders. The
combined effect of the rights and the recent deals will be to reduce
<PERSON>Cookson</PERSON>'s net borrowings from Pounds 330m to Pounds 230m.
Gearing, which was above 100 per cent when the group suffered a crisis of
confidence last <DATE>autumn</DATE>, will fall to 35 per cent.
Most important of the deals is the Pounds 23.7m sale of <ORGANIZATION>Cookson Plibrico
International</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>ILVA</ORGANIZATION>, the Italian state-owned steel group. Plibrico makes
furnace linings for steelworks and made operating profits of Pounds 2.9m
last year.
The other deals, which are worth less than Pounds 5m each, include the
acquisition by <ORGANIZATION>Cookson of Metacon</ORGANIZATION>, a private Swiss company which designs
slide gates for steel casting, and two acquisitions by <ORGANIZATION>Vesuvius Italia</ORGANIZATION>, an
existing joint venture of <ORGANIZATION>ILVA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Cookson</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06194004 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06194004 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Ron Reagan jokes about mom Nancy's biographer on 'An Evening at
the Improv.'  </CAPTION>
<LEADPARA>  (box) Commercial Broadcast; 7:30 p.m. The Making of Terminator 2: Judgment Day
CH44 Behind the scenes of the hit sequel.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HIGHLIGHTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> Verdict CH5 CH46 The trial of a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran, accused of killing a
neighbor, who says his wartime experiences as a Marine made him pull the
trigger.; <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME> 20/20 CH7 CH11 Stone <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> reports on the increasing
injuries sustained by children playing youth baseball and the call for safety
equipment.; (box) Cable; <TIME>8 p.m</TIME>. An Evening at the <ORGANIZATION>Improv A&amp;E</ORGANIZATION>. Host <PERSON>Ron Reagan</PERSON>
takes shots at mother <PERSON>Nancy Reagan</PERSON>'s biographer, <PERSON>Kitty Kelley</PERSON>, on this new
edition. He also introduces comics <PERSON>Judy Gold</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keith Robinson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Teddy Bergeron</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Jim Tavare</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mike Sullivan-Irwin.</PERSON>; (box) PBS; <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> National Geographic
CH60 Excavations at <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> reveal the devastation caused by <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Vesuvius</ORGANIZATION>' eruption in 79 A.D.; (box) <DATE>Friday</DATE> Talk Shows; 9 a.m. <PERSON>Sally Jessy
Raphael</PERSON> CH7 CH8 Battling couples.; <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> Geraldo CH11 Guests: <ORGANIZATION>Penn &amp; Teller</ORGANIZATION>.
(Also 4 p.m. CH4); <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> Donahue CH7 CH8 Discrimination and the Boy Scouts.;
(box) Radio; <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> KGO-AM (810) <PERSON>Ronn Owens</PERSON> Show: <PERSON>Gwen Bohnenkamp</PERSON> on pet
behavior.; <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> KNBR-AM (680) <PERSON>Peter B. Collins</PERSON> Show: <PERSON>Lewis B. Puller Jr.</PERSON>,
author of "Fortunate Son."; <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME> KPFA-FM (94) Doo-Wop Delights: "Women in
R&amp;B"  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Steve Marinucci  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910712  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  229  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 12, 1991
00194004,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111989-0117 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 137051 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 19, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Westside; Part J; Page 1; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
86 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AROUND THE WESTSIDE; 
</P>
<P>
J. PAUL GETTY MUSEUM: LOCATION: 17985 PACIFIC COAST HIGHWAY, MALIBU 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Millionaire oilman <PERSON>J. Paul Getty</PERSON> in <DATE>1954</DATE> purchased a large ranch-style home on 
65 acres in <LOCATION>Malibu</LOCATION>, in which he opened a museum to display art objects he had 
been collecting. As his collection grew, <PERSON>Getty</PERSON> built a new museum, designed as 
a reconstruction of a Roman seaside villa that was buried in an eruption of <LOCATION>Mt. 
Vesuvius</LOCATION> in AD 79. Completed in <DATE>1974</DATE>, the museum contains 38 galleries of art, 
including antiquities from <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, as well as <ORGANIZATION>Renaissance</ORGANIZATION> and Baroque 
paintings and French decorative arts. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, J. Paul Getty Museum 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-811</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CI0ADAAXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920926
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 SEP 92 / Books: Dips into history
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEPHEN AMIDON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE VOLCANO LOVER by <PERSON>Susan Sontag Jonathan Cape Pounds 14.99</PERSON>, 419 pages
FATHERS AND CROWS by <PERSON>William T.  Vollmann Andre Deutsch</PERSON> Pounds 17.99, 990
pages
THE PROMISE OF LIGHT by <PERSON>Paul Watkins Faber</PERSON> Pounds 14.99, 218 pages
IN A time when so many novelists are raiding the history books for subject
matter, you would have hoped that at least <PERSON>Susan Sontag</PERSON>, a writer
unsurpassed at tackling the major cultural questions of our time, would use
a foray into fiction to take an incisive look at the way we live now. No
such luck. Her third novel, The Volcano Lover, is a rich, intelligent,
historical romance that turns out to be little more than a prolonged
meditation on dormant themes.
The novel, set in the late 18th and early 19th centuries, tells the story of
Sir <PERSON>William Hamilton</PERSON>, his wife <PERSON>Emma</PERSON> and her lover <PERSON>Lord Nelson</PERSON>. Sir <PERSON>William</PERSON>
is the effete English ambassador to <LOCATION>Naples</LOCATION> whose main interests lie in
collecting art and studying <LOCATION>Mount Vesuvius</LOCATION>, active during his tenure in
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. After the death of his first wife he marries <PERSON>Emma Hart</PERSON>, a beautiful
yet coarse woman who in turn falls in love with <PERSON>Nelson</PERSON>, fresh from his
victories over <LOCATION>Napoleon</LOCATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION>.
I read the book in the hope that at some point it would erupt into
significance, that it would shed the quaint fabric of historical romance to
assume a more timely garb. But <PERSON>Sontag</PERSON> plays it pretty straight throughout,
using her skill to examine the political turmoil, aesthetic obsessions and
emotional dilemmas facing her largely frivolous characters.
It is a lively and erudite read, though nothing distinguishes it from the
glut of other recent novels that seem to grow more out of assiduous research
than any attempt to unravel the tangled knot of our times.
Another writer who has made good use of his library card is <PERSON>William T.
Vollmann</PERSON>. At 32, <PERSON>Vollmann</PERSON> stands as a living reproach to slothful young
writers everywhere, having already published something like 5,000 pages of
fiction. Fathers and Crows is the second in his seven-volume fictional
history of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>. It deals with the French Jesuits' conquest of
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and its indigenous population in the <DATE>17th century</DATE>, giving us tales of
a continent's worth of priests, explorers and native people, most
interestingly one <PERSON>Catherine Tekakwitha</PERSON>, an Algonquin convert beatified by
<PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
There is no doubting that <PERSON>Vollmann</PERSON> has a brain the size of <LOCATION>Saskatchewan</LOCATION>, and
that he is not afraid to have fun with history. He also possesses a
narrative skill that surfaces on occasion amid the welter of detail. But, in
the end, the book proves too dense a forest for the casual walker to find
his way through. The central narrative is complicated by numerous
geographical and temporal digressions, as well as enough personal and place
names to fill a phone book and an atlas. Strictly for the reader with a
specialist interest in the history of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, or those possessing a
Jesuitical temperament.
Another chasteningly productive young writer is 28-year-old <PERSON>Paul Watkins</PERSON>.
His fourth novel, The Promise of Light, is, like his earlier work, a
coming-of-age story cloaked in the guise of an adventure yarn. Set in <DATE>1921</DATE>,
it follows young <PERSON>Ben Sheridan</PERSON> as he travels from his native <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> after learning that the couple who raised him were not his real
parents. As he searches for his true identity he soon finds himself enmeshed
in the horrors of the Civil War, eventually forced to fight with the <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION>
against the Black and Tans. As in all <PERSON>Watkins</PERSON>'s work, the hero is forced to
undergo a bloody rite of passage before his true nature can be revealed.
<PERSON>Watkins</PERSON>'s writing is as terse and lively as ever, employing a precision that
is often cinematic, particularly in the combat scenes. Unfortunately, the
story itself is somewhat predictable and superficial, draining the taut
prose of much of its narrative drive. One gets the feeling both <PERSON>Ben</PERSON>'s and
<LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>'s searches for selfhood are little more than pegs upon which the
author hangs daring midnight raids and heroic slogs across the bogs. And the
ending is informed more by the ethos of the B-Movie than serious fiction.
Watkins is a talented writer who should perhaps think of changing to a less
frenetic gear.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890504-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-04-89 2352EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BadWriting 1stLd-Writethru a0790 05-04 0715</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bad Writing, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0790,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Literary Sting Exposes Wretched Writers</HEAD>
<HEAD>INSERTS 2 grafs after 6th, `For his...,' to UPDATE with quote, background
on winner.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEVE WILSTEIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JOSE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The would-be novels began badly and
turned worse before their first sentences thudded to an end,
laughable tributes to a once popular Victorian master of banality
and gratuitous polysyllabic prose.
   And those were the winners!
   The <ORGANIZATION>8th International Bulwer-Lytton Fiction Contest</ORGANIZATION>, sponsored
by the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State University English</ORGANIZATION> department, unleashed its,
uh, best entries <DATE>Thursday</DATE> from ``the seamy underside of
literature.''
   The grand prize from the nearly 10,000 execrable entries from
around the world went to <PERSON>Ray C. Gainey</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> for this bit
of amusing, albeit repulsive, imagery:
   ``Professor <PERSON>Frobisher</PERSON> couldn't believe he had missed seeing it
for so long _ it was, after all, right there under his nose _ but
in all his years of research into the intricate and mysterious ways
of the universe, he had never noticed that the freckles on his
upper lip, just below and to the left of the nostril, partially
hidden until now by the hairy mole he had just removed a week
before, exactly matched the pattern of the stars in the <LOCATION>Pleiades</LOCATION>,
down to the angry red zit that had just popped up where he and his
colleagues had only today discovered an exploding nova.''
   For his effort, <PERSON>Gainey</PERSON> gained a word processor, confirming the
computer age adage, ``Garbage in, garbage out.''
   ``My wife was jumping up and down when she called me at work,''
said <PERSON>Gainey</PERSON> in a telephone interview. ``They dragged me out of a
meeting. I thought somebody was dead.''
   <PERSON>Gainey</PERSON>, who enters as many as 30 items a year, said he won
dishonorable mentions in <DATE>1985</DATE>, <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The contest, founded by English professor <PERSON>Scott Rice</PERSON>, honors, as
it were, <PERSON>Edward George Bulwer-Lytton</PERSON>.
   Rice describes <LOCATION>Lytton</LOCATION> as the ``author of some of Victorian
literature's most turgid prose'' and notes that the ponderous,
meandering opening sentence to his novel, ``<PERSON>Paul Clifford</PERSON>,'' which
began, ``It was a dark and stormy night ...'' inspired not only the
contest but the famous literary beagle, <ORGANIZATION>Snoopy</ORGANIZATION>.
   The contest, which <ORGANIZATION>Rice</ORGANIZATION> calls ``a sneaky but enjoyable way to
encourage writing,'' invites insipid inkslingers to offer opening
sentences to the worst possible hypothetical novels.
   ``As anyone who has spent time on an entry knows, it takes a
good writer to write bad deliberately,'' <PERSON>Rice</PERSON> says.
   Here, then, are some of the deliberately bad winners, the creme
da dreck, in various genres:
   Detective Fiction _ ``Sgt. <PERSON>Tom Katt</PERSON> wasn't <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> sure of
anything but he knew something wasn't quite right when the factory
foreman told him that the nightshift guard had fallen into a vat of
baby oil and softened to death.'' _ <PERSON>Wayne D. Worthey</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   Historical _ ```Rumbling, Schmumbling!' retorted Bulonius to his
wife's alarm at the sounds coming from <LOCATION>Mt. Vesuvius</LOCATION>, `that stupid
volcano always makes noise _ and besides, our insurance agent at
<ORGANIZATION>Pompeii Mutual</ORGANIZATION> says that if it does erupt we'll be covered.''' _
<PERSON>John L. Ashman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
   Vile Puns _ ``As <PERSON>Wilbur</PERSON>, long obsessed though unfamiliar with
pointilism, escorted his wife, <PERSON>Katy</PERSON>, into the Modern wing of the
local art museum, he exclaimed jubilantly, `Kay, Seurat!, Seurat!,'
to which she replied, yawningly, `Whatever, <PERSON>Wilby</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wilby</PERSON>.' '' _
<PERSON>Matthew Kaslow</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   Western _ ``<PERSON>Sheriff Blalock</PERSON> groped for his shooting iron, as the
thought that he was up for re-election crossed his mind, because he
wasn't going to let this varmint get away with insulting Miss
<ORGANIZATION>Beulah</ORGANIZATION>'s girls, even if they did kind of resemble a string of
horses that had been rode hard and put away wet.'' _ <PERSON>Lucile R.
Addington</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>.
   Romance _ ``Jake liked his women the way he liked his kiwi
fruit: sweet yet tart, firm-fleshed yet yielding to the touch, and
covered with short brown fuzzy hair.'' _ <PERSON>Gretchen Schmidt</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Coral
Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Adventure _ ``It was the third day of the Iditarod sled race,
and a frigid wind blew ice crystals into <PERSON>Preston</PERSON>'s grizzled,
windburned face as he urged his dogs on: `Mush! Let's go, <PERSON>Jason</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Jennifer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jeremy!</PERSON> Move it out, <LOCATION>Chelsea</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Brian!</PERSON> Come on, <LOCATION>Buffy</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Muffy!</PERSON> Mush!'' _ <PERSON>Michael J. Saxton</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Davis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890621-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-21-89 0041EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-APainting'sValue     06-21 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-A Painting's Value,0298</SECOND>
<HEAD>Canvas that Cost $8 in 1956 Sells for $150,000</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 19th-century painting set in ancient <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> of a
young woman about to bathe has been sold at auction for <MONEY>$153,450</MONEY> _
nearly 20,000 times its <DATE>1956</DATE> purchase price of <MONEY>$8</MONEY>.
   ``It certainly does reflect an extraordinary change in taste, but
that isn't unique in art,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Simon Taylor</PERSON> after the
sale <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> of ``Diadumene'' by Sir <PERSON>Edward Poynter</PERSON>.
   The auction house had expected more because of the vogue for
once-neglected Victorian works. It had estimated the painting would
fetch up to <MONEY>$232,500</MONEY>.
   Poynter, in <DATE>1885</DATE>, had painted the young woman nude but he added
diaphanous drapery after it was exhibited at the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Academy of
Arts</ORGANIZATION> and provoked letters from shocked viewers.
   One letter to the press, signed ``British Matron,'' said the
writer had barred her daughters from going to the the exhibition.
Another letter said the painting would produce a ``burning sense of
shame'' in any ``modest woman on the arm of father, brother or
lover.''
   Poynter was known for such paintings but his most famous work,
reproduced in the tens of thousands in its day, was ``Faithful unto
Death.'' It depicted a Roman sentry staying at his post during the
destruction of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> by the Vesuvius volcano.
   The seller and buyer of ``Diadumene'' were not identified.
   The painting had been auctioned in <DATE>1956</DATE> at a sale of the contents
of <PERSON>Ashley Manor</PERSON>, owned by Lady <PERSON>Agnes Chichester</PERSON> Dixon-Hartland.
   Top price at <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s auction of <DATE>19th century</DATE> European art was
<MONEY>$2.3 million</MONEY> _ more than double the estimate _ paid anonymously for
``Grandfather's Birthday,'' a family fireside scene by Austrian
artist <PERSON>Ferdinand Georg Waldmueller</PERSON>. It was a record for his work.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880727-0033 </DOCNO>
<HL> Italy Gets Back Six Stolen Artworks Found Last Year </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP </CO>
<DATELINE> ROME (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six stolen artworks discovered a year ago hidden in the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> home of an Italian have been returned to <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Ministry</ORGANIZATION> announced yesterday. 

   A 15th-century triptych by <PERSON>Gabriele di Francesco</PERSON> was among the works. 
The painting, in three side-by-side panels, was stolen in <DATE>1985</DATE> from the altar of the Cathedral of Roniglione, 33 miles north of <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. 

   A 15th-century painting by <PERSON>Francesco Raibolini</PERSON>, three 17th-century compasses with ivory cases, and <PERSON>Francesco Netti</PERSON>'s <DATE>1800</DATE> "Procession of Penance During the <DATE>1794</DATE> Eruption of Vesuvius" also were recovered. 
They were stolen from <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> between <DATE>June 1983</DATE> and <DATE>August 1984</DATE>. 

   The Italian news, <ORGANIZATION>ANSA</ORGANIZATION>, said the works were found in the home of <ORGANIZATION>Giambattista Ongaro</ORGANIZATION>. 
It quoted ministry officials as saying several other works that had been exported illegally from <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> also were found in the home. 

   No charges were filed against <PERSON>Mr. Ongaro</PERSON>. 
The ministry said there is no evidence to link him to the thefts. 
