<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062890-0054 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 239762 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 28, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 12; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
395 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ERMA BOMBECK: SNAKES LEAVE HER A LITTLE RATTLED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ERMA BOMBECK 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This is the time of year in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> when people look where they're going and 
walk on the sunny side of the rocks. It's stinking hot and it's snake time. 
</P>
<P>
We hear relatively few stories about snakebites, but <PERSON>Peter Aleshire</PERSON> reported an 
incredible story in the <LOCATION>Arizona Republic</LOCATION> the other day: A man was bitten on the 
tongue while kissing a rattlesnake. 
</P>
<P>
Now here's the weird part. He decided to try a non-scientific, quack-type 
remedy he had heard about to counteract snakebite. A word of caution: Do not 
try this in your own home. He'd heard that if you run an electrical current 
through the wound, it is supposed to break down the venom. So, after he was 
bitten, he wired his mouth to a pickup battery and tried to jump-start his 
tongue. It knocked him out cold, and he ended up in the hospital where he lost 
part of his tongue and one lip. My views on snakes are well known. I do not for 
a single minute believe they're as afraid of me as I am of them. They are not 
trying to get out of my way when they see me coming, and people who keep them 
around to keep the rodent population down should be heavily sedated. 
</P>
<P>
When my husband and I first moved to this state, we were invited one night to 
the town of Prescott to witness a festival celebrating Indian lore. It featured 
a group of men with snakes tattooed on their arms who performed the famous 
"Smoki Snake Dance." Our host was a "Smoki." 
</P>
<P>
As a couple of dozen men danced around a circle to the beat of a tom-tom, each 
dancer was given a snake (non-poisonous). He was to clench the snake between 
his teeth closely behind the head and just out of striking distance while he 
held the tail in his hand and waved it around as he kept the beat. 
</P>
<P>
When the dance was over, we went down to the field to say good night to our 
host. There was blood streaming down his face as he said, "Shoot, I got bit 
last year. Next year, I've got to get a better grip on him closer to the head." 
</P>
<P>
When I asked him where all the snakes had gone, he looked around him on the 
ground and said, "We just release 'em when we're finished. They're probably 
halfway to the parking lot by this time." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona Poison Control Center</ORGANIZATION> was quoted as saying that most 
snakebites come from people kissing snakes, playing with them and handling them 
on a routine basis. 
</P>
<P>
Do you see a personality profile developing here anywhere? 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880225-0242 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-88 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakebiteHomicide     02-25 0321</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snakebite Homicide,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Found Guilty Of Manslaughter In Snakebite Death of Toddler</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. GEORGE, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man was convicted of manslaughter
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the snakebite-death of a girl around whose shoulder he
had draped a rattlesnake.
   District <PERSON>Judge J. Philip Eves</PERSON> announced the verdict against
<PERSON>Darrell Wessendorf</PERSON> in the non-jury trial.
   Wessendorf, 24, had been charged with second-degree murder in
the death last year of 21-month-old <ORGANIZATION>Stevie LuRen Kirkwood of La
Verkin</ORGANIZATION>. He had pleaded innocent by reason of insanity.
   The judge said that he found Wessendorf guilty of the lesser
charge because the defendant hadn't been aware of the possible
results of his actions.
   Wessendord, who was renting an upstairs apartment from the
child's mother, <PERSON>Jeri Ann Kirkwood</PERSON>, at the time, testified that he
found the 5-foot rattlesnake on a road and was trying to show the
girl that that it would not hurt her.
   He said he had partially wrapped the snake around the child's
shoulder when <PERSON>Mrs. Kirkwood</PERSON> entered the room and screamed, causing
him to flinch and the snake to bite the child.
   Sentencing was set for <DATE>April 11</DATE>. Manslaughter carries a one- to
15-year sentence. Second-degree murder would have brought five
years to life.
   Defense attorney <PERSON>J. MacArthur Wright</PERSON> had claimed that only <PERCENT>0.2
percent</PERCENT> of those bitten by rattlesnakes die and called on the judge
to ``make a distinction here on what constitutes a grave risk of
death.''
   ``People bitten by rattlesnakes are often not even treated,'' he
said.
   Prosecutor <PERSON>O. Brent Rowe</PERSON> argued that <PERSON>Wessendorf</PERSON>'s actions were
intentional and malicious.
   Earlier <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, a psychologists, <PERSON>George Dunford</PERSON>, said that
Wessendorf suffered from mild schizophrenia and that he did not
believe the defendant understood he was endangering the child.
   An expert on snakes, <PERSON>James Glenn</PERSON>, testified for the defense that
the snake is one of the least aggressive types of rattlers and that
the hospital did not give the girl enough anti-venom.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890304-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-89 1833EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakebiteRescue     03-04 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snakebite Rescue,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doctors Await Serum To Treat Snakebite Victim, But May Not Use It</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB BLACK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Physicians treating a snake-venom
researcher received a shipment of serum from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> to counteract a
deadly viper bite <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, but a hospital spokesman said doctors
may elect not to use it.
   Antivenin was flown in <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> for <PERSON>William E. Haast</PERSON>,
78, who remained in serious but stable condition at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Utah Health Sciences Center</ORGANIZATION> after being bit on the left hand by a
Pakistani pit viper earlier in the week.
   ``The doctors are evaluating it,'' said <PERSON>John Dwan</PERSON>, hospital
spokesman. ``We're hopeful that it's not needed, but that remains to
be seen.''
   In an unusual effort initiated by <PERSON>Stephen Studdert</PERSON>, special
assistant to President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, antivenins effective against the bite
were located in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs
rules were waived to place the shipments quickly on flights to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The British shipment from the <ORGANIZATION>English National Poison Unit</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> arrived <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. But doctors did not administer it to
<LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>, deciding instead to wait for the more effective Iranian
serum, said nursing supervisor <PERSON>Rick Taylor</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> said the shipment from the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> was being
arranged through direct, government-to-government contacts, but in
<LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, ``people-to-people, non-government'' contacts were used. There
are no formal ties between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>'s
fundamentalist Moslem government, which has repeatedly referred to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> as the ``Great Satan.''
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>'s fibrinogen level, an element in the blood that
regulates how the blood coagulates and is destroyed by the snake
bite venom, has been improving, although it remained far below
acceptable levels, according to hospital spokesman <PERSON>John Dwan</PERSON>.
   ``We have been replacing fibrinogen through transfusions and his
body appears to be making fibrinogen,'' <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said.
   The Iranian antivenin arrived at mid-afternoon and one of <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>'s
friends transported it to the hospital. Before it is used, <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said
doctors would monitor <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>'s condition and run checks on the
antivenin.
   ``These antivenins are not miracle cure-alls,'' he said. ``There
are negative side effects that we have to guard against.'' He said
antivenins, which are made from horse serum, can cause lung and
kidney problems.
   Haast had been treated earlier with antivenins from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> and from a lab in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said he had
not been given antivenins for about 24 hours.
   The supply of the serum from the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> was being sent from
the <ORGANIZATION>Tashkent Institute of Vaccines</ORGANIZATION>. That serum was being flown to
<LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> and was expected to get to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Haast, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> at the
university's <ORGANIZATION>Research Park</ORGANIZATION>, has been bitten 148 times by snakes and
is immune to the venom of dozens of reptiles. But he had no immunity
to withstand the viper's bite and checked himself into the hospital
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after being bitten <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The Pakistani pit viper, or saw-scaled viper, is one of 1,000
exotic, poisonous snakes <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> keeps at the lab, where their venom
is extracted for sale to universities and health organizations for
use in research and the manufacture of antivenins.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA092490-0066 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 282211 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 24, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
144 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN BRIEF: SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
SNAKEBITE ANTIDOTES IMPROVED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times staff and Wire reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A new way to make effective snakebite anti-venom antidotes that have fewer side 
effects than existing products has been developed by researchers at the 
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Madison</ORGANIZATION>. About 45,000 people worldwide die each year 
from poisonous bites and stings, and many times that number are treated 
successfully. 
</P>
<P>
As many as <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of all patients treated with conventional anti-venoms develop 
allergic reactions to horse proteins in the anti-venoms. 
</P>
<P>
Molecular biologists <PERSON>Sean B. Carroll</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bruce Thalley</PERSON> report in today's 
edition of BioTechnology that they have made effective anti-venoms by injecting 
the poisons into chickens. The antibodies are concentrated in egg yolks, which 
makes isolation and purification easy. Chicken proteins also do not produce as 
severe a reaction as horse proteins. The anti-venoms have not yet been tested 
in humans. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SNAKES; POISONS AND POISONINGS; DRUGS; MEDICAL RESEARCH; MEDICAL TREATMENTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890304-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-89 0657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Bush-SnakebiteRescue     03-04 0577</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-Snakebite Rescue,0592</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doctors Awaiting Serum From Iran To Treat Snakebite Victim</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURIE SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Physicians treating a snake-venom
researcher, whose need for rare medicine prompted <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
intervention, were awaiting a shipment of serum from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> today to
counteract a deadly viper bite.
   In an unusual effort initiated by <PERSON>Stephen Studdert</PERSON>, special
assistant to President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, antivenins effective against the bite
of a Pakistani pit viper were located in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Customs rules were waived to place the
shipments quickly on flights to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The antivenins were sought for <PERSON>William E. Haast</PERSON>, 78, who was in
serious but stable condition at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Utah Health
Sciences Center</ORGANIZATION> today after being bitten in the left hand by the
viper earlier in the week.
   The British shipment from the <ORGANIZATION>English National Poison Unit</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> arrived <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. But doctors did not administer it to
<LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>, deciding instead to wait for the more effective Iranian
serum, said nursing supervisor <PERSON>Rick Taylor</PERSON>.
   ``The one from <LOCATION>Tehran</LOCATION> is the best one, I understand, because of
its properties,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. ``We will not give the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> one
unless <PERSON>Mr. Haast</PERSON>'s condition deteriorates.''
   Haast was being given plasma intermittently to replace
coagulating elements of his blood. The snake's venom prohibits blood
from coagulating and victims often bleed to death.
   Haast, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> at the
university's <ORGANIZATION>Research Park</ORGANIZATION>, has been bitten 148 times by snakes and
is immune to the venom of dozens of reptiles. But he had no immunity
to withstand the viper's bite and checked himself into the hospital
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The Pakistani pit viper, or saw-scaled viper, is one of 1,000
exotic, poisonous snakes <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> keeps at the lab, where their venom
is extracted for sale to universities and health organizations for
use in research and the manufacture of antivenins.
   Haast had been treated earlier with antivenins from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, including one shipment obtained through an unusual
airport relay involving zoo personnel, a helicopter and a departing
jetliner.
   Studdert of Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> said he became involved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>
when he received a call from an associate of <ORGANIZATION>Haast's</ORGANIZATION>. The associate,
who had read accounts of a speech <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> gave in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> describing
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s ``kinder, gentler'' approach to human problems, said the
serum could only be located in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and asked
for the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration's help.
   <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> said he immediately set up conference calls with people
around the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and in other countries after doctors and
specialists advised the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> that the serums Haast needed
were unavailable in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   Using an American interpreter who speaks <LOCATION>Farsi</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> put
<LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>'s representatives in telephone contact with serum specialists
in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>.
   Two different serums were needed, he said, one for young pit
vipers and another for older snakes of the same breed.
   Vials of the Iranian serum were due to arrive in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> <TIME>this
afternoon</TIME>.
   The serum found at the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> institute was the antivenin used
for younger vipers.
   Another supply of the serum was obtained through the <ORGANIZATION>Tashkent
Institute of Vaccines</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. That serum was being
flown to <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> for eventual shipment to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``When I decided I should get involved, I clearly did not want to
disturb the president,'' <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> said. ``But I decided, this is
what the president would have wanted us to do.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890305-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-05-89 2213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SnakebiteRescue     03-05 0571</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snakebite Rescue,0587</SECOND>
<HEAD>Snakebite Victim Resting Comfortably, But Remains In Danger</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PEG McENTEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A snake-venom researcher bitten by a deadly
viper rested comfortably <DATE>Sunday</DATE> while doctors considered whether to
treat him with antivenins from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, a
hospital spokesman said.
   <PERSON>William E. Haast</PERSON>, 78, remained in serious but stable condition at
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Utah Health Sciences Center</ORGANIZATION> after being bitten on
the left hand <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by a Pakistani pit viper, also known as a
saw-scaled viper, said hospital spokesman <PERSON>John Dwan</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Mr. Haast</PERSON> is resting very comfortably, eating and chatting with
friends,'' <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said. ``He's just in danger, if you will.''
   Haast, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> at the
university's <ORGANIZATION>Research Park</ORGANIZATION>, has been bitten 148 times by snakes and
is immune to the venom of dozens of reptiles. But he had no immunity
to the viper's bite and checked himself into the hospital <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The saw-scaled viper's venom attacks its victim's ability to
produce fibrinogen, an element of blood that regulates coagulation.
A lack of fibrinogen can cause uncontrolled bleeding.
   <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said the level of <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>'s fibrinogen had been improving
slightly although it remained ``dangerously low'' <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Doctors were replacing <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>'s fibrinogen with transfusions and
it appeared his system had begun to produce it again, <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said.
   He said <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>'s blood was being analyzed every four hours, and
that by <DATE>late Saturday</DATE> his fibrogen level was about one-third of
normal. On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, he said, ``for all intents and purposes (it
was) at zero.''
   Haast's plight prompted an effort by <PERSON>Stephen Studdernt</PERSON>, special
assistant to President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, to coordinate the acquisition of
antivenins from the three nations and expedite shipment to <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said antivenins from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> had arrived, but he
did not know if the one from the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> had. The antivenin
from <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> was more specifically made to counteract venom from the
species of viper that bit <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>, he said.
   However, he said doctors were ``very leery about giving
medication to someone from a source about which we know very little
about.''
   Antivenins are made from horse serum and can cause negative side
effects such as lung and kidney problems, he said.
   ``We want to emphasize the fact that we're grateful to everyone
who went to such great lengths to get the antivenin,'' <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said.
``The decision on whether to use them or not will be based on <PERSON>Mr.
Haast</PERSON>'s condition. Hopefully we won't have to use them.''
   Haast had been treated earlier with antivenins from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> and from a lab in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
he had not been given antivenins for about 24 hours.
   He said doctors also had contacted scientists and physicans in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to discuss treatment.
   ``It's a special kind of snake, with a special kind of poison,
and the immunology is complicated,'' <PERSON>Dwan</PERSON> said. ``Our physicians
aren't just winging it on their own.''
   <PERSON>Studdert</PERSON> said the Iranian government apparently did not interfere
with the shipment of the antivenin despite the strained relations
between the two nations. Iranian leader <PERSON>Ayatolla Khomeini</PERSON> has often
called the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> the ``great Satan.''
   The Pakistani pit viper is one of 1,000 exotic, poisonous snakes
<LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> keeps at the laboratory, where their venom is extracted for
sale to universities and health organizations for research and the
manufacture of antivenins.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06287209 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06287209 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (12); PHOTO: ASSOCIATED PRESS; SHARK; PHOTOS: (2) MERCURY NEWS;
EARTHQUAKE AND LIGHTNING; PHOTOS: (2) NATURAL SELECTION; SALAMANDER AND BEES;
PHOTOS: (5) ANIMALS ANIMALS; (Black Widow Spider, Jimson Weed, Mushrooms,
Toad, Jellyfish); PHOTO: COPYRIGHT JOE McDONALD -- ANIMALS ANIMALS;
(Rattlesnake) (color); COVER PHOTO: Cover photograph by Judy Griesedieck;
Still Shaky After These Two Years?; If the anniversary of the quake has you
edgy, see page 14. We'll give you more reasons to worry about living in
California. (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENVIRONMENT; INSECT; ANIMAL; FISH; PLANT; VIOLENCE; HUMAN; ...; STATISTIC;
SF-BAY-AREA; LIST; SAFETY; GUIDELINE; MAJOR-STORY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  WHENEVER I START PICTURING Mother Nature as a benign, comforting, nurturing
Mom I remind myself of the lullaby my own dear mother sang to me so many years
ago:;   Rockabye Baby,  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  West  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE SUM OF ALL FEARS
TWO YEARS AFTER LOMA PRIETA, SOME OF US HAVE
STOPPED TREMBLING. BUT EVEN IF THE REAL BIG ONE
ISN'T AT HAND, NATURE HAS A LOT OF OTHER TRICKS UP
HER SLEEVE.  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  LEE QUARNSTROM is a staff writer in the Mercury News Santa Cruz bureau.; See
also related article on page 18 of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     on the tree top.;   When the wind blows,;   the cradle will rock.;   When
the bough breaks,;   the cradle will fall,;   And down will come Baby,;  
cradle and all.;   Now what's that all about? Why would a mom sing about Baby
plunging to a certain death when the breeze picks up? Do moms know or intuit
something about Mother Nature that the rest of us don't?;   Perhaps so.
Consider this:;   Just two years ago most of us were rocking gently in <ORGANIZATION>Ma
Nature</ORGANIZATION>'s cradle. Then, on <DATE>Oct. 17, 1989</DATE>, at 5:04 in the afternoon, the <LOCATION>Loma
Prieta</LOCATION> earthquake slammed the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>, bringing death, destruction and,
perhaps most significant, disillusionment as it jolted our homes, our world.; 
 For many of us, the disillusionment was with <ORGANIZATION>Mother Nature</ORGANIZATION>, with our trust in
the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> itself. Sure, we'd read about killer earthquakes in <LOCATION>Armenia</LOCATION>,
hurricanes and typhoons in distant oceans, volcanoes in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and
even more remote parts of the world. But this is <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and part of being
in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is, or was, being gently rocked in Mom's cradle.;   Once that
bough breaks, you come to the conclusion that there's no end to the ways that
Mother Nature can get you. She can poison you, drown you, chew you up or burn
you to a crisp.;   In fact, <ORGANIZATION>Mother Nature</ORGANIZATION> has a lot in common with <PERSON>Lucrezia
Borgia</PERSON> or with <PERSON>Winnie Ruth Judd</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>'s infamous trunk murderer of the
<DATE>1930s</DATE> who hacked up a couple of acquaintances in <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and checked them
through to <ORGANIZATION>Union Station</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> stuffed in several pieces of luggage.;
  Most of us have been looking at Mom with a somewhat more skeptical eye since
the 7.1 magnitude <LOCATION>Loma Prieta</LOCATION> quake. We all know now that the Big One -- the
Real Big One -- will hit one of these years or even one of these days and that
death and destruction will be much more widespread than it was two years
back.;   Don't be lulled to sleep. That bough can still break and that cradle
can still plummet to earth. Mother Nature has some other tricks up her
housecoat's sleeve. Some can knock you on your ass; some can kill you.;
RATTLESNAKES;   How about these bastards? Can you think of anything scarier
than rattlesnakes? (Well, maybe black widow spiders. Or sharks, now that I
think about it. See below.);   The rattlesnake is not man's best friend. Some
are even less so than others, particularly the Mojave rattlesnake, native to
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and a small portion of the <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> desert.;   Our local
variety, the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Pacific Rattlesnake</ORGANIZATION>, is one of the more aggressive
rattlers. It will, when provoked, bite. About three-quarters of the time it
will also envenomate its victim, i.e., inject the unfortunate soul with a
potentially fatal mixture of proteins and enzymes that can cause serious nerve
and tissue damage if not treated in time.;   Last year, the <ORGANIZATION>Regional Poison
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> -- which serves <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Benito</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Monterey</ORGANIZATION> and San <PERSON>Luis Obispo</PERSON> counties -- had 10 emergency calls about
rattlesnake bites from individuals and doctors. The center maintains a
24-hours-a-day hot line to provide over-the-phone help to poisoning victims
and doctors treating them.;   Four of the 10 victims logged by the center
developed life-threatening symptoms, according to <PERSON>Gary Everson</PERSON>, director of
the facility. None died.;   "The first thing we recommend, if it's at all
possible," says <PERSON>Everson</PERSON>, "is to go directly to a hospital.";   No one
recommends the old cut-and-suck-out-the-venom treatment anymore. An
overzealous application of this chestnut of the <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> oaters of
our youth can result, experts say, in severed tendons or even cut arteries
that can lead to fatal bleeding.;   Anti-venin is prescribed, says <PERSON>Everson</PERSON>,
only when patients develop symptoms such as swelling and bruising around a
rattlesnake bite. Occasionally, something called the <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> extractor, a
suction cup on the end of a syringe, is recommended for hikers in rattlesnake
country far from medical treatment.;   Most of the snakebite calls to the
Poison Center come from <LOCATION>San Benito</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> and San <PERSON>Luis Obispo</PERSON> counties,
although the rattler can be found throughout <LOCATION>Central California.</LOCATION>;   <PERSON>Naturalist
John Lane</PERSON>, director of education at the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>,
recommends common sense as the best way to avoid snakebites: Don't walk
barefoot to the john at night when you're camping; don't pick up snakes, alive
or dead (even a dead rattler can envenomate you); don't stick your hand in
crevices or brush piles.;   "Most snakebite victims were doing something
totally stupid," says <PERSON>Lane</PERSON>, who notes that the vipers can be found throughout
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION> "from the beach to the top of <LOCATION>Mount Whitney</LOCATION>."; SPIDERS;  
<LOCATION>Arachnophobia</LOCATION>! Why not? Is there anything creepier than a spider?;   In our
neck of the woods there are apparently two dangerous spiders. <PERSON>Gary Everson</PERSON>
says one has never been seen, but has bitten some folks anyway.;   The deadly
spider that has been seen in <LOCATION>Central California</LOCATION> is the black widow, the
creepy-crawler with the distinctive red hourglass marking on the abdomen of
the mature female. (The female gets more press than the male because she tends
to eat the poor devil if he hangs around too long after sex.);   This spider
is particularly dangerous to children, old people and anyone with
cardiovascular problems.;   Don't stick your hand into places you can't see,
like the proverbial woodpile or into dark places under the house.;   Symptoms
of a black widow bite can include local pain, cramps in the back, chest,
shoulders or belly, and nausea, headache, vomiting and anxiety.;   If you get
bitten, rush to a hospital. First aid is not recommended at home. If you can't
see a doctor, call the <ORGANIZATION>Poison Control Center</ORGANIZATION>, which logged 34 black widow
bites in its five-county region last year.;   The other dangerous local
spider, experts think, is the infamous brown recluse or violin spider. (It has
a distinctive dark brown mark shaped like a violin, hence the name.) While its
bites aren't as potentially fatal as the black widow's, they can lead to
painful tissue loss.;   <PERSON>Everson</PERSON> notes that as far as he knows, no one has ever
seen a brown recluse or violin spider in these parts. However, since people
have suffered symptoms of brown recluse bites, it's assumed they're here.;  
The brown recluse or violin spider is what's called a necrotic arachnid. The
bite causes tissue around the area to die, a condition known as necrosis. It's
not uncommon for the dead tissue to have to be cut out, a painful process if
you wait for treatment, since the venom spreads outward from the bite, killing
more and more of the victim's flesh.;   Whether or not our local necrotic
arachnid is the brown recluse or some cousin, wisdom dictates keeping your
hands to yourself instead of poking into dark places and other hidey-holes.;
SHARKS;   Unfortunately, great white sharks love the seas off the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
coastline, where they grow to two tons or more. Over the past four decades
there have been 57 reports of great white attacks, including seven that
resulted in deaths.;   The easiest way to avoid these killers, of course, is
to stay out of the water -- or to swim in lakes, rivers, pools and other
bodies of fresh water.;   The latest local victim, 32-year-old <PERSON>Eric Larsen</PERSON>,
saved his own life a few months ago by bopping the attacking great white on
the snout, pulling his arm out of the creature's toothy mouth, then struggling
back to the beach at <LOCATION>Davenport Landing</LOCATION>, 10 miles north of <LOCATION>Santa Cruz.</LOCATION>;   After
<PERSON>Larsen</PERSON>'s heroic efforts at self-preservation, a state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and
Game biologist opined that "more people here die of bee stings than shark
attacks." That, of course, is of little solace to a surfer sporting a wetsuit
that makes him look like a tasty harbor seal to the 16-foot great white shark
circling nearby.; BEES;   Unless you're allergic to bees, you don't have to
worry about the occasional sting of the honeybee, wasp or yellow jacket. If
you are allergic, get to a hospital immediately.;   To relieve the pain, a
paste of baking soda can be put on the sting. And even though experts don't
really believe it, meat tenderizer rubbed onto the booboo seems to work for
some people.;   If you get a bee in your bonnet, or car, while you're behind
the wheel, don't kill yourself by driving into a tree while you're trying to
shoo the little bugger out the window.; AMPHIBIANS;   Yes, there are a
salamander and a couple of toads, including bufo vulgaris, that can, but
generally don't, secrete some dangerous milky goo through their skin. <PERSON>Gary
Everson</PERSON>, at the <ORGANIZATION>Poison Control Center</ORGANIZATION>, says the only case of this kind he can
recall is that of a dog that tried to eat a bad toad and had to go to the vet.
He does not recall whether <PERSON>Bowser</PERSON> survived.;   Though this milky secretion can
cause paralysis, cases are so infrequent that <PERSON>Everson</PERSON> advises parents not to
become hysterical if Junior picks up a frog.; JELLYFISH;   The gelatinous
creatures found occasionally along the <LOCATION>Central California</LOCATION> coastline can cause
painful stings but nothing like the infamous Portuguese-man-of-war or the
lethal box jellyfish of tropical ocean waters.; SCORPIONS;   Another stinger,
but not anything to worry about, certainly not as bad as the feared bark
scorpion of the <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> deserts. The local version is dangerous only to
people with allergies, according to <PERSON>John Lane</PERSON>, naturalist at the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz
Museum of Natural</ORGANIZATION> History.; SHELLFISH;   If you want to scare yourself
sometime, call the <ORGANIZATION>State Health Department</ORGANIZATION>'s Shellfish Information Line at
(415) 540-2605. I did, and I've decided I'm no longer quite so upset that the
voracious little sea otters have scavenged most of the <LOCATION>Pismo</LOCATION> clams from the
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz County</LOCATION> beaches where I used to dig them.;   Presently, the annual
mussel quarantine is in effect until the end of <DATE>October</DATE>. Going into effect
each <DATE>May 1</DATE>, the quarantine is designed to protect us from paralytic shellfish
poisoning -- which is just what it sounds like and can kill you.;   When I
called the hot line last month there was another ban in effect for all bivalve
shellfish taken along the <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION> coastlines. In <DATE>August</DATE>, some
people had ignored the ban and scarfed some mussels in <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION>. Three,
including one person in critical condition, had to be airlifted to the
hospital.;   Another recent state order prohibited eating cockles and
littleneck clams gathered between <ORGANIZATION>Monterey</ORGANIZATION> and Marin counties. Also, the state
said not to eat the guts, the dark parts, of any shellfish caught along the
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> coastline.;   It seems that shellfish eat highly toxic plankton,
then concentrate the poison in their gooey bodies -- where it can prove lethal
to humans.;   "Probably as many people die from shellfish poisoning as from
rattlesnake bites," warns naturalist <PERSON>John Lane.</PERSON>; TICKS;   While <PERSON>Gary Everson</PERSON>
says there are no documented cases of full-blown <ORGANIZATION>Lyme Disease</ORGANIZATION> developing in
<LOCATION>Central California</LOCATION>, he points out that doctors in the region have used
antibiotics to stop the spread of the characteristic target-shaped rash around
some tick bites. Medication is only recommended, he says, if symptoms of Lyme
Disease develop.;   <LOCATION>LIGHTNING</LOCATION>;   Two <LOCATION>Monterey County</LOCATION> farmworkers were killed
by lightning just a few weeks ago. We've read about golfers being struck by
bolts of lightning while standing on the fairway. The best advice is either to
get inside or, if that's impossible, to become unobtrusive, to wait out the
electrical storm lying in a hole or swale.; MUSHROOMS;   We've all heard about
the mythical family that used to live down the street but was wiped out by
some poisonous toadstools after a foray into the woods looking for edible
mushrooms.;   And most of us have read about the real families from other
parts of the world who've gone mushroom-hunting here in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> only to get
sick or die after eating some highly toxic fungi that resemble tasty varieties
that are common -- and safe -- back home.;   There is a very popular mushroom
in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, for instance -- <PERSON>Julius Caesar</PERSON>'s mushroom -- that resembles the
delicious coccora or amanita calyptrata found near oak and madrone trees in
our part of the New World. Unfortunately, the Italian fungus also bears a
dangerously close resemblance to the lethal amanita phalloides or "death cap"
mushroom.;   Also, says <PERSON>Phil Carpenter</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Fungus Federation of
Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION>, there is apparently a resemblance between the death cap and a
popular mushroom of <LOCATION>Southeast Asia.</LOCATION>;   <ORGANIZATION>Carpenter</ORGANIZATION> warns that the death cap and
the "destroying angel," or amanita ocreata, are not only lethal but quite
common in this area.;   This pair is doubly dangerous because by the time
symptoms appear, 12 to 24 hours after ingestion, the kidneys and livers of
victims are already failing. "It's an ugly way to go," warns <PERSON>Carpenter</PERSON>. "You
die in your own poisons.";   There are plenty of other poisonous mushrooms out
there under the oaks and in the woods, but none so dangerous as the death cap
and destroying angel.;   <ORGANIZATION>Carpenter</ORGANIZATION> stresses that there are no tests for
amateurs to determine whether a mushroom is benign or a killer.;   And <PERSON>Gary
Everson</PERSON>, at the Poison Center, notes that "It's impossible to identify
mushrooms over the phone.";   <ORGANIZATION>The Fungus Federation</ORGANIZATION>, which has a membership
stretching from <LOCATION>Redwood City</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Monterey</LOCATION>, meets monthly at the
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Museum of Natural History</ORGANIZATION>. For more information call (408)
684-2275.; PLANTS;   There is a veritable salad of dangerous plants out
there.;   Not too long ago, some schoolchildren in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> required
treatment after mistakenly sampling poison hemlock on a field trip to a nearby
state park. This weed, the one that did in <LOCATION>Socrates</LOCATION>, is plentiful -- but not
too difficult to identify. Check for the purple spots on the green stalk of
this plant, which is common in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and sometimes thick along roadsides
and in moist areas.;   Poison hemlock can grow to a height of 10 feet and has
small white flowers in little clusters at the top. Ingestion can cause
vomiting, diarrhea, dizziness and all the other usual symptoms of poisoning,
and can result in fatal respiratory failure.;   Other seriously toxic plants
include the oleander, which has been planted extensively along the sides and
down the center dividers of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s freeways; the English yew, an
ornamental in many gardens; pokeweed, castor bean, foxglove, jimsonweed and
meadow death camas.;   The long and short of it is Don't Eat Plants You Don't
Know To Be Safe and Edible.;   IT SOUNDS LIKE MOM USED TO SOUND, DOESN'T it?
Remember the warnings?;   "Don't play in the street. Don't put strange things
in your mouth. Don't talk to strangers. Stay out of the water (or don't swim
unless you're on the 'buddy system'). Don't put your hand in dark places.";  
However, lest we start looking at <ORGANIZATION>Mother Nature</ORGANIZATION> with a completely jaundiced
eye, let's keep in mind the simple fact that humanity is generally much more
adept than she is at bumping itself off. You're still far more likely to die
cruising home behind the wheel after happy hour than in a bosky glade after
gnawing some suspicious mushrooms and unknown weeds.;   Consider the motor
car:;   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, according to statistics gathered by the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Health Services</ORGANIZATION>, 5,663 people died as the result of motor vehicle accidents on
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> highways and byways, most of them -- 4,092 -- white males.;   In
fact, according to the <ORGANIZATION>National Safety Council</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> records more motor
vehicle fatalities than any of the remaining 49 states, more than half-again
as many as <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which ranks second on the grim list of traffic deaths. The
good news, however, is that our highway death rate is below the national
average, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Safety Council</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> motorists, passengers and
unlucky bystanders cash in their chips at the rate of 2 for every 100 million
miles driven. The national highway death rate is 2.2 victims per 100 million
miles. Neighboring <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> has the worst rate, 3.6 per 100 million miles.;   Or
think about this:;   The second major cause of fatal injury in the <ORGANIZATION>Golden
State</ORGANIZATION> is suicide! Word from <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> is that 3,862 Californians took their
own lives in <DATE>1989</DATE> -- the vast majority of them white males.;   Again eclipsing
the minuscule number of victims of Mother Nature, Californians murdered 3,298
of their number in <DATE>1989</DATE> -- with white males continuing to lead the deadly pack
with 2,633 victims.;   Why white males? <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Department of Health
Services</ORGANIZATION> opines that since "male deaths substantially outnumber female deaths
for causes like vehicular mishaps, poisonings, homicide and suicide" the
figures "are consistent with the notion that males in our culture find
themselves or even place themselves in situations carrying a high risk of
injury." I didn't say that; the Emergency Preparedness and <ORGANIZATION>Injury Control
Program</ORGANIZATION> of the health department did, in its "Fatal Injuries in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
<DATE>1988</DATE>" report.;   While white males tend to die of injuries in greater numbers
than members of ethnic minorities, the rates of injury-related deaths per
capita are higher among black and Hispanic populations. Suicide rates are
lower, but, the state reports, this "is more than offset by their greater risk
of death by such causes as homicide, poisonings, pedestrian mishaps and
drowning.";   And disease, of course, kills more Californians than <ORGANIZATION>Mother
Nature</ORGANIZATION> and mankind together combine to wipe out. In <DATE>1988</DATE>, for instance, 16,354
cancer deaths were recorded in the state and 12,675 people died of heart
disease. That same year 3,094 Californians died of AIDS.;   That kind of
number-crunching, of course, provides no comfort to the families of the 64
people killed by the <LOCATION>Loma Prieta</LOCATION> earthquake or the two farmworkers struck by
lightning south of <LOCATION>Salinas</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE>. But the figures do make Mother Nature
seem somewhat benign compared with the ravages of disease and the homicidal
tendencies of our own species.;   Of course, if you're a fatalist you might
believe that somewhere out there there's a spider -- or a bullet or a
toadstool or a jetliner -- with your name on it. And if you're a fatalist, you
know what? You're probably right.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Lee Quarnstrom  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911013  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  14  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  3,168  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, October 13, 1991
00287209,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901114-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-14-90 0426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Gulf-Infirm     11-14 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gulf-Infirm,0485</SECOND>
<HEAD>Desert Shield Soldiers Shipped to Germany With Broken Bones,
Snakebite</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Gulf Rdp, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>By GEORGE BOEHMER</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 1,400 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops assigned
to Operation Desert Shield have been airlifted to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> for
treatment of broken bones, depression, snake bites and other
afflictions, military officials say.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> is treating fewer GIs than anticipated for a
population of 230,000 people, ``based on health risk assessments
for that region of the world,'' said <PERSON>Barbara Slifer</PERSON>, spokeswoman
for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>7th Medical Command</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Heidelberg</LOCATION>.
   Forty-three soldiers have died in the deployment, mostly in
accidents.
   Officials say two <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> hospitals in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had received 926
evacuated patients as of <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
hospital in <LOCATION>Wiesbaden</LOCATION> had received 515 since <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>, when <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
troops were sent to <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>.
   The figures mean that of the 230,000 GIs sent to the <LOCATION>Persian
Gulf</LOCATION> region, about one soldier in every 166 has had a medical
problem.
   Some have been treated and returned to the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> region,
and others with more serious conditions have been transferred to
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Ms. Slifer</PERSON>.
   She said 88 remained hospitalized at the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s regional
hospital in <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> and 53 in the regional hospital at Landsthul.
Capt. <PERSON>Robert Lenahan</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>'s hospital in <LOCATION>Wiesbaden</LOCATION> said
39 Desert Shield patients were still there as of <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Military medical officials have said that facilities newly set
up in the gulf region can care for most casualties as well as
hospitals anywhere. But evacuating patients to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> keep beds
free in the gulf in case of hostilities.
   The medical problems ``run the gamut,'' <PERSON>Ms. Slifer</PERSON> said.
   ``The predominant area of care that we've been providing is
orthopedic, broken bones. We've had one snakebite case, we've had
gallbladder attacks,'' she said.
   She said a few soldiers were also sent back for psychological
care.
   ``I think the psychological ailments are pretty much what you
would expect in any type of military-type environment.''
   Most of the patients coming through <LOCATION>Wiesbaden</LOCATION> are sent back to
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, unless they can be treated in ``a fairly short
timeframe,'' <PERSON>Lenahan</PERSON> said.
   ``But we have people coming back with kidney stones, torn knee
ligaments, things that take more than just a couple of weeks to
repair,'' <PERSON>Lenahan</PERSON> said.
   He said that long-term patients requiring treatment of more than
three to four weeks are sent back to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> ``so that we
still have enough empty beds here for other patients that may come
up.''
   In addition to injuries, patients needed treatment for
allergies, asthma and dermatological problems, he said.
   He said that the allergies and asthma are apparently due to the
very dry climate in <LOCATION>Saudi Arabia</LOCATION>. ``People who wouldn't normally
have asthma problems are experiencing that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06286066 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06286066 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Washington Post; Snake-handler Dewey Chafin says he's been
bitten 116 times. He refuses to get treatment, putting faith in God to heal
him.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  REPTILE; REACTION; RELIGION; ORGANIZATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  'WHEN I die, I wanna snake-bit die.";    Dewey Chafin's voice is soft as
gauze, but the sentiment is hammered iron. You can't doubt a man's sincerity
when he's standing at a pulpit in shirt sleeves holding two fistfuls of
squirming rattlesnake.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Religion &amp; Ethics  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SERPENTS DON'T RATTLE SNAKE-HANDLING FAITHFUL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Yes, Lord," answers a parishioner.;    "Praise JEEsus," howls another.;   
This is the Church of the Lord Jesus in the last state in the union where
religious snake-handling is legal. The church isn't affiliated with any
official Christian denomination. It has no religious statuary, no baptismal
fountain, not even a cross. Which is not to suggest it has no religion.;   
"I'm a snake-handler," says <PERSON>Chafin</PERSON>. His mother beams. She's here too, and
she's holding a hissing rattler of her own.;    <PERSON>Chafin</PERSON> is 58, a disabled coal
miner and a Korean War vet, and like the five dozen people standing hip to
buttock in this makeshift rural church, he believes in the <LOCATION>New Testament</LOCATION>
exactly as it was written. And that includes the Book of Mark, Chapter 16,
Verse 18, where Jesus says, "They shall take up serpents; and if they drink
any deadly thing, it shall not hurt them; they shall lay hands on the sick,
and they shall recover.";    And so it is that each dance with snakes is a
test of faith.;    In 35 years of snake-handling, <PERSON>Chafin</PERSON> says, he's been
bitten 116 times. He's been fanged on the hands, the arms, and not long ago a
five-foot diamondback took him through the right eyebrow.;    Like all
snake-handlers, <PERSON>Chafin</PERSON> says he's never treated a bite with anything other than
prayer.;    Around him are some 50 members of his church. Not one of them
drinks, not one of them smokes, and all of them dress like ladies and gents.
The rules in this church are posted high for anyone to see. Neatness is
required. "Lying" is outlawed, along with "gossiping" and "backbiting.";   
Here is <PERSON>Lydia Hollins</PERSON>, the organist. She is <ORGANIZATION>Dewey</ORGANIZATION>'s niece, a handsome woman of
38.;    <PERSON>Hollins</PERSON> is the daughter of <PERSON>Columbia Chafin</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1962</DATE>, when
<PERSON>Lydia</PERSON> was just a girl. She snake-bit died, at the age of 22. To this day, she
remains the Church of the <ORGANIZATION>Lord Jesus</ORGANIZATION>'s only fatality, <PERSON>Dewey Chafin</PERSON> says. She
was his sister.;    And now the dead woman's daughter is gently cradling a
big- bellied viper in both hands, and praising the <LOCATION>Lord.</LOCATION>;    There is
fanaticism in this room, and there is bravery and passion and something
strangely moving that is not easily put into words.;    Snake-handlers have
been practicing their religion throughout <LOCATION>Appalachia</LOCATION> and in the hills and
hollows of <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> since the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE>. It's still going on in
all of those places, most always in defiance of one law or another. Not here.;
   According to <PERSON>Kenneth Ambrose</PERSON>, a sociologist at <ORGANIZATION>Marshall University</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W. Va.</LOCATION>, who has studied snake- handling, politicians in the state
of <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> have learned that it's useless to try to legislate against
something that folks want to do, just because it's for their own good.;   
Even when untreated, bites from <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s venomous snakes seldom kill
healthy adults, but they sometimes do. On the average, snakebites kill 13
Americans a year, but since <DATE>1909</DATE>, only a dozen or so of those deaths have been
traced to religious ceremonies.;    Snake-handlers believe they survive
through the power of their prayer, and they'll brook no argument on that
point.;    As an impromptu rendition of "Reach Out and Touch the Lord" blasts
through the room, the children are separated in the back of the room. The
adults are on their feet and moving. Everyone is dancing -- a free-style,
spirited, rolling shuffle- stomp. Most everyone is singing.;    Snakes are
passed from hand to hand, man to woman, woman to man, man to man, gingerly,
reverently.;    When the music stops after maybe a quarter hour of snake-
handling, the men and women almost reluctantly place the animals back in the
boxes.;    "A lot of people call us a lot of names because of the way we
choose to worship the Lord. They think we're not all there because we handle
snakes," <ORGANIZATION>Pastor Bob Elkins</ORGANIZATION> says at a microphone. "We don't try to push our
religion on anybody.";    "Yes, Jesus.";    "They say when we get bit we're
just tempting the Lord. Well, it says right in the <LOCATION>Bible</LOCATION> that the Lord can't
be tempted. It's in the Book of James.";    "Amen, Jesus.";    Then <ORGANIZATION>Elkins</ORGANIZATION>
announces: "Remember, if you're under 18, stay out of the boxes."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BILL SNEAD, Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Jolo, W. Va.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911012  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  786  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, October 12, 1991
00286066,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06198127 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06198127 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TENNESSEE; UNUSUAL; RELIGION; SERVICE; REPTILE; ACCIDENT; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A man whose stepfather appealed a state ban on snake handling to the U.S.
Supreme Court has died from a snakebite.;    Jimmy Ray Williams Jr., 28, of
Hot Springs, N.C., was bitten on the right arm by a three-foot black timber
rattler Saturday during a religious service at the House of Prayer in Jesus
Name, authorities said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WORSHIPER DIES FROM SNAKE BITE
CHURCH MEMBER DEFIED STATE LAW  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Snake handling is classified under <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> law as cruelty to animals,
punishable by six months in jail.;    "People at the house were very
close-mouthed about it, even though it's just a small misdemeanor," White Pine
Police Chief <PERSON>Jeff Manis</PERSON> said.;    <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>' father, <PERSON>Jimmy Ray Williams Sr.</PERSON>,
died in <DATE>1973</DATE> after drinking strychnine during a worship service. Snakes were
handled at his funeral.;    In <DATE>1974</DATE>, <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>' stepfather, the Rev. <PERSON>Liston
Pack</PERSON>, appealed <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION>'s snake-handling ban to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>. He
argued that it violated his right to freedom of religion. He lost.;    Pack's
brother took poison and died with the elder <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Morristown, Tenn.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910716  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  162  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 16, 1991
00198127,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880225-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-25-88 0748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SnakebiteHomicide     02-25 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Snakebite Homicide,0260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Convicted of Manslaughter in Child's Death</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ST. GEORGE, Utah (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A man who said he put a rattlesnake over
the shoulder of a 21-month-old girl to show her it would not hurt
her was convicted of manslaughter in the child's death from
snakebite.
   <PERSON>Darrell Wessendorf</PERSON>, 24, faces a possible one- to 15-year prison
sentence for the <DATE>May 8, 1987</DATE>, death of <ORGANIZATION>Stevie LuRen Kirkwood of La
Verkin</ORGANIZATION>.
   Wessendorf had been charged with second-degree murder, which
carries a possible sentence of five years to life. He had pleaded
innocent by reason of insanity.
   Wessendorf had caused a ``grave risk of death'' by bringing the
snake so close to the girl and ``engaging in activities that
eventually caused the reptile to bite the child,'' District <PERSON>Judge
J. Phillip Eves</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Wessendorf, a former Page, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, resident, said he was trying
to show the girl that the snake would not hurt her when it bit her
on the shoulder.
   He said he showed her the snake that he had found on a nearby
road and partially placed it over her shoulder. The child's mother
entered the room and screamed, causing Wessendorf to flinch and the
snake to bite the child, he said.
   Defense attorney <PERSON>J. MacArthur Wright</PERSON> argued that only <PERCENT>0.2
percent</PERCENT> of those bitten by rattlesnakes die and that those bitten
often are not treated. He said the judge had to ``make a
distinction here on what constitutes a grave risk of death.''
   Eves set sentencing for <DATE>April 11</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910826-0136
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910826-0136.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Of Skinks and Worm Snakes
   ----
   By Michael Pearce
</HL>
<DATE>
08/26/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<LP>
   Lawrence, Kan. -- For some it would have been a nightmare
come true. The forest was crowded with trees and brush on a
day that hung heavy with dark, ominous clouds, suffocating
humidity and an eerie calm that's all but unheard of in a
state named after the southwind. Except for the occasional
soothing whistle of a bobwhite quail, the woods seemed void
of natural noises.
   Yet there were plenty of unnatural sounds being made by
the two men who preceded me along a rock-strewn ridgetop. The
ring of metal against stone and the clack of stone against
stone left no doubt of their determination as the pair used
small picks and gloved hands to lift and overturn tire-sized
rocks. Errol Hooper was the first to strike pay dirt. Happy
with his find, Mr. Hooper placed it in Joe Collins's waiting
hands -- a treasure of scales, wriggling tail and flicking
tongue.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Though the small, brown-striped lizard was gently resting
in a single hand, it was as though it was being held by two
different people. On the one hand, <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> spoke as a
nationally-respected zoologist when he said, "five-lined
skink, you can tell by the head that it's a female and she's
obviously carrying an abdomen full of eggs that are about
ready to be laid. She has a regenerated tail. You can tell by
the color that her original broke off."
   Yet the excited eagerness of his fingers and the gleam in
his eyes as <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> examined the five-inch reptile were
that of a boy who's deep into an activity that he dearly
loves.
   <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON>'s affair with herpetology (the study of
reptiles and amphibians) is one that has spanned most of his
half-century of life. It began, he said, with the capture and
domestication of a queen snake from the <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> hardwoods. It
intensified quickly when he tried to learn more about
reptiles.
   "It was a really fun time when I was growing up, because
there really wasn't a lot known about these kinds of animals.
We were still in the discovery stage on a lot of things,"
said <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON>, now a herpetologist and editor for the
there was no real monetary use for reptiles, very little time
had been spent studying and writing about them. We spent a
lot of time with new and not yet discovered things. It wasn't
until <DATE>1958</DATE> that <PERSON>Roger Conant</PERSON> came out with the first handbook
for <PERSON>Peterson</PERSON> Field Guides."
   Yet it was still dozens of years before <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> began to
drop its "the only good snake is a dead snake" mentality.
Though keeping lizards and snakes for pets has long been
fashionable in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> credits <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s growing
environmental and natural awareness with a skyrocketing
interest in herpetology.
   "People are really figuring out that reptiles offer a
wealth of recreational value," said <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON>. "We're not
up there with the bird people yet, but we're growing. We have
an increasing number of herpetological societies. Back in the
late '70s I estimated their memberships at 10,000. That's got
to be 50,000 now. . .and there are many, many more who don't
belong to an organization."
   Minutes after he'd released the skink, <PERSON>Mr. Hooper</PERSON> lifted a
western worm snake from its lair. With a coal-black back and
a vivid, carnation-pink belly, the docile snake's beauty
rivaled the plumage of a cock pheasant or a drake wood duck.
And you could touch it, too.
   Unlike most wildlife observation, herping can provide a
hands-on, as well as an eyes-on, experience. "When was the
last time you heard of someone holding and stroking a
cardinal or a sandhill crane. We've sure got that aspect over
birding," joked <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON>. "You get a whole new
appreciation for living things when you can hold them and get
a feel for what they're like." And if you like them, you can
often take them home.
   "The concept of keeping reptiles is really catching on in
this country," said <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON>. "In fact, some states are
really encouraging youngsters to get a lizard, snake or
salamander for a pet. Here in <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> you can keep up to five
of any one species as long as it's not on the threatened and
endangered list. Some reptiles really adapt well to
{captivity}. That's something that's simply not true with
wild mammals and birds."
   Unquestionably the best introduction to all this is a
field guide that <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> recently co-authored with a
friend he calls "the grand old man of herpetology"<PERSON>Roger
Conant</PERSON>. "Reptiles and Amphibians Eastern/Central <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>" (<ORGANIZATION>Houghton Mifflin Co.</ORGANIZATION>, 450 pages, <MONEY>$17.95</MONEY>) gives a
detailed description of 595 species and subspecies. The book,
part of the prestigious <ORGANIZATION>Peterson Field Guide</ORGANIZATION> series, contains
more than a thousand full-color plate illustrations and
drawings, and more than 300 detailed distribution maps.
   Just as importantly, this definitive guide offers solid
information on the tools and techniques for searching for,
handling and keeping reptiles and amphibians. There's also a
chapter on poisonous snakebites, an aspect of the field that
<PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> claims adds spice to the life of a herpetologist:
"There's always been a mystique around animals that can hurt
you -- grizzly bears, mountain lions, gray wolves. .
.rattlesnakes. The danger of dying from a snakebite is
greatly exaggerated, but it can keep things interesting."
   Our herping trip got "interesting" when we left the rocky
ridge <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> nicknamed "hernia heaven" and headed for
the car. <PERSON>Mr. Hooper</PERSON> spotted a yard -- plus timber rattlesnake
stretched beside a wood rat nest. He closed to within a few
feet of the snake and watched as it lazily crawled beneath a
table-sized slab of limestone near where we stood. When its
dangerous head was well under the rock, <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> stomped
the ground to draw the rattle. The sound brought a grin to
his face that lasted for hours.
   "I've seen lots of them but there's always something
special about seeing a timber rattler," <PERSON>Mr. Collins</PERSON> later
said. "It can make a good morning even more memorable. That's
the kind of experience that we dream about."
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Pearce</PERSON> writes about the outdoors from <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06078164 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06078164 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  REPTILE; POISON; TEXAS; LETTER; SERVICE; EMPLOYEE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Neither sleet nor snow nor rain nor dark of night will keep a letter carrier
from his appointed rounds. And you can add rattlesnakes to the list.;    Ed
Brown of Brady, a 40-year-old contract letter carrier, says he's glad to be
alive after four days in the hospital as a result of his tussle with a rattler
on his rounds last week.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VENOMOUS SNAKE FAILS TO RATTLE TEXAS MAIL
CARRIER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     He started his route as usual last <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>northern McCulloch County</LOCATION>, he
said, and was planning to finish in time for his mother's funeral at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>;  
 "I had my radio on and when I pulled up beside one of the boxes, I
accidentally dropped a piece of mail. I should have known better, but I never
thought about anything except picking up that letter," <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said.;    He
opened the car door, leaned out and stuck his right hand into the weeds to
find the letter. "I saw a quick movement at the same time I felt a bite, but
between the radio and the noise of the car's motor, I did not hear a warning
rattle of the snake," he said.;    "I looked at my hand and saw blood coming
out and it immediately began hurting. I know this sounds stupid, but I kept on
delivering the mail for the next 20 or more minutes," <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said.;    He said
his swelling hand kept hurting and he tried to suck venom out of it.;    "When
I arrived in <PERSON>Lohn</PERSON> (20 miles from <LOCATION>Brady</LOCATION>), I knew I needed help. Then I
remembered I had heard that the latest treatment for snakebite is to use
high-voltage electricity, such as a spark plug or a cattle prod on the bite. I
didn't have a cattle prod, so I pulled a wire off the distributor and held my
hand against the distributor post," he said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Fort Worth Star-Telegram  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Brady, Texas  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910318  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  52D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  307  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday March 18, 1991
00078164,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890311-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-89 1322EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Snake-aholic     03-11 0800</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Snake-aholic,0820</SECOND>
<HEAD>When Viper Bit William Haast, The Viper Died</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY ISRAELSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first time <PERSON>William Haast</PERSON> brought home
poisonous snakes, his horrified mother left home for three days. She
came back only because she realized her son's interest wasn't about
to slither away.
   At 78, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> remains a self-described ``snake-aholic,'' who has
kept his energy and enthusiasm though he just weathered his 148th
snake bite. It is not surprising it was the viper, not <PERSON>Haast</PERSON>, who
passed on.
   Haast is founder and director of the <ORGANIZATION>Miami Serpentarium
Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>, which he started in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> in <DATE>1946</DATE>. He relocated the
lab to Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> five years ago to concentrate on venom
research and production.
   Haast claims to be the first to standardize snake venom and
produce it for research use. His clients include <ORGANIZATION>Wyeth Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>,
the only producer of antivenins in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, and almost every
university in the country. He also has helped foster research into
the use of venom against such diseases as polio, multiple sclerosis
and AIDS.
   Haast was in his lab collecting venom from a Pakistani pit viper
<DATE>Feb. 28</DATE> when the serpent bit his left thumb. Not overly concerned,
he waited to see if the weekly venom injections he has given himself
for 40 years would provide immunity to the poison.
   When the bite was still bleeding after 24 hours, he took himself
to the hospital and was diagnosed in critical condition, the venom
robbing his blood of the ability to clot. Doctors said he could have
bled to death from a bump or fall.
   ``I guess I excited every hematologist (blood doctor) in town,''
he said. ``They dug up all the information they had on snake bites.''
   Haast, who was released from the hospital <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, praised the
extraordinary efforts in his behalf to obtain antivenins from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and even from private sources
in <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION>. A <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> aide helped contact foreign sources and ease
passage of the medicines through Customs.
   ``Those people involved in getting the antivenins are the heroes
of the story,'' he said. ``All I am is the result of an accident.''
Haast's condition started improving after he received the serum from
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, and doctors in the end opted not to use the foreign
serums.
   The night before <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> was bitten, he and <PERSON>Nancy Harrell</PERSON>, who
helps direct the lab, went to a local steak house for what she
called ``anything goes day.''
   Sometimes at the end of the month <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> abandons a strict routine
that includes eating animal protein only on even-numbered days and
never touching refined sugar. <TIME>This night</TIME>, he consumed four chocolate
sundaes.
   ``When I let myself go, I really let go,'' he said.
   The next day, <PERSON>Harrell</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> was a little hastier than usual
in his work. ``He was really buzzing around the lab that day,'' she
said.
   He believes his strict regimen _ which also includes always
walking up the 11 flights to his condominium _ helped him overcome
the viper's venom and to cleanse his system. It wasn't until nine
days after the bite that he ate solid food. Meantime, the snake had
died of natural causes.
   Haast, first bitten in <DATE>1926</DATE>, says his interest in snakes dates
back nearly 70 years to when he collected garter snakes out of
canals in <LOCATION>Paterson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>
   In <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION>'s serpentarium near the highway to the <LOCATION>Florida
Keys</LOCATION> was as much a tourist attraction as a laboratory. Visitors
could watch from a glass-enclosed amphitheater while <LOCATION>Haast</LOCATION> extracted
venom from hundreds of different species of snakes.
   He and <PERSON>Harrell</PERSON> moved the facility to <LOCATION>Salt Lake City</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> to
focus more on research. He declines to say just how well the
business is faring except to say it's ``holding its own.''
   Haast collects venom from each snake about once a week, at the
same time they are fed a high-protein formula he mixes himself.
Harrell helps with the feedings; feeding and venom collection are
done at the same time to minimize trauma to the snakes.
   Nearly 50 years ago, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> had a hunch that snake venom may be
valuable in treating polio and was proved right. Later, he had the
same feeling about multiple sclerosis and more recently has explored
the possibility of using venom in the fight against AIDS.
   Haast and <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> businessman <PERSON>Alan Glanville</PERSON> have organized AIDS
experimental treatment and research in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Both hesitate to
discuss the project, saying it is in its infancy and the hospitals
and researchers involved require anonymity.
   Even after his latest brush with death, <PERSON>Haast</PERSON> says there is
little chance he will retire. In fact, he plans to start giving
himself booster shots to create an immunity to the species of viper
that bit him.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880609-0142 </DOCNO>
<HL> Secret Weapons System Goes on Display In England as Part of New Arms Treaty </HL>
<AUTHOR> John J. Fialka (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> EUROP FREST </CO>
<IN> ARO NUK </IN>
<G> DEF </G>
<DATELINE> GREENHAM COMMON, England  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   "Snakebite," an example of one of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most secret, high-technology weapons systems, went on display at a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> base here yesterday for the first time. 
Soon, Soviet inspectors will scrutinize the newly groomed system. 
Then, Snakebite will be sawed apart, crushed, and torched in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   It is all part of the process of removing and destroying an entire class of European-based nuclear weapons as called for in the new superpower arms treaty recently ratified by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> and the Supreme Soviet. 

   Looking like a low-slung, camouflaged truck, Snakebite and other vehicles that carry nuclear-tipped cruise missiles were put on display here and at three other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bases in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> as part of unprecedented press briefings. 
The vehicles will be the star attractions next month, when the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> formally begin the process of carrying out the arms treaty. 

   <LOCATION>Greenham Common</LOCATION>, 60 miles west of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, is home to most of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s allotment of U.S.-manned cruise missiles. 
It is one of 27 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bases that will be visited by a team of 200 Soviet inspectors in the first phase of the destruction of medium-range nuclear missiles in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
Under the treaty, effective last week, Soviet inspectors will visit here and other sites where the missiles are stored or produced in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. 
About 200 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> inspectors will tour 133 bases in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION>, said Lt. Col. <PERSON>Ken Keating</PERSON>, an official of the new <ORGANIZATION>U.S. On-Site Inspection Agency</ORGANIZATION>, at yesterday's news conference here. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, Soviet Foreign Minister <PERSON>Eduard Shevardnadze</PERSON> invited members of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> and other international bodies to watch the first round of destruction of Soviet intermediate-range nuclear missiles. 
"This, of course, is not the <ORGANIZATION>Bolshoi Theater</ORGANIZATION>, but a major premiere nonetheless, a momentous historic event," <PERSON>Mr. Shevardnadze</PERSON> said. 
He didn't say where the destruction would take place. 

   At <ORGANIZATION>Greenham Common</ORGANIZATION>, Col. <PERSON>Bill Jones</PERSON>, its commander, gave reporters a base tour, including a look at the mammoth, bunker-like garages where cruise-missile launch vehicles are stored. 
Like Snakebite, each vehicle carries four missiles, each with a thermonuclear warhead capable of incinerating a medium-sized city. 

   The Soviet inspectors "have 48 hours to tell me where they want to go" and then they will have 24 hours to examine the base, said Col. <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>. 
The inspectors will be able to measure and weigh parts of the missile system and examine it with portable radiation-detection devices. 

   The inspection job will require a full-time bureaucracy on each side. 
After the initial "baseline inspection," designed to affirm the number of missiles at each site, there will be additional inspections for three years to ensure the weapons' removal and destruction. 
A ten-year inspection period will follow to make sure new weapons aren't produced. 

   According to Lt. Col. <PERSON>Keating</PERSON>, Snakebite's missiles will be taken to <ORGANIZATION>Davis-Monthan Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, and then cut in half, lengthwise. 
The launch vehicle also will be destroyed. 
Nuclear warheads, which aren't covered by the treaty, will be removed and recycled into other weapons systems. 

   Lt. Col. <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> said each side will decide when and where to deploy its inspection teams. 
The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> doesn't know when the first Soviet visitors will arrive at <LOCATION>Greenham</LOCATION> Common or other nuclear-weapons bases. 
Women demonstrators, who have staged some memorable protests at <LOCATION>Greenham</LOCATION> Common over the past five years, showed up in only token force yesterday. 
They pushed a sign up to the base's fence that read: "Bread, not Bombs." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911212-0005
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911212-0005.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   It's Man vs. Snake
   In Guam. For Now,
   Bet on the Snake
   ---
   Millions of Slithering Serpents
   Frustrate Control Efforts;
   Will Sex Do the Trick?
   ----
</HL>
<DATE>
12/12/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<IN>
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
</IN>
<NS>
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
</NS>
<GV>
AGRICULTURE DEPARTMENT (AGD)
CONGRESS (CNG)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
INTERIOR DEPARTMENT (INR)
</GV>
<RE>
FAR EAST (FE)
GUAM (GU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   GUAM -- Tourist advisory: While in Guam, keep your toilet
seat down when not in use.
   Snakes like to come in through the toilets.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At night, they hang from trees like fat, brown strands of
cooked spaghetti. They attack <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military bases. They
slither up power poles. They wipe out entire bird
populations, attack children and crawl into homes looking for
food. Some are 10 feet long. And they're so tough they
actually can bump up against an electrified fence and keep
coming back for more.
   This is really gross.
   There are as many as three million snakes here on a land
mass of 212 square miles. That's an average of 14,000 snakes
per square mile, or 22 snakes for every man, woman and child.
Now, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government, armed with <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> from
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, is mounting a counterattack. Wildlife biologist
<PERSON>Thomas Fritts</PERSON> and a team of researchers have been zapping the
snakes silly in experimental electric corrals, luring them
into traps, testing fumigants and trying to figure out if, in
the case of snakes, sex can kill. If all else fails, they
figure maybe at least they can establish some "snake-free
zones."
   What makes this research work so difficult is the nature
of the foe. "Boiga irregularis" -- known as a brown tree
snake -- lives in trees but is equally adept on the ground,
so it's difficult to keep the snake in or out of any large
area. The snakes are hard to starve out because they will
dine on any small critter.
   Indigenous to the <LOCATION>Solomon Islands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> and northern
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, the snakes first turned up in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> shortly after
World War II, apparently as stowaways on a cargo ship. They
proliferate maddeningly fast because they have no natural
predators on <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>. For decades, the snakes were mostly
unnoticed, content to devour lizards and birds. But by the
early <DATE>1980s</DATE> local biologists discovered the snakes had wiped
out nine of 12 native birds species, critically depleted the
rest and had run so low on lizards that they began foraging
in homes for more varied food.
   "Two snakes came through the commode of my home the other
day," says <PERSON>Marilyn D.A. Manibusan</PERSON>, a territorial senator. "I
threw boiling water at them." A lot of people put screens
over their sewer vents to keep the snakes from entering via
the toilet.
   By day, the nocturnal snakes seem to disappear. Indeed,
many people in <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> say they've never seen one. But the
snakes, which are mildly poisonous, have been found coiled
around screaming infants, their mouths locked on tiny hands
in vain attempts to swallow the babies. Though no known
deaths have resulted, 53 emergency room cases of snakebites
were reported in the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Memorial Hospital</ORGANIZATION> between <DATE>1986</DATE> and
<DATE>1989</DATE>, including four in which doctors said infant victims
came perilously close to death.
   The problem finally drew widespread public attention after
the snakes began crawling over power lines and electrocuting
themselves, knocking out power in the process. Between <DATE>1978</DATE>
and <DATE>1990</DATE>, <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> was hit by an estimated 680 snake-related
outages, in some cases blacking out the entire island.
Exasperated, the <ORGANIZATION>Guam Power Authority</ORGANIZATION> wound up turning off
from dusk to dawn a utility pole that had suffered 17 faults,
effectively ceding it to the snakes.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military soon found out itself that the reptile
is a resourceful opponent. At one base, commanders ordered
the bottoms of power poles wrapped with sleeves of slick
metal in hopes of keeping the snakes off. They were chagrined
to later discover the snakes don't even go up the poles; they
prefer the supporting guy wires. So the next tack was to
erect screen-wire barriers around the guy wires. The snakes
simply climbed over.
   So, what to do?
   <PERSON>Gordon Rodda</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Cooperative Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Research Unit</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, tried to build a better snake trap.
He tried using lizards, chicken litter and quail as bait, but
found that white mice work best. "If you put out 100 traps
with quail bait, you find six snakes in them, but with white
mice you find 25 snakes out of 100 traps," he says.
   The downside: "We don't really want to import a million
white mice to <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Mr. Fritts</PERSON>. So <PERSON>Mr. Fritts</PERSON> says the
researchers hope to come up with an artificial white mouse
that can be used in its place.
   In fact, just about every solution seems to have a catch.
Officials considered importing mongooses or paying a bounty
on dead snakes. But mongooses hunt by day and sleep by <TIME>night</TIME>
-- opposite of the snakes -- and <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> officials concluded
that a bounty would only encourage enterprising entrepreneurs
to start raising snakes commercially.
   <PERSON>Earl Campbell</PERSON>, a researcher with the <ORGANIZATION>Ohio Cooperative Fish</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Research Unit</ORGANIZATION>, has designed electrified snake
fences that carry 8,000 volts. He says he has sat up <TIME>night
after night</TIME> watching surrounded snakes zap themselves -- and
then zap themselves again. In the long run, though, "the
mortality rate is <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT>," he says. But the fences are expensive
and can only be used in small areas, perhaps such as the
airport and port. They could also be used to create a few
snake-free <PERSON>Edens</PERSON>.
   Great hopes are also being placed on work being done by
<PERSON>Peter Savarie</PERSON>, a Denver-based research pharmacologist with
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>. He says methyl bromide,
in appropriate doses, kills the snakes. But that also could
only be used in small areas, and requires trained personnel.
   A snake-killing virus is one idea, but no one knows yet
which virus would do the trick. Another possibility is using
sex pheromones to attract snakes into a designated "poison
station," where they could be killed off. Great idea, except
no one knows for sure that the snakes are actually attracted
by such sex lures.
   As biologist <PERSON>Fritts</PERSON> says: "Each line of research may have
some place, but no one of them is going to solve the
problem."
   Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Guam's Division of Aquatic</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Resources</ORGANIZATION> is pushing its own modest proposal: recipes for
brown tree snake, such as snake meat in coconut milk,
deep-fried snake and sweet-and-sour snake. "I haven't eaten
it personally," says wildlife biologist <PERSON>Michael McCoid</PERSON>, "but
people who have say it's tasty, like" -- you guessed it --
"chicken."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-10706</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBGABADNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930206
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 FEB 93 / Travel: Crocodile awareness syndrome - Practical Traveller
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL THOMPSON-NOEL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FOUR years ago I spent a couple of days at <LOCATION>Nkamba Bay Lodge</LOCATION>, by the shore of
<LOCATION>Lake Tanganyika</LOCATION>, within <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>'s Sumbu national park. I could have gone
fishing. I did go for game walks, escorted by a guide, <PERSON>Olvitti Chasaya</PERSON>, and
his supremely ancient rifle. What I did not attempt, because of the
crocodiles, was to walk near the lake.
The reason I respect crocodiles is my awareness of the number of people
grabbed in recent years by the fearsome estuarine saltwater crocodiles -
'salties' - of northern <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. Mainly, estuarine crocs range from
southern <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and the Malay archipelago to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sri Lanka</LOCATION>, taking in
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Solomons</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Papua New Guinea</LOCATION>
once I asked a tribal chief what to do if chased by a croc. 'Jump in the
river,' he said brusquely. It is possible he was joking.
For a rundown on crocs, alligators and other animal (and insect) hazards
when travelling in tropical parts, you need the latest edition of <ORGANIZATION>The
Tropical Traveller</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>John Hatt</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Penguin</LOCATION>, Pounds 6.99).
The writer insists that you should never run from a wild cat. 'Although
terrifying, it is much safer to face them. One acquaintance was charged by a
tiger in <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION>. His guide rushed at the tiger, shouting and yelling. The
tiger retreated.' Other tips:
<LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> and hippopotamus are far more dangerous than lions. On <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Natal</ORGANIZATION> coast a cow hippo was once seen to plunge into the sea, seize
a 300lb shark from the surf, haul it on to the beach and trample it to
death.
Piranhas' ferocity, on the other hand, is much exaggerated (says <PERSON>Hatt</PERSON>),
though the red-bellied piranha, common in savanna ponds, can inflict
terrible bites. It is likely that most piranha wounds are caused out of
water. Landed piranhas (fishing boat or river bank) flop about and gnash
their teeth.
Sharks: you are in greatest danger when near a wriggling fish, as
spear-fishermen will confirm. Avoid night-time swimming: some of the most
dangerous species, including the tiger shark, come into the shallows at
night.
Good news about snakes: there are no dangerously venomous snakes in <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, most of <ORGANIZATION>Polynesia</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Micronesia</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Galapagos</LOCATION>, the
Canaries, <LOCATION>Malta</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Orkneys</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Shetlands</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Madagascar</LOCATION> and numerous other
islands. A South African survey showed that 74 per cent of snakebites are
inflicted below the knee, and 67 per cent below the ankle. Lesson: wear
boots and thick trousers. The snake's fangs may penetrate the trousers, but
the amount of venom delivered will be greatly reduced.
Dogs: again, do not run away. Face the dog, look fierce and bend down as if
to pick up a stone. If the dog still threatens, throw a stone at the dog's
(dogs') head(s). Dogs are not only a problem in undeveloped countries. In
the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, more than 1m dog-bites a year require hospital attention.
Mosquitoes: about 1m people a year die of malaria, but mosquitoes also carry
some 80 other diseases. Insect repellants last far longer on material
(clothes, sheets) than on your skin. Many mosquito species like to bite
ankles, so wear socks doused in repellant. 'This may deter mosquitoes more
than you think,' says <PERSON>John Hatt</PERSON>, 'because many of them begin their
investigations as close to the ground as possible.'
Hatt covers a broad range of subject matter: travel preparations, money
(carrying it, keeping hold of it), equipment, flying, health, transport and
accommodation, culture shock and so forth. There is even an index.
I especially liked his disclaimer: 'The author and publisher have tried to
make the advice and information as accurate as possible, but they accept no
responsibility for loss, injury, inconvenience or other liability arising
from any person using this book.'
Another worthwhile paperback, recently updated, is <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> By Train, by <PERSON>Katie
Wood</PERSON> and <PERSON>George McDonald</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Fontana</LOCATION>, Pounds 7.99). It is packed with
information, some of it otiose, some of it twee, but all of it well
marshalled.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731  Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06118187 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06118187 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  AMERICAN-INDIAN; RELIGION; CONTROVERSY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Prescott residents who call themselves the Smoki People no longer will dance
with live snakes in their mouths in an annual rite detested by Indians who
have called it sacrilege.;    Dropping the Indian-style performances staged in
Prescott by the mostly Anglo group every August since 1921, the Smokis instead
will try to persuade Indian tribes to send their own dancers to perform at
events sponsored by the 350-member organization.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHITE 'INDIANS' STOP SNAKE RITUAL IRRITATING
TO HOPIS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Smoki Snake Dance</ORGANIZATION>, the highlight of the annual <PERSON>Smoki Ceremonials</PERSON>, was
one of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>'s oldest non-Indian traditions and long has been a major
tourist attraction.;    "These are changing times," said "Chief Ponytail," a
36-year-old construction contractor elected leader of the Smokis in
<LOCATION>September.</LOCATION>;    <ORGANIZATION>Smoki</ORGANIZATION> tradition prohibits members from using their real names
when talking about the organization.;    "Feelings have been generated against
our dance for some time," Chief Ponytail said.;    For this year, at least,
all imitation Indian dances by <ORGANIZATION>Smoki</ORGANIZATION> members have been canceled, he said.;   
Religious and secular leaders of the <LOCATION>Hopi Tribe</LOCATION>, who demonstrated in Prescott
against the dance last year, hailed the decision as a breakthrough in cultural
understanding.;    Hopi Chairman <PERSON>Vernon Masayesva</PERSON>, who led anti-Smoki
picketing by about 100 tribal members, said <PERSON>Hopis</PERSON> "plan to go to <PERSON>Prescott</PERSON>
again, not to demonstrate, but to show the city our gratitude for hosting us
last year and to thank the <ORGANIZATION>Smoki</ORGANIZATION> for a wise decision.";    Saying that
complaints of sacrilege have arisen sporadically for 15 years, although not
all Indians objected to the dances, Chief Ponytail said, "Probably what our
job will be in the future is promotion.;    "We want to sponsor Indians who
dance. We want to lean toward artwork and basket weaving. But anything we do
will definitely steer away from imitating any religious tradition.";    The
group, whose members bear snakebite tattoos, long had maintained that its
version of the <ORGANIZATION>Snake Dance</ORGANIZATION> gave non-Indians a glimpse of a dying culture. Many
prominent Arizonans have been <ORGANIZATION>Smoki</ORGANIZATION> members through the years, including
former <PERSON>Sen. Barry Goldwater.</PERSON>;    <PERSON>Radford Quamahongnewa</PERSON>, who is snake priest at
the Hopi Reservation village of Shungopavi, called the group's announcement
"very good news.";    Hopis believe that the rattlesnakes their priests dance
with take prayers for rain to the spirit world when they are released at the
end of ceremonies.;    Smokis danced with non-venomous bullsnakes.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Arizona Republic  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Prescott, Ariz.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910427  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  13A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  389  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday April 27, 1991
00118187,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111589-0022 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134812 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 15, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
346 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SNAKE BITES THE HAND THAT'S FREEZING IT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL GRANBERRY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Aveteran snake handler at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> was bitten <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by a venomous 
mole viper, the first such incident in the zoo's history, officials said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Charles W. Radcliffe</PERSON>, 48, who has worked at the zoo three years and previously 
handled snakes at zoos in <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> and Ft. Worth, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, was listed in good 
condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night in the intensive care unit of <ORGANIZATION>UC San Diego Medical 
Center</ORGANIZATION>. Hospital officials said they expect <ORGANIZATION>Radcliffe</ORGANIZATION> to be released <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Zoo spokesman <PERSON>Jeff Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON> was about to put the mole viper into a 
freezer in preparation for feeding it to a poisonous red-headed krait from 
<LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION> when he was bitten at <TIME>9:50 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Kraits feed on other 
snakes, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said, noting that the mole viper is one of 20 "feeder" snakes 
that had arrived in a shipment from a private dealer from out of state. 
</P>
<P>
"Our curator of snakes had never seen a mole viper in 29 years," <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said. 
"He had to get a magnifying glass and count the scales on its stomach to be 
able to make a positive identification. The 20 snakes, including the mole 
viper, were not identified as to species or whether or not they were venomous. 
In fact, the mole viper looks exactly like two or three other species of 
nonpoisonous snakes." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON> was bitten on the index finger of his right hand, which 
began to "swell and hurt immediately after the bite." <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the zoo keeps 
a well-stocked supply of anti-venom for most poisonous snakes, but has no such 
serum for the mole viper. 
</P>
<P>
Coincidentally, <PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said the zoo was notified <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by officials at the 
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> Zoo that one of their handlers was bitten by an African puff adder, 
necessitating a shipment of puff adder anti-venom from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Mexico 
City</LOCATION>, via the <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> airport. He said <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> police rushed the anti-venom 
to <LOCATION>Tijuana</LOCATION> for the flight out. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jouett</PERSON> said <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON>'s was the second bite a poisonous reptile had inflicted 
on a handler, the first occurring in <DATE>1984</DATE>, when a Gila monster bit two 
handlers. But it was the first time a venomous snake had bitten a handler. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082390-0001 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 265591 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 23, 1990, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
North County Focus; Page 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2012 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
YOUR HOME MAY BE THEIR CASTLE, TOO; 
</P>
<P>
COEXISTING WITH WILDLIFE JUST A MATTER OF TOLERANCE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DIANE CALKINS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Although the ubiquitous <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> bulldozers chase many critters away 
forever, other wild animals stay on, somehow managing to survive, even thrive. 
In fact, most of the survivors, while retaining their wildness, also learn to 
take advantage of living close to man. 
</P>
<P>
Skunks often nest in basements, even between walls, and rattlesnakes rest under 
plants or on rocks in the back yard. Raccoons sneak in through cat doors and 
snack on feline food, while coyotes make meals of the felines themselves. 
</P>
<P>
Reactions of human co-habitants range from "Oh, how cute, let's feed it" to 
fright, horror -- even lethal action. The reactions depend not only on the 
sentiments of the people involved, but also the species of wildlife. 
</P>
<P>
Some creatures, such as rattlesnakes, almost always evoke a negative response, 
while others elicit mixed or sympathetic feelings. Many of the species regarded 
as nuisances are the very ones that thrive in our midst. 
</P>
<P>
"Coyotes, raccoons, skunks, starlings, sparrows and pigeons are preadapted to 
man-modified habitats," says <PERSON>Douglas Bolger</PERSON>, a graduate student in biology at 
<LOCATION>UC San Diego</LOCATION>. "They have evolved in an environment like that created by man." 
</P>
<P>
Although few people yearn for a world without wild animals, most city folks 
don't know what to do when confronted with rabbits in the ranunculus or bats in 
the belfry. Guided by common sense and tolerance, most <LOCATION>North County</LOCATION> residents 
can peacefully coexist with the remaining wild creatures. 
</P>
<P>
"For the past four years, the Humane Society of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has been 
conducting seminars on humane solutions to problems with urban wildlife," said 
<PERSON>John Grandy</PERSON>, the society's vice president for wildlife. "The seminars have 
become remarkably popular, because everyone has problems." 
</P>
<P>
The Humane Society will publish a book on the subject this <DATE>fall</DATE>. In the 
meantime, <PERSON>Grandy</PERSON> and local experts have both philosophical and practical 
