<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06010225 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06010225 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  NEW-YORK; PUBLIC; LIBRARY; BOOK  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IN 1857, Elisha G. Otis invented the passenger elevator. Fifteen years later,
William LeBaron Jenny designed the first skyscraper, a 10-story structure.;   
Naturally, someone had to invent the elevator before someone could build a
skyscraper, but the same year that gave us the skyscraper gave us the
commercial electric fan. Cool.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHADDYA WANT TO KNOW? IT'S HERE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Books  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     If these seemingly disparate historical tidbits attract you, then leaf
through "The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Public Library Desk Reference," a book full of
surprises. It is based on the more than 5 million questions the library and
its 82 branches answer each year.;    <PERSON>Vartan Gregorian</PERSON>, former president and
chief executive officer of the library, writes in his preface, ". . . unlike
annuals and almanacs that need revising and updating each year, the <ORGANIZATION>Desk
Reference</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Stonesong Press</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$34.95</MONEY>) holds a considerable amount of true
reference information, unchanging basic facts and background.;    "We also
hope that our book will be easy to read and fun to browse through.";    It
is.;    For instance, if you know <PERSON>Thomas Alva Edison</PERSON> invented the phonograph
in <DATE>1878</DATE>, you will be pleased to know <PERSON>L.O. Colvin</PERSON>  invented the milking machine
the same year, and <PERSON>James J. Ritty</PERSON>  invented the cash register the year after
that.;    These were heady times, a veritable cascade of brainstorms. But
every year was like that.;    For instance, last year was the 110th birthday
of the hearing aid, and the 120th for linoleum and the snap button. It also
was the 100th anniversary of motion pictures and the electric subway. It was
the 90th anniversary of the paper clip.;    This year is the 100th birthday of
the flashlight (by <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bristol Electric Lamp Co.</ORGANIZATION>), the aluminum boat (by
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Escher Wyss &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>) and the zipper (by <PERSON>Whitcombe L. Judson</PERSON>).;   
The Desk Reference has less esoteric fare. It tells you how to write your
member of congress and how to call toll-free for rental cars and hotels. There
are 15 pages of visa requirements to travel anywhere from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> to
Zimbabwe.;    There is an illustrated section on the human anatomy and one on
how to play board games from backgammon to Scrabble or cards  from blackjack
to solitaire.;    There is simply no way to list all of the tidy bits of
information from dietary tables to musical terms and symbols,  from extinct
animals to semaphore, from etiquette to legal forms, from animal first aid to
a directory of poison control centers.;    It's also a settler of arguments.
Take religion: The book says there are 648 million Hindus, 18 million Jews,
840 million Muslims, 158 million Orthodox Catholics, 307 million Buddhists and
5.6 million followers of Confucius.;    In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, there are 31
million Baptists, 2.7 million Episcopalians, 13.5 million Methodists, 2.8
million Mormons, 8 million Lutherans and 700,000 Jehovah's Witnesses. But
worldwide, there are 900 million Roman Catholics, the largest <ORGANIZATION>Christian Church</ORGANIZATION>
in the world. It takes 6 1/2 pages to list all the popes.;    One thing that
strikes the reader is how long ago some of the inventions sprang from the
human mind. And what in the world did mankind do before they came along?;   
We were blessed with the screwdriver and wrench about 1550 by unknown
gunsmiths.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JOHN BARBOUR, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910110  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  530  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, January 10, 1991
00010225,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901231-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-31-90 1349EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--LibraryTrivia ADV13   12-31 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Library Trivia, ADV 13,0900</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv13</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 13</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1
graphic.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By JOHN BARBOUR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV Sunday Jan. 13</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE - There is a fascination for some, usually the
doers of crossword puzzles and fans of Trivial Pursuit, in trifling
information. Here is a book of facts great and small, distilled
from millions of questions asked of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Public Library</ORGANIZATION> by
people who can't take ``don't know'' for an answer.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881031-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-31-88 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     10-31 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0652</SECOND>
<HEAD>On the Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An avid football fan is hoping to score with a
book designed to help people tell the difference between the
end-around and the end zone.
   ``Football For Men And Women Who Want To Learn The Game,''
teaches the beginning fan the fundamentals of professional
football, author <PERSON>Donna Foehr</PERSON> said. It also contains information
about college, high school, pee-wee and Canadian football, she
added.
   ``Football is not for everyone, but there are a lot of people
who want to learn more about the game,'' she said.
   Foehr, 57, of suburban <LOCATION>Bloomfield Hills</LOCATION>, said she has gone to
football games for as long as she can remember and is a
season-ticket holder for <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> Lions games.
   Almost all topics of the game are defined in the <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY> book
published by <ORGANIZATION>National Press</ORGANIZATION>, from the dimensions of the field to
little-used plays like the drop kick.
   ``It took me about five months to write the book but once that
was done, I spent about 500 hours re-editing it,'' she said. ``It
seemed that every time the publisher sent me changes in the
manuscript, I would change them back again and that went on several
times.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>OLYMPIA, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An avid football fan is hoping to score with a
book designed to help people tell the difference between the
end-around and the end zone.
   ``Football For Men And Women Who Want To Learn The Game,''
teaches the beginning fan the fundamentals of professional
football, author <PERSON>Donna Foehr</PERSON> said. It also contains information
about college, high school, pee-wee and Canadian football, she
added.
   ``Football is not for everyone, but there are a lot of people
who want to learn more about the game,'' she said.
   Foehr, 57, of suburban <LOCATION>Bloomfield Hills</LOCATION>, said she has gone to
football games for as long as she can remember and is a
season-ticket holder for <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> Lions games.
   Almost all topics of the game are defined in the <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY> book
published by <ORGANIZATION>National Press</ORGANIZATION>, from the dimensions of the field to
little-used plays like the drop kick.
   ``It took me about five months to write the book but once that
was done, I spent about 500 hours re-editing it,'' she said. ``It
seemed that every time the publisher sent me changes in the
manuscript, I would change them back again and that went on several
times.''
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MILWAUKEE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An avid football fan is hoping to score with a
book designed to help people tell the difference between the
end-around and the end zone.
   ``Football For Men And Women Who Want To Learn The Game,''
teaches the beginning fan the fundamentals of professional
football, author <PERSON>Donna Foehr</PERSON> said. It also contains information
about college, high school, pee-wee and Canadian football, she
added.
   ``Football is not for everyone, but there are a lot of people
who want to learn more about the game,'' she said.
   Foehr, 57, of suburban <LOCATION>Bloomfield Hills</LOCATION>, said she has gone to
football games for as long as she can remember and is a
season-ticket holder for <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> Lions games.
   Almost all topics of the game are defined in the <MONEY>$9.95</MONEY> book
published by <ORGANIZATION>National Press</ORGANIZATION>, from the dimensions of the field to
little-used plays like the drop kick.
   ``It took me about five months to write the book but once that
was done, I spent about 500 hours re-editing it,'' she said. ``It
seemed that every time the publisher sent me changes in the
manuscript, I would change them back again and that went on several
times.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920210-0148
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920210-0148.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Hoechst Celanese
   Restructure, Names
   Four to New Posts
</HL>
<DATE>
02/10/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B2
</SO>
<CO>
   G.HFA WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
</MS>
<IN>
CHEMICALS, PLASTICS (CHM)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
GERMANY (GE)
NEW JERSEY (NJ)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   SOMERVILLE, N.J. -- Hoechst Celanese Corp. said it
restructured its management to two executive vice presidents
and two senior vice presidents from three group presidents
and two vice presidents.
   Hoechst Celanese Corp. is the chemicals and fiber unit of
Hoechst AG, Frankfurt, Germany.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Thomas F. Kennedy</PERSON>, 49 years old, and <PERSON>Joseph H. Patterson</PERSON>,
52, were named executive vice presidents. <PERSON>Mr. Kennedy</PERSON>, who
had been president of the chemicals and specialty chemicals
groups, will add the textile fibers and technical fibers
groups, resins, fibers raw materials and administration, and
strategic business development and specialty businesses to
his responsibilities. <PERSON>Dr. Patterson</PERSON>, who had been president
of the advanced materials, advanced technology and fibers and
film groups, will add the life sciences group to his
responsibilities.
   <PERSON>Harry R. Benz</PERSON>, 54, and <PERSON>Karl E. Engels</PERSON>, 48, were named
senior vice presidents. <PERSON>Mr. Benz</PERSON>, who will continue to serve
as chief financial officer, will also head corporate finance
and accounting, the specialty polymers and waxes businesses,
the corporation's Canadian businesses, and <ORGANIZATION>Celanese Mexicana</ORGANIZATION>,
based in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Engels</PERSON>, who had been vice
president, administration, will now head the chemical group
and corporate administration.
   <PERSON>Hubert H. Huckel</PERSON>, 60, the third group president, will
continue to head the life sciences group, but will report
directly to <PERSON>Dr. Patterson</PERSON>, instead of <ORGANIZATION>Hoechst Celanese</ORGANIZATION>'s
four new appointments are effective <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
   Additionally, but not part of the reorganization, <PERSON>Donald
G. Whitcomb</PERSON>, 46, was named vice president, business
development and administration, for the life sciences group.
<PERSON>Mr. Whitcomb</PERSON>, whose position is newly created, had been vice
president and treasurer.
   Also, <PERSON>Klaus Schmieder</PERSON>, 43, was named vice president and
treasurer. <PERSON>Mr. Schmieder</PERSON>, who had been regional manager for
the <ORGANIZATION>Hoechst AG</ORGANIZATION> Asia/Pacific region, succeeds <PERSON>Mr. Whitcomb</PERSON>.
Both of these appointments were effective <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880818-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-88 0242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-CVN--Quayle-Guard     08-18 0429</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CVN--Quayle-Guard,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>No Strings Pulled to Stay Out of Vietnam, Quayle Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> aide said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that <PERSON>Dan
Quayle</PERSON> was asked, before being selected as running mate, whether
strings were pulled to get him into the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> and avoid
service in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> said none were, the aide recounted.
   ``The question was, I believe, was there any pull or some
influence in some way for him to get into the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION>. My
impression is the answer is absolutely not,'' <PERSON>Robert Teeter</PERSON> told
reporters.
   ``He, at some point said, `I simply applied, like anyone
else','' said <PERSON>Teeter</PERSON>, who oversaw <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s vice presidential
selection process.
   Quayle himself, in an interview on <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>, said he was ``almost
certain'' that the governor or lieutenant governor of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> were
not asked to help him get in the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1969</DATE>.
   ``Many of us got in,'' he said, adding that he was speaking on
the basis of recollections that are 20 years old.
   At the time, men <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>'s age were being drafted into the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>
and many were sent to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   In an interview with <ORGANIZATION>ABC News</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> said he chose the <ORGANIZATION>National
Guard</ORGANIZATION> _ rather than risking the draft _ because that course allowed
him to fulfill his military obligation and still attend law school.
   But if his <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> unit had been called up _ none were
during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War _ he said he ``would have gone and served
very proudly.''
   And he told CNN: ``I was willing and ready to serve my country.
I chose to serve my country in the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> like millions of
other people.''
   The question arose as every aspect of <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>'s life came under
intense scrutiny following his surprise selection by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   An NBC-owned <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> television station, WRC-TV, said
<PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> ``may have received help from then <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Edgar
Whitcomb</PERSON>.'' Citing Republican sources it did not name, the station
said <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> was working as an administrative assistant in the
governor's office in <DATE>1969</DATE> and <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> moved <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> to the top of a
``lengthy'' waiting list for enrollment in the guard.
   However, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>'s biography showed that he had not started
working for <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> until <DATE>1971</DATE>, two years after he joined the
<ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Jeff Nesbit</PERSON>, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> press secretary, told of the television
station's report, said: ``I can say nothing more than what he
(<PERSON>Quayle</PERSON>) said. Basically some of the other folks he went to college
with wanted to get in and most of them got in. What he said has to
stand at this time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880217-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-17-88 0552EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BabyMMovie     02-17 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Baby M Movie,0401</SECOND>
<HEAD>Television Movie To Portray Baby M Controversy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOYCE A. VENEZIA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>JoBeth Williams</PERSON> will portray surrogate mother <PERSON>Mary Beth
Whitehead-Gould</PERSON> in an <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION> television movie about the landmark court
battle over custody of ``Baby M,'' a network spokeswoman said.
   The two-part movie, to air at an undetermined date this <DATE>spring</DATE>,
will also feature <PERSON>John Shea</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dabney Coleman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bruce Weitz</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>
spokeswoman <PERSON>Laurel Whitcomb</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The goal of the movie ``is to tell the story without adopting
any one point of view,'' <PERSON>Ms. Whitcomb</PERSON> said in a telephone interview
from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   The movie will include an update at the end because the case is
still unfolding, <PERSON>Ms. Whitcomb</PERSON> said.
   The latest developments involve legal proceedings to determine
the visitation schedule for <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON>, whose parental
rights to the 22-month old child were restored in a <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey
Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> decision earlier this month.
   The state's highest court overturned a lower court decision that
upheld a <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> contract under which <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON> was
artificially inseminated with <PERSON>William Stern</PERSON>'s sperm and bore the
child for him and his wife, <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>.
   In addition to stripping <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON> of her parental
rights, the lower court last <DATE>March 31</DATE> awarded custody to the <LOCATION>Sterns</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> maintained custody for the Sterns but voided
the contract and ruled that <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON> was entitled to a
hearing on visiting the child.
   Attorneys for <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON> and the <PERSON>Sterns</PERSON> have agreed to
try to reach an out-of-court settlement on visitation rights.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON>'s attorney, <PERSON>Harold Cassidy</PERSON>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
that his client would be seeking more visitation time than the
current two hours a week.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON>, who originally called the child <PERSON>Sara</PERSON>,
``has agreed to call the child <PERSON>Melissa</PERSON> and do whatever it takes to
achieve harmony,'' the attorney said.
   Williams starred in ``The Big Chill,'' ``Poltergeist'' and
``<PERSON>Kramer vs. Kramer</PERSON>,'' and received an Emmy nomination for her part
in the TV movie ``Adam.''
   Shea, who starred in ``Witness'' and ``Windy City,'' will
portray Stern. <PERSON>Coleman</PERSON>, star of television's ``The Slap Maxwell
Story'' will star as <PERSON>Gary Skoloff</PERSON>, the attorney representing the
<PERSON>Sterns</PERSON>.
   Weitz will portray <PERSON>Mrs. Whitehead-Gould</PERSON>'s former husband,
<PERSON>Richard</PERSON>, whom she divorced last year.
   <PERSON>Robin Strasser</PERSON> will portray <PERSON>Elizabeth Stern</PERSON> and <PERSON>Anne Jackson</PERSON>
will star as <PERSON>Lorraine Abraham</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Baby M</ORGANIZATION>'s court-appointed guardian.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900604-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-04-90 0657EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-PepperSpray     06-04 0249</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pepper Spray,0257</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cayenne Spray Adds Spice to War on Thugs</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DENVER (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pocket-sized spray version of cayenne pepper is
being used by growing numbers of police agencies to temporarily
disable drunks, drug addicts and snarling dogs, the device's
manufacturer says.
   <PERSON>Gardner Whitcomb</PERSON>, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Cap-Stun Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said his company's
sales have quadrupled this year to more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>.
   More than 1,000 police agencies have switched from mace to
Cap-Stun since the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> decided to switch to the pepper spray last
<DATE>fall</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>The Denver Post</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   Women concerned about a <PERCENT>57 percent</PERCENT> surge in rapes in the <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>
area over the past year also are turning to Cap-Stun. But some
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> police officials have doubts about its effectiveness.
   ``Unless it hits you right in the open eyes, it takes too long to
incapacitate you,'' said Sgt. <PERSON>Dave Abrams</PERSON>, supervisor of the <ORGANIZATION>Denver
Police Department</ORGANIZATION>'s SWAT team. ``I've seen it take more than a
minute.''
   <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> police spray at too close a range to allow
formation of a mist that can be inhaled.
   A <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> chemist developed the spray 20 years ago when his
wife, summoned to court to testify about a holdup she witnessed,
wanted nonlethal protection against thugs who threatened her life.
   Cap-Stun is supposed to stop dogs and intoxicated or drugged
criminals, who often are unaffected or angered by mace. The pepper
attacks membranes inside the nose.
   The spray does not have lasting effects, promising reduced
brutality charges against police.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910523-0169
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910523-0169.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   They Could Be Like the French
   And Close the State for August
   ----
   By Carrie Dolan
</HL>
<DATE>
05/23/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
</RE>
<LP>
   PALO ALTO, Calif. -- Attorney Richard Such says he could
have "spent my whole life wishing vaguely to have more
vacation." But instead, he decided to work on changing
things.
   Mr. Such is launching a drive to amend the California
Constitution to grant workers six weeks off every year.
Noting that "there has been little progress in American
vacation policy since the Depression," he says the amendment
would bring "California vacation policy up to the European
standard."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   If the proposal became law, families would be able to
spend time "more meaningfully than in the classic American
frantic effort to squeeze a visit to grandma, a glimpse of
the <ORGANIZATION>Grand Canyon</ORGANIZATION> and a stop at <LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION> into two or three
weeks," <PERSON>Mr. Such</PERSON> says. More leisure time would also cure
worker burnout, he claims, as employees "return rested,
invigorated . . . with new perspectives and new ideas, ready
to do better work."
   In order to make the plan palatable to employers, workers
would have to meet certain conditions to qualify for six
weeks off, including having a high-school education, not
smoking on the job and not having convictions for drug or
alcohol abuse. Employees could skip one of the conditions by
taking public transport, car pooling or cycling to work.
   "If this gets on the ballot, it will pass overwhelmingly,"
predicts <PERSON>Mr. Such</PERSON>.
   But <PERSON>Fred Main</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>California Chamber of
Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, says it would have a "horrible economic impact." He
calls the initiative a "silly proposal with little, if any,
chance of qualifying" because it has no organized support.
   Under <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> law, any registered voter who pays <MONEY>$200</MONEY>
can submit an initiative. To qualify for the <DATE>June 1992</DATE>
ballot, a sponsor must gather 615,957 signatures.
   In the past two years, citizens have submitted 69
initiatives, including ones that would allow prayer in
school, legalize marijuana, prohibit aliens from owning land
and let juries decide whether certain laws should be on the
books. (Of those, 18 qualified for the ballot and six became
law.)
   "All {proposals} are treated equally, and given the same
scrutiny, even if some people think they're wacko," says <PERSON>Mary
Whitcomb</PERSON> of the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Justice</ORGANIZATION>'s government-law
section, which is required to review proposals. Whatever
happens, <PERSON>Ms. Whitcomb</PERSON> won't get extra time off. The six-week
vacation initiative doesn't include any government workers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910729-0026
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910729-0026.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Some Author May Write This Up
   As the American `Les Miserables'
   ----
   By Laurie M. Grossman
</HL>
<DATE>
07/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<RE>
GEORGIA (GA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   The crime report in Cobb County, Ga., looks a bit strange
these days. To the list of assaults, break-ins and armed
robberies, add: picking flowers and not returning movie
rentals.
   In a pair of cases that have local attorneys shaking their
heads, police appear to be cracking down on some fairly mild
misdeeds. Rebecca Anding, 29 years old, spent six hours in
jail on Easter Sunday after she was caught picking tulips
from an office park in Marietta, Ga. And Linda Judson, 28,
spent four hours in jail after she was arrested at her home
in late May. The charge: She hadn't returned two rentals to
her local video store after having them for a couple of
months.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "I feel like I'm negligent, irresponsible and stupid, but
I don't feel like I stole," says <PERSON>Ms. Judson</PERSON>. "If I wanted a
stupid movie, I'd buy it."
   County officials defend the arrests, saying even minor
crimes can't be ignored. But lawyers are astounded the county
is wasting its time. "It probably fits within the four
corners of the statute, but that doesn't mean it's right,"
says <PERSON>Don Samuel</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> criminal-defense attorney. "Let's
really deter people from these heinous crimes," he adds. "Why
not just use the death penalty?"
   <PERSON>Ms. Anding</PERSON> says she was cutting flowers for her
grandmother's grave when she was handcuffed and booked for
misdemeanor theft. "I was shook up," she says. But <PERSON>Patrick
Head</PERSON>, county solicitor, raises the specter of a barren
landscape: "Think what the complex would look like if
everybody could pick flowers."
   <PERSON>Ms. Judson</PERSON> contends that she put the two movies in her car
and completely forgot about them when she left the state on a
series of business trips. She says she received no written or
telephone reminder to return the films. And they weren't
charged to her credit card, the usual policy for long-overdue
videos, she says.
   <PERSON>Mark Michael</PERSON>, manager of <ORGANIZATION>West Coast Video of Smyrna</ORGANIZATION>, says
he doesn't have a credit-card number for <PERSON>Ms. Judson</PERSON> and adds
that he did call her. "We perceive it as theft," he says.
   Both women are going to court in <DATE>August</DATE> rather than plead
no contest, pay hefty fines and get a criminal record. The
maximum penalties, which <PERSON>Mr. Head</PERSON> says are absolutely out of
the question, are a year in jail and a <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> fine.
   <PERSON>Ms. Anding</PERSON> says the incident has made her cautious about
flowers, even when buying them. "I save the receipts."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881002-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-02-88 1356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-LaptopComputers Bjt   10-02 0806</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Laptop Computers, Bjt,0831</SECOND>
<HEAD>Announcements This Week Should Fuel Laptop Explosion</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER COY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Klaus K. Obermeier</PERSON> used to compute only in his
office. Now that he has a laptop computer, he computes in the back
seat of the car, on the plane, beside the pool and even, he admits,
in bed.
   <PERSON>Obermeier</PERSON>, who works for <ORGANIZATION>Battelle Memorial Institute</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, is the kind of person who is making laptop models
into one of the hottest segments of the computer business.
   Until recently, laptop computers tended to be underpowered and
overpriced, with small, poorly lit screens and batteries that ran
out at inconvenient times.
   Those problems have not been conquered completely, but enough
progress has been made to release a flood of pent-up demand among
business people, students, writers and others.
   Sales of laptop computers will surpass <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> this year and are growing at a rate of <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> annually,
   This fall, in some ways, marks the coming of age of laptop
computers.
   This week, on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NEC
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> are expected to unveil new models for the laptop market, an
industry segment where they have enjoyed some of their greatest
success in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Compaq Computer Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which disdained the market until now, is
expected to introduce its first laptop model at an <DATE>Oct. 17</DATE> press
conference in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. The Houston-based company says only that it
will announce a ``new dimension'' in personal computing.
   Finally, analysts say <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION> will
come out soon with a successor to its 2-year-old PC Convertible, a
relatively slow machine that has been criticized by computer buffs.
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Scott Brooks</PERSON> confirmed that a new laptop is planned
but would not say when it would be available.
   As a sign of the market's importance, <ORGANIZATION>Zenith Electronics Corp.</ORGANIZATION>,
which dominates the government market for laptops, has even managed
to make the machines the linchpin of its entire data systems
business.
   ``The laptop market is one that is coming into its own after
many years of really being a niche market,'' said <PERSON>Margaret
Rodenberg</PERSON>, vice president of marketing for <ORGANIZATION>Entre Computer Centers
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a retail chain.
   Laptop computers have always gotten good press, perhaps because
journalists were some of their earliest users. <ORGANIZATION>Tandy Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Radio
Shack TRS 80 Model 100 even earned an affectionate nickname on the
campaign trail _ the ``Trash 80.''
   But people who needed more computing power shied away from them.
<PERSON>John Vanden Brink</PERSON>, a consultant in <LOCATION>Des Plaines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, said he once
destroyed an entire database when he tried to transfer something
out of his <ORGANIZATION>Radio Shack</ORGANIZATION> and exceeded the memory limit.
   The newest models, in contrast, are loaded with power. Toshiba
and <ORGANIZATION>NEC</ORGANIZATION> are both announcing models this week that use <ORGANIZATION>Intel Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s
top-of-the-line 80386 microprocessor, PC Week newspaper says.
   The problem with speedy computers is they are ravenous for
electricity and drain batteries quickly. Seizing an opportunity,
<ORGANIZATION>Chips and Technologies Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, recently
introduced a set of chips that will double or triple the length of
time that many laptops can run on batteries.
   Prices for laptops are relatively high _ <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> _
because of the expense of the batteries, energy-saving CMOS memory
chips and the complex technology of flat screens.
   The flat screens of laptops flip up like the top of a clamshell
and usually display 25 lines at a time, in comparison to the 40
lines of a regular personal computer. Brightness and contrast,
although much improved, still don't match those of full-sized PCs.
   Once on the road, laptop owners have abundant headaches: No
place to recharge batteries, no modular phone jacks, hotel phone
switches that can't handle data transmissions, 3{-inch disks that
aren't compatible with other people's 5\-inch disks.
   Still, something keeps laptop users tapping away.
   Laptops, like cellular phones, allow people to keep working
while others are stuck in traffic or thumbing through the in-flight
magazine. They also encourage spontaneity by letting people record
or try out ideas while they are fresh.
   ``I would say there's like a 150 to <PERCENT>200 percent</PERCENT> improvement in
my productivity. I can't even think with a paper and pencil
anymore,'' said <PERSON>Jeffrey Greene</PERSON>, a laptop enthusiast who works in
the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> office of <ORGANIZATION>Hay Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a Washington-based
personnel consulting firm.
   Of course, working through the night on a laptop on a long
flight can be bad for one's public image, said <PERSON>Jerry Whitcomb</PERSON>, a
consultant at <ORGANIZATION>Atlanta-based Management Science America Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``People think you're a workaholic,'' <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON>, nonetheless, is a confirmed laptop user. He even uses
it in the office: ``It does everything a regular PC does so I don't
need to have both,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA070490-0014 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 242462 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 4, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 9; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
455 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AIRWAVES TURN PATRIOTIC FOR FOURTH OF JULY; 
</P>
<P>
RADIO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID ROBERTSON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
SPECIALS: KRTH-FM (101.1) for the 13th year airs its "Firecracker 300," which 
counts down the top 300 pop hits ever, according to an audience survey. . . . 
<PERSON>Shadow Steele</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Pirate Radio</ORGANIZATION> (100.3 FM) will celebrate the holiday by 
broadcasting from <LOCATION>Gladstone</LOCATION>'s 4-Fish in <LOCATION>Malibu</LOCATION>, noon until <TIME>4 p.m</TIME>. The coverage 
continues with a free fireworks display from a barge off the coast from <TIME>9 p.m. 
to midnight</TIME>. Information: GL4-FISH. 
</P>
<P>
At <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> KIIS (102.7 FM) begins to provide periodic coverage of the Rose Bowl 
Americafest, a five-hour combination of fireworks, music and marching bands. In 
addition to what is touted as the largest pyromusical event on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, 
the Rose Bowl celebration features performances by <PERSON>Wilson Phillips</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michael 
Bolton</PERSON>, <PERSON>Glenn Medeiros</PERSON>, The Cover Girls, <PERSON>Alisha</PERSON> and A'me <LOCATION>Lorain</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Rick Dees</PERSON> will 
appear on the program along with others from the KIIS crew, including <ORGANIZATION>Magic 
Matt</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hollywood Hamilton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ellen K.</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
MUSIC: KCRW-FM (89.9) will pay tribute to two musical giants, <PERSON>Irving Berlin</PERSON> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Louis Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>. Host <PERSON>Ian Whitcomb</PERSON> features rare and unusual recordings of 
<LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> songs from noon until <TIME>3 p.m</TIME>. One such piece will be "Reaching for the 
Moon" which was deleted from the <DATE>1929</DATE> movie of the same title. <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> is heard 
singing "This Is the Army <PERSON>Mr. Jones</PERSON>" from his <DATE>1942</DATE> Broadway Review "This Is the 
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>." A patriotic <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> wrote the review to help the war cause, according to 
program host <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON>, who said of the composer's rare recordings, "People 
forget that he was a performer before he became a song writer. He was probably 
very critical of himself." 
</P>
<P>
Also on <ORGANIZATION>KCRW</ORGANIZATION>, from 3 to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Louis Armstrong</LOCATION>, who would have been 90 years 
old today, is revealed via recorded interviews with <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> himself as well 
as other musicians and music critics. Host <PERSON>Billy Taylor</PERSON> explores <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION>'s 
influence on the Swing Era and modern pop music. 
</P>
<P>
Music personality <PERSON>Don Kirshner</PERSON> begins the day at <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME> on <ORGANIZATION>KRLA</ORGANIZATION> (1110 AM) with 
a special look at the "British Invasion" of music in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> during the '60s. 
Featured groups on this four-hour program include the Beatles, <PERSON>Herman</PERSON>'s 
Hermits, the Animals, the Rolling Stones and others. 
</P>
<P>
KRLA will then move to <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION> for its Fourth of <DATE>July '50s</DATE> Beach Bash at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Newport Dunes Resort</ORGANIZATION>, beginning a live broadcast at <TIME>9 a.m. 
</P>
<P>
KLOS</TIME> (95.5) will present <PERSON>Joe Walsh</PERSON> from 6 to <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME> live at the <ORGANIZATION>Fountain 
Valley Festival</ORGANIZATION>, a holiday carnival with rides, booths and food. 
</P>
<P>
KLSX (97.1 FM) airs a six-hour Westwood One program at noon called "Sixties at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Beeb</ORGANIZATION>," featuring British groups that appeared on the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> during the '60s. 
The program will include music as well as recorded interviews with <PERSON>David Bowie</PERSON>, 
members of <ORGANIZATION>Pink Floyd</ORGANIZATION> and others. <PERSON>DAVID ROBERTSON</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
List 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040689-0153 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 40531 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 6, 1989, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
<P>
Correction Appended 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
449 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LONGTIME LAGUNA BEACH RESIDENT; 
</P>
<P>
JOAN SELZNICK, OF THE MOVIE FAMILY, DIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID REYES, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan Selznick</PERSON>, a member of one of <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s most celebrated families, died at 
her <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION> home, a family spokesman said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
A spokesman for the <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> coroner's office said <PERSON>Selznick</PERSON>, 58, was found 
dead at her residence <DATE>March 28</DATE>. A preliminary autopsy report says that she had 
died of natural causes <DATE>March 27</DATE>. The coroner's office is waiting for 
toxicological tests to be completed, the spokesman said. 
</P>
<P>
She was born <PERSON>Joan Selznick</PERSON> to agent <PERSON>Myron Selznick</PERSON>, who helped launch the 
careers of some of the biggest names of the silent screen, including <PERSON>Olive 
Thomas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Constance Talmadge</PERSON>, <PERSON>Owen Moore</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lew Cody</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bert Lytell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Corinne Griffith</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Marjorie Daw</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Myron Selznick</PERSON> married Daw, <PERSON>Joan</PERSON>'s mother, but they were divorced in <DATE>1942</DATE>, 2 
years before he was to die in his mid-40s of an internal hemorrhage. Joan was 
14 at the time and living in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> with her mother. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Name Changes 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan</PERSON> had changed her name several times, however. The name listed on the death 
certificate is <PERSON>Frances Whitcomb</PERSON>, said <PERSON>Geoffrey Selznick</PERSON>, a cousin of <PERSON>Joan</PERSON> and a 
film producer in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Geoffrey Selznick</PERSON> said <PERSON>Joan</PERSON> had been married and divorced twice and that "for 
reasons we don't know" took the name of <PERSON>Frances Whitcomb</PERSON>. She had no children. 
She had been living in <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION> for at least 20 years, he said, as a "very, 
very private person." 
</P>
<P>
"She loved it in <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Geoffrey Selznick</PERSON> said, "but she was a recluse, 
and the neighbors report that she had not been out of the house in the <DATE>last 10</DATE> 
to 12 years." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan Selznick</PERSON> inherited some prime real estate from her father, including the 
corner plot in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> now occupied by the <ORGANIZATION>Neiman Marcus</ORGANIZATION> department 
store, which is leasing the land. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Uncle Was Producer 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan</PERSON>'s uncle was producer <PERSON>David O. Selznick</PERSON>, whose most successful film was 
"Gone With the Wind," released in <DATE>1939</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
She was the granddaughter of <PERSON>Lewis J. Selznick</PERSON>, one of the film industry's 
early moguls. 
</P>
<P>
Legend has it that her father brought <PERSON>Vivien Leigh</PERSON> to <PERSON>David Selznick</PERSON> during the 
filming of the burning of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and told him, 'Here's your Scarlett."' 
</P>
<P>
At the time, <PERSON>David Selznick</PERSON> had tested other actresses but had not made a final 
selection for the coveted role of <PERSON>Scarlett O'Hara</PERSON>, the heroine of the story. 
</P>
<P>
The county public administrator/guardian's office has opened an investigation 
to help settle <PERSON>Joan Selznick</PERSON>'s estate. The office routinely opens such an 
investigation after a resident dies alone, a spokeswoman said. 
</P>
<P>
Graveside services will be <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Pacific View Memorial Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Newport 
Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
She is survived by several other cousins, including film producer <PERSON>Daniel 
Selznick</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Florence Howard of Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<CORRECTION-DATE>
<P>
April 7, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</CORRECTION-DATE>
<CORRECTION>
<P>
FOR THE RECORD 
</P>
<P>
An obituary Thursday for Joan Selznick of Laguna Beach was accompanied by the 
wrong photograph. The photograph was of Joan Selznick of Los Angeles, who 
married Daniel Selznick, a cousin of the deceased woman. The Times regrets the 
error. 
</P>
</CORRECTION>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Joan Selznick 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900228-0286 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-28-90 1940EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-DesignShow     02-28 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Design Show,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>Design Show Highlights Engineering Technology</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHERINE SCOBEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Innovations expected to propel the manufacturing
industry into the future, including video headsets and floating
concrete, are on display at the <ORGANIZATION>National Design Engineering Show</ORGANIZATION>
and Conference.
   About 25,000 engineers are expected to converge on <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s
lakefront <ORGANIZATION>McCormick Place</ORGANIZATION> through <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to see new designs from
companies such as <ORGANIZATION>Dow Chemical Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Minnesota Mining &amp;
Manufacturing Co.</ORGANIZATION> _ even <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   Many of the products and materials on display represent minor
advances _ a fiber that resists fading just a bit longer, for
example. Nevertheless, consumers will feel the effect of the new
technology.
   ``You and I, ultimately, in some way will be related or involved
with every single product in this show, whether it's paint on an
automobile or the <DATE>spring</DATE> in the seat or the knobs to turn on your
hi-fi,'' said <PERSON>Robert Rosaler</PERSON>, director of an engineering conference
conjunction with the show.
   Some new products debuting at the show take a broader step into
the future.
   For example, a <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> company is showing a miniature
video display monitor slightly larger than a lipstick. Through the
use of a magnifying lens, the one-inch display window produces an
image that looks as though it is on a 12-inch screen.
   ``This is basically the walkman of the future. It's a
videoman,'' said <PERSON>Raymond Hoffer</PERSON>, a representative of Reflection
Technology of <LOCATION>Waltham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   By <DATE>Christmas</DATE>, the mini video monitor is due to appear in stores
as a component in a 5-by-2 inch paperless pocket fax machine, said
<PERSON>Neil Golden</PERSON>, director of sales for <ORGANIZATION>Reflection Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   The 2-ounce terminal can display 25 lines of 80 characters each
on a red-and-black screen. It can attach to a headband that
positions the video screen a few inches in front of the eyes,
allowing a person to look up information while leaving the hands
free to work.
   At least eight other companies plan to use Reflection
Technology's monitor in products including a 5-by-3 portable
computer and a patient monitor that doctors can wear in the
operating room, Golden said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is at the show ``to make the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> engineering and
scientific community aware that there is <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> technology available
that they may use,'' said <PERSON>Walter Heiland</PERSON>, manager of the agency's
<ORGANIZATION>Technology Utilization Office</ORGANIZATION>.
   The space agency has a history of spinning off its technological
advances.
   For example, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s need in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> for a tool that Apollo
astronauts could use to scoop up moon rocks, resulted in hand-held
cordless vacuum cleaners that eventually reached consumers. More
recently, a version of a pump developed for the Viking Mars lander
has been implanted in people to deliver medicine such as insulin.
   3M is showcasing a lightweight concrete subsitute called
Macrolite that weighs about a third as much as the real thing.
   To illustrate, 3M representatives filled a tub with water and
put in two ``concrete'' logs. One sinks. The other, made of the
substitute, floats.
   Developed by 3M in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the lightweight concrete can be used
for building in earthquake-prone areas.
   ``You can build the same high-rise buildings, only much lighter,
so when they sway they don't topple over,'' said <PERSON>William Whitcomb</PERSON>,
a company representative.
   3M says the ceramic substance, pumped with air, is a better
insulator than concrete. An 8-inch wall of Macrolite provides the
insulating power of 65 inches of concrete, <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> said.
   Dow Plastics, a division of <LOCATION>Midland</LOCATION>, Mich.-based Dow, is on hand
with a product it has no intention of producing _ a plastic,
elliptical lawnmower that cuts a swath about a foot wider than
traditional push mowers.
   Plastic allows a bigger machine that is no tougher to push than
steel and aluminum models, said mower designer <PERSON>Robert Cleereman</PERSON>.
   The idea is to show commercial engineers that plastics _
particularly Dow plastics _ can be used in place of metals and
woods, said <PERSON>Cleereman</PERSON>, who also is director of <ORGANIZATION>Dow</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Materials
Engineering Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Here's an example where plastics not only do it as well, they
do it better,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06113090 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06113090 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEPHONE; SERVICE; TECHNOLOGY; RELATION; PROFESSIONAL; BASEBALL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  If ever you doubted that civilization is going straight into the tank, wonder
no more.;    The decline of America, and everything good about it, can pretty
much be traced by the proliferation of telephones. Not just the number, of
course, but where they're ending up.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PLEASE DON'T PHONE ME AT THE OLD BALLGAME
FAN BALKS AT PITCH FOR PHONES IN THE STANDS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Around The Bay  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     No doubt you've read, or more likely somebody has called to tell you, that
the <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> and A's now offer at-your-seat telephone service during weekday
baseball games.;    "It's sort of a far-out idea still for some people," says
<PERSON>Lorreta Whitcomb</PERSON>, who speaks for Cellular One, a key instigator in the
scheme.;    For others, it's sort of a pain in the butt.;    <ORGANIZATION>Like Giants</ORGANIZATION>
fanatic <PERSON>Ellen Chandler</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, who arrived at Candlestick Park
recently with her headset radio, binoculars, score card, hat decorated with
<ORGANIZATION>Croix de Candlestick</ORGANIZATION> pins and the full expectation of reveling in the ecstasy
of day baseball on a day when ordinarily she would be at work.;    Uh-uh. In
the bottom of the second, with <PERSON>Matt Williams</PERSON> at bat, Cellular One came calling
for <PERSON>Ellen Chandler</PERSON>. She had a call from <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>. As she was trying to figure
out what was going on and how to work her way from her seat in the middle of
the row to the aisle and the cellular telephone, <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> lofted one over the
left field fence. Home run.;    Did she see it?;    "Yeah," she lied. "Well, I
didn't see where the ball landed.";    Seems a friend -- or by now a former
friend -- knew where <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> was sitting and had set up a three-way
conference call among old chums. In short, the technology had fallen into the
wrong hands.;     "He's <PERSON>Mr. Telephone</PERSON>," <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said. "He's always calling
from his car.";    Face it, telephones do not belong in cars, on planes or on
trains. You should not carry them in your pocket, and anyone who brings one to
the golf course should be shot.;    They certainly do not belong in the
bathroom, where they are turning up with disturbing regularity. What call
could be important enough to interrupt <ORGANIZATION>Nature</ORGANIZATION>'s own, with the possible
exception of an emergency ring for toilet paper. Even then, whom are you going
to call and what exactly are you going to say?;    For years we survived quite
nicely with a phone at home, one at work and a pay phone here and there. But
now, that's just not good enough.;    "It's EASY &amp; FREE," the publicity pieces
sent to baseball fans trumpet. "You can return calls FREE from your seat with
mobile phones brought to you by CELLULAR ONE.";    First the wave, then dot
racing, now this.;     If you're just too important to break away -- or even
if you just think you are -- here's how this deal works. First, give your
boss, partners, clients, bookie or probation officer the special number that
will put them through to helpful cellular people at Candlestick or the
<ORGANIZATION>Coliseum</ORGANIZATION>. Then give the same helpful celluloids your seat number.;    When
that vital call comes, a Cellular Oner will rush over with the message and a
space-age phone that will let you call the all-important person back.;   
"It's the greatest thing in the world," insists <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON>, "to be interrupted
at the game to hear that you just saved <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> or you just made <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>.";   
Good news to be sure, but can't it wait? What are you going to do? Run up and
buy 8,000 bags of peanuts and 3,000 or so beers with your new-found wealth?;  
 Of course not. You could never carry all that.;    The simple solution: Don't
conduct business at the ballpark. Just don't. Anyone caught doing so should be
tossed immediately. Give those seats to someone who wants to watch batting
practice, debate the infield fly rule, chomp on peanuts or quaff a beer.;   
Go to the ballpark to get away from business. Sneak out of work. Get sick. Go
see a mysterious client in <LOCATION>The City</LOCATION>. At most, slide over to the pay phone
before the first pitch, beer firmly in hand. Tell your boss you've run into a
couple of "bottlenecks" that will keep you out the rest of the day.;    It's
an old one, but a good one. Now, excuse me, I've got a call to make.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MIKE CASSIDY, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910422  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  718  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 22, 1991
00113090,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA052289-0009 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 60211 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 22, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 2; Column 3; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
130 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEOPLE: L.A. COUNTY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
group, announced that <PERSON>Ray W. Judson</PERSON> has been appointed president. <PERSON>William E. 
Leonhard</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive, also announced the following changes: 
</P>
<P>
Chief Financial Officer <PERSON>Thomas L. Langford</PERSON> was elected to the board and 
promoted to executive vice president. <PERSON>Leonard J. Pieroni</PERSON> was promoted to 
replaced <PERSON>Judson</PERSON> as president of the <ORGANIZATION>Ralph M. Parsons Co.</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, and 
<PERSON>William E. Hall</PERSON> was named senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>RMP</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>RMP</ORGANIZATION> unit also announced the promotions of <PERSON>Dennis E. Pisula</PERSON> to vice 
president-petroleum and chemical division, and <PERSON>Sanford Holst</PERSON> to vice president 
and manager, management systems department. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-15020</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJTEUADJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 94 / Arts: Lucinda Childs - Dance
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CLEMENT CRISP
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in the early <DATE>1960s</DATE> dance experiment was centred on <ORGANIZATION>Judson
Church</ORGANIZATION>. There the earnest and the eager set about forging a new dance -
post-modern, post-Cunningham - which sought a radical re-shaping of
everything that 'dance' had meant up to then.
It was, I suppose, symptomatic of its time, and marked by a Puritanism that
accorded well with current theatrical and musical austerities. One of
<PERSON>Judson</PERSON>'s formative figures was <PERSON>Yvonne Rainer</PERSON>, who declared 'No to spectacle;
No to virtuosity; No to transformations and magic and make-believe . . .' (I
saw a <ORGANIZATION>Rainer</ORGANIZATION> performance, which was crucifyingly boring, and offered no
substitute for anything at all - least of all dance). An ideal had been
stated for many who followed in her unlovely footsteps.
This year <PERSON>Lucinda Childs</PERSON>, one of the most acclaimed <PERSON>Judson</PERSON> graduates, is
making a first British visit with her company. Sophie Constanti reported
here on her <ORGANIZATION>Edinburgh Festival</ORGANIZATION> debut; on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, as the <ORGANIZATION>Dance
Umbrella</ORGANIZATION> season got under way, <PERSON>Miss Childs</PERSON> and her troupe came to the <ORGANIZATION>South
Bank</ORGANIZATION> - a glum and not inapt location. The <PERSON>Childs</PERSON> manner offers small cells
of activity which repeat and repeat, re-align and slowly mutate - it is no
accident that she uses minimalist scores as accompaniment - so that the
viewer is made aware of a cumulative structure.
This building-blocks approach to dance would be more fascinating - as the
Shades entry in <LOCATION>Bayadere</LOCATION> is fascinating in its repetitions and augmentation
 -were the blocks themselves of interest. But to pile up banalities, to
shift their direction, to pass them among a cast like so many tiny
austerities, is not so much architecture as parsimony.
The major piece in <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s programme was Available Light, almost an hour
of routines set below and on a bridge-structure. First made as a museum
installation in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> <DATE>a decade ago</DATE>, it has a score by <PERSON>John Adams</PERSON> which
is vastly more enterprising in the working out of its patterns than <PERSON>Childs</PERSON>'
movement sequences. Ten dancers (looking like sci-fi laboratory assistants
in overalls that reveal pallid inner legs and arms) tread and re-tread their
well-worn paths. Virtuosity is Rainer-ishly denied - the cast look
unstretched - and the development of these ideas is simple-minded. ('Those
two have just turned and run. That means that the other two in black, and
then the four in red, will do the same' - and they do). Miss <PERSON>Childs</PERSON>
manifests herself twice, Cunningham-fashion, but even in these unambitious
technical surroundings, her performance has a constrained air.
The second piece, Concerto, dates from last year and uses <PERSON>Gorecki</PERSON>'s
harpsichord concerto. It lasts nine minutes, and its dancers, in smart black
shirts and trousers, nip along pre-destined tracks with something like
vivacity. (The trams are moving faster). Here <PERSON>Childs</PERSON>' style matches the
motor energy of the score in recurring patterns of action, if not in
emotional density. The piece is short enough for the message to seem
intriguing without turning into an acreage of tape-loop repeats. Brevity is
not the soul of post-modernism - but it is a tremendous bonus here.
<PERSON>Lucinda Childs</PERSON> is at the <PERSON>Queen Elizabeth Hall</PERSON> until <DATE>October 20</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7929 Entertainers and Entertainment Groups.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911113-0060
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911113-0060.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Human Services Group
</HL>
<DATE>
11/13/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<RE>
COLORADO (CO)
CONNECTICUT (CT)
MICHIGAN (MI)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- A small human services agency that pairs
disabled foster children with welfare families was the first
group to receive a new award for Nonprofit Innovation from
Peter F. Drucker, one of America's most prominent management
gurus.
   Judson Center, Royal Oak, Mich., won the $25,000 prize for
boosting the independence and self-sufficiency of
participants in its "Living in Family Environments" program.
Judson moves developmentally disabled foster children out of
hospitals and other institutions; families receive salaries
and training to care for the children, trading their public
support for earned income.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "This group has a very clear focus and the results are
startling," <PERSON>Mr. Drucker</PERSON> said.
   Some 809 nonprofit groups applied for the award,
administered by a nonprofit foundation and research center
that <PERSON>Mr. Drucker</PERSON> started last year. He said he established
the annual award because many nonprofit organizations,
particularly small ones, "aren't recognized and encouraged"
enough for their social contributions and management
strategies.
   Four nonprofit organizations received honorable mentions
in the contest: <ORGANIZATION>Gleaners Community Food Bank</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>;
<ORGANIZATION>Connecticut Association for Human Services</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>;
<ORGANIZATION>Intercultural Development Research Association</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>Regis University</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021590-0112 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 176693 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 15, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Westside; Part J; Page 14; Column 5 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1346 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SPORTSCOPE; 
</P>
<P>
PEPPERDINE AND LOYOLA WILL SLUG IT OUT IN 3-GAME SERIES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Pepperdine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Loyola Marymount</ORGANIZATION> baseball teams, preseason favorites in the 
<ORGANIZATION>West Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION>, will meet in a three-game series this <DATE>weekend</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>George 
C. Page Stadium</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Westchester</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The teams will play a single game at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and a double header at <TIME>11 
a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> . 
</P>
<P>
Pepperdine is 4-4 overall and 2-1 in conference. The Lions are 6-4, 2-1. The 
Waves are ranked 23rd nationally by <LOCATION>Baseball America</LOCATION> and 29th by <ORGANIZATION>Collegiate 
Baseball</ORGANIZATION>. The Lions are ranked 13th by <LOCATION>Baseball America</LOCATION> and are unranked in the 
other poll. 
</P>
<P>
The Waves, who opened conference play by winning two of three games from the 
<ORGANIZATION>University of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION>, will play at <TIME>2:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>UC Irvine</ORGANIZATION> and 
play host to <LOCATION>Cal State Los Angeles</LOCATION> at <TIME>2:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Eddy D. Field 
Stadium</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Pepperdine Coach <PERSON>Andy Lopez</PERSON> is pleased with his team's .327 batting average but 
displeased with his relief pitching. "We have lost a few late-inning leads 
because we cannot find someone to take charge on the mound," he said. "Right 
now I am searching for a pitcher who can be a stopper for us." 
</P>
<P>
Top hitters for the Waves are <PERSON>Mike Truschke</PERSON>, batting .458; freshman <PERSON>Dan 
Melendez</PERSON> at .444, freshman <PERSON>Steve Rodriguez</PERSON> at .379 and <PERSON>Chris Martin</PERSON> at .364 
with a team-high 13 runs batted in. 
</P>
<P>
The No. 5 Pepperdine women's tennis team, led by <PERSON>Ginger Helgeson</PERSON> and 5-1 as the 
week began, will play host to No. 6 USC at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> and No. 16 
University of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> . 
</P>
<P>
Last week <PERSON>Helgeson</PERSON> became the first Wave woman to win a major college singles 
championship. She defeated <PERSON>Andrea Farley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, 6-3, 2-6, 7-5, in the 
final of the <ORGANIZATION>Intercollegiate Tennis Coaches Assn.</ORGANIZATION>'s national indoor hardcourt 
championships in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The No. 2 <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> women's tennis team (5-0) will entertain <LOCATION>U. S. International</LOCATION> at 
<TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at the Sunset Canyon courts and <DATE>play Saturday</DATE> at <LOCATION>San Diego 
State</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The No. 3 UCLA men's tennis team (8-0 at the start of the week) will open 
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference action when it plays host to <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> 
<DATE>Friday</DATE> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Tennis Center</ORGANIZATION> on 
campus. 
</P>
<P>
The Bruins will play at <LOCATION>Pepperdine</LOCATION> at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> . 
</P>
<P>
At last week's ITCA championships, the Bruin doubles team of <PERSON>Bill Barber</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Mark Quinney</PERSON> were eliminated in the quarterfinals by <PERSON>Luis Ruette</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Sandon 
Stolle of Texas Christian</ORGANIZATION>, 6-3, 7-6 (7-5). 
</P>
<P>
The No. 16 Pepperdine men's tennis team (3-1 as the week began) will play host 
to Rice at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and to No. 3 <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> . 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Waves shut out <ORGANIZATION>U.S. International</ORGANIZATION>, 8-0. 
</P>
<P>
The top-ranked <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> men's volleyball team (9-0 overall, 4-0 in the <ORGANIZATION>Western 
Intercollegiate Volleyball Assn.</ORGANIZATION> at the start of the week) will play <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
<TIME>night</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION> (2-3, 0-2) and entertain No. 9 Pepperdine (5-1, 3-1) at 
<TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Pauley Pavilion</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Bruins won the championship of the <ORGANIZATION>George Mason University</ORGANIZATION> 
tournament, defeating the host school in the finals in four games. In the first 
round, <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> posted a four-game victory over <LOCATION>Ball State</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Against <ORGANIZATION>Ball State</ORGANIZATION>, middle blockers <PERSON>Mike Whitcomb</PERSON> and <PERSON>Trevor Schirman</PERSON> combined 
for 33 kills and 11 blocks. In the <PERSON>George Mason</PERSON> match, <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> had 20 kills 
without an error, and <PERSON>Schirman</PERSON> had a season-high 15 blocks. 
</P>
<P>
Schirman was named the tournament's most valuable player, and <PERSON>Whitcomb</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> 
freshman Rich Bland were selected on the all-tournament team. 
</P>
<P>
The No. 9 Pepperdine men's volleyball team (5-1 overall, 3-1 in the WIVA as the 
week began) will play at No. 6 <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State</ORGANIZATION> (6-5, 0-3) at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
and at No. 1 <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> (9-0, 4-0) at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Pauley Pavilion</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Waves defeated UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> in four games to improve their road 
record to 4-0. Outside hitter <PERSON>Geoff Hart</PERSON> led Pepperdine against the Anteaters 
with 16 kills, freshman middle blocker <PERSON>Tom Sorenson</PERSON> had 12 kills and nine 
blocks, and middle blocker <PERSON>Brian Merrick</PERSON> had 11 kills and five blocks. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hart</PERSON> has a team-high 96 kills, <PERSON>Sorenson</PERSON> has 91 kills and leads the team with 49 
blocks and 13 service aces. Merrick has 86 kills and is hitting a team-high 
.589. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Karch Kiraly</PERSON>, former <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> All-American who starred on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> volleyball team 
that won a gold medal at the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympics, has been selected as the Player of 
the <DATE>1980s</DATE> in the <ORGANIZATION>Western Intercollegiate Volleyball Assn.</ORGANIZATION> by a vote of 
conference coaches. 
</P>
<P>
Other players on the All-1980s first team are <PERSON>Tim Hovland</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Dusty Dvorak</ORGANIZATION> and 
<PERSON>Steve Timmons</PERSON> of <LOCATION>USC</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Asbjorn Volstad</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pepperdine</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jeff Stork</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Second-team members are <PERSON>Ricci Luyties</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doug Partie</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bob Ctvrtlik</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Pepperdine</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pat Powers</PERSON> of <LOCATION>USC</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Scott Fortune</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Allen Allen</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Honorable mention went to <PERSON>Craig Buck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Troy Tanner</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pepperdine</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Adam 
Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bill Yardley</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Peter Vidmar</PERSON> International Boys' <ORGANIZATION>Gymnastics Invitational</ORGANIZATION> will be held at 
<TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Feb. 24</DATE> and 25 at <ORGANIZATION>University High School</ORGANIZATION>, 11800 <ORGANIZATION>Texas St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>West Los 
Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
More than 350 boys from 25 states and three foreign countries will compete in 
the event sponsored by <PERSON>Vidmar</PERSON>'s foundation and the <ORGANIZATION>Broadway Gymnastic School 
and Foundation</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Vidmar</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>UCLA All-American</ORGANIZATION>, was on the gold-medal <PERSON>U. 
S.</PERSON> gymnastics team at the <DATE>1984</DATE> Olympics and also won a gold and a silver medal 
in individual competition at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> games. 
</P>
<P>
The invitational will feature competitors ranging from age 7 to elite gymnasts 
in their 20s. Top gymnasts at the <DATE>Feb. 25</DATE> session will include <PERSON>Charles Lakes</PERSON> of 
the <DATE>1988</DATE> <PERSON>U. S. Olympic</PERSON> team, former <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> star and <PERSON>U. S.</PERSON> national team member 
<PERSON>David St. Pierre</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Tony Pineda</PERSON>, who also competed for <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and in the <DATE>1988</DATE> 
Olympics, and is <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s national champion. 
</P>
<P>
For tickets, call (213) 450-0012. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> women's basketball team (13-8 overall and 8-3 in the Pac-10) will play 
tonight at <ORGANIZATION>UC Berkeley</ORGANIZATION> (13-8, 5-6) and <DATE>Saturday</DATE> (2-17) at No. 2 Stanford (20-1, 
10-1). 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Bruins defeated <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>90-75</DATE>, and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, 73-69. Against 
<ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Rehema Stephens</PERSON> had career-highs of 33 points and 12 rebounds. 
</P>
<P>
Trying to snap a four-game losing streak, the <LOCATION>Pepperdine</LOCATION> women's basketball 
team (12-12 overall and 3-7 in the <ORGANIZATION>West Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION> as the week started) 
will play host to <ORGANIZATION>Loyola Marymount</ORGANIZATION> (13-11, 6-4) at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> at 
<ORGANIZATION>Firestone Fieldhouse</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Shannon Frowiss</PERSON> leads the Waves with averages of 18.1 points and eight rebounds 
a game, while <PERSON>Sherri Murrell</PERSON> is averaging 12.8 points and a team-high 4.9 
assists. 
</P>
<P>
The top-ranked <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> women's softball team (4-2) begins play today in the 
<ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION> tournament, which ends <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. UCLA will play host to 
<LOCATION>Loyola Marymount</LOCATION> at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the Sunset Canyon diamond. 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Bruins won three of four games in the <LOCATION>Big West</LOCATION> Conference-Pac-10 
tournament. Freshman <PERSON>DeDe Weiman</PERSON> made her first start for <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> in a 1-0 victory 
over <LOCATION>Cal State Fullerton</LOCATION>. Another freshman, <PERSON>Heather Compton</PERSON>, made her pitching 
debut and got the win over <LOCATION>Fresno State</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Lisa Longaker</PERSON> was the pitcher of 
record as the Bruins defeated <ORGANIZATION>Fresno State</ORGANIZATION>, 5-1. The Bruins lost the final to 
<LOCATION>Cal State Fullerton</LOCATION>, 2-0. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA's <PERSON>Shelly Montgomery</PERSON> got five hits in nine at-bats in the tournament, and 
teammate <PERSON>Missy Phillips</PERSON> had three hits including a home run, four RBIs and 
scored two runs. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> men's swim team (9-3 overall and 3-1 in the Pac-10) will compete 
against <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the Coliseum Olympic Pool. 
</P>
<P>
Last week the Bruins lost to <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>64-49</DATE>, and defeated <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, 59-54. 
Bruin Mark Dean won his 11th and 12th consecutive victories in the 200-yard 
butterfly against the <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> schools. 
</P>
<P>
USC leads the series with <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>, 24-9, and has won four straight meets, 
including a 57-56 decision last year at <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The No. 7 <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> women's swim team (7-2) is idle this week after defeating No. 10 
USC, 86-54. 
</P>
<P>
Against the Trojans, freshman <PERSON>Christy Richards</PERSON> set a <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> record of 1:03.76 in 
winning the 100 breast-stroke and also won the 200 breast-stroke. Other Bruin 
double winners were <PERSON>Sheri Smith</PERSON> in the 500 and 1,650 freestyles and <PERSON>Kris Stoudt</PERSON> 
in the 50 and 100 freestyles. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910917-0064
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910917-0064.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Parsons Picks Langford
   To Be Next President
</HL>
<DATE>
09/17/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
</MS>
<IN>
HEAVY CONSTRUCTION; INDUSTRIAL AND COMMERCIAL (CON)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   PASADENA, Calif. -- Thomas L. Langford was named president
of Parsons Corp., succeeding Ray W. Judson, who will retire
from that post Oct. 1 after turning 65 this month.
   Mr. Langford, 50 years old, is executive vice president
and chief financial officer of the engineering and
construction company. He will be the first company president
who wasn't trained as an engineer, a Parsons spokeswoman
said.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Since joining <PERSON>Parsons</PERSON> in <DATE>1970</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Langford</PERSON> has held
various operational and administrative posts. In <DATE>1985</DATE>, he
oversaw the purchase of the company from public stockholders
by <PERSON>Parsons</PERSON>' employee stock ownership plan. He was named
   <PERSON>Mr. Langford</PERSON> holds bachelor of science and master's
California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>. His successor as executive vice
<PERSON>Parsons</PERSON> said. <PERSON>Parsons</PERSON> also has an executive vice president of
business development.
   After his retirement, <PERSON>Mr. Judson</PERSON> will become a special
assistant to <PERSON>Leonard J. Pieroni</PERSON>, <PERSON>Parsons</PERSON>' 52-year-old
chairman and chief executive officer. <PERSON>Parsons</PERSON> said it had
<DATE>1990</DATE> revenue of about <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA042389-0215 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 48331 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 23, 1989, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 16; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
797 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PREPS: INEVITABLE DELAYED, BUT SINGBANDITH WINS TRIPLE JUMP 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ELLIOTT TEAFORD, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Phouphet Singbandith of <ORGANIZATION>Magnolia High School</ORGANIZATION> arrived at <ORGANIZATION>Mt. San Antonio College</ORGANIZATION> 
at <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> expecting to begin triple-jumping as scheduled at noon. 
</P>
<P>
But the <ORGANIZATION>Turner Broadcasting System</ORGANIZATION>, the cable TV network that was televising 
the Mt. SAC Relays, had other ideas. 
</P>
<P>
The network asked for, and got, a late scheduling change, which pushed back the 
start of the boys' invitational triple jump to about <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
So while the fans watched <PERSON>Larry Myricks</PERSON> win the open long jump, held at noon, 
in a wind-aided 28-feet 5-inches, Singbandith found himself with time on his 
hands. And, to make matters worse, <PERSON>Singbandith</PERSON> had injured his left knee 
slightly in a dual meet <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and wore a brace for support. 
</P>
<P>
It was hardly the best of circumstances for Singbandith, who was intent on 
breaking the <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> record of 50-3 1/2, set by <PERSON>Ken Williams</PERSON> of Troy in 
<DATE>1982</DATE>. He came into the meet with a best of 50-3, the second-best jump by a 
county athlete ever. 
</P>
<P>
As it turned out, Singbandith is as unflappable as he is good at hopping, 
skipping and jumping. 
</P>
<P>
He didn't get the record, but he won the event by jumping 49-10 1/2. <ORGANIZATION>Lenny 
McGill of Orange Glen</ORGANIZATION> was second with a mark of 49-2 1/2. <ORGANIZATION>Russell White of 
Crespi</ORGANIZATION>, the all-time state career rushing leader, was third with a 47-7 1/2 
jump. 
</P>
<P>
Singbandith said neither the time delay nor the sore knee bothered him. 
</P>
<P>
"Waiting was probably better for me," he said "I got a chance to rest my knee." 
</P>
<P>
And even if he did break <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>' record, the wind would have been over the 
allowable 2.0 meters per second. It was 2.47 meters per second on his winning 
jump. 
</P>
<P>
Singbandith said he was just happy to win. 
</P>
<P>
He was the only <ORGANIZATION>Orange County</ORGANIZATION> athlete to win an event in the two-day high 
school portion of the meet. 
</P>
<P>
Others came close, but none closer than <PERSON>Eddie Lavelle</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Corona del Mar</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
With 500 meters left in the boys' invitational 1,500 meters, <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON> began 
moving toward the front of the pack. 
</P>
<P>
The leaders had gone through the 400 in a swift 61.1 seconds and the 800 in 
2:06.4 and <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON>, who had been running not-so-comfortably in the pack, 
figured it was time to head into the lead. 
</P>
<P>
He was passed shortly thereafter by <PERSON>Louie Quintena</PERSON> of <PERSON>Arroyo Grande</PERSON>, but got 
back into the lead and looked strong going into the final 100 meters. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Francis O'Neill</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Pasqual</LOCATION>, who had led for the first half of the race, 
rocketed past in the final 60 meters for the victory. 
</P>
<P>
O'Neill's winning time of 3:53.78 is the best in the nation this season. 
<PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON>, who finished second, ran 3:54.27, the No. 2 time in the country this 
year. 
</P>
<P>
"I tried to hold on as long as I could," <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON> said. "<PERSON>O'Neill</PERSON> had a good kick 
today." 
</P>
<P>
It was a personal best for <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON>, who rebounded from a seventh-place finish 
in the 3,000 <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't run too well <TIME>last night</TIME>," he said. "I'm more happy with how I reacted 
to the competition today." 
</P>
<P>
That didn't include dodging other runners in the close pack early in the race, 
however. Lavelle had two spike wounds, one on each shin, to show for his time 
spent in the pack. 
</P>
<P>
"War wounds," he called them. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Doug Nichols</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION> found the going equally as difficult in the boys' 
invitational 800. 
</P>
<P>
He ran most of the first lap, covered in 54.96 by <PERSON>Mike McLean</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Edmonton</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, out in the third lane. 
</P>
<P>
He settled into position on the second lap and finished third behind <PERSON>McLean</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Arturo Espejel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
McLean ran 1:52.34 and <PERSON>Espejel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nichols</PERSON> were each timed in 1:52.54. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nichols</PERSON>' time is the best in the state this season. 
</P>
<P>
Not bad for a guy who ran just his fourth 800 on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Nichols had been a 
400 runner until moving up in distance this season. 
</P>
<P>
Mt. SAC Notes 
</P>
<P>
Brent Noon of <LOCATION>Fallbrook</LOCATION> won the shotput with a throw of 66-feet-3 1/2 inches. 
Among those Noon -- the national leader this season with a throw of 68-1 3/4 -- 
defeated was <PERSON>Greg Thurston</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION>, who threw 55-9 1/2 for fourth place. 
<PERSON>Jerry Gillespie</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Westminster</LOCATION> was fifth with a toss of 54-10. . . . <PERSON>Eric 
Whitcomb</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Valencia</LOCATION>, who had competed in a number of relay events <DATE>Friday</DATE> at 
Mt. SAC, took third in the pole vault <DATE>Saturday</DATE> with a leap of 14-6. <PERSON>Jason 
Henlon</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lynwood</LOCATION> was the winner, going 15-0. . . . Walnut, aided by a strong 
1,600-meter leg by <PERSON>Scott Hempel</PERSON>, won the distance medley relay in 10:19.3. <LOCATION>San 
Pasqual</LOCATION>, with <PERSON>Francis O'Neill</PERSON> anchoring, was second in 10:25.0. El <LOCATION>Modena</LOCATION>, with 
<PERSON>Joe Komarinski</PERSON> running the final leg, was third in 10:26.6. . . . Corona del 
Mar was third in its heat of the shuttle hurdles relay. . . . <PERSON>Dariel Whipple</PERSON> of 
Western was fourth in the long jump with a leap of 20-11. <PERSON>Robert Anderson</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> won by jumping 22-0 3/4. . . . <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION> finished fourth in the 4 x 
800 relay in 8:00.69. Eisenhower won in a swift 7:49.37. . . . Canyon was third 
in the 4 x 200 relay with a time of 1:31.58. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Phouphet Singbandith, left, leaps to victory in the triple jump, but 
Eddie Lavelle has to settle for a second-place finish in the 1,500 meters at 
the Mt. SAC Relays. ; Photo, Eric Whitcomb of Valencia High School soars to 
third-place finish in pole vault. GLENN KOENIG / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060389-0134 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 66334 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 3, 1989, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 14; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
818 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STATE TRACK AND FIELD CHAMPIONSHIPS; 
</P>
<P>
EDISON'S TAYLOR LEARNS A LESSON WHILE QUALIFYING IN 1,600 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BARBIE LUDOVISE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NORWALK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Edison High School</ORGANIZATION> freshman <PERSON>Shelley Taylor</PERSON> learned a quick lesson about the 
quality of competition found at the <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> track and field championships <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
<TIME>night</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Cerritos College</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Her teacher? <ORGANIZATION>Rancho Buena Vista</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Kira Jorgensen</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Running in a preliminary heat of the girls' 1,600 meters, <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON>, the 
two-time defending State champion at 1,600 meters and a two-time national 
champion in cross-country, cruised to an easy victory in 4 minutes 55.44 
seconds. 
</P>
<P>
Athletes who won their heat, plus the next five fastest overall, qualified for 
tonight's finals, beginning at <ORGANIZATION>Cerritos College</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>5 p.m. 
</P>
<P>
Taylor</TIME>, who despite being in her first year of competitive running had not lost 
a 1,600-meter race since mid-April, could only watch as <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON> loped away at 
the start for a commanding lead. Taylor started out in mid-pack and eventually 
made her way to second, where she finished in 4:58.77, a half-second personal 
improvement and good enough to qualify for tonight's final. 
</P>
<P>
Taylor's improvement, her fourth in as many races, didn't seem to satisfy her, 
though. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't feel great in the race," she said. "I guess I put a lot of pressure 
on myself (to win). I think I expect too much out of myself sometimes." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> wasn't impressed with her finish, <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON> certainly was. Said 
<PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON>: "She's not depressed is she? She should be proud of herself, 
especially making it this far as a freshman. I never made it to <ORGANIZATION>State</ORGANIZATION> finals as 
a freshman." 
</P>
<P>
In the boys' 1,600, <ORGANIZATION>Mater Dei</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Mike Nielsen</PERSON> advanced with a third-place finish 
in his heat in 4:15.05, the fifth-fastest time overall. <PERSON>Nielsen</PERSON>, who last year 
did not advance past the Southern Section preliminaries, started out in 
mid-pack, then gradually worked his way into fourth. 
</P>
<P>
With 200 meters to go, <PERSON>Nielsen</PERSON>, trying to maintain his crisp, efficient stride, 
charged to third and then tried to catch <LOCATION>Burbank</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Todd Lewis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Arroyo 
Grande</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Louie Quintana</PERSON> but could not. <PERSON>Lewis</PERSON> won in 4:12.66, and <LOCATION>Quintana</LOCATION> was 
second in 4:13.00. 
</P>
<P>
"I felt pretty good," <PERSON>Nielsen</PERSON> said. "I think I have a lot left. They went by me 
and beat me fair and square." 
</P>
<P>
Corona del Mar's <PERSON>Eddie Lavelle</PERSON> finished a surprising and disappointing eighth 
in his 1,600 heat and did not advance. <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON>, who has a best time -- and 
county-leading time -- of 4:11.95, came through the first 300 meters fourth 
from last but worked his way into what appeared to be a comfortable third. 
</P>
<P>
But with 200 meters to go, <PERSON>Lavelle</PERSON> faded and, without a kick, dropped to 
eighth. After the race, he walked off the track with a noticeable limp, his 
left shin bleeding from spike marks. 
</P>
<P>
After a disappointing finish in the long jump, <ORGANIZATION>Canyon</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Allison Franke</PERSON> 
qualified in her specialty, the discus, with a toss of 151-feet-10, fourth best 
overall. <PERSON>Franke</PERSON>, who fouled twice in the long jump before leaping 17-7, made up 
for the disappointment with an discus series of 151-5, 151-10 and 150-8. 
<LOCATION>Bakersfield</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Melisa Weis</PERSON> leads the field at 163-9, her first and only throw of 
the night. 
</P>
<P>
In the girls' shotput, <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Bev Oden</PERSON> advanced with a mark of 40-9, 
eighth-best overall. Edison's <PERSON>Leslee Briggs</PERSON>, the county's season leader at 
41-11 1/2, fouled on two of her three attempts. Her only legal mark was 39-8, 
which tied her for tenth. Only 2 3/4 inches separated <PERSON>Briggs</PERSON> from advancing to 
tonight's final. 
</P>
<P>
In the girls' high jump, <LOCATION>El Dorado</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Lori Svoboda</PERSON> advanced with a leap of 5-6. 
That mark tied her for first with defending state champion <ORGANIZATION>Crissy Mills of 
North Hollywood Campbell Hall</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Svoboda</PERSON>, who defeated <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> last <DATE>Friday</DATE> to win 
the <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> title, passed on the first three heights, cleared 5-4 on her first 
attempt, passed at 5-5 and cleared 5-6 again on her first try. Mills duplicated 
<PERSON>Svoboda</PERSON>'s series exactly. 
</P>
<P>
Other county athletes who advanced to tonight's finals were <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Doug 
Nichols</PERSON> (sixth-best 800 at 1:54.11); <LOCATION>Capistrano Valley</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Laurinda Mulhaupt</PERSON> 
(fifth-best 800 at 2:15.38); <ORGANIZATION>Magnolia</ORGANIZATION>'s Phouphet Singbandith (fourth-best 
triple jump at 49-7 3/4); <ORGANIZATION>Westminster</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Shelly Tochluk</PERSON> (the final 400 qualifier 
at 56.34); <ORGANIZATION>Valencia</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Eric Whitcomb</PERSON>, and <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sean Rogan</PERSON> (both 14-4 in the 
pole vault); <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Greg Thurston</PERSON> (56-3 3/4 shotput) and <ORGANIZATION>Edison</ORGANIZATION>'s boys' 
1,600-meter relay team (3:19.84). 
</P>
<P>
State Meet Notes 
</P>
<P>
The boys' and girls' 3,200-meter finals are tonight and include <LOCATION>Santa Ana 
Valley</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Jimmy Rodriguez</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Katella</LOCATION> sophomore <PERSON>Martha Pinto</PERSON> . . . Other county 
athletes whose season came to an end <DATE>Friday</DATE> included: Esperanza's <PERSON>Chuck 
Underwood</PERSON> (54-2 1/2 shotput); <ORGANIZATION>Foothill</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Elizabeth Bauer</PERSON> (5-2 in the high 
jump); <PERSON>Woodbridge</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Louie Muniz</PERSON> (39.56 in the 300 hurdles); <LOCATION>Sonora</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Shannon 
Bryant</PERSON> (300 hurdles); Mater Dei sophomore <PERSON>Melissa McDonald</PERSON> (17-11 1/4 in the 
long jump); Mission Viejo's <PERSON>Allison Axtell</PERSON> (17-5 in the long jump); <LOCATION>San 
Clemente</LOCATION> sophomore <PERSON>Tim Martin</PERSON> (10.77 in the 100 meters; ties for alternate 
position); Foothill's <PERSON>Janette Reed</PERSON> (2:21 in the 800). 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Eric Whitcomb of Valencia, left, qualified for pole vault final. At 
center is Edison's Shelley Taylor in 1,600 heat. Allison Franke, right, of 
Canyon takes a long jump. JOHN FUNG / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051189-0076 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 55422 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 11, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
827 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DISSIDENTS' WIN AT MAZDA PLANT STUNS UAW, FIRM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JAMES RISEN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
DETROIT 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dissident workers opposed to Japanese-style management techniques swept to 
victory <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in the first local union elections at <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> auto 
assembly plant in suburban <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The dissident victory stunned both <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> and the national leadership of the 
<ORGANIZATION>United Auto Workers</ORGANIZATION>, which represents the <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> workers, and raised new 
questions about how well Japanese management policies can be integrated into 
the American workplace. 
</P>
<P>
"We're upset about it, and I'm sure <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> is upset also," said one <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> 
official. 
</P>
<P>
For the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>, in fact, the timing of the rebellion at <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> couldn't be worse. 
The union, which now represents workers at three of the new Japanese-managed 
assembly plants in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, is on the verge of calling for an 
organizing election at <ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Tennessee</LOCATION> complex. Any sign of labor trouble at 
<ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> could be used by <ORGANIZATION>Nissan</ORGANIZATION> management in a campaign to oppose the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>'s 
organizing drive. 
</P>
<P>
While <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> leaders and <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> officials tried to downplay the significance of the 
vote, the election seemed to reveal a deep-seated sense of frustration among 
the workers over <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s labor policies, which are similar to those used by 
other Japanese companies now opening factories all over the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Dissidents, who ran on a platform opposing union cooperation with <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s 
policy of kaizen, or continuous improvement, took the top two posts in the 
first election of officers at the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>'s newly created Local 3000, which 
represents the 2,700 hourly workers at <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s Flat Rock, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, plant. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Philip Keeling</PERSON>, a line worker at <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> and kaizen foe, was elected president of 
the local by a margin of nearly two to one over <PERSON>Bill Judson</PERSON>, the incumbent 
appointed to the post by the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>'s leadership when the local was first created. 
</P>
<P>
According to results released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Greg Drudi</PERSON>, who ran on <PERSON>Keeling</PERSON>'s 
dissident slate, also defeated incumbent <PERSON>Ben Hemmingway</PERSON> for the powerful post 
of shop chairman. In <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> locals, the shop chairman handles union affairs on the 
factory floor, while the president administers the local. 
</P>
<P>
Keeling and <PERSON>Drudi</PERSON> are allied to a larger dissident movement, called "New 
Directions," that has been contesting local and regional elections throughout 
the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>. The New Directions group has attacked the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> leadership's willingness 
to cooperate on joint labor-management programs in the domestic auto industry. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Donny Douglas</PERSON>, president of a <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> local at <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> and the leader of the 
New Directions movement, spoke to a meeting of <PERSON>Keeling</PERSON>'s supporters just before 
the <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> election. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> officials and <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION> leaders were still trying to sort out the 
impact of the dissident victory. The American personnel director at the plant 
found that he had to give <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s Japanese executives a quick lesson in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
labor politics. 
</P>
<P>
"The Japanese executives here are concerned, from the standpoint that they 
didn't expect this," said <PERSON>C. Robert Leadbetter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president of 
personnel. "They don't know the culture in this area, they don't know about 
union politics," he added. "This is something new to them." 
</P>
<P>
Keeling could not be reached for comment <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, but <PERSON>Judson</PERSON> said he believes 
that the workers felt <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> had not lived up to rosy promises of Japanese-style 
employee involvement that were given workers when they were hired. 
</P>
<P>
"People don't feel they have had the input in decision-making that they were 
told they would have," said <PERSON>Judson</PERSON>. "Management thinks that employee 
involvement means that managers listen to what the workers say, and then go 
ahead and make the decisions themselves. The people were told in orientation 
that it meant they would be involved in the actual decision-making." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Look for Improvement 
</P>
<P>
Such worker disillusionment seems to be at the heart of the dissidents' 
opposition to kaizen, which is the basis of <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION>'s labor relations philosophy. 
</P>
<P>
Kaizen, defined by management as the search for continuous improvement, 
essentially calls on all workers to constantly look for ways to improve 
productivity and quality, even if those improvements make their jobs obsolete. 
</P>
<P>
In return, the workers are given job security; they thus have an incentive to 
make their jobs easier. 
</P>
<P>
However, workers at a number of Japanese plants in this country have complained 
that such policies often lead to heavier work loads and production line 
speed-ups. 
</P>
<P>
Workers at <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> blame the American supervisors on the shop floor for 
manipulating the Japanese labor policies to increase output. 
</P>
<P>
"Kaizen is set up to benefit both sides, but it is something you have to 
police," said <PERSON>Judson</PERSON>. "You do have supervisors who will use it strictly as a 
productivity tool." 
</P>
<P>
Despite the dissident victory, <PERSON>Leadbetter</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Mazda</ORGANIZATION> remains committed to 
kaizen -- and to working with the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"We have had good relationship with the <ORGANIZATION>UAW</ORGANIZATION>, and we expect to continue to have 
a good relationship," he said. "We just need to establish a relationship with 
<PERSON>Keeling</PERSON>." 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNION ELECTIONS; UNITED AUTO WORKERS; MAZDA MOTOR CORP; AUTOMOBILE INDUSTRY -- 
LABOR RELATIONS; NEW DIRECTIONS (ORGANIZATION); UNIONS; MANAGEMENT -- LABOR 
RELATIONS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031689-0178 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 31702 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 16, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 5; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1023 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DEFENSE FIRMS PROTEST L.A. OFFICE'S TARDY BILL PAYMENTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RALPH VARTABEDIAN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
An administrative crisis at the <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION>'s main business office in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
has prompted an unusual protest this week in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> by aerospace 
contractors, who say they are not being paid for their defense contracts. 
</P>
<P>
Many smaller companies say they are being driven to virtual insolvency by the 
crisis. Larger prime contractors have had to increase their borrowing by 
<MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> to offset the unpaid bills. 
</P>
<P>
The problems are occurring at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> regional headquarters of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Defense Contract Administration Service</ORGANIZATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Department of Defense</ORGANIZATION> agency that is 
