<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14735</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJOCVABOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931015
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 OCT 93 / Uruguay Round draws fire from Perot camp
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MR ROSS PEROT</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> billionaire, is refusing comment on a report that
he will pitch his political organisation, <ORGANIZATION>United</ORGANIZATION> We Stand, and his extensive
resources behind opposition to a <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round agreement, <PERSON>Nancy Dunne</PERSON> writes
from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>United We Stand</ORGANIZATION> said he has not yet taken a position on the
Round, in order to focus his energies on defeating the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free
Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> co-wrote a book detailing criticism of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> after
claiming, during the presidential debates, that 'a giant sucking sound'
would draw American jobs over the US-Mexican border.
His co-author, <PERSON>Mr Pat Choate</PERSON>, yesterday said he opposed <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round
provisions weakening US dumping laws and establish-ing a multilateral
trading organisation to oversee the world trading system.
Ms <PERSON>Lori Wallach</PERSON>, a prominent anti-Nafta organiser with <ORGANIZATION>Public Citizen</ORGANIZATION>, which
works closely with the <PERSON>Perot</PERSON> forces, said many of the same groups which
oppose the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> will also fight a <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round pact.
'<PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON> feels about <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> the way a vampire feels about garlic,' she
said. '<PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON> feels about <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> the way a vampire feels about daylight.
One he regards with revulsion; the other means death.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CHZ  Switzerland, West Europe.
    USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-7619</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKSDHAA6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 93 / World Trade News: Clinton hails Nafta vote by Congress - US
now has 'economic, political and moral standing' to push for conclusion to
Uruguay Round
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
A JUBILANT President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> flew off to his Asian summit in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>
yesterday on the wings of a famous victory in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and promising new
initiatives to liberalise word trade.
Approval on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> by the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives of the North
American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> was, he declared on the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> lawn, 'a
long step in the right direction' of more open markets and more vigorous
international competition.
The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote gave the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> 'the economic, political and moral standing' to
make its case, he said, not only with the Asian leaders but also in the
final push successfully to conclude a new <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of global trading
talks. Vital Gatt talks are to be held next week in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> between <PERSON>Mr
Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> Trade Representative, and Sir <PERSON>Leon Brittan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>
commissioner.
The <ORGANIZATION>US Senate</ORGANIZATION> is expected to approve <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> next week, as is its Mexican
counterpart. <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> said President <PERSON>Salinas</PERSON> had invited Vice President <PERSON>Al
Gore</PERSON> for the Mexican side of the ratification process.
The new trading bloc, which also includes <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, is to take effect on
<DATE>January 1</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> victory, on a vote of 234-200, was far more comfortable than had
appeared likely even as the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> debated the agreement until late in the
<TIME>evening</TIME>. The majority was composed of 132 of the 175 Republicans and 102 of
the 258 Democrats, with the sole independent voting against.
Before he went to bed, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> signed letters of thanks to all who had
voted in favour and hoped that the bipartisan spirit that had carried the
day could be applied to other great upcoming issues, such as health care
reform.
But the president also went to great lengths to compliment the opposition
and to heal the open wounds in his own Democratic Party, especially with
organised labour. He promised new initiatives on education and worker
retraining, while <PERSON>Mr Gore</PERSON> said the administration was 'uncomfortable in
being in disagreement with the folks we normally fight along with, side by
side.'
Trade union leaders, however, were unmollified. The full hierarchy of the
<ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>, the umbrella union organisation, held a press conference to regret
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s passage.
'It has little to do with the national interest,' said <PERSON>Mr Lane Kirkland</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> president, but was 'a secure means of escape' from <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> laws for US
and multinational corporations. <PERSON>Mr Bill Bywater</PERSON>, head of the electricians,
warned those Democrats who voted in favour: 'We're gonna make sure we get
even at the polls.' <PERSON>Mr Owen Bieber</PERSON>, of the car workers, said <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> votes
next week would be duly noticed, too. <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, a loser in the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
debate, also threatened retaliation by his independent movement.
<PERSON>Mr Jim Jontz</PERSON>, director of the Citizens' Trade Campaign against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>,
promised similar scrutiny of a <ORGANIZATION>Uruguay Round</ORGANIZATION> agreement. 'I feel we already
won because clearly <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> could not be sold on its merits and the president
had to start dealing to get votes.'
Republican leaders were generally pleased with the co-operation with the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> over an accord first negotiated by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. Several said
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would have failed without overwhelming Republican support and that,
therefore, the party could no longer be accused of perpetuating 'gridlock'
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
But a <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> staff member predicted 'serious disagreements' with <PERSON>Mr
Clinton</PERSON> on health care and spending cuts.
Another one under his belt, Page 25; <PERSON>Lex</PERSON>, Page 26
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-5709</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIBB8ABBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930902
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 SEP 93 / World Trade News: Chicago back-room operator to sell Nafta -
Laurie Morse on a Daley drafted in to lead ratification drive
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LAURIE MORSE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE MAN President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> has chosen to head the task force to help get
his free trade pact with <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> ratified may lack experience in
international trade arenas. But he comes to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> well prepared for the
kind of back-room political arm-twisting that will be required to persuade a
divided <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to pass it.
<PERSON>William Daley</PERSON> is younger brother and chief adviser to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s mayor
<PERSON>Richard M Daley</PERSON> and offspring of the legendary Democratic machine 'Boss',
the late <PERSON>Richard J Daley</PERSON>. Unlike his hot-tempered and very public brother,
45-year-old <PERSON>Bill Daley</PERSON> is a smooth-talking behind-the-scenes operator with
important connections in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and long-standing ties with organised
labour. He has never run for political office.
<PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> accepted the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> position after being passed over for a cabinet
position and turning down an offer to be <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s chief negotiator at
He chaired <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s election campaign in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, where he delivered 48
per cent of the vote to <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>, above the national average, and continues
as a tangible supporter. Most recently, he arranged a posh <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> dinner
for the president that raised Dollars 1m (Pounds 670,000).
However, <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON>'s appointment to chair the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>'s task force on the
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> Free Trade Agreement is not a cosy political payoff. Recent
polls show that as many as two-thirds of the American people do not support
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, and grassroots opposition fuelled by labour groups is growing.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> himself reserved his support for the deal, negotiated under
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s administration, until side agreements dealing with
environmental and labour issues were reached last month. Many Democrats in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, including some in the powerful <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> delegation, are
uncommitted. With the agreement fated to unravel if it is not ratified by
<DATE>January 1</DATE>, the battle for congressional support will be fierce, fast, and
visible.
<PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> was chosen for the job, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> observers say, because he has
proven he can sway votes and is willing to take the risk of losing a
controversial battle. '<PERSON>Bill Daley</PERSON> is no <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> neophyte. <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> needs
someone with political sense to move this thing through <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Daley</PERSON>
has the connections,' says a fellow <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lobbyist.
Opposition to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> comes from core Democratic constituencies, making it a
potential political pothole for <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON>'s talents have been
summoned, insiders say, to convince moderate Democrats to back the
agreement.
The president needs 218 votes in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to ratify <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. The
administration counts 125 Republicans in favour of the agreement. <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>
ally and fellow <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Democrat, <PERSON>Mr Dan Rostenkowski</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
ways and means committee, is expected to deliver the 20 Democrats on his
committee. However, <PERSON>Mr Rostenkowski</PERSON> is under investigation for improper use
of his post office perks and faces an uneasy future.
By rough count, <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> will have to marshall 73 votes from Democratic
representatives of states standing to gain the most from the agreement:
those along the border with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and those with big agricultural, consumer
product, or manufacturing export interests.
His Chicago-style back-room muscle will be an invisible counterweight to the
public tactics of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s most prominent opponent, <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s
populist anti-Nafta campaign touts the 'giant sucking sound' that will be
heard as Nafta-loosened jobs flow south of the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> border.
'It is a very interesting juxtaposition of styles,' says <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> political
commentator <PERSON>Mr Bruce DuMont</PERSON>. '<PERSON>Bill Daley</PERSON> is like a Stealth bomber. You may
not see him, but you'll see the results.'
<PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> has taken four months out from his <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> law firm to lead the
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> push. He recently rejoined the firm after a three-year stint as
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Amalgamated Bank of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, which was founded by the
<ORGANIZATION>Amalgamated Textile Workers</ORGANIZATION> union in <DATE>1922</DATE>. Although it passed into private
ownership in <DATE>1966</DATE>, its board is still dominated by high-profile union
officials.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> may be banking on <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON>'s union ties to help the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> effort.
However, <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON>, by pushing <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, runs the risk of alienating his union
supporters. <PERSON>Mr Jim Jontz</PERSON>, former congressman from <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and director of
the anti-Nafta Citizen's Trade Campaign, said: 'I don't know why <PERSON>Bill Daley</PERSON>
would want to be in a position like that. It's just wrong.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    CAZ  Canada.
    MXZ  Mexico.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8197</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKQCRABDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931117
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 NOV 93 / Nafta Countdown: Congress gears up for vote
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE WIDESPREAD assumption is that if the North American Free Trade Agreement
is defeated in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> tonight the cause of liberalised
world trade is in deep trouble.
There is little doubt, for example, that an even bigger cloud will promptly
gather over the head of the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION>, itself due to be completed by the
congressionally mandated deadline of <DATE>December 15</DATE>.
Yet there is one element in this equation which may not stand up to scrutiny
 -that a defeat for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> denotes such a depth of protectionism in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
that even if the Round is concluded it, too, would face certain rejection on
<LOCATION>Capitol Hill</LOCATION>.
The pro-Nafta forces, led with exceptional intensity as the vote approaches
by President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, understandably prefer to confine public
connections between the two to warnings of the fearful consequences for the
wider agreement and for the damage a <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> defeat would inflict on <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
leadership as it pursues a more open global trading regime.
In private, however, <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s supporters, and even some of its opponents,
will even go so far as to argue that a cathartic rejection of the
hemispheric pact would, if anything, reinforce prospects of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>
Round getting through. But to admit this openly would, for the
administration, have the effect of lowering the stakes and thus raising
chances of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s rejection.
Everything, of course, initially depends on there being a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> agreement at
all, the hopes for which will certainly not be improved if <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> goes down.
But US diplomats are quite encouraged by signals from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> that French
resistance to agricultural concessions may be softening and that it will not
use a defeat for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> as a cover for its own refusal to reach agreement in
the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Edouard Balladur</PERSON>, prime minister, is understood to have been particularly
impressed by <DATE>last week</DATE>'s <ORGANIZATION>OECD</ORGANIZATION> report which concluded that a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> agreement
could enrich the world by as much as Dollars 270bn by <DATE>2002</DATE>, the highest
independent estimate yet of the potential accrued benefits.
But the key to the more optimistic <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> private scenario is the sense that it
will be hard to duplicate in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> the sort of opposition to the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>
Round that, win or lose, has characterised the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> debate.
Some elements of the anti-Nafta coalition, which includes the far right and
the progressive left, will remain dead set against the <ORGANIZATION>Uruguay Round</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr
Ralph Nader</PERSON>'s populist consumer movement, for example, sees it as yet
another plot by multinational corporations to extend their hegemony over the
international economy.
The '<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> First' lobby, associated with <PERSON>Mr Pat Buchanan</PERSON>, the conservative
ideologue-politician, is inherently suspicious of international
entanglements. <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, last year's independent presidential
candidate, is also making threatening noises against the Round. But the
clout of the populists in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> still does not even remotely approximate
that of organised labour.
And the trade union movement, which has made <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> into such an immediate
life-or-death jobs issue that it has entered into unholy alliances with the
populists of the right, has no record of entrenched opposition to global
trading accords as a matter of first principle.
Indeed, since President <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> secured passage in <DATE>1962</DATE> of his Trade
Expansion Act, no global bill has faced a tough fight in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. This is
essentially because congressmen, including those on the left of the
<ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, do not like being labelled protectionist. Vice president
<PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> knows this full well from his years in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
Gatt agreements, often imperfectly understood on Capitol Hill, rarely can be
construed to pose particular threats to the constituencies of individual
members. As one lobbyist observed this week, 'It is hard to get people in
<LOCATION>Evanston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, excited about competition from <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>.'
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, on the other hand, deals with two neighbours, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, the
second of whom is demonstrably different from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> politically, socially,
and in its economic development. It is a very particular <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> policy
initiative, with no exact antecedents.
Any consolation that believers in free trade may take from the above
argument does not reduce the importance of tonight's vote. Even allowing for
the hyperboles being thrown by both sides, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> political bottom line is
that the authority of the president is at stake, as may be the political
future of this incumbent, <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>. This, in turn, has imponderable
international ramifications on issues way beyond free trade.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8630</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKOCBAAUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931115
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 NOV 93 / Trade pact vote hanging in the balance: Arm-twisting on
Nafta will go on to the last minute before the US Congress decides
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE debating, cajoling and arm-twisting will continue up to the very last
minute this week as members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> prepare for <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s crucial vote
in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> on the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION>
with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
The congressional votes have been counted, recounted and double-counted, and
still no-one can predict the outcome with real confidence.
'The undecided members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> still hold the balance,' Vice-President
<PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> said yesterday.
If <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> passes the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, it is expected to be approved more easily by the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. It would then come into effect on <DATE>January 1</DATE>, lowering tariffs and
dismantling trade barriers between the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> said this <DATE>weekend</DATE> that he had won 27 members over to
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> in the three days since <PERSON>Mr Gore</PERSON> debated the issue with <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>
on television, and claimed to have the necessary momentum to win on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. One more member, <PERSON>Ms Maria Cantwell</PERSON>, was due to announce her
support yesterday, despite <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s anti-Nafta rally in her <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>
district.
But Congressman <PERSON>David Bonior</PERSON>, the Democratic whip who is leading the battle
in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, said he had topped the 218 needed to win in the
434-member <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
'We have about 222 votes going into <DATE>this weekend</DATE> and we think we are going
to hold our votes,' <PERSON>Mr Bonior</PERSON> said yesterday, though other anti-Nafta
campaigners said they wanted a cushion of at least eight or nine members to
counter last-minute defections.
The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>'s strategy for winning the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote is built on gaining
around 100 of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>'s 258 Democrats and around 120 of the 175
Republicans.
Some pro-Nafta campaigners believe they will have the Democratic votes they
are counting on, but worry that the Republicans are so far assured of only
105 members and will be hard pressed to find their 120-vote contribution.
In the <DATE>last month</DATE>, however, the administration has been hard at work on a
wider spread of side-deals to alloy the doubts of wavering members.
'The only deal that hasn't been made is for working families,' <PERSON>Mr Bonior</PERSON>
complained.
Votes have been hard to buy. Deals on citrus and sugar won fewer vote
commitments than the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> had hoped for, and the promise of a <ORGANIZATION>North
American Development Bank</ORGANIZATION> doubled its yield this week when Congressman <PERSON>Ed
Pastor</PERSON> cited it as a reason he would vote for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
Asparagus growers and airlines have also received a helping hand, but the
administration denied that it had promised to build sewers or bridges in the
districts of uncommitted members.
What many congressmen are looking for, however, is a political umbrella. <PERSON>Mr
Clinton</PERSON> offered one to hesitant Republicans by promising to help them in
next year's congressional elections if his fellow Democrats bring up their
vote for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> against them.
Congressional vote counters say that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> is unlikely to pass by more than
one or two votes, if it passes at all. Several members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> may have
promised the president that theirs will not be the vote that kills the trade
pact; if the Ayes top 218, there will be a rush of these provisional <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
supporters to vote No.
Editorial comment, Page 19
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
TRADE TALKS CALENDER
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
<DATE>NOVEMBER 17</DATE>, <LOCATION>WASHINGTON</LOCATION>: <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> votes on North American Free Trade
                         Agreement, linking the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
                         Failure would flag serious US difficulties in
                         ratifying a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt Uruguay Round</ORGANIZATION> deal, even if an
                         agreement is reached in principle in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> by
                         <DATE>December 15</DATE>.
NOVEMBER <DATE>17-21</DATE>, <LOCATION>SEATTLE</LOCATION>: The <ORGANIZATION>Apec</ORGANIZATION> summit cements closer economic and
                         political ties across the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>. Leaders are
                         committed to providing fresh <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round
                         initiatives if needed.
DECEMBER 2, <LOCATION>BRUSSELS</LOCATION>:    <ORGANIZATION>Economic Union</ORGANIZATION> (formally <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION>) foreign ministers
                         meet: will they clip the wings of <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION>
                         negotiators in the final critical states of
                         <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round negotiations?
<DATE>DECEMBER 15</DATE>, <LOCATION>WASHINGTON</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> administration's negotiating authority in
                         the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round expires, imposing an
                         effective deadline for the talks. Brinkmanship
                         can be expected to the last minute, as the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
                         has to deliver an agreement to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> by
                         <TIME>midnight</TIME> - or 6:00am <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> time
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9258</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKKCTAD5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931111
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 NOV 93 / Clinton pledges to broaden area for free trade
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By GEORGE GRAHAM
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
PRESIDENT <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> yesterday raised the prospect of a broad free trade
zone in the western hemisphere by putting the whole of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> back at
the centre of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade policy.
Speaking at a <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> press conference, he promised to build on the
<ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> between the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> by
expanding it to include free-market democracies such as <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
The president, who has been fighting an uphill battle to win <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
approval for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, predicted that the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> would give
its backing in its deciding vote next week. 'I honestly believe we're going
to win it now,' he said.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> said he did not want to exaggerate the potential job gains to be
derived from <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> alone, although he believed it was clear it would create
more jobs than it lost.
Much greater opportunities would come, however, when the pact could be
expanded to other market-oriented economies and with the successful
conclusion of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of negotiations on the <ORGANIZATION>General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade</ORGANIZATION>.
'The real job growth . . . will come when all the other Latin American
democracies and free-market economies also join in a great trade group with
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
'And it will come because, once this happens, we will have enormously
increased influence in the world community to argue that we ought to adopt a
worldwide trade agreement before the end of the year,' he added.
After <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> debate between vice-president <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr
Ross Perot</PERSON>, the former independent presidential candidate, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> sought
to portray next week's <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> vote as critical for the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>'s ability to
negotiate freer trade opportunities from its partners not only in <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION> but also in the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Gore</PERSON> warned in the debate that a defeat for <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would make conclusion
of the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> round difficult.
An expansion of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> to include the rest of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> was promised by
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s predecessor, <PERSON>Mr George Bush</PERSON>. But little has been heard of such
talk in recent months as the prospects of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> accepting free trade even
with neighbouring <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> seemed so remote.
Mexican stocks soared 81.49 points to a record close at 2,035.33, and the
peso recovered because of optimism over the result of the Gore-Perot debate.
Gore scores, Page 5
No such thing as a free treaty, Page 19
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>MKTS  Foreign trade.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 20
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10092</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKHDHAAAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931108
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 NOV 93 / Clinton steps up campaign for backing over Nafta: President
accuses unions of 'roughshod' tactics on free trade agreement
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
PRESIDENT <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> turned up the political heat yesterday on opponents
of the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> by accusing <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> organised labour
of using 'roughshod, muscle-bound' tactics to defeat the agreement in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
His attack on the labour movement, a traditional bastion of his own
Democratic party, underlined the importance he is attaching to the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
vote in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>November 17</DATE>.
The vote is widely seen as crucial not just to ratification of the accord
between the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> but also to <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade policy in general and
to the success of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of world trade negotiations, due to be
completed by <DATE>December 15</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>, whose comments came in a morning television interview, left the
impression that he was more concerned about pressure being exerted on
members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> by the trade unions - by threatening to withhold
financial support and to run candidates against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> supporters - than he
was by the publicity campaign waged against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, the
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> billionaire and last year's independent presidential candidate.
The president also criticised <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> business for not doing enough to support
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, at least compared with labour's grassroots campaign against the
agreement. But he was confident that Vice-President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> would acquit
himself well in his televised debate with <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>, scheduled for prime time
tomorrow night, because of his 'command of the facts'.
<PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>, warming up for the TV encounter, yesterday afternoon addressed
supporters in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, and claimed there was evidence that he was to
be the target of an assassination attempt by a pro-Nafta group either at
<LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> or at the debate with <PERSON>Mr Gore</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>, in his interview, said <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> was adept at 'keeping things
stirred up'. He denied he was boosting <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s apparently declining
popularity by agreeing to the debate, noting that 'he has enough money to
elevate himself'. The president remained confident that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would have the
votes by <DATE>November 17</DATE>, even though they did not exist today. In particular,
he emphasised the safeguard clauses in <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s 'side agreements' protecting
against surges in imports from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
Only if these proved inadequate and there was overwhelming evidence that the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> was losing jobs would he contemplate renegotiating <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
But Congressman <PERSON>David Bonior</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, chief <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> opponent in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>,
claimed yesterday to be 'on the brink' of winning the 217 votes needed to
vote the agreement down.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> stressed the serious international consequences of rejecting the
agreement. It would, he said, send the wrong message to Asian leaders he was
to meet in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> the day after the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> vote - a view echoed yesterday by
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Republican leader, <PERSON>Mr Robert Dole</PERSON>.
Passage, on the other hand, would constitute 'a clear statement' that the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
was intent on 'competing and winning' in international markets and was
committed to global free trade. It would put additional pressure on <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to complete the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of trade talks by the mid-December
deadline.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    CAZ  Canada.
    MXZ  Mexico.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-16221</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DAHCDABFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930108
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 JAN 93 / World Trade News: Clinton's first big challenge: meet
Salinas and save Nafta - The two men have much in common
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ON his maiden foray into international diplomacy, President-elect <PERSON>Bill
Clinton</PERSON> is going only one state away - to <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, where he will today
meet Mexican President <PERSON>Carlos Salinas</PERSON>.
The two presidents will find they have much in common. Both attended
university abroad (<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr Salinas</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>) and became
young government reformers with pro-business views. Both are 'policy wonks'
 -fascinated with the technicalities of making government work. They are
both 'baby boomers' and know that unless they 'bond' swiftly, the future of
the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> - involving the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> - is at risk.
However, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> assured <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s Prime Minister <PERSON>Brian Mulroney</PERSON> by
telephone yesterday that he would not be left out of any serious discussions
with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. The meeting with <PERSON>Mr Salinas</PERSON> would only be a
'get-acquainted session'.
It was <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, the independent presidential candidate, who fanned the
burning coals of public doubt about <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> into blazing opposition during the
televised campaign debates. The quirky <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> billionaire repeatedly claimed
to hear 'a sucking sound' to the south, drawing <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> manufacturing jobs out of
the country.
Those who opposed the agreement - carefully cultivated by grassroots
environmental, labour and citizen groups - had little difficulty in
extracting promises from numerous congressmen to oppose the treaty. It
stands in danger of defeat.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> should have already won favour with the Mexican president, by
agreeing not to demand a renegotiation. Instead he promised to negotiate
'supplemental' agreements to protect the environment and labour standards
and guard against import surges.
Among <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s Democratic supporters are three factions: business
groups, which care only that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> offers opportunity for new investment,
markets and cheap labour; the opponents, who believe the pact can be
improved with tough enforcement measures; and those - many in unions - who
will work to kill any deal.
There is also organised opposition in both <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, and the
citizens from the three countries will marry their views in a common paper
to be delivered this month.
Although there are some differences in interpretation of the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> text,
most opponents say the current version would depress wages and employment
levels, diminish labour rights and standards, degrade the environment and
promote massive migration and human rights violations.
'<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> is by no stretch of the imagination free trade,' says <PERSON>Ms Thea Lee</PERSON> of
the labour-supported <ORGANIZATION>Economic Policy Institute</ORGANIZATION>. 'It is an investment
agreement and a sophisticated form of managed trade for the multinational
corporations.'
The <ORGANIZATION>Economic Strategy Institute</ORGANIZATION>, in a recent report called '<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>: Making it
Better', concluded that the pact as it now stands would stimulate foreign
investment in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, but at the expense of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> industry.
The opposition has grown so strong that <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> lobbyists acknowledge the
necessity of negotiating the side agreements and presenting them as a 'new'
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, different from the one savaged by <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>.
'We have to reposition the issue to take the focus away from the loss of
manufacturing jobs and focus on the overall closer economic and political
relationship between two neighbours,' says <PERSON>Mr Harry Freeman</PERSON>, a trade
lobbyist.
Those willing to accept a 'new' <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> want one which would encourage
pollution clean-up in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, raise standards of food safety, and boost the
living standards of Mexican workers. Their goal is 'the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> model' under
which countries were only admitted after democratic reforms took root and
the poorer countries are given compensatory payment for social programmes.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> has promised to establish a strong environmental protection
commission with substantial powers and resources to prevent and clean up
water pollution and encourage enforcement of air pollution laws.
But he has been vague about the relationship between the side agreements and
the original <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> text. The critics will insist that this linkage be
formalised, so failure by any of the three governments to meet their
obligations on environment and labour could be punished by higher tariffs.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> will also have to make changes to the proposed dispute settlement
mechanism, according to <PERSON>Mr Alex Hittle</PERSON>, a spokesman for Friends of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, who is willing to support 'a <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> with teeth'. The president-elect
apparently envisions a process under which citizen groups would take their
complaints to <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> officials, who would then pass them to their Mexican or
Canadian partners.
Environmentalists want the process opened to public participation. The
current text says both sides in a dispute must agree before outsiders are
brought into the process.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> will be leaned on hard, and he will have to press <PERSON>Mr Salinas</PERSON>, who
in turn has signalled that the price of new negotiations could be a
multi-billion-dollar fund to help pay for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> to develop infrastructure
and clean up its environmental. He may also reopen talks about labour
mobility.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  USA.
    MXZ  Mexico.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721  International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment and Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-7646</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKSDHAAFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 93 / Clinton pledges trade initiatives: Approval of Nafta hailed
as boost for Gatt talks
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
A JUBILANT <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> president <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> arrived in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> for his Asian summit
yesterday on the wings of a famous victory in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, and promising new
initiatives to liberalise world trade.
His mission, he said, was to drive down world trade barriers as a spur to US
economic revival.
Earlier, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> declared from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> lawn that the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>' approval of the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> was 'a
long step in the right direction' of more open markets and more vigorous
international competition.
The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote gave the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> 'the economic, political and moral standing' to
make its case, he said, not only with the leaders of the <ORGANIZATION>Asia-Pacific
Economic Cooperation</ORGANIZATION> group but also in the push for a successful conclusion
to the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of global trade talks.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s optimism was echoed by trade officials in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> who said the
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote had improved the chances of an agreement on trade liberalisation
measures under the Geneva-based General Agreement on Tariffs and Trade by
the <DATE>December 15</DATE> deadline.
<PERSON>Mr Peter Sutherland</PERSON>, director general of <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION>, said: 'There is no negotiator
in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> today who isn't breathing a sigh of relief as a result of the
vote.'
The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> debate had cast a shadow over <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks for several weeks, tying
US negotiators' hands even though time was perilously short. It is now hoped
that talks next week in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> between <PERSON>Mr Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade
representative, and Sir <PERSON>Leon Brittan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> commissioner, will give
long-awaited impetus to the negotiations.
The <ORGANIZATION>US Senate</ORGANIZATION> is expected to approve <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> next week, as is its Mexican
counterpart. <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> said President <PERSON>Salinas</PERSON> had invited <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> vice-president
<PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> for the Mexican side of the ratification process. The new trading
bloc, which includes <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, is to take effect on <DATE>January 1</DATE>.
The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> victory, on a vote of 234-200, was far more comfortable than had
appeared likely even as the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> debated the agreement. The majority was
composed of 132 of the 175 Republicans and 102 of the 258 Democrats, with
the sole independent voting against.
Yesterday, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> thanked all who had voted in favour of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> and hoped
that the bipartisan spirit that had carried the day could be applied to
other great issues facing the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, such as healthcare reform.
The president also went to great lengths to compliment the opposition and to
heal the open wounds in his especially with organised labour.
Trade union leaders remained unmollified. The full hierarchy of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>,
the umbrella union organisation, held a press conference to express regret
at <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s passage. <PERSON>Mr Bill Bywater</PERSON>, head of the electricians, warned those
Democrats who voted in favour: 'We're going to make sure we get even at the
polls.' <PERSON>Mr Owen Bieber</PERSON>, of the car workers, said <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> votes next week
would be duly noticed, too.
<PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, a loser in the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> debate, also threatened retaliation by
his independent movement.
US stocks fell after investors took the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote as a signal to take
profits. The Dow closed off 19.01 points at 3,685.34.
In <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Sutherland</PERSON>, at a briefing to underline trade liberalising
moves that have already been provisionally agreed, warned of difficulties
ahead. He said: 'The overall picture is heartening, but there are still
significant difficulties in bringing the round to a conclusion.'
In <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, Sir <PERSON>Leon</PERSON> said the vote would remove a big distraction for the
US and allow a final drive for a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> agreement.
Vote raises <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> hopes; Backing at bargain price, Page 6 Another one under
his belt, Page 25 Lex, Page 26
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-3669</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIMC4ABBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930913
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 SEP 93 / Clinton still requires a winning Nafta vision: The
president's uphill battle to win the hearts of Congress
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
PRESIDENT <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> tomorrow formally launches his uphill battle to make the
<ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> acceptable to a dubious <ORGANIZATION>US Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
With ex-presidents <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> expected at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> for a
Rose Garden ceremony, <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> will sign the supplemental agreements on
labour, environment and import surges negotiated over seven months with
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> is also hoping to acquire the salesmanship skills of <PERSON>Mr Lee
Iacocca</PERSON>, former head of <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> and a pitchman notable enough to challenge
<PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, leader of the strong <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> opposition.
There is now a determination in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> to portray the pact, along
with its side agreements, as '<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>' and therefore one which
should be more acceptable to labour and environmentalists. However, if the
side pacts have won any adherents, they have yet to announce their
conversion.
As is usual with trade issues, the spotlight is on <PERSON>Mr Richard Gephardt</PERSON>, the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> majority leader, whose backing is seen as key to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s passage in
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Mr Gephardt</PERSON> leaves a tantalising opening in his current
insistence that he cannot support the pact - as it stands.
<PERSON>Mr Gephardt</PERSON> has been demanding for a long time a fixed funding source,
dedicated to pay for environmental clean-ups at the US-Mexican border and
for worker retraining. An outline of the financing plans may be released
tomorrow.
The administration plans to propose a scaled down version of a <ORGANIZATION>North
American Development Bank</ORGANIZATION>. However, this could be expanded by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,
where there is support for an institution capable also of start-up business
loans in districts threatened by job losses.
Currently, the proposal is to limit the <ORGANIZATION>Nadbank</ORGANIZATION> to environmental projects at
the border and to locate it within the <ORGANIZATION>InterAmerican Development Bank</ORGANIZATION>.
However, congressional supporters of a larger bank may well prevail when the
plan gets to <LOCATION>Capitol Hill</LOCATION>.
It has been suggested that <PERSON>Mr Gephardt</PERSON> might find acceptable a cross-border
tax which would provide the embryonic funding for a <ORGANIZATION>Nadbank</ORGANIZATION>. The tax would
be 'finite' - in place only until it raised the Dollars 600m (Pounds 390m)
currently envisaged from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> for paid-in capital - which may
make it acceptable to the business lobby.
Vice President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> yesterday suggested that the implementation of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
may be delayed beyond its scheduled launch on <DATE>January 1 1994</DATE>. He
acknowledged that the vote may not come until early next year, but scoffed
at press reports that the administration is backing away from the
controversial agreement.
The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> has established a <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> 'war room', reminiscent of the
quick-response team which won high praise for its wit and speed in last
year's presidential campaign. <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> captains are in place - <PERSON>Mr Bill Daley</PERSON>,
an accomplished Democratic backroom deal-maker, and <PERSON>Mr Bill Frenzel</PERSON>, a
former <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Republican congressman - although neither has been visible
much in public.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s lack of enthusiasm in defending <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> has fuelled doubts about
his commitment to the cause. He has seemed remote from the fray, unable to
inspire the public and unwilling to articulate a vision of an expanded home
market with more jobs to gain than to lose. He can hardly be pleased about
the rift it is creating between the moderate and liberal wings of the
Democratic party.
However, reports that the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> is backing away from <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> have
'enraged' the administration. One jubilant official said: 'The political
will is there; the fight is now starting.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-12429</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJ0CNAA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931027
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 OCT 93 / Canadian Elections: Liberal party softens its approach to
freer trade - Trade Pacts
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By BERNARD SIMON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>CANADA</LOCATION>'S Liberal party has substantially softened its stand on North
American free trade since the last general election in <DATE>1988</DATE>. During that
election, which they lost, the Liberals made abrogation of the US-Canada
free trade pact a key plank of their policy platform.
By this year's campaign, however, the Liberals had pledged only to seek
renegotiation of some elements of the <DATE>1989</DATE> accord, the <ORGANIZATION>FTA</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>North
agreements should only be a last resort if satisfactory changes cannot be
negotiated,' the Liberals' campaign platform said.
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> is due to come into force on <DATE>January 1 1994</DATE>. Diplomats and political
observers predict that, with a little help from President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, the
<ORGANIZATION>US Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of multilateral trade talks, the Liberals
will eventually sign on to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> in time to meet the implementation date.
The outgoing Progressive Conservative government pushed <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> enabling
legislation through <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>summer</DATE>. Only formal promulgation is
required to put it into law.
The Liberals pledged in the campaign to seek four specific 'improvements' to
the <ORGANIZATION>FTA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>: a subsidies code, an anti-dumping code, a more effective
dispute settlement mechanism, and the same protection for Canadian energy
producers as is envisaged for <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
Some Liberal concerns would be addressed if the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION> is
successfully wrapped up this year. The previous Conservative government
tried but failed to negotiate a subsidies package in the <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>FTA</ORGANIZATION>.
Anti-Nafta pressure on <PERSON>Mr Chretien</PERSON> would also be eased if the <ORGANIZATION>US Congress</ORGANIZATION>
ratifies <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. Votes are scheduled in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> next month.
On other issues, diplomats predict that <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> will find a
face-saving formula which will enable <PERSON>Mr Chretien</PERSON> to point out that his
concerns are being met, and allow him to proceed with implementation of
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. A visit to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> will be among the new prime minister's early
priorities.
President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> said yesterday he did not expect the election to have an
impact on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
The results of the election should also make it easier for <PERSON>Mr Chretien</PERSON> to
press ahead with <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. The left-leaning New Democratic Party, the only
parliamentary group unambiguously opposed to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, ended up with only eight
seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Commons</ORGANIZATION>. The two regional parties, the <LOCATION>Bloc Quebecois</LOCATION>
and the Reform party, which will form the bulk of the opposition, generally
favour the free trade agreements.
Even within the Liberal party itself, support for free trade is more vocal
and opposition more muted than it was <DATE>five years ago</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9199 General Government, NEC.
    P9721 International Affairs.
    P8651 Political Organizations.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10268</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKGAGAA4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931106
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  06 NOV 93 / Gore-Perot joust seen as gamble for Clinton
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
PRESIDENT <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> has taken a political gamble in sending Vice
President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> into televised battle with <PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> populist,
on the merits of the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION>.
The confrontation was last night fixed for <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> evening in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, with <PERSON>Larry King</PERSON>, the talk show host, as moderator. There may be
other TV debates before the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> votes on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>November 17</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> is giving a hour-long interview on one of tomorrow's
regular <DATE>Sunday</DATE> morning current affairs programmes. <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> is certain to
consume a fair part of this.
Yesterday, <PERSON>Mr Warren Christopher</PERSON>, secretary of state, warned <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> of the
dire consequences of rejecting <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. Drawing together the treaty, the
<LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round trade negotiations and the <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION> summit in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> later this
month, he said, 'these are 40 days that can shake the economic world and
shape <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s future position in it'.
Last <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s round of off-year elections, which saw the Democrats lose
three big races in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, might have stiffened
resistance to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> among the 50 plus Democrats still reckoned to be
undecided.
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> was not an issue in any of the contests but the results have been
freely interpreted as demonstrating that <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>'s political coattails
are very short and that congressmen may be inclined to pay more attention to
local opinion against the agreement.
The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> also thinks <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s credibility is diminishing, a
conclusion borne out by public opinion polls. But <DATE>last year</DATE>'s three
televised presidential debates showed how effective he could be with his
homespun arguments.
It was considered inappropriate for <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> himself to take <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> on,
while fielding <PERSON>Mr Lee Iacocca</PERSON>, pugnacious former head of <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> and a
prominent pro-Nafta campaigner, might have resulted in verbal fireworks, but
too much on <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s terms.
<PERSON>Mr Gore</PERSON>, his many years in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> notwithstanding, is not a natural
television debater. His confrontation last year with then vice president <PERSON>Dan
Quayle</PERSON> showed him to be a bit stiff. But it is thought his dignity and
ability to marshal arguments and facts will stand up well against <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s
tendency to shoot wildly, if divertingly, from the hip.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
    P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-7609</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKSDHABGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 93 / World Trade News: Nafta vote raises Gatt deal hopes - US
decision means just half of the battle is won, says Sutherland
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID DODWELL and LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   GENEVA, BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
TRADE officials urged yesterday that <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> congressional approval of the <ORGANIZATION>North
American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> should be used to secure a successful
completion of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of trade liberalisation talks.
and Trade</ORGANIZATION>, praised President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>'s success, but noted that the
234-200 vote in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> was 'just half of the battle
won'.
The priority would now necessarily turn to successful completion of the
<LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> round.
'<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> and similar enterprises - no less the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> - cannot thrive
in isolation. They are not economically self-sustainable and must be part of
a broader world trading system under the aegis of the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION>,' he said.
'The other half of the battle, making the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> a genuine positive force in
the world economy, must be the conclusion of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round.'
The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote cast a shadow over <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks in recent weeks, tying <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
negotiators' hands when the time remaining for completing the round has been
perilously short, and difficult deadlock-breaking compromises have been
urgently needed.
Amid rising optimism that a long-elusive trade-liberalsing package is
finally within negotiators' grasp, expectations have run high in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> that
the success of the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote would free top US and <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> trade negotiators
meeting in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> early next week to provide long-awaited impetus.
<PERSON>Mr Sutherland</PERSON>'s comments came during a briefing intended to underline trade
liberalising moves that have already been provisionally agreed in <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>
Round negotiations, and to focus on what is at risk if the small number of
outstanding differences result in failure.
'What is in the bank is still capable of being lost,' he said.
In <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, Sir <PERSON>Leon Brittan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> trade commissioner, welcomed the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
vote in favour of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, saying it would remove a big distraction for the
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> administration and allow a final drive for agreement in <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks.
However, <PERSON>Sir Leon</PERSON> sounded a note of caution, telling reporters that he
needed to look at the 'small print' to see what the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> may have
offered members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to get their vote and how it might affect <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION>.
With only four weeks remaining to the <DATE>December 15</DATE> deadline for a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> deal,
<PERSON>Sir Leon</PERSON> is due to hold talks with <PERSON>Mr Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade
representative, in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> next week.
Meanwhile, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> said it was now up to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> to produce 'new proposals' to
bring the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> negotiations to the same successful conclusion as the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
accord.
<PERSON>Mr Gerard Longuet</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s foreign trade minister, said the the <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>
administration could and should henceforth 'devote itself fully to the
<LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round'.
<PERSON>Mr Sutherland</PERSON> warned that 'if what is currently on the table is now lost,'
then 'the threat from unreconcilable disputes will be intense'.
<PERSON>Mr Gijs de Vries</PERSON>, a Dutch member of the European Parliament speaking for the
body's liberal group, hailed the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote as a 'victory for common sense'.
'The only 'sucking sound' Americans will hear is the sound of exports going
south,' he said, referring to <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>'s oft-quoted description of
Americans losing their jobs to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> as a result of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
Another one under his belt, Page 25
Lex, Page 26
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CHZ  Switzerland, West Europe.
    BEZ  Belgium, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8748</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKNANAD6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931113
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  13 NOV 93 / Markets: Traders nonplussed by trade vote - Wall Street
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICK HARVERSON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   THE POLITICS of international trade can be devilishly complicated
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
just try explaining what <ORGANIZATION>GATT</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round or <ORGANIZATION>Blair House</ORGANIZATION> are all
about - but <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> investors have adopted a sensibly direct approach to the
North American Free Trade Agreement: if <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passes the treaty next
week, it will be good for the economy, good for US companies, good for the
stock markets, and good for President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>.
Their reasoning is quite simple. Investors believe that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> will lift
corporate profits because in a more open trading environment between the
three signatory countries the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, with its superior industrial productivity
rates and better-quality products, will enjoy the greatest economic
benefits. The expectation is that growth in <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> exports to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>
will outpace growth in imports from its neighbours to the north and south.
Investors are not alone in their optimistic view of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. Most Wall Street
economists are pro-Nafta, as are the majority of business leaders, if recent
polls are to be believed.
There is, however, the dark side of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> to consider. What if <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
votes no? Investors fear that a rejection of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would have dangerous
knock- on effects around the world, depressing share prices in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION> and eventually <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and endangering vital trade negotiations over
the <LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION>. By coincidence, the day after next week's <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote,
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> will be in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> for a trade conference with leaders of <ORGANIZATION>Asian
Pacific Nations</ORGANIZATION>. If he arrives there fresh from defeat on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, the
President's authority on trade issues will be compromised.
Investors' darkest fear is that a no vote on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would throw such a
spanner in the works of world trade that it would lead to a new era of
international protectionism, higher inflation and slower world economic
growth.
In this scenario, inflation would be the biggest concern of markets. Many
economists argue that the competitive forces unleashed by the accelerating
collapse of international trade barriers have helped restrain global
inflation. Low worldwide inflation has kept bond yields at historic lows,
which in turn have boosted share prices to record highs in many markets.
Thus, any reversal in that trend - a return of trade barriers, higher
inflation, higher bond yields, - could undermine equity markets that are
already vulnerable to a sharp downward correction because of expensive stock
valuations.
Then there is the political cost of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s failure to consider. Although
the President inherited the trade pact from his Republican predecessor, he
has invested a lot of his own political capital in getting <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> through
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. On paper, this should not be a particularly difficult task,
because <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is controlled by Democrats.
Yet, opposition to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> among Democratic legislators beholden to labour
interests is considerable. Anti-Nafta forces have warned that opening up
trade with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> will lead to a migration of American jobs south of the
border, where wages are much lower. Because the domestic labour market
remains weak, this line has struck a strong chord with ordinary Americans.
The result is that the President faces a tough fight ensuring that the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
of Representatives votes to approve the treaty on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
As of yesterday, the outcome of the vote was deemed too close to call. Stock
markets in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, however, believe the chances of success for
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> improved this week. Share prices in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> rose on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and US stocks made solid gains, following the televised debate on
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> between Vice-President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON>, who is <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s most
celebrated opponent.
Gore clearly bested <PERSON>Perot</PERSON> in a heated war of words, and polls taken over the
next few days revealed that more Americans had been won over to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
Whether this helped swing the votes of some anti-Nafta legislators the
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> administration's way remains to be seem.
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> is playing on investors' minds because doubts over its passage through
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> have arisen at a vulnerable time for stock and bond prices. A week
ago bond yields jumped amid worries that resurgent economic growth might
rekindle inflation. Although data released this week on producer and
consumer prices showed that fears of rising inflation are, at least for now,
unjustified, equity investors remain nervous about rising bond yields.
Amid all the doubts over the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, one thing is certain, trading on markets
next week is likely to be hamstrung by uncertainty over <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s
vote, which, like the battle over President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>'s first budget, will be
extremely close.
 -----------------------------------------------
<DATE>Monday</DATE>         3647.90    +   04.47
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>        3640.07    -   <DATE>07.83
Wednesday</DATE>      3663.55    +   23.48
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>       3662.43    -   01.12
<DATE>Friday</DATE>         3684.51    +   22.08
 -----------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6231 Security and Commodity Exchanges.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-10911</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKCDEADZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931103
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 NOV 93 / Party loyalties do not apply: The stakes are high in the
battle to guide Nafta through the US Congress
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN and NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
'They'd sell off bits of the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> lawn for a vote if they could'
 - <PERSON>Jim Jontz</PERSON>, head of the Fair Trade Campaign against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> 'It's one
president, all the living former presidents, 41 governors, 14 Nobel
Laureates and 284 economists versus <PERSON>Perot</PERSON>, <PERSON>Buchanan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>; it's your
choice'
 - <PERSON>Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade representative
Barring the unforeseen, the latest addition to the matriarchy of all
political battles will be finally decided on <DATE>November 17</DATE> when 258 Democrats,
175 Republicans, and one independent in the 435-member <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> (there is one vacant seat) vote on whether to approve the
North American Free Trade Agreement linking the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> on
<DATE>January 1</DATE>. A simple majority of 218 is all that is needed. If it passes, the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> will almost certainly follow suit; if it fails, the upper chamber
does not have to act.
The stakes are enormous - for the political credibility of President <PERSON>Bill
Clinton</PERSON> early in his term and for the legacy of President <PERSON>Carlos Salinas</PERSON> as
he nears the end of his, for the evolution of the Mexican and US economies,
and for a global trading structure in which a <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round agreement
scheduled to be reached by <DATE>December 15</DATE> may be unattainable if <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> goes
down.
Conventional party lines are irrelevant in the intense retail political war
now going on in pursuit of the 218-vote nirvana. More Republicans, perhaps
as many as 120 according to congressman <PERSON>Jim Kolbe</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, far fewer
according to <PERSON>Mr Jim Jontz</PERSON>, a former congressman from <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, will vote for
than against, not least because the original <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> was negotiated by the
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration. This leaves <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> needing at most 40 per cent of
his own party to triumph - and therein lies the problem.
For the Democratic coalition that just - by one vote - sustained the
president in the great budget battle against unanimous Republican
opposition, is in tatters. In <DATE>July</DATE> it was the 'new' Democrats, especially
moderates from the south, who deserted <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> while the old liners -
labour, liberals, blacks - held their noses and held fast. On <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, the
positions are in good measure reversed.
According to Ms <PERSON>Lori Wallach</PERSON>, a leading co-ordinator of the 'anti-'
campaign, the 'no' camp already numbers 208-210 'including some leaners'.
<PERSON>Bill Daley</PERSON>, drafted from his <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> domain to direct the 'yes' campaign,
disputes this estimate, counts about 195 in favour and says that some 55
Democrats are still undecided. <PERSON>Mr Jontz</PERSON> disagrees, reckoning there are now
more Republicans than Democrats on the fence. He thinks the freshman class -
<DATE>66</DATE> Democrats and 48 Republicans - is particularly resistant to <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
Both sides hail and blast each new convert. Democrat <PERSON>John Dingell</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> came out for the 'noes<DATE>' this week</DATE>, but <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> counters that he
could never understand why anybody thought he would do anything different.
Ms <PERSON>Wallach</PERSON> is equally dismissive of the impact of the 'yes' declarations of
Democrats <PERSON>Joe Kennedy</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Esteban Torres</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
The latter, she insists, probably could not carry the 18-member Hispanic
caucus.
The politics of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> have produced uneasy dalliances among political
heavyweights. In one bed lie the president, the Republican leadership,
including <PERSON>Newt Gingrich</PERSON>, a fervent conservative, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> majority leader,
the Speaker of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, most leaders of big business, and some prominent
environmental groups: in the other can be found the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> majority leader
(<PERSON>Richard Gephardt</PERSON>) and most of the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic House</ORGANIZATION> whips, including <PERSON>David
Bonior</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, the chief anti-Nafta strategist, plus <PERSON>Ralph Nader</PERSON>, the
consumer advocate, most of the labour unions, <PERSON>Pat Buchanan</PERSON>, the right-wing
ideologue, and <PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON>, last year's independent presidential candidate.
Ms <PERSON>Wallach</PERSON>, who portrays the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> divide as one between 'populists and the
elites', says there is little top-level contact with <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>, who first
spoke of the 'giant sucking sound' of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> jobs going south to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, but
that his troops offer access to conservatives and small businesses. <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON>
says that '<PERSON>Perot</PERSON>'s credibility is diminishing because he has become a
politician', an assessment borne out by several recent opinion polls.
Both sides agree that the role played by President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> himself is
crucial. 'He is my number one worry - never underestimate the power of the
presidency,' says <PERSON>Ms Wallach</PERSON>. He got off to a slow start. In the <DATE>summer</DATE> he
was consumed by the budget, and more recently distracted by healthcare,
<LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Somalia</LOCATION>. Meanwhile the opposition was off and running early.
The administration pinned a lot of its midsummer hopes on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>'s 'side
agreements', covering Mexican environmental and labour laws and guarding
against import 'surges', meeting most objections. But these were only
completed in <DATE>mid-August</DATE>, later than planned, and were only partly
successful. Six prominent US environmental groups came out in favour, but
union opposition became entrenched. Most important, Congressman <PERSON>Gephardt</PERSON>,
whose backing could probably have ensured passage, declared he was not
satisfied.
<PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> insists it does not matter that the president started late because
'in politics, decisions are only taken in the last few days'. Whatever the
merits of this argument, there is no questioning that the pro-Nafta campaign
is now in full swing, with plans that <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> himself do little other
than argue for the agreement in the next two weeks.
Every day brings a new media show. Last week saw Products Day on the <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION> lawn, a display of 175 goods that would benefit from <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>. Last
weekend the president went to <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> to maintain that <ORGANIZATION>JFK</ORGANIZATION> would have been
pro-Nafta. On <DATE>Monday</DATE> he appeared at an electronic 'town meeting' with
members of the <ORGANIZATION>American Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. Later this week he is in
<LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Sunday</DATE> an hour-long TV interview is scheduled.
About twice a week he has 15-20 congressmen in his office for a <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
exhortation. He works the phones constantly, and all members of his cabinet
are fully engaged, sometimes inventively. <PERSON>Mr Kantor</PERSON>'s latest pitch is that
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> and would, along with <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, seek to profit from its
defeat. The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> 'war room', operating out of the Old Executive Office
building next to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, co-ordinates it all and makes sure that
businessmen keep up the pressure on individual members.
Certain actions, both substantive and personal, get taken with <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> in
view. Last week's creation of the <ORGANIZATION>North American Development Bank</ORGANIZATION>, with its
funds available for border clean-up, obviously helped Congressman <PERSON>Torres</PERSON>
come off the fence. At the other extreme, <ORGANIZATION>Congressman E Clay Shaw</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
Republican, is demanding that the administration put pressure on <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> for
the extradition of an accused rapist. <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> says: 'We have made our views
known to the Mexican government on this, though they knew about it already.'
All this activity is matched with fervour and skill by the other side. Ms
<PERSON>Wallach</PERSON> claims to have kept a lid on vote switching. She points out that
Congressman <PERSON>Kweisi Mfume</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>, leader of the 38-strong black
Democratic caucus previously so loyal to <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>, is helping <PERSON>Mr Bonior</PERSON>
garner votes against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, and that only one black congressman has come out
in favour. On broader policy issues, both camps were bombarding the media
with their respective spins after last week's Canadian election result.
'They've thrown everything at us, but it hasn't made a difference so far,'
she insists.
With two weeks to go, neither side will publicly admit the possibility of
defeat. <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> says he will not sell the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> lawn, but seen
crossing it yesterday was a gaggle of living Nobel Laureates, including
<PERSON>Henry Kissinger</PERSON>, last seen being nice to <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> on <ORGANIZATION>Martha's Vineyard</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>August</DATE>. The grass seemed in place.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
    P8651 Political Organizations.
    P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-7648</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKSDHAADFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 93 / Nafta vote hailed as boost for Gatt: 'A long step in the
right direction,' says Clinton
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID DODWELL and LIONEL BARBER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   GENEVA, BRUSSELS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
TRADE officials said yesterday that <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> congressional approval of the <ORGANIZATION>North
American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> should be used to secure a successful
completion of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of trade liberalisation talks.
and Trade</ORGANIZATION>, praised President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>'s success, but was quick to note
that the vote in the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, by 234 to
200, was 'just half of the battle won'.
He said: 'Half the battle because <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> and similar enterprises - no less
the <LOCATION>European Union</LOCATION> - cannot themselves thrive in isolation. They are not
economically self-sustainable and must be part of a broader world trading
system under the aegis of the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION>.
'The other half of the battle, making the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> a genuine positive force in
the world economy, must be the conclusion of the <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round.'
Trade negotiators in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> have set a <DATE>December 15</DATE> deadline for completion
of the round. The <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote had cast a shadow over <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks for several
weeks, tying <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> negotiators' hands when the time remaining for completing
the round has been perilously short.
Amid rising optimism that long-elusive trade-liberalising measures are
finally within negotiators' grasp, expectations have run high that the
success of the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> vote would allow top US and <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> trade negotiators
meeting in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> early next week to provide long-awaited impetus.
<PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>, before flying to his Asian summit in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
approval of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> was 'a long step in the right direction' of more open
markets and more vigorous international competition.
The vote gave the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> 'the economic, political and moral standing' to make
its case with the Asian leaders and in the final push to conclude the
<LOCATION>Uruguay Round</LOCATION>.
The measure was passed by a far more comfortable margin than had appeared
likely even as the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> debated the agreement.
<PERSON>Mr Sutherland</PERSON>'s comments came during a <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION> briefing intended to underline
trade liberalising moves that have already been provisionally agreed, and to
focus on what is at risk if the few outstanding differences result in
failure.
'What is in the bank is still capable of being lost,' he said. 'The overall
picture is heartening, but there are still significant difficulties in
bringing the round to a conclusion.
'There is a lot there that should stimulate the participants with the
knowledge of how much they stand to lose.'
In <LOCATION>Brussels</LOCATION>, Sir <PERSON>Leon Brittan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> trade commissioner, also warmly welcomed
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> vote, saying it would remove a big distraction for the <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON>
administration and allow a final drive for agreement in the <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks.
However, <PERSON>Sir Leon</PERSON> sounded one note of caution, telling reporters that he
needed to look at the 'small print' to see what the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> may have
offered members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to get their vote and how it might affect <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION>.
With only four weeks remaining to deadline for a <ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> deal, <PERSON>Sir Leon</PERSON> is due
to hold talks with <PERSON>Mr Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade representative, in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
next week.
A measure of concern exists that so much remains to be negotiated in the
<ORGANIZATION>Gatt</ORGANIZATION> talks, with so little time remaining. 'You have a feeling that each
side has spent half of its time calculating how to blame the other in the
event of a failure,' one <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> official said.
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> hails vote; Backing at a bargain price, Page 6
Another one under his belt, Page 25
Lex, Page 26
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 1
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9116</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKLCNAA0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931112
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  12 NOV 93 / US public opinion swings behind Nafta
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE and DAMIAN FRASER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON, MEXICO CITY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE FIGHT over the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> yesterday shifted
outside <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to the Congressional districts of members, sampling
public opinion at home during this Veterans<DATE>' Day holiday weekend</DATE>.
The pro-Nafta forces, exulting over the debate victory of Vice President <PERSON>Al
Gore</PERSON> over <LOCATION>Texan</LOCATION> billionaire <PERSON>Ross Perot</PERSON>, hoped they had finally captured the
elusive momentum necessary to carry them to victory in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> vote next
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. A <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> Today/CNN poll of debate watchers found support for the
trade pact between the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> had shot up from 34 per cent
before the debate to 57 per cent after it.
<ORGANIZATION>Arthur Andersen &amp; Company</ORGANIZATION> yesterday released a survey, by its tax and
business advisory service, which found that large majorities of executives
of medium-sized companies in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> strongly support
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
Meanwhile in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> the country's <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> launched a fierce attack on <PERSON>Mr
Perot</PERSON> and other critics of its political system yesterday, in a furious
response to <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s comments in the debate.
<PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> claimed Mexicans were treated worse than animals and livestock in
the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, were oppressed by the government, and enjoyed few if any labour and
democratic rights. He said just 34 families owned half the country, and some
85m others lived in poverty.
The Mexican <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> issued a statement, supported by most political
parties, which said: 'We cannot ignore however, that certain judgments
expressed, apart from showing a serious ignorance for our country, attack
and offend Mexicans. We condemn them as inadmissible and without
foundation.'
US opponents of <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> believe that fear of job and investment losses to
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> will outweigh any new-found enthusiasm for the pact.
'The only thing that matters is the economy,' said <PERSON>Mr Christopher Whalen</PERSON>, a
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> trade consultant.
'The political equation still is going to be that congressmen who vote for
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> will have to look for other employment next year.'
Trying to blunt any momentum for the administration, Congressman <PERSON>David
Bonior</PERSON>, an anti-Nafta whip, on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> announced that he had 219 of 434
members pledged to vote against the pact. However, he needs at least 10-12
votes more than the majority to prevent last-minute switches, as the
<ORGANIZATION>Administration</ORGANIZATION> increases its pressure.
The <ORGANIZATION>Administration</ORGANIZATION> this week has picked up 10 public endorsement votes, and
claims to have a total of 192. It is publishing a free 800 telephone number
with the offer to voters to send, free of charge, pro-Nafta telegrams to
their congressman.
Around the country, the opposition troops are planning rallies, marches,
town hall meetings and 'accountability meetings' with congressmen. Ms <PERSON>Lori
Wallach</PERSON>, an anti-Nafta leader, said <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would be won or lost in the
congressmen's home districts.
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> will not be bereft of activity over the long weekend. The
anti-Nafta Citizens' Trade Campaign is bringing '<ORGANIZATION>Nafta Claus</ORGANIZATION>' to the Capitol
to distribute gifts in a parody of the president's effort to sell <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> to a
reluctant <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    MXZ  Mexico.
    CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-7614</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKSDHABBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931119
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 NOV 93 / World Trade News: Gore up front and deals in the backrooms -
What turned the tide in the fight for Nafta
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
VOCIFEROUS opposition to the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> first
surfaced three years ago when a coalition of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> labour, environmentalists,
consumer groups, farm and church organisations formed to oppose extension of
the 'fast track' authorisation, under which <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> agrees to vote on trade
pacts such as <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> without amendment.
These groups comprise the worker bees of the Democratic party, so it was
with trepidation that the supporters of then Governor <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> watched
their candidate endorse <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> during the primary and general election
campaigns last year.
<PERSON>Mr Mickey Kantor</PERSON>, the campaign chairman and now <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> trade representative,
said <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> immediately recognised that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> would not be 'politically
viable' - with either the electorate or the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> later on - without the
side deals ultimately negotiated on labour, environment and unexpected
import surges.
The big business backers of the trade pact perceived that <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> was in deep
trouble when, during the presidential debates, <PERSON>Mr Ross Perot</PERSON>, the
independent candidate, repeatedly raised the threat of a 'giant sucking
sound' drawing <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> factories south of the US-Mexico border. The phrase found
resonance in the steady drumbeat of corporate cutback announcements,
fuelling worker insecurity as the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> economy restructures.
Organising against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> continued as negotiations over the supplemental
pacts dragged on for seven months. The administration was in a squeeze;
business, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> were resisting a strong deal guaranteeing the
right of Mexican workers to organise and strike. It was not clear that the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> unions would support any <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> at all.
Just as Republicans and the business community were grumbling that President
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> did not have his heart in <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> returned from its
<DATE>summer</DATE> recess alarmed about the pact's unpopularity, the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> put on
a spectacular launch ceremony. On the bill were President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> at his
most passionate (inexplicably, he is always his best on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>) and the
endorsements of former Presidents <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gerald Ford</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>,
all of which came to symbolise the extraordinary bi-partisanship which in
the end got <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> through the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
Thereafter, a succession of <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> events, including <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> endorsements
by practically every living former cabinet official and economist,
presidential trips and speeches, just barely moved public opinion on <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>.
'Four weeks ago not one person, outside a few, thought we could pass this
<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>,' <PERSON>Mr Kantor</PERSON> said.
The president was eating with, jogging with and pressuring congressmen, but
making little apparent headway until Vice President <PERSON>Al Gore</PERSON> suggested
debating <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>.
It was a brilliant strategy, because it personalised <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> in the form of an
arrogant, secretive and peculiar <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> billionaire. <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON>'s televised
threats - and those of labour - that they would eject from office all <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>
supporters in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> was a big miscalculation. It caused resentment among
congressmen and a determination by some not to be seen as being in labour's
pocket.
Implicitly acknowledging that backroom deals would be key to passage, the
administration brought in as '<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> czar' <PERSON>Mr William Daley</PERSON>, son of the late
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> mayor 'Boss' <PERSON>Richard Daley</PERSON> and brother of the current mayor. It was
a series of deals that <PERSON>Mr Daley</PERSON> was involved in and which were detailed in
presidential letters to congressmen, and a turnaround in public opinion
after the debate, which brought a flood of endorsements just before the vote
and clinched the 234-200 victory.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-6020</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFACAAAYFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930601
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 JUN 93 / Perot attacks Nafta over 'threat to jobs': Prince of the pie
charts returns to the screen
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NANCY DUNNE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   WASHINGTON
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MR ROSS PEROT</PERSON>, independent presidential candidate in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, this
weekend accused the <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> administration of using taxpayers' dollars to
promote the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION>.
The Texan billionaire warned Americans that the pact with <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>
would jeopardise their jobs.
In a paid television 'info-mercial', he made his case against <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> with the
sort of pie charts and graphs he wielded during the presidential campaign,
and with film of Mexican slums.
Greedy factory owners would move south of the border to take advantage of a
minimum wage of <MONEY>58 US cents</MONEY> (37 pence) an hour, <PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> said. The loss of
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> jobs would make it impossible to balance the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> budget.
'If you and I sit here complacently, it will create the giant sucking sound
I've been talking about,' he said of the job flight to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. He urged
voters to write '<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> yes' or '<ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION> no' on a piece of paper and send it to
their Congressmen, the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> and him.
<PERSON>Mr Perot</PERSON> excoriated the 'lobbyists in the employ of foreign governments',
who he said had written the agreement. He signed off the half-hour broadcast
somewhat awkwardly, concluding, 'I love you'.
Supplements to the <ORGANIZATION>Nafta</ORGANIZATION>, signed last year for the US by the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration, are being negotiated by <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>.
