<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890113-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-13-89 0531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-AborigineProbe     01-13 0339</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Aborigine Probe,0354</SECOND>
<HEAD>Head Of Government Inquiry Into Aboriginal Deaths Resigns</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CANBERRA, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The head of a government probe on the
deaths of 104 aborigines in police custody has resigned, and
indigenous activists today called the decision a devastating blow to
the inquiry.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> said <PERSON>James Muirhead</PERSON>, federal court judge
since <DATE>1977</DATE>, resigned <DATE>late Thursday</DATE> to become administrator of the
<ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>.
   Aboriginal groups called the decision a blow to their cause and
expressed concern that the inquiry, set up in <DATE>1987</DATE> to investigate 44
aboriginal deaths in police custody since <DATE>1980</DATE>, could be downgraded.
   Since the inquiry began, the number of aboriginal deaths in
police custody has grown to 104, and <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> had said the increased
number would extend his work _ expected to be completed <DATE>last month</DATE> _
two years minimum.
   Aboriginal activists have charged police brutality as the cause.
   An interim report issued last month recommended aboriginal
recruits replace white police officers suspected of racism and that
drunkenness be abolished as a crime for aborigines.
   Most aborigines have died in police cells by hanging after being
picked up on charges of being drunk and disorderly.
   <PERSON>Hawke</PERSON> said <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON>, who also was the judge in the <PERSON>Lindy
Chamberlain</PERSON> trial, would continue in his job until <DATE>April</DATE>. The
<PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON> trial was the basis for the recent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> movie starring
Meryl Streep entitled ``A Cry in the Dark.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Black Action Group</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Committee to Defend Black Rights</ORGANIZATION>,
which represents many of the families of aborigines who have died in
custody, urged the federal government ensure that justice is not
denied the country's indigenous population following <ORGANIZATION>Muirhead</ORGANIZATION>'s
resignation.
   Aborigines, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s original inhabitants, number about
160,000, or <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the 16 million population. Government
figures statistics show aborigines are socially and economically
deprived.
   Aboriginal activists declared <DATE>last year</DATE>'s Bicentennial marking
European settlement a year of mourning.
   Muirhead, 63, said aborigines should not fear the probe will wind
down.
   ``I think the commission is well established,'' he said.
   No replacement was immediately named.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890502-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-89 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Aborigines     05-02 0302</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Aborigines,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Probe Into Aborigine Deaths Looks At Why More Go To Jail</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> broadened a
probe into the deaths of aborigines in police custody to discover
why proportionately more of the native people than other
Australians end up in jail.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Royal Commission of Inquiry</ORGANIZATION> said it was concerned by
government statistics that show aborigines, about <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the
16 million population, are six times more likely to go to jail than
white Australians.
   ``While investigation of aboriginal deaths in custody is
important, so too is learning the lessons of the past and acting to
prevent further deaths,'' said <PERSON>Elliott Johnston</PERSON>, who is heading the
inquiry.
   <PERSON>Johnston</PERSON>, a lawyer, this week replaced judge <PERSON>James Muirhead</PERSON> on
the commission, which was established by Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON>
in mid-1987.
   Muirhead, in an interim report issued in <DATE>December</DATE>, urged states
to abolish drunkenness as a criminal offense, indicating this was
perhaps a chief reason aborigines were arrested. In <DATE>February</DATE>, the
government pledged the equivalent of <MONEY>$8 million</MONEY> to set up
drying-out facilities as an alternative to jail for people arrested
on drinking charges.
   The commission is investigating the deaths while in police
custody of 104 aborigines between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>May 31, 1987</DATE>. Some
activists blame police brutality, and others have said the jailing
causes despair, which often leads to suicide, <PERSON>Johnston</PERSON> said.
   Conclusions will be reached by year's end, he said.
   In <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION>, a spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>South Australian Aboriginal
Deaths in Custody Watch Committee</ORGANIZATION> criticized the commission's <DATE>May
31</DATE> cutoff date.
   ``The cut-off date must be when there are no more deaths so
justice can be seen to have happened,'' said <PERSON>Mrs. Alice Dixon</PERSON>,
whose 19-year-old aboriginal son died in custody in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Aborigines are <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s original inhabitants, settling the
continent 40,000 years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881228-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-28-88 0417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Australia-Aborigines     12-28 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Aborigines,0693</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report On Deaths Among Aborigines In Police Custody Urges Changes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To stem a rash of aborigine deaths in
police custody, a government report today urged that drunkenness be
abolished as an offense and racist police officers be replaced by
aboriginal recruits.
   The preliminary report calls for widespread changes in
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s legal, police, prison and medical systems to tackle the
problem and warns that a failure to institute such changes would
damage <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s reputation abroad.
   It was issued by <PERSON>James Muirhead</PERSON>, a lawyer who Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob
Hawke</PERSON> appointed last year as head of a royal commission formed to
investigate the deaths of 44 aborigines in police custody since <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The commission was to have concluded its probe this week, but the
number of aborigine deaths in police custody has more than doubled
to 100 since it began work. Most aborigines have died in police
cells by hanging after being picked up on charges of being drunk and
disorderly.
   Aboriginal activists charge police brutality.
   <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> said the increase in his workload means the final report
will be delayed by two years. In the meantime, he issued 56
recommendations to prevent more aborigines from dying in custody.
   In the report, <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> also criticizes attempts that have been
made to hamper his investigation.
   ``It will be unfortunate if the work of this commission is
impeded by narrow, selfish or political considerations,'' he says.
``Our performance is being assessed not only in this country but in
overseas forums and I fear that our country's reputation will suffer
if expediency rather than honesty prevails.
   ``<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> must know the truth behind the deaths or else we must
forever live with the knowledge that our fear of the truth or our
misguided sense of priorities caused us to abandon an essential and
momentous decision to examine a little of our national character and
the behavior of people in authority.'' In <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>, the
state where there the most deaths have occurred, police and prison
officers' unions, backed by the state government, have launched a
federal court challenge to some of the commission's powers.
   A royal commission has wider powers than any judicial body in the
country, but is not empowered to pass legal judgment. Its findings,
however, can result in legal action at the state and federal level.
   Aborigines, the country's original inhabitants, number about
160,000, or <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s 16 million people.
   The inquiry comes at a particularly sensitive time with ongoing
bicentennial celebrations marking European settlement. Aboriginal
activitists have declared <DATE>1988</DATE> a year of mourning.
   Muirhead, says in his report that governments at the state and
federal level should legislate to ensure that jail is used only as a
last resort for drunkenness.
   Justice Minister <PERSON>Michael Tate</PERSON> said the federal government
generally agrees with the thrust of the report.
   Muirhead refused comment beyond his recommendations, which
included:
   _ That drunkenness be abolished as an offense, accompanied by
programs to treat alcohol abuse and changes to the law to force
police to consider alternatives to jail for drunk people; that a
national task force be set up to examine social and health problems
among aborigines caused by alcohol abuse;
   _ That people found unconscious by police should be taken to a
hospital or a qualified health worker and not to jail. He encouraged
the recruitment of aboriginal police and prison officers, and
screening to prevent racist police and prison officers from being
retained.
   Federal statistics show that aboriginal life expectancy is 20
years less than for other Australians, while infant mortality among
aborigines is almost three times higher than among non-aborigines.
   Aborigines, according to government figures, also have a far
higher rate of diseases like trachoma while imprisonment rates for
aborigines are 16 times higher than the national average.
   Aboriginal unemployment is some six times the national average.
There are virtually no aborigines in professions such as law,
education and medicine despite <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> each year in
federal funds for aborigines.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880928-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-28-88 1236EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Aborigine-Killings     09-28 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Aborigine-Killings,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prominent Aboriginal Artist And His Family Slain</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DARWIN, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A leading aboriginal artist and four
members of his family were shot and killed at their camp in a
remote reservation, police said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Police in the aboriginal area of Arnhem Land in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern
Territory</ORGANIZATION> said the bodies of tribal elder <PERSON>Dick Ngueli Ngueli</PERSON>, also
known as <ORGANIZATION>Muru Muru</ORGANIZATION>, and his wife, daughter and two young grandsons
were found <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Police said relatives found the five victims lying face down in
a creek at a remote camp in Arnhem Land, 180 miles east of <LOCATION>Darwin</LOCATION>.
   Police said a sixth victim, apparently <ORGANIZATION>Ngueli</ORGANIZATION>'s brother, was
also found dead, but gave no details.
   Superintendant <PERSON>Terry O'Brien</PERSON> of the <PERSON>Darwin</PERSON> police said the five
family members were killed with a shotgun and that used cartridges
were found near the bodies.
   Police said they plan to question tribal aborigines in the area
and were searching for <ORGANIZATION>Ngueli</ORGANIZATION>'s son-in-law, the <ORGANIZATION>Australian
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   Ngueli, about 60 years old and a member of the Namok tribe, is
an internationally acclaimed bark painter whose works are on
display at the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>, the federal capital.
   The slayings followed media reports that aboriginal elders in
Arnhem Land had started ``singing to death'' _ a ritual death curse
_ another aboriginal artist for presenting a bark painting
depicting legends of creation to Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON>.
   The reports said <PERSON>Galarrwuy Yunupingu</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern
Territory Land Council</ORGANIZATION>, was condemned in <DATE>June</DATE> for revealing secret
tribal lore to a white man.
   Police did not link the two incidents.
   Rituals practiced by aborigines, while seldom reported, are
still common in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   During a re-enactment <DATE>Jan. 26</DATE> of the arrival of the first fleet
of ships that bought convict settlers to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, aborigines
stood on the foreshore of <LOCATION>Sydney Harbor</LOCATION> pointing sharpened bones _
a symbol of imminent death _ at the incoming ships.
   Aborigines, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s first settlers, number about 160,000, or
<PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the country's 16 million population. They are believed
to have arrived at least 40,000 years ago.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-4754</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CFDA4AARFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 92 / Aborigines achieve land claim victory
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
AUSTRALIAN aborigines yesterday threatened an avalanche of land claims,
after a High Court judgment had recognised the existence of land titles
pre-dating European settlement in <DATE>1788</DATE>.
The High Court ruled that the <PERSON>Miriam</PERSON> people of the <LOCATION>Murray Islands</LOCATION>, part of
the <LOCATION>Torres Strait</LOCATION> islands group off the north coast of mainland <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>,
had retained ownership of their land under common law.
The court restricted its judgment to the Murrays, and ruled that the concept
of 'native title' could exist only where such rights had not been
extinguished by the government.
However, aboriginal leaders said the judgment challenged the legal status of
the Australian government, which relies for its legitimacy on the claim that
the country was terra nullius when annexed by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
This signifies that the land was effectively unoccupied, or occupied by
people who lacked a system of land tenure which would have inhibited
annexation and settlement.
The concept is regarded as a significant obstacle to land rights claims by
aborigines, who account for less than <MONEY>1 per cent</MONEY> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s 17m
population, but claim ownership of much of the country.
<PERSON>Mr Galarrwuy Yunupingu</PERSON>, chairman of the aboriginal <ORGANIZATION>Northern Lands Council</ORGANIZATION>,
said the federal government would face 'a barrage of litigation' unless it
moved quickly to negotiate a treaty with aborigines. 'The pathetic excuse of
terra nullius is now dead,' <PERSON>Mr Yunupingu</PERSON> said.
The court decision was 'a turning point in the history of this country, and
it kills off all the nonsense that Aboriginal people don't exist. It sets a
whole new precedent for aboriginal people,' he added.
<PERSON>Mr David Allen</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Lands Council</ORGANIZATION>'s senior legal adviser, said 'significant
numbers' of aboriginal people would have a 'reasonable prospect' of
succeeding in land claims based on the decision.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-981</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLVCCAA8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 DEC 93 / Aboriginal land bill passed by Canberra Senate
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
A native title bill, which sets up a system for deciding land claims by
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s Aborigines and <LOCATION>Torres Strait</LOCATION> islanders, was approved by the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> yesterday.
The legislation, passed after a marathon parliamentary debate that began on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, will come into effect on <DATE>January 1</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr Paul Keating</PERSON>, the Australian
prime minister who took a personal role in negotiating the bill with
Aboriginal leaders, described it as 'a turning point for all Australians'.
'This has been the longest continuing problem that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has faced for
200 years, recognising that indigenous people, that native people, had the
right to their own soil,' he said.
For two centuries <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s land management system has operated on the
principle that the land was uninhabited before European settlement. This
concept was overturned in a High Court ruling last year, which said native
title could exist where there had been 'close and continuing' association
with the land in question. However, the court added that land titles
acquired under accepted law since European settlement should not be
disturbed. The native title bill tries to marry these two rulings.
The bill has been highly controversial. Mining companies argue it will mean
that exploration becomes more costly and unpredictable. But the government
and Aboriginal groups say the number of successful land claims will be
small, benefiting perhaps 10 per cent of the Aboriginal population and
mainly involving vacant crown land.
Over one-seventh of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s 1m square miles has already been set aside,
in one way or another, for the country's 265,000 aboriginal and <LOCATION>Torres
Strait</LOCATION> islander people.
The bill, debate over which had threatened to continue over the holiday
period, passed the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> 34-30 just after <TIME>midnight</TIME>. The lower <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>, where the government holds a majority, is scheduled to
approve the bill <TIME>this morning</TIME>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6541 Title Abstract Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890203-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-03-89 0942EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-AborigineDeaths     02-03 0360</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Aborigine Deaths,0374</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aborigines Angered at Findings into Blacks' Deaths in Custody</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Families of four aborigines who died in
police custody today denounced a government report on the deaths
that criticized police but stopped short of recommending criminal
charges.
   The report, issued <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, found no evidence of foul play in
the four deaths but said they probably could have been avoided.
   Judge <PERSON>James Muirhead</PERSON> was ordered by the government of Prime
Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> in <DATE>1987</DATE> to investigate 44 aboriginal deaths
nationwide since <DATE>1980</DATE>. Since the inquiry began, the number of deaths
has jumped to 107.
   Most of the offenders were arrested on minor charges such as
being drunk and disorderly.
   <PERSON>Alice Dixon</PERSON>, whose son, <PERSON>Kingsley</PERSON>, was found hanging in his cell
in <LOCATION>Adelaide</LOCATION> jail in <DATE>1987</DATE>, wept when she heard the report.
   ``I expected some retribution. They're murdering our people, our
boys, and they're getting away with it,'' she said. ``My son is
dead, other sons are dead and other mothers are grieving and this is
the result we are going to get.''
   <PERSON>Leila Murray</PERSON>, whose 21-year-old son <PERSON>Eddie</PERSON> was found hanged in
<DATE>1981</DATE>, said: ``I've never believed police.'' She said the finding her
son took his own life ``shatters my faith in white justice.''
   <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> said police fabricated evidence and withheld evidence
during the inquiry's investigation of <ORGANIZATION>Murray</ORGANIZATION>'s death.
   The judge concluded that proper custodial care and observance of
prison regulations could have prevented <PERSON>Dixon</PERSON>'s death, and that the
death by heart attack of <PERSON>Charles Sidney Michael</PERSON>, 31, in <DATE>1984</DATE> might
have been avoided.
   <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> said the fourth death, that of <PERSON>John Clarence Highfold</PERSON>,
37, at <LOCATION>Adelaide Jail</LOCATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE> was from natural causes.
   <PERSON>Muirhead</PERSON> didn't say when another report on more deaths would be
released.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Aboriginal</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Islander Legal Service</ORGANIZATION>, which helped
pressure the government to investigate, criticized the inquiry.
   ``There is no message in there that says to police, `Stop if you
are killing people or if you all allowing aboriginals to die,'''
said service director <PERSON>Peter Coe</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s indigenous aborigines number about 160,000, or about
<PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the 16 million population.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-11386</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DG2CSAFZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930729
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 JUL 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: Miners unhappy with aboriginal
land decision
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By REUTER
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   CANBERRA
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE AUSTRALIAN federal government has moved to dampen a heated national
debate over native land claims, granting some rights to aborigines over
mining leases but overriding claims to residential and pastoral land,
reports Reuter from <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>.
Special minister of state <PERSON>Mr Frank Walker</PERSON>, leading negotiations on the
issue, said the cabinet decision should allay aborigines' concerns over
mining on native lands.
'The government has decided that we will give aboriginal people the same
rights as everyone else in the community, a right to negotiate and then if
that doesn't work a tribunal who'll arbitrate,' <PERSON>Mr Walker</PERSON> said in a radio
interview.
The issue has flared up in the past few months following land claims by
aborigines on the basis of a landmark <DATE>1992</DATE> high court ruling that their
native title to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> had not been extinguished by white settlement in
<DATE>1788</DATE>. As a result aborigines theoretically can lay claim to vast parts of
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, including prospective mining areas.
Mining industry leaders criticised the ruling and warned that it threatened
foreign investment.
The <ORGANIZATION>Australian Bankers' Association</ORGANIZATION> yesterday called for an end to
uncertainty over land title, saying its members were reluctant to lend to
businesses in areas subject to claims.
The compromise does not give aborigines a veto over mining on native lands
but the right to negotiate and refer disputes to a new tribunal, government
officials confirmed. But the government could still override a tribunal
decision if it was not regarded to be in the public interest, they added.
<PERSON>Mr Walker</PERSON> said that mining companies whose leases on native land expired
would also have to negotiate with aborigines to renew them.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P10   Metal Mining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 0717EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Australia-Aborigines     05-16 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Aborigines,0324</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aborigines Attack Report Saying Prison No Deterrent For Them</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRISBANE, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Aborigine group today branded as
racist and ridiculous an official report saying their people
receive better care in prison than at home and do not see
incarceration as a deterrent.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Queensland Corrective Services Commission</ORGANIZATION> said in a report
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night to the state parliament that prison provided better
housing, education, medical and recreational facilities than most
aborigine prisoners experience outside.
   ``Tragically they do not see it as a deterrent,'' State Justice
Minister <PERSON>Glenn Milliner</PERSON> said.
   The report said aborigines and another group of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>
natives, the <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait Islanders</ORGANIZATION>, comprise <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of prison
inmates in <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> state, but only <PERCENT>2.6 percent</PERCENT> of the population.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Queensland Aboriginal Legal Service</ORGANIZATION> called the findings
racist and ridiculous. The legal service's vice-chairman, <PERSON>Steve
Mam</PERSON>, said the vast majority of Aborigines and Islanders would be
``horrified'' if charged with a criminal offense, let alone sent to
prison.
   ``Most prisoners come out of jail having learned only about
violence and brutality,'' he said in a statement.
   Aborigines have been living in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> for at least 40,000
years and today number about 160,000, or less than <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the
total population.
   <PERSON>Keith Hamburger</PERSON>, director general of the <ORGANIZATION>Corrective Services
Commission</ORGANIZATION>, said Australian society has to confront the social
crisis facing Aborigines and Islanders.
   ``There is no doubt that if the community as a whole would face
up to its responsibility to solve the awful social crisis facing
this much-maligned and disadvantaged, yet potentially talented
ethnic minority, there would be immense social benefits to our
society as a whole,'' he said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Aboriginal Affairs</ORGANIZATION> said Aborigines have a life
expectancy 20 years less than other Australians and an unemployment
rate six times the national average.
   The government has said that 100 aborigines have died in police
custody since <DATE>1980</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-5360</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFDB5ABFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930604
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 JUN 93 / Aboriginal land deal proposed: Australian package condemned
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EMILIA TAGAZA
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE AUSTRALIAN govern-ment yesterday proposed a sweeping package to protect
private mining and pastoral leases from aboriginal land claims. The 33-point
package includes legislation that would validate land titles issued between
<DATE>1975</DATE> and the <DATE>end of this month</DATE>.
The move came on the eve of the first anniversary of a high court decision
which, for the first time, acknowledged that indigenous people had occupied
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> before European settlement and still had rights to the land under
common law. Since that decision, aboriginal land councils have been
preparing to present claims in various courts around <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
One aboriginal tribe in the state of <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION> recently lodged a writ
calling for the commonwealth and state governments to give up almost a
quarter of the state.
The government package also proposes to establish a formula under which
federal and state governments would share compensation payments to
aboriginal groups that might incur losses when leases are granted to private
holders. It also calls for the setting up of a special tribunal to deal with
aboriginal land claims.
Aboriginal land council officials have called the package a 'slimy and
useless piece of paper'. Meanwhile, the Aboriginal and <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait
Islander Commission</ORGANIZATION> insists on veto power over land development, and on
mining royalties for development on land with native titles.
<PERSON>Mr Robert Tickner</PERSON>, the minister for aboriginal affairs, said the package was
on the table for discussion. 'It is not set in concrete,' he said.
The government has already attempted legislation to protect a large
development project in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>. Last week it supported a
local government bill that would override native titles covering leases to a
ADollars 300m (Pounds 134m) lead-zinc mining project.
The <PERSON>McArthur</PERSON> river project, proposed to be developed by the Australian
mining group <ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION> and its Japanese partners, is expected to earn ADollars
200m a year in exports.
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s foreign debt as at the end of the <DATE>March quarter</DATE> stood at
ADollars 160.6bn (Pounds 72bn), a fall of 3.9 per cent from the figure at
the end of the previous <DATE>December quarter</DATE>.
This was the first quarterly fall in almost three years and was attributed
to debt repayments made by both the public and private sectors taking
advantage of lower interest rates.
The figure is, however, 7.9 per cent higher than at the end of the <DATE>March
quarter last year</DATE>.
Of the net foreign debt, the private sector accounted for 65 per cent or
ADollars 104.6m.
The ratio of the net foreign debt to <ORGANIZATION>GDP</ORGANIZATION> was 40.6 per cent, down <MONEY>1.9 per
cent</MONEY> at the end of the previous quarter.
A permanent reduction in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s foreign debt is unlikely in the
foreseeable future because of the continuing high current account deficit.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9532 Urban and Community Development.
    P1031 Lead and Zinc Ores.
    P9311 Finance, Taxation, and Monetary Policy.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
    ECON  Inflation.
    ECON  Gross domestic product.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900711-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-11-90 1100EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Australia-Aborigines     07-11 0461</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Australia-Aborigines,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aboriginal Leader Declares Provisional Government</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A group of Aborigines declared a
provisional government today, claiming they have been neglected for
decades by state and federal governments and see little prospect
for change.
   <PERSON>Michael Mansell</PERSON>, secretary of the <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal Provisional
Government</ORGANIZATION>, said it would be autonomous, raise its own funds, have
its own passports and seek recognition by foreign governments.
   ``It is a political body set up to provide leadership to the
aspirations of Aboriginal people,'' the Aboriginal activist told a
news conference. ``All we are asking is the right to control
ourselves on our own land. We don't want to interfere with you
people, but just leave us alone as well.''
   It was not immediately clear what effect, if any, the
declaration would have. The <DATE>1981</DATE> census said <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> had about
160,000 Aborigines, comprising less than <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of the
population at the time.
   Estimates indicate the country had 300,000 or more Aborigines,
the indigenous people, when European settlers arrived.
   ``We would set ourselves a stage that in 20 to 30 years from
now, we would actually have enough land in this country so that
Aboriginal people could raise their own economy, legal system and
run their own government on it,'' <PERSON>Mansell</PERSON> said.
   The new government received an early rebuff when <ORGANIZATION>Federal
Aboriginal Affairs</ORGANIZATION> Minister <PERSON>Robert Tickner</PERSON> canceled a meeting set
for <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with <PERSON>Mansell</PERSON> and other <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal</ORGANIZATION> representatives to
discuss the return of ancestoral Aboriginal skeletal remains from
overseas.
   A spokesman for <PERSON>Tickner</PERSON> said the minister would not meet any
representatives of a provisional Aboriginal government.
   <PERSON>Mansell</PERSON> said the provisional government would encourage local
Aboriginal communities to take back what they consider their land
by squatting on it and would provide them with financial and
``people'' support to resist police and government attempts to
remove them.
   However, <PERSON>Mansell</PERSON> said the provisional government was purely a
political body and would not compete with any government bodies
that provide services to Aboriginal people.
   He said the provisional government's main aims were obtaining
land rights, gaining control over Aboriginal culture and heritage,
and pursuing the return of the Aboriginal skeletal remains from
overseas.
   <PERSON>Mansell</PERSON> denied the new government would cause greater division
between Aborigines and whites.
   ``There will always be divisions in this country because there
are two distinct peoples and there is nothing wrong with being
different,'' he said. ``The only thing that's wrong with people
being different is where one group imposes its will upon another.''
   Funding for the new government would be provided by a system of
rent payments, the sale of Aboriginal passports and donations.
   Under the rent-payment system, already in operation in <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>
state, sympathetic whites who believe in Aboriginal sovereignty
over the continent pay nominal rent to the black community.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-4293</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFJB6ABBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930610
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 JUN 93 / Aboriginal land claim row jolts investors
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EMILIA TAGAZA
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
INVESTORS in the Australian mining, pastoral and timber industries were
yesterday thrown into confusion by a deadlock in talks between federal and
state governments on how to deal with aboriginal land claims.
And while the officials grappled with a definition of 'native land title'
the Australian High Court has been flooded with aboriginal claims covering
vast tracts of land, including the whole of the <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> region. Large areas
in <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> are also being claimed.
The meeting between <PERSON>Mr Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime minister, and state premiers was
to have drawn up a national procedure to deal with aboriginal land claims
triggered by the so-called Mabo decision handed down by the High Court a
year ago. The court recognised that native titles existed before European
occupation of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
The decision abolished the accepted doctrine that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was no one's
land when the Europeans arrived. As a result of the decision, aboriginal
groups able to demonstrate a continuing link with an area of land are now
able to claim native titles.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON>'s Labor government has accepted the principle of native titles,
and has tried to get agreement from state governments to establish tribunals
to hear and resolve claims to them. And in a move to protect mining and
business leases that might be covered by aboriginal claims, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> has
proposed to introduce legislation validating leases granted between <DATE>1975</DATE> and
the time of the Mabo decision in <DATE>1992</DATE>. He has also proposed compensation be
paid to Aborigines suffering losses from such leases.
While the state governments agreed to legislate and validate leases, two of
the most resource-rich states, <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>, have rejected
the Mabo decision, arguing that state parliaments could legislate to
extinguish native titles.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> has now threatened to introduce federal legislation to force
state governments to come into line.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-9312</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHKB7AAVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930811
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 AUG 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: Government supports mine over
aborigine land claim
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>AUSTRALIA</LOCATION>'S federal government, under pressure from miners and state
governments, yesterday gave its support to a <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> aluminium and
bauxite project that promises 2,000 jobs but is under threat from an
aboriginal land claim.
<PERSON>Mr Michael Lavarch</PERSON>, the attorney general, said legislation protecting
<ORGANIZATION>Comalco</ORGANIZATION>'s Weipa project, the first working mine to be hit by a native title
claim, may be introduced in <DATE>September</DATE>. 'The mining leases which <ORGANIZATION>Comalco</ORGANIZATION> hold
will be validated,' he said in a radio interview.
The Weipa bauxite mine leases are included in a claim by the aboriginal Wik
people for more than 35,000 sq km of land on the western side of <LOCATION>Cape York</LOCATION>
peninsula.
A landmark <DATE>1992</DATE> high court case, known as the Mabo case after one of the
aboriginal litigants, established aboriginal native title. It ruled that
where aborigines could prove a continuing relationship with their
traditional lands, their native title might not have been extinguished by
white settlement.
<ORGANIZATION>Comalco</ORGANIZATION>, 67 per cent owned by <ORGANIZATION>CRA</ORGANIZATION>, had said the aboriginal claim would scare
off lenders from a planned ADollars 1.83bn (Pounds 830m) expansion of its
smelter and electricity generating operations at the port of <LOCATION>Gladstone</LOCATION>.
It declined to comment on <PERSON>Mr Lavarch</PERSON>'s remarks. But <PERSON>Mr Lauchlan McIntosh</PERSON>,
executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Mining Industry Council</ORGANIZATION>, praised the
move. '<PERSON>Mr Lavarch</PERSON> has seen the value of the project to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>,' he said.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1099 Metal Ores, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Facilities.
    GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-2522</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DLND1ABJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931214
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 DEC 93 / Land bill leaves Australians unclear where they stand: An
Aborigine rights law that pleases few
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Noel Pearson</PERSON>, a 28-year-old lawyer, tells a group of Australian senators why
he, and fellow Aborigines, negotiated a milestone land rights deal with the
government: 'It was a salvage exercise - a desperate salvage exercise.'
<PERSON>Michael Mansell</PERSON>, speaking for the more radical <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal Alliance
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, tells the senators that the proposed legislation which has come
out of those negotiations and could be passed into law this week, would do
little to help his people. Worse, it could impede their rights in some
areas.
Both men are presenting their views in a <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> committee room which, with
its air-conditioning and wood-panelling, is far from the scorched red earth
at the centre of this fight. There, everyone agrees, Aborigine communities
hope of grasping the complex legal tussle that is going on.
'I can't say that half of Aborigines have any understanding of this bill,'
says <PERSON>Mr Mansell</PERSON>.
The Australian government's native title bill is also perplexing the
business community. Lawyers for the nation's mining and resource-based
companies have spent weeks scouring the wording and wondering whether money
poured into project development would now be secure from lengthy legal
battles.
'Let's put it like this. The lawyers haven't found any problems - yet,' says
one mining executive, when asked about the likely go-ahead for a stalled
multi-million-dollar deal. Summing up the general concern, <PERSON>Mr John Prescott</PERSON>,
head of <ORGANIZATION>BHP</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s largest industrial company, has likened the
legislation to 'reading porridge'.
For all the confusion, its significance is difficult to understate. In
simple economic terms, land-related industries are crucial to the nation's
prosperity. Mining and agriculture, for example, account for about 7.5 per
cent of gross domestic product and provide more than 60 per cent of
merchandise exports.
The native title bill represents an attempt by today's <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to come to
terms with a less than glorious aspect of its past. When European settlers
first arrived in <LOCATION>Botany Bay</LOCATION> in the <DATE>late 18th century</DATE>, they worked on the
premise that land was uninhabited. This was despite an evident indigenous
population who were simply 'dispossessed'. This was compounded by decades of
shoddy treatment meted out to the Aboriginal community. A law prohibiting
racial discrimination came into force only in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
Unemployment is high among indigenous people and social conditions are poor.
Tensions lurk close to the surface. The death recently of <PERSON>Daniel Yock</PERSON>, a
young Aborigine dancer who had been arrested in a <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION> street brawl,
prompted riotous demonstrations, allegations of police brutality, and a
public inquiry.
The immediate catalyst for some form of native title legislation has been
legal rather than moral, however. Last year, the Australian high court
decreed that native title could exist where Aborigines had maintained a
close and continuing relationship with the land, although it added that land
titles acquired under accepted law since European settlement should not be
disturbed. The bill is an attempt to marry these two pronouncements.
In essence it provides for a system of 'validating' existing land titles.
Where this happened, and except in the case of mining leases, native title
claims would be extinguished. In the case of mining leases, native title
would be allowed to stand alongside an existing lease, then take over when
that lease expired.
However, where a genuine native title claim was extinguished, compensation
would be paid by state or federal government. A system of tribunals would be
set up to handle claims and adjudicate on compensation matters. Native title
holders or claimants would have negotiating rights over the land in question
but no veto right.
The compromise nature of the legislation means that its likely practical
implications please no one. On the Aborigine side, it is estimated that no
more than 10 per cent of the indigenous population would have any chance of
successfully asserting native title claims. In most cases, victorious claims
would be levelled against vacant Crown land, the largest amounts of which
lie in western <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
This makes all important the federal government's promise of a land fund to
help the majority of Aborigines who did not gain from the bill. 'The only
way my people in <LOCATION>Cape York</LOCATION> are going to benefit is via the land fund,' says
<PERSON>Mr Pearson</PERSON>, for example. But the dollar amount has yet to be spelt out.
Moreover, as more radical voices such as <PERSON>Mr Mansell</PERSON>'s point out, even where
Aborigines do establish native title they would not get back everything
which the land holds. Mineral rights, for instance, would remain with the
Crown.
While the mining and pastoral industries know that government would pick up
compensation costs, this would not prevent long hearings to establish native
title rights. In theory, the private sector should be no more than a
bystander in this process; in practice, it would probably incur legal and
other costs.
Meanwhile, the ability of native title claimants or holders to negotiate
over developments may lead to unwanted delays. Such uncertainties - and
there are others - could affect the availability and cost of project
finance, it is argued. The nation's biggest mining companies warned this
month that the need to establish the native title position before beginning
exploration would divert the industry's investment abroad. 'You'll see the
exploration dollar vote with its feet,' says one executive.
And for the general public, there is the big unanswered question of how much
the compensation claims would cost, but the government refuses to be drawn.
One <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION> official has hinted that higher taxes may be down the road.
Opposition leaders have warned that the sums, including the land fund, could
be considerable; the government says it is impossible to assess, although it
expects that the number of successful native title claims would be limited.
Judging by opinion polls, this leaves the public as wary as everyone else
about the legislation's merits.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6541 Title Abstract Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT932-4298</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DFJB6AA6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930610
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 JUN 93 / Aboriginal land claims deadlock jolts investors
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By EMILIA TAGAZA
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MELBOURNE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
INVESTORS in the Australian mining, pastoral and timber industries were
yesterday thrown into confusion by a deadlock in talks between federal and
state governments on how to deal with aboriginal land claims.
And while the officials grappled with a definition of 'native land title'
the Australian high court has been flooded with aboriginal claims covering
vast tracts of land, including the whole of the <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> region. Large areas
in <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> are also being claimed.
The meeting between <PERSON>Mr Paul Keating</PERSON>, the prime minister, and state premiers
was to have drawn up a national procedure to deal with aboriginal land
claims triggered by the so-called Mabo decision handed by the high court in
<DATE>June last year</DATE>.
The court recognised that native titles existed before European occupation
of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The decision abolished the accepted doctrine that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>
was no one's land when the Europeans arrived.
As a result of the decision, aboriginal groups able to demonstrate a
continuing link with an area of land are now able to claim native titles.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON>'s Labor government has accepted the principle of native titles,
and has tried to get agreement from state governments to establish tribunals
to hear and resolve claims to them. And in a move to protect mining and
business leases that might be covered by aboriginal claims, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> has
proposed to introduce legislation validating leases granted between <DATE>1975</DATE> and
the time of the Mabo decision in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
He has also proposed that compensation be paid to Aborigines suffering
losses from such leases.
While the state governments agreed to legislate and validate leases, two of
the most resource-rich states, <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>, have rejected
the Mabo decision, arguing that state parliaments could legislate to
extinguish native titles.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> has now threatened to introduce federal legislation to force
state governments to come into line.
<PERSON>Mr Richard Court</PERSON>, the premier of <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>, said that his state
would become ungovernable if security of title under the state's land
management system was undermined by <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON>'s proposal.
<PERSON>Mr Jeff Kennett</PERSON>, the premier of <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>, warned that the public would be
'baying for blood' of politicians if key investment projects were
jeopardised by the proposal.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-5964</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DCCCKAGTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930303
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 MAR 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: Eddie Mabo's legacy of fear for
Australian miners - A judgment named after an obscure aborigine is
threatening the industry
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN MINING circles, the best known name in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is not <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, the
prime minister, but <PERSON>Eddie Mabo</PERSON>, an obscure aboriginal activist who lived all
his life on an isolated island off the tropical north coast. <PERSON>Mr Mabo</PERSON>, who
died last year, gave his name to a historic judgment by <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s High
Court which many mining companies claim is a threat to the future of the
resources industry.
Both the Labor government and the conservative opposition have played down
the implications of the Mabo case, partly in order to avoid a damaging row
with aboriginal activists. However, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s approaching federal election
has focussed attention on the multitude of questions raised by the case that
will face whichever is in government after polling day, <DATE>March 13</DATE>.
The uncertainty flows from a High Court ruling that <PERSON>Mr Mabo</PERSON>'s Meriam
aboriginal group owns <LOCATION>Murray Island</LOCATION>, which lies in the <LOCATION>Torres Strait</LOCATION> between
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION>. The significance of this is the court's
recognition that a form of 'native title' may exist where ownership of land
has not been explicitly transferred to private hands - for example, by
freehold sale.
The judgment was greeted with jubilation by aboriginal activists because it
extinguishes the constitutional doctrine that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was terra nullius,
or unoccupied, when European settlement began in <DATE>1788</DATE>.
In the long-term, the judgment will help to legitimise aboriginal claims
that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s indigenous inhabitants were disposessed by British settlers
and may increase pressure on the government to negotiate a treaty. More
immediately, however, it has prompted claims from aborigines and mining
groups alike that other areas, many of which include mines or mining
prospects, may be open to similar land claims.
Already, aboriginal groups have indicated that ownership claims will be made
on much of the Kimberleys region of <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION> and the Nabalco
bauxite mine at <ORGANIZATION>Gove</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>. Other claims have been
discussed, though not yet filed, on <ORGANIZATION>MIM Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' <LOCATION>McArthur River</LOCATION>
lead/zinc/silver project in the territory and most of central <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, the
state capital of <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>. More claims are likely according to <PERSON>Mr Mick
Dodson</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Land Council</ORGANIZATION>, an aboriginal advisory group,
who says 'blanket land claims' across <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> are likely to prove a 'gold
mine' for aborigines.
The ruling was the last straw for many people in the mining industry, which
was already concerned about the federal government's decision to block a
gold project at Coronation Hill because of Aboriginal religious objections.
Sir <PERSON>Arvi Parbo</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Western Mining Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, says the ruling
raises doubts about the legality of existing mines and warns that new
projects may be delayed or cancelled.
Ironically, the federal government has made determined efforts over the last
year to overcome unease about the Coronation Hill decision by establishing a
'fast tracking' approval mechanism for major projects. The accelerated
approval procedure is likely to be undermined, however, if projects are made
the subject of land claims relying on the precedent of the Mabo decision.
<ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION>, for example, received approval within nine months for the ADollars 250m
(Pounds 120m) <LOCATION>McArthur River</LOCATION> project. It believes it holds legal title to
the area and intends to press on with development.
It is not clear, however, how the title granted under existing legislation
would be affected if the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Land Council</ORGANIZATION> went ahead with its threat to
file a land claim. This is because the High Court judgment says that native
title exists only where aboriginal groups can prove continuous occupation or
close association with the land being claimed. In addition, the extent of
the native title would depend on the traditional rights of the aborigines
concerned, which might vary from full ownership to hunting or fishing
rights. A further complication is that native title is likely to have been
extinguished by mining titles issued before <DATE>1975</DATE>, most of which effectively
transferred the land to private ownership. However, most mining titles
issued since <DATE>1975</DATE> would not extinguish native title because of the
provisions of the federal Racial Discrimination Act, which prevents the
abolition of land claim rights without compensation.
<PERSON>Mr Hugh Morgan</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>WMC</ORGANIZATION>'s managing director, has called on the federal
government to ease the problem by repealing the Race Discrimination Act.
However, such a step is unlikely because it would breach <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s
international treaty obligations.
An alternative approach would be for mining companies to reach specific
agreements with local aboriginal groups under which they would trade
compensation for a binding agreement that no land claim would be made.
<LOCATION>Zapopan</LOCATION>, a small mining company, recently reached such an agreement with the
Jawoyn aborigines which will allow the development of a gold mine at <ORGANIZATION>Mount
Todd</ORGANIZATION>, about 300 km (180 miles) south of <LOCATION>Darwin</LOCATION>. Other mining groups say,
however, that this strategy is fraught with danger because of the fragmented
nature of aboriginal society.
'It is impossible to know whether the people signing have the authority to
sign on behalf of all the groups which may have an association with the
area,' says an executive involved in land claims negotiations.
Faced with this uncertainty both the government and the Liberal/National
Party coalition have promised consultations with aboriginal and mining
groups to try to find an agreed solution. The coalition has said it would
legislate 'if necessary', but has not explained how the legislation would
work. Nor has it supported threats by the conservative <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>
government to block land claims by legislation.
<PERSON>Mr Gregory McIntyre</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Perth</LOCATION> lawyer who represented <PERSON>Mr Mabo</PERSON>, says it may
be possible to resolve some of the claims by negotiation, or by legislation
that clarifies aboriginal rights. But the complexity of the judgment means
that many cases will have to be decided by the courts, prolonging the
uncertainty for miners and aborigines alike.
'The only alternative would be for the <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION> to rule in the next test
case that mining rights extinguish native title (in all cases),' <PERSON>Mr McIntyre</PERSON>
says. 'That would put an ened to all the uncertainty. But if the court rules
favourably for the Aboriginal people then there would be a drawn out process
of claims being made.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P10   Metal Mining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Natural resources.
    GOVT  Legal issues.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 30
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8449</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKPCNAA1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931116
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 NOV 93 / Keating plea over Aborigine rights
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, Australian prime minister, yesterday called on the nation
to use high court recognition of Aborigines' land rights as 'an opportunity
to transcend the history of dispossession' for <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s indigenous
people.
In a rare televised address to the country, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> - who has taken a
large personal role in negotiations between the government and Aborigine
leaders over the highly-contentious native title issue - said that
Australians could not ignore the matter, either 'legally or morally'.
However, he provided no advance details of the government's bill on
Aboriginal land rights, which is due to be introduced into parliament later
this week, possibly today.
The proposed legislation follows a High Court ruling <DATE>last year</DATE>, which did
away with the notion that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was uninhabited before European
settlement and said native title could exist where there had been 'close and
continuing' association with the land.
Despite <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON>'s claims that there needed to be a national standard for
land rights determination, the recalcitrant Western Australian government
maintained its opposition to the federal package yesterday. Western
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is the area most likely to be affected by the land rights
legislation. In theory, about 40 per cent of the state could be subject to
native title claims.
<PERSON>Mr Richard Court</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION>'s premier, threatened to speed the
passage of his own state's rival land rights legislation if the commonwealth
denied full public and parliamentary debate on the federal legislation.
The <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION> government has already published a bill which would
extinguish native title, but recognise in law the rights to 'traditional
usage' of the land by Aboriginal people. Mr Court has been emphatic that the
states should retain control of land management, and should not be
constrained by any commonwealth measures.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9532 Urban and Community Development.
    P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-14755</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJOCVAA4FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931015
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 OCT 93 / Keating to act on Aborigine land rights
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, the Australian prime minister, is to present draft
legislation to his cabinet on <DATE>Monday</DATE> setting out a system for deciding land
claims lodged by Aborigine groups.
The legislation could then be delivered to parliament in a matter of weeks.
In <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> yesterday, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> said the proposed legislation would allow
Aborigine groups to choose either federal or state jurisdictions, recognised
by the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>, for the hearing of native title claims.
Some states had argued that all native title decisions should lie in their
hands. However, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> added that decisions over the economic use of
native title land would remain exclusively with Commonwealth-approved state
tribunals.
'Existing grants of interest will be validated and be secure, and the states
and territories will continue to have the capacity to manage land if they
meet the standards of the Commonwealth bill,' he said.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> indicated that native title could, under the government's
legislation, co-exist with some existing leasehold titles, but he did not
detail which leases would come under this category. Aborigine groups have
been pushing to extend an earlier proposal that mining leases should be the
only significant class of leases not to extinguish native title. They have
been seeking to ensure that native title could sit alongside pastoral,
tourism or forestry leases, and revive once these expired.
The issue of Aborigine land rights has been contentious for the past 18
months. In <DATE>May 1992</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION> quashed the notion that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> had
been unoccupied before European settlement and indicated that native title
could apply where Aborigines had maintained close association with the land.
This prompted an outcry from the mining industry, generated concerns among
international investors and pitted some state governments against the
<ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6541 Title Abstract Offices.
    P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 5
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-6917</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBZCKAGRFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930226
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 FEB 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: Aboriginal claim may threaten
mine project
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
MIM HOLDINGS, the Australian resources group, is considering a potential
claim by an aboriginal group for ownership of the site of its <LOCATION>McArthur River</LOCATION>
lead/zinc/silver project in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION> has received a letter from the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Land Council</ORGANIZATION>, an aboriginal
advisory group, seeking consultations about the project on behalf of
aborigines in the territory and in northern <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>. This follows
suggestions by the council that a legal claim for ownership of the land
might be filed unless <ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION> agreed to provide jobs and compensation to
aborigines claiming connection with the area.
<ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION> and a group of Japanese joint venturers received permission to develop
the mine last year after complying with the environmental and planning
regulations of the federal and territorial governments.
However, the status of some mining rights has been thrown into doubt by a
High Court decision last year that overthrew the legal doctrine that
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was terra nullius, or unoccupied, when European settlement began
in <DATE>1788</DATE>. The decision created a form of 'native title' applying to
government-owned land where aboriginal groups can prove uninterrupted
occupation or a continuous close relationship.
A legal claim for ownership of <LOCATION>McArthur River</LOCATION> could delay development of the
mine, which is 70 per cent owned by <ORGANIZATION>MIM</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Nippon Mining and Metals</ORGANIZATION> owns 15
per cent, and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsui</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Materials</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Marubeni</ORGANIZATION> 5 per cent each.
The land council's action angered the territory's government, which claimed
that aboriginal and environmental opposition to mining has reduced
investment proposals.
<PERSON>Mr Shane Stone</PERSON>, mines and energy minister, said the threat of a land claim
against <LOCATION>McArthur River</LOCATION> was 'beyond the pale'. He said the project was 'too
important to become another Coronation Hill' - a gold project in the
<ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> that was blocked in <DATE>1991</DATE> after the federal government
accepted aboriginal claims that the site was sacred.
The territory government did not make clear how it planned to overcome the
provisions of federal race discrimination legislation.
The federal Labor government and the conservative opposition have said that
land claims should be resolved by negotiation.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>MIM Holdings.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P1031 Lead and Zinc Ores.
    P1044 Silver Ores.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Facilities.
    RES  Natural resources.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 32
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880509-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-88 2010EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Australia-Queen     05-09 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Queen,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Queen Opens New Parliament Building; Aborigines Protest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CANBERRA, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Queen <PERSON>Elizabeth II</PERSON> presided <DATE>Monday</DATE> at
the opening of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s new <ORGANIZATION>Parliament House</ORGANIZATION>, which took nearly
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> and eight years to build. About 2,000 aborigines
protested outside.
   The British queen called the building a crowning expression of
Australian faith in parliamentary democracy and noted that it
replaces a provisional Parliament building opened 61 years earlier
by her father, <PERSON>King George VI</PERSON>.
   Aboriginal activists and sympathizers began gathering at dawn to
protest the proceedings and their number grew to about 2,000 by the
time the queen arrived.
   Chants of ``Shame, shame, shame!'' and ``We want land rights
now!'' virtually drowned out the national anthem ``Advance
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> Fair'' during welcoming ceremonies attended by Prime
Minister <PERSON>Bob Hawke</PERSON> and other dignitaries.
   <PERSON>Robyn Dass</PERSON>, an aboriginal activist, said the new building is on
a site sacred to the aborigines.
   Police said cables of the outdoor public address system were cut
before the queen arrived but were restored about 10 minutes into
the ceremony.
   The opening of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament House</ORGANIZATION> is a highlight of year-long
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   At a final cost of <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> (<MONEY>$836 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>), it also is
the nation's most expensive building. There is enough concrete in
it to build 25 replicas of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>'s landmark <ORGANIZATION>Opera House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Opening it was <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON>'s last official function of a
three-week tour that was her 11th visit to the country as queen.
   Huge crowds welcomed her and her husband, <LOCATION>Prince Philip</LOCATION>. The
aborigines turned their backs on the royal couple and sat down en
masse.
   During the queen's inspection of an honor guard, a 3-year-old
aboriginal girl left the crowd and thrust a bouquet of flowers into
her hands.
   She accepted the flowers, wrapped in aboriginal ribbons of
black, red and gold, but did not speak to the girl, <PERSON>Zena Wickes</PERSON>.
   In dedicating the bulding, the queen said: ``I rather doubt that
the founding fathers of the Australian federation could have
foreseen that their work would be crowned by such a confident
expression of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s faith in parliamentary democracy.''
   Hawke paid tribute to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s indigenous people in his
speech, noting that they had lived in the area for 21,000 years.
The aboriginal word ``canberra'' means meeting place.
   The new <ORGANIZATION>Parliament House</ORGANIZATION> has 4,500 rooms, public galleries
seating 1,000 people, kitchens capable of producing 8,000 meals a
day and parking space for more than 2,000 vehicles.
   The old building, half a mile away, is to become a museum.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-17668</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJGDBAA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941007
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 OCT 94 / Aborigines turn to land fund for redress: The ink had barely
dried on the Native Title act when problems started surfacing
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Less than a year since <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> made a kind of peace with its indigenous
population, the question of Aboriginal rights threatens to become
politically contentious again.
In <DATE>December last year</DATE>, the federal parliament passed a law allowing
Aborigines and <LOCATION>Torres Strait</LOCATION> islanders to assert native title claims over
the country's large land mass. If claims were valid and land had since been
put to other uses, compensation would be paid. This was the first formal
acknowledgment - other than a <DATE>1992</DATE> High Court ruling - that the country was
inhabited before European settlement.
But, with the implementation of that package caught in a tussle between
federal and state authorities, the focus is turning to a ADollars 1.5bn
(Pounds 700m) land fund, designed to help those indigenous people who have
little chance of benefiting from the <ORGANIZATION>Native Title</ORGANIZATION> act itself.
In theory, the land fund is a good idea. The problem with last <DATE>December</DATE>'s
law was that it required an indigenous community to demonstrate a 'close and
continuing' association with the land it was claiming. Many Aborigines,
however, have moved from their original homelands.
To some extent, this drift has been voluntary. But it has also been due in
part to the behaviour of white settlers. Aboriginal leaders estimate that no
more than 10 per cent of their people have any chance of benefiting directly
from the new law.
So, in the lengthy negotiations leading up to Native Title Act's passage,
they wrung a promise from the government that a fund would be set up to
acquire land on behalf of the remaining 90 per <MONEY>cent</MONEY> - a concession some saw
as of more practical significance than the main legislation. The government
published details earlier this year, and the necessary legislation is
working its way through parliament in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>.
The problem is that interested parties on all sides have reservations about
the scheme's design. Some Aboriginal representatives say the fund is too
small to be viable, and that the administrative framework is offensively
paternalistic.
Opposition politicians, by contrast, have argued the money could be better
spent on Aborginal health and housing. They have offered a raft of
amendments, saying they will only support the legislation if these are
accepted. It took the government only hours to reject this proposition.
But perhaps the most critical views, from a political standpoint, are those
of the minor parties who hold the balance of power in the senate,
parliament's upper house, through which any legislation must pass. Already,
the two Green party senators, who hail from <LOCATION>Western Australia</LOCATION> and hence have
an important Aboriginal constituency, have expressed serious concerns about
the fund's parameters.
'The question is whether this becomes yet another <ORGANIZATION>Native Title</ORGANIZATION> debate,' said
one official at the <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait Islanders Commission</ORGANIZATION>
(<ORGANIZATION>ATSIC</ORGANIZATION>), which represents Aboriginal interests. He was referring to the
mammoth parliamentary effort which was needed to ensure the original bill's
passage. 'The Greens are playing the same role - trying to extract more
(from the federal government),' he added.
The objectors have a point. The fund is less generous than it originally
appeared. The ADollars 1.5bn figure mentioned in the last budget is made up
of a ADollars 200m contribution from federal coffers in <DATE>1994/5</DATE>, and ADollars
121m a year for the next nine years.
The bulk of this money, moreover, will be invested to ensure the fund is
self-sustaining after the first decade. Only ADollars 45m out of each annual
payment will go to acquire land, or to fund land management. Moreover, funds
<ORGANIZATION>ATSIC</ORGANIZATION> already devotes to this purpose from its own budget - ADollars 21m a
year - will be incorporated in the ADollars 45m figure.
ATSIC has taken the view that any increase is better than none, and that,
having done its best in negotiations, it will support the bill as it stands.
But it is not overjoyed. As <PERSON>David Ross</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>ATSIC</ORGANIZATION> commissioner, has put it: 'I
think the fund is adequate . . . I am certainly not saying that it is
over-generous.'
Other Aboriginal representatives are more critical. <PERSON>Mr Aden Ridgeway</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>New South Wales Aboriginal Land Council</ORGANIZATION>, who represents the
interests of indigenous people in that state, has pointed out that the
annual funding works out at ADollars 5.5m per state or territory, and that
this low level will force the land fund to spread its money around
second-grade properties.
'You will not get really viable land when you do not have much money to
spend,' he warned. 'You will end up with land in the low rainfall area which
obviously will not be productive and viable.'
Equally thorny are the questions of how land purchases will be organised and
prioritised. The legislation is thin on operational details, but it does
provide for the formation of a new body, the <ORGANIZATION>Indigenous Land Corporation</ORGANIZATION>, to
handle purchases and management. After some compromise, the <ORGANIZATION>ILC</ORGANIZATION>'s
prospective board has been extended to seven, and the chairperson plus at
least four other directors must be Aborigines or <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait Islanders</ORGANIZATION>.
Even so, the fact that these appointments are to be made by a federal
minister and that the federal finance minister has ultimate power over the
land fund's investment touches a nerve. It smacks, in some eyes, of
condescension, even racism.
Moreover, in the first three years, the ADollars 45m will be divided between
<ORGANIZATION>ATSIC</ORGANIZATION> and the ILC, with the latter taking on full responsibility after this
interim period. Sorting out how these bodies weigh up the mass of
applications which will almost certainly be presented,and perform
complementary investment roles, is no easy task. As one <ORGANIZATION>ATSIC</ORGANIZATION> adminstrator
points out, it is not a question of maximising financial returns. Outback
land of spiritual significance, for example, might have to be weighed
against the desire of an urban group to build a local community centre.
There is a fair amount of goodwill surrounding the land fund discussions.
There is also considerable reluctance to repeat the trauma of the main
legislation. Nevertheless, as <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> found last year, the road to
reconciliation is long and bumpy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6541 Title Abstract Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-8217</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKQCRAATFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931117
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 NOV 93 / Keating to push land rights bill: Legislation sparks bitter
debate
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE KEATING government yesterday introduced its native land rights bill into
the Australian parliament, and indicated that it hopes to have the
contentious and complex legislation on the statute book by <DATE>Christmas</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mr Kim Beazley</PERSON>, leader of the government's business in the <ORGANIZATION>House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>, declined to rule out use of a parliamentary guillotine,
saying that speedy passage was desirable to ensure certainty. <PERSON>Mr Paul
Keating</PERSON>, the prime minister, also said that 'most aspects of the bill' would
come into force by <DATE>January 1</DATE>, provided parliament approved the package.
However, any forcing of the pace is being resisted by the opposition
parties, and by the West Australian government, which is vehemently opposed
to the federal package and has introduced rival land rights legislation.
The legislation aims to protect native title where Aborigines can show a
continuous link to traditional lands. Aborigines will be empowered to
negotiate on land use but will not have the right to veto development.
Native title tribunals are to be set up to rule on land claims and set
compensation. Mining leases will be validated, but native title rights can
be exercised after a grant expires.
The issue has sparked a bitter debate in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, with business, mining
and conservative political leaders predicting dire economic consequences if
Aborigines gained rights to land taken from them by white settlers.
The bill also establishes a <ORGANIZATION>National Aboriginal</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait Islander
Land Fund</ORGANIZATION>, which will help dispossessed Aborigines acquire and maintain
land.
<PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> gave no figures yesterday on the size of this fund, or on the
expected cost of compensation for the ending of native title claims. An
explanatory memorandum attached to the bill said that about ADollars 6m
(Pounds 2.6m) had been set aside to fund its initial implementation, but
added that it was impossible to identify any direct liability for
compensation that the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> might have to bear, although the sums
could be 'considerable'.
Both the opposition, which has yet to formulate a response to the land
rights issue, and the minority parties who hold the balance of power in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, were <TIME>last night</TIME> studying details of the bill before declaring their
positions.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880111-0076 </DOCNO>
<HL> The Pacific: Aborigines Are Australian, Too </HL>
<AUTHOR> Robert Liddle </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST </CO>
<DATELINE> ALICE SPRINGS, Australia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> begins its bicentennial year amid protests by some of its Aborigine population, one proposal that has cropped up has been for a treaty or compact between the government and its Aboriginal citizens that would recognize the Aborigines' prior ownership of the land. 
Such a treaty, however, is inherently divisive and undoubtedly would create more problems than it would solve. 
In particular, it would perpetuate differences and increase resentment at a time when we should be seeking to weld a strong nation out of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s many ethnic and cultural components. 

   The current national ferment about Aborigines and other minority groups seems to derive from two sources: first, general Australian ignorance about history and the rest of the world; second, an exaggerated paternalism that wishes to ensure that every possible contingency is tied into some piece of legislation. 
Indeed, there is a cultural tendency in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to believe that nothing comparable has ever happened anywhere else. 
Yet the history of the world is full of incidents that compare with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s treatment of Aborigines, and the landing of the British on this soil 200 years ago this <DATE>Jan. 18</DATE> and their subsequent actions were in accord with international law and the accepted attitudes and practices of the time. 
Indeed, in the context of the times, Capt. <PERSON>Arthur Phillip</PERSON>'s treatment of the Aborigines around the <LOCATION>Botany Bay</LOCATION> area was remarkable for its leniency. 

   Apart from the dubious assumption that Aborigines can be addressed en masse -- anyone who understands Aborigines knows that they have a host of tribal and other associations that would have to be dealt with -- a treaty between the government and the Aborigines would be offensive and totally irrelevant to the millions of Australians whose families played no part in the European settlement. 
I am not sure, for example, that Australians of Chinese, Greek, Italian, Vietnamese or dozens of other ethnic backgrounds would appreciate being included in the mass apology of a treaty. 
Perhaps the government will then counter with a treaty between the Aborigines and only those Australians who feel guilty. 

   The point is that since <DATE>1967</DATE> we Aborigines have all been full Australians under the constitution, and that is the way we should be regarded. 
To single out Aborigines as a race apart by means of a treaty or compact is reminiscent of <LOCATION>Fiji</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> or any other country where measures have been taken to protect permanently the interests of one particular group. 
The result is always smoldering resentment. 

   Of course there is much that can be done to help Aborigines improve their lot. 
Some Aboriginal values, attitudes and physical locations stand in the way of their success in the world; the Pintupi people on the Northern Territory/Western Australian border, for example, suffer from their total isolation from the education that might help raise their standard of living. 
Other Aboriginal groups lack English skills or are hurt by plain poverty. 
Any responsible government will take steps to relieve distress and assist people to play their full part in the affairs of the nation. 
The way to do that, however, is to treat everyone as a full Australian -- not separating them into ethnic and racial categories. 
We should be building on what we have in common, not emphasizing our differences. 

   An example of a program that has backfired is the Land Rights Act in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>, designed to improve relations between Aborigines and the rest of the community. 
This woolly-minded paternalism has much to answer for. 
Land is granted to appease the non-Aborigine conscience in the large cities, but Aborigines are not allowed to use it freely because paternalists do not think the black man is sufficiently mature to behave responsibly. 
For example, Aborigines are prohibited from selling, leasing or trading their land -- thus they are shut out from most of the activities that would make their land an economic asset. 

   On top of this, some Aborigines have used Land Rights as a lever in their effort to carve out an Aborigine nation -- something that has never existed. 
Land Rights and a treaty simply cannot create a nation out of a people who constitute but <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s population and are scattered about its vast continent. 
From the other side, some non-Aborigines have used the record of Land Rights to suggest that avarice, bad faith and gullibility are the hallmarks of agreements with the Aborigines and their advisers. 
In the eyes of many Australians, therefore, as Aborigines have won more land they have lost much good will. 
It would be a tragedy were this source of racial disharmony to be enshrined and perpetuated by any sort of treaty. 

   Most likely, such a treaty would be used as the thin edge of the wedge to push for the forming of an Aboriginal nation. If successful, any number of new issues would arise:
   --Would the Aboriginal nation, with its capacity to act in relation to the <LOCATION>Commonwealth</LOCATION>, be able to act in relation to other states as well -- <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, for example? 

   --Would it have rights and obligations under international law? 

   --Would it have standing in international organizations, the <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION> Pact for example? 

   --What would happen to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s position of Australian sovereignty in matters such as resources, transport, communications and trade? 

   Despite these misgivings about a treaty, I am optimistic that the future of Aborigines will be bright once the taint of paternalism can be eradicated. 
Some months ago the Economist magazine described <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> policy toward its native peoples as "helping those who want to join the mainstream society and building wigwams for those who don't." 
In <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, younger people especially are drifting away from the wigwams, looking for a place in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s contemporary society. 
They must be allowed to change and grow over time, just like any other people, so that they are not condemned to permanent dependence. 
Many Aborigines are making a go of it in mainstream <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
They don't parade their Aboriginality; they just get on with living as Australians in today's world. 

   Yet they often come up against unnecessary obstacles. 
Government policies over the past 20 years have priced Aborigines out of the job market. 
In addition, much of the <MONEY>two billion Australian dollars</MONEY> that have been spent on Aboriginal welfare over the past 10 years has been wasted on an unnecessary bureaucracy and projects that were doomed to fail from the outset. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Aboriginal Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, to name but one, should be abolished and direct funding provided to local Aboriginal Councils in rural communities. 
Greater opportunities should be made for Aborigines to enter the private sector, and the disincentives for them to make their own way must be removed. 
In this way Aborigines would not only benefit themselves, but their participation in the economy would also make for a more productive <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 

   Aboriginals played a part in developing <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
Aboriginal troopers and soldiers defended it. 
They want to share in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s future-not contest it. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Liddle</PERSON> is a <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> businessman who runs his own resource consulting firm, <ORGANIZATION>R. Liddle &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-9094</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EKQEIABPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941117
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 NOV 94 / Aborigine fund move defeated
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Efforts to increase significantly the money available to a federally
constituted Aboriginal land fund were defeated yesterday in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, the
Australian parliament's upper house. The fund is designed to acquire land on
behalf of the vast majority of Aborigines who will see no practical benefit
from the country's <ORGANIZATION>Native Title</ORGANIZATION> legislation, which was passed with much
difficulty last year. The <ORGANIZATION>Native Title</ORGANIZATION> act was the first piece of
legislation to acknowledge that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was inhabited before European
settlement.
At that stage the government promised to set up a land fund to make
acquisitions on behalf of dispossessed Aborigines. However, when details of
the scheme were released, critics said it was too small to be viable, and
poorly structured. Amendments put forward, but defeated in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
yesterday, would have increased funds flowing into the land fund to ADollars
15bn (Pounds 7bn) over a 10-year period. The current government plan is for
just ADollars 1.4bn, over the same decade - with much of this money being
invested to ensure that the fund is self-sustaining in 10 years.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9121 Legislative Bodies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Government News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890504-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-04-89 2208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Australia-Gunman 1stLd-Writethru a0781 05-04 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Australia-Gunman, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0781,0403</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Arrest Aboriginal Gunman After Controversial Manhunt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 2nd pvs, `John Porter...,' to UPDATE with
policeman dying. Pick up 3rd pvs, `The manhunt...' DELETES 9th pvs, `One
of..,' to remove outdated material.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Australian aborigine at the center
of a manhunt that sparked a public uproar was arrested with a
hostage on the <ORGANIZATION>Queensland Gold Coast</ORGANIZATION> after a 10-day sweep across
three states, police said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>John Porter</PERSON>, captured <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE>, was the key suspect in the
shooting and wounding of two <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> policemen during an attempted
car theft on <DATE>April 24</DATE>.
   One of the policemen allegedly shot by <PERSON>Porter</PERSON>, 26-year-old <PERSON>Alan
McQueen</PERSON>, died <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> despite emergency surgery in which
doctors removed a lung, a kidney and most of his liver.
   The manhunt for <PERSON>Porter</PERSON> led to a dawn raid on a surburban <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>
home last week in which an unarmed aborigine was fatally shot,
sparking an outcry among Australians over the rough treatment of
aborigines.
   Aboriginal activists responded to the killing of <PERSON>David Gundy</PERSON> by
putting posters up around the city calling for the murder of <PERSON>Ted
Pickering</PERSON>, police minister of <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION> state.
   They also demanded a royal commission _ the highest form of
inquiry available _ into police conduct.
   Aborigines, who number about 160,000 or 1 per cent of the 16
million population, also are angered by the slow progress of a
government inquiry into more than 100 aboriginal deaths in police
custody since <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Police conduct during the manhunt for <PERSON>Porter</PERSON> captured front-page
headlines after authorities admitted that <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> police faked
an arrest, watched it reported on the evening television news and
then told the media it was a hoax.
   Police said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that <PERSON>Porter</PERSON>, 27, recently was released from
jail on parole and said he had six other criminal convictions on
drugs and assault charges.
   Police said <PERSON>Porter</PERSON> tried <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to kidnap a woman, but she
escaped and alerted police.
   They said <PERSON>Porter</PERSON>, who was armed with a .32-calber pistol,
surrendered quietly when surrounded outside an apartment block on
the famed coastal strip of northeast <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   Police said he apparently took a man hostage after driving north
from <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>. The hostage was not injured.
   <PERSON>Porter</PERSON> was charged at the <ORGANIZATION>Brisbane Magistrate</ORGANIZATION>'s court with
kidnapping, grievous bodily harm and use of an unlicensed firearm.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-13852</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DJTC2ABTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 93 / Keating pulls off Aborigine land rights deal: Compromise
package satisfies most farmers, mining interests and Aborigines
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>PAUL Keating</PERSON>, the Australian prime minister, has not enjoyed too many
political successes in recent months. But yesterday he was finally able to
declare that the issue of Aborigine land rights, which has provoked a storm
of controversy in the mining and farming sectors, was a big step closer to
resolution.
A compromise package, which clears the way for legislation later this year,
was carved out in a long cabinet meeting on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. As the details
became clearer during the day, cautious support from many of the interested
parties - including the mining and farming lobbies - began to emerge.
All this was the result of some hairy, last-minute bargaining. On <DATE>Monday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME>, for example, <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> told parliament that land which was held
under pastoral leases could be subject to native title claims - a statement
which reversed an earlier government commitment to farmers.
Yet by the time the cabinet meeting broke up in the small hours of <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME>, this concession to the Aborigine contingent had been dropped.
Instead, <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal</ORGANIZATION> representatives agreed to an alternative proposal - that
they be allowed to convert their own pastoral leases into native title, thus
giving them permanent security on such land.
For the <DATE>past 16 months</DATE>, it has been touch-and-go whether the government
could broker a solution to a High Court decision which makes land rights
legislation imperative. This ruling was handed down in <DATE>June 1992</DATE>, when the
court determined that the Meriam people in the <LOCATION>Torres Strait</LOCATION> were holders of
native title on about nine square kilometres of land. The judgment became
known as the 'Mabo' decision, after <PERSON>Eddie Mabo</PERSON>, leader of the Meriam people
who had begun the court action a decade earlier.
The land involved in <LOCATION>Mabo</LOCATION> may have been modest, but the implications were
huge. Australian law had always operated on the assumption that the land was
unoccupied before European settlement - the principle of 'terra nullius'.
The High Court, by contrast, ruled that native title claims could be
successful where the indigenous people had maintained a close connection
with the land, although it also said that land titles acquired under
accepted law since European settlement should not be disturbed.
To complicate matters further, the Mabo decision determined that states and
territories could extinguish native title - but only in accordance with the
country's constitution and laws, notably the <DATE>1975</DATE> Racial Discrimination Act.
In short, compensation could be required.
Unfortunately, the <ORGANIZATION>High Court</ORGANIZATION> ruling was made in the narrow context of one
claim, and gave little guidance on the practical application of these
principles. From the outset, the federal government was forced to tread a
fine line between meeting Aboriginal demands, now backed up by the Mabo
ruling, and delivering a degree of reassurance to existing land users, such
as the mining companies and farmers, so that economic stability was not
threatened. To make the task harder, it also had to juggle a delicate
relationship with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s states and territories, traditionally
responsible for land management.
The final package, as agreed by the cabinet this week, is complex.
Essentially, it will allow indigenous people to pursue claims for native
title either through the federal court or through state jurisdiction.
Decisions on the economic use of land, however, will remain the domain of
the states, provided they comply with the 'spirit and principles' of the
<ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> legislation.
All existing leases can be 'validated', and native title will then be
extinguished for all categories other than mining leases. Governments will
pick up any compensation costs resulting from validation of existing grants
and 'there will be further discussions with states and territories on
cost-sharing arrangements between the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> and complying states'.
Where land is subject to native title, the indigenous holders will not have
a veto on development, but they will have a 'right to negotiation'. <PERSON>Mr
Keating</PERSON>'s statement suggested that the time limits for negotiation would be
set at four months in the case of exploration licences, and six months for
mining leases. There would also be four- and six-month arbitration periods
for the two respective categories.
Will the package fly? On the political front, the Australian Democrats, one
of the two minority parties whose parliamentary support is essential,
welcomed the package. State premiers in <LOCATION>New South Wales</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Australia</LOCATION>
and the chief minister in the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> reserved judgment, but
<LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON> came out in support.
<ORGANIZATION>National Federation of Farmers</ORGANIZATION> supported the deal. Even the <ORGANIZATION>Australian
Mining Industry Council</ORGANIZATION>, an umbrella group for the large mining companies,
gave lukewarm endorsement. It noted that the package would at least provide
certainty by validating existing leases. But the <ORGANIZATION>AMIC</ORGANIZATION> still quarrelled with
the lack of parity between mining and pastoral leases; claimed that native
title claimants' right to choose between federal and state jurisdictions
would prove unwieldy; and maintained that all states would need to be
supportive for the package to work.
This may be the sticking point. Western <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> - a key natural resources
state - has taken the hardest line against the federal proposals to date.
Yesterday, <PERSON>Mr Richard Court</PERSON>, the Liberal premier, said the legislation could
lead to long court battles, and pointed out that up to 40 per cent of the
state may be subject to native title claim. He is due to hold talks with <PERSON>Mr
Keating</PERSON>'s legal advisers in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION> today.
The Aborigines' response, meanwhile, was mixed. Although Aboriginal
representatives were closely involved in the final negotiations, more
radical elements within the indigenous community were far from impressed.
'It's the coming of the second invasion,' said <PERSON>Mr Bob Weatherall</PERSON>, a
Brisbane-based activist and chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Aboriginal Provisional
Government</ORGANIZATION>.
It was up to Aboriginal people to prove that native title existed rather
than the other way round, he commented. 'The High Court made it plain that
it was wrong for governments and commercial groups to collude in taking away
Aboriginal land interests in the past without accounting to Aboriginal
people. It must be equally wrong for the federal parliament, and the states
and territories, in <DATE>1993</DATE> to repeat the dose by 'validating'.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
    P01   Agricultural Production-Crops.
    P02   Agricultural Production-Livestock.
    P10   Metal Mining.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 9
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-15542</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CDABOAA1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920401
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 APR 92 / Australia plans Aborigine aid package
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KEVIN BROWN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SYDNEY
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE Australian government yesterday announced plans to spend ADollars 150m
(Pounds 66m) over five years to try to improve living conditions for the
country's Aboriginal minority, and combat discrimination by white
Australians.
The spending forms the first government response to the report of a <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Commission</ORGANIZATION> into the deaths of 99 Aborigines and <ORGANIZATION>Torres Strait Islanders</ORGANIZATION> in
police custody. The <ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION> found that the prisoners, most of whom
committed suicide, were victims of 'entrenched and institutionalised racism
