<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900419-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-90 0130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Leukemia     04-19 0317</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Leukemia,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Drug Effective Against Rare Form of Leukemia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A single round of treatment with an experimental
new medicine appears to be highly effective against a rare form of
leukemia and may help fight other kinds of blood cancer as well,
says a study published today.
   The new drug was developed at <ORGANIZATION>Scripps Clinic and Research
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>La Jolla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, where doctors tested it on patients
with hairy cell leukemia. In almost every case, the medicine erased
all signs of the disease.
   Hairy cell leukemia affects the white blood cells that make
disease-fighting antibodies. Doctors are also testing the drug
against chronic lymphocytic leukemia, non-Hodgkins lymphoma and
cutaneous T cell lymphoma.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Scripps</ORGANIZATION> doctors concluded that the medicine, called
2-chlorodeoxyadenosine, or 2-CdA, ``may well be the drug of choice
in the treatment of hairy cell leukemia.''
   The study was directed by <PERSON>Dr. Lawrence D. Piro</PERSON> and published in
the <ORGANIZATION>New England Journal of Medicine</ORGANIZATION>.
   In their study, doctors gave the drug to 12 patients. Of these,
11 have remained completely free of all signs of the disease for
periods up to four years.
   The doctors cautioned that longer follow-up will be necessary
before they can be sure they have actually cured the disease.
   Two other treatments for hairy cell leukemia have been developed
in recent years. They are interferon and deoxycoformycin, a drug
that is similar to 2-CdA. However, interferon is less effective,
and both of those treatments produce serious side effects.
   By contrast, the only unwanted effect of 2-CdA was a few days of
fever. Patients experienced no nausea, hair loss, rashes or other
symptoms typical of cancer therapy. Also unlike other treatments,
this one appears to work after a single seven-day course of therapy.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Scripps Clinic</ORGANIZATION> reached an agreement recently with <ORGANIZATION>Johnson &amp;
Johnson</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ortho Pharmaceuticals</ORGANIZATION> to produce the drug, which is not
yet approved for routine use.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900418-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-18-90 1412EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Leukemia-Drug     04-18 0330</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Leukemia-Drug,0338</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Drug Effective Against Rare Form of Leukemia</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For release at 6 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An experimental cancer drug that works after a
single round of treatment appears to be the most effective medicine
yet for a rare form of leukemia, according to a study.
   The drug _ called 2-chlorodeoxyadenosine, or 2-CdA _ has
produced complete remissions in almost all hairy cell leukemia
patients treated, and none has relapsed so far.
   Researchers who developed and tested the medicine report that it
``may well be the drug of choice in the treatment of hairy cell
leukemia.''
   The drug also has been used successfully against chronic
lymphocytic leukemia. It, like hairy cell leukemia, is a cancer of
the white blood cells, which produce disease-fighting antibodies.
   The latest study, published in <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s New England Journal of
Medicine, was directed by <PERSON>Dr. Lawrence D. Piro</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Scripps
Clinic and Research Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>La Jolla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. Scripps recently
made an agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Johnson &amp; Johnson</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ortho Pharmaceuticals</ORGANIZATION> to
produce and distribute the drug once it's approved by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Food
and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   In the published work, doctors gave the drug to 12 patients as
far back as four years ago. In 11, the disease disappeared and they
remain disease free.
   In all, the <ORGANIZATION>Scripps</ORGANIZATION> doctors have treated 24 patients with almost
complete success. However, they caution that longer follow up will
be necessary before they can be sure they have actually cured the
disease.
   Two other treatments for hairy cell leukemia have been developed
in recent years. They are interferon and deoxycoformycin, a drug
that is similar to 2-CdA. However, interferon is less effective,
and both of those treatments produce serious side effects.
   By contrast, the only unwanted effect of 2-CdA was a few days of
fever. Patients experienced no nausea, hair loss, rashes or other
symptoms typical of cancer therapy. Also unlike other treatments,
this one appears to work after a single seven-day course of therapy.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900419-0016
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900419-0016.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology &amp; Medicine:
   New Drug Shows
   Promise Treating
   Type of Leukemia
   ----
   By Ron Winslow
</HL>
<DATE>
04/19/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   JNJ
</CO>
<IN>
DRUG MANUFACTURERS (DRG)
MEDICAL AND BIOTECHNOLOGY (MTC)
</IN>
<LP>
   A new cancer drug proved strikingly successful with very
few side effects in treating a relatively rare form of
leukemia, researchers said.
   The drug, called 2-CdA, was nearly 100% effective treating
12 patients with hairy-cell leukemia. The patients underwent
just one seven-day treatment and experienced almost none of
the debilitating side effects such as vomiting, hair-loss and
kidney and liver problems associated with other chemotherapy.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The results need to be replicated by other researchers
before definitive conclusions can be made, and the long-term
effect of the treatment remains unknown. But the initial
experience with the compound is especially promising, and an
apparent improvement over other therapy for the disease,
scientists said.
   "There aren't many {drugs} where you can administer one
course of treatment and have the disease go away and stay
away for as long as four years," says <PERSON>Lawrence Piro</PERSON>, chief of
cancer research at <ORGANIZATION>Scripps Clinic &amp; Research Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>La
Jolla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, where the drug was developed. "The leukemia
hasn't come back in any of the patients we treated." The
study is published in today's New England Journal of
Medicine.
   "It is without doubt the most effective treatment for
hairy-cell leukemia, in terms of rapidity of response," adds
<PERSON>Elihu H. Estey</PERSON>, a cancer researcher at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Texas-M.D. Anderson Cancer Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Dr. Estey</PERSON>
recently began treating patients with 2-CdA and has had
similar results with five patients. "It's a striking
finding," he says. "It's very unlikely to be a fluke."
   Hairy-cell leukemia, so-called because of the appearance
of the cancerous cells under the microscope, affects about
6,000 people in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, with 600 new cases a year. As the
disease progresses, patients become anemic, are vulnerable to
infection and often need blood transfusions.
   Until the mid-1980s, treatments were ineffective, and
patients often died of blood problems and infections. Since
then, alpha interferon, a drug sold by <ORGANIZATION>Hoffmann-La Roche Inc.</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Schering-Plough Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and an experimental drug called
deoxycoformycin have significantly reduced death rates from
hairy-cell leukemia. <PERSON>Hoffmann-La Roche</PERSON> is the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> subsidiary
of <ORGANIZATION>F. Hoffmann-La Roche &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   But neither drug is as effective as 2-CdA appears to be in
low doses and both can cause such side effects as nausea,
vomiting, skin rashes and nervous-system disorders,
researchers say. "With the lack of toxicity and the ease with
which people go into remission {with 2-CdA}, I think there's
something really going on here," says <PERSON>Ellin Berman</PERSON>, a staff
leukemia doctor at <ORGANIZATION>Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Scripps</ORGANIZATION> said it negotiated an agreement with a subsidiary
of <ORGANIZATION>Johnson &amp; Johnson</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New Brunswick</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, to produce and
distribute 2-CdA to other centers for broader clinical
trials. The researchers said the drug is easy to produce and
thus is likely to be less expensive than other cancer
treatments.
   In the 12-patient study, 2-CdA, short for
2-chlorodeoxyadenosine, was administered continuously for
seven days to patients aged 36 to 61. Within eight to 10
weeks, 11 of the patients had no trace of cancer in their
blood or bone marrow; the 12th had a small amount remaining
in the marrow, but he declined further bone marrow
monitoring, <PERSON>Dr. Piro</PERSON> said. His blood tests are normal, <PERSON>Dr.
Piro</PERSON> added. None of the patients have had a relapse; complete
remission has lasted from seven to 46 months after treatment,
according to the study.
   "When you can make all the disease go away with a single
infusion of therapy, you have a disease which may be able to
be cured," <PERSON>Dr. Piro</PERSON> said. But because hairy-cell leukemia
proliferates slowly, a relapse could occur long after
treatment. Longer follow-up is necessary to determine whether
2-CdA actually cures the disease.
   The drug was first made about 10 years ago at <ORGANIZATION>Scripps</ORGANIZATION> by
<PERSON>Dennis A. Carson</PERSON>, who studied severe combined
immunodeficiency disease, made famous a few years ago by the
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> boy that lived in a bubble. People with that disease
lack an enzyme that processes deoxyadenosine, a chemical
that, without the enzyme, builds up in infection-fighting
white blood cells and kills them. Since cancer patients have
the enzyme, <ORGANIZATION>Scripps</ORGANIZATION> scientists developed a compound that
mimics deoxyadenosine, but tricks the enzyme so it can't be
processed. The compound then kills the white blood cells,
including those that are cancerous. New, normal white cells
are then generated in the bone marrow.
   Because hairy-cell leukemia is rare, a 12-patient study
"is considered a pretty good series," says Sloan-Kettering's
<PERSON>Dr. Berman</PERSON>. "It's ironic that we have three active drugs for
a disease that's fairly rare, but for some of the more common
forms of leukemia, we don't yet have good treatments."
   <PERSON>Dr. Piro</PERSON> said 2-CdA has also been used effectively in
initial trials to treat more common cancers, including
chronic lymphocytic leukemia, non-Hodgkins lymphoma and
cutaneous T-cell lymphoma. About <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of patients --
most of whom had failed other treatments -- responded to the
drug, some with complete remission, he said. "Now, we will
use {2-CdA} as a first treatment to see if response and
remission are higher," he said. Meanwhile, researchers at
on AIDS-related lymphoma.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901211-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-11-90 0811EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Smoking-Leukemia     12-11 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Smoking-Leukemia,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>Survey Finds Strong Smoking-Leukemia Link</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cigarette smoking appears to increase the
risk of developing leukemia, and kicking the habit may not be
enough to dodge the dreaded blood disease, a study says.
   <PERSON>Paul K. Mills</PERSON>, a professor at <ORGANIZATION>Loma Linda University</ORGANIZATION> and the
principal author of the study, said research suggests that even
former smokers are at high risk.
   ``It's very discouraging,'' <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``We saw a strong
association between prior cigarette smoking and the risk of
developing leukemia.''
   The study's results are being published this month in the
   Cigarette smoking also has been linked to cancers of the lung,
bladder, pancreas, esophagus, throat and cervix.
   The study is part of the <ORGANIZATION>Adventist Health Study</ORGANIZATION>, a major
epidemiological investigation of the causes of various cancers
among <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> members of the Seventh-day <ORGANIZATION>Adventist Church</ORGANIZATION>. About
34,000 Adventists responded to the study.
   Although the vast majority of Adventists do not smoke by church
proscription, many are adult converts to the religion who smoked
cigarettes prior to their baptism into the church.
   The researchers found that the ex-smokers had twice the risk of
developing leukemia than non-smokers.
   For people who regularly smoked more than 25 cigarettes a day,
the risk of developing leukemia increased threefold. The Adventists
who had smoked for more than 15 years had a 2{-fold increased
leukemia risk.
   Leukemia is a bone marrow cancer in which the marrow is replaced
by immature, abnormal white blood cells. The disease kills 18,000
people a year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Clark Heath Jr.</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>American Cancer Society</ORGANIZATION> said the
causes of leukemia are largely unknown.
   But several studies in recent years, including a large study of
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military veterans, have suggested smoking as a cause, he said.
   The <LOCATION>Loma Linda</LOCATION> study estimates that about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of leukemia
cases were linked to smoking.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880909-0170 </DOCNO>
<HL> Smokers Are More Apt Than Nonsmokers To Die From Leukemia, Study Concludes </HL>
<AUTHOR> Joann S. Lublin (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> TOB </IN>
<DATELINE> LONDON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Men who smoke heavily are nearly twice as likely as nonsmokers to die from a common form of leukemia, concludes a report by the <ORGANIZATION>University of Edinburgh</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The analysis, based on a previous study of 248,046 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> veterans, offers the firmest link yet between cigarette consumption and the disease. 
The finding could add leukemia to the already lengthy list of suspected health risks from smoking. 

   The report in tomorrow's British Medical Journal "may well have an emotional impact on some people who are vacillating" about quitting smoking "and for one reason or another have a fear of leukemia," suggested <PERSON>Nicholas Wald</PERSON>, an epidemiologist at the <ORGANIZATION>Medical College of St. Bartholomew's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> here. 

   "The balance of evidence suggests that smoking may cause leukemia," <PERSON>Dr. Wald</PERSON> wrote in an accompanying commentary on the analysis, which was conducted by <ORGANIZATION>University of Edinburgh</ORGANIZATION> epidemiologist <PERSON>Leo Kinlen</PERSON>. 

   <PERSON>Dr. Kinlen</PERSON>, who directs the university's Cancer Epidemiology Unit, examined leukemia deaths from a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> study that had tracked veterans' smoking between <DATE>1954</DATE> and <DATE>1969</DATE>. 
The earlier study tallied overall deaths from various causes, including 723 deaths due to leukemia. 
<PERSON>Dr. Kinlen</PERSON> found veterans who had smoked more than 21 cigarettes a day were the most likely to die from myeloid leukemia, the most common form of the disease in middle-aged people. 

   These heavy smokers had a <PERCENT>93%</PERCENT> greater chance of developing fatal leukemia than the veterans who never had smoked. 
For those smoking between 10 and 20 cigarettes a day, the increased risk was <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT>. 
And men using fewer than 10 cigarettes daily were <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> more likely to die from leukemia than nonsmokers, according to the report. 

   Previous studies have observed higher death rates from leukemia among smokers, but either involved fewer patients or didn't compare amounts smoked with incidence of the disease. 
For this reason, leukemia "has in general not been regarded as a a malignancy related to smoking," <PERSON>Dr. Kinlen</PERSON> wrote. 

   The latest analysis doesn't prove a causal link, <PERSON>Dr. Kinlen</PERSON> noted in a phone interview. 
But "it is the best evidence to date that the relationship is genuine." 

   If the link is causal, an editorial in the medical journal said, "then smoking is a more important cause of leukemia in adults than all other known causes combined." 
Current known causes include radiation and exposure to the chemical benzene. 

   Leukemia is fairly rare. 
An estimated 18,100 Americans will die from it this year, making the disease the fifth-greatest cause of cancer deaths. 
But leukemia represents the third-leading cause of death in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> children, behind accidents and birth defects, according to the <ORGANIZATION>American Cancer Society</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 0617EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CancerGenes     01-11 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cancer Genes,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Loss of Interferon Genes Linked with Leukemia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A form of blood cancer that strikes children
appears to be sometimes linked with genetic damage that hinders the
body's ability to make interferon, according to a study published
today.
   The researchers speculate that genes that oversee the body's
production of interferon, a disease-fighting substance, may play a
role in warding off the development of cancer.
   The researchers speculate that the interferon genes may act as
regulators that stop the body's cells from becoming cancerous.
   The researchers, based at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, found an
association between loss of the genes and development of acute
lymphoblastic leukemia, the most common form of childhood leukemia.
   They tested 62 patients with this kind of leukemia and found
that <PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT> of them were missing the interferon genes.
   Their work, directed by <PERSON>Dr. Manuel O. Diaz</PERSON>, was published in the
<ORGANIZATION>New England Journal of Medicine</ORGANIZATION>. It adds to the growing list of
cancers that have been associated with the presence or absence of
particular genes.
   Some genes, known oncogenes, are though to trigger cancer.
Cancer can also occur when other genes, known as anti-oncogenes,
are missing.
   Interferon plays a variety of roles in regulating the body's
immune defenses and controlling cell growth.
   The production of two forms of interferon, known as alpha and
beta-1, are controlled by two genes that are close together on
chromosome 9 in the body's library of genes.
   In the latest work, the researchers found that this section of
the chromosome was frequently missing in those with acute
lymphoblastic leukemia. However, they left open the possibility
that some other gene in this region besides those that make
interferon could also be the tumor-suppressing gene.
   Acute lymphoblastic leukemia accounts for about one-quarter of
all childhood cancers. It strikes one in every 30,000 children.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880909-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-88 2113EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Smoking     09-09 0430</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Smoking,0444</SECOND>
<HEAD>Heavy Smokers Show Significantly Higher Leukemia Death Rate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARCUS ELIASON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The death rate from leukemia was nearly <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT>
higher among smokers of more than 10 cigarettes a day than among
non-smokers, according to a study published <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   While no direct link has been established between smoking and
leukemia, research published in the British Medical Journal showed
that the leukemia death rate among people who smoked fewer than 10
cigarettes a day was <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT> higher than among non-smokers.
   For smokers of 10 to 20 cigarettes a day it was <PERCENT>57 percent</PERCENT>, and
for smokers of 21 or more cigarettes <PERCENT>63 percent</PERCENT>, the study showed.
   ``If the findings in our study represented a direct relationship
between smoking and leukemia, then it must follow that smoking is
responsible for more cases of leukemia than all the hitherto
established causes combined,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Leo Kinlen</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Cancer Epidemiology Unit</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Edinburgh</ORGANIZATION>.
   Kinlen conducted the study of 248,000 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military veterans
with <PERSON>E. Rogot</PERSON>, a statistician at the <ORGANIZATION>National Heart</ORGANIZATION>, Lung and <ORGANIZATION>Blood
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>.
   They wrote that it was ``the largest study of leukemia and
smoking habits to date (and) represents additional evidence that
leukemia is a smoking-related disease.''
   In an editorial in the prestigious weekly, Professor <PERSON>Nicholas
Wald</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>St. Bartholemew's Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> cautioned that no
cause-and-effect relationship had been established.
   But he added: ``Whatever the mechanism, the balance of evidence
suggests that smoking may cause leukemia.''
   It should therefore be added to the <ORGANIZATION>World Heath Organization</ORGANIZATION>'s
list of tobacco-related causes of death, he wrote.
   The study was conducted on data collected from 248,000 veterans
between <DATE>1954</DATE> and <DATE>1969</DATE>, the researchers wrote. During that period
723 died of leukemia. Of these 330 were cigarette smokers, 185 were
ex-smokers, 46 smoked cigars or and 162 were non-smokers.
   The study found that in some types of leukemia, the death rate
among smokers was sharply higher than the average.
   Thus for monocytic and myeloid leukemias, the rate among smokers
of more than 20 cigarettes a day was <PERCENT>93 percent</PERCENT> higher, compared
with <PERCENT>48 percent</PERCENT> for lymphatic leukemias.
   For smokers of 10 to 20 cigarettes a day the rate of death from
lymphatic leukemia was <PERCENT>76 percent</PERCENT> higher, and for one to 10
cigarettes, <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> higher.
   When the data was broken down into smokers and ex-smokers, it
suggested that ex-smokers also are significantly more at risk. The
death rate among smokers was <PERCENT>53 percent</PERCENT> higher, and among
ex-smokers <PERCENT>39 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121190-0080 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 320704 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 11, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
710 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SURVEY FINDS STRONG SMOKING-LEUKEMIA LINK; 
</P>
<P>
MEDICINE: ADVENTIST STUDY SAYS EVEN EX-SMOKERS ARE AT HIGH RISK. NUMBER OF 
CIGARETTES AND DURATION OF HABIT ALSO ARE FACTORS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT STEINBROOK, TIMES MEDICAL WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Cigarette smoking appears to be a major risk factor for the development of 
leukemia and may be responsible for more than 1 in 5 cases of the feared blood 
cancer, according to a study by <ORGANIZATION>Loma Linda University</ORGANIZATION> researchers. 
</P>
<P>
The researchers consider the findings particularly significant because almost 
all of the 34,000 Seventh-day Adventists studied who had smoked had stopped 
years earlier, suggesting that some of the adverse effects may not be 
reversible. The report increases the credence of other recent studies that have 
suggested a link between smoking and leukemia. 
</P>
<P>
The results, being published this month in the Journal of the <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer 
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, add to a growing list of cancers that have been linked to cigarette 
smoking. The list includes cancers of the lung, bladder, pancreas, esophagus, 
throat and perhaps the cervix. 
</P>
<P>
The study is part of the ongoing <ORGANIZATION>Adventist Health Study</ORGANIZATION>, a major 
epidemiological investigation of the causes of various cancers among <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
residents. 
</P>
<P>
Although the vast majority of Adventists do not smoke by church proscription, 
many are adult converts to the religion who smoked cigarettes prior to their 
baptism into the church. 
</P>
<P>
The researchers found that the Adventist ex-smokers had twice the risk of 
developing leukemia than similar individuals who never had smoked. 
</P>
<P>
The results are "very discouraging," said <PERSON>Paul K. Mills</PERSON>, an assistant professor 
of preventive medicine at <LOCATION>Loma Linda</LOCATION> and principal author of the study. "We saw 
a strong association between prior cigarette smoking and the risk of developing 
leukemia." 
</P>
<P>
The findings "obviously strengthen the gathering impression that cigarette 
smoking is related to leukemia risk and that the association is likely to be 
causal," <PERSON>Dr. Clark W. Heath Jr.</PERSON>, a vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Cancer 
Society</ORGANIZATION>, wrote in an editorial published in the medical journal along with the 
study. 
</P>
<P>
The risk of developing leukemia was also increased by a greater number of 
cigarettes smoked daily and a longer duration of smoking, which <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> said was 
"important evidence of a causal relationship." 
</P>
<P>
Individuals who regularly smoked more than 25 cigarettes a day had a threefold 
increased risk of developing leukemia. The Adventists who had smoked for more 
than 15 years had a 2 1/2-fold increased leukemia risk. 
</P>
<P>
Leukemia is a bone-marrow cancer in which the marrow is replaced by immature, 
abnormal white blood cells. Leukemia is a relatively uncommon tumor compared to 
breast, colon or lung cancer. Each year, there are about 27,000 newly diagnosed 
cases and 18,000 deaths attributed to leukemia in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
According to <LOCATION>Heath</LOCATION>, until <DATE>1986</DATE> it was generally accepted that tobacco use was 
not a significant cause of leukemia. Since <DATE>1988</DATE>, several studies, including a 
large study of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military veterans and two <ORGANIZATION>American Cancer Society</ORGANIZATION> studies, 
had provided preliminary evidence of a link. 
</P>
<P>
The causes of leukemia are largely unknown. Those that have been identified, 
such as the chemical benzene and ionizing radiation, appear to account for only 
a small percentage of cases, according to <ORGANIZATION>Heath</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Loma Linda</LOCATION> study calculated that about <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of leukemia cases were 
associated with prior smoking. In all, there were 46 new cases of leukemia 
diagnosed during the six-year study period. 
</P>
<P>
On the basis of this and earlier preliminary studies, <ORGANIZATION>Heath</ORGANIZATION> estimated that from 
<PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of leukemia cases may be linked to smoking. 
</P>
<P>
Because cigarette smoking is very common in the general population -- more than 
<PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of adults smoke -- the proportion of total leukemia risk that may be 
attributed to cigarette smoking is significant, according to the researchers. 
</P>
<P>
In a related finding, the <ORGANIZATION>Loma Linda</ORGANIZATION> researchers found that ex-smokers among 
the Adventists had a threefold increased risk of developing myeloma, another 
bone-marrow tumor, as compared to individuals who had never smoked. Mills 
cautioned that this result should be considered "preliminary" because it was 
based on 23 cases. Previously, this association has not been closely examined. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Adventist Health Study</ORGANIZATION> began in <DATE>1974</DATE>. Participants in the current study 
completed a questionnaire about their lifestyle in <DATE>1976</DATE> and were followed for 
the development of new cancers through the end of <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MEDICAL RESEARCH; LEUKEMIA; SMOKING; LOMA LINDA UNIVERSITY; SEVENTH DAY 
ADVENTIST CHURCH; ADVENTIST HEALTH STUDY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011590-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 162474 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 15, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
153 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IN BRIEF: SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
GENE LOSS, LEUKEMIA LINKED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Loss of genes that make interferon, a natural disease-fighting substance, has 
been linked with development of a form of leukemia, researchers said. The 
researchers speculate that the interferon genes may act as regulators that stop 
the body's cells from becoming cancerous. 
</P>
<P>
Researchers from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago</ORGANIZATION> found an association between loss of 
the genes and development of acute lymphoblastic leukemia, a blood cancer that 
is the most common form of childhood leukemia. 
</P>
<P>
They tested 62 patients with this kind of leukemia and found that <PERCENT>29%</PERCENT> of them 
lacked the interferon genes. Their work, directed by <PERSON>Dr. Manuel O. Diaz</PERSON>, was 
published in the <ORGANIZATION>New England Journal of Medicine</ORGANIZATION>. It adds to the growing list 
of cancers that have been associated with the presence or absence of particular 
genes. 
</P>
<P>
Interferon plays a variety of roles in regulating the body's immune defenses 
and controlling cell growth. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
INTERFERON; LEUKEMIA; GENES; CANCER RESEARCH; MEDICAL RESEARCH 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880524-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-88 1542EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Interferon-Cancer Bjt   05-24 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Interferon-Cancer, Bjt,0654</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interferon Found Effective against Multiple Myeloma and Leukemia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The natural protein interferon, combined with
standard chemotherapy drugs, shows promise in controlling multiple
myeloma, a lethal form of bone cancer, researchers said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``We finally have a leg up on arresting the natural progression
of the disease and producing patients who are alive at five years,
which has been a rarity,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Martin M. Oken</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION>.
   His research is part of a new effort by scientists to find a
role for interferon by combining it with the drugs that have long
been used to attack cancer.
   Oken said interferon might provide a knockout punch after cancer
has been weakened, but not destroyed, by medicines.
   The work may also represent a revival of the fortunes of
interferon, which has been on a roller coaster of public acclaim
and disdain for a decade.
   Interferon is a natural, hormone-like substance that, among
other things, helps regulate the body's immune system. When the
human gene that makes this chemical was isolated, some experts
predicted many uses for interferon in eliminating cancer and
infections.
   However, studies showed that when used alone, interferon had
little major impact on any cancer except an exceedingly rare
malignancy called hairy cell leukemia, for which it has become
standard therapy.
<ORGANIZATION>American Association of Clinical Oncology</ORGANIZATION>, doctors found that
interferon plus chemotherapy produced complete remissions in <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of the 54 patients studied.
   Such remissions, in which all signs of the disease are gone, are
rare in multiple myeloma, and they are the first step toward curing
the disease.
   In all, <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT> of the patients had remissions that were
complete or nearly complete. In an earlier study, only <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT>
of the patients reached this level after receiving chemotherapy
alone.
   In another study presented at the meeting, doctors from the
<ORGANIZATION>University of North Carolina</ORGANIZATION> showed promising early results of
testing interferon against chronic myelogenous leukemia.
   ``These are interesting results,'' said <PERSON>Dr. James Griffin</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Dana-Farber Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>. ``Response rates can be
improved and toxicity minimized by these recombinant proteins.''
   About 11,000 new cases of multiple myeloma and 5,000 cases of
chronic myelogenous leukemia are found each year.
   This form of leukemia can be effectively treated with bone
marrow transplants. However, many victims do not receive
transplants because no suitable narrow donors are available.
   <PERSON>Dr. Howard Ozer</PERSON> and his colleagues at the <ORGANIZATION>University of North
Carolina</ORGANIZATION> found they could reduce the outward signs of myelogenous
leukemia and help the body replace defective cells with normal ones.
   ``For the first time, there is a drug available that potentially
keeps the abnormal (cell) clone under control and allows the normal
clone to come back,'' <PERSON>Ozer</PERSON> said.
   His team tested interferon on 112 people with this form of
cancer. They found that <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of them improved, although it is
still too soon to know how the treatment affects long-term survival.
   He said that interferon may have to be given for several years
to keep the disease under control.
   Oken said more study will be needed as well to see how
interferon affects multiple myeloma over time. However, he added,
``I think it's a real advance.''
   Typically, about <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of multiple myeloma patients survive
for five years.
   Just how interferon works against cancer is unclear. Ozer
speculates that it acts as a sort of negative growth regulator,
shutting down bone marrow cells that produce cancerous blood cells.
   Interferon is produced by inserting a human gene into bacteria
or yeast, which can churn out the substance in limitless
quantities. It is just one of several otherwise rare natural
chemicals to be made through genetic engineering.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900104-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-04-90 0613EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CancerTreatment     01-04 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cancer Treatment,0360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Studies Show Cancer Treatment Can Cause Leukemia</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chemotherapy drugs that were used to treat ovarian
cancer may have sharply increased the risk of leukemia, a study has
found.
   Researchers found that among women treated between <DATE>1960</DATE> and
<DATE>1985</DATE>, the risk of leukemia was 12 times higher in those who
received chemotherapy rather than surgery alone, according to the
   Although the study did not measure the benefits of treatment,
chemotherapy drugs given during that time frequently failed to stop
ovarian cancer. But doctors say that newer drugs now in use against
this form of cancer are more effective, and their benefits probably
outweigh their risks.
   The research, directed by <PERSON>Dr. John M. Kaldor</PERSON> of the
based on 114 women with leukemia who were among 99,113 survivors of
ovarian cancer in seven European countries and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Doctors have long known that the powerful medicines used to
attack cancer may also cause the disease. The latest research
demonstrates the magnitude of this risk.
   In a second study, the same researchers found that the risk of
leukemia is also substantially increased in people given
chemotherapy for <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease, another form of cancer. But
since <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease is often curable with drugs, the benefits
of treatment clearly outweigh the risks.
   In this work, the doctors reviewed 163 cases of leukemia among
29,552 Hodgkin's disease patients. They found that the risk of
leukemia was nine times higher among those who got chemotherapy
instead of radiation treatment.
   ``The risk in <LOCATION>Hodgkin</LOCATION>'s disease is well worth it, because the
treatment does extend life. In ovarian cancer, it's not necessarily
worth it,'' commented <PERSON>Dr. Charles A. Coltman Jr.</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University
   Several of the cancer drugs taken by the European women for
ovarian cancer are no longer used.
   ``Management of ovarian cancer is moving ahead very rapidly,''
said <PERSON>Coltman</PERSON>. ``Some of the more recent studies suggest an impact
on survival'' that outweighs the increased risk of leukemia.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881122-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-88 0112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AIDSDrug     11-22 0591</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AIDS Drug,550</SECOND>
<HEAD>FDA Approves Drug To Treat Cancer Common Among AIDS Patients</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Alpha interferon, a natural disease fighter
already used to treat leukemia, can now be used to battle <ORGANIZATION>Kaposi</ORGANIZATION>'s
sarcoma, a cancer that primarily attacks AIDS patients.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Food and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Monday</DATE> that alpha
interferon was shown in tests to be effective against <ORGANIZATION>Kaposi's</ORGANIZATION> and
now is approved for treatment of the cancer that has become common
among AIDS victims.
   Alpha interferon is a disease-fighter that is present in the body
naturally in small amounts, but has been artifically produced in
large quantities in recent years through the use of gene-splicing
techniques. It previously had been approved for treatment of
hairy-cell leukemia and for genital warts.
   <PERSON>Frank E. Young</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> commissioner, said approval of the man-made
alpha interferon ``shows biotechnology's emerging role in helping
modern medicine fight some of the most serious diseases which plague
mankind.''
   Kaposi's sarcoma, named for a European doctor who first described
it more than 100 years ago, was a rare cancer until the appearance
early in this decade of AIDS, or acquired immune deficiency syndrome.
   The cancer causes purple or brown lesions on the skin and can
attack the lungs, brain and gastrointestinal tract. Kaposi's can
cause death when it attacks the lungs or other vital organs,
although most AIDS patients die of other causes.
   Alpha interferon was used experimentally to treat <ORGANIZATION>Kaposi</ORGANIZATION>'s in a
number of studies, including some conducted at the <ORGANIZATION>National
Institutes of Health</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Anthony S. Fauci</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>NIAID</ORGANIZATION> director, said that studies by <PERSON>H.
Clifford Lane</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>NIAID</ORGANIZATION> ``demonstrated that alpha interferon was
an effective anti-Kaposi's sarcoma agent'' in patients who were in
the early stages of the AIDS infection.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>, several human studies showed that high
doses of alpha inteferon would reduce <ORGANIZATION>Kaposi</ORGANIZATION>'s tumors in 40 to <PERCENT>45
percent</PERCENT> of patients who were in early stages of the AIDS infection.
   AIDS patients who were helped most were those whose blood showed
a T4-helper cell count of above 200 per square centimeter, and who
have not experienced other opportunistic infections. T4-helper cells
are part of the body's immune system and are attacked by the AIDS
virus. Healthy people have a T4-helper cell count of 800 to 1,000.
   Those with more advanced AIDS tend to have T4-helper cell counts
below 200 and do not benefit from the alpha interferon treatment.
   Alpha interferon was first identified in <DATE>1957</DATE> as a hormone-like
protein that is a natural disease-fighting component of the blood.
In the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, researchers were able to insert the gene coded
for alpha interferon into a bacteria which then produces the protein
in large quantities. This is the technique called gene-splicing.
   The <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> said that alpha interferon is marketed by <ORGANIZATION>Schering Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
of <LOCATION>Kenilworth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, under the brand name Intron-A, and by
<PERSON>Hoffmann-La Roche</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nutley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> under the brand name Roferon. Both
products were first approved in <DATE>1986</DATE> for the treatment of hairy-cell
leukemia, and <DATE>last June</DATE> for the treatment of genital warts.
   AIDS is a contagious disease that attacks the body's immune
system, rendering it incapable of resisting other diseases and
infections. The virus most often is spread through contact with
blood, blood products or semen from infected persons. AIDS is
incurable and fatal.
   As of <DATE>Nov. 7</DATE>, AIDS had been diagnosed in 77,994 Americans, of
whom more than half, or 43,888, have died since <DATE>June 1, 1981</DATE>,
according to the government.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900523-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-90 0155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Cancer-Vitamin     05-23 0780</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Cancer-Vitamin,770</SECOND>
<HEAD>Form of Vitamin A Turns Cancer Cells into Normal Ones</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a unique assault on leukemia, doctors have
found that a form of vitamin A will turn cancer cells into normal
ones.
   Medicine's usual way of combating cancer is to kill it. Doctors
administer powerful toxic drugs in the hopes that they will destroy
more cancerous cells than healthy ones.
   The new approach instead tries to reform cancer cells. It
changes the cells' genetic program, bypassing the genetic mix up
that makes them kill. In this way, the treatment induces the cancer
cells to live, to grow and eventually to die by the same rules that
govern the rest of the body.
   The drug, a synthetic form of vitamin A called all-trans
retinoic acid, was developed in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and tested in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. Though
it has drawbacks and works in just one rare form of leukemia,
doctors hope it will provide clues for short-circuiting the basic
errors that underlie all cancers.
   ``The dogma has been to try to kill cancer cells,'' said <PERSON>Dr.
Laurent Degos</PERSON>. ``Is it possible to change a cell, and not kill it,
so it becomes normal?''
   Degos, a researcher at <ORGANIZATION>Hopital Saint-Louis</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, presented
evidence that this indeed is possible in a report <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the
   He tested the drug on victims of acute promyelocytic leukemia, a
rare blood cancer that strikes a few hundred people in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> each year. All of them had failed earlier standard therapy.
   He achieved complete, though often temporary, elimination of all
signs of the disease in 16 of 17 patients who had relapsed for the
first time. There was complete remission in one of four patients
who had relapsed a second time.
   ``There was no killing of cells, but they change,'' said Degos.
``We see more mature cells.''
   This form of leukemia is caused by a specific genetic defect,
the mislocation of a piece of one string of genes, or chromosome,
onto another chromosome. As a result, the cells get stuck in their
juvenile stage. They fail to mature normally and eventually die.
   Treatment with all-trans retinoic acid appears to bump the cells
past this roadblock in their development so they grow old.
   ``This is a smashing development,'' commented <PERSON>Dr. Charles
Schiffer</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maryland</ORGANIZATION>. ``It has impressed even the
most cynical. This is a different approach to anything we have done
in this disease in the past.''
   Dr. <PERSON>Bruce Chesen</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION> said the
institute plans soon to sponsor four small safety studies of the
drug. Once those are done, it will begin a larger review of its
effectiveness.
   Though the synthetic vitamin wiped out obvious signs of the
leukemia, the disease frequently came back, apparently because some
cancer cells were resistant to the drug. Degas said it may be
necessary to combine the treatment with standard chemotherapy to
try to obliterate the few remaining cancer cells.
   The drug was developed in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Wang Zeng Yi</PERSON>, dean of
<ORGANIZATION>Shanghai University II</ORGANIZATION>, a French-speaking medical school. It is now
being produced by <PERSON>Hoffman LaRoche</PERSON>, the pharmaceutical firm.
   In an earlier report, doctors said they found that the acne
medicine Accutane, another synthetic form of vitamin A, prevents
new tumors from developing in people treated for smoking-related
throat cancer.
   Among other research presented at the meeting:
   _<PERSON>Dr. Steven A. Rosenberg</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION>
outlined the first results of his pioneering attempt to insert
foreign genes into cancer patients. The initial effort, carried out
on seven melanoma patients, was intended to show that gene therapy
is possible.
   Doctors removed cancer-fighting blood cells from the patients'
tumors, inserted a bacteria gene into them and then put them back
into the patients' bodies. The manipulated cells zeroed in on their
tumors. The doctors hope soon to repeat the experiment, this time
inserting a gene that produces a cancer-killing chemical called
tumer necrosis factor.
   _A survey of American and <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> blacks in central <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>
showed that a surprising <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> were infected with
cancer-causing human T-cell leukemia virus Type 1, or HTLV-I. <PERSON>Dr.
Harvey Dosik</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Interfaith Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> said the
infection rate is 200 times higher than that seen nationwide in
blood donors.
   _<PERSON>Dr. Lode J. Swinnen</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Loyola University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> said he had
found evidence that OKT3, an antibody treatment widely given to
recipients of organ transplants, significantly increases their risk
of non-Hodgkins lymphoma, a blood cancer. He reviewed 154 heart
transplant patients and found that <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> of those getting OKT3
since <DATE>1986</DATE> had developed the disease.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880519-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-19-88 1625EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AIDSTrigger     05-19 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AIDS Trigger,0681</SECOND>
<HEAD>Leukemia Virus May Trigger AIDS In Patients Infected By Both
Viruses</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: For release at 6 p.m. EDT</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   People infected by the AIDS virus may be more
likely to go on to develop the deadly disease if they also are
infected by a related virus that can cause a particularly fatal
form of leukemia, a study says.
   ``These laboratory results suggest that doubly infected
individuals have a worse prognosis for developing AIDS'' than those
who are infected only by the AIDS virus, said molecular virologist
<PERSON>Irvin S.Y. Chen</PERSON>, who published his study in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s issue of the
journal Science.
   ``The chances of any individual being infected by both viruses
are very slim, but among selected populations, such as intravenous
drug abusers, the chances are quite high,'' said <PERSON>Chen</PERSON>, of the
   Except among IV drug abusers, the leukemia virus is quite rare
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. It is fairly common in southern <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chen</PERSON> said. So the study suggests
that people in those areas may be more likely to develop
full-fledged AIDS if they are exposed to the AIDS virus.
   But more study of people infected by both viruses must be done
to confirm the suspicion raised by laboratory studies, said <PERSON>Dr.
Stanley H. Weiss</PERSON>, chief of AIDS epidemiology at <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Medical
School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>. Weiss is already undertaking such research in the
<LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> area.
   Acquired immune deficiency syndrome is caused by the human
immunodeficiency virus, or HIV, which usually remains dormant in
infected people for years before it may be activated to cause
full-fledged AIDS, which cripples the disease-fighting immune
system.
   Previous studies suggested almost any infection may help trigger
the dormant AIDS virus into an active killer.
   Chen and his colleagues performed experiments in laboratory
culture dishes showing that AIDS-infected white blood cells called
T cells produce large amounts of active AIDS virus if the cells
also are exposed to the human T-cell leukemia virus type I, or
HTLV-I.
   People infected by HTLV-I have a <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> lifetime chance of
developing a blood cancer called adult T-cell leukemia, which often
kills quickly. It is an important cause of leukemia in southern
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. HTLV-I also is linked to a potentially
fatal, degenerative nerve disease that causes spasticity and
paralysis of the legs.
   Last month, the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> recommended that all donated
blood be tested for HTLV-I as soon as scientists develop a
practical test. A <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> study found about one out of every
4,286 units of donated blood carries HTLV-I. The risk of AIDS virus
in blood has been reduced to about one in 40,000 units because
donors are tested for signs of AIDS infection.
   A study performed by <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> when he worked for the <ORGANIZATION>National
Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION> showed HTLV-I is spreading among intravenous drug
abusers, with infection rates of <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> among <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
addicts, <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> among <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> addicts overall, and <PERCENT>49
percent</PERCENT> among black addicts in <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>.
   Intravenous drug addicts also are high risk for infection by the
AIDS virus, which also is spread in blood on shared needles and by
sexual contact.
   Infection by HTLV-I apparently activates the AIDS virus by
stimulating AIDS-infected white blood cells to divide, according to
the study Chen performed with molecular virologists <PERSON>Jerome Zack</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Alan Cann</PERSON> and <PERSON>James Lugo</PERSON>.
   While the study in Science deals only with HTLV-I, unpublished
laboratory results suggest full-fledged AIDS also may be triggered
in AIDS-infected people who also are infected by HTLV-II, an
extremely rare virus that can cause another type of leukemia.
   The AIDS virus is distantly related to the leukemia viruses.
   Dr. <PERSON>Edward L. Murphy Jr.</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION> expert on
HTLV-I, agreed with Chen that the problem of dual infection by the
AIDS and leukemia viruses is mainly a problem for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug addicts
and for people in areas such as the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880414-0254 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-14-88 1424EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Cyanamid-LeukemiaDrug     04-14 0176</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cyanamid-Leukemia Drug,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Leukemia Drug Available</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pharmaceutical company said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> it has
begun selling a new leukemia drug, the fourth new cancer agent
since <DATE>1983</DATE> and the third leukemia drug in 10 years to gain federal
approval.
   Novantrone mitoxantrone hydrochloride is to be used in
combination with other agents for treating adults with acute
nonlymphocytic leukemia, <ORGANIZATION>Lederle Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement.
   The disease strikes about 8,000 Americans a year, the statement
said. The drug apparently disrupts the functioning of genetic
material in cancer cells, the company said.
<DATE>1987</DATE>, but the agency's official rating of the drug indicates it
represents little or no advantage over other treatments.
   The other three new cancer drugs approved in the past five years
are etoposide for testicular cancer, approved in <DATE>1983</DATE>; leuprolide
acetate for advanced prostate cancer, <DATE>1985</DATE>; and interferon,
approved in <DATE>1986</DATE> to fight hairy cell leukemia, said <PERSON>Dr. John
Johnson</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Lederle</ORGANIZATION> is a division of <ORGANIZATION>American Cyanamid Co</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900216-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-90 0325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Mouse-Leukemia     02-16 0669</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mouse-Leukemia,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mouse Model for Human Leukemia May Help Fight Killer Disease,
Experts Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Researchers report today they have succeeded
in giving a form of human leukemia to laboratory mice, producing an
animal that now can be used to test therapies against the disease.
   ``With this new animal model, experimental therapies that might
otherwise be tried in human patients can now be tested in these
mice,'' said <PERSON>George Daley</PERSON>, lead researcher in the study conducted
<LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   ``You obviously can do more with the mice than you could with
human patients,'' he said.
   The study, published <DATE>today</DATE> in Science, says the <LOCATION>Whitehead</LOCATION>
researchers used intricate genetic engineering to inject into the
bone marrow of laboratory mice the human gene linked to chronic
myelogenous leukemia (CML), a form of a blood cancer that usually
attacks adults and is only rarely cured.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said the study also proves <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> is initiated by the fusion
of parts from two broken chromosomes, a finding that was suggested
by earlier studies in other laboratories. Those parts have been
identified as the so-called <ORGANIZATION>ABL</ORGANIZATION> gene from chromosome 9 and a gene
called <ORGANIZATION>BCR</ORGANIZATION> from chromosome 22.
   Cells containing this hybrid gene produce a protein, called
P210, that changes healthy cells into cancer cells.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said his study showed that transferring the BCR@ABL gene
into mouse bone marrow and then putting these infected cells into
healthy mice could produce <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> in those mice.
   ``It answers a question of basic science, that is, what causes
the disease,'' said <PERSON>Daley</PERSON>. ``We now know that the BCR@ABL gene is
sufficient to induce the leukemia.''
   He said it is still not known precisely what causes the two
chromosomes to break and create the hybrid gene, but a high
exposure to radiation is thought to be a factor.
   <PERSON>Dr. George Canellos</PERSON>, chief of medical oncology at the
<ORGANIZATION>Dana-Farber Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, said the <LOCATION>Whitehead</LOCATION> finding is ``an
important advance in understanding the disease.''
   He said the new animal model of the disease may help scientists
find ways to block the action of the P210 protein produced by the
BCR@ABL gene, thus preventing the disease.
   ``In screening biological substances, it will make a very nice
model,'' said <PERSON>Canellos</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said the mouse can be used to test ``biological
inhibitors'' that would prevent the P210 protein from transforming
normal cells into cancers. Such inhibitors formally could only be
tested on human patients, a process that could take years. With a
mouse model of the disease, experiments can be sped up and can be
more extensive.
   To create the mouse model, <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said he and his colleagues
inserted the human BCR@ABL gene into a virus. Normal mouse bone
marrow cells were then exposed to the virus, which transferred the
gene into the marrow cells.
   Thirty healthy mice were then irradiated to kill their bone
marrow cells. Next, the bone marrow carrying the BCR@ABL gene was
transplanted into the 30 mice.
   Within five months, 13 of the 30 mice developed a blood disease
that mimicked human chronic myelogenous leukemia.
   CML in humans can be controlled by chemotherapy for 3 to 5
years. This remission period usually ends with the sudden increase
in abnormal cells, a disease phase called ``blast crisis'' that
usually results in death. The only successful therapy used now is
to kill the diseased bone marrow in the patient and replace it with
healthy bone marrow from a compatible donor, but even this
treatment often fails.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said that continued studies of the <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> mice show that many
of the laboratory animals develop the ``blast crisis'' phase of the
disease. This, he said, is further verification that the course of
the disease in the mice mimics <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> in humans.
   <PERSON>Richard A. Van Etten</PERSON> and <PERSON>David Baltimore</PERSON>, both of the <ORGANIZATION>Whitehead
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, were coauthors of the study with <PERSON>Daley</PERSON>. Science, which
published the study, is the journal of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association</ORGANIZATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>Advancement of Science</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891110-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-89 1543EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Cancer     11-10 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Cancer,0595</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study Indicates Radiation Not Linked to Childhood Leukemia</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Increases in leukemia among young people living
near nuclear plants are not caused by exposure to radiation, said a
study released <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Researchers found that death rates from leukemia and <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s
disease among young people were about as high in areas that were
only considered for nuclear plants as in areas that actually
contained nuclear plants.
   Hodgkin's disease is a cancer of the lymph glands. Researchers
said it has never been linked to radiation exposure.
   The cause of heightened cancer rates found in the study remains
a mystery.
   But the researchers said their findings indicate an increased
risk of leukemia is not associated with exposure to radiation, with
the possible exception of the Sellafield nuclear reprocessing plant
on <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>'s northwest coast.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Sellafield</ORGANIZATION> plant has been plagued by radioactive leaks.
Government studies have found a 10-fold increase in childhood
leukemia a mile from the plant, and concluded the plant is linked
to the disease.
   In the study released <DATE>Friday</DATE>, researchers from the <ORGANIZATION>Medical
Research Council</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Cancer Research Fund</ORGANIZATION> said the new
findings suggest that areas near existing and potential nuclear
sites might share ``unrecognized risk factors other than
environmental radiation pollution.''
   Dr. <PERSON>Sarah Darby</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Cancer Research Fund</ORGANIZATION> said the
findings point to something possibly ``in the lifestyle of the
young but at the present time we don't have a great deal of handle
on it.''
   The researchers investigated death statistics in 400 districts
of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> near existing or potential nuclear sites. The
results were published in the The Lancet, a weekly medical journal.
   ``Excess mortality due to leukemia and <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease in
young people who lived near potential sites was similar to that in
young people who lived near existing sites,'' researchers wrote.
   <PERSON>Ms. Darby</PERSON> said: ``There was a <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT> increase in childhood
leukemia mortality in areas near nuclear installations compared
with the rest of the country after adjusting for factors such as
urban-rural status. When the same analysis was carried out for
areas near potential installations, there was a <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>
increase.''
   ``We carried out this study because estimates of radiation
received by children living near nuclear installations are
extremely low, and it has been suggested that increases in the
number of deaths are not caused by the presence of the
installations, but by some other feature of the districts in which
they tend to be built,'' she said.
   The new findings on leukemia bolster this hypothesis, the
researchers wrote. Other previous theories, such as those involving
exposure to radon gas or viruses, could not account for all the
excess cancers in young people, they said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Darby</PERSON> said the study also would disprove stress or
psychosomatic illness being a possible cause since most people
living around the potential sites ``wouldn't have been worried
about it.''
   She said the main theory that needs investigation is ``that
people who are exposed less frequently to infection very early in
life are at a slightly higher risk of leukemia later on.''
   <PERSON>Mel Greaves</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Leukemia Research Fund</ORGANIZATION>, who originated the
theory, ``has biological reasons for thinking that is the case,''
she said.
   ``Our data support that,'' she said, explaining that areas with
a higher proportion of people in the upper social classes had a
slightly higher risk of leukemia than people in areas with a higher
proportion of manual workers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900215-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Leukemia-Mouse     02-15 0665</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Leukemia-Mouse,640</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release at 6 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<HEAD>Mouse Model For Human Leukemia May Help Fight Killer Disease,
Experts Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Researchers, using an intricate manipulation
of genes and transplantation of bone marrow, have produced a mouse
that suffers from a vicious form of human leukemia, giving
scientists a new way to test therapies against the killer disease.
   In a report to be published <DATE>Friday</DATE> in the magazine Science,
they have discovered a way to give chronic myelogenous leukemia,
<ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION>, to laboratory mice. <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> is a form of leukemia that usually
attacks adults and is only rarely cured.
   ``With this new animal model, experimental therapies that might
otherwise be tried in human patients can now be tested in these
mice,'' said <PERSON>George Daley</PERSON>, lead researcher in the study at
<LOCATION>Whitehead</LOCATION>. ``You obviously can do more with the mice than you could
with human patients.''
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said the study also proves that <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> is initiated by the
fusion of parts from two broken chromosomes, a finding that had
been suggested by earlier studies in other laboratories. Those
parts have been identified as the so-called <ORGANIZATION>ABL</ORGANIZATION> gene from
chromosome 9 and a gene called <ORGANIZATION>BCR</ORGANIZATION> from chromosome 22.
   Cells containing this hybrid gene produce a protein, called
P210, that changes healthy cells into cancer cells.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said his study showed that transferring the BCR@ABL gene
into mouse bone marrow and then putting these infected cells into
healthy mice could produce <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> in those mice.
   ``It answers a question of basic science, that is, what causes
the disease,'' said <PERSON>Daley</PERSON>. ``We now know that the BCR@ABL gene is
sufficient to induce the leukemia.''
   He said it is still not known precisely what causes the two
chromosomes to break and create the hybrid gene, but a high
exposure to radiation is thought to be a factor.
   <PERSON>Dr. George Canellos</PERSON>, chief of medical oncology at the
<ORGANIZATION>Dana-Farber Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, described the <LOCATION>Whitehead</LOCATION> finding as
``an important advance in understanding the disease.''
   He said the new animal model of the disease possibly may help
scientists find ways to block the action of the P210 protein
produced by the BCR@ABL gene, thus preventing the disease.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said that the mouse can be used to test ``biological
inhibitors'' that would prevent the P210 protein from transforming
normal cells into cancers. Such inhibitors formally could only be
tested on human patients, a process that could take years. With a
mouse model of the disease, experiments can be speeded up and can
be more extensive.
   To create the mouse model, <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said he and his collegues
inserted the human BCR@ABL gene into a virus. Normal mouse bone
marrow cells were then exposed to the virus, which transferred the
gene into the marrow cells.
   Thirty healthy mice were then irradiated to kill their bone
marrow cells. The bone marrow carrying the BCR@ABL gene was then
transplanted into the 30 mice.
   Within five months, 13 of the 30 mice developed a blood disease
that mimicked human chronic myelogenous leukemia.
   CML in humans can be controlled by chemotherpy for 3 to 5 years.
This remission period usually ends with the sudden increase in
abnormal cells, a disease phase called ``blast crisis'' that
usually results in death. The only successful therapy now is to
kill the diseased bone marrow in the patient and replace it with
healthy bone marrow from a compatible donor, but even this
treatment often fails.
   <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> said that continued studies of the <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> mice shows that
many of the laboratory animals develop the ``blast crisis'' phase
of the disease. This, he said, is further verification that the
course of the disease in the mice is similar to <ORGANIZATION>CML</ORGANIZATION> in humans.
   Co-authors of the study with <PERSON>Daley</PERSON> were <PERSON>Richard A. Van Etten</PERSON> and
<PERSON>David Baltimore</PERSON>, both of the <ORGANIZATION>Whitehead Institute</ORGANIZATION>. Science, which
published the study, is the journal of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association</ORGANIZATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>Advancement of Science</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880128-0006 </DOCNO>
<HL> More Data Emerges That Cancer Virus Is Tainting U.S. Blood-Bank Supply </HL>
<AUTHOR> Jerry E. Bishop (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> PHA </IN>
<TEXT>
   More evidence emerged that a cancer virus is contaminating the nation's supply of banked blood. 

   Researchers in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> reported evidence that some hospital patients who had received multiple blood transfusions had been infected with the virus. 
This follows other, tentative reports in recent months hinting that <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> of blood donors in some localities and as many as <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> of drug addicts tested in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> may be infected with the virus. 

   Such reports prompted the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>November</DATE> to urge rapid development and federal approval of a definitive test that could be used to screen blood donors for evidence of infection by the cancer virus. 

   The cancer virus is related to the AIDS virus and is believed to be spread by the same routes, that is, by blood transfusions, sexual contact and the sharing of contaminated needles among drug addicts. 
The virus is known to cause a rare but rapidly fatal type of leukemia that, until now, has been confined largely to southern <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and certain areas in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. 
It also has been linked to a multiple sclerosis -- like nerve ailment, called tropical spastic paraparesis, occurring in children in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. 

   The virus is known as HTLV-1, for human T-cell leukemia virus. 

   The presence of the virus in the blood supply poses an unusual public health dilemma. 
Although only <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of people infected with the virus develop leukemia, the blood cancer doesn't occur until many years, perhaps decades, after the initial infection. 
An increase in the incidence of leukemia that would confirm that the virus is spreading among Americans mightn't occur for another decade. 
By that time, millions might have become infected, leading to an epidemic of tens of thousands of cases lasting well into the next century. 

   The newest evidence of the virus's presence in the blood supply was reported in the New England Journal of Medicine by a research team at <ORGANIZATION>Memorial Sloan-Kettering Cancer Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
They tested blood samples from 211 patients who had been treated at the center for various types of leukemia. 
None of the patients suffered the T-cell type of leukemia caused by the virus, but all had received multiple transfusions of blood during their therapy. 
Six of the patients had antibodies to HTLV-1, indicating they had been exposed to the virus. 
All of these patients died of their blood cancers long before there was any chance of developing disease from the HTLV-1. 

   The researchers said they couldn't determine when the six patients had been infected. 
The tests were run on blood samples that had been taken and stored for other reasons. 
But in three of the patients, samples were available that were taken before the transfusions. 
These were negative for the virus antibodies, while samples from the same patients taken after transfusions were positive. 
There wasn't any way of determining who donated the contaminated blood. 

   Last fall, the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> said it had completed preliminary screening of blood from 40,000 healthy donors and found 10 who might be positive for HTLV-1 exposure. 
More elaborate and time-consuming tests now are being done to check the accuracy of this preliminary screening. 
This prevalence, though tiny, is about the same as the prevalence of the acquired immune deficiency syndrome virus in donated blood before screening programs began. 

   Studies in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> have confirmed that HTLV-1 can be transmitted by blood transfusions, but so far there aren't any known cases of T-cell leukemia developing in people so infected. 
The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> scientists noted, however, that patients such as theirs, who receive multiple transfusions, can serve as a "sensitive indicator" of the virus's presence in the blood supply. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900802-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-90 0244EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HepatitisCure Bjt   08-02 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hepatitis Cure, Bjt,0585</SECOND>
<HEAD>Interferon Provides First Cure for Hepatitis B</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists today reported finding the first
treatment capable of relieving and even curing chronic hepatitis B,
one of the world's biggest killers.
   A study in the <ORGANIZATION>New England Journal of Medicine</ORGANIZATION> indicates that
shots of a synthetic form of the natural protein interferon can
prevent the virus from destroying the liver in nearly half the
people chronically infected.
   One in 10 victims can be cured, while the drug had no benefits
for <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the 169 people studied in clinical trials,
researchers said.
   Hepatitis B is the chief underlying cause of liver cancer and
cirrhosis and the world's ninth-leading cause of death, just behind
lung disease and well ahead of AIDS, according to the <ORGANIZATION>World Health
Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   An estimated 1 million to 1.5 million people in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> are long-term carriers of the hepatitis B virus. At least
half of them have liver disease. Worldwide, 300 million people, or
<PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of the world's population, are chronically infected.
   Until now, there has been no treatment or cure for the virus.
   ``This is an encouraging result. All of us would feel a lot
happier if we had a better treatment. This spurs us on to find
that,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Baruch S. Blumberg</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Fox Chase Cancer Center</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Blumberg</PERSON> won the <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Prize</ORGANIZATION> in medicine in <DATE>1976</DATE> for identifying
the virus.
   The latest research, which involved 169 people at 12 hospitals,
confirms several smaller studies suggesting that interferon works.
   Other studies have also shown that interferon works against
hepatitis C, another serious but less common variety of the virus.
   Although the <ORGANIZATION>Food and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION> has not yet
recommended interferon for hepatitis B, physicians can use it any
way they choose, and <PERSON>Blumberg</PERSON> said some doctors have already begun
prescribing it for this disease.
   Doctors said the latest study is big enough so physicians can
use the results to predict how interferon will affect their
patients if _ as seems likely _ it becomes the standard medicine
for hepatitis B.
   ``We can be relatively sure what doctors will find in practice:
<PERCENT>Ten percent</PERCENT> will be cured and 40 or <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> will be made better
and their liver disease will be stopped in its tracks,'' said <PERSON>Dr.
Robert P. Perrillo</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>St. Louis Veterans Affairs Medical
Center</ORGANIZATION>, the principal author of the study.
   He defined a cure as the complete disappearance of the virus.
   Experts cautioned the treatment should be used only for those
with chronic infections who show signs of liver damage.
   The results were published along with an editorial by <PERSON>Dr. Jay H.
Kidney Diseases</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``For now, interferon alpha offers the best hope'' for treating
chronic hepatitis B, <PERSON>Hoofnagle</PERSON> wrote.
   Hepatitis is likely to become the first major use for
interferon. Isolating the natural disease-fighting substance was
one of the early goals of genetic engineering.
   In a decade of testing, interferon has turned out to be useful
against a variety of diseases, none as common as hepatitis. The <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>
has approved use of the drug for hairy-cell leukemia, AIDS-related
<ORGANIZATION>Kaposi</ORGANIZATION>'s sarcoma and genital warts.
   In hepatitis B, <PERSON>Perrillo</PERSON> said the treatment appears to offer the
best chance of a cure if given during the first two years of
infection.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870120-0009 </DOCNO>
<HL> Concerns Grow That Cancer Virus
Is Spreading in Same Ways as AIDS
---
By Jerry E. Bishop and Michael Waldholz
<DD> 01/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CELP DD GOVMT
PHARMACEUTICALS, HOSPITAL SUPPLIES, MANAGEMENT (PHA) </IN>
<TEXT>
   Researchers are quietly conducting a large-scale sampling of the nation's blood supply to see if a rare virus capable of causing cancer and, possibly, a mysterious nerve disease is being spread among Americans. 

   The virus, until now, has been confined to small areas of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION>. 
It is, however, similar to the virus that causes acquired immune deficiency syndrome, or AIDS. Now, scientists are increasingly concerned that the virus, which can cause a form of adult leukemia, is being transmitted like AIDS: through an exchange of blood by hypodermic syringes, sexual practices or transfusions. 

   Although it is far too early to tell how many people have been infected and how many will actually develop cancer or the nerve disease, evidence already suggests that many drug addicts in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> have been exposed to the virus. 
And there is at least one cluster of cases of the rare leukemia in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Bedford-Stuyvesant</LOCATION> neighborhood, although doctors don't know how the victims acquired the virus. 

   In an unannounced move, the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> late last week began testing for evidence of the virus in blood donated by 30,000 people in six unidentified cities around the country. 
The effort follows the federal government's approval of an experimental test kit to detect antibodies to the virus. 
The sampling, while technically a trial of the accuracy of the new blood test, should also indicate whether the cancer virus is enough of a threat for blood banks to begin routine screening of donated blood as is now done for AIDS and hepatitis. 

   "We have evidence now that a virus spread by blood and associated with a very serious disease has been detected in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>S. Gerald Sandler</PERSON>, medical director of the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>. 
"Since this is happening, it is the responsibility of the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> to be at the head of a scientific investigation to quantify the incidence of the virus's presence and spread." 

   Adds <PERSON>Bernard Poiesz</PERSON>, head of the division of hematology-oncology at the <ORGANIZATION>State University of New York</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION>: "Incidence of the virus in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> has been sporadic, but it is increasing now. 
We are now beginning to realize that the virus is causing a real health problem in this country." 

   The virus poses an unusual threat because of its long latency period. 
People infected with the virus may not develop leukemia for several years. 
Thus, if the virus is spreading now, it may be a decade before enough leukemia cases develop to trigger the nation's epidemic alarm system. 
No one knows what percentage of infected individuals will develop leukemia or the nerve disease. 

   Although the cancer threat alone has worried health officials for several months, those concerns have increased following reports that link the virus with a nerve condition known as tropical spastic paraparesis or TSP, explains <PERSON>William A. Blattner</PERSON> of the environmental epidemiology branch of the <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The nerve disease is similar to multiple sclerosis and afflicts muscle function. 
It was first identified in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> in <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>. 
Last fall, however, French researchers in <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION> linked the nerve disease to the virus after finding that many TSP victims had been infected with the leukemia virus. 
Subsequently, Japanese researchers found that many TSP victims in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> had previously had blood transfusions. 

   Although the incidence of <ORGANIZATION>TSP</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> isn't known, the links between the leukemia virus, the nerve disease and blood transfusions have apparently spurred the preliminary screening of blood supplies by the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The virus is known as human T-cell leukemia virus one, or HTLV-I. 
The T cell is a particular type of white blood cell that is infected and turned malignant by the virus. 
Less than a decade ago, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Japanese scientists proved that HTLV-I was responsible for a type of leukemia seen in southern <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
The virus thus became the first virus proved to cause a human cancer. 
So far, it is the only proven human cancer virus, although many patients infected with the AIDS virus develop a previously rare type of skin cancer. 

   The rare leukemia, once it develops, is devastating. 
"The median survival is three months," says <PERSON>Harvey Dosik</PERSON>, director of medicine at the <ORGANIZATION>Interfaith Medical Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Dr. Dosik</PERSON> and his colleagues have seen 15 cases of the leukemia in the past two years. 
"Only one of the 15 is still alive," he says. 

   The 15 cases constitute the largest cluster of the leukemia in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
The victims were all blacks who moved into the <LOCATION>Bedford-Stuyvesant</LOCATION> ghetto in <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> from the <LOCATION>Carribbean</LOCATION> and the southern <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, areas where the presence of the virus has been known for some time. 
None of the 15 victims was known to be an intravenous drug user, <PERSON>Dr. Dosik</PERSON> says. 
Mainly because of the lack of funds, researchers have been unable to explore the victims' backgrounds to discover what they might have in common that would account for the disease, <PERSON>Dr. Dosik</PERSON> says. 

   Evidence of the virus's spread among Americans comes largely from tests of drug addicts. 
In <DATE>1984</DATE>, British health officials, while screening for AIDS, first noted that about <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> of addicts there had developed antibodies to HTLV-I, evidence that they had been exposed to the virus. 

   Earlier this year, a team from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Institutes of Health</ORGANIZATION> checked blood samples taken five years ago from 56 drug addicts in the <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> section of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
The results indicated that as early as <DATE>1981</DATE> as many as <PERCENT>9%</PERCENT> of the intravenous drug addicts had been exposed to HTLV-I. 
If the spread of the AIDS virus since then is any kind of index for the growth of HTLV-I, the virus is presumably even more widespread now. 

   Some researchers are also worried that blood screening such as that being done by the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> may not give a broad enough picture of the prevalence of HTLV-I. 
Blood banks have been carefully excluding donors who are at risk of developing AIDS -- but those are the people who are also most likely to have been exposed to HTLV-I. 
Thus, sampling only donated blood might result in underestimating the true extent of the virus. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> screening program was made possible by the development of test kits by <ORGANIZATION>Cellular Products Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, biotechnology company, and by <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del</LOCATION>. 
Both companies already produce tests to detect the AIDS virus, and the new tests use the same technology. 

   Cellular Products began working on a test at the "insistence of Dr. Poiesz" in <LOCATION>Syracuse</LOCATION>, "who told us he was seeing enough instances in his lab to warrant nationwide screening soon," says <PERSON>Richard Montagna</PERSON>, Cellular's president. 
<PERSON>Dr. Poiesz</PERSON>'s lab has been testing blood samples from around the world, but the lab's test isn't simple enough for use by blood banks. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont</ORGANIZATION> spokesman says the company is gearing up to produce six million test kits a year, based on <ORGANIZATION>Du Pont</ORGANIZATION>'s own studies of the spread of the virus. 
Based on these studies, he adds, the company believes there will be a need within a few years for about 50 million to 75 million test kits, about the same number currently used to screen for the AIDS virus. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880803-0161 </DOCNO>
<HL> Letters to the Editor: 'But, Doc, I'm Going to Die!' </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> PHA </IN>
<TEXT>
   In your second-front-page article "Approved Drugs Find Unapproved Uses" (<DATE>July 12</DATE>), your approach to the problem of <ORGANIZATION>Food and Drug Administration</ORGANIZATION> approval of medicines fails to take into account the complexities of modern medicine. 
For example, picture yourself sitting in front of me in my office. 

   "<PERSON>Mr. 
X</PERSON>," I might begin, "you unfortunately have a rare cancer of the adrenal gland. 
Treatment of this is very difficult, and up to this point, all patients with this have died. 
However, at one of our recent cancer meetings, there were two reports that a combination of the chemotherapy drugs etoposide and cisplatin were able to shrink this cancer in 10 of 11 patients. 
These are not experimental drugs, but drugs well known to us for the treatment of other cancers. 
Unfortunately, these drugs are not approved for this cancer, since adrenocortical cancer strikes only a few hundred patients a year." 

   "Well, <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>," you answer, "I'll go ahead and take the drugs anyway; those odds sound pretty good." 

   "Yes, they do, <PERSON>Mr. X. Unfortunately</PERSON>, your insurer does not pay for any medicines given for 'unapproved' indications. 
Since you have a rare disease, you certainly cannot expect these drug companies to spend <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> to get approval for such a rare problem, can you? 
If you owned stock in them, you'd throw the management out. 
I'd like to give you the drugs, but since you live in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, your insurer makes me take assignment for your treatment, and not only will they not pay me, by law you can't pay me out of your pocket either. 
These are expensive drugs, and we can't give them away." 

   "But <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>, you're an expert in cancer medicine; certainly if you tell the insurer that this is the best thing for me, it will be OK." 

   "I wish it were that simple, <PERSON>Mr. X</PERSON>," I go on, "but your policy clearly states that only drugs approved by the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> for that disease can be reimbursed; how else can they hold down runaway costs? 
But don't feel bad; you're not alone. 
Why, when etoposide first came out every oncologist already knew that it was the best single drug for small cell lung cancer. 
There are a lot of those patients (why couldn't you get a common disease?) and it only took the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION> a few years to approve the application for that use. 
Of course, the average patient with that disease lived only 11 months then, but what are 10,000 or 20,000 lives compared with the safety of a whole country, not to mention the asset base of the insurance companies?" 

   "Well, I certainly understand the problem, <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>. 
Let's just write to the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>, tell them the facts you told me, and they'll approve it." 

   "You may understand your problem, <PERSON>Mr. X</PERSON>, but you don't understand the <ORGANIZATION>FDA</ORGANIZATION>. First of all, they require a fairly large amount of data to approve a drug, but there aren't enough cases of your disease in a year to give a large enough data base. 
Second, only the company that manufactures the drug can apply for approval. 
As we discussed, that usually requires several years and costs <MONEY>tens of millions of dollars</MONEY>. 
Once a drug is on the market for a common disease, why on earth should they spend the money for a rare disease? 
They'd never make back their investment." 

   "But, <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>, I'm going to die of this," you plead. 
"This just isn't fair. 
Anyway, my insurance broker always told me it would pay for everything." 

   "I sympathize, but think of the whole country. 
Why, this policy has saved thousands from damaging their scalps trying to grow hair with minoxidil. 
Anyway, <TIME>this morning</TIME> already, I've had to tell one women with chronic myelocytic leukemia that I would like to treat her with alpha-interferon, but unfortunately she didn't have hairy cell leukemia. 
Another woman with breast cancer needed mitoxantrone, and I tried to figure out how I could convince her insurer that she had acute leukemia." 

   "Doc, at least my insurance premiums have been held down. 
But how could we have come to something like this, in this day and age? 
I figured that by <DATE>1990</DATE> we'd have thought about it." 

   "Well, at least you won't have to worry about the side effects." 

   <PERSON>Joseph J. Muscato</PERSON> M.D. 
