<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06198012 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06198012 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Lindy Chamberlain; ... Inspired trial movie  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MONEY; AWARD; FAMILY; INFANT; DEATH; AUSTRALIA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The couple whose trial and wrongful convictions in the death of their infant
daughter inspired the movie "A Cry in the Dark" was awarded $320,000 in
damages today by the government of Northern Territory.;    Lindy and Michael
Chamberlain said their daughter was carried away by a wild dog, or dingo.
Their convictions were overturned after a lengthy legal battle, and most of
the damage award will go to legal fees.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COUPLE IN DINGO CASE WINS $320,000  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The baby, <LOCATION>Azaria</LOCATION>, vanished from the couple's campsite near <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION> in
central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> in <DATE>August 1980</DATE>. Her body was never found.;    In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Lindy
Chamberlain</PERSON> was convicted of murder. Her husband was found guilty of being an
accessory after the fact.;    Many people said they believed <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>
was guilty simply because she showed little emotion during the trial.;    She
was sentenced to life in prison but was released in <DATE>1986</DATE> after the infant's
jacket, missing since the disappearance, was found near <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1988</DATE>,
the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> government threw out the convictions.;    Northern
Territory Attorney General <PERSON>Daryl Manzie</PERSON> said <MONEY>$306,000</MONEY> of the award would go to
the <ORGANIZATION>Seventh Day Adventist Church</ORGANIZATION>. The church, where <PERSON>Michael Chamberlain</PERSON> once
served as a minister, covered the couple's legal expenses.;    The remaining
<MONEY>$14,725</MONEY> was being paid to the Chamberlains for the loss of their car and
personal effects.;    The Chamberlains are also seeking an additional <MONEY>$3.1
million</MONEY> in damages. The claim has not yet been heard by the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION>
government.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Darwin, Australia  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910716  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  26C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  248  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 16, 1991
00198012,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06199106 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06199106 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Chamberlain  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  AUSTRALIA; FAMILY; PRISON; SENTENCE; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The government Tuesday awarded $320,000 in damages to a couple whose trial and
wrongful convictions in the death of their infant daughter inspired the movie
"A Cry in the Dark.";    Lindy and Michael Chamberlain said their daughter was
carried away by a wild dog, or dingo. Their convictions were overturned after
a lengthy legal battle, and almost all of the damage award will go to legal
fees.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  'CRY IN THE DARK' COUPLE WIN DAMAGES
WOMAN HAD BEEN SENT TO PRISON AFTER SAYING
DINGO KILLED BABY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The baby, <LOCATION>Azaria</LOCATION>, vanished from the couple's campsite near <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION> in
central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> in <DATE>August 1980</DATE>. Her body was never found.;    In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Lindy
Chamberlain</PERSON> was convicted of murder and was sentenced to life in prison. Her
husband was found guilty of being an accessory after the fact.;    Many people
said they believed <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON> was guilty simply because she showed
little emotion during the trial.;    <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON> was freed in <DATE>1986</DATE> after
the infant's jacket, missing since the disappearance, was found near <ORGANIZATION>Ayers
Rock</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1988</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> government threw out the convictions.;  
 Northern Territory Attorney General <PERSON>Daryl Manzie</PERSON> said <MONEY>$306,000</MONEY> of the award
would go to the Seventh-day Adventist Church. The church, which <PERSON>Michael
Chamberlain</PERSON> once served as a minister, covered the couple's legal expenses.;  
 The remaining money was being paid to the Chamberlains for the loss of their
car and personal effects.;    In a separate claim, the Chamberlains are
seeking <MONEY>$3.1 million</MONEY> in damages. That claim has not yet been heard by the
<ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory</ORGANIZATION> government.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Darwin, Australia  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910717  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  242  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday July 17, 1991
00199106,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880916-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-16-88 0323EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-DingoBaby     09-16 0778</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dingo Baby,0804</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Clears Lindy Chamberlain After Sensational Murder Case</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD BILL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A woman who said a wild dog snatched
and ate her newborn child has been found innocent of murder.
   The court decision closes the book on an 8-year-old case that
divided <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and captured headlines worldwide.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Northern Territory Court of Criminal Appeal</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Darwin</LOCATION> on
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> overturned <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>'s sentence of life
imprisonment with hard labor. She spent about four years in jail.
   It also quashed the conviction of her husband, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, a pastor
for the <ORGANIZATION>Seventh Day Adventist Church</ORGANIZATION>, on charges of being an
accessory to murder.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON>, who was born in <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, became a
household name in <DATE>1980</DATE> when she said a dingo, or native Australian
dog, carried off her 6-week-old daughter <PERSON>Azaria</PERSON> while the family
camped in the <LOCATION>Outback</LOCATION> near <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION>, a sacred aboriginal site.
   Replete with rumors of black magic and a suicide that led to a
break in the case, the <PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON> story made Page 1 in newspapers
across <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and elsewhere. All Australians seem to have an
opinion on the woman's story.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, she was pardoned but her conviction was not overturned.
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s innocent verdict finally sealed the case shut.
   Gasps filled the courtroom when the decision was announced.
<PERSON>Michael Chamberlain</PERSON> clasped his hands to his head and wept. His
wife, who had been staring at the judges, slumped in her seat.
   ``The law of the land holds the Chamberlains to be innocent,''
said the ruling.
   The Chamberlains' defense attorney had accused the <ORGANIZATION>Northern
Territory</ORGANIZATION> government, which originally prosecuted the pair, of
waging a ``modern-day witchunt.''
   The lawyer, <PERSON>Stuart Tipple</PERSON>, said the Chamberlains were waiting to
see whether the government would pay the couple compensation before
deciding on any civil action. Earlier, he said the couple was
seeking about <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY>.
   After the verdict, <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON>, a tiny woman in high-heeled
red shoes, was thronged by curious onlookers as she strode with
straightened shoulders from the courthouse.
   The crowd clamored for a closer look as the couple made their
way through the large crowd to their car. Construction workers
nearby downed tools and whistled while others jeered.
   The <PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON> drama began on a cold night in <DATE>August 1980</DATE> when
<PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> cried out at the family camp side at <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION>,
central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, ``A dingo's got my baby!''
   At first, the <ORGANIZATION>Chamberlains</ORGANIZATION>' story was believed. But when the
couple went to court, <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> was accused of slitting her
baby's throat.
   The baby's body was never found, but bloodstains were found in
the couple's tent.
   On <DATE>Oct. 29, 1982</DATE>, the Chamberlains were found guilty and <PERSON>Mrs.
Chamberlain</PERSON> was sentenced to life in prison, where she to gave
birth to a second daughter, <PERSON>Kahlia</PERSON>. Her husband was sentenced to a
suspended 18-month sentence.
   The couple has two other sons, <PERSON>Aiden</PERSON> and <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>. Although the
prosecution never alleged black magic as a motive, many Australians
have linked the death of baby <LOCATION>Azaria</LOCATION> to witchcraft and satanic
rites, believing the children have mystical names.
   The family denied rumors that the name <PERSON>Azaria</PERSON> meant ``sacrifice
in the wilderness.'' Many Australians also thought it significant
that the death occurred at <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION>, sacred to aborigines in one
of the most remote parts of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>February 1986</DATE>, a remarkable breakthrough in the case came
when a British tourist jumped off the huge monolith to his death.
   Aboriginal trackers investigating the suicide found the tattered
remains of <ORGANIZATION>Azaria</ORGANIZATION>'s jacket, which <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> swore the baby
was wearing the night she vanished.
   The discovery of the jacket proved that <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> had not
been lying about at least one aspect of her baby's death and
prompted officials to reopen the case.
   Five days after the jacket was found, <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> was
released from prison. On <DATE>June 2, 1987</DATE>, a federal judge pardoned her
and said <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> may have told the truth when she said the
dingo snatched and ate the baby.
   ``Indeed, the evidence affords the view that a dingo may have
taken her,'' federal <PERSON>Judge Trevor Morling</PERSON> wrote in his opinion.
   But under Australian law, the pardon was as far as <PERSON>Trevor</PERSON> could
go and the Chamberlains returned to court to overturn the
conviction.
   ``There is no satisfaction, no joy, knowing they still believe
you are guilty,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Chamberlain</PERSON> said at the time.
   Although the court case is over, the <PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON> story will
continue.
   American movie star Meryl Streep recently finished filming a
movie on the case based on a book titled ``Evil Angels.'' The
American release is provisionally called ``A Cry In The Darkness.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-5416</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIDAYAEFFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940903
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 SEP 94 / Travel: Air-conditioned Outback - Kate Bevan travels to
Ayers Rock by coach and watches sunrise with flash-bulbs
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By KATE BEVAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The spectacular beauty of <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION> today holds no reminders of the tragedy
of <PERSON>Azaria Chamberlain</PERSON>, the nine-week-old daughter of <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael
Chamberlain</PERSON> who was taken by a dingo at the <ORGANIZATION>Rock</ORGANIZATION>. Azaria's death and the
ensuing legal actions convulsed <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, culminating in <PERSON>Lindy
Chamberlain</PERSON>'s belated release from jail.
Today the Rock is haunted more by the spectre of mass tourism than by the
ghost of <LOCATION>Azaria</LOCATION>. The campsite and jumble of motels and buildings at the
eastern base of the Rock where the Chamberlains stayed have been largely
done away with; what is left was turned over to the local Aboriginal
community.
The site might as well not exist: tourist buses rumble along the sealed road
and arrive via the western side of the Rock to disgorge their mainly foreign
passengers. Most Australians, facing outrageously high domestic airfares,
find it too expensive to visit the area.
Visitors now stay at <LOCATION>Yulara</LOCATION>, the depressingly soulless resort 18km away from
the Rock which was built to contain the growing number of tourists visiting
this inhospitable but breathtakingly beautiful region of central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
And there, perhaps, lies the rub: the region is becoming easier to visit as
<LOCATION>Yulara</LOCATION> neutralises the brutal climate. No longer do tourists have to brave
campsites and dirt roads to see <ORGANIZATION>Ayers Rock</ORGANIZATION> - now known by its Aboriginal
name, <LOCATION>Uluru</LOCATION> - rising starkly from pancake-flat desert. Visitors flocking to
the Rock arrive by air-conditioned coach or by jet to Connellan airport,
minutes away from <LOCATION>Yulara</LOCATION>.
Visitors are catered to with cool efficiency, from those able to pay the
prices for the five-star Sails in the Desert hotel, complete with Rock
views, to the back-packers staying at the campsite. And organised tours
ferry the tourists out to experience sunrise and sunset en masse.
The problem is that you have to stay at <LOCATION>Yulara</LOCATION> to get the most out of a
visit. It is the only place to stay for 500km in each direction. And with
the cost of taking a hire car to the area so high, it is almost inevitable
that just about every visitor will end up going out to the Rock in a coach.
This is good news for the coach companies based at <LOCATION>Yulara</LOCATION>, but bad news for
the tourist hoping to capture some of the magic of the desert.
It is magical. The intense colours of the red earth, green trees and endless
blue skies take the breath away before fading to delicate purples and then
inky black as the day ends. The immense emptiness overwhelms, even in the
company of a full coachload.
But to share the sunrise with five other coachloads is depressing. The
astonishing sight of the dark rock flaming orange and then red as the sun
appears over the horizon is dulled by flash-guns.
There is an uncomfortable sense of being herded through the experience as
coaches draw up to the parking lot, leaving their engines running to
maintain the air-conditioning. Even in low season - the heat of <DATE>December</DATE> -
the sheer volume of coachloads of predominantly Japanese tourists deadens
the effect. I dread to think what it is like in the cooler Australian winter
months.
I wanted to be about 10kms further back, too, as the parking area is at the
base of the <ORGANIZATION>Rock</ORGANIZATION>, making it impossible to appreciate the isolation and
beauty of the monolith.
I took my best photographs from 20kms away, on the road out to the Olgas, or
<PERSON>Kata Tjuta</PERSON>, as the Aboriginals call this formation of red, softly-rounded
domes that rear up out of the desert 32km west of <LOCATION>Uluru</LOCATION>. Even on a coach it
is possible to capture a sense of the emptiness and intense heat of the
Outback as many visitors, on a two-day package, miss out the Olgas
altogether. That is their loss, but a bonus for those who go.
The Olgas are so completely unexpected that they cannot fail to impress.
Ayers Rock, by contrast, is exactly what you do expect - large and red.
There is a sense of mystery about the Olgas with their winding trails,
undulating humps and startling colours. My group watched the sun go down in
silence, awed by the flamboyant light show played out on the domes.
The 6km walk through the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Winds</ORGANIZATION> is far more rewarding than the
haul up <LOCATION>Uluru</LOCATION>, and you sidestep the heavy-breathing queue determined to
conquer the Rock. Starting from the car park, the <ORGANIZATION>Valley of the Winds</ORGANIZATION> trail
winds through a spectacular gorge punctuated by unexpectedly green trees and
vegetation before culminating in a scramble up to the lookout, from where
the rest of the range stretches out to meet the desert.
The evening light is mellow and gold, and takes the startling desert colours
to their most intense before fading delicately. Then all the stars come out.
The skies over central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> are some of the darkest in the world and
make the northern hemisphere's pallid night sky, bleached by city lights,
sad by comparison.
In the desert you can see shooting stars flaring in the heavens while
satellites appear as falling points of light and the Milky Way winds
overhead like a giant ribbon.
Most people want to climb <PERSON>Ayers Rock</PERSON>, but it is sobering to see the plaques
at the bottom commemorating some of the climbers who have lost their lives.
The practice of placing plaques on the Rock was stopped some time ago, but
the death toll continues to rise.
The only surprise is that the toll is not higher, given the motley crew of
fat and ill-prepared tourists that starts the climb. A sign at the bottom
points out that it is not for the unfit, and that the local aboriginal tribe
would rather you did not climb the Rock, but it is blithely disregarded by
the hordes determined to sign the visitors' book at the top.
In the ultimate sanitisation of the Rock, the Japanese parties are issued
with white gloves to protect their hands from the chain with which you haul
yourself up the steepest part of the climb. It is a real climb, not a steep
walk. There are parts where you dare not stand up straight, while the gentle
breeze that took the edge off the
the bottom swiftly becomes a gale, threatening your balance as well as hats
and lens-caps.
No doubt the view from the top is tremendous - I decided that I was not
there to kill myself and came back down - but you can see it from a light
aircraft. There are several operators who will fly you around both the Rock
and the Olgas at sunset for a few dollars more.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>AUZ  Australia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881117-0017 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: Film: Unsettling Picture Puts Society on Trial </HL>
<AUTHOR> Julie Salamon </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   For her latest movie, "A Cry in the Dark," <PERSON>Meryl Streep</PERSON>'s head has been helmeted into a dark <PERSON>Buster Brown</PERSON> hairdo. 
This blunt cut gives her the wary look of a punt returner facing the unfriendly heavyweights waiting to tackle. 

   At first it's off-putting; you think, there she goes again, acting with her hair. 
But as this unsettling picture progresses, you realize that the look is deliberately off-putting. 
You are supposed to see <PERSON>Ms. Streep</PERSON>'s character, <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>, as the world saw her -- cold and remote, peering out from that protective headgear. 
And even more effectively than usual, <PERSON>Ms. Streep</PERSON> disappears into that cool character speaking with an impeccably rough-hewn Down Under accent. 

   The real <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON> became a tabloid queen in <DATE>1980</DATE>, when she took a vacation in the Australian outback with her husband, a minister, and their three children. 
One evening as the family prepared its campsite, their youngest child, a nine-week-old girl, disappeared. 
Though no one saw who took her, the family believed it was a dingo, the bushy-tailed Australian cousin of the American coyote. 
The story was played as a tragedy for a while. 
But the Chamberlains, who didn't have media advisers, watched their lives spin out of control. 
They became the objects of rumors and suspicions that <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON> had murdered their daughter and that her husband, <PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, had covered up for her. 

   The case became an Australian "cause celebre." 
Public opinion moved against the Chamberlains because they were Seventh-Day Adventists and because they seemed to enjoy the publicity they were getting -- and later because <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON>, with her stoniness and snarls, wasn't publicity-conscious enough. 
Despite the scant evidence and absence of motive, she was convicted of murder, at which point the journalistic community began to feel some sympathy for her. 
In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <PERSON>John Bryson</PERSON> wrote about the case in "Evil Angels," the book that became the foundation for the movie. 

   "Cry in the Dark" has a distracted quality, as though director <PERSON>Fred Schepisi</PERSON>, who was born and raised in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, wants to keep his characters at a distance, the way they might seem on the <TIME>evening</TIME> news. 
He doesn't bow to the conventions of dramatic build, and for the most part gives little sense of time passing or what his characters are thinking or feeling. 
Yet the picture's power draws from this deliberate distancing; the movie isn't about <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON> so much as it is about the way the facts become obscured by imagery and by rumor, which feed a collective mythology. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Schepisi</PERSON>'s strategy -- he co-authored the script with <PERSON>Robert Caswell</PERSON> -- is to quickly dispense with the question of <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON>'s innocence. 
The opening sequence makes the film maker's position clear. 
Lindy may have made a mistake by failing to zip her baby into the tent, but she didn't -- as was later suggested -- cut the baby's head off and then, coolly, join her family for a campfire cookout. 
The film matter-of-factly lays out the horrible nighttime hunt for the child and the cruel, mundane details of the day after; for example, the district nurse supplies <PERSON>Lindy</PERSON>, who was still nursing the baby, with a breast pump and a diuretic to dry up her milk. 

   Thus, as the rest of the film unfolds, the audience is made to feel the way <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>'s closest friends must have felt as they watched their man keep repeating his mistakes on camera as though he'd never taken a look at himself on videotape. 
The audience is put in the position of believing in <LOCATION>Lindy</LOCATION>, and watching her do everything exactly wrong, from a <LOCATION>P.R.</LOCATION> perspective. 
Her sound bites on the <TIME>evening</TIME> news show a woman wearing a mask. 
"You could crack walnuts on her face," someone mutters. (She does look a little witchy when a detractor spits at her in a phone booth and she starts laughing. 
It's probably a neurotic reaction but it looks bad. 
She even looks out-of-place in her own family: Her husband and kids are towheads while her mop is dark.) 
The film observes that people don't like to watch a mother speak about her murdered child dispassionately, though such behavior might be called stoicism in a man. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Schepisi</PERSON>'s body of work keeps returning to his fascination with myth and with the chaos that inevitably follows when civilization intrudes on nature. 
In "The Chant of <PERSON>Jimmie Blacksmith</PERSON>," he told the story of an aborigine half-caste who vents his frustration by murdering whites; "Iceman" was about a primitive exploited by scientists. 
The director has brought a supernatural sensibility to the Western genre ("Barbarosa") and to romantic comedy ("Roxanne"). 

   Here, he and his longtime collaborator, cinematographer <PERSON>Ian Baker</PERSON>, have visually split the film. 
The sequences shot in the outback are resonant and sweeping, full of portent. 
The film makers return again and again to <ORGANIZATION>Ayer's Rock</ORGANIZATION>, the sacred aboriginal site that has become <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s biggest tourist attraction. 
It was at this strange place -- the mountainous "rock" looks like a huge clump of red dirt that somebody tossed in the desert among the scrub brush -- that the <PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON>'s baby, <LOCATION>Azaria</LOCATION>, disappeared. 
The camera zooms in on <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s Rock with such speed it seems as though the rock is exerting a centripetal force. 
It's as though the film makers are saying: "Maybe we shouldn't tramp all over nature's preserve. 
Bad things will happen." 

   When the action turns to the humans, the colors wash out and the action slows down. 
The civilized world seems faded and remote -- as though the whole thing were being watched on TV monitors with bad reception. 

   Throughout the picture, <PERSON>Mr. Schepisi</PERSON> has set up a rotating chorus of kibitzers. 
He lays out the distortions and wild rumors by planting clumps of people in bars, at restaurants, at dockside, all of them talking about the <PERSON>Chamberlain</PERSON> case. 
The methodology is a little clunky; it's actually quite rare to see rooms of reporters sit goggle-eyed in front of TV sets and trade judgment calls, the way they do over and over again in this movie. 

   Still, it's a way to efficiently convey information to the audience. 
So we learn that people thought that <PERSON>Azaria</PERSON>, the child's name, meant "sacrifice in the wilderness" and believed that Seventh-Day Adventists were some weird cult that periodically killed babies. 
The gossip also reveals a strange nationalistic support of dingoes, as though the very act of accusing the indigenous wild dog of murder proved the Chamberlains were outcasts (women showed up at <LOCATION>Lindy</LOCATION>'s trial wearing T-shirts with the slogan, "The Dingo Is Innocent"). 

   The picture has the sensibility of a strong piece of journalism. 
You never quite get inside the characters; it's not they who are fascinating but the situation they're in. 
Yet there are glimpses into the Chamberlains at home that are powerfully telling. 
Lindy becomes pregnant again after <PERSON>Azaria</PERSON>'s death; she gets bigger and bigger as her trial approaches, and more tetchy. 
Her husband -- played sensitively by the Irish-born New Zealander <PERSON>Sam Neill</PERSON> -- finds himself overwhelmed by what's happened to them. 
He's a minister forced to question his faith in the most fundamental way. 
He's full of emotion; he picks at his head until it bleeds during the trial. 
Lindy, meanwhile, seems to be receding into her own flesh, occasionally emerging with a flash of anger. 

   This is a tough character to get hold of -- but <PERSON>Ms. Streep</PERSON> manages to do it. 
Though the accents, and certainly the coifs, ought to be old hat by now, this is a startling performance: You never see where it starts and where it ends. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901102-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-02-90 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-DingoBaby     11-02 0209</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dingo Baby,0235</SECOND>
<HEAD>Couple in Australia's Dingo Baby Case to Divorce</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SYDNEY, Australia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>, the
couple who claimed their infant daughter was spirited off by a
dingo in the Australian outback, are planning to divorce, a
newspaper said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The marriage fell victim to the strains of fighting for more
than nine years to clear their names, the <ORGANIZATION>Sydney Morning Herald</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   The couple claimed in <DATE>August 1980</DATE> that their daughter <PERSON>Azaria</PERSON> was
carried away by a dingo, an Australian wild dog, from the tent
where they were camping in central <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> near Ayer's Rock.
   The child's body was never recovered. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>
was charged and later convicted of her daughter's murder. She spent
3{ years in prison but was released after new evidence was
discovered - a piece of clothing that indicated a dingo might
indeed have taken the child.
   The infant's disappearance, one of the most hotly disputed
criminal cases in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s history, was the subject of a
Hollywood movie ``A Cry in the Dark,'' starring Meryl Streep as
<PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON>.
   The newspaper said the couple is still living together at their
home north of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> and that it has not been decided who will have
custody of their three remaining children.
   <PERSON>Lindy Chamberlain</PERSON> is in <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> on a nine-day trip to
promote her book, ``Through My Eyes.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880204-0125 </DOCNO>
<HL> Gillette Awards European Account To N.W. Ayer Inc. </HL>
<AUTHOR> Laurie Cohen (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GS FCB </CO>
<IN> MKT </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said its European network of ad agencies won an assignment for <ORGANIZATION>Gillette Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
The annual budget for the assignment is estimated at <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY>. 

   The assignment was held by the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> office of <ORGANIZATION>Chicago-based Foote, Cone &amp; Belding Communications Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Ayer has worked for <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> since <DATE>1986</DATE> and in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> since <DATE>1979</DATE>. 
The new assignment includes advertising for <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> personal division brands, including Aapri facial scrub, Silkience shampoo and conditioner and a variety of new products. 
Ayer already creates the domestic ads for many of those same products. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Foote Cone</ORGANIZATION> competed with Ayer for the account. 
That account was put under review last year, when Boston-based <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> reorganized its businesses. 
Since last month, <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> has been operating its European operations under the same umbrella as its <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Canadian businesses. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said that giving the account to <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> made sense. 
"<PERSON>Foote Cone</PERSON> has no (<ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION>) business here" in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> he said. 
"Ayer has the bulk of that business here, so for consistency, it made sense to give them" the European account. 

   For <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> assignment is the largest the agency has in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
An Ayer spokeswoman said it is also the agency's "biggest international account gain since" winning the advertising account for <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1978</DATE>. 
Ayer no longer works for the airline holding company, having lost the account in <DATE>1981</DATE> to <LOCATION>New York-based Wells</LOCATION>, Rich, <ORGANIZATION>Greene Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870128-0012 </DOCNO>
<HL> Army Breaks Tie
With Ayer, Awards
Ad Pact to Young
---
Agency Vows Legal Action
On Decision to Terminate
19-Year-Old Relationship
---
By Joanne Lipman
<DD> 01/28/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SACHY IPG OGIL
MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION>, breaking off a 19-year-old relationship with its advertising agency, <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, awarded a <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> advertising contract to <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Ayer said it will take "appropriate legal action" against the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> "to recover from the damage unjustly inflicted on this company and its reputation." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> had decided in <DATE>October</DATE> that it wouldn't extend Ayer's contract, and opened its advertising to competitve bidding. 
In <DATE>November</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> was suspended from bidding on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government contracts because of alleged improprieties by a former employee. 
It took a number of legal steps to try to overturn the government suspension so that it could compete for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> advertising contract; those steps, however, were unsuccessful. 

   In an interview <TIME>last night</TIME>, <PERSON>Louis T. Hagopian</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, said, "We're going to sue for all of the money we spent in the resolicitation that we were encouraged to take part in as if we had an equal chance." 
He said the company currently is calculating how much it spent in the preparation of the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> bid, but that the figure could be as much as the low <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>. 

   In a bitter memo to employees, <PERSON>Mr. Hagopian</PERSON> added: "We are convinced that we won the resolicitation competition. 
Someday, we will know for sure, when the Freedom of Information Act allows us to get into that." 
He elaborated in the interview that he believes the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> had decided to choose Ayer, but changed its mind after <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> was suspended from government bidding. 

   An <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said: "<PERSON>N.W. 
Ayer</PERSON> was considered up until the time they were suspended. 
We aren't getting into if they would have won." 

   Closely held Ayer created the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s highly successful "Be All You Can Be" campaign, and the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> was among its largest and most prestigious accounts. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> chose closely held <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam</ORGANIZATION> over five competitors, not including Ayer. 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam</ORGANIZATION>'s contract would call for <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> of print and broadcast advertising in <DATE>1987</DATE>, with annual renewable options for <DATE>1988</DATE> through <DATE>1991</DATE>, giving the lucrative contract a value of as much as <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY>. 
The contract includes advertising for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> reserve, and the <ORGANIZATION>Army Reserve Officers Training Corp</ORGANIZATION>, or ROTC. 

   <PERSON>Alex Kroll</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman and chief executive officer, called the award "a singularly important achievement," and noted that "the competition for this account was intense and challenging." 
<ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam</ORGANIZATION> long has hoped to win the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> account. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> said the other ad agencies in the running included the New York-based agencies <PERSON>Batten</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Barton</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Durstine &amp; Osborn Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>DFS Dorland Worldwide Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Saatchi &amp; Saatchi PLC</ORGANIZATION> unit; and SSC&amp;B:<ORGANIZATION>Lintas Worldwide</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Interpublic Group of Cos</ORGANIZATION>. 
Other bidders were <ORGANIZATION>Ogilvy &amp; Mather</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>New York-based Ogilvy Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Woodbridge</PERSON>, Va.-based <ORGANIZATION>Wilmar Group Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   New York-based <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s suspension from bidding was based on <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> charges that Ayer falsified time cards from <DATE>1979</DATE> to <DATE>1983</DATE> and submitted noncompetitive bids through a scheme with subcontractors. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> also said that a former <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> vice president pleaded guilty to accepting kickbacks. 

   In his memo yesterday, <PERSON>Mr. Hagopian</PERSON> said: "We have been treated shabbily through a <DATE>three-and-one-half year</DATE> investigation that has produced no formal charge or indictment against us as a company." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871109-0099 </DOCNO>
<HL> Investigation of N.W. Ayer
By U.S. Attorney Is Closed</HL>
<DD> 11/09/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Federal officials ended their investigation into <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s handling of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> recruiting campaign, the ad agency said. 

   <PERSON>Louis T. Hagopian</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, said he had been notifed by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Rudolph W. Giuliani</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> that the case had been closed. 

   The investigation, which began in <DATE>July 1983</DATE>, resulted in a former Ayer employee's guilty plea in <DATE>1986</DATE> to a charge of accepting kickbacks from a supplier of recruiting films. 

   Last <DATE>November</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> broke off a 19-year-old relationship with <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, "largely because of this investigation and the innuendoes it generated," <PERSON>Mr. Hagopian</PERSON> said. 

   "The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney's decision leaves us with a profound sense of relief that our confidence in the honor and integrity of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> is vindicated at last," he added. 
"We're not angry any more." 

   Ayer had been responsible for the "Be all you can be" ad campaign for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>. 
The <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> account was awarded to <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861223-0121 </DOCNO>
<HL> NW Ayer to Buy
Most of C&amp;W Unit
Of Mickelberry
---
By Joanne Lipman
<DD> 12/23/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MBC
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The advertising agency <ORGANIZATION>NW Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> agreed to buy most of <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an agency that accounts for about <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of the revenue of <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>'s parent holding company, <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Ayer said it agreed, as expected, to purchase <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>, which is the parent of <ORGANIZATION>Cunningham &amp; Walsh Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and two other ad agencies, except for the group's <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> office. 

   <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>'s clients include <ORGANIZATION>American Home Products Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble Co</ORGANIZATION>. Ayer's clients include <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Avon Products Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gillette Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   A price wasn't disclosed, but industry sources said it was between <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>. 

   The merged agency's combined billings would have placed it as the nation's 15th-largest agency in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 

   Ad agencies in the past have typically received as commissions <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of an advertiser's billings, the total cost of placing ads. 
The purchased units had <DATE>1985</DATE> billings of <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY>. 
Ayer had <DATE>1985</DATE> billings of <MONEY>$826.4 million</MONEY>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION>, a holding company for advertising and marketing concerns, decided to sell <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> because "we got a very good offer," said <PERSON>John Morton</PERSON>, assistant treasurer. 
He added that <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> will probably reinvest the proceeds of the sale in other marketing acquisitions. 
"We will undoubtedly continue to specialize in market service specialty companies, and that may or may not include advertising agencies," he said. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> in the past hasn't been a strong performer: While revenue increased every year from <DATE>1983</DATE> to <DATE>1985</DATE>, net income dropped steadily, and the company had a <MONEY>$1.8 million</MONEY> loss last year. 
<PERSON>Mr. Morton</PERSON> said that <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> has been a "prime" cause of that lackluster performance. 
He added that <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION>'s remaining units "are healthy, profitable, and growing." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> units <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> agreed to sell account for about <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of its revenue, according to <PERSON>Mr. Morton</PERSON>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> is keeping the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> office "to maintain a presence in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>" and because of a client conflict with Ayer. 

   Ayer has relatively few accounts in the consumer packaged goods area, while <ORGANIZATION>P&amp;G</ORGANIZATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> client, is one of the most prestigious clients in that field. 
Moreover, <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>'s strong <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> operations will allow <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> to double its size there while becoming more involved in the region's high-technology businesses, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   The acquisition, which is expected to close in the next few weeks, comes at a good time for <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>. 
It currently faces the possibility of losing the lucrative <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> account, for which it created the "Be All You Can Be" campaign. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> has put its account up for bid on the heels of charges of impropriety by an <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> executive dealing with the account. 
The service will choose an agency in <DATE>January</DATE>. 

   Ayer said its "eventual goal" is to combine the two advertising companies under the Ayer name. 
<PERSON>Louis T. Hagopian</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, added that "if there are going to be consolidations of jobs, they are down the way, and we expect that economies of scale will come through attrition rather than layoffs." 
The combined agencies have 3,030 employees. 

   Three senior officers of <ORGANIZATION>Cunningham &amp; Walsh</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, are expected to become directors of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, which is closely held. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880718-0059 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Noted... </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> WNEWS </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   ADVERTISING: New York-based ad agency <ORGANIZATION>N W Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> agreed to buy <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of British ad agency <PERSON>Ayer Barker</PERSON> for about <MONEY>$4.7 million</MONEY>. 
The price is subject to adjustments in <DATE>1990</DATE> based on after-tax profit. 
Ayer also said it plans to purchase an additional <PERCENT>31%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer Barker</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1990</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Ayer Barker</PERSON> is a unit of British communications firm <ORGANIZATION>Charles Barker PLC</ORGANIZATION>, a public company in which <ORGANIZATION>N W Ayer</ORGANIZATION> has a <PERCENT>12.7%</PERCENT> stake. 
The purchase doesn't affect Ayer's shareholding in the parent company. 

   WHO'S NEWS: <ORGANIZATION>Burson-Marsteller</ORGANIZATION> named <PERSON>Terrence Hill</PERSON> executive vice president and director of corporate advertising. 
He was with a division of <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group PLC</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>J. Walter Thompson</PERSON> advertising unit. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861216-0011 </DOCNO>
<HL> NW Ayer Is Expected
To Agree to Acquire
Unit of Mickelberry</HL>
<DD> 12/16/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MBC
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NW Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an advertising agency, will likely agree to buy another agency, <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, within the week, according to sources close to the negotiations. 

   The sources said that, barring unforeseen difficulties, an announcement will be made by the end of this week or early next week. 
Although it isn't clear how much closely held Ayer would pay, industry sources value <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> in the <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> range. 

   <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>, parent of <ORGANIZATION>Cunningham &amp; Walsh Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, creates advertising for clients such as <ORGANIZATION>American Home Products Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble Co</ORGANIZATION>. Ayer clients include <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Avon Products Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gillette Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> is the largest unit of <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, an advertising agency holding company. 
<ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> historically hasn't been a star advertising performer; while its revenue increased every year from <DATE>1983</DATE> to <DATE>1985</DATE>, net income dropped steadily, and the company posted a <MONEY>$1.8 million</MONEY> loss last year. 
"You can't turn (a company) around on short notice," said <PERSON>Alan Gottesman</PERSON>, an analyst with <PERSON>L.F. Rothschild</PERSON>, <PERSON>Unterberg</PERSON>, <PERSON>Towbin</PERSON>. 
"But they've had the time. 
If they were going to do something, they would have done it by now." 

   <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> officials declined to comment on the reports of the impending purchase. 

   Analysts and industry executives speculated that if <ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION> sells <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> it might use the proceeds to diversify into other businesses or liquidate itself. 
Without <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION>, it would only have a few relatively small advertising and marketing units. 
<ORGANIZATION>Mickelberry</ORGANIZATION>, which was founded in <DATE>1893</DATE>, was a food-processing company before branching into communications more than a decade ago. 

   For <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, a purchase of <ORGANIZATION>C&amp;W</ORGANIZATION> couldn't come at a better time. 
Ayer is currently facing the possibility of losing the lucrative <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> account, for which it created the "Be all you can be" campaign. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> has put its account up for bid on the heels of charges of impropriety by an <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> executive dealing with the account. 
It will choose an ad agency next month. 
If Ayer doesn't win the account, it would lose revenue while its overhead costs would remain the same, said <PERSON>Mr. Gottesman</PERSON>. 
It might need an acquisition "to fill that void." 

   C&amp;W billed <MONEY>$399.9 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE> and was the 24th-largest ad agency. 
Ayer, with billings of <MONEY>$826.4 million</MONEY>, was ranked as the 18th-largest agency by Advertising Age, a trade publication. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870929-0093 </DOCNO>
<HL> Burger King Shifts $200 Million Account
To N.W. Ayer From J. Walter Thompson
---
By Joanne Lipman
<DD> 09/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> PSY
MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT)
FOOD &amp; BEVERAGE, HOUSEHOLD GOODS, SUPERMARKETS, TOBACCO (FAB) </IN>
<DATELINE> NEW YORK  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Burger King Corp.</ORGANIZATION> ended a five-month advertising agency review by awarding its <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> domestic account to <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, snubbing incumbent <ORGANIZATION>J. Walter Thompson Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The account move is believed to be the largest such switch in history. 
It deals a powerful blow to <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s ad agency for 11 years. 
Miami-based <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> had been <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s second-largest account, after <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>, and contributed <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> a year in revenue, industry executives said. 

   "We're very disappointed. 
It's a big emotional loss and a large revenue loss," said <PERSON>Stephen G. Bowen Jr.</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> operations for <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>, a unit of London-based <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group PLC</ORGANIZATION>. 
"But we've known, even though we refused to quit," <PERSON>Mr. Bowen</PERSON> said, adding that "we've done our <DATE>1988</DATE> planning with the assumption that we wouldn't retain it." 
He said there will be layoffs, but declined to speculate on how many. 
More than 100 people worked on the Burger King account, with varying degrees of involvement. 

   Officials of <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> and closely held <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> didn't unveil a new ad campaign, and <PERSON>Charles S. Olcott</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Burger King U.S.A.</ORGANIZATION>, said Ayer commercials wouldn't appear until early <DATE>1988</DATE>. 
But the new campaign likely will take a different tack from the current "The Best Food for Fast Times" campaign, which has been criticized in the industry as inconsistent and unfocused. 

   <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>, a unit of Minneapolis-based <ORGANIZATION>Pillsbury Co.</ORGANIZATION>, could use a boost from advertising. 
Average unit sales were slightly above <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for the 12 months ended <DATE>May 31</DATE>, about flat with the previous year, <PERSON>Mr. Olcott</PERSON> said. 

   "What you're going to see is a consistent brand identity and less switching around," <PERSON>Mr. Olcott</PERSON> said in an interview after a press conference at a Burger King here. 
He said the new ads would emphasize the personal contact customers get at <ORGANIZATION>Burger King restaurants</ORGANIZATION>, as well as three selling points: "flame-broiling, 'Have it your way,' and quality food." 
He also said that <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> and Ayer would step up local and regional marketing efforts. 

   The account switch is a setback for <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group</ORGANIZATION>, which purchased <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> and its parent, <ORGANIZATION>JWT Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, during the <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
<ORGANIZATION>JWT</ORGANIZATION> had been saddled with management turmoil and high turnover during the past year. 
After buying <ORGANIZATION>JWT</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group</ORGANIZATION> was lauded for bringing back several highly respected former <ORGANIZATION>JWT</ORGANIZATION> officers, including <PERSON>Burton J. Manning</PERSON>, now <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>'s chairman and chief executive officer. 
Burger King is the first major client loss since <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group</ORGANIZATION> took over. 

   Although the account loss will hurt the ad agency, analysts said they aren't lowering earnings estimates for <ORGANIZATION>WPP Group</ORGANIZATION>. 
"There's probably going to be some minor setback to the earnings turnaround (at <LOCATION>Thompson</LOCATION>), but I don't know if it will be demonstrable," said <PERSON>Greg Ostroff</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Alan Gottesman</PERSON>, an analyst with <PERSON>L.F. Rothschild</PERSON>, <PERSON>Unterberg</PERSON>, <PERSON>Towbin</PERSON>, added that the Burger King account apparently wasn't highly profitable for <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>, in part because it was on a fee basis that generated less revenue than the traditional <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> commission would have produced. 
Ayer will also operate on a fee rather than on a commission basis. 

   For <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, which was the nation's 15th-largest ad agency in <DATE>1986</DATE> according to Advertising Age, the account helps make up for a recent setback. 
In <DATE>January</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> lost the <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION> account after <DATE>19 years</DATE> of creating its advertising, including the slogan "Be All You Can Be." 

   Ayer was one of three finalists in the competition, along with <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a closely held agency here. 
At <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, some 50 to 70 employees have worked since early <DATE>summer</DATE> preparing the pitch, culminating last week in a polished presentation to Burger King that included finished commercials. 
"Last week," said <PERSON>Jerry J. Siano</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ayer</PERSON>'s vice chairman, "was a constant all-nighter." 

   Ayer's competitors estimated that the agency spent in excess of <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> to prepare its pitch. 
<PERSON>Mr. Siano</PERSON> declined to comment on the amount. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900126-0257 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-26-90 1750EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-ContinentalAds     01-26 0589</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Continental Ads,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Continental Airlines Fires Ayer As Ad Agency</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> it had
dismissed <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer</ORGANIZATION> as its advertising agency, ending an
association that began in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   The Houston-based carrier, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, notified
the agency late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that it was placing its advertising
assignment up for review, the agency said.
   ``Ayer is no longer <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s agency as of today,''
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Art Kent confirmed by telephone from <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>.
``We just felt it was time for a change.''
   He said he could not elaborate and did not know what steps were
being taken to get another agency.
   Ayer had been using the theme ``Working to be your choice'' in
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s advertising. Recent ads touting service to
warm-weather destinations used the line, ``We've got your place in
the sun.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> planned to spend an estimated <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$40
million</MONEY> on its advertising this year, executives familiar with the
account said. Kent said he did not know the actual figure.
   Ayer, a privately-held agency based in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, handles <MONEY>$1.3
billion</MONEY> in advertising billings worldwide and counts among its
and <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   The decision came as a surprise to <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> executives, said Vice
Chairman <PERSON>Thomas F. Maxey</PERSON>. ``We had no indication this was coming,''
he said.
   Ayer opened an office in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> after it was awarded the
account in <DATE>1986</DATE>, and the office currently employs about 30 people.
Ten to 15 more employees work on the <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> account in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Maxey</PERSON> said it was likely that the <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> office would be closed
after an orderly transition. Ayer expects to continue servicing the
account for up to 90 days. In addition to the <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> account,
the <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION> office handles only a few small public service
assignments at no charge.
   <PERSON>John Walsh</PERSON>, an executive vice president who oversees the
<ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION> account, said he understood that <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s business
was improving although the industry has been troubled by declining
traffic and rising fuel costs.
   ``They said they felt they needed a change. In our estimation of
the situation, the situation was good and our work was good,'' he
said.
   Kent confirmed <ORGANIZATION>Continental</ORGANIZATION>'s business was improving. He said the
airline earned <MONEY>$59.1 million</MONEY> for the <DATE>first nine months of 1989</DATE>, in
contrast to a loss of <MONEY>$215.9 million</MONEY> a year earlier.
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Air</ORGANIZATION> also owns <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, which has been operating
since <DATE>March</DATE> under protection of federal bankruptcy laws and has
been losing millions of dollars.
   Airline accounts are particularly labor-intensive, industry
executives say, because of frequent price changes within the
industry and the need to develop different print ads for each
market.
   But <PERSON>Maxey</PERSON> said Ayer would be interested in going after another
airline account anyway. He said the agency handles advertising
assignments for <ORGANIZATION>Iberia Airlines</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air France</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Scandanavian
Airline System</ORGANIZATION>.
   He said the agency is one of the finalists for four different
advertising assignments, which he declined to identify.
   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, Ayer was fired by <ORGANIZATION>Burger King Corp.</ORGANIZATION> after working as
its ad agency for 18 months and producing the campaign, ``We do it
like you'd do it.'' The fast-food chain was spending <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> a
year on its advertising then.
   Among Ayer's recent notable ads have been its commercials for
<ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> long-distance service that featured people near the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>
Wall and a commercial for <ORGANIZATION>Phillip's Milk of Magnesia</ORGANIZATION> that used a
roll of toilet paper to illustrate the powers of the laxative.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890421-0270 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-89 1739EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-BurgerKingAds     04-21 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burger King Ads,0662</SECOND>
<HEAD>Burger King to Drop Ayer as National Ad Agency</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SKIP WOLLENBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Burger King Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> it is looking for
a new agency to handle its national advertising after just 18
months with <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the firm that created the slogan, ``We
Do It Like You'd Do It.''
   The Miami-based fast-food restaurant operator said it had
already selected three agencies to compete for the assignment and
expected to decide by <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The decision was not entirely unexpected because the nation's
second largest fast-food chain has undergone extensive managerial
changes since its parent, <ORGANIZATION>Pillsbury Co.</ORGANIZATION>, was acquired earlier this
year by <ORGANIZATION>Grand Metropolitan PLC</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>.
   Burger King's sales have been sluggish and it has been unable to
increase its share of the fast-food market, now estimated at about
<PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>.
   One of the three finalists is the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> office of <PERSON>J. Walter
Thompson</PERSON>, whose <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office was <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s agency for 11
years until it was dumped in favor of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>September 1987</DATE>.
   The other two finalists, <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON> said, are <ORGANIZATION>D'Arcy Masius
Benton &amp; Bowles</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Advertising</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>.
   D'Arcy formerly worked for the <ORGANIZATION>Hardee's Food Systems</ORGANIZATION> fast-food
chain and its <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> office currently is the agency for
<ORGANIZATION>Denny</ORGANIZATION>'s restaurants.
   Saatchi created the ``Where's the Beef'' advertising campaign
for <ORGANIZATION>Wendy's International Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in the mid-1980s.
   <PERSON>Barry Gibbons</PERSON>, <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s chief executive, said he was
looking for a national agency ``with global capabilities, solid
industry experience, bold creative and media expertise and sound
strategic thinking _ and then have the determination to stick with
that agency.''
   He said the company had informally reviewed potential agencies
since <DATE>January</DATE>. The three finalists are expected to present
proposals to <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> in three to four weeks after which a
decision will be announced.
   <PERSON>Gary Langstaff</PERSON>, <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s new marketing chief, said the
search for a new national agency ``does not apply to our regional
agency structure,'' which apparently means <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> will continue
producing local advertising.
   <PERSON>Joyce Meyers</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman, said <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s
marketing budget for <DATE>1989</DATE> is about <MONEY>$215 million</MONEY> including spending
on national and local advertising and promotions. She said no
decision has been made on how much of that figure will be spent on
national advertising alone this year.
   Officials at the <ORGANIZATION>New York-based Ayer</ORGANIZATION> said they handled about
<MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> in billings for Burger King last year, split fairly
evenly between national and local advertising.
   ``We are disappointed, surprised, but not unprepared,'' <PERSON>Louis T.
Hagopian</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ayer</PERSON>'s chairman and chief executive, said in a memo
distributed to employees.
   He noted that in the time Ayer held the account, <ORGANIZATION>Pillsbury</ORGANIZATION> had
four different chief executives while <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> had four chief
executives and four heads of marketing.
   ``It is just a shame the agency has to take the rap for the
errors and inconsistencies of so many others who have come and gone
and come and gone,'' he wrote.
   <PERSON>Hagopian</PERSON> said that while there may be some layoffs, the agency
would do so ``as considerately as is humanly possible.'' About 100
Ayer people work on the account.
   He said the account represents about <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of the agency's
<MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> in billings and that the agency's finances were strong.
   ``This is a blow, but it isn't even touching the foundations,''
he said.
   Ayer launched the ``We Do It Like You'd Do It'' campaign in
<DATE>February 1988</DATE>. The company has relied less heavily on the theme in
recent months, however, focusing on individual product promotion
instead.
   Burger <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Myers</PERSON> said the decision to select a new national
agency was not as much a reflection on <ORGANIZATION>Ayers</ORGANIZATION>'s work as a desire by
the company's new management ``to start with clean sheet and signal
this is a new Burger King.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890518-0272 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-89 1520EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-BurgerKing Bjt   05-18 0731</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Burger King, Bjt,0756</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fast-Food Giant Selects Two Ad Agencies</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Burger King's new management moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to turn
around years of erratic advertising results by selecting two new
agencies to handle the major portion of its <MONEY>$215 million</MONEY>
advertising and marketing account.
   ``This is a non-traditional approach, but for us it is far more
important to be right, rather than conventional,'' said <PERSON>Barry J.
Gibbons</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Burger King Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s chief executive.
   D'Arcy <ORGANIZATION>Masius Benton &amp; Bowles of New York</ORGANIZATION> will concentrate on
reinforcing brand identity, while <ORGANIZATION>Saatchi &amp; Saatchi Advertising of
New York</ORGANIZATION> will concentrate on day-to-day brand retailing, <PERSON>Burger
King</PERSON> said.
   The agencies replace <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, the New York-based ad agency
hired 20 months ago that created the ``We do it like you'd do it''
theme Burger King began using in <DATE>January 1988</DATE>.
   The British-based conglomerate <ORGANIZATION>Grand Metropolitan PLC</ORGANIZATION> acquired
Burger King as part of its buyout of the <ORGANIZATION>Pillsbury Co.</ORGANIZATION>, based in
<LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, in <DATE>January</DATE>. The Miami-based <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON> is a
subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>Pillsbury</ORGANIZATION>.
   Burger King, which had systemwide sales of <MONEY>$5.4 billion</MONEY> in 5,800
restaurants during <DATE>fiscal year 1988</DATE>, has had little or no sales
growth over the past four years although it has held on to its
second-place position in the fast-food market behind industry
leader <ORGANIZATION>McDonald's Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Average sales per restaurant slipped <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> <DATE>last year</DATE>, but
finished above <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> for the fourth consecutive year, <PERSON>Burger
King</PERSON> said.
   The company estimates its market share has held fairly steady
over that period at about <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>.
   <PERSON>Gary L. Langstaff</PERSON>, hired in <DATE>April</DATE> as <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s executive
vice president of marketing after three years with <ORGANIZATION>Hardee</ORGANIZATION>'s, said
the dual-agency approach is part of an overall effort to improve
the focus of <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> advertising.
   ``There are two keys for us _ day-to-day and long-term branding.
Our goal is to make both of those work in tandem,'' <PERSON>Langstaff</PERSON> said.
   He said no decision had been made yet on how ad spending would
be split between the two new agencies. He also declined to estimate
when advertising from the new agencies may start running.
   <PERSON>Langstaff</PERSON> said <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON> will continue to work on a
project-by-project basis with both its national promotion agencies,
<ORGANIZATION>Einson-Freeman Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, and <DATE>August</DATE>, Bishop and <PERSON>Meier</PERSON>. Burger King's
relationships are unchanged with other advertising agencies,
<ORGANIZATION>UniWorld Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Castor Spanish International</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>UniWorld</ORGANIZATION> and
Castor create ads for Burger King aimed at minority markets.
   Burger King disclosed last month that it planned to replace Ayer
on the national portion of its advertising business, but said Ayer
would continue to produce regional advertising.
   With <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s announcement, <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> indicated it would
sever all ties with Ayer after a brief transition period.
   Ayer was selected in <DATE>September 1987</DATE> as <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION>'s ad agency,
ending the fast-food company's 11-year association with <PERSON>J. Walter
Thompson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Thompson's work for <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> included a roundly criticized
<DATE>1986</DATE> campaign that featured a search for the nerdy <PERSON>Herb</PERSON>, who had
never been to a <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION>.
   Subsequent campaigns from <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> that used the themes ``This
is a Burger King Town'' and ``The Best Food for Fast Times'' failed
to spark sales.
   But <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s ``We do it'' campaign also failed to boost sales.
Burger King also underwent a series of unsettling management
changes during Ayer's tenure.
   ``It has been said many times that timing is everything,'' <PERSON>Jerry
Siano</PERSON>, the head of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a memo to his employees.
``We were a year and a half early.''
   He said Grand Met has indicated ``a commitment to management
stability and marketing focus that will become the vital
ingredients to <PERSON>Burger King</PERSON>'s future success. We wish them much
success.''
   A jubilant <PERSON>Edward J. Wax</PERSON>, chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Saatchi &amp;
Saatchi</ORGANIZATION>, said he and other executives would travel soon to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to
begin defining roles and working up strategies.
   ``Obviously, we think they're a tremendous company,'' Wax said
from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. ``There's a lot to be done, there's been a lot of
negative stuff written. It's a big challenge. But we're excited.''
   Wax called the two-agency approach fascinating and innovative
and said his earlier study of <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION> found strong management
commitment to improvement.
   His agency in the past has handled assignments for the fast food
operators <PERSON>Krystal</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wendy</PERSON>'s, and <ORGANIZATION>Arby</ORGANIZATION>'s, Wax said, and experienced
executives from those accounts will work on <ORGANIZATION>Burger King</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891011-0048 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891011 </DD>
<AN> 891011-0048. </AN>
<HL> Marketing &amp; Media -- Advertising:
@  Ayer Set to Enter Joint Venture
@  For the Production of TV Shows
@  ----
@  By Joanne Lipman </HL>
<DD> 10/11/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> SAA ITGR KO EUROP </CO>
<IN> MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT) </IN>
<TEXT>
   N <ORGANIZATION>W Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> expects to announce today a joint venture that will vault it into television production on a world-wide basis -- a venture that will create TV movies and miniseries, aired both here and abroad, sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> clients. 

   The venture is among the most ambitious efforts yet by an ad agency to tackle TV programming, an area advertisers dominated in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and are returning to in increasing numbers now. 
It would allow Ayer's roster of big international clients -- including <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> -- to produce TV programs not just in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, but in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and elsewhere. 
It also would give Ayer's European clients a chance to produce TV movies for their home turf. 

   The joint venture pairs Ayer with <ORGANIZATION>World International Network</ORGANIZATION>, known as WIN, an organization representing TV networks in 106 countries that has already co-produced a number of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> TV movies. 
WIN, formed in <DATE>1988</DATE>, has had a hand in TV movies including <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION>'s recent "In the Line of Duty: The <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> Murders"; <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>'s "Day One," about the decision to drop the atomic bomb; and "The Final Days," chronicling the end of <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>'s presidency, which is to air <DATE>Oct. 22</DATE>. 

   The joint venture calls for Ayer clients to help finance and sponsor TV movies. 
At the same time, WIN's member stations, none of which are in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, would pay to air the movie in their countries. 
Most of the TV movies would also air in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> on network or cable stations. 
The arrangement would spread production costs around, while guaranteeing that the movie would air both here and abroad. 

   Advertisers disillusioned with the paltry fare on television have rediscovered TV production in the past few years; Ayer clients <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION>, which co-produced "Day One," are just two that have gotten involved in programming. 
But advertiser efforts so far have focused on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> -- and the joint venture gives <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s clients the ability to sponsor programs in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and elsewhere, too. 

   "Even clients in European countries who couldn't otherwise have afforded programming now will have access to it. 
The bottom line is, it offers access to more programming for our clients," says <PERSON>Marcella Rosen</PERSON>, Ayer executive vice president and managing director for media services. 
Besides, she adds, the venture would allow Ayer clients to pick movies "that stand out . . . that aren't your standard bad tear-jerkers." 

   For WIN, the venture gives its member TV stations more programming, with the cost defrayed by the advertisers. 
Because of deregulation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, TV stations are proliferating at breakneck speed. 
Europe "needs good product, and needs tons of programs," says <PERSON>Larry Gershman</PERSON>, WIN's chairman and chief executive officer. 

   According to <PERSON>Mr. Gershman</PERSON>, the venture expects in its first year to create about three movies sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> clients. 
It plans to grow quickly after that, with perhaps eight to nine productions the following year, he says. 

   The joint venture also gives <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s clients a way to circumvent last week's edict by the <ORGANIZATION>European Community</ORGANIZATION> that the majority of European programming be produced in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
Even for movies geared primarily to a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> audience, WIN/Ayer hopes to find some projects that can be filmed at least in part abroad, qualifying the movies as home-grown European programs. 
Other projects might focus primarily on <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, backed by some of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>'s Europe-based clients. 

   Ayer joins a number of other agencies that have gotten involved in TV programming, but it is among the front-runners in cracking the European market. 
Earlier this year, <ORGANIZATION>Interpublic Group of Cos.</ORGANIZATION> became <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s largest supplier of game shows by buying a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Fremantle International</ORGANIZATION>, a distributor of 43 game shows produced in nine European countries. 
And <PERSON>Foote</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Cone &amp; Belding</ORGANIZATION>'s FCB/Telecom has created programming for 11 years for <ORGANIZATION>Foote Cone</ORGANIZATION> clients. 
It says it plans to expand aggressively into <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> next year. 

   ---

   <PERSON>Mullen</PERSON> Gets the <ORGANIZATION>Juice 

   Veryfine Products Inc.</ORGANIZATION> selected <ORGANIZATION>Mullen Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to handle advertising for its juice products. 
The account bills about <MONEY>$8 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> annually. 

   The <LOCATION>Wenham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, agency, which has billings of <MONEY>$63 million</MONEY>, beat out <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> heavyweights <PERSON>Scali</PERSON>, <PERSON>McCabe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sloves</PERSON>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Ogilvy</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mather</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Cliff Freeman &amp; Partners</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Saatchi &amp; Saatchi</ORGANIZATION>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Veryfine</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Westford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, dropped Chiat/Day, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, earlier this year because of a client conflict. 

   ---

   Ad Notes. . . . 


   COKE ON CASSETTE: <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola Co.</ORGANIZATION> will be the sole sponsor in the second issue of Persona Video, a celebrity-oriented "magazine" on videotape that will be sold at checkout stands next week in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>. 

   NEW ACCOUNT: <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Wyse Advertising</ORGANIZATION> is named agency of record for <ORGANIZATION>Integra Financial Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a Pittsburgh-based banking firm. 
The account bills about <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900710-0045
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900710-0045.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing &amp; Media -- Advertising:
   Ayer is Considering Going Public
   As It Pays Heed to Financial Side
   ----
   By Joanne Lipman
</HL>
<DATE>
07/10/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B6
</SO>
<CO>
   AHP MBC WNEWS WPPGY X.TMP IPG CL
</CO>
<IN>
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   Ayer, one of the ad industry's oldest names and one of
just a handful of huge agencies to remain privately held, is
considering going public, its new chief financial officer
said.
   In an interview, Glenn Corlett said that financial
pressures on the beleaguered agency, which is still reeling
from two major client losses, are prompting him to explore a
number of alternatives, including going public.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   That admission is startling, considering that <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> has
repeatedly stressed its determination to remain independent
and private. It also augurs a new direction for <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, which,
perhaps for the first time, is taking its finances as
seriously as it takes its ads.
   <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> said the likelihood of such a drastic step is
probably less than <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>, but that he nevertheless must give it
some consideration. "Taking this agency public is certainly
one thing we need to look at from time to time. We've
historically said we want to remain independent. . . . But
the fact of the matter is, in this changing world, you have
to re-evaluate that preference regularly. I'm looking at
that." He added that "the mandate I've been given is,
`nothing is out of bounds.'"
   <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> said he would also consider other options,
such as selling a minority stake in <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> to a foreign firm,
or a setup similar to the one between <ORGANIZATION>Foote, Cone &amp; Belding</ORGANIZATION>
and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Publicis</ORGANIZATION>, in which each holds a minority stake
in the other. He said selling all or a majority of <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> to
another company isn't under consideration. Any of those
alternatives would be a radical departure for <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, founded
121 years ago and known for its emotional ads for blue-chip
clients like <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Procter &amp; Gamble</ORGANIZATION>.
   The fact that <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> is even considering steps that
management had until recently ruled out categorically points
up just how distressed the advertising industry has become.
Ayer in particular has had a few rough years. Since <DATE>1988</DATE>,
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> billings have plunged <PERCENT>23%</PERCENT>, to an estimated <MONEY>$726 million</MONEY>
from <MONEY>$947 million</MONEY>, mostly because of the loss of two huge
accounts: Burger King in <DATE>1989</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Continental Airlines</ORGANIZATION>
earlier this year. The agency recently closed its <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>
office and last year had to merge its <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> office with a
local agency there after the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> outpost lost almost all
its clients.
   <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON>, who became chief financial officer last
month, spoke candidly in the interview about Ayer's financial
situation. In the past year, he said, revenue slid <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>,
mostly because of the loss of the two clients. At the same
time, New York-based Ayer hasn't cut costs enough to counter
the revenue loss. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> payroll costs, for example, have
declined only <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> since <DATE>1988</DATE>, to an estimated <MONEY>$59 million</MONEY>
this year. The upshot: While the agency remains profitable,
its profitability fell last year and will remain about flat
this year, he said.
   Layoffs might seem a reasonable step to improve
profitability. But <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, which prides itself on its
paternalistic tradition of avoiding layoffs, is determined to
preserve that culture. Considering layoffs "was clearly
discouraged" by top management, <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> said. He said he
is hoping to cut costs by attrition, doing away with some
duplicated functions and more fully computerizing the
company.
   Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, like other large privately held agencies,
must wrestle with how to expand and compete with agencies
that have access to funds from the public. The mega-agencies
that grew and merged throughout the <DATE>1980s</DATE> relied on raising
money through the public markets. Private agencies had to use
their own money and bank loans to keep up. Now, with ad
spending in a stubborn lull and with the economy awash in
uncertainty, the private agencies are finding expansion
difficult.
   Ayer, for one, used to make acquisitions with internally
generated cash. But in the past two years, it had to borrow
about <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> to make several dozen European acquisitions
with a total price tag of over <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> said.
Part of his mandate is to find "economical ways to service
that debt," he said, while part is to find new ways to
continue growing.
   "You can raise money from the public markets if you're
public. But if you aren't, you've got a real problem with
financing that rapid growth," he said. "We are struggling
under the issues of how do we finance our growth and control
the related costs." He said one possible answer will be to
create joint ventures abroad, rather than to buy existing ad
agencies outright. The agency has 71 offices in 41 countries
and owns either the majority or <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> of most of its agencies
abroad.
   Emphasizing that <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION> has ruled out selling all or a
majority of the agency to an outsider, <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> said that
to remain independent, the agency "is willing to accept
tightening our belt and a little less profit."
   <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON>'s appointment is a sign that even the most
traditional Madison Avenue holdouts are taking finances more
seriously. A Price Waterhouse veteran, <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> is the
first Ayer chief financial officer to come from the "outside"
and the first who didn't start his career in advertising. His
predecessor at <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, began as an account
executive.
   <PERSON>Mr. Corlett</PERSON> also is the first chief financial officer in
the agency's history to be named to the board. The fact that
his predecessors weren't "gives you a hint of what the
advertising people thought of that function -- they didn't
hold it in high regard," he said.
   "The financial function is coming out of the closet, and
it's becoming a lot more important in terms of whether the
agencies can remain competitive," he said. "Today, in order
to survive and compete, you'd better have effective financial
management. It probably hasn't been true before, but in the
<DATE>1990s</DATE>, it certainly is going to be true. You'll see a lot of
ad agencies go out of business because they don't pay
attention to the financial side."
   ---
   Ad Notes. . . .
                                                                                                       

   ANACIN: <ORGANIZATION>American Home Products</ORGANIZATION>' <ORGANIZATION>Whitehall Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>
division in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> awarded its <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY> Anacin account
to <ORGANIZATION>Partners &amp; Shevack</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. The account had been handled
at <ORGANIZATION>Young &amp; Rubicam</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
                                                                                                       

   WHO'S NEWS: <PERSON>Alan Maites</PERSON> was named president of <PERSON>William A.
Robinson</PERSON>, the Chicago-based sales promotion unit of <ORGANIZATION>Ketchum
Communications</ORGANIZATION>.
                                                                                                       

   NEW ACCOUNTS: <ORGANIZATION>Australian Meat &amp; Live-Stock Corp.</ORGANIZATION> awarded
the ad account for its Fresh Australian Range Lamb program to
Brouillard/LGFE, a New York-based unit of <ORGANIZATION>WPP</ORGANIZATION> Group. . . .
<PERSON>Caroline Jones</PERSON> Advertising, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, was awarded the ad
account for <ORGANIZATION>Trump City</ORGANIZATION>, the planned waterfront development on
the <LOCATION>West Side of Manhattan</LOCATION>. . . . <ORGANIZATION>Colgate-Palmolive</ORGANIZATION> awarded
the <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> Viadent toothpaste and mouthwash account for
its <ORGANIZATION>Vipont Pharmaceutical</ORGANIZATION> unit to <ORGANIZATION>Pallas Advertising</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. Pallas takes over the account from
McCann-Erickson.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880523-0048 </DOCNO>
<HL> Ayer Agrees to Pay U.S. $750,000 to Settle Charges </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> MKT </IN>
<G> DEF </G>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   N <ORGANIZATION>W Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> agreed to pay the government <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> to settle overcharge claims involving advertising work for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> stretching back to <DATE>1978</DATE>. 

   The settlement documents contend that the New York-based advertising company knowingly mischarged the government by using inaccurate time cards and record keeping for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> ad campaign that popularized the slogan "Be All You Can Be." 
The documents also contend that Ayer failed to obtain competitive bids for subcontracts. 

   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, officials of N W Ayer weren't available to comment on the matter. 

   The company was suspended in <DATE>November 1986</DATE> from bidding on government contracts after <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> investigators asserted that N W Ayer overcharged the government. 

   Under terms of the settlement, the government agreed to lift the suspension. 
The company didn't admit any wrongdoing, but agreed to drop a civil suit against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> seeking at least <MONEY>$525,000</MONEY> in damages, and to tighten internal accounting and time-keeping procedures. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870113-0092 </DOCNO>
<HL> 
 </HL>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> lost its bid for a temporary restraining order to prevent the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> from awarding its advertising contract to another company. 

   <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, a New York-based advertising agency, sought the order in federal <ORGANIZATION>District Court</ORGANIZATION> here after the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> last week decided, as previously reported, to uphold the company's suspension from bidding on <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> contracts. 

   Ayer, which was the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s advertising agency for 19 years and created the successful "Be all that you can be" campaign, was suspended by the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>November</DATE> because of various allegations of irregularities in timekeeping and subcontracting. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1987</DATE> contract is expected to be decided soon. 

   <PERSON>Stephen Lawrence</PERSON>, a partner in the law firm <ORGANIZATION>Pepper, Hamilton &amp; Sheetz</ORGANIZATION>, which represents <ORGANIZATION>Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, said the company will continue to try to prevent a competitor from winning the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> contract. 
A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> couldn't be reached for comment. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880331-0125 </DOCNO>
<HL> GM Selects Ayer, Hill Holiday, Riney As Finalists for Its Big Saturn Account </HL>
<AUTHOR> Laurie P. Cohen (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GM </CO>
<IN> AUT MKT </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Saturn Corp.</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary has narrowed to three the number of agencies it will consider for its advertising account, the largest up for grabs in the ad industry. 

   New York-based <ORGANIZATION>N W Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, Boston-based Hill, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Connors, Cosmopulos Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>San Francisco-based Hal Riney &amp; Partners Inc.</ORGANIZATION> were told earlier this week that they had been selected as the finalists in the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> competition, according to advertising industry executives. 

   Troy, Mich.-based <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> is expected to decide by the end of <DATE>May</DATE> which agency will handle the car account. 
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s annual billings are expected to total about <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>, making it one of the largest accounts by ad industry standards. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> officials declined to comment on the selection of ad agency finalists. 
Officials of <ORGANIZATION>N W Ayer</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hill Holliday</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Riney</PERSON> all acknowledged they had been contacted by <DATE>Saturn this week</DATE>, but declined to elaborate. 

   Late last year, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> had been contacted by some 50 agencies that expressed interest in getting the account. 
Saturn <DATE>earlier this year</DATE> narrowed its list to a handful of agencies, which also included <ORGANIZATION>D'Arcy Masius Benton &amp; Bowles Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>TBWA Advertising Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Case &amp; Taylor Inc.</ORGANIZATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>McCann-Erickson Worldwide &amp; Dailey &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of the <ORGANIZATION>Interpublic Group of Cos</ORGANIZATION>. 

   There have been previous reports that N W Ayer and <PERSON>Hill Holliday</PERSON> were being considered for the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> account, but that <PERSON>Hal Riney</PERSON> was also being considered came as a surprise to many in the industry, including several who were competing for the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> account. 

   Riney grabbed headlines late last year when it resigned as the advertising agency for <LOCATION>Modesto</LOCATION>, Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>E.&amp; J. Gallo Winery</ORGANIZATION>, after a brush with the Gallos. 
<PERSON>Riney</PERSON> was the creator of <ORGANIZATION>Gallo's Bartles &amp; Jaymes</ORGANIZATION> wine-cooler campaign. 
Other clients include <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Good Housekeeping Magazine</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>California Prune Board</ORGANIZATION>. 

   But <PERSON>Riney</PERSON> also is the agency for <ORGANIZATION>Austin Rover Cars of North America</ORGANIZATION>'s Sterling cars. 
Austin Rover is the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales arm of <ORGANIZATION>Rover Group PLC</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. 
Some ad executives said that could pose a potential conflict if <PERSON>Riney</PERSON> wins the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> competition. 

   However, <PERSON>Riney</PERSON> president <PERSON>Jim Travis</PERSON> yesterday said, "There's no problem with Sterling." 
Officials of both <ORGANIZATION>Sterling</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> "don't consider it a conflict" because "They're in entirely different markets," he said. 

   Hill <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON>, however, would likely have to resign from one of its advertising accounts if it succeeds in getting <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> as a client. 
The agency represents <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> dealer groups. 
Hill <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> also creates ads for <ORGANIZATION>Wang Laboratories</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>John Hancock Cos.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Revlon Group Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   N W Ayer's only automobile client is G.M., <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s parent. 
The agency does corporate advertising for the auto maker. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021790-0146 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 178363 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 17, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 6; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
225 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ORANGE COUNTY FOCUS: COUNTYWIDE; 
</P>
<P>
AYERS DIES OF INJURIES FROM SUICIDE TRY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WENDY PAULSON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION> woman who attempted suicide in her <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> jail cell by 
hanging herself from a shower rod died <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> from related injuries, 
authorities said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pamela Pauline Ayers</PERSON>, 45, had been held since <DATE>Aug. 12</DATE> in the women's jail as a 
suspect in the fatal shooting of prominent <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>Gerald 
Goldfarb</PERSON>, a 49-year-old appellate lawyer and columnist for the <ORGANIZATION>Whole Life 
Times</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Deputies conducting a routine check <DATE>Thursday</DATE> discovered the woman hanging from 
a bedsheet tied to a shower rod. Ayers, a former interior decorator, was alone 
in her cell when the attempted suicide occurred, <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Sheriff</ORGANIZATION>'s Lt. 
<PERSON>Bob Rivas</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON> died of multiple wounds to the head and body, and <PERSON>Ayers</PERSON> underwent 
surgery for a self-inflicted wound to the abdomen shortly after the shooting 
outside her <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION> condominium. 
</P>
<P>
Police alleged that <PERSON>Ayers</PERSON> fired 10 shots from a 12-gauge shotgun that she had 
bought just hours before the slaying. Investigators also allege that <PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Ayers</PERSON> had argued shortly before the shooting. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ayers</PERSON>' attorney has said the woman mistook <PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON>'s friendship and legal 
counsel for a love relationship. <PERSON>Ayers</PERSON>' daughter, <PERSON>Christina Irwin</PERSON>, 27, said the 
two were romantically involved and were trying to have a child until <PERSON>Ayers</PERSON> 
suffered a mental breakdown early last year. WENDY <PERSON>PAULSON</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SUICIDES -- ORANGE COUNTY; MURDERS -- ORANGE COUNTY; PRISON DEATHS; PRISONERS 
-- ORANGE COUNTY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870112-0009 </DOCNO>
<HL> Army Upholds Suspension
Of Ayer in Bids for Work</HL>
<DD> 01/12/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MARKETING, ADVERTISING (MKT)
DEFENSE DEPARTMENT (DEF) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> said that, after reviewing an appeal by <ORGANIZATION>N.W. Ayer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, it has decided to uphold the advertising agency's suspension from bidding on government contracts. 

   Ayer, which was the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s advertising agency for 19 years and created the successful "Be all that you can be" campaign, was suspended by the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>November</DATE> because of various allegations of improper timekeeping and subcontracting. 

   The continued suspension eliminates the company from competing for the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1987</DATE> advertising contract, which is expected to be decided this week. 

   Ayer said that it plans to seek a temporary restraining order today to bar the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> from awarding the <DATE>1987</DATE> contract until the company can make a full appeal. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to oppose any such attempt. 
