<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890206-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-89 0236EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AntarcticAftermath     02-06 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctic Aftermath,0671</SECOND>
<HEAD>Antarctic Oil Spill Creates ``The Experiment Nobody Wanted''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After decades of studying wildlife in an
unspoiled area of <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, scientists have begun a new, unwelcome
line of research: the effects of an oil spill.
   ``This disaster is the experiment nobody wanted,'' said <ORGANIZATION>National
Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jack Talmadge</PERSON>.
   By <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, American cleanup crews are expected to reach the area
affected by the sinking of an oil-laden supply ship, which ran
aground <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE> off the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>.
   Scientists have already seen oil-covered and apparently lethargic
seals, three dead penguins and disappearances of young nesting
birds, said <PERSON>Ted DeLaca</PERSON>, chief scientist of the foundation's division
of polar programs.
   Thirty-eight of 40 penguins checked <DATE>Friday</DATE> bore traces of oil.
Thousands of dead and dying krill, shrimplike crustaceans that are a
key food for bigger animals, have shown up on beaches, DeLaca told
reporters by telephone from <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>, a research outpost near
the spill.
   ``All the principle (penguin) rookeries here are now surrounded
by fuel oil,'' he said. ``What its effect could be on the birds is
anybody's guess.''
   Adelie penguin chicks are expected to leave their nests for the
first time in a few days, swimming into contaminated waters. Other
birds are being exposed to the oil as they land on water or dive
into it to feed.
   Scientists are concerned that birds may freeze to death if the
oil disrupts their natural insulation, or be poisoned if they
swallow oil while preening themselves or eating oil-covered prey.
   The spill struck an area that has ``the largest and most diverse
plant and animal populations of the continent,'' said <PERSON>Polly Penhale</PERSON>,
manager of the science foundation's polar biology and medicine
program.
   Apart from the large seal population, about 30,000 sea birds live
there, including <LOCATION>Adelie</LOCATION> and chinstrap penguins, cormorants, kelp
gulls and giant petrels, she said.
   Scientists have studied wildlife in the area for more than 20
years, but now the pristine nature of the area has been altered.
   ``The paths of research that have been followed down there have
been forever changed,'' said <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON>. ``I think if you're a
scientist in the year <DATE>2035</DATE>, you've got to remember there was an oil
spill.''
   DeLaca said the highly sensitive environment ``has been
compromised in a way that we can't even evaluate right now.''
   <PERSON>Langdon Quetin</PERSON>, research biologist at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
California</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, said if the oil spill causes dramatic
damage or long-term effects on plants and animals, ``then we can't
really depend on the area as a natural uncontaminated laboratory.''
   ``That really is unfortunate, to say the least, because it is one
of the few areas in the Antarctic we have good logistics to,'' he
said. ``It will be the ruination of a good laboratory, at least in
the near future, at least as a natural uncontaminated study area.''
   Some scientists are particularly concerned about fish and other
organisms kept in tanks at <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>, which marine botanist
``probably the best marine biology laboratory in the Antarctic.''
   The tanks draw water from the nearby harbor, and if oil
contaminates that supply, the experiments might have to be stopped.
Nobody knows yet whether that will be a problem, <PERSON>Penhale</PERSON> said.
   Neushul said one factor boding poorly for the area's wildlife is
that the spill involved fuel oil, which is ``much more toxic than
crude oil'' because it can damage biological tissue.
   Neushul, who investigated a spill of partially refined oil off
the <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> coast some 30 years ago, said the effects of
that spill lasted 17 years.
   In addition, recovery in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> may be prolonged because
bacteria there will need a long time to break the oil down, said
<PERSON>Paul Dayton</PERSON>, professor of marine ecology at the <ORGANIZATION>Scripps Institute of
Oceanography</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>La Jolla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890204-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-89 1155EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AntarcticAftermath Bjt   02-04 0821</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Antarctic Aftermath, Bjt,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>Antarctic Oil Spill May Threaten Wildlife Research, Scientists Fear</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MALCOLM RITTER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Oil from a sunken ship off <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> threatens
not only the environment in a pristine bay, but also wildlife
research in a biologically rich area prized until now for its
unspoiled state, scientists say.
   ``The paths of research that have been followed down there have
been forever changed,'' said <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
<PERSON>Jack Talmadge</PERSON>. ``I think if you're a scientist in the year <DATE>2035</DATE>,
you've got to remember there was an oil spill.''
   <PERSON>Ted DeLaca</PERSON>, chief scientist of the foundation's polar programs,
said the highly sensitive environment ``has been compromised in a
way that we can't even evaluate right now.''
   While the spill's effect on future research cannot yet be
determined, ``it's something I find personally disturbing,'' he said
by telephone <DATE>Friday</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>, a research outpost near the
spill.
   The oil is leaking from an Argentine research and supply ship
that ran aground <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE>. The ship is nearly submerged on shoals in
the <LOCATION>Bismarck Strait</LOCATION> just off the Antarctic peninsula, 600 miles from
the tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   Authorities said the ship carried at least 200,000 gallons of
fuel oil in its tanks and more in drums lashed to the deck. American
cleanup crews are expected to reach the site sometime this week.
   Some scientists said the effects of the spill may be magnified
because it involved fuel oil, more dangerous to wildlife than crude
oil, and because Antarctic conditions could slow the oil's
decomposition.
   The spill struck an area that has ``the largest and most diverse
plant and animal populations of the continent,'' said <PERSON>Polly Penhale</PERSON>,
manager of the science foundation's polar biology and medicine
program.
   Apart from a large seal population, some 30,000 sea birds live in
the area affected by the spill, including <ORGANIZATION>Adele</ORGANIZATION> and chinstrap
penguins, cormorants, kelp gulls and giant petrels, <PERSON>Penhale</PERSON> said.
   ``It is one of the most spectacularly beautiful areas in the
whole <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Sayed Z. El-Sayed</PERSON>, an oceanography
professor at <ORGANIZATION>Texas A&amp;M University</ORGANIZATION> who has studied it for 25 years.
   Most plants and animals live on islands off the mainland, where
the science foundation operates <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> on a spit of rock.
   Scientists have already seen oil-covered and apparently lethargic
seals, three dead penguins and disappearances of young nesting
birds, <ORGANIZATION>DeLaca</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Thirty-eight of 40 penguins checked <DATE>Friday</DATE> bore traces of oil.
Thousands of dead and dying krill, shrimplike crustaceans that are a
key food for bigger animals, have shown up on beaches, he said.
   ``All the principal (penguin) rookeries here are now surrounded
by fuel oil,'' he said. ``What its effect could be on the birds is
anybody's guess.''
   Birds can freeze to death if the oil disrupts their natural
insulation, or be poisoned if they swallow oil while preening
themselves or eating contaminated prey.
   Scientists have studied wildlife in the area for more than 20
years, focusing on birds and seals and also on such organisms as
fish, kelp, krill and shelled animals called limpets.
   ``One of the main concerns of the scientists ... is that that
area stay pristine, because we have a lot of environmental research
that's going on,'' said <PERSON>Langdon Quetin</PERSON>, research biologist at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>.
   ``It is one of the few areas in the Antarctic we have good
logistics to,'' he said. The spill ``will be the ruination of a good
laboratory, at least in the near future, at least as a natural
uncontaminated study area.''
   Some scientists are particularly concerned about fish and other
organisms kept in tanks at <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>, which marine botanist
``probably the best marine biology laboratory in the Antarctic.''
   The tanks draw seawater from the nearby harbor, and if oil
contaminates that supply, the experiments might have to be stopped.
Nobody knows yet whether that will be a problem, <PERSON>Penhale</PERSON> said.
   Neushul said one factor boding poorly for the area's wildlife is
that the spill involved fuel oil, which is much more toxic than
crude oil because it can damage biological tissue.
   Neushul, who investigated a spill of partially refined oil off
<LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> 30 years ago, said that spill caused mass deaths of
fish, starfish, sea urchins and other animals. The same may happen
to similar animals in the Antarctic, he said.
   In the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> spill, the environment took 17 years to
recover, he said. Recovery in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> may take even longer
because bacteria there will need a long time to break the oil down,
said <PERSON>Paul Dayton</PERSON>, professor of marine ecology at the <ORGANIZATION>Scripps
Institute of Oceanography</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>La Jolla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   After years of studying wildlife in a pristine environment,
researchers are now turning to monitor how the wildlife responds to
the oil spill, <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said. ``This disaster is the experiment
nobody wanted,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122189-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 151423 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 21, 1989, Thursday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
588 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THINGS HATCHING AT SEA WORLD'S PENGUIN ENCOUNTER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At 10 degrees below freezing, the delivery room at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION> is colder than 
most. 
</P>
<P>
So far this year, however, a record-breaking number of feathered couples have 
become parents at the marine park's "Penguin Encounter," and recently the 45 
tiny hatchlings have started to get some notice. 
</P>
<P>
Lately, the glassed-in, 5,000-square-foot cold climate exhibit has begun to 
resemble a hospital infant ward, as park visitors strain to get a glimpse of 
the 14 fast-growing adelie penguins that are just beginning to venture outside 
their nests. 
</P>
<P>
But some of the the most exciting additions to the park's penguin colony are 
not yet on public display. Besides 23 more adelies, two baby gentoo penguins 
are being hand-raised by park keepers, the first gentoos to be born from eggs 
laid in captivity at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION>. Six baby Humboldt penguins are being 
hand-raised as well, and keepers say that, by observing the young, they hope to 
learn more about preserving Humboldts, the one penguin species that is 
endangered. 
</P>
<P>
"If there was a oil spill off the coast of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> where the Humboldts 
are, that could disrupt the whole species," said <PERSON>Joop Kuhn</PERSON>, supervisor of 
aviculture at <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION>. "We'd need to know what to feed them, how often, how 
much. But we're getting a pretty good understanding -- we'd know where to 
start." 
</P>
<P>
With more than 500 penguins, the marine park's 6-year-old exhibit is the 
largest penguin colony outside of the Antarctic. As part of a project conducted 
with the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, the park keeps detailed records on each 
penguin from nine species. 
</P>
<P>
There's a file, for example, on <ORGANIZATION>King Tut</ORGANIZATION>, the first king penguin park keepers 
hand-raised from an egg that was laid in the wild. There's another on <ORGANIZATION>Elvis</ORGANIZATION>, 
another king penguin named for the "king of rock 'n' roll," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Files include personal details, he said: "Who they're paired up with, how many 
offspring they've had, if they've changed mates -- for the most part, they're 
monogamous, but we've seen a slight divorce rate in our enclosure." 
</P>
<P>
Park experts know which birds have showed a knack for keeping their eggs warm, 
and which birds have wandered off to let the eggs fend for themselves. They 
know that a penguin lays two eggs, as they often do, as a kind of "insurance," 
<PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Most penguin species will lay two eggs 
</P>
<P>
but rarely will they be able to raise both young. It's survival of the 
fittest," he said. 
</P>
<P>
But park keepers, eager to supplement their growing colony, have begun rescuing 
the second eggs from the nests before they hatch. 
</P>
<P>
"Mother Nature is very tough on her own. We try to sort of soften that by 
artificial incubating," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. "If we take one egg from our birds, and 
leave them with one, they will put all their effort and energy there." 
</P>
<P>
The hand-raised babies are treated to what keepers call penguin milkshakes, a 
tasty mixture of herring filets, shrimp-like crustaceans, half-and-half cream, 
water and vitamins that is heated to 90 degrees to resemble the regurgitated 
meals their parents would feed them in the wild, <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said the park had also hoped to hatch some chinstrap penguins this year, 
which have never been hatched in captivity. Chinstrap penguins, named for the 
black stripe across their necks, laid eggs for the first time at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION> this 
year. But the eggs proved infertile. 
</P>
<P>
"The first year they try and do it," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. "They do their best sitting on 
the eggs. Hopefully, by the second year, they've figured out the copulation 
thing and see if they can pull it off." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Gentoo penguins at the Penguin Encouter at Sea World. Two gentoo chicks 
are among the 45 penguin offspring at the park. ; Photo, Laurie Burch, left, 
and Marla Bronovich with a friendly gentoo hatchling. ; Photo, Adelie penguins 
with their chick at the Penguin Encounter. BRUCE K. HUFF / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122189-0125 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 151721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 21, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
567 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COLD FEET IN THE DELIVERY ROOM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AMY WALLACE, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At 22 degrees Fahrenheit, the delivery room at Sea World may be colder than 
most, but no less productive. 
</P>
<P>
In fact, more feathered couples than ever are becoming parents at the marine 
park's "Penguin Encounter" and their 45 hatchlings are attracting attention. 
</P>
<P>
Lately, the glassed-in, 5,000-square-foot cold climate exhibit has begun to 
resemble a hospital infant ward, as park visitors strain to get a glimpse of 
the 14 fast-growing <LOCATION>Adelie</LOCATION> penguins that are just beginning to venture outside 
their nests. 
</P>
<P>
But some of the most exciting additions to the park's penguin colony are not 
yet on public display. In addition to 23 other <LOCATION>Adelie</LOCATION> babies, two <LOCATION>Gentoo</LOCATION> 
penguins are being hand-raised by park keepers -- the first Gentoos to be born 
from eggs laid in captivity at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION>. Six baby Humboldt penguins are being 
hand-raised as well. Keepers say that by observing the young, they hope to 
learn more about preserving Humboldts, the one penguin species that is 
endangered. 
</P>
<P>
"If there was an oil spill off the coast of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> where the Humboldts 
are, that could disrupt the whole species," said <PERSON>Joop Kuhn</PERSON>, supervisor of 
aviculture at <ORGANIZATION>Sea World</ORGANIZATION>. "We'd need to know what to feed them, how often, how 
much. But we're getting a pretty good understanding -- we'd know where to 
start." 
</P>
<P>
With more than 500 penguins, the park's 6-year-old exhibit is the largest 
penguin colony outside of the Antarctic. As part of a project conducted with 
the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, the park keeps detailed records on each 
penguin from nine different species. 
</P>
<P>
There's a file, for example, on <ORGANIZATION>King Tut</ORGANIZATION>, the first King penguin park keepers 
hand-raised from an egg that was laid in the wild. There's another on <ORGANIZATION>Elvis</ORGANIZATION>, a 
King penguin named for the "king of rock and roll," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Files include personal details, he said: "Who they're paired up with, how many 
offspring they've had, if they've changed mates -- for the most part they're 
monogamous, but we've seen a slight divorce rate in our enclosure." 
</P>
<P>
Park experts know which birds have shown a knack for keeping their eggs warm, 
and which have wandered off to let the eggs fend for themselves. They know when 
a penguin lays two eggs, as they often do as a kind of "insurance," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Most penguin species will lay two eggs but rarely will they be able to raise 
both young. It's survival of the fittest," he said. 
</P>
<P>
But park keepers, eager to supplement their growing colony, have begun rescuing 
the second eggs from the nests before they hatch. 
</P>
<P>
"Mother Nature is very tough on her own. We try to sort of soften that by 
artificial incubating," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. "If we take one egg from our birds, and 
leave them with one, they will put all their effort and energy there." 
</P>
<P>
The hand-raised babies are treated to what keepers call penguin milkshakes, a 
tasty mixture of herring filets, shrimp-like crustaceans, half-and-half cream, 
water and vitamins that is heated to 90 degrees to resemble the regurgitated 
meals their parents would feed them in the wild, <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said the park had also hoped to hatch some Chinstrap penguins this year, 
which have never been hatched in captivity. Chinstrap penguins, named for the 
black stripe across their necks, laid eggs for the first time at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION> this 
year. But the eggs proved infertile. 
</P>
<P>
"They do their best sitting on the eggs. Hopefully by the second year . . . 
they can pull it off," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Sea World employees, above from left, Laurie Burch, Marla Bronovich and 
Corrine Brindley, examine a 29-day-old Gentoo penguin, one of 45 hatchlings at 
"Penguin Encounter" center. Below, parent Adelie penguins with their chick, in 
rocks at bottom center. BRUCE K. HUFF / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PENGUINS; BIRDS; ANIMAL BREEDING; SEA WORLD OF CALIFORNIA; ANIMAL RESEARCH 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890204-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-89 0144EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-AntarcticSpill     02-04 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctic Spill,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Seals, Penguins Harmed By Oil Spill In Antarctic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PUNTA ARENAS, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ship laden with more than 50 tons of
equipment headed toward the Antarctic today to try and contain an
oil spill that experts say is killing wildlife and threatening to
wipe out a colony of baby penguins.
   The spill, from a sunken Argentine supply ship, has fouled the
once-pure waters of a pristine bay and was endangering more than
24,000 penguins and other nesting birds, said biologist <PERSON>Ted De Laca</PERSON>.
   ``It's very disturbing. Everything right now is worrisome,'' said
<PERSON>De Laca</PERSON>, a researcher at the <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research outpost
on the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>.
   About 52 tons of equipment flown from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
loaded onto the 219-foot <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION> here from a giant <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force
C-5 Galaxy</ORGANIZATION> cargo plane.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION> departed shortly after <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and was
expected to reach the area in four days.
   The oil is leaking from the Argentine research and supply ship
<LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>, which is trapped and nearly submerged on shoals in
the <LOCATION>Bismarck Strait</LOCATION> just off the Antarctic peninsula.
   Thousands of penguins, terns, gulls and other birds live around
the site of the accident, and the waters teem with marine life,
including whales. Two areas nearby are set aside by the Antarctic
Treaty for scientific study.
   Punta Arenas is at the windblown tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> about 600
miles from the stricken Argentine vessel.
   <PERSON>Thomas Forhan</PERSON>, ocean projects manager for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, leads the cleanup mission.
   American scientists, wearing respirators as protection against
the smell of oil fumes, are working in open boats to try to limit
the damage, but De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> said ``virtually all of the area is exposed
to fuel,'' causing young birds to disappear and killing small sea
animals ``in large numbers.''
   De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> spoke by telephone with the <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   About 24,000 penguins nest in rookeries in the affected area, and
De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> said 38 of the 40 adult birds checked by scientists have
been ``fuel-dipped.''
   The fear of the experts, he said, is that penguin chicks, due to
leave nests within a few days, will swim in the oil-coated water and
be sickened or killed. At least three dead penguins have been
sighted, said De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON>.
   ``All of the rookeries are surrounded by oil,'' he said.
   A number of seals were seen to be covered with oil and were
acting in a ``lethargic fashion,'' said the scientist.
   ``We have a slick 150 meters (yards) by 2 miles long going south
from the vessel,'' moving ``along and a little bit away'' from the
coast, <PERSON>Forhan</PERSON> said in an interview aboard the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>.
   He said there were reports of birds smothered by oil and of dead
krill, shrimp-like creatures that whales feed upon in large numbers,
floating ashore.
   Scientists and workers at <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> collected 112 compressed
gas cylinders and 15 oil drums from the waters around the wreck,
<PERSON>Forhan</PERSON> said, and ``there are more in the water.''
   The <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> ran aground <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE>. The more than 250 people
aboard were taken off without injury.
   Authorities said the ship carried at least 200,000 gallons of
fuel oil in its tanks and more in drums lashed to the deck.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890201-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-01-89 1848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Ship-Antarctica 1stLd-Writethru   02-01 0773</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ship-Antarctica, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0686,0791</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede BUENOS AIRES</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with U.S. team en route to spill,
details. No pickup. Changes byline.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BAI1, ST3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team of experts and 50 tons of
equipment headed to the Antarctic on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to battle a huge oil
spill that experts said was killing wildlife in the pristine polar
region.
   A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> cargo plane was bound for the southern city of
<LOCATION>Punta Arenas</LOCATION>, where the equipment will be transferred to a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
research vessel, the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> said.
   Officials stressed they still were trying to assess the magnitude
of the spill, which was caused by a sunken Argentine supply ship,
but said it represented the first major environmental threat to the
Antarctic.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> said the crippled
Argentine ship carried 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel and that an
``incurable disaster'' would result if all the fuel leaked into the
unspoiled waters in the region.
   In <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>, the Argentine navy played down the spill and
said it did not pose a serious ecological threat.
   But <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> launched a massive effort to stem
the spill, which was four miles in diameter and moving to the
southwest, said <PERSON>Jack Talmadge</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION>.
   The spill occurred after the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Paradise Bay</ORGANIZATION>), an
Argentine navy vessel, ran aground on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Bismarck
Strait</LOCATION>, about 600 miles south of the southern tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>
and 1{ miles from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Palmer Research Station</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>.
   All passengers and crew were rescued, but the vessel floated free
in heavy seas and then capsized <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, spilling barrels of
oil and several hundred propane gas containers into the water,
<PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said.
   ``It has leaked oil,'' he said. ``We're not sure whether the oil
leak is continuing. The water surrounding the ship is covered with a
couple of centimeters (about an inch) of oil. There is a sheen of
oil in a much wider area around the ship, including evidence of oil
on the coastline of the several islands there.''
   A private yacht 10-15 miles away reported earlier that it had
seen oil patches on the water, he said. Oil also was spotted at the
research station.
   ``Wildlife has already begun to be affected,'' including krill,
the small crustaceans that form the basis of the Antarctic food
chain, <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said.
   ``Birds which have eaten the krill are showing behavior
differences,'' he said. ``One dead penguin had been found as of a
few hours ago.''
   A <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> statement said about 12,000 pairs
of penguins and other sea birds nested in the area last year.
   ``In a few weeks, hatchling penguins will leave their nests and
enter the now-fouled Antarctic waters, as will their parents,'' said
the statement.
   A team of 15 experts and 52 tons of equipment on a giant <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> C-5B cargo plane left <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. It was to
arrive here on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and then go by ship across the <ORGANIZATION>Drake Passage</ORGANIZATION>
to the accident site along the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION> by <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
<PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> manages the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Antarctic
Program, which includes <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>, a scientific outpost.
   <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said scientists from the station have been going out in
boats to assess the damage and try to catch the oil barrels and
propane containers floating in the water.
   ``We're trying to get those, but that's a pretty massive
project,'' he said. ``We're using all the lifeboats from the ship
and any other boats we can get hold of in the area.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> is organizing the clean-up
mission, with assistance from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and the
   In <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Argentine navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said: ``There could
be a small stain'' from the release of oil in the engine room of the
ship. ``Anything else, no,'' He said.
   The ship carried tourists as well as fuel for several polar
stations. All 300 ship occupants were taken to the <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> station
after the vessel ran aground.
   Another <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> spokesman in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jack
Renerie</PERSON>, said in a telephone interview that the cargo plane was
carrying a 35-foot ``skimming boat'' for scooping up spilled oil and
pumping it into floating tanks; a small tugboat; inflatable booms to
contain the spill, and a special truck for loading and unloading the
equipment.
   He said it was accompanied by a crew from two private <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
clean-up companies, <ORGANIZATION>Marine Polution Control and Global Associates</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890208-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-08-89 0327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-AntarcticSpill     02-08 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctic Spill,0510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Baby Gulls Dying From Antarctic Oil Slick</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chilean frogmen worked to stop oil from
leaking from a partially submerged ship off <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, authorities
said, and a report <DATE>today</DATE> said thousands of polar seabirds have
already died near the spreading slick.
   Crewmen from the Chilean cutter Yelcho on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> encircled the
nearly sunken <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> vessel <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> with floating booms
designed to contain any further leakage, said a navy communique
released in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>New Zealand Press Association</ORGANIZATION> today reported that thousands of
baby Polar Skua gulls had died because their parents were unable to
find food.
   The predatory birds also can freeze to death if the oil disrupts
their natural insulation or be poisoned if they swallow oil while
preening themselves or eat contaminated prey.
   The news agency, citing unidentified scientists at the nearby
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Palmer Station on the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>, said the oil slick
has surrounded penguin rookeries near the wrecked ship.
   An operator reached by telephone at the research station referred
all inquiries to the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>,
which oversees the base 590 miles from the tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   The Argentine research and supply ship grounded on shoals <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE>.
   The ship holds about 800 tons of fuel, including diesel oil in
bulk and aviation fuel in steel drums. The <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> says oil is leaking slowly from the ship, which gradually
sank in the shallow waters. Only a section of its superstructure
remains above the surface.
   Foundation officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that a slick nearly 500 feet
wide and two miles long was trailing away from the vessel toward the
south, threatening the frozen continent's fragile and unspoiled
environment. Today's <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> report said the slick was four
miles long. It did not mention width.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research vessel, the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>, was expected to join
cleanup efforts. It carries military and civilian experts and 52
tons of sophisticated equipment.
   A research vessel of the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean Antarctic Institute</ORGANIZATION> also was at
the spill site evaluating environmental damage, said the insitute's
director, <PERSON>Antonio Massei</PERSON>.
   In a telephone interview in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, he said the area around the
accident is home to 29,000 penguins. Scientists say many baby
penguins soon will take their first swim in the waters, and they are
worried the youngsters could suffocate in the oil.
   Other wildlife also is threatened, including krill, a tiny
shrimp-like crustacean considered a vital link in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s food
chain.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> researchers say a number of seals were seen covered with oil
and moving slowly in the waters.
   Both the <PERSON>Yelcho</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION> left <DATE>Friday</DATE> from the Chilean
port of <ORGANIZATION>Punta Arenas</ORGANIZATION>, a major supply point for Antarctic operations.
   Two Argentine vessels were in the area of the spill and planned
to help, according to the Chilean navy. However, the ships were
awaiting equipment being flown from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to a Chilean-run base
200 miles from the wreckage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890204-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-04-89 0151EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AntarcticaShipwreck     02-04 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctica Shipwreck,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Environmental Damage Grows From Antarctica Fuel Oil Spill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Birds and other wildlife in one of the most
remote parts of the world are being injured and killed by fuel oil
spilled from a ship wrecked on an <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> island, and more damage
is possible before cleanup crews arrive.
   Biologist <PERSON>Ted De Laca</PERSON>, chief scientist at <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, said that more than 24,000 penguins and other birds are
endangered by an oil spill that threatens to wipe an entire
generation of chicks maturing in nests surrounded by the pollution.
Some wildlife already has been killed, he said.
   ``The environment has been compromised in a way that we can't
even evaluate right now,'' De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> said in a telephone conference
call from <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's very disturbing. Everything right
now is worrisome.''
   Palmer Station scientists, wearing respirators to protect against
the eye-stinging fumes of the oil slick, worked in open boats to
recover debris littering the fouled bay and to evaluate the damage.
   But De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> said a more effective effort to contain the spill
must await the arrival <DATE>Monday</DATE> of a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> oil pollution control team
from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   He said the fuel oil is spilling from the Argentine ship <LOCATION>Bahia
Paraiso</LOCATION> at the rate of about two gallons a minute and if it
continues the vessel could dump about 250,000 gallons into the
previously pure, untainted waters nearby.
   The ship, which doubled as a cruise ship and a supply vessel for
an Argentine research station, ran aground near <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION> <DATE>last
Saturday</DATE>. It later floated free, went aground again 1.1 miles from
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> outpost and then turned over on its right side against
another island. As it turned, fuel oil and deck cargo spilled into
the <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> Station embayment, home to a number of large bird
rookeries.
   <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> is a <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> research station.
Twenty-six scientists and staff are now working at the station under
the director of De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON>, the chief scientist. Palmer is about 600
miles south of <LOCATION>Cape Horn</LOCATION>, the tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> reported that krill, a tiny shrimp-like crustacean, have
been killed by the thousands and are lining the nearby beaches.
Birds feeding on the krill seem sickened, he said. In a nesting area
of the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Skua</ORGANIZATION>, a bird of prey, up to <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the chicks
have disappeared, possibily because parent birds sickened by the oil
are unable to protect their young, he said.
   About 24,000 penguins nest in rookies in the affected area, and
De <PERSON>Laca</PERSON> said that 38 of 40 adult birds checked by scientists have
been ``fuel dipped.''
   A number of seals were seen to be covered with oil and were
acting in a ``lethargic fashion,'' said the scientist.
   The precise number of animals killed by the oil is difficult to
calculate because other animals quickly eat the dead. ``It's pretty
depressing,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890323-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-89 1817EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AntarcticaSpill     03-23 0618</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Antarctica Spill,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Argentine Navy Ends Oil Spill Cleanup Efforts, Claims No Damage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deteriorating weather has forced the Argentine
navy to halt efforts to clean up a fuel oil spill from a ship that
went aground <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE> near an American Antarctic research station.
   A statement released <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Embassy</ORGANIZATION> said that
five Argentine naval ships that had been participating in
contamination control work were being withdrawn ``due to glacier and
meteorological conditions.''
   The statement said that oil spilled from the Argentine supply
ship <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> has been removed from the sea surface and that
all ``potential pollutants'' have been removed from the wrecked ship.
   American experts, however, say about 50,000 gallons of fuel oil
are still aboard the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman <PERSON>Jack Talmadge</PERSON> said that ``there has never been ship with
oil in it that withstood an <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> winter.''
   ``We're concerned about what might happen over the <DATE>winter</DATE>,'' he
said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bahia Paraiso</ORGANIZATION> lodged on rocks on <LOCATION>DeLaca Island</LOCATION> near the
<PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> station and dumped about 170,000 gallons of diesel and jet
fuel into the pristine waters nearby. An American research camp
called <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> is 1.1 miles away.
   Experts from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> stopped further
leaks from the vessel and cleaned up much of the oil, but the
Argentine navy now is leaving the scene while tons of fuel remain in
the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> tanks.
   <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said the vessel could quite likely be susceptible to
shifting by the force of ice and tide through the winter.
   The approaching Antarctic winter will not halt American efforts,
<PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said, because the <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> icebreaker <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION> is able to
operate out of <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION> in virtually all seasons.
   The Argentine statement also claimed that ``no visible harm to
the local ecosystem was noticed, especially with respect to its
fauna.''
   But experts at the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which operates
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research program in the region, said that the spill of fuel
oil from the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> did cause some loss of wildlife in the
area near <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>, and that the eventual impact of the spill
may not be known for years.
   An extra team of American scientists went to <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>
earlier this month to conduct new studies on the effects of the fuel
oil spill. They are expected to return in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> scientists have been monitoring the effects of the spill
since the ship first went aground and have reported:
   _Among a population of 30,000 birds of at least eight species,
fewer than 30 are known to have died directly as a result of
ingesting the fuel oil. However, there is indirect evidence of other
losses.
   _Penguins returning to the sea after nesting were forced to swim
through oil-covered water. Some penguins now are apparently being
eaten at sea by giant petrels, a long-winged bird. ``This diet,
unusual for petrels, is evidence that the oil spill affected
penguins,'' an <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> statement says.
   _An entire generation of <LOCATION>South Polar</LOCATION> skuas died in one rookery
near <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>. The skua is a gull-like bird of prey. <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION>
experts said skua parents were apparently affected by the oil spill
and failed to protect their nestlings from other skuas and other
predatory birds. There are, however, many skua rookeries in the
<LOCATION>South Polar</LOCATION> region.
   _The loss most feared by scientists is that the area around
<LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>, which has been a science outpost for 20 years, may
no longer be suitable for study because of distortions caused by the
oil spill. ``The usefulness of ... Palmer Station for basic research
(of) the undisturbed Antarctic ecosystem is in question,'' an <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION>
statement said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890202-0179 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-89 1626EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-AntarcticSpill Bjt   02-02 0691</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Antarctic Spill, Bjt,0710</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. to Help Clean Up Oil Spill; Penguins Threatened</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> experts with 52 tons of cleanup gear
were bound for <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to tackle a fuel oil spill
that officials said threatened baby penguins about to take their
first swim.
   A giant <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> C-5 Galaxy cargo plane carrying the gear
and experts landed in <LOCATION>Punta Arenas</LOCATION>, on the straits of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the
official news agency <PERSON>Orbe</PERSON> reported.
   From there, the mission was to board the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
research ship bound for the spill, about 590 miles south of the <LOCATION>Cape
Horn</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Anton L. Inderbitzen</PERSON>, head of Antarctic staff for the
Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, said the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>
was to depart <DATE>Friday</DATE> and take about four days to reach the spill,
just off the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION> and about two miles from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
scientific base <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Our concern right now is primarily for the birds,'' he told
reporters at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s airport. ``All the young penguins are just
about at the age where they take their first swim.
   ``When these birds enter the water for the first time, it could
be the last time.''
   There were conflicting reports of the extent of the spill, which
occurred when an Argentine research and supply boat hit a rock
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and listed before sinking <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The 9,300-ton vessel, the <LOCATION>Paradise Bay</LOCATION>, was carrying 250,000
gallons of diesel fuel, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>.
   The boat was leaking fuel oil at an undetermined rate, and
hundreds of drums of oil and canisters of compressed gas had slipped
from its decks, the foundation said.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Ministry of Defense</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
``there really wasn't a (significant) spill.''
   A short communique issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Argentine navy</ORGANIZATION> said its planes
will fly over the sunken vessel ``to make a visual evaulation of the
damage and take photographs that allow us to decide the best means
to employ to combat the effects that could be presented.''
   Also, an icebreaker was to arrive at the scene <DATE>Friday</DATE> to ``assess
the best ways available to combat the pollution,'' the communique
said.
   Some environmental experts and scientific groups have said
hundreds of gallons of fuel oil leaked from the ship and created a
slick up to 16 miles long, but the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean navy</ORGANIZATION> said the reports
appeared exaggerated.
   ``The information that we have is that there is no big spill,''
said <ORGANIZATION>navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Lt. <PERSON>Juan Pablo Barros</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Jack Renirie</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said, however, that
a slick did exist and that personnel at <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION> were
gathering drums of fuel oil and tanks of compressed gas from around
the grounded ship.
   ``The latest we have now is that there's probably 150 to 200
barrels in the water'' that slipped from the vessel's deck, <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON>
said in a telephone interview from <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. ``And there's still oil
coming out of the ship.''
   Inderbitzen said the <ORGANIZATION>Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which organized the
cleanup mission and directs all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> activities in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>,
feared lasting environmental damage.
   Some dead penguins had already been sighted, and the slick had
caused isolated schools of krill, a shrimp-like animal, to surface,
<PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said.
   Inderbitzen said <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s delicate, unspoiled environment
requires special measures to contain the spill, which is near two
areas set aside for special scientific study under terms of the
<ORGANIZATION>Antarctic Treaty</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``In warm weather it's easier for plants and even animals to
recover from an accident,'' he said. ``But in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, it takes
plants and animals many, many years to recover because of the cold.
It's a very, very fragile environment.''
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cargo plane, which is twice the size of a <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747,
carries a 35-foot ``skimming boat'' for scooping up spilled oil and
pumping it into floating tanks, and a small tugboat and inflatable
booms to contain drifting oil.
   The cleanup work will be peformed by <ORGANIZATION>Marine Pollution Control
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, under contract to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Chilean navy</ORGANIZATION> said it will provide logistical support and
dispatch its own ship with scientists and equipment to assist ``in
case any contamination exists.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890216-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-16-89 2104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Antarctic-Damage     02-16 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Antarctic-Damage,0608</SECOND>
<HEAD>Environmental Damage From Sunken Ship Less Than Feared</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ED McCULLOUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Damage to the pristine Antarctic
environment from an Argentine ship that ran aground and leaked oil
appears to be less than initially feared, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientist reported
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> .
   ``There were not thousands of birds killed. What we saw was the
death of a few birds and there may be more,'' said <PERSON>Ted DeLaca</PERSON>, chief
of the <ORGANIZATION>Division of Polar Programs</ORGANIZATION> of the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National
Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Some said this was an eco-catastrophe of biblical proportions.
That clearly is not true. Others said it was nothing. That's not
true, either. The truth is somewhere in between.''
   Many krill, a small, shrimplike crustacean that is the main food
for whalebone whales, washed up on islands after the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>
ran aground on <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE> and began leaking fuel oil.
   The Argentine navy oceanographic vessel had been chartered for a
tourist excursion.
   The accident took place near the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> polar research station
<PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> on the Antarctic peninsula, 600 miles below the tip of <LOCATION>South
America</LOCATION>. DeLaca was on the scene and helped organize the transfer of
tourists from ship to land by motorized rubber boats.
   The partially submerged ship was carrying an estimated 800 tons
of diesel oil, butane, compressed gas and other fuel, which
immediately began to leak. How much leaked and how much will be
recovered was not known, <PERSON>DeLaca</PERSON> said.
   He said some penguins and cormorants died after ingesting oil or
getting it on themselves, and thousands of limpets, a small, marine
animal, also died.
   However, navy experts from <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and scientists
aboard the foundation vessel Polar Duke quickly recovered floating
fuel canisters, patched the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>'s hull, stopped the leak
and contained the spill and now are cleaning it up.
   ``For the most part, the stuff that went into the water seems to
have dispersed and gone away,'' DeLaca, a bearded, 45-year-old
marine microbiologist, said in an interview.
   The concern now is what possible long-term effects the spill may
have on animal and plant life and on research such as that conducted
at Palmer since <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   ``The Antarctic is a hostile, unforgiving environment,'' <PERSON>DeLaca</PERSON>
said. ``The organisms that live there are specially adapted. The
margins for survival are narrow. ... Anything that takes away an
edge, that compromises their fitness, could mean the difference
between life and death.''
   He said ingesting oil may affect the penguins' capacity to store
oxygen and thus their ability to dive deep for food. Oil on the
feathers of skuas, a large predator bird related to the seagull,
could affect their ability to float or stay warm.
   Lack of limpets and krill near a nesting may affect breeding
patterns and the ability of young creatures to survive, he said.
   He said researchers also will wonder now whether the results they
obtain are valid, or a reflection of the oil spill.
   ``This is the first significant spill in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>DeLaca</PERSON>
said. ``It was a pristine environment and experimental results were
taken as accurate indicators of the Antarctic environment. This
spill could call into question future results.''
   A team of scientists from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>
will arrive at <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION> next month to collect data before
<DATE>winter</DATE> sets in.
   ``When next <DATE>spring</DATE> comes is when the story will be told'' about
the damage caused by the spill, <ORGANIZATION>DeLaca</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``The environment will recover. No question about that. The
question is, is what comes back what was there before.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890207-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-07-89 1638EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-AntarcticSpill     02-07 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Antarctic Spill,0487</SECOND>
<HEAD>Frogmen Start Cleaning Spill; Try to Seal Ship's Tanks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chilean navy frogmen plunged into icy
Antarctic waters <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to seal shut the fuel tanks of a crippled
ship and stop the spread of an oil slick threatening the pristine
area's wildlife, authorities said.
   A navy communique said the cutter <PERSON>Yelcho</PERSON> arrived <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
the first cleanup vessel to get to the spill site 590 miles from the
tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and close to the shores of the <LOCATION>Antarctic
Peninsula</LOCATION>.
   Crew members <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> morning encircled the nearly sunken vessel
Bahia Paraiso (<ORGANIZATION>Paradise Bay</ORGANIZATION>) with floating booms designed to contain
any further oil leak, according to the communique read by a
spokesman at <ORGANIZATION>navy</ORGANIZATION> headquarters in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>.
   Divers then entered the frigid waters to seal shut the <LOCATION>Bahia
Paraiso</LOCATION>'s tanks, it said.
   The Argentine research and supply ship grounded on shoals <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE>
about two miles from <LOCATION>Palmer Station U.S.</LOCATION> research base. Scientists
say the area teams with wildlife, including thousands of penguins.
   The ship holds about 800 tons of fuel, including diesel oil in
bulk and aviation fuel in steel drums. Officials of the
Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> say oil is leaking
slowly from the ship, which gradually sank in the shallow waters.
Only a section of its superstructure remains above the surface.
   They say a slick nearly 500 feet wide and two miles long is
trailing away from the vessel toward the south, threatening the
frozen continent's fragile and unspoiled environment.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research vessel, the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>, was expected to arrive at
the spill later <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. It carries a multimillion-dollar cleanup
mission organized by the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> that includes
military and civilian experts and 52 tons of sophisticated equipment.
   Both the <PERSON>Yelcho</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION> left <DATE>Friday</DATE> from the Chilean
port of <ORGANIZATION>Punta Arenas</ORGANIZATION>, a major supply point for Antarctic operations.
   Two Argentine vessels are in the area of the spill and plan to
help, according to the Chilean navy. However, they await equipment
being flown from <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, to a Chilean-run Antarctic
base 200 miles from the accident.
   An <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Embassy</ORGANIZATION> official in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> told reporters <DATE>Monday</DATE>
the government would try to salvage the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> once the
environmental threat is stemmed.
   A research vessel of the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean Antarctic Institute</ORGANIZATION> also is at
the spill site to evaluate environmental damage, said the insitute's
acting director, <PERSON>Antonio Massei</PERSON>.
   In a telephone interview in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, he said the area around the
accident is home to 29,000 penguins. Scientists say many baby
penguins soon will take their first swim in the waters, and they are
worried they could suffocate in the oil.
   Other wildlife also is threatened, including Antartic gulls and
terns, and krill, a tiny shrimp-like crustacean considered a vital
link in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s food chain.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890203-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-03-89 0348EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Antarctica Bjt   02-03 0662</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctica, Bjt,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. To Help Clean Oil Spill That Threatens Delicate Ecosystem</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> experts were en route today to
<LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> to clean an oil spill that threatens the delicate
ecosystem, but an environmentalist said only a few weeks remain
before the area's frigid waters begin to freeze.
   A giant C-5 cargo plane flew the crew and 52 tons of cleanup gear
to the southern port of <ORGANIZATION>Punta Arenas</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The crew was to
board on a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research ship departing today for the spill, about
590 miles south of the <LOCATION>Cape Horn</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Anton Inderbitzen</PERSON>, head of Antarctic staff for the
Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, said the vessel <ORGANIZATION>Polar
Duke</ORGANIZATION> would take about four days to reach the spill, just off the
<LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION> and about two miles from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientific
base <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>.
   However, a <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> spokesman cautioned that less than two
months remain to contain the damage.
   ``They can't hang around too long,'' said <PERSON>Peter Wilkinson</PERSON> from
the <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> ship <LOCATION>Gondwana</LOCATION> in Antarctic waters. ``By mid- to
late-April the ice will start to freeze over.''
   ``Any ship that's underwater in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> with that amount of
fuel poses a big problem,'' he said in a radio telephone interview
to <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   The environmental group is calling for an international effort to
contain damage caused by the sinking <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> of an Argentine navy
carrying 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel.
   In a stop in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, Inderbitzen told reporters the
crew would focus efforts on saving baby penguins in the polluted
area.
   ``All the young penguins are just about at the age where they
take their first swim,'' he said. ``When these birds enter the water
for the first time, it could be the last time.''
   The 9,300-ton <LOCATION>Paradise Bay</LOCATION> was leaking fuel oil at an
undetermined rate, and hundreds of drums of oil and canisters of
compressed gas had slipped from its decks, the foundation said.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Ministry of Defense</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
``There really wasn't a (significant) spill.''
   An Argentine navy statement said an icebreaker was to arrive at
the scene today to ``assess the best ways available to combat the
pollution.''
   Some environmental experts and scientific groups have said
hundreds of gallons of fuel leaked from the ship and created a slick
up to 16 miles long, but the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean navy</ORGANIZATION> said the reports appeared
exaggerated.
   ``The information that we have is that there is no big spill,''
said a navy snnel at <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION> were
gathering drums of fuel oil and tanks of compressed gas from around
the grounded ship.
   ``The latest we have now is that there's probably 150 to 200
barrels in the water,'' <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said in a telephone interview from
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. ``And there's still oil coming out of the ship.''
   Inderbitzen said the <ORGANIZATION>Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which organized the
cleanup mission and directs all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> activities in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>,
feared lasting environmental damage.
   Some dead penguins had already been sighted, and the slick had
caused isolated schools of krill, a shrimp-like animal, to surface,
<PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said.
   Inderbitzen said <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s unspoiled environment requires
special measures to contain the spill, which is near two areas set
aside for scientific study under terms of the <ORGANIZATION>Antarctic Treaty</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``In warm weather it's easier for plants and even animals to
recover from an accident,'' he said. ``But in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, it takes
plants and animals many, many years to recover because of the cold.
It's a very, very fragile environment.''
   The crew has a 35-foot ``skimming boat'' for scooping up spilled
oil and pumping it into floating tanks, and a small tugboat and
inflatable booms to contain drifting oil.
   The cleanup work will be peformed by <ORGANIZATION>Marine Pollution Control
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, under contract to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020389-0037 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 13551 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 3, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 8; Column 4; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
656 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BID TO CONTAIN ANTARCTIC OIL SPILL STALLED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, Times Science Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Foul weather off the tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> forced one Argentine ship 
to abandon its effort to reach a stricken vessel that is leaking oil into the 
pristine waters off <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, and scientists warned that as winter approaches 
in the <LOCATION>Southern Hemisphere</LOCATION>, storms could soon cut off any hopes of salvaging 
the ship and containing the spill. 
</P>
<P>
"If they don't solve it right away, the winter storms will tear it up," said 
<ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> marine biologist <PERSON>Bill Hamner</PERSON>, who has spent five seasons studying the area 
where the ship ran around <DATE>last Saturday</DATE> just two miles from the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>. A second Argentine vessel should arrive in 
the area <DATE>today</DATE>, but it is not clear if that ship is equipped to attempt salvage 
operations. 
</P>
<P>
The foundation said that the stricken ship was still afloat despite earlier 
reports that it had sunk. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hamner</PERSON> and others said the accident could not have happened at a worse time for 
the wildlife in the area, particularly the penguins. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Birds' Insulation in Peril 
</P>
<P>
One of <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s largest penguin colonies is in the area, <PERSON>Hamner</PERSON> said, "and 
this is the time when the penguins are fishing most heavily" and young penguins 
are beginning to swim. 
</P>
<P>
That will expose them to the oily water and tar that could destroy the 
insulation system that protects them from the cold temperatures. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hamner</PERSON> said the penguin's feathers trap a layer of air between "the skin and 
the outside, so the birds can swim in ice water, and they are not cold because 
they are beautifully insulated. It probably wouldn't require very much tar to 
break down the insulation and bring cold into direct contact with the body 
core." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Anton L. Inderbitzen</PERSON>, head of the Antarctic staff for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science 
Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, told reporters in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, that the greatest concern now is 
that the oil will affect the young birds. 
</P>
<P>
"All the young penguins are just about at the age where they take their first 
swim," he said. "When these birds enter the water for the first time, it could 
be the last time." 
</P>
<P>
There were conflicting reports <DATE>Thursday</DATE> over just how much oil has already 
leaked from the vessel, which is <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> under water but still afloat, according to 
<PERSON>Jack Renirie</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Argentine Ministry of Defense</ORGANIZATION> initially said the leakage from the Argentine 
cruise ship, the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>, "really wasn't a significant spill" but later 
conceded some contamination is inevitable. 
</P>
<P>
Observers in the area radioed to officials in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> that a spill several 
miles long had been sighted. 
</P>
<P>
Any spill in such a pristine area is bound to have a serious local impact, 
although <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said the incident was not likely to be as "catastrophic" as 
some reports have indicated. 
</P>
<P>
"This was not a tanker," <PERSON>Renirie</PERSON> said. The ship was carrying about 250,000 
gallons of bunker oil used for its own propulsion system, plus 200 barrels of 
other types of fuel. 
</P>
<P>
By contrast, large tankers carry many millions of gallons of oil and are 
capable of creating massive oil slicks during accidents. 
</P>
<P>
The temperature in the area is running in the mid-40s, because it is still 
<DATE>summer</DATE> in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, but winter is rapidly approaching. Heavy storms could hit 
the area by the end of this month, and by late <DATE>March</DATE> the weather is expected to 
be so foul that little could be done. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Killed Every Animal 
</P>
<P>
When the tanker <LOCATION>Tampico</LOCATION> ran aground near <LOCATION>Ensenada</LOCATION> in <DATE>April, 1957</DATE>, it released 
diesel fuel into the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> said it proved extremely toxic to 
marine life. 
</P>
<P>
"It essentially killed every animal in the area," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> experts with 52 tons of cleanup gear arrived in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> aboard a 
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> C-5B. From there the experts and their equipment were to be 
loaded aboard the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research ship Polar Duke for the 600-mile, four-day trip 
to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
All 316 persons aboard the 435-foot Bahia Paraiso were rescued by other vessels 
in the area. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
OIL SPILLS; WATER POLLUTION -- ANTARCTICA; SHIP ACCIDENTS -- ANTARCTICA; 
WILDLIFE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890201-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-01-89 0207EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-US-AntarcticRescue 3rdLd-Writethru a0435 02-01 0500</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Antarctic Rescue, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0435,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Argentine Ship Sinks Off Antarctica</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: REORGANIZES throughout</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BUENOS AIRES, Argentina (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Argentine supply ship that ran
aground off <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> sank <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in heavy seas and high winds,
the government said, and there was concern oil in its hold could
leak and damage the environment.
   The sinking of the 400-foot <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> followed warnings from
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> that the unspoiled Antarctic
could face ecological disaster if the 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel
aboard the ship were to spill.
   No injuries were reported in the sinking. Tourists aboard and the
crew had been evacuated from the vessel, which was 600 miles south
of <LOCATION>Cape Horn</LOCATION>, the tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>. Salvage efforts had been
hampered by 50 mph winds.
   The double-hulled oceanographic ship sank at about <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME>, the
government news agency <ORGANIZATION>Telam</ORGANIZATION> said, citing a navy communique. Telam
did not say whether the ship broke up or if diesel oil spilled when
it went down.
   The depth of the water in which the ship sank was not immediately
known.
   The ship had been carrying supplies including jet fuel, gasoline
and canisters of compressed gases to the Argentine Esperanza station
near the tip of the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement released in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   The ship ran aground <DATE>Saturday</DATE> about two miles from <LOCATION>Palmer
Station</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research facility on the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>, the
continent's tip. It sustained a 35-foot-long gash in its hull, and
some of the 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel began leaking, washing
ashore near <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> station.
   The fuel killed some krill, a tiny shrimp-like creature that is a
vital part of the Antarctic food chain, and has affected penguins,
sea gulls and giant petrel birds, the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>
statement said.
   There were no immediate details about the extent of damage to the
wildlife in the pristine surroundings.
   Agency spokesman <PERSON>Jack Renerie</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> before the ship sank
that the leak, which was threatening penguins and other wildlife,
had stopped.
   ``Scientists are concerned that some research search projects may
already have been affected by the leak,'' a foundation statement
said. It said two Argentine salvage vessels were expected to arrive
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> or <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Before the sinking, Argentine officials had discounted a spill.
   Telam quoted <ORGANIZATION>Argentine navy</ORGANIZATION> sources as saying: ``The fuel it
carried, both for itself and the Antarctic stations, was in steel
drums so a spill is practically impossible.''
   The 316 people aboard the ship when it ran aground, including 82
taken to <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>.
   The passengers and most of the crew were taken by cruise ship to
the <LOCATION>South Shetland Islands</LOCATION>, from which they were airlifted to the
South American mainland <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. But 104 crewmen remain at the
station, said Renerie.
   Because the station is equipped for only 40 people, food has been
rationed to two meals a day, a <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> statement
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920131-0014
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920131-0014.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Penguin USA Names
   Two to Top Positions
   At Principal Divisions
</HL>
<DATE>
01/31/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B8
</SO>
<CO>
   U.PSO WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
PUBLISHING, INFORMATION SERVICES COMPANIES (PUB)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Pearson PLC's Penguin USA named two executives
to the top editorial posts at its principal hardcover and
paperback divisions.
   Al Silverman, a vice president and contributing editor of
Penguin USA, was named publisher and editor in chief of the
Viking division, which publishes hardcovers. Mr. Silverman,
65 years old, was chairman and chief executive officer of
Time Warner Inc.'s Book of the Month Club before joining
Penguin in 1989.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Silverman</PERSON> succeeds <PERSON>Christine Pevitt</PERSON>, who resigned in
<DATE>June</DATE>. <PERSON>Ms. Pevitt</PERSON> presided over both the hardcover and
paperback divisions, but those duties have now been split.
   <PERSON>Kathryn Court</PERSON>, 43, was named publisher and editor in chief
of Penguin Books, the paperback division. Ms. Court had been
editorial director of Penguin.
   Literary agents and other publishers applauded the
appointments, saying both <PERSON>Mr. Silverman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ms. Court</PERSON> are
known as skilled editors and "book lovers," unlike some
recent management hires in publishing, whose experience was
more financial than literary.
   Also, <ORGANIZATION>Penguin USA</ORGANIZATION> named <PERSON>Arnold Dolin</PERSON>, 63, to the new post
of publisher and editor in chief of Plume Books, the
paperback line in the NAL/Dutton division. <PERSON>Mr. Dolin</PERSON>
continues to serve as associate publisher of NAL/Dutton.
   The appointments follow a period of turbulence at <ORGANIZATION>Penguin
USA</ORGANIZATION>. After a drop in profit in <DATE>1990</DATE>, the publisher shuffled
executives, streamlined its back-office operations, abolished
about 20 jobs and cut back its list of titles by more than
<PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>.
   <PERSON>John F. Moore</PERSON>, recently named president of <ORGANIZATION>Penguin USA</ORGANIZATION>,
said the company's performance has improved considerably. He
said <ORGANIZATION>Penguin USA</ORGANIZATION> had "the best <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE> in the
company's history."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910628-0111
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910628-0111.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing &amp; Media:
   Publisher, Editor
   At Penguin USA's
   Viking Unit Quit
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
06/28/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   U.PSO WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Penguin USA, a publisher that has suffered
declining profits and management turmoil, announced the
departure of the head of its Viking hardcover division along
with a top editor there.
   Christine Pevitt, publisher of the Viking Penguin division
of Penguin USA, whose parent is London-based Pearson PLC,
left "to pursue other interests," the company said. Penguin
insiders cited conflicts between Ms. Pevitt and her two
superiors, Michael Jacobs, Viking Penguin president, and
Peter Mayer, chairman of Penguin USA.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ms. Pevitt</PERSON>, who had been with the publisher about four
years and took on the top job at Viking about <DATE>18 months ago</DATE>,
couldn't be reached for comment.
   Also departing is senior executive editor <PERSON>Amanda Vaill</PERSON>, 42
years old, a 14-year veteran who has edited such authors as
<ORGANIZATION>Taylor Branch</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Iris Murdoch</PERSON> and <PERSON>T.C. Boyle</PERSON>. Replacements
weren't named for either post.
   In <DATE>1990</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Penguin</ORGANIZATION> reported a <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> drop in world-wide profit.
Like most publishers of trade (general-interest) books,
Penguin's sales have slumped in the recession. In recent
years it also has suffered severe distribution problems, a
rash of complaints from authors about royalty statements, and
problems resulting from the <DATE>1989</DATE> merger of NAL/Dutton, which
included editorial cutbacks.
   Along the way, <ORGANIZATION>Penguin USA</ORGANIZATION> has fired or lost a number of
top managers who still haven't been replaced, including
<PERSON>Morton Mint</PERSON>, who quit as chief executive officer <DATE>last August</DATE>
after 10 months in the job. <PERSON>Marvin Brown</PERSON>, chief
administrative officer, was put in as a replacement "for the
time being," but still serves in that capacity. After two
years, the top editorial post at the Penguin paperback
division still hasn't been filled.
   <PERSON>Mr. Jacobs</PERSON>, who has been president of Viking Penguin for
about a year, called the latest departures "strictly some
personnel moves that are necessary," rather than a plan to
reduce staff levels. He added that "both Viking and Penguin
distinctly need someone to lead them, and I'm looking for
strong editorial leaders. I think this is a great house, but
we can publish books better."
   The publisher will be cutting the number of titles it
publishes by <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> in both hardcover and paperback, said
<PERSON>Mr. Jacobs</PERSON>. Viking publishes about 150 hardcover titles a
year; <ORGANIZATION>Penguin</ORGANIZATION> publishes about 250 paperback titles.
   Referring to perceptions in the publishing industry that
<PERSON>Viking Penguin</PERSON> has been in turmoil and trouble for several
years, <PERSON>Mr. Jacobs</PERSON> said: "I'm tired of hearing about it.
Changing perceptions isn't easy, but the perception of this
house needs to be strengthened. Some people still think we
have distribution problems, for one thing, and they were
solved 18 months ago."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890202-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-89 1022EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Antarctica-Spill 2ndLd-Writethru a0494 02-02 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctica-Spill, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0494,0683</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Team Flies To Battle Huge Antarctic Oil Spill</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to UPDATE with efforts to collect barrels
and tanks, Chilean navy saying spill not serious. Picks up 10th graf pvs,
``The water...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> plane carrying tons of
equipment and a team of clean-up experts headed to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> today
to fight an oil spill that some scientists say could pose a major
environmental threat.
   The huge C-5 plane was bound for the southern city of <LOCATION>Punta
Arenas</LOCATION>, where its cargo and the 15-member team will be transferred
to a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research vessel, the <ORGANIZATION>Polar Duke</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> said.
   In the Antarctic, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientists were trying to catch floating
oil barrels and propane containers near the spill, which was four
miles in diameter and moving to the southwest, the <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The agency said in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> the Argentine supply vessel that
released the oil after it ran aground and sank was carrying 250,000
gallons of diesel fuel. It said an ``incurable disaster'' would
result if all the fuel leaks into the region's unspoiled waters.
   In <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>Argentine navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the spill would
not pose a serious ecological threat.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean navy</ORGANIZATION> agreed. ``The information that
we have is that there is no big spill,'' said Lt. <PERSON>Juan Pablo Barros</PERSON>
in a telephone interview today.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bahia Paraiso</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Paradise Bay</ORGANIZATION>) ran aground on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the
<LOCATION>Bismarck Strait</LOCATION>, 600 miles south of the southern tip of <LOCATION>South
America</LOCATION> and 1{ miles from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Palmer Research Station</ORGANIZATION> on the
<LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>. The ship was carrying supplies for Antarctic
outposts and sightseers.
   All 250 passengers and crew were rescued, but the ship floated
free in heavy seas and sank <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, dropping barrels of oil and
several hundred propane gas containers into the water, said <PERSON>Jack
Talmadge</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>.
   Another foundation spokesman in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jack Renerie</PERSON>, said
most of the oil was in steel drums so the ecological threat may not
be great. However, ``There's a bunch of free (drifting) oil down
there,'' he said. ``The slick has arrived at Palmer Station,'' a
scientific outpost run by the foundation.
   Renerie said personnel at the station had collected some steel
barrels of fuel oil and tanks of compressed gas near the ship.
   ``The latest we have now is that there's probably 150 to 200
barrels (still) in the water,'' <PERSON>Renerie</PERSON> said in a telephone
interview today from <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. ``And there's still oil coming out of
the ship.''
   He said the ship is about ``80 to <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> underwater'' but
appears to have settled firmly on a shoal.
   ``The water surrounding the ship is covered with a couple of
centimeters (about an inch) of oil. There is a sheen of oil in a
much wider area around the ship, including evidence of oil on the
coastline of the several islands there,'' <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said.
   ``Wildlife has already begun to be affected,'' including krill,
the small crustaceans that form the basis of the Antarctic food
chain, <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said.
   ``Birds which have eaten the krill are showing behavior
differences,'' he said. ``One dead penguin had been found as of a
few hours ago.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> transport left <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and was
to arrive in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> today. <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said its crew and 52 tons of
cargo would reach the accident site by <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The cargo includes a 35-foot ``skimming boat'' for scooping up
spilled oil and pumping it into floating tanks; a small tugboat;
inflatable booms to contain the spill, and a special truck for
loading and unloading the equipment, said Renerie. He said it was
accompanied by a crew from two private <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> clean-up companies,
<ORGANIZATION>Marine Pollution Control and Global Associates</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> is organizing the clean-up
mission with assistance from the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890320-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-20-89 1510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Antarctica-Impact Adv26   03-20 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Antarctica-Impact, Adv 26,0365</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, March 26, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>AP SPOTLIGHT: Antarctica _ Shipwreck Revises U.S. Mission</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: One of a four-story package. With b0729-b0730.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PALMER STATION, Antarctica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For two decades scientists
enjoyed a cloistered existence at this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research center,
studying wildlife in conditions as unspoiled as anywhere in the
world.
   No longer.
   The mission of <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>, perched on a gravelly point
beneath a towering glacier, changed overnight when the Argentine
supply ship <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> ran aground <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE> and spilled its cargo
of diesel fuel just offshore.
   ``This is changing from a place where people studied untouched
nature long-term to a place where people study the effects of an oil
spill long-term,'' said <PERSON>Margaret Rubega</PERSON>, an ornithologist from <ORGANIZATION>The
University of California-Irvine</ORGANIZATION>. She was studying skuas and kelp
gulls at the station when the wreck occurred.
   ``As an ecosystem that was basically undisturbed, it's a horrible
loss. Really it's tragic,'' <PERSON>Miss Rubega</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>William Fraser</PERSON>, an ornithologist from the Point Reyes (<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>)
Bird Observatory, said there already are indications of some
poisoning of penguins, skuas, cormorants and other bird species that
populate the rocky islands around the spill.
   ``We have no direct evidence of heavy mortality, but we have
indirect evidence,'' he said.
   Scavanging giant petrels who live on the rocky islands around the
base were feeding their newborn chicks an unusually rich diet of
penguin meat after the spill, <PERSON>Fraser</PERSON> said.
   ``What this means is you had large numbers of penguins dying
locally.''
   In addition, 726 pairs of polar skuas were nesting in the area
when the spill occurred.
   ``Every single one lost their chicks,'' <PERSON>Frazer</PERSON> said.
   He stressed that the evidence was not conclusive. A team of 15
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientists has just begun more comprehensive studies.
   Ironically, the site offers an excellent base of information for
a before-and-after examination of a spill. The wealth of data on
bird and marine life collected since the station went into operation
can be used for comparison, <PERSON>Fraser</PERSON> said.
   ``It's a terrible disaster, but it's an incredible natural
experiment.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, March 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890131-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-31-89 2038EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w US-AntarcticRescue 1stld-writethru a0743 01-31 0454</FIRST>
<SECOND>US-Antarctic Rescue, 1st ld-writethru, a0743,470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: To update with Argentine report, adds 2 grafs after 4th graf
previous ``Two Argentine''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An Argentine ship which ran aground off the
<LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION> has floated free, and a leak of diesel fuel that
was threatening penguins and other wildlife has stopped, <ORGANIZATION>National
Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jack Renerie</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   But the ship, from which all passengers and crew members have
been evacuated, is in danger of sinking.
   Renerie said the vessel is taking on water, is down at the stern
where water is up to the first deck, and is heeled over 25 degrees.
   Two Argentine vessels were headed to the vessel to try to pump
the remaining fuel from the ship and salvage it if possible, but it
remained in danger of sinking and had drifted against a nearby
island, he said.
   In <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, the government news agency <ORGANIZATION>Telam</ORGANIZATION> reported that the
ship, the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>, would probably be towed to <PERSON>Rio Gallegos</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> to be repaired.
   Telam quoted <ORGANIZATION>Argentine navy</ORGANIZATION> sources as saying: ``The fuel it
carried, both for itself and the Antarctic stations, was in steel
drums so a spill is practically impossible.''
   The ship, a 400-foot-long double-hulled vessel, ran aground
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> about two miles from <LOCATION>Palmer Station</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research
facility which is located about 600 miles south of <LOCATION>Cape Horn</LOCATION>, the
tip of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   The 316 people aboard, including 82 passengers and 234 crew
members, were rescued by power boats and taken to <ORGANIZATION>Palmer Station</ORGANIZATION>.
The passengers and most of the crew were taken by cruise ship to the
<LOCATION>South Shetland Islands</LOCATION>, from which they were airlifted to the South
American mainland <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. But 104 crewmen remain at the station,
said Renerie.
   Because the station is equipped for only 40 people, food has been
rationed to two meals a day, said a <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> statement.
   The crewmen will remain until the two Argentine salvage vessels
are expected arrive <DATE>Thursday</DATE> or <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the statement said.
   The ship sustained a 35-foot-long gash in its hull, and some of
the 250,000 gallons of diesel fuel began leaking, washing ashore
near <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> station.
   The fuel killed some krill, a tiny shrimp-like creature that is a
vital part of the Antarctic food chain, and has affected penguins,
sea gulls and giant petrel birds, the statement said.
   There were no immediate details about the extent of damage to the
wildlife in the pristine surroundings.
   ``Scientists are concerned that some research search projects may
already have been affected by the leak,'' the <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> statement said.
   The ship was carrying supplies including jet fuel, gasoline and
canisters of compressed gases to the Argentine Esperanza station
near the tip of the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>, it said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890320-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-20-89 1509EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Antarctica Adv26-1stAdd   03-20 0699</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Antarctica, Adv 26-1st Add,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv26</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, March 26, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>PALMER STATION: maritime disaster.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   And station workers said only fair weather prevented a disaster.
They said most of the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION>'s lifeboats were open,
inflatable rafts without oars or motors. The day was calm and they
could be towed ashore by station workboats without difficulty. But
they could have overturned or been blown out to sea if the volatile
Antarctic weather had taken a turn for the worse, the workers said.
   In response to the diesel spill, the <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>
dispatched navy and civilian pollution control experts with 52 tons
of specialized equipment. The mission cost more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>. The
Chilean and Argentine navies also sent costly clean-up missions.
   The clean-up ended in mid-March, although the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> still
holds about 63,000 gallons that can't be safely reached and pumped
out. It could spill if the ship breaks up in a winter storm or
simply seep out for many months as the wreck gradually
disintegrates. Experts say it would be too costly to haul the wreck
away.
   The area of the spill teems with wildlife, including penguins,
skuas, cormorants, Arctic terns and other birds. Seals and whales
frequently pass through the bay.
   Scientists say there already exists indirect evidence that many
penguins and other birds were poisoned by the spill, but they have
been unable to determine the extent of the damage. A special team of
15 researchers from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has
arrived to begin a comprehensive study on the spill's environmental
impact. It will take years to complete.
   Yet there is no way a claim for damages can be made. Since the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has no property rights to the area at or around <LOCATION>Palmer
Station</LOCATION>, it has no legal grounds for seeking compensation. The area
of the accident, on the <LOCATION>Antarctic Peninsula</LOCATION>, is claimed by <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>.
   Chile recently announced plans to propose, at the next <ORGANIZATION>Antarctic
Treaty</ORGANIZATION> meeting in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>October</DATE>, an article to hold each country
financially responsible for environmental or other damage. The
<ORGANIZATION>Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> plans to press for agreement on cost sharing in
clean-up of spills and other accidents, and for formation of an
international coordinating office for emergencies.
   But there could be some opposition.
   ``We must act with prudence, without falling into decisions that
could be a little hasty,'' said <PERSON>Roberto Daverede</PERSON>, head of Antarctic
affairs for the <ORGANIZATION>Argentine Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> claims a thick
wedge of the continent and, like the other claimant nations, rejects
any foreign or international jurisdiction.
   Daverede played down the effects of the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> spill.
   ``This is far from being a natural catastrophe,'' he said. He
called the wreck ``an isolated incident.''
   Nonetheless, less than a month after the <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> accident a
Peruvian research ship ran aground 300 miles away, near <LOCATION>King George
Island</LOCATION>. The vessel, called the Humboldt and touted as the flagship
of <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>'s territorial claim, also spilled some diesel fuel but was
soon refloated.
   By world standards neither accident would qualify as a major
environmental disaster.
   ``I've walked away from bigger diesel spills than this where
nothing died, absolutely nothing,'' said <PERSON>Jim O'Brien</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Gretna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>,
a pollution control expert hired by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government for the
<LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> clean-up.
   But there is special concern that <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s environment may be
especially fragile. There's also a growing belief that its huge cold
mass plays a key role in long-term global weather patterns.
   There also are some indications that the strain on the local
environment may be straining political relations.
   For decades, a unique spirit of international friendship and
cooperation has reigned in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>. Political conficts were left
at the doorstep, and missions from such idealogically distinct
countries as the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and right-wing <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> lived as
next-door neighbors, sharing supplies, equipment and a drink or two
on the cold nights.
   In early <DATE>March</DATE>, however, the Chileans criticized what they called
the poor waste handling at the Soviet Bellinghousen base, literally
a stone's from their own <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> base on <LOCATION>King George Island</LOCATION>. They said
they would file a complaint at the next treaty meeting.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, March 26</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900514-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-90 0024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AntarcticaTravel     05-14 0779</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Antarctica Travel,0805</SECOND>
<HEAD>Call Out For U.S. Regulation of Its Burgeoning Antarctica Tour
Industry</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM R. CORMIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour operators are planning to send a
record 4,000 or more travelers to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, prompting calls for
strict government regulation to protect penguins, other wildlife
and the very fate of the frozen continent.
   ``The number of tourists visiting <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> has more than
tripled in the past five years,'' said <PERSON>Bruce Manheim</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
activist of the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Defense Fund</ORGANIZATION> who calls existing
controls inadequate.
   <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> has become a ``hot'' travel destination for the
<DATE>1990s</DATE>, beckoning older Americans seeking more adventure than <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
and hoping to see a fragile frontierland visited by only a
privileged few in their youth.
   They are fueling fresh growth in the adventure travel industry,
an estimated <MONEY>$1.3 billion-a-year</MONEY> phenomenon.
   About 800 American tourists traveled to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>,
3,000 in <DATE>1989</DATE>, and tour operators expect at least 4,000 in the
<DATE>December-February summer</DATE> season. Manheim says it could reach 5,000.
   ``There's clearly a trend toward these type of expeditionary
visits to remote places in the world,'' said <PERSON>Manheim</PERSON>.
   He filed an appeal <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with the government urging more
regulation.
   ``We are not trying to prohibit tourists from going to
<LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, we just think tourism is something that has to be
regulated carefully,'' he said.
   Concern began mounting after the <DATE>January 1989</DATE> grounding of the
Argentine naval ship <LOCATION>Bahia Paraiso</LOCATION> in which an estimated 175,000
gallons leaked into marine habitats, killing seals, penguins and
other marine life. The vessel remains at the site off <LOCATION>Palmer
Station</LOCATION> with some oil in its tanks.
   Particularly worrisome to critics are the plans of <ORGANIZATION>Ocean Cruise
Lines</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION> to send the largest cruise ship in years
to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>, the 460-passenger <ORGANIZATION>Ocean Princess</ORGANIZATION>.
   Rates begin at <MONEY>$3,895</MONEY> per person for a double-occupancy cabin on
its three wine-and-caviar cruises, which are selling briskly. The
first round trip from <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, begins <DATE>Dec. 22</DATE>.
   Manheim's appeal is urging the government to place strict
controls on helicopter flights near wildlife sites, guidelines on
tourist observation of penguins and seals, and coordination of
cruise ship visits to breeding grounds.
   He said ships had made repeated tourist visits to the same
wildlife sites, disrupting the breeding of seals, penguins and
other birds.
   ``A year after <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>'s most significant environmental
disaster, we still don't have regulations to prevent similar
catastrophes,'' said <PERSON>Manheim</PERSON>.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government responds that effective regulations are
already in place.
   ``We have tried, and we believed we have dealt succesfully with
the explosion of <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> tourism,'' said <PERSON>Jack Talmadge</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which regulates <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> activities in
<LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Talmadge</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> has issued tourist regulations,
established a mechanism for assessing fines for violations and
taken steps to limit visits to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research stations.
   He said the tour operators are also cooperating with the <ORGANIZATION>NSF</ORGANIZATION> to
minimize the impact of tourism, including giving advance notice of
ship visits.
   Although 16 nations fly flags in <LOCATION>Antactica</LOCATION> and seven claim
slices of it, no nation holds title to the continent, which is
larger than the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> combined.
   Military flights and small ships carrying about 100 tourists
have been frequent modes of travel to <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> since the first
tourists visited in <DATE>1958</DATE>.
   Now, the Chilean government has opened a spartan hotel at its
<ORGANIZATION>Teniente Marsh Station on King George</ORGANIZATION> island, and <ORGANIZATION>LanChile</ORGANIZATION> airlines
began commercial flights to that Antarctic stop last year.
   Australian entrepreneurs have proposed a five-story hotel,
airstrip and hovercraft dock. The Canada-based Adventure Network
