<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880308-0144 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS: The Chimes at Kendall: Paul Matisse's Subway </HL>
<AUTHOR> David Stipp </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Cambridge, Mass.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For months beneath the streets of this college town, artist <PERSON>Paul Matisse</PERSON> and his audience have been communing about music, joy and mechanical engineering. 

   It began in <DATE>October</DATE> after he installed 16 massive chimes in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>'s recently renovated <LOCATION>Kendall Square</LOCATION> subway station. 
The piece, called "Pythagoras," was broken the day after its unveiling, and despite repairs and redesignings, it has been broken repeatedly since then. 
It isn't vandalism. 
<PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> just hadn't taken into account the urgency of the yearning to make euphony behind all those tired, poker faces on the subway. 

   Working on commission from the <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge Arts Council</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> specifically designed the piece so strap-hangers could make it ring. 
And ring it does, when you pull on one of two handles, which are really aluminum arms projecting from the walls of the inbound and outbound platforms and linked via overhead rods and levers to the chimes, which hang out of reach between the tracks. 
The chimes themselves are aluminum cylinders, four inches in diameter and as much as almost nine feet long. 
When rung, they make soul-satisfying tintinnabulations, like big gongs in a cave. 

   The handles are the weak links in this troglodyte's delight. 
Gently rocking them swings the hammers, which sway back and forth like the tongues of bells to strike the chimes. 
The handles look strong, but some commuters get carried away and throw themselves onto them like Rocky training for his last-chance match. 
The resulting breakdowns at first chagrined <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>, who is the grandson of the painter <PERSON>Henri Matisse</PERSON> and the stepson of artist <PERSON>Marcel Duchamp</PERSON>. 
This <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> got his training at <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> in design, he has dabbled in physics, engineering and architecture, and he takes pride in getting the details right. 
His specialty is precisely machined mobiles -- things of steel wheels and interlockings sweet enough to charm the socks off a mechanical engineer. 

   When he heard his chimes had broken, <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> headed for the station to set things right. 
Arriving from his home, which once was and still looks like a big, white Baptist church in <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, about an hour's drive away, the 55-year-old artist witnessed a subway rider "really putting his back into it and just working away with tremendous force" on the remaining unbroken handle. 
"There are people," he reflects like a traveler just back from a strange land, "who live in that world in which action is put over all the other stuff." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>'s dialogue with his audience began when he posted gently admonishing, apologetic notes next to the disabled handles. 
A typical one said: "This time it was an epoxied joint that gave in to someone's enthusiasm . . . 
Thanks for waiting." 

   The <LOCATION>Kendall Square</LOCATION> station is the stop for <ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION> and it is two stops from <LOCATION>Harvard</LOCATION>, which partly explains why many passers-by reacted to the notes like professors grading a pet student's paper. 
Instead of defacing <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>'s 8 1/2-by-11 sheets, they penned criticisms, praise, advice and all manner of marginalia on them. 

   As the chimes' ups and downs continued, <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>'s notes became a kind of spontaneous art forum. 
It continues, for though "Pythagoras" is working again, he still posts messages about progress on two other musical contraptions he is making for the station. 
He has collected an impressive sheaf of the annotated notes next to the personal computer he used to design the chimes' acoustics, which are based on the same blend of mathematics and music that fascinated Pythagoras, the ancient Greek inventor of a musical scale and the geometry theorem that bears his name. 

   The "Pythagoras" graffiti tell, sometimes eloquently, of an outburst of delight and surprise in a place of monotonous routine. 
"Heaven couldn't have better bells than this," wrote one passing critic. 
"Thanks for making me forget the horrors of this day," inscribed a harried soul. 
Another enchanted commuter confessed that he "felt like the Hunchback of <LOCATION>Notre Dame</LOCATION>" when ringing the chimes. 

   Many comments sound like excerpts from a standing ovation for an opera performed at the <ORGANIZATION>Tower of Babel</ORGANIZATION>. 
"Wunderbar," roared one passerby with his pen. 
"Magnifico," shouted another. 
At least one excited scribbling seems to be in <LOCATION>Sanskrit</LOCATION>. 

   A few of these underground music critics strive toward poetry, with such lyrical reactions as, "a tender use of metal" or the chimes "transform a subway pit to a subterranean cathedral." 

   The majority, however, seem to have come right out of the heart of <LOCATION>MIT</LOCATION>, whose plain buildings are identified by numbers rather than names. 
<PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>'s technical difficulties have fired the imaginations of the scientists and engineers passing through the station. 
"A viscous clutch might do the job," wrote one laconic observer. 
Another sketched a picture of a proposed solution, in which opposing pistons absorb excessive forces. 
One <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> insider offered the services of the school's mechanical engineers, who "would love to take this on as a project." 
The most succinct suggestion came from a self-described physicist, who simply jotted down an equation for the desired motion of the hammers. 

   Small debates soon broke out among the technical kibitzers. 
"The problem is with the length of the hammers; the rhythm needed to ring the long and short {ones} does not correspond," wrote one of them. 
But "that's what creates interesting rhythmic variations," countered a second. 
Try to "hit the natural frequency," advised a third. 

   When one petulant perfectionist advised <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> to take an introductory <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> class in mechanical design "coz it's obvious you don't know the first thing about it," someone else scribbled underneath, "<PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, Pay No Mind!! 
This guy is an ass." 

   Perhaps the ultimate testament to the chimes' success as mass-transit art are the comments from those who don't seem to be part of the academic crowd. 
"Groovy tunes, dude," inscribed one reviewer; "Like, dude, way kickin'," wrote another. 
In large, eloquent block letters, one of <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>'s favorite appreciators opined: "Radical move, dude." 

   Comments <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON>, "I'm very pleased that my work seems to be universally affecting. 
It isn't art in the usual sense. 
Art in the usual sense is a mystery at the moment. 
I love the immediately evident, rather than the more abstract, abstruse focusings." 

   For their part, the <PERSON>Kendall</PERSON> band, as <PERSON>Mr. Matisse</PERSON> calls those who ring his chimes, continue to dream up responses to his work that are more gratifying to him than normal art criticism. 
Recently, he experienced a kind of epiphany when finishing up some work in the station a little after <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME> (<PERSON>Mr. 
Matisse</PERSON> can work on his subway art pieces only in the <TIME>early morning</TIME>, when the trains aren't running.) 

   As he recalls it: "On the other side of the tracks, there were two ladies, who I think were coming home from all-night cleaning jobs. 
They sat down, and one of them looked over at me and gestured for me to play the chimes. 
They just wanted to hear them. 
So I played." 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Stipp</PERSON> is a reporter in the Journal's <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> bureau. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910522-0124
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910522-0124.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
   Beauty in Numbers: Pythagoras Revisited
   ----
   By Jim Holt
</HL>
<DATE>
05/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   In ancient times, the mathematical mystic Pythagoras
proclaimed that the world was made of numbers. While this
seems slightly mad to us today, I have heard of people in
Paris and New Haven, Conn., who subscribe to the equally
barmy belief that the world is made of words or "texts." In
any case, the Pythagoreans were the first to discover the
numerical basis of harmony in music, and hence the link
between mathematics and beauty. They also thought, historians
tell us, that it was sinful to eat beans.
   I do not know whether John Allen Paulos abstains from
beans, but, as a self-avowed "numbers man," he does seem to
be a bit of a neo-Pythagorean. Two years ago Mr. Paulos wrote
a surprise best seller called "Innumeracy" that was both a
lament for the inability of Americans to think about the
world mathematically and an entertaining attempt to do
something about it. Now this Temple University professor has
produced a follow-up volume, "Beyond Numeracy: Ruminations of
a Numbers Man" (Knopf, 285 pages, $22), for those who would
like to be initiated into the higher mysteries.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   It is in essence a tour through 70 topics in mathematics:
some elementary (algebra, matrices), some advanced (topology,
platonic solids), some avant-garde (chaos theory) and some
philosophical (the fractal nature of consciousness,
mathematics in ethics, math and humor).
   His brief essays are arranged alphabetically by topic, and
as with one of its precursors, <ORGANIZATION>Voltaire</ORGANIZATION>'s "Philosophical
Dictionary," it makes for an often-jolly little book. Also a
reassuring one: In his discussion of probability, <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON>
notes that if you add up the chances of being murdered by all
the terrorists, muggers, serial killers, drunk drivers and
other homicidal types in the world, the probability is
greater that you will kill yourself.
   The main point of any book such as this should be to
convince mathematical philistines of the keen pitch of
aesthetic pleasure the subject affords. Beauty, indeed, is
the paramount criterion of good mathematics; as the great
English number theorist <PERSON>G.H. Hardy</PERSON> once remarked, "There is
no permanent place in the world for ugly mathematics." This,
of course, will come as a surprise to the vast majority of
educated people who never got beyond calculus, for "school
mathematics" is extremely dull and is usually taught in the
most unimaginative possible way.
   <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON> does reasonably well in conveying the aesthetic
appeal of mathematics. He presents <ORGANIZATION>Euclid</ORGANIZATION>'s proof that there
are infinitely many prime numbers, which exemplifies the
elements of economy, surprise and inevitability that go to
make up mathematical elegance. He also gives a nice, simple
account of the different orders of infinity, an awesome idea
that everyone really ought to know about -- although perhaps
not too much, considering that the man who discovered them in
the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>, <PERSON>Georg Cantor</PERSON>, came to a rather sticky
and demented end.
   Several essays draw connections between mathematics and
the arts. The author explains the "golden section," a ratio
heavily exploited by the designers of the <LOCATION>Parthenon</LOCATION> and at
one time believed to be the universal key to beauty in nature
and art. He delves into the mathematical basis of music. And
he provides a much-needed -- for Americans, at least --
introduction to a French society of mathematically inclined
litterateurs called OULIPO (the French acronym for Workshop
of Potential Literature). Typical of their output is <PERSON>Raymond
Queneau</PERSON>'s "Cent mille milliards poemes." Achieved by a
combinatoric sleight of hand, this sequence of one hundred
trillion sonnets -- which <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON>, in what one hopes is a
rare lapse for a numbers man, miscalculates as a mere 10
trillion -- dwarfs the rest of the world's poetic output.
   Where <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON> goes wrong, I feel, is in seeing
mathematics as a font of practical wisdom. It is true that
those who have some grounding in probability and statistics
are less likely than innumerates to be gulled by astrologers,
bureaucrats and other charlatans. But this is lowbrow
mathematics. Real mathematics has almost nothing to do with
the world of affairs. The theory of numbers, for example, is
perhaps the most daunting yet aesthetically gratifying area
of mathematics; it is also supremely useless -- "l'art pour
l'art."
   Moreover, those who spend too much time communing with
abstract mathematical entities tend to behave in an arrogant,
foolish, even mischievous manner when it comes to practical
matters. A case in point is one of <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON>'s heroes,
<PERSON>Bertrand Russell</PERSON>. Of this sometimes pacifist, sometimes
atomic saber-rattler, full-time scourge of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign
policy, the historian <ORGANIZATION>G.M. Trevelyan</ORGANIZATION> aptly remarked: "He may
be a genius at mathematics -- as to that I am no judge; but
he is a perfect goose at politics."
   If there is much to take issue with in "Beyond Numeracy,"
there is also much to be amused and enlightened by. The lore
has it that when Pythagoras discovered his great theorem on
right triangles, he was so transported that he sacrificed 100
head of oxen to the gods as a token of gratitude. On this
scale, <PERSON>Mr. Paulos</PERSON>'s book is surely worth an ox or two.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Holt</PERSON>, an erstwhile mathematician, is a columnist for
the <ORGANIZATION>Literary Review</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880328-0222 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-28-88 1437EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--Matisse Adv08-10   03-28 0829</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Matisse, Adv 08-10,0852</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv08-10</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Weekend Editions, April 8-10 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Artists: Radical Move, Dude</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE JAHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GROTON, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's a <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION> hanging in a <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>
subway station that has nothing to with fauvism, impressionism or
any of the other labels commonly associated with the name.
   Most Matisses appeal to the eye. The subway Matisse _ 16 massive
aluminum chimes and teak-tipped hammers suspended between the
tracks at the <LOCATION>Kendall Square</LOCATION> stop _ pleases the ear with a majestic
sound that comes when a handle from the platform is pulled.
   <PERSON>Henri Matisse</PERSON> is considered one of the most influential
20th-century artists. His boldy colored canvases that typify the
fauvist movement hang in famous galleries worldwide. Fauvism was a
French expressionist movement that involved such artists as
<ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Vlaminck</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Derain</PERSON> and utilized strong, bold colors and
distorted forms.
   His grandson, <PERSON>Paul Matisse</PERSON>, is less famous. He doesn't paint,
but since setting up the chimes of ``Pythagoras'' last <DATE>October</DATE>, he
is cherished by hundreds of commuters who have left their scribbled
comments on a pad near the handle.
   ``I am getting a Proustian rush: Is this normal?'' reads one. A
less profound comment says simply: ``Radical move, Dude.''
   Others have viewed his functional mobiles at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Museum
of Modern Art and the Metropolitan Museum of Art; the <ORGANIZATION>National
Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; the <LOCATION>Musee</LOCATION> d`Art Moderne in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>; the
<LOCATION>Bienalle</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>; and at other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and foreign galleries.
   Matisse, whose father, <PERSON>Pierre</PERSON>, is a well-known art dealer in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, lives and works in a former Baptist church in <LOCATION>Groton</LOCATION> _ a
sleepy town about 50 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> _ with his wife,
artist <PERSON>Linda Hoffman</PERSON>, and their two children.
   He talked about himself and his grandfather during a recent
interview in his workshop _ a clutter of drill presses, lathes,
jigsaws and other tools he wields to create works that titillate
the imagination through movement, sight and sound.
   As a boy visiting <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> for <DATE>summer</DATE> holidays, <PERSON>Matisse</PERSON> sat
frequently for his grandfather and has recollections of him as ``a
terrifying presence.''
   ``When he looked at you to draw you, you were looked at,'' he
said. ``He was like a 50,000-watt search light.''
   Matisse bears some physical resemblance to his grandfather. He
now does not seem to suffer from the burden of living up to such a
famous heritage.
   It was not always so.
   ``What happens is in a lifetime you go through a whole series of
responses,'' he said with a chuckle. ``So you go through a negative
response. I've gone beyond that, and I feel a very positive
appreciation of the fact that he was back there.''
   But he is at pains to emphasize the obvious _ there is no
similarity between his works and that of his grandfather, who died
in <DATE>1954</DATE>.
   ``When he drew a line, he drew a line he wanted to draw,'' he
said. ``He knew exactly what he wanted to do, and I remember him
telling me that his hand was his servant, and I don't work that way
at all.
   ``I have to draw (while drafting), so I do. But it's not so much
that, it's just that I don't have a great love of color and form,''
the 55-year-old artist said. ``I have a great love of ideas, which
is different entirely, and I think I'm much closer to <PERSON>Duchamp</PERSON> in
respect.''
   Matisse's kinship with <PERSON>Marcel Duchamp</PERSON>, the famed French artist
who began challenging traditional art concepts during the <DATE>early
years of this century</DATE>, goes beyond a love for the unusual. Duchamp,
who died in <DATE>1968</DATE>, was <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>'s stepfather.
   Matisse, an acknowledged authority on <PERSON>Duchamp</PERSON>, referred several
times to one of his stepfather's most controversial works _ a
common urinal entitled ``Fountain,'' which shocked the art world of
his time. He hinted at a common bond in describing DuChamp as an
ideas man.
   ``I said <PERSON>Duchamp</PERSON> because <PERSON>Marcel</PERSON> rebelled against `painterly
art,''' he said, commenting on artistic influences. ``He wanted art
with intelligence.
   ``<PERSON>Duchamp</PERSON> said things like `bete comme un peintre' (stupid like
a painter). ``The influence I treasure from him is his point of
view.''
   While mentioning that <PERSON>Duchamp</PERSON> frequently expressed support of
his creations, <PERSON>Matisse</PERSON> emphasized that he is very much an
individual, personally and artistically.
   ``I am delighted that I was as close to him as I was,'' he said.
``But his character was very much his character and in no way does
mine reflect his.
   Although expressing reluctance to characterize his own art,
<ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION> alluded to his creative philosophy in comments on
``Pythagoras.''
   ``The important part is to do whatever your spirit wants, and
... when you hang up a bell or tube, you do not get beautiful
sound,'' he said.
   ``I was able to do all that, so why should I be jealous of my
grandfather's ability to draw lines?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, April 8-10</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-6943</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EB0AFAFUFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940226
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 FEB 94 / Books: Mystical music tour
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHRISTIAN TYLER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE MUSIC OF THE SPHERES: MUSIC SCIENCE AND THE NATURAL ORDER OF THE
UNIVERSEby <PERSON>Jamie James Little Brown</PERSON> Pounds 18.99, 260 pages
The power of music over mankind, for dancing, fighting, love-making, praying
or mourning, is one of life's unsolved mysteries. Even cows are said to find
it soothing, while <PERSON>Brahms</PERSON>'s spider was literally moved - charmed down its
thread by the composer's harmonies and sent scuttling up again by his
dissonances.
Various solutions to the riddle have been attempted. <PERSON>Deryck Cooke</PERSON> tried 35
years ago in The Language of Music to establish a musical grammar of human
emotions. More recently the psychiatrist <PERSON>Anthony Storr</PERSON> tackled it from the
psycho-biological end in his discursive Music and the Mind.
To describe the abstractions of music in words is notoriously difficult: so
it is not surprising that most music-lovers, and critics, are content to
leave it at that. But it is also a commonplace that science and music have
some affinity (think of all those boffins who play in string quartets), so
that when little Emily passes her Grade 5 piano with distinction the
neighbours exclaim: 'Oh, she must be good at maths]'
Therefore it is somewhat disappointing not to find in this present excursion
into the metaphysics of music any account of current scientific thinking
about why human beings react as they do when they hear certain tones or
rhythms or cadences. Nor are we left much the wiser about that extraordinary
combination of intellectual and emotional satisfaction which the playing and
hearing of 'good' music brings.
The author, an American magazine writer on both science and music, does,
however, trace the history of these phenomena right back to <LOCATION>Pythagoras</LOCATION> -
credited with discovering the mathematics of musical intervals - and his
cult of mystic number-crunchers. Through Plato, the early Christians, and
the Renaissance the cosmic character of music, the link between the universe
and the soul, went unchallenged. It was <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s father who broke the
Pythagorean spell when he discovered that the old Greek's ratios were not
perfect, and a vicious controversy ensued: some even said it against the
natural order to tune keyboards so that music could modulate.
Newton (an alchemist in his spare time) and <PERSON>Kepler</PERSON> (a keen astrologer) were
in thrall to the concept of the music of the spheres; while <PERSON>Leibniz</PERSON>, a
contemporary of JS <PERSON>Bach</PERSON>, said music was 'the hidden arithmetical exercise of
a soul unconscious that it is calculating.' This cosmic conception was only
dispersed by the anthropocentric Romantic movement, a period the author is
reluctant to define too sharply but appears, on balance, to regret.
The feverish cult of the virtuoso and genius gave way in turn to the atonal
<PERSON>Schoenberg</PERSON>, writing at the same time that <PERSON>Einstein</PERSON> was rewriting <PERSON>Newton</PERSON>'s
physics. Even so <PERSON>Schoenberg</PERSON> (developer of the 12-tone system) could seem the
most mystical musician since Pythagoras. He was superstitious about the
number 13 (naturally) and displayed, says the author, a similar 'veneration
of the numinous power of number.'
James completes his tour with an essay on what he sees as the fragmented,
selfish sterility of the contemporary scene. Even here, he finds in
<PERSON>Stockhausen</PERSON>'s account of the sympathetic and healing vibrations of music a
harking back to the time of <ORGANIZATION>Boethius</ORGANIZATION>.
This is a learned, sophisticated book, full of surprises. But it is not at
all clear what conclusion the author wants us to draw from his exegesis: he
is by no means anti-science, yetseems to be saying that music composed in
the cheerless, random world depicted for us by modern hypotheses is bound to
leave us cold and unsatisfied.
If so, he should talk to <PERSON>John Tavener</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910701-0200
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910701-0200.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   These Teaching Guides Credit Blacks
   For Math, Science and the Pyramids
   ----
   By Gary Putka
</HL>
<DATE>
07/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A2
</SO>
<RE>
GEORGIA (GA)
ILLINOIS (IL)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
OREGON (ORG)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Much of the curriculum of the Afrocentric movement is
based on teaching guides called the African-American Baseline
Essays, published by the Portland, Ore., public schools. The
essays -- on art, language arts, mathematics, music, social
studies and science -- contend that much of their content has
been deliberately omitted by standard "Eurocentric" texts.
Yet many more-traditional scholars say the essays themselves
contain numerous inaccuracies and distortions. What follows
are some excerpts from the essays.
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   From ART, by <PERSON>Michael D. Harris</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Morehouse College</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>:
                                                                                                       

   "<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> ca. 3100 B.C. was a Black nation. The first 1,100
years of <LOCATION>Dynastic Egypt</LOCATION> during the first six Dynasties was a
period of undisturbed Black rule, and was the period when
most of the pyramids (and Sphinx) were built. . . . The great
18th Dynasty re-established Black rule and brought many of
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most famous personages to power. Akhnetan,
<LOCATION>Tutankhamun</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nefritari</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nefertiti</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hatshepsut</PERSON>, and Tutmosis
were among the familiar names. This all means that the art
forms and architecture we relate to <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> are, in fact, forms
of Black art. . ."
                                                                                                       

   From LANGUAGE ARTS, by <PERSON>Joyce Braden Harris</PERSON>, director,
<ORGANIZATION>Black Educational Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>:
                                                                                                       

   "Black literature is manipulated and controlled by white
editors and publishers. . . . Black writers who are published
generally receive little or no promotion for their works."
   "The Ten Commandments . . . are very similar in content to
The Negative Confessions {of ancient Egyptian tombs}. . . .
The inscription of Nefer-Seshem-Re of the <ORGANIZATION>Sixth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>
provides further evidence of the African origins of the Ten
Commandments."
                                                                                                       

   From MATHEMATICS, by <PERSON>Beatrice Lumpkin</PERSON>, associate professor
of mathematics, retired, <ORGANIZATION>Malcolm X College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>:
                                                                                                       

   "Since <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> was the birthplace of the human race, it
follows that <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> was the birthplace of mathematics and
science."
   ". . . Specific examples indicate that ancient Egyptians
were conducting investigations that could have led to the
formation of the so-called Pythagorean theorem. There is hard
evidence that the theorem was known 1,000 years before
Pythagoras."
   "Euclid . . . lived and died in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. There is no
suggestion that he ever left <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. Yet he is pictured in
textbooks as a fair European Greek, not as an Egyptian. We
have no pictures of these mathematicians, but we could at
least visualize them honestly in costumes, complexions, and
features true to the people of their times."
                                                                                                       

   From SOCIAL STUDIES, by <PERSON>John Henrik Clarke</PERSON>, professor
emeritus, <ORGANIZATION>Hunter College</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>:
                                                                                                       

   "Non-Biblical history . . . indicates that the Hebrews
were not slaves in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. Some of the Hebrews mistakenly took
sides with the enemies of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and were punished. This
punishment did not consist of slavery. The Hebrews, like the
Greeks, Romans, <LOCATION>Hyksos</LOCATION>, and other foreigners, benefited
religiously and intellectually from their sojourn in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>."
   "Cleopatra . . . was of mixed African and Greek parentage.
If she were alive today, there is no way she could pass for
Caucasian. If living today, she would probably be living in
one of the Black communities in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>."
                                                                                                       

   From SCIENCE, by <PERSON>Hunter Havelin Adams III</PERSON>, scientist,
<ORGANIZATION>Argonne National Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>:
                                                                                                       

   ". . . The discovery of time, the control and use of fire
. . . tool technology, language and agriculture. Nothing in
the <DATE>20th century</DATE> has touched humanity so totally as those
things which were first accomplished by Africans. . . ."
   "Today the science contributions of the Islamic-African
science tradition are relatively unknown in the Western world
because of the lack of humility of many Medieval European
scholars who diligently imitated, copied and plagiarized the
works of many Islamic scientists."
   (See related story: "Making a Difference -- Curricula of
Color: Course Work Stressing Blacks' Role Has Critics But
Appears Effective --- In <LOCATION>Atlanta Schools</LOCATION>, Teachers See Rise
in Self-Esteem, Interest and Test Scores --- <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> as
Wellspring of Science" -- WSJ <DATE>July 1, 1991</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-338</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CC3A2ACGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920330
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 MAR 92 / Observer: High class
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
In essence, Observer has only one thing to say to readers who tackled last
<DATE>Monday</DATE>'s numeracy-style questions. It is: 'Go to the top of the class]'
After all, any candidate who got 82.8 per cent of the total marks available
in a test would be considered to have done very well. But that was merely
the average score of the 151 of you who entered the quiz.
The questions, with the answers in italics, were:
1 What is the conventional name for the result of dividing the circumference
of a circle by its diameter? Pi.
2 What is <MONEY>12 1/2 per cent</MONEY> of 60 per cent? 7 1/2 per cent.
3 If 93 folk enter a knock-out singles tournament at tennis, how many
matches are needed before one player emerges as overall winner? 92.
4 In the A1, A2, A3 . . . series of paper-sizes, what mathematical
relationship does the length of each sheet's longer side bear to the length
of its shorter side? When the shorter side is designated as 1, the longer is
the square root of 2.
5 Name the ancient philosopher specifically associated with the theorem that
sheds light on question 4. Pythagoras.
6 What - apart from the fact that no other number is the same as it - is
unique about the number 1,729? It is the smallest number that can be formed
from the sum of two cubes in two different ways (13x123=1,729;
103x93=1,729).
7 Name the unusual mathematician who saw the answer to 6 instantly.
Ramanujan.
As Observer reported <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>, 62 of you produced perfect answers
within the time limit, so necessitating a tie-breaker to find the winner of
the bottle of malt whisky.
As threatened, it is a stinker calling for knowledge both of numerate and of
literary culture. It has two parts.
The focus is the ancient problem: Which number when added to one seventh of
itself equals 19? It is easily solved by algebra which allows a
non-numerical 'place-holder', such as x, to stand for the initially unknown
number constituting the answer - for example, x + x/7 = 19.
But algebra is a relatively recent method which was scarcely known in
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, at least, until the mid-16th century. Before then, there was no
facility for using unknown place-holders, and such problems had to be solved
by calculating solely with whole numbers and fractions (as distinct from
decimals), the preferred method being called 'The way of falsehood.' Now to
the question:
A Show how the problem could be worked out by such a pre-algebraic method.
B Which 16th-17th century English poet hinted that he understood the then
new algebra, and in which poem?
All entries welcome, but only the previous 62 timely and all-correct
entrants will be in line for the prize. Answers by fax to Observer on
071-873 3926 or 071-873 3196 by 6pm <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> time tomorrow, or by mail
postmarked the same day.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-11281</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EG4ARAFDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940730
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 JUL 94 / Such woolly ideas
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIGEL SPIVEY
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Once it was fur coats. Now, since fashion gurus have obscured the difference
between real and ersatz hides, it is woolly jumpers. Shops one thought of as
staid - the Scottish knitwear specialists, with their changeless tartan ties
and avuncular cardigans - have become targets of the Animal Rights Militia.
This is the organisation which gutted the <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> store of <ORGANIZATION>Edinburgh
Woollen Mills</ORGANIZATION> earlier in the month. The local animal rights spokesman
allocated precise credit for the action to a guerrilla sub-group of his
movement, known as the <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>. And justice, he said, had been
done on the grounds that 'sheep-shearing leaves sheep susceptible and cold
as a naked human.'
This was not an isolated incident. The <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> branch of Boots the
<ORGANIZATION>Chemists</ORGANIZATION> was set alight, and certain research units around <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> have
received a new sort of home-made bomb: an exploding mousetrap primed with
razor blades. This aims not only to remove the digits of those scientists
suspected of animal abuse, but also makes a statement on behalf of mice, so
often the choice for laboratory tests.
A flurry, then, of animal rights activity. There is nothing new in this. But
the extension of anathema-status to pullovers is new, and it is always
interesting to watch how the British deal with such issues, for the British
make it part of their self-definition that they are kind to animals when
others in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, especially southern <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, are not.
This nationalistic pride was trumpeted during European negotiations about
rules for transporting livestock. Even those of us who like a good steak, it
seems, are concerned that the ox shall travel to his slaughter in decent
comfort.
Gourmets will point out that a well-rested beast tastes better, so this is
not pure charity; still, it is true that the British get angry about the
ill-treatment of animals, and in that sense the animal rights movement is
never entirely marginal.
Whether many wool-wearing people or even woolly liberals will ever feel pity
for chilly sheep is doubtful. But translating kindness towards animals into
justice for animals is something that we ought to take more seriously than
we do, and scientists, with distinguished exceptions, such as <PERSON>James Gaia
Lovelock</PERSON>, are too quiet about it.
Those activists who resort to pyromania are probably not the sort to engage
in rational argument. Yet it is a debate which used to be very much alive in
pagan philosophy. Pythagoras, who first articulated vegetarianism in the
sixth century BC, was only one of many thinkers who addressed animal rights.
But Christian theologians from <ORGANIZATION>St Augustine</ORGANIZATION> onwards have quelled the issue,
being content to accept the animal kingdom as a part of creation subordinate
to human needs. According to <ORGANIZATION>St Augustine</ORGANIZATION>, if we took the commandment 'Thou
shalt not kill' as an injunction not to slaughter animals, we should also
have to prohibit ourselves from uprooting parsnips.
This is what logicians call a slide. To say that one move will lead to
another is a familiar method for blocking moral progress. Faced with a man
who believes that sheep should not be shorn, we might then insist that he
abstain from the consumption of honey, milk and eggs - all of which have
been regarded as theft by some legally-minded purists - and, like <ORGANIZATION>St
Augustine</ORGANIZATION>, challenge him to wrench a happy parsnip from the earth.
The application of human justice to the animal world hinges, as <PERSON>Richard
Sorabji</PERSON> demonstrated recently in Animal Minds and Human Morals (<ORGANIZATION>Duckworth</ORGANIZATION>),
on how far we consider animals to share in the human capacity for reason.
<PERSON>Charles Darwin</PERSON> believed that there was no human trait which could not be
found reflected in one animal or another; but modern scientists, following
Aristotle, have been forced to use an exclusion zone based on a
technicality. The technicality is that animals have no syntax. It follows
that if a creature cannot construct a sentence, then we are at liberty to do
with it what we will in the slaughterhouse or the research institute.
Consideration of babies, parrots and chimpanzees will immediately generate
worries about the absolute logic of this technicality. Indeed, it is hard to
see what relevance it has in a debate which is primarily about pain and the
capacity of living things to feel it.
Pythagoras stopped a man beating a dog because he recognised in the dog's
yelps the voice of an old friend. Most of us, if we think about it, will
admit unease about testing chemicals on beagles. That does not mean,
necessarily, that we would not wish chemicals to be tried on rats, nor that
we should charitably prefer to wear nylon rather than wool.
What matters is that we give the matter some thought. In that sense, one has
to feel grateful for the occasional arson attack. Crass as they are, such
actions are not unfounded. They rightly make us think.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9512 Land, Mineral, Wildlife Conservation.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880919-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-88 0231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Lites     09-19 0860</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Lites,0897</SECOND>
<HEAD>On The Light Side</HEAD>
<DATELINE>VIRGINIA CITY, Nev. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes, love reins, especially
when a couple in their finest Western duds exchanges marriage vows
while sitting atop their horses in ``Bonanza'' country.
   <PERSON>Carol Clifford</PERSON>, 47, and <PERSON>B.D. Lapham</PERSON>, 46, said they decided to
tie the knot on horseback <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in this town near <PERSON>Ben
Cartwright</PERSON>'s Ponderosa ranch on the old ``Bonanza'' TV series
because of their love of horses.
   With more than 150 guests watching from hay bales, the couple
said their ``I do's'' in front of a hitching post. But before they
could kiss, the crowd's clapping spooked the horses, causing them
to gallop up a hill. The couple later walked back in with the
horses.
   They originally planned to have a small wedding. ``But then I
said `Let's get married on the horses' and friends started asking
if they could come to the ceremony,'' <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> said.
   Like their ceremony, their invitations were unusual. They were
designed like an old wanted poster and a friend shot bullets
through all of them.
   They met earlier this year when <PERSON>Clifford</PERSON>, a Reno newspaper
classified ad supervisor, was out walking. She met <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> outside
the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboys &amp; Indians</ORGANIZATION> saloon he manages, putting out his flags.
   She stopped and said, ``Oh, you have nice flags,'' and the
romance blossomed from there.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ROCHESTER, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes, love reins, especially
when a couple in their finest Western duds exchanges marriage vows
while sitting atop their horses in ``Bonanza'' country.
   <PERSON>Carol Clifford</PERSON>, 47, and <PERSON>B.D. Lapham</PERSON>, 46, said they decided to
tie the knot on horseback <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in this town near <PERSON>Ben
Cartwright</PERSON>'s Ponderosa ranch on the old ``Bonanza'' TV series
because of their love of horses.
   With more than 150 guests watching from hay bales, the couple
said their ``I do's'' in front of a hitching post. But before they
could kiss, the crowd's clapping spooked the horses, causing them
to gallop up a hill. The couple later walked back in with the
horses.
   They originally planned to have a small wedding. ``But then I
said `Let's get married on the horses' and friends started asking
if they could come to the ceremony,'' <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> said.
   Like their ceremony, their invitations were unusual. They were
designed like an old wanted poster and a friend shot bullets
through all of them.
   They met earlier this year when <PERSON>Clifford</PERSON>, a Reno newspaper
classified ad supervisor, was out walking. She met <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> outside
the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboys &amp; Indians</ORGANIZATION> saloon he manages, putting out his flags.
   She stopped and said, ``Oh, you have nice flags,'' and the
romance blossomed from there.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes, love reins, especially
when a couple in their finest Western duds exchanges marriage vows
while sitting atop their horses in ``Bonanza'' country.
   <PERSON>Carol Clifford</PERSON>, 47, and <PERSON>B.D. Lapham</PERSON>, 46, said they decided to
tie the knot on horseback <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in this town near <PERSON>Ben
Cartwright</PERSON>'s Ponderosa ranch on the old ``Bonanza'' TV series
because of their love of horses.
   With more than 150 guests watching from hay bales, the couple
said their ``I do's'' in front of a hitching post. But before they
could kiss, the crowd's clapping spooked the horses, causing them
to gallop up a hill. The couple later walked back in with the
horses.
   They originally planned to have a small wedding. ``But then I
said `Let's get married on the horses' and friends started asking
if they could come to the ceremony,'' <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> said.
   Like their ceremony, their invitations were unusual. They were
designed like an old wanted poster and a friend shot bullets
through all of them.
   They met earlier this year when <PERSON>Clifford</PERSON>, a Reno newspaper
classified ad supervisor, was out walking. She met <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> outside
the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboys &amp; Indians</ORGANIZATION> saloon he manages, putting out his flags.
   She stopped and said, ``Oh, you have nice flags,'' and the
romance blossomed from there.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes, love reins, especially
when a couple in their finest Western duds exchanges marriage vows
while sitting atop their horses in ``Bonanza'' country.
   <PERSON>Carol Clifford</PERSON>, 47, and <PERSON>B.D. Lapham</PERSON>, 46, said they decided to
tie the knot on horseback <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in this town near <PERSON>Ben
Cartwright</PERSON>'s Ponderosa ranch on the old ``Bonanza'' TV series
because of their love of horses.
   With more than 150 guests watching from hay bales, the couple
said their ``I do's'' in front of a hitching post. But before they
could kiss, the crowd's clapping spooked the horses, causing them
to gallop up a hill. The couple later walked back in with the
horses.
   They originally planned to have a small wedding. ``But then I
said `Let's get married on the horses' and friends started asking
if they could come to the ceremony,'' <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> said.
   Like their ceremony, their invitations were unusual. They were
designed like an old wanted poster and a friend shot bullets
through all of them.
   They met earlier this year when <PERSON>Clifford</PERSON>, a Reno newspaper
classified ad supervisor, was out walking. She met <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> outside
the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboys &amp; Indians</ORGANIZATION> saloon he manages, putting out his flags.
   She stopped and said, ``Oh, you have nice flags,'' and the
romance blossomed from there.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LINCOLN, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sometimes, love reins, especially
when a couple in their finest Western duds exchanges marriage vows
while sitting atop their horses in ``Bonanza'' country.
   <PERSON>Carol Clifford</PERSON>, 47, and <PERSON>B.D. Lapham</PERSON>, 46, said they decided to
tie the knot on horseback <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in this town near <PERSON>Ben
Cartwright</PERSON>'s Ponderosa ranch on the old ``Bonanza'' TV series
because of their love of horses.
   With more than 150 guests watching from hay bales, the couple
said their ``I do's'' in front of a hitching post. But before they
could kiss, the crowd's clapping spooked the horses, causing them
to gallop up a hill. The couple later walked back in with the
horses.
   They originally planned to have a small wedding. ``But then I
said `Let's get married on the horses' and friends started asking
if they could come to the ceremony,'' <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> said.
   Like their ceremony, their invitations were unusual. They were
designed like an old wanted poster and a friend shot bullets
through all of them.
   They met earlier this year when <PERSON>Clifford</PERSON>, a Reno newspaper
classified ad supervisor, was out walking. She met <PERSON>Lapham</PERSON> outside
the <ORGANIZATION>Cowboys &amp; Indians</ORGANIZATION> saloon he manages, putting out his flags.
   She stopped and said, ``Oh, you have nice flags,'' and the
romance blossomed from there.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-2735</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CLKB5AA6FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921211
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 DEC 92 / BJP sees Ayodhya as desperate rallying call: The aspirations
of India's Hindu militant opposition party
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEFAN WAGSTYL
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW DELHI
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>MR Kewal Ratan Malkani</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Bharatiya Janata</ORGANIZATION> party, the
radical Hindu party whose militant supporters stormed the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> mosque at
the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, scorns the view that the incident will backfire against the
<ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION>.
'It is only the upper classes who are shocked by this. The masses are
delighted,' he said an interview yesterday. 'Look at <LOCATION>Maharashtra</LOCATION> (the state
which includes <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> and has born the brunt of the post-Ayodhya violence).
If we had an election there tomorrow we would win.'
The Delhi intelligentsia believes that <PERSON>Mr Malkani</PERSON> is quite wrong. Newspaper
commentators insist that most Indians will now reject the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> on the grounds
that it foments intolerance. But the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> has long learnt to do without the
support of commentators.
<PERSON>Mr Malkani</PERSON>'s boasts reflect the party's defiant mood. The crisis has
suddenly focused its energies. All the arguments over strategy and tactics
which have dogged it over the past year as it saw its popularity waning have
been set aside. So clear is the aim of advancing Hindu militancy that even
the arrest of top <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> officials, including <PERSON>Mr L K Advani</PERSON>, the leader, for
alleged incitement of religious hatred, has barely curtailed the party's
activities.
Today the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> plans to stage demonstrations at the Pakistani and <ORGANIZATION>Bangladeshi
High Commissions</ORGANIZATION> to protest against the destruction of Hindu temples in
those countries.
<PERSON>Mr Malkani</PERSON> was outraged by the suggestion that Moslems were merely reacting
to the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> assault. 'They started this. Nobody is as patient as a Hindu
but there are limits to our patience.'
<PERSON>Mr Malkani</PERSON> said he regretted that the assault on the mosque was against the
law. He also regretted the violence which has since swept <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. But he
accepted none of the responsibility. Instead, he blamed the government of <PERSON>Mr
P V Narasimha Rao</PERSON>, the prime minister, and on the courts for repeatedly
delaying settlement of long-standing Hindu claims to the mosque site.
He also blamed Moslems for allegedly promoting intolerance. 'They smashed
3,000 temples (in the conquest of northern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>). We want just three back.'
The three are at <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, and at <LOCATION>Mathura</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Varanasi</LOCATION> - two other Hindu holy
cities where mosques stand on disputed sites.
<PERSON>Mr Malkani</PERSON>, who is 71 and has spent his life working for militant <LOCATION>Hinduism</LOCATION>,
speaks like a man who knows that if the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> cannot fire Hindu passions now,
with the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> issue burning, perhaps it never will.
The <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> was formed in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE> out of politicians linked to the
<ORGANIZATION>Rashtriya Swayamsevak Sangh</ORGANIZATION>, the well-disciplined Hindu militant group which
was one of three Hindu organisations banned <TIME>last night</TIME>. It sought to offer
an alternative to the dominant <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> (I) party. But it won just two lower
house parliamentary seats in the <DATE>1984</DATE> general elections.
However, in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr Advani</PERSON> began to fan the flames of the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>
controversy. He also exploited growing disillusion with the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> party's
secularism which had united Indians during the struggle to build
post-independent <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> but now seemed sterile.
He won particular support from upper-caste Hindus, some of whom felt they
were losing status as economic modernisation opened more opportunities to
the low-caste masses. The party's financial strength came from many small
shopkeepers and tradesmen, who felt <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> pampered the big corporations
at their expense.
The <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> tried to make its ideology coherent. <PERSON>Mr Advani</PERSON> said it was a 'nation
first' party. Ideologues explained <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> should reject secularism and become
an overtly Hindu nation. Historians rewrote parts of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s past to
emphasise, for example, the role of Hindu princes, instead of Moslems, in
opposing British rule. Even maths was not spared  - the Pythagoras theorem
was attributed in one BJP-sponsored textbook to <LOCATION>Baudhayan</LOCATION>, an Indian
mathematician who allegedly discovered it 450 years before <PERSON>Pythagoras</PERSON>.
In last year's general election, the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> secured 119 seats out of 543,
making it the second largest party after <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. It also won control of
the state government in four states - the first taste of real power.
However, the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> then lost ground. It was unlucky in being unable seriously
to challenge <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>'s economic reforms - a key issue over the past 18
months. <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> leaders were early fans of economic deregulation but the prime
minister stole their clothes. The party's clean image was sullied by
divisions between leaders and a minor sex scandal. In governing states, it
suffered from inexperience.
Moreover, even as they were wooed by the cause of Hindu unity, Hindus could
hardly forget their many differences - including caste, language, wealth and
regional origin. Without <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION>, it was difficult for the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION> to offer
enough to hold them together. This <DATE>autumn</DATE>, when the <LOCATION>Ayodhya</LOCATION> conflict had
temporarily gone quiet, an opinion survey showed just 14 per cent of those
polled wanted <PERSON>Mr Advani</PERSON> as prime minister, against 49 per cent for <PERSON>Mr Rao</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Mr Pran Chopra</PERSON>, a leading political analyst, is convinced <PERSON>Mr Advani</PERSON>'s rating
has fallen further this week: '<ORGANIZATION>Ayodhya</ORGANIZATION> will damage the <ORGANIZATION>BJP</ORGANIZATION>'s share of the
total vote. The feelings of committed supporters may have hardened, but the
party will lose mass support.' <PERSON>Mr Chopra</PERSON> believes the voice of moderation
will prevail - a view shared by other analysts.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871006-0127 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf:
Quips and Quintessences
---
By Raymond Sokolov</HL>
<DD> 10/06/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   In all the current excitement about education that has made best sellers out of <ORGANIZATION>E.D. Hirsch Jr.</ORGANIZATION>'s "Cultural Literacy" and <PERSON>Allan Bloom</PERSON>'s "The Closing of the American Mind," there is one central issue. 
It is the failure of the schools to lure students into the slipstream of intellectual history. 
<PERSON>Mr. Hirsch</PERSON> wants to correct this on the cheap, by teaching a short list of terms that will allow his acolytes to pass themselves off as intellectuals. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON> has a higher aim, a return to high educational standards through hard mental work. 

   In their separate ways, both of these authors have been making a hero of the intellectual. 
<PERSON>Mr. Hirsch</PERSON>'s list is a kind of magic elixir, a Superman suit that will transform Video Dolt into Highbrow. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON>'s high-toned attack on mush-brained curricula is also a campaign for what might be called higher education, whose goal must be the routine production of highbrows, people who speak <PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON>'s language. 

   Both <PERSON>Mr. Hirsch</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON> should consider recommending a new book that exemplifies the virtues they have been acclaiming -- and goes beyond them. 
W.V. <PERSON>Quine</PERSON>'s "Quiddities: An Intermittently Philosophical Dictionary" (<ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>, 249 pages, <MONEY>$20</MONEY>) can be said, in a way, to follow the <PERSON>Hirsch</PERSON> method. 
It defines various concepts and lists them in alphabetical order, commencing, indeed, with "alphabet" and ending with "zero." 
These may sound too elementary for the Hirschite intent on expanding his vocabulary to include nominally intellectual shibboleths of use in the tohubohu of cocktail parties. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Edgar Pierce Professor of Philosophy Emeritus</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> and arguably the leading philosophical mind in the world, has much to teach most people about alphabets and the meaning of zero. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON> might find him too analytical, not interested enough in the history of philosophy as <PERSON>Mr. Bloom</PERSON> teaches it. 
But I think he would concede that <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON> is an intellectual -- high, wide and handsome -- opening his mind to the rest of us here in a way that exemplifies the best of what a first-rate mind can do when aiming to explain himself to nonspecialists in mostly nontechnical language. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON>, who has in his time changed the face of symbolic logic and ordinary language philosophy, here turns his mind to standard philosophical subjects such as free will, to topics in number theory and to matters of language. 
He has spent a lifetime making things clear, and the 85 mini-essays collected here are models of clarity in the discussion of difficult ideas. 
Some of the entries, especially those built on mathematical set theory, will make most people slow down and think hard, but even these sections are entertaining. 

   That is, perhaps, faint praise, too faint for the constant stream of wit and word play that <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON> throws off as naturally as he breathes. 
<PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON> is a very funny man. 
He doesn't do it to please you and me so much as to please himself. 
He is someone who can see the humorous side to <ORGANIZATION>Fermat's Last Theorem</ORGANIZATION> without distorting its complexity. 
"Let me begin," he begins, "in the words of <PERSON>W.S. Gilbert</PERSON>, with a lot of news about the square on the hypotenuse." 
There follows an account of the "notorious" equation left behind unproved at his death by the French mathematician <ORGANIZATION>Pierre de Fermat</ORGANIZATION> (1601-65). 
The theorem purports to expand Pythagoras's formula for the square on the hypotenuse to cover all higher powers. 
After running us through the history of this famous conundrum, <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON> adds a clever restatement of the idea put in terms of sorting objects into colored bins. 

   Every phrase in this book is a condensation of ideas usually stated at greater length, but <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON> has the gift of turning the complex into the conversational without sanding off the edges. 
Often he sounds like the world's most intelligent stand-up comic. 
Here he is edging into a discussion of necessity: "'Must,' we are told, implies 'is.' 
Whatever is necessarily the case is the case. 
Yet I say 'He must be halfway home' precisely to allow for my missing my guess and his not being halfway home. 
Otherwise I would say 'He's halfway home' flat out. 
Clearly something must give, and what must give is 'must.' 
The word may express necessity half the time, but half the time it connotes precisely the lack of necessity, or the lack anyway of certainty. 'Must' is a law unto itself, if 'law' is the word I want." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON>'s gift for fresh restatement crops up everywhere. 
On free will, he states neatly: "One is free, in the ordinary sense of the term, when one does as one likes or sees fit; and this is not altered by the fact, if fact it be, that what one likes or sees fit has had its causes . . . freedom to choose to do otherwise than one likes or sees fit would be a sordid boon." 

   It is impossible in this space to exhibit the full Quinian magic, the magnificent command of reasoning, pace, rhetoric and humor -- how in two pages he considers the traditional arguments justifying altruism as self-interest, finds them wanting, but does not see this as a threat to morality: "I say that such a justification would have been unworthy anyway, smacking of the venal and the sordid. 
Let virtue be its own reward." 
He draws the line, however, at altruism aimed at the welfare of subhuman species: "The human heart is distended until it is as big as all outdoors." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Quine</PERSON>'s own heart is actually a warmer and more capacious place than his life in numbers and syllogisms might make you think. 
He concludes "Altruism" with an appeal to human sympathy: ". . . there are uncharted moral wastes over which only our dim consciences, briefed by a conscientious assessment of probable consequences, are our faltering guides." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06346157 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06346157 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; EDUCATION; SPACE; SCIENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  TWO IMPORTANT celestial events are coming up shortly, on successive days in
fact, and each can provide a great opportunity for us and for our children to
learn more about the wonders of our solar system.;   In the early morning
hours of Saturday, Dec. 21, a small part of our moon will pass through the
shadow of the Earth. This partial eclipse of the moon is not as rare, nor will
it be as impressive, as the solar eclipse we witnessed last July, but it's a
wondrous event just the same. It can also serve as a teaching and learning
vehicle to help prepare us for some more-spectacular eclipses that will occur
during the new year.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LUNAR ECLIPSE TO SHOW EARTH'S SHADOW  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in EX1/9, EX4/4, WL2; Education; Family Learning; Dr. William F.
Russell's books for parents and children include "Classics to Read Aloud to
Your Children" and "Classic Myths to Read Aloud."  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     To acquaint your children with the mechanics of a lunar eclipse, it may be
helpful to have a flashlight on hand, along with several common spheres, such
as a marble, a pingpong ball, a tennis ball or a grapefruit, that you can use
to represent the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and moon. By placing a marble or pingpong ball on a
table, and holding a lighted flashlight near the table's surface, you can
create a long shadow that extends from the object and narrows like a cone down
to a point. (This shadow is called the "umbra," from the Latin word for
"shadow," which is the root for our word "umbrella.");    THE EARTH casts this
same type of shadow in space -- 24 hours a day -- because the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is always
standing in the path of some of the light from the sun. This circular shadow
is widest at the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface, and when people on the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> rotate into the
shadow, they refer to it as "night.";   From there, this same shadow stretches
approximately 850,000 miles out into space, but the circle gets smaller and
smaller before it narrows down to nothing. In all that immense distance,
however, there is only one object that the shadow can fall upon. Every once in
a while, our moon, which is whizzing around the Earth at nearly 2,280 mph,
will cross the path of this shadow, and some or all of the sunlight falling on
the moon's surface will be blocked out until the moon emerges from the shadow
once again.;   At <TIME>2 a.m. PST</TIME> on <DATE>Dec. 21</DATE>, the very bottom part of the moon will
touch the very top of this shadow, and by <TIME>2:33 a.m.</TIME>, almost <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of the
moon will be hidden, while the remainder will be bathed in bright sunlight.;  
By using the flashlight and two of the spherical objects, you can demonstrate
why an eclipse can occur only during the time of a full moon. The moon has to
be in line with the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the sun to enter the <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s shadow, and so
anyone on the "night" side of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> would see the moon fully lighted until
it touches that shadow.;   WHY DON'T we have an eclipse during every full
moon? Well, first of all, that alignment is tremendously precise. Think of
trying to align a grapefruit (the Earth), and a pingpong ball 12 feet away
(the moon), and a large house about a mile down the road (the sun). Even more
critical than this, however, is the fact that the moon doesn't orbit the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
on the same plane that the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbits the sun. The moon's orbit is tilted
about 5 degrees, and so the moon usually passes above or below the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
shadow.;   When some ancient Greek thinkers, such as <ORGANIZATION>Pythagoras</ORGANIZATION> and Aristotle
many centuries ago, saw this phenomenon we call a "partial eclipse," they
noticed that no matter where in the sky the eclipse occurred, the shape of the
shadow on the moon was always curved in the arc of a circle. Through their
reasoning and logic alone, therefore, they concluded that the Earth could not
be flat, and must be a giant sphere.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  William F. Russell column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911211  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  680  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, December 11, 1991
00346157,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890119-0280 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-19-89 1409EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-PhoenixReborn Adv29   01-19 0934</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Phoenix Reborn, Adv 29,0960</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv29</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Jan. 29, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Archaeologists Resurrecting City Where Phoenix Rose from Ashes</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   AL-MATARIYA, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> (AP) _ Ancient <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION>, where legend says
the phoenix was resurrected from its own ashes, is buried or in
ruins. But like the fabulous bird that brought it fame, the city
itself is emerging from the ashes of time.
   Egyptian archaeologists are discovering remains under farmlands,
in the shadow of apartment high-rises, down alleyways and in
mid-campus at <ORGANIZATION>Ein Shams University</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``So much is left, but there's so much trouble getting to it,''
said <PERSON>Mohammed Abdel-Galil</PERSON>, chief antiquities inspector for
al-Matariya, a crowded suburb six miles north of downtown <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>. He
is heading the search for ancient <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION>, struggling to keep a
step ahead of a critical need for space to accommodate an exploding
population.
   The isolated temple columns, mud-brick houses, fallen obelisk,
decorated tombs with star-studded ceilings and pieces of mummies
hint of the glory of the lost spiritual center the Greeks named
<LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> _ City of the Sun. It honored the sun god Re, whose
temple complex dominated ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s history.
   An elegant reminder of <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION>' past, an obelisk, stands in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION>. Its twin, the misnamed ``Cleopatra's
Needle,'' graces the bank of the <LOCATION>Thames River</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   The most impressive <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> remnant in its original home is a
solitary obelisk of red <LOCATION>Aswan</LOCATION> granite, erected almost 4,000 years
ago by Pharaoh Senwosret I. It weighs 121 tons and towers more than
67 feet above a quiet park amid the daily hubbub of modern life.
   Gamal Fares Abu-Fares, a young antiquities inspector, plucked a
blue faience statuette from a desecrated brick tomb more than 2,000
years old.
   ``Grave robbers took the valuable things and tossed relics like
this one aside,'' he said. ``The whole area is one vast cemetery.''
   Nearby, an angry-looking man paced back and forth _ the owner of
the construction site where the tomb was discovered.
   ``Every time we find another relic, he shakes his head,''
Abu-Fares said, explaining that it means the owner can do no work
until the excavators finish.
   By law, construction cannot begin in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> without a permit from
the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION> certifying the site's
historical unimportance.
   In al-Matariya, where the probability is high of archaeological
significance, Abu-Fares spends part of each day riding through new
housing areas checking building permits. His reception can be far
from friendly.
   ``Sometimes, we get into fistfights,'' he said.
   Historians fear for the city whose intellect dazzled early
Mediterraneans. It gave the world the obelisk. Its mathematicians
and astronomers created a solar calendar, 365 days divided into 12
months.
   Ancient <PERSON>Heliopolis</PERSON>' high priests created a think tank that
beckoned the leading brains of the day: the law-giver Solon came, as
did the mathematician Pythagoras. Plato spent years absorbing
<LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION>' storehouse of knowledge.
   The sprawling modern suburb that Cairenes know as <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> lies
southeast of the ancient city, which covered what is now Al-Matariya
and nearby areas.
   For almost 3,000 years of pharaohs, <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> stood undaunted,
bowing only to a brash young Macedonian, <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> the Great, who in
331 B.C. founded a rival city 130 miles to the north, <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>.
   By the time Christianity took hold more than 400 years later,
<LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> _ called ``On'' in the Old Testament _ was a ghost town.
Its remains were slowly covered by sand or they were carted away to
build the medieval city of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   In legend, ancient <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION> lives side-by-side with the
phoenix. That dying magical bird set fire to itself on the altar in
the great temple of Re, and a new phoenix would fly from the ashes
to heaven, a promise to the ancients of resurrection.
   But two years ago, the city became far more than legend to
construction workers digging the foundation for an engineering
school at <ORGANIZATION>Ein Shams University</ORGANIZATION>, named for the <DATE>spring</DATE> where ancient
Egyptians believed the sun took its daily baths <TIME>morning and night</TIME>.
   As they dug, they unearthed evidence of a tomb, the first of an
eventual 15 that archaeologists would find.
   On a recent day at the dig, a tin can sat on the ground, holding
hundreds of colorful mummy beads that once adorned the dead. Skulls,
pieces of mummies hacked by grave robbers searching for jewelry and
layers of mummy wrappings were clearly evident in the
cross-sectioned hillside, frozen in time.
   To the din of nearby construction, excavators gingerly removed
remains with picks and shovels.
   A mile away, inspectors are excavating a large cemetery with
tombs decorated for officials 2,500 years ago. Sarcophagi line
uneven ground where a high-rise had been planned.
   Al-Matariya's Abdel-Galil, a soft-spoken man, constantly tours
such excavation sites, trying to piece together the meaning of
relics saved from steam shovel and pile driver. His work takes him
bumping from one rocky road to another, from modern suburb to remote
village, a 10-minute trip through a time tunnel.
   He said the most important find so far is a mile-long double
mud-brick wall separating a suburb from farming fields. According to
surviving accounts of early travelers to ancient <LOCATION>Heliopolis</LOCATION>, the
wall stretched for more than three miles, surrounding an enormous
city.
   In a quiet village about a mile from the wall, Abdel-Galil walked
among columns heralding the exploits of pharaohs <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Ramses IV</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We think a large temple of <ORGANIZATION>Ramses III</ORGANIZATION> is near here, maybe under
the fields,'' Abdel-Galil said. ``We have to find out, but we have
problems. The villagers don't have a sense of history.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Jan. 29</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910701-0124
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910701-0124.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Making a Difference -- Curricula of Color:
   Course Work Stressing
   Blacks' Role Has Critics
   But Appears Effective
   ---
   In Atlanta Schools, Teachers
   See Rise in Self-Esteem,
   Interest and Test Scores
   ---
   Africa as Wellspring of Science
   ----
   By Gary Putka
</HL>
<DATE>
07/01/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<GV>
EDUCATION DEPARTMENT (EDN)
</GV>
<RE>
DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA (DC)
GEORGIA (GA)
INDIANA (IND)
MARYLAND (MD)
MICHIGAN (MI)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
OREGON (ORG)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
WISCONSIN (WI)
</RE>
<LP>
   {One in an occasional series}
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   ATLANTA -- <PERSON>Ollie Smith</PERSON>'s third-graders are willing.
   "The number is 2,427," says <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>, a teacher at
<ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Avenue Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> here. An eager volunteer,
one of 17 blacks in a class of 18, walks to the blackboard
beneath the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> flag in a scene familiar to anyone -- until
the chalk moves.
   Instead of the numeral 2, the girl draws two lotus
flowers, followed by four coiled ropes, two oxen yokes, and
seven vertical strokes.
   "Very good, <PERSON>Jeannette</PERSON>," says <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>, praising a
perfect rendition of 2,427 in ancient Egyptian hieroglyphics.
"You can take your seat."
   <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>'s arithmetic lesson is part of a new
Africa-centered curriculum that is fast spreading in urban
schools. <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, are in various stages of similar
course-content changes that stress, to a high degree, the
history and culture of black people.
   This approach, sometimes called "Afrocentric," claims that
typical school textbooks have played down or outright ignored
black scholars, writers and mathematicians. One of a set of
essays used in Afrocentrist curricula sees "the vision of the
African people as being the wellspring of creativity and
knowledge on which the foundation of all science, technology
and engineering rests, and draws continuing inspiration."
   Many prominent scholars say the claims of the
Afrocentrists are grossly inaccurate, as well as racially
inflammatory. According to the Afrocentric essays, for
example, Cleopatra was black and the rich culture of ancient
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> was largely African. That's why <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>'s students
learn hieroglyphics.
   But to say that <PERSON>Cleopatra</PERSON> was a black "is baloney," says
<PERSON>Frank Yurco</PERSON>, an expert on ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Field
Museum</ORGANIZATION>, who says the record of her Greek and Macedonian
lineage is well established. <PERSON>Mr. Yurco</PERSON> adds that to suggest,
as the teaching guides do, "that <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> derived from <LOCATION>Central
Africa</LOCATION> is a major distortion."
   Still, in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, the first black majority district to
introduce an African-oriented curriculum in all its schools,
there is mounting evidence of educational gains.
   Many principals and teachers say students are taking more
interest in school and raising their aspirations since the
African Infusion Project started. In 17 schools that piloted
"infusion" in the 1989-90 school year, the percentage of
students scoring at or above norms on standardized reading
and math tests rose by a higher rate than in the system as a
whole. Average attendance at the 17 schools rose by about a
percentage point to <PERCENT>91.5%</PERCENT>, catching up with the overall
district rate after trailing it in <DATE>1988-89</DATE>.
   "We have seen positive results," says <PERSON>Eunice Robinson</PERSON>, the
principal of <LOCATION>Cleveland Avenue</LOCATION>, where students at or above
reading norms shot up to <PERCENT>64%</PERCENT> of enrollment in the <DATE>spring of
1990</DATE>, from <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>. <PERSON>Sherman Lofton</PERSON>, principal of <ORGANIZATION>Brown High
School</ORGANIZATION> in one of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s poorer black neighborhoods, adds:
"It really helps kids with their self-esteem. We've got more
saying they want to go to college and training school."
   Curriculum change is one of many new efforts aimed at
improving the education of black children, especially in the
inner cities, where traditional methods don't seem to be
working. In the 37 years since the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> struck down
segregated schools, blacks have narrowed the educational gap
with whites, but still lag badly in college-admissions and
other test scores, graduation and college-going rates.
   Proposed remedies are becoming more radical. Some blacks
favor vouchers they could use at private schools. <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> have considered schools exclusively for
black boys that would concentrate on providing role models
and other help. Ironically, they must overcome the legal
legacy of the desegregation decision to get them started.
   Proponents of Afrocentrism say it offers something for all
schools. In <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, the first major system to endorse
increased African input, <PERCENT>74%</PERCENT> of students are white. The
school board there plans to add American Indian, Hispanic and
Asian course plans to the African-American Baseline Essays,
or teaching guides, that already have been developed.
   Atlanta and other cities with African approaches haven't
focused on curricula tailored to other minorities. They are
merely trying to more effectively address large black
majorities.
   The mere notion, though, that any school would tailor its
curriculum to an ethnic group draws many critics. <PERSON>Diane
Ravitch</PERSON>, an educational historian and the new <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
nominee to head research at the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Education</ORGANIZATION>, says
much of what is being done under the Afrocentric banner is
"teaching racial antagonism." What's more, she says, "To say
you're going to make another continent the center of your
curriculum, and center science, math and English around this
continent, is pedagogically unsound."
   Rising test scores don't make her feel any better about
it. "White southerners used to say to me, `We get the best
test scores in segregated schools. Why integrate?'" she
observes. "If we discovered that apartheid produced higher
test scores, would that make apartheid a good system?"
   But <PERSON>Asa Hilliard</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Georgia State University</ORGANIZATION> professor and
consultant on Africa-oriented learning, says, "There is a
massive amount of validated non-trivial data about <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
that is missing from schools, data without which the general
events in many areas of content can't be understood. I simply
advocate that the record be researched and the most truthful
picture possible be given in the curriculum. I don't think
that can be done without including African and black people
in every subject."
   In many ways, the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> public schools are an ideal
crucible for the Afrocentric approach. Enrollment, now about
59,600, has been declining for years, first because of white
flight from desegregation and more recently because of a low
opinion by the public, both white and black, of school
quality. The system is as Afro-American as they come: <PERCENT>92%</PERCENT> of
students and <PERCENT>93%</PERCENT> of staff are black. Test scores,
college-enrollment and dropout rates are consistently among
the worst in <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>. Alarmed, business and school leaders
have launched studies of the problem. Afrocentrism emerged
from one of them.
   Teachers participating in the Afrocentric curriculum in
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> insist they are getting across the traditional
information all students need. In <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>'s class at
<LOCATION>Cleveland Avenue</LOCATION>, each drill in hieroglyphics also conveys
something about addition. When a student writes 214 as <PERSON>King
Tut</PERSON> did, for example, her classmates recite together, "200
plus 10 plus four."
   Similarly, in an African geography lesson at <ORGANIZATION>Sutton Middle
School</ORGANIZATION>, students demonstrate knowledge that might be useful
in a broader sphere. "What's a word for a high, flat land
mass?" asks <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Stanley</ORGANIZATION>, a sixth-grade teacher.
"Plateau," says one of many students with hands up.
Classmates quickly define arid tracts as deserts, find the
Strait of <LOCATION>Gibraltar</LOCATION> on a world map, and relate how sleepiness
induced by the bite of tse-tse fly kills both cattle and
people. <PERSON>Ms. Stanley</PERSON>'s students, about a third of whom are
white, later get a lesson about a Medieval pilgrimage to
Mecca by <PERSON>Mansa Mussa</PERSON>, king of <LOCATION>Mali</LOCATION>.
   In teaching from a black perspective, though, the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>
schools do cover material many white adults don't know. They
also prompt black students to consider racial questions they
might not otherwise ponder. When world history teacher <PERSON>Jill
Beracki</PERSON> guides her tenth-grade class at <ORGANIZATION>Frederick Douglass
High School</ORGANIZATION> through the Industrial Revolution, familiar
themes are explored. But the tour also goes by way of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
with a major stopover in the African diaspora.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Beracki</PERSON> wants to know "why <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> led the way" in
industrialization, and her students respond. "Skilled labor
force," says one. Government policies and naval prowess are
discussed. Then discussion turns to sources of raw materials
in British colonies and other matters. When, 10 minutes into
the period, <PERSON>Mrs. Beracki</PERSON> asks what role blacks played in the
Industrial Revolution, her students say it can't be found in
the textbook.
   "This book is written from a European point-of-view," says
student <ORGANIZATION>Emanuel Easter</ORGANIZATION> matter-of-factly. "It doesn't really
focus on black Americans." Classmate <PERSON>Tommy Phillips</PERSON> agrees.
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, he says, gets "two whole chapters" in this unit.
"<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the whole rest of the world is just one
little section."
   "For some reason," <PERSON>Mrs. Beracki</PERSON> tells the class, "black
Americans have been omitted from the history of
industrialization. As a compensation, I've asked you to do
some reports on black inventors." There is no lack of raised
hands when <PERSON>Mrs. Beracki</PERSON> asks for someone to start.
   Emanuel tells of <PERSON>Garrett Morgan</PERSON>, a Clevelander who created
the first traffic light and gas mask. Makila Sands did her
report on <PERSON>Elijah McCoy</PERSON>, possibly the namesake for the "real
McCoy," she says, because his automatic machine lubricator
was much copied but never replicated. A somewhat
self-conscious student gets up and turns to face the class.
"I want to tell you about <PERSON>James Matzeliger</PERSON>," he says with a
nervous stutter. "He was born in <LOCATION>Lynn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1852</DATE>. . . .
He made Lynn the shoe capital of the world. . . . They
couldn't make a machine to sew soles to last. People said it
was impossible to make such a machine."
   But <PERSON>James Matzeliger</PERSON>, a black man, did it.
   Much research shows that students do better when schools
involve parents and the community in education. One of the
goals of the Afro-based curriculum is to improve this
involvement in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, where the black community is the main
one served by public schools.
   One bright chilly morning, 17 community volunteers gather
in the library of <LOCATION>Cleveland Avenue Elementary</LOCATION>, making
preparations for a day of African storytelling and readings
of black American poetry. Some wear the colorful native garb
of <LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION>, but others sport a more conventional business
look. That's more important than middle-class people might
know, says <PERSON>Eunice Robinson</PERSON>, the principal.
   "We have children who don't usually see black males in
suits and ties," she says. "This give them a chance to see
that black males don't all shoot dope. These kids can tell
you what the dope dealer wears, and what he drives, but they
can't tell you how a black businessman is supposed to look."
   Dispersing to the classrooms, the volunteers read aloud
tales such as "Why Mosquitoes Buzz in Peoples' Ears" and "How
the Rabbit Lost His Tail." <PERSON>Brieu Madison</PERSON>, a local college
student, dons a housedress and head scarf to play a sarcastic
mother, rousing a lazy child from sleep in the <PERSON>Paul Laurence
Dunbar</PERSON> poem "In the Morning." Avid fifth-graders come forward
to act alongside her, and a tangle of hands shoots up when
<PERSON>Ms. Madison</PERSON> asks for comment on a <PERSON>Langston Hughes</PERSON> poem.
   After applauding, several students wonder aloud what it
might be like to be an actor. <ORGANIZATION>Nse Ufot</ORGANIZATION>, a fifth grade fan,
pens an acrostic to <PERSON>Ms. Madison</PERSON>, using her first name:
"Brilliant, Radiant . . . Important . . . Enthusiastic,
Unbeatable."
   Infusion has altered what goes on in many <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>
classrooms, but as with any major curricular change,
implementation has been spotty. In the 1989-1990 school year,
17 pilot schools were supposed to redesign their curriculum
at every grade, while five others were picked to introduce
the program in selected classes. For the year just ended, the
entire system was supposed to be "infusing" at every grade
level in every subject, but the district admits that outside
of math and social studies, implementation has been spotty.
   Afrocentrism isn't merely changing content, but methods as
well. In subjects like history and English, black and African
contributions can be included without much altering the way
subject matter is covered. It's merely a matter of changing
some of the people and literature studied.
   But in science and math, the fit is more difficult. At
<LOCATION>Cleveland Avenue</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mrs. Smith</PERSON>'s students learn Egyptian
numerals before Roman numerals. The system also wants
teachers to personalize math and science. Geometry is
traditionally covered with only a passing reference to <LOCATION>Euclid</LOCATION>
and Pythagoras; but <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> wants black mathematicians and
their contributions not only to be mentioned, but to serve as
a pivot for lessons.
   In a fifth-grade class, teacher <PERSON>Loretta Palmer</PERSON> readies a
special lesson. "We're going to take a lesson in math and
social studies together," she announces. "Our lesson is going
to be about time, with someone who was very concerned with
time" -- <PERSON>Benjamin Banneker</PERSON>, mathematician and maker of the
first clock in colonial <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   At any opportunity, <PERSON>Mrs. Palmer</PERSON> strives to include a black
message. When subtraction exercises concern a boy who is
always late, she tells her children "Benjamin Banneker loved
to be on time." With the objective of the day -- "Solve a
problem involving time" -- on the blackboard, she tells the
class, "That's part of your great heritage, to be there on
time."
   After class, <PERSON>Mrs. Robinson</PERSON>, the principal, asks the
children to talk about their black and African-American
heroes and knowledge. Adrian, an irrepressible contributor,
says his hero is "King Tut -- he was king of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>."
   Turning phrases like a practiced orator, young <PERSON>Daron
Walters</PERSON> says what he knows: "<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> has been going on for
millions and millions of years. I know this because of
stories I have read. I have learned about great men who ruled
1,363 years before Christ, and seen masks that men made
before Christ was born." When asked who some of these
pre-Christian kings were, he mentions "<PERSON>Shaka Zulu</PERSON>." It is an
error. Shaka was indeed a Zulu king, but of the <DATE>19th century</DATE>
A.D.
   Returning to her office, <PERSON>Mrs. Robinson</PERSON> is beaming with
pride, but feeling somewhat apologetic. "When you hear my
children, you hear wrong answers," says <PERSON>Mrs. Robinson</PERSON>. "I
hear answers where there were no answers before."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051590-0018 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 218912 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 15, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 9; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
746 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BOOK REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
A SPECIAL TEXT PRESENTS MATH AS AN ART FORM; 
</P>
<P>
JOURNEY THROUGH GENIUS: THE GREAT THEOREMS OF MATHEMATICS BY WILLIAM DUNHAM 
JOHN WILEY &amp; SONS $19.95, 300 PAGES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DEMBART 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Reviewing a book a week doesn't allow much time to stop and dawdle, but 
"Journey Through Genius" is one that I wanted to savor for a while. It's a very 
special math book, as good as any popular book in the subject sincT. Bell wrote 
"Men of Mathematics" in <DATE>1937</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
There's probably no such thing as a math book for people who don't like 
mathematics, but "Journey Through Genius" comes close. <PERSON>William Dunham</PERSON>, a 
mathematician at <ORGANIZATION>Hanover College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, has written an inspired piece of 
intellectual history that explains a dozen of the greatest theorems in the 
history of mathematics, placing them in their historical contexts in the larger 
world as well as in the narrower world of pure thought. 
</P>
<P>
For example, his chapter on <ORGANIZATION>Euclid</ORGANIZATION>'s proof of the Pythagorean theorem ("In a 
right triangle, the square of the hypotenuse is equal to the sum of the squares 
of the other two sides") gives a rounded synopsis of the history of mathematics 
and the history of <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> before turning to <LOCATION>Euclid</LOCATION>, geometry and right 
triangles. 
</P>
<P>
To get to the Pythagorean theorem, which is the 47th proposition in the first 
book of Euclid's "Elements," <PERSON>Dunham</PERSON> marches straight through the first 46 
propositions, arguing that the 47th is the emotional climax, the theorem to 
which all the others point. 
</P>
<P>
Similarly, the chapter on <PERSON>Isaac Newton</PERSON>, which includes a terrific description 
of <ORGANIZATION>Newton</ORGANIZATION>'s approximation of pi, begins by placing <ORGANIZATION>Newton</ORGANIZATION> in the same century 
as <PERSON>Cervantes</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>, as well as <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Descartes</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pascal</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Fermat</ORGANIZATION>. 
Logarithms were perfected and introduced just before <PERSON>Newton</PERSON> was born in <DATE>1642</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
(The book has a welcome paragraph on logarithms. We who take pocket calculators 
and computers for granted should recall this early and very successful method 
for speeding up arithmetic. A century later, Pierre-Simon <LOCATION>Laplace</LOCATION> observed that 
logarithms "by shortening the labors doubled the life of the astronomer." By 
what factor have computers lengthened scientists' lives today?) 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dunham</PERSON>'s project is to treat mathematics like an art form: Just as great 
novels, great symphonies and great paintings are the objects of study in 
appreciating literature, music and art, theorems are the appropriate objects of 
study in appreciating mathematics. 
</P>
<P>
When he describes the actual proof of the theorem, the timeless logical insight 
that solved a problem in pure thought, <PERSON>Dunham</PERSON>'s descriptions are crystal clear. 
Not all of them are easy (<PERSON>Cardano</PERSON> and the solution of the cube and <PERSON>Cantor</PERSON>'s 
investigation of the transfinite realm, for example). 
</P>
<P>
But they all reward effort. They are written for interested, non-specialist 
readers -- preferably those who enjoyed high school math and remember some of 
it. 
</P>
<P>
Dunham notes that mathematics is built on the twin pillars of arithmetic and 
geometry -- numbers and space -- and they have alternately held sway as long as 
people have thought about such things. As a result, the book embraces geometry 
(<ORGANIZATION>Archimedes</ORGANIZATION>' "On the Sphere and the Cylinder") and numbers (<ORGANIZATION>Euler</ORGANIZATION>'s number 
theory). In each case, <PERSON>Dunham</PERSON> lucidly describes the problem and then equally 
lucidly presents the ingenious solution. 
</P>
<P>
Unlike any other sphere of human inquiry, the truths of mathematics, once 
proved, are proved forever. They do not rest on experiment or judgment or 
opinion. They rest on naked logic. 
</P>
<P>
In general, we think of Greek science as quaint, if anything, but we read 
Euclid with awe. Twenty-three centuries later, its beauty is still compelling. 
</P>
<P>
Dunham's book captures and conveys the power behind mathematical proof. 
Mathematics is the science of pure thought. I shudder to think it. 
</P>
<P>
The book contains a fair amount about the characters who do mathematics. It 
takes a special kind of person to muck about in naked logic, and these 
peculiarities sometimes manifest themselves in other aspects of mathematicians' 
lives. They tend to be odd people. 
</P>
<P>
But most important is their work. Having opened up for examination a dozen 
great theorems, <PERSON>Dunham</PERSON> wonders what about them makes them great and concludes, 
with <PERSON>G. H. Hardy</PERSON>, that they possess "economy, inevitability and 
unexpectedness." 
</P>
<P>
In that sense, too, mathematics is like art. The combination of inevitability 
and unexpectedness packs unbeatable emotional appeal. 
</P>
<P>
OK. So this isn't a book for everyone. I wish it were. But for those who like 
this sort of thing, this book is a gem. 
</P>
<P>
Next: <PERSON>Jonathan Kirsch</PERSON> reviews "Shark Tank: Greed, Politics and the Collapse of 
Finley Kumble" by <PERSON>Kim Isaac Eisler</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010990-0127 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 159603 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 9, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 1; Column 2; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
987 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JIM MURRAY: A NECESSITY FOR MAKING SUPER BOWL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JIM MURRAY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Don't look now but events over the weekend in pro football seem to give ringing 
endorsement to one of my long-cherished <ORGANIZATION>Murray's Laws of Athletic Probability</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
You all know what these laws are, if you've been paying attention: propositions 
as immutable as <ORGANIZATION>Pythagoras</ORGANIZATION>' Theorem. 
</P>
<P>
You may not ordinarily think of me as a man of science -- I have trouble 
opening a fuse box -- but when it comes to sports behavior I am infallible. I 
have decades of observable phenomena to verify me. 
</P>
<P>
For instance, who can quarrel with <PERSON>Murray</PERSON>'s Law of geographic probability: 
"Whatever can go to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, will?" That is as demonstrably true as the rule 
of geometry that sides opposite equal angles are equal. Even its corollary is 
true: "Whatever can go to <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, won't." 
</P>
<P>
Then, there is the tried and true <PERSON>Murray</PERSON>'s Law that, "On any obvious passing 
situation late in an <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> game, the quarterback can help himself to 15 to 20 
yards anytime he wants." This happens so often, the point need not be 
belabored. 
</P>
<P>
But what has heartened me considerably over this past week is the prove-out of 
one of <ORGANIZATION>Murray</ORGANIZATION>'s All-Time Pet Laws. It is this: "Quarterbacks get you to the 
Super Bowl." 
</P>
<P>
Now, I admit it does not have the ring of basic theorems of history as, "The 
of the other two sides," but it is, nonetheless, equally valid and provable. 
</P>
<P>
Look at the Super Bowl tournament. Every team in it has a prime quarterback on 
hand. As usual. 
</P>
<P>
Let's examine what we have: <PERSON>Joe Montana</PERSON>? Well, of course. What more do you need 
to say? He comes with the Super Bowl. If he ain't in it, it ain't a Super Bowl. 
<PERSON>John Elway</PERSON>? Natch! Here's a guy who has put mediocre teams in <LOCATION>Super Bowls</LOCATION>. 
Elway is the most perfect proof of <ORGANIZATION>Murray</ORGANIZATION>'s Law there is. Can you think of any 
other reason why <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> is always in a Super Bowl -- or right next to it? 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bernie Kosar</PERSON>. Look! This may be the really smartest quarterback in the game. He 
unloads the ball in a kind of ungainly sidearm motion like a guy dropping a 
suitcase, but let me tell you something, <PERSON>Stan Musial</PERSON> didn't have the best 
batting form you ever saw. Neither did <PERSON>Ty Cobb</PERSON>. Kosar's passes look just fine 
on a scoreboard. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim Everett</PERSON>? Well, he's a relative newcomer, some would say untried. But let me 
put it this way -- is there another quarterback besides the ones we've already 
mentioned who's any better? <PERSON>Dan Marino</PERSON>? Perhaps. 
</P>
<P>
The history of the Super Bowl is, you go there, so to speak, on the arm. 
Certainly, not the hoof. 
</P>
<P>
Check the records: The only possibly unqualified QB in the long history of the 
Super Bowl might be <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>David Woodley</PERSON> in <DATE>1983</DATE>. No one ever mixed <PERSON>David</PERSON> up 
with <PERSON>Sammy Baugh</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
For the rest, there was almost always a legend or semi-legend in the irons. 
<PERSON>Fran Tarkenton</PERSON> used to get his team in the Super Bowl. <PERSON>Joe Namath</PERSON> did it. <PERSON>Bart 
Starr</PERSON> did it. <PERSON>Lenny Dawson</PERSON>. <PERSON>Roger Staubach</PERSON>. <PERSON>Otto Graham</PERSON> would have. 
</P>
<P>
It's the one constant in a Super Bowl game. 
</P>
<P>
None of this appears to rub off on general managers. Given the presence of 
all-hype running backs in the <DATE>spring</DATE> draft, they fall all over themselves to 
pick up 1,000-yard runners, Heisman winners, speed freaks. They usually pass up 
quarterbacks. "Not a good year for QB's," they usually sniff. 
</P>
<P>
Why? Have you noticed <PERSON>Eric Dickerson</PERSON> isn't even in the Super Bowl hunt? Never 
