<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881107-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-07-88 0735EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-Brazil-IndianBacker Adv17   11-07 0921</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Brazil-Indian Backer, Adv 17,0942</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv17</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs PMs Nov. 17 or Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>American Naturalist Helping Brazilian Indians Faces Jail</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE HANDLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An American tropical insect expert
faces a possible prison term in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> for backing native Indians
trying to stop the building of hydroelectric dams that could flood
their tribal lands in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Darrell Posey</PERSON>, 41, a native of <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, who holds a Ph.D.
from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Georgia</ORGANIZATION>, has been charged by <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s federal
police under a law that prohibits foreigners from ``getting involved
in internal Brazilian affairs'' and ``denigrating the country's
image.'' The maximum penalty is three years in prison, followed by
expulsion.
   Authorities also have forbidden the stocky, bearded, soft-spoken
naturalist from entering certain areas inhabited by native tribes
with which he has worked since <DATE>1977</DATE>. And, under the threat of
dismissal from his Brazilian government job as a professor-level
researcher for the <ORGANIZATION>National Research Council</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> is barred from
leaving <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   ``The <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle is being destroyed at an a alarming rate,''
<PERSON>Posey</PERSON> recently told a group of foreign correspondents in <LOCATION>Rio de
Janeiro</LOCATION>. ``Meanwhile, native Indians have lived in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> for
20,000 years in perfect coexistence with the environment. I'm trying
to call serious attention to the native philosophy for preserving
ecology.
   ``How can that be considered subversive?''
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> traditionally has eyed the vast hydroelectric potential of
the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> as a way to expand its already sophisticated industrial
base, situated mostly in the southern part of the country.
   Posey irked Brazilian authorities when earlier this year he took
two chiefs of the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe to a seminar at the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Florida</ORGANIZATION> where they spoke against reported government hydroelectric
projects in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> and then to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> where they repeated
their views to the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, which frequently helps finance such
projects.
   ``It was the first time outsiders got to hear the Indians' side
of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> development story,'' <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said. Chiefs Kube-i and
<PERSON>Paulinho Paiakan</PERSON>, wearing native headdresses and collars and jungle
body paint, addressed their <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> hosts in Portuguese, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
official language, and <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> translated.
   In an inexplicable move, the government also indicted the
Indians, who were born in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and never had been out of the
country before, for violating the Foreigners Law.
   ``The charges against the Indians have no legal basis. We'll get
the accusations thrown out,'' said <PERSON>Jose Carlos Castro</PERSON>, a lawyer in
the Amazon-delta city of <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> is based. ``The real
purpose is to intimidate Professor <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> and make him shut up.''
   ``This is purely political,'' added <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>, who along with Kube-i
and Paiakan, also met with foreign reporters.
   ``We tried to get information about dams from our own
government,'' said <PERSON>Paiakan</PERSON>. ``But they wouldn't tell us anything.
They treated us like children. So we went to the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, and it
turned out they didn't know much about these projects. Now they do.''
   Federal power officials deny claims by radical environmentalists
that they have a ``secret plan'' to build 26 hydroelectric dams
along <LOCATION>Amazon River</LOCATION> tributaries where Indians from 11 tribes,
including the 8,500-member Kaiapos, live, fish and hunt in
relatively untouched primitive conditions.
   Of the estimated 5 million Indians here when Portuguese explorers
discovered <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>, only around 250,000 remain, in an
over-all population of 144 million. Anthropologists have expressed
fears about the Indians' continued survival, as hundreds of
thousands of non-Indian homesteaders, ranchers and prospectors
stream into the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> annually, chopping and burning away the
rainforest and ignoring demarcations of native tribal areas.
   ``There have been a lot of gossip and rumors about hydroelectric
plans in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Diomedes Ferreira Jr.</PERSON>, the spokesman for a
government Amazonian power company called Eletronorte (cq
Eletronorte), said in <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>, the capital. ``We have looked into
only six potential dam sites, and we're talking about projects that
wouldn't be carried out until well into the <DATE>21st century</DATE>.''
   ``The government will do everything possible to protect the
environment and the Indians,'' <PERSON>Ferreira</PERSON> said.
   Meanwhile _ and without saying whether the Indians' sudden high
profile had anything to do with it _ the government says it has
shelved plans for a proposed dam known as Babaquara on the <LOCATION>Xingu
River</LOCATION>, a major <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> tributary that passes through the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION>
lands. Its reservoir would have covered 2,300 square miles, twice
the size of <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> had intended to ask the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>
to finance it.
   Now, says <PERSON>Ferreira</PERSON>, the only Xingu dam under possible
consideration is one called <PERSON>Kararao</PERSON>, with a reservoir one-fifth the
size of that of Babaquara.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> said construction of the 11
million-kilowatt Kararao installation _ nearly twice as large as
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s Grand Coulee Dam, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>' biggest _ could
not begin until <DATE>1991</DATE> or <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ferreira</PERSON> said, ``So far we're talking only about hydroelectric
potential feasibility studies. We're not saying Kararao will be
built. But even if it is, there wouldn't be another dam in that
region before <DATE>2010</DATE>.''
   Nonetheless, a <ORGANIZATION>Kayapo Legal Fund</ORGANIZATION>, partially coordinated by <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>,
an eye on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> dam situation.
   The Kayapos plan to call a multitribal meeting of up to 5,000
Indians in late <DATE>January</DATE> to discuss the overall problem of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
development projects.
   ``The Indians are serious,'' said <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>. ``The problem is that
hardly anyone takes them seriously _ and they have so much to teach
us.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Thurs PMs Nov. 17</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890215-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-89 2209EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     02-15 0456</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0468</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Suspends Trial Of Indians And American</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge has suspended the trial of
two Indian chiefs and a American who were charged with criticizing
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> during a trip to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, an official said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Federal <PERSON>Judge Milton Luiz Pereira</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> halted the trial of
American <PERSON>Darrell Posey</PERSON> and chiefs Kube-I and <PERSON>Paulo Paiakan</PERSON> because
of ``unsound accusations and a lack of just cause,'' <PERSON>Claudia de
Oliveira</PERSON>, an official in the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Appeals Court</ORGANIZATION>, said by
telephone from <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>.
   Kube-I and <PERSON>Paiakan</PERSON>, both of the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe, and <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>, 41, a
native of <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, and an expert on tropical insects, were
accused of breaking <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s foreigners law during a trip last year
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, where they denounced the white man's
encroachment upon Indian lands in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   Brazilian law prohibits foreigners from making political
statements or interfering in the country's legal affairs.
   The trial caused a sensation in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> because it marked the
first time native Indians had been legally considered foreigners.
Legally, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s 220,000 Indians are wards of the state and do not
have the full rights of other citizens.
   Pereira ordered the trial suspended because Kube-I and Paiakan
were found to be ``native Brazilians recognized by the federal
constitution'' and because <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> resident, proved he had
acted solely as a language interpreter when the remarks were made,
de <PERSON>Oliveira</PERSON> said.
   The court's action appeared to be an attempt by the government to
back off the controversial case. De Oliveira would not comment on
why the judge suspended the trial instead of simply throwing the
charges out.
   He said the proceedings could be renewed but the possibility of
that was ``very, very unlikely.''
   The trial began in <DATE>August</DATE> in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, capital of the northern
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle state of Para.
   The Brazilian government charged the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs and <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> with
illegal political activities after they spoke at <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Florida
International University</ORGANIZATION> about forest conservation. <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said he
attended the forum as a friend and interpreter for the chiefs.
   Soon after the forum, environmental groups invited Paiakan and
Kube-I to speak to the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, where they
criticized deforestation in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle, erosion, mercury
pollution from gold mining, and the construction of hydroelectric
projects that caused flooding in low-lying jungle areas and
displaced Indian tribes.
   Later, the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> held back funds for the Xingu hydroelectric
project, which would have inundated an estimated 18.8 million acres
of mostly Indian land.
   Many Brazilian observers credited the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs with blocking
the project.
   But <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>, also a federal researcher in the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian National
Research Council</ORGANIZATION>, said funding had been suspended because of
financing problems with the government power company Eletronorte.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890220-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-20-89 1507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     02-20 0670</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amazon Tribes Join Against Dams that Would Flood Their Lands</HEAD>
<UNK>By PETER MUELLO ^Associated Press Writer</UNK>
<DATELINE>ALTAMIRA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of Indians, painted for war and
representing tribes of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, began a historic effort <DATE>Monday</DATE> to
stop the government from building two hydroelectric dams that would
flood native lands.
   It is the first time diverse tribes from the vast <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain
forest have joined in a political movement.
   ``We will bring Indian peoples together, to fight,'' said Chief
Sebirop of the Gaviao tribe. ``We will not accept the dams. Where
will we live? What will we eat?''
   He and the others oppose construction of the Kararao and
Babaquara dams on the <LOCATION>Xingu River</LOCATION>, a major <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> tributary, which
would flood an estimated 3,000 square miles of rain forest and
displace 7,000 Indians.
   Thousands of pro-dam demonstrators in trucks, cars and on
horseback paraded through the streets of this remote jungle town
carrying signs reading ``The dams mean more jobs and more progress''
and ``Gringos leave us in peace.'' Airplanes with banners carrying
similar slogans buzzed overhead.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has about 220,000 Indians in a total population of 144
million. Historians say the number has declined from about 5 million
when Portuguese explorers landed in <DATE>1500</DATE>.
   Tribes along the Xingu face opposition from government and
industry, which say the power the dams would generate is vital to
economic growth.
   About 500 Indian men, women and children from more than 20 tribes
attended the opening session of the conference <DATE>Monday</DATE> at a brick
community center in this city of 38,000 people 2,000 miles northwest
of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   Included were 100 warriors from the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe, the main
organizer of the gathering. They ran into the center chanting,
wearing green-and-yellow feathered headdresses and daubed with red
and black war paint.
   They circled in a ritual dance, then put palm ronds on the
concrete floor and sat. Kayapo women carrying machetes, many with
young children, sat around the group.
   Whites predominated in the crowd packing the concrete bleachers
and the auditorium's balcony. They cheered and applauded as each
tribal delegation arrived.
   Brazilian and foreign environmentalists were among the onlookers.
Foreign organizations represented included the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Defense
Fund</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, and Friends of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, which has its
headquarters in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   Chiefs stepped onto a wooden platform in turn and spoke about the
dams.
   ``We want the goverment to rethink the dams, said <PERSON>Jorge Terena</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>Terena</ORGANIZATION> tribe. ``The land is sacred to us. It has the roots of
our culture and our ancestors. The electricity won't benefit
Indians, only whites and their industries.''
   <PERSON>David Yanomami</PERSON> of the primitive <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION> tribe that recently won
a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> ``Global 500 '' award for defense of the environmental
defense, took the platform and declared: ``We will not accept the
dams. The river will rise. The fish will die. The game will move
away.''
   All the chiefs spoke in Portuguese, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s national language,
sometimes with accents and imperfect grammar.
   Some Kayapos made a videotape of the meeting to replay for their
villages.
   The Indians invited President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> and ranking Cabinet
ministers to the meeting, but the government sent <PERSON>Fernando Mesquita</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Environment Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   Boos and whistles came from the crowd when <PERSON>Mesquita</PERSON> said: ``We
recognize that great indignities were committed against the Indian
people, but now it is a question of national awareness. We are here
to listen.''
   Sarney, who was out of the country <DATE>Monday</DATE>, has said he favors
protecting of Indians and the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> environment but does not want
foreigners telling him how.
   The government has temporarily shelved plans for the Babaquara
dam but is actively studying the Kararao project, which is intended
to produce 11 million kilowatts.
   Officials say work on Kararao could start in the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>.
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has approached the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> about partial financing.
   Environmentalists are trying to discourage the bank and other
international lending institutions from putting money into Third
World development projects considered harmful to the environment or
native peoples.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880826-0223 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-88 2040EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-Anthropologist     08-26 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Anthropologist,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazil Threatens Kentucky Scientist and Indians with Expulsion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> anthropologist and two
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> Indian chiefs were arraigned <DATE>Friday</DATE> on charges of engaging
in illegal political activities and could be expelled from <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Darrell Posey</PERSON>, 41, of <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, and chiefs <PERSON>Paulo Paiakan</PERSON>
and Kube-I of the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe were accused of breaking <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
Foreigners Law during a trip to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> this year.
   The law, passed in <DATE>1980</DATE> when <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> was under a military
government, prohibits non-Brazilian residents or visitors from
speaking out publicly on domestic political issues.
   The trial has caused a sensation here. It is first time native
Indians have been legally considered foreigners.
   Posey's lawyer, well-known human rights defender <PERSON>Jose Carlos
Castro</PERSON>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the trial was suspended ``at least until
<DATE>December</DATE>'' because Kube-I had returned to his village for the
harvest and festival period and refused to show up at court.
   The court gave Kube-I 90 days to present himself for arraignment.
   ``This is a landmark case. I've been studying native peoples for
24 years, and this is the first time a native group has been
considered foreign by a white government,'' <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said by telephone
from his office in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, a city at the mouth of the <LOCATION>Amazon River</LOCATION>
2,140 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   He said the two <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs were invited by <ORGANIZATION>Florida
International University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to speak about forest
conservation. <PERSON>Posey</PERSON>, who has lived and worked in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> since <DATE>1977</DATE>,
said he went along as a friend and interpreter.
   ``They (the two Indians) said they were worried about
deforestation in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, erosion, mercury pollution from gold
mining, and hydroelectric projects that displace Indian tribes.
They're especially upset at the Xingu project that will inundate
about ... (18.8 million acres) of land, mostly Indian territory,''
<PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said.
   The Kayapos number about 5,500 and live in the southern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
jungle.
   Environmental groups later invited Paiakan and Kube-I to speak
to the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The bank suspended funding for the
Xingu project.
   Many Brazilians believe the Indians were responsible for
blocking the project, but <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said funding already had been
suspended because of financing problems with the government power
company Eletronorte.
   The trial began <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>3rd Federal Court of
Para</ORGANIZATION>, a northern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle state. If found guilty, the three
face a prison term of up to three years each and expulsion from
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   It was not clear where the Indians could be expelled to.
   ``That's a very interesting question. But it's the government's
problem,'' <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said.
   Legally, Indians are wards of the state and don't have the full
rights of other citizens.
   <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said he felt the trial was an attempt by the government to
intimidate scientists and native Indians and keep them from
speaking out on politically sensitive issues.
   ``No matter what the outcome of the trial is, the effects will
be very unpleasant. I am prohibited from working in any Indian area
as long as the case is pending. My work is paralyzed,'' he said.
   The Foreigners Law was enacted and often used by the military
governments that ruled <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> from <DATE>1964</DATE> to <DATE>1985</DATE>. Foreign priests
and students who spoke out about political affairs were charged and
sometimes expelled from the country.
   However, this is the first time the law has been used since
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> returned to civilian rule in <DATE>1985</DATE> under President <PERSON>Jose
Sarney</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said he wasn't afraid of being expelled.
   ``If I'm found guilty ... I wouldn't want to stay here any
more.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881014-0238 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-14-88 2218EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     10-14 0515</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indians in Tribal Garb Protest Outside Courthouse</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 350 <ORGANIZATION>Amazon Indians</ORGANIZATION>
wearing loincloths and warpaint protested <DATE>Friday</DATE> outside a
courthouse where their chief appeared for a hearing on alleged
illegal political activities, a lawyer said.
   Federal <PERSON>Judge Iran Velasco</PERSON> do Nascimento canceled the hearing
because chief Kube-I appeared before the court in a loincloth,
which the judge said was disrespectful, said Kube-I's lawyer, <PERSON>Jose
Carlos Castro</PERSON>.
   Kube-I, chief <PERSON>Paulo Paiakan</PERSON>, both of the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe, and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
anthropologist <PERSON>Darrell Posey</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>, are accused of
breaking <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s foreigners law, which bans foreigners from making
political statements or interfering in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s internal affairs.
   During a trip to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>earlier this year</DATE>, the three
complained about the white man's encroachment upon Indian lands.
   The trial, which began in late <DATE>August</DATE>, has caused a sensation
because it is the first time native Indians have been legally
considered foreigners.
   At the hearing in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, 2,140 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>
in the northern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle state of <ORGANIZATION>Para</ORGANIZATION>, Kube-I told the judge
that as chief of his tribe he has never worn a suit and tie and
refused to begin doing so now, <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said.
   ``The judge then said Kube-I's decision to wear his tribal
clothes to the hearing was disrespectful and said the hearing was
no longer necessary,'' <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said.
   Outside the courthouse, <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said, more than 350 Kayapo
Indians in loincloths and green and yellow warpaint danced, chanted
tribal songs and shot arrows into nearby trees as they protested
the hearing. They were surrounded by heavily armed federal police
and more than 1,000 onlookers.
   <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> said he would file a petition to drop charges against the
two <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs on the grounds that they are Brazilian Indians
and cannot be tried as foreigners.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s 220,000 Indians, including 5,500 Kayapos, are wards of
the state and do not enjoy the full rights accorded other citizens.
   Posey, however, said in a telephone interview that he wanted to
see the trial continue because ``if it's shelved, it could be
brought against others in our situation.
   ``This is a real aggression against myself, the Indians, the
scientific community in general and we want to see justice done.''
   Posey and the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs were charged with illegal political
acitivites after they appeared at <ORGANIZATION>Florida International University</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to speak about forest conservation.
   Later, the chiefs spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>,
where they criticized the deforestation of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, erosion,
mercury pollution from gold mining, and hydroelectric projects that
displace Indian tribes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> later suspended funding for the Xingu
hydroelectric project, which will inundate about 18.8 million acres
of mostly Indian land.
   Many Brazilians believe the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> chiefs were responsible for
blocking the project. But <PERSON>Posey</PERSON> said funding already had been
suspended because of financing problems with the government power
company Eletronorte.
   Posey, 41, an anthropologist and biologist, is an outspoken
critic of the government's Indian policy. He has lived in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>
since the late <DATE>1970s</DATE> and already has been threatened with expulsion.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890221-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-21-89 0045EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-AmazonProtest Bjt   02-21 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Amazon Protest, Bjt,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Native Indians Meet to Protest Hydroelectric Dams</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALTAMIRA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In their first joint political action,
more than 500 Indians from 20 <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest tribes have
gathered in this jungle town to protest planned hydrolectric dams
that would flood their lands.
   Sporting green-and-yellow feathered headdresses and red and black
warpaint, about 100 warriors from the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe ran chanting into
a brick community center <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>Altamira</ORGANIZATION>, which is 2,000 miles
northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janiero</ORGANIZATION>.
   The tribe circled in a ritual dance, then sat to applaud as the
men, women and children of each subsequent tribe arrived for a week
of debates, speeches and other events.
   For the first time, <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> tribes were together to discuss common
concerns.
   The Indians are protesting the proposed Kararao and Babaquara
dams on the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>'s Xingu river. If built, the reservoirs would
flood about 3,000 square miles of jungle, displacing 7,000 of the
220,000 Indians who remain in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   About 5 million Indians roamed the country when the Portuguese
arrived in the <DATE>1500s</DATE> and ``settled'' what is now <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>'s
largest nation.
   Anthropologists have expressed fears about the Indians' continued
survival, as hundreds of thousands of non-Indian homesteaders,
ranchers and prospectors stream into the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> annually, chopping
and burning away the rain forest and ignoring demarcations of native
tribal areas.
   ``We want the government to rethink the dams,'' <PERSON>Jorge Terena</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>Terena</ORGANIZATION> tribe told a cheering crowd packed into the community
center. ``The land is sacred to us. It has the roots of our culture
and our ancestors.''
   ``We will not accept the dams,'' said <PERSON>David Yanomami</PERSON> of the
primitive <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION> tribe. ``The river will rise. The fish will die.
The game will move away.''
   Later in the day, thousands of farmers and local shopowners
marched through <ORGANIZATION>Altamira</ORGANIZATION>, a town of 38,000, carrying placards saying
``Dams mean more jobs and more progress'' and ``Gringos leave us in
peace.''
   ``I know the Indians will have problems, but I'm in favor of the
dams,'' said <PERSON>Raimundo Castro Bastos</PERSON>, owner of an <ORGANIZATION>Altamira</ORGANIZATION> bar. ``I
believe the dams will bring development and progress for us.''
   Government and industry leaders say the energy provided by the
dams is vital for the growth of this <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION> nation.
   The government representative to the meeting, <PERSON>Fernando Mesquita</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Environment Institute</ORGANIZATION>, spoke to whistles
and boos from the crowd, which included native Indian leaders from
around the world, hundreds of foreign and Brazilian
environmentalists, and droves of journalists.
   ``We recognize that great indignities were committed against the
Indian people. But now it is a question of national awareness. We
are here to listen,'' <PERSON>Mesquita</PERSON> said.
   The late <DATE>December</DATE> shooting death of internationally-known <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>
ecologist <PERSON>Francisco Mendes</PERSON>, who fought against the destruction of
the rain forest by ranchers, increased international awareness of
the movement to preserve the jungle and protect its native peoples.
   Environmentalists are concerned that slash burning of the rain
forest is contributing to the warming of world temperatures and
destroying both a vital source of oxygen and an important habitat
for animal and plant life.
   The ecologists are trying to discourage foreign lending
institutions from putting money into Brazilian development projects
considered harmful to the enviroment and native peoples.
   Foreign governments and environmental groups have, for example,
proposed that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> swap part of its <MONEY>$115 billion</MONEY> foreign debt for
promises to preserve parcels of jungle territory.
   President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON>, for his part, has said he doesn't want any
meddling in domestic affairs by foreigners.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890121-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-21-89 0511EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Portugal-Language     01-21 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Portugal-Language,0530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Foreign Minister's Good English Seen As Bad For Portuguese Diplomacy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The foreign minister of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> has had
his knuckles rapped for what is usually considered an essential
skill in modern diplomacy _ speaking English.
   Newspapers and politicians have harshly criticized <PERSON>Joao de Deus
Pinheiro</PERSON> ever since he spoke English earlier this month at an
international conference on chemical weapons in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Critics say it breaks a pledge by the seven Portuguese-speaking
nations to promote their language _ the sixth most widely spoken in
the world _ at international events.
   More importantly, they charge <PERSON>Pinheiro</PERSON> hurt <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> at a time
when its influence among former colonies is increasingly being
challenged by one of them _ <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   ``No speak Portuguese,'' was the motto plastered across the
T-shirt of a cartoon of <PERSON>Deus Pinheiro</PERSON> on the cover of the satirical,
right-wing weekly O Diabo.
   Another paper this week showed the stocky, bearded minister
introducing himself as ``God Pine'' _ the direct English translation
of his name.
   While <PERSON>Deus Pinheiro</PERSON> has been busy drumming up international
financial support for an economic recovery plan for the other major
Portuguese-speaking countries of <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has
outflanked <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> on trade and relief efforts.
   Trade between <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has quadrupled the last three
years to more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s trade with <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> dropped from about <MONEY>$165 million</MONEY> in
<DATE>1986</DATE> to <MONEY>$127 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>. For the <DATE>first eight months of 1988</DATE>,
the countries' did about <MONEY>$103 million</MONEY> in business.
   Deus <PERSON>Pinheiro</PERSON>'s recovery plan foresees <MONEY>$600 million dollars</MONEY> worth
of aid from several nations to <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, but <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has already
granted <LOCATION>Luanda</LOCATION> a <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> credit that the African nation repays
in oil it produces.
   According to one government official in <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>, next week's
planned visit by President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, the first ever by
a Brazilian head of state, should increase cooperation between the
countries.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> already sells food, cars, and farm machinery to the
southern African nation and is helping to build a hydroelectric dam
there. Brazilian companies are now showing interest in helping
rebuild <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>'s ravaged telephone and power networks.
   ``We think <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> made an error (at the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> conference),''
said <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>'s secretary of state for foreign affairs, Antonio
Materrula. ``We have to push our mutual language at an international
level.''
   Portuguese is not an official language of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, but
the countries that use it _ <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cape Verde</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Guinea-Bissau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Sao Tome</LOCATION> e Principe _ count
about 180 million inhabitants.
   Only Mandarin Chinese, <ORGANIZATION>Hindi</ORGANIZATION>, English, Spanish and Russian are
spoken by more people worldwide.
   Brazilian and Mozambican delegates at the chemical weapons
conference spoke in Portuguese, further enraging <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s
politicians, scholars and journalists.
   ``It's a scandalous insult to the values and interests of our
language,'' said <PERSON>Herminio Martinho</PERSON>, leader of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s New
Democratic Party.
   ``The importance of this language should be turned into a
diplomatic tool _and we (<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>) don't have many others,'' said
<PERSON>Jorge Sampaio</PERSON>, newly elected leader of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s main opposition
<ORGANIZATION>Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890224-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-24-89 2103EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     02-24 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Brazilian Indians Demand Suspension of Amazon Dam</HEAD>
<UNK>By PETER MUELLO ^Associated Press Writer</UNK>
<DATELINE>ALTAMIRA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chiefs of Amazon Indian tribes ended a
historic meeting <DATE>Friday</DATE> with a demand to stop plans to build a
hydroelectric dam that would flood native lands.
   Hundreds of Indians, wearing colored feathers, beads and red and
black paint, stood and chanted their support as Indian leader <PERSON>Ailton
Krenac</PERSON> read an appeal to protect <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION>, home to most of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
220,000 native people.
   ``We do not want the construction of dams on the <LOCATION>Xingu River</LOCATION> and
on other rivers in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>, because they threaten Indian
nations,'' he said. The mostly white audience of townspeople and
representatives of environmental groups cheered and applauded.
   More than 500 Indians from about 40 native groups met for five
days in this eastern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> city, 2,000 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de
Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>, to protest the proposed <ORGANIZATION>Belo Monte Dam</ORGANIZATION> on the <LOCATION>Xingu River</LOCATION>,
an <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> tributary. It was the first time Indians in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> set
aside longstanding tribal rivalries and banded together in a
political movement.
   The reservoir of the <MONEY>$5.8 billion</MONEY> dam would flood 500 square
miles of rain forest. The dam would have a generating capacity of <MONEY>11
million kilowatts</MONEY> _ <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> more than that of <LOCATION>Grand Coulee</LOCATION>, the
biggest hydroelectric dam in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   ``For a long time, the white man has ignored our thinking and the
spirit of our ancestors. Now this must stop. Our territory is the
sacred site of our people, the home of our creator that cannot be
violated,'' <PERSON>Krenac</PERSON> said.
   The government contends <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> must tap the vast hydroelectric
potential of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> basin to progress. Federal electric power
officials at the gathering told the Indians that dams will be built.
Earlier in the week, one Indian woman thrust a machete just inches
from the face of an electricity company representative. Other tribal
people said that was merely a symbolic gesture.
   Congressman <PERSON>Tadeu Franca</PERSON>, pledged to carry on the Indians' fight
in <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>, the capital. ``Because of this meeting, it will be
Indians, working together _ not some presidential decree _ that will
build the Indians' history,'' he said.
   ``Nothing like this has ever happened before. The Indians will go
back to their villages with the sense that something really new and
important has happened,'' said <PERSON>Terry Turner</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> anthropologist
who has worked more than 20 years with the <LOCATION>Kayapo Indians</LOCATION>.
   Construction of the dam is scheduled to start in <DATE>1993</DATE>. It must
first be approved by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has shown interest in getting partial financing for the
project from the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, but Indians and environmental groups
are asking the Washington-based institution not to put up any money.
   In a small victory this week, the Indians won an agreement from
the government electric power company in <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> to change the name
of the project to <ORGANIZATION>Belo Monte</ORGANIZATION> from Kararao. Kararao is a war cry of
the <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> tribe and was offensive to other tribes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890221-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-21-89 2057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Brazil-Indians 1stLd-Writethru a0674 02-21 0645</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0674,0664</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amazon Indians Point Machetes, Lances at Energy Officials</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto ALT1A</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: ADDS 3 grafs on Sting visit. No pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ALTAMIRA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Angry Amazon Indians thrust lances and
machetes at government electric power officials <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in a second
day of heated debate over a proposed hydroelectric dam that would
flood tribal lands.
   More than 500 Indians from 37 native groups packed the city's
community center for the historic encounter of tribes in this east
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> city, 2,000 miles northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   The meeting is the first united political movement by the native
tribes, and seeks to block construction of the Kararao dam on the
<LOCATION>Xingu River</LOCATION>, an <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> tributary. <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> says the energy is vital
for development in this land of 144 million people.
   Tempers flared when <PERSON>Jose Lopes</PERSON>, engineering director for
Eletronorte, the government <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> power company, told the Indians
the dam would not raise the river beyond its present level.
   ``You're lying! Everything you say is a lie!'' shouted Tuira, a
Kayapo Indian woman as she strode through the crowd and brandished a
machete in <PERSON>Lopes</PERSON>' face.
   Her words in <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> were translated into broken Portuguese by
Chief Paulo Paiakan. He said her gesture is ``one of our traditions,
it does not mean war.''
   Kayapo warrior Uh-Te also protested angrily and repeatedly thrust
a red-feathered lance at the company offical.
   ``We don't know what energy means. I was raised on game, fish and
wild honey in the forest. Why didn't you consult us about the dam?''
said Uh-Te with Paiakan translating.
   The Indians, some wearing a green-and-yellow feathered headresses
and black warpaint on their faces and bodies, raised their war clubs
in a sign of agreement.
   <PERSON>Lopes</PERSON> said <PERSON>Eletronorte</PERSON> was preparing an environmental impact
report on the Kararao project. ``If the dam affects Indian land, it
must be approved by congress,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s Indian population has been decimated by development
projects such as hydroelectric dams and the Trans-Amazon highway.
There are about 220,000 Indians left in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, down from an
estimated 5 million when the country was discovered by Portuguese
explorers in <DATE>1500</DATE>.
   ``The dam is not a reality until construction starts,'' and that
won't happen for at least five years,'' <PERSON>Lopes</PERSON> said. He said
Eletronorte has scrapped plans for other contested <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> dams at
<LOCATION>Babaquara</LOCATION> and Iriri.
   Chief Paiakan also complained that Indians had not been consulted
about the name of the dam. Kararao is a <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION> war cry, he said.
``To our youths, the government is calling us to war,'' <PERSON>Paiakan</PERSON> said.
   Lopes promised the project would be given a ``white name.''
   Earlier in <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>, Interior Minister <PERSON>Joao Alves</PERSON> said the
government would not consider stopping the Kararao project. He said
the dam was fundamental for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s future and would dislocate only
about 280 Indians.
   Kararao will generate 11 million kilowatts of electricity, <PERSON>Alves</PERSON>
said _ second only to the <ORGANIZATION>Itaipu</ORGANIZATION> dam, the world's largest, located
on <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s southwestern border with <LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION>.
   Brazilian and international environmental groups attending the
five-day meeting said the Kararao project was probably unstoppable.
   ``I don't think it's likely they'll stop construction of Kararao.
But that doesn't mean the meeting is a waste,'' said <PERSON>Barbara
Bramble</PERSON>, a director of the Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Fund</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This could be a real milestone in the formation of alliances
among Amazonian peoples to work together to save the place they live
in.''
   Joining the protesters was British rock star Sting, who told the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> Indian chiefs he was starting an international campaign to
raise money to create a huge <ORGANIZATION>Amazon National Park</ORGANIZATION>. He said the
campaign would begin <DATE>April 12</DATE> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   ``I'm not here on behalf of one people. If the rain forest dies
all of us are in danger,'' Sting said.
   He said he got permission for his project from President <PERSON>Jose
Sarney</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32350 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat025_m_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-025 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Amorim Meets Cuba's Lage, Says Brazil Opposes U.S. Trade 
Embargo </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY0402151494 Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network in 
Portuguese 0900 GMT 4 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY0402151494 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> has 
criticized the decision of certain countries to adopt unilateral 
measures which are not supported by international laws. 
Indirectly referring to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the minister said 
measures like this harm the development of countries like <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
  Amorim spoke during a meeting with Cuban Vice President 
<PERSON>Carlos Lage</PERSON>, who is currently visiting <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. Minister Amorim 
also confirmed that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> opposes the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trade embargo 
against <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32691 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat030_m_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-030 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Memorandum, Agreement Signed With Portugal </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY1002181694 Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network in 
Portuguese 0900 GMT 10 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY1002181694 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by (<ORGANIZATION>Arlette Milhomem</ORGANIZATION>)] </F>
  [Text] Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> and 
Portuguese Foreign Minister <PERSON>Jose Durao Barroso</PERSON> have signed a 
memorandum of understanding whose main point involves the 
recognition of professions in the two countries. 
  The recognition of diplomas will be studied by the 
professional associations of the two countries. If no agreement 
is reached, the governments intend to draft specific legislation 
that will ensure the validity of registries. 
  Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> noted that it will now be up to the 
Portuguese institutions to discuss the situation of these 
professionals. He noted that the agreement applies to 
professions such as attorneys-at-law, doctors, and architects. 
  The two ministers also signed an agreement that guarantees 
the promotion and protection of investments between the 
governments of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. 
  Foreign Minister <PERSON>Durao Barroso</PERSON> believes that this also 
represents a great opening for <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> to negotiate with other 
European nations. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890315-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-89 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-EXP--RainForests Adv19-2Takes   03-15 1113</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Rain Forests, Adv 19 - 2 Takes,1140</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv19</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Sunday, March 19, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Campaign to Preserve Rain Forest Progresses Slowly</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhotos, LaserGraphics</HEAD>
<HEAD>An Explorations Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM COHEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A campaign to preserve the remaining half of the
world's tropical rain forests has finally taken root, but the task
is enormous and the last gasp for the ``lungs of the Earth'' could
be less than a century away.
   Environmentalists are pleased with their initial success three
years after they began challenging governments, industries and
banks. But an area the size of a soccer field is destroyed each
minute, and the young preservation movement seeks fundamental
changes in political, economic and social structures to save the
teeming jungles of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>.
   An aggressive campaign of publicity, education and confrontation
began in <DATE>1985</DATE> and appeared to capture the world's attention last
year. Almost overnight, it seemed, world leaders began calling for
greater efforts to halt the chopping and burning of rain forests.
Conferences discussed such technical conservation issues as
``sustainable management.'' Rock stars Sting and The Grateful Dead
played benefit concerts for the cause. Media coverage increased.
   Some recent fruits of that effort:
   _<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>October</DATE> announced suspension of tax benefits for
landowners who destroy the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest, the largest and
fastest-disappearing on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   _<ORGANIZATION>The International Tropical Timber Organization</ORGANIZATION> approved a <MONEY>$4
million</MONEY> project in northern <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> that calls for loggers to consult
with environmental groups, government agencies, native Indians and
local workers to plan long-term forest development and preservation.
   _Some 500 Brazilian Indians from 20 tribes gathered last month to
oppose planned hydroelectric dams in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> that could flood
rain forest areas, including their homes. The meeting was the first
by the tribes, which traditionally have battled over territory and
remained isolated.
   _<LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> imposed a nationwide logging ban after
environmentalists blamed uncontrolled timber harvesting for floods
that killed more than 350 people in <DATE>November</DATE>. Last <DATE>April</DATE>, officials
suspended plans for a hydroelectric dam that environmentalists said
would have ruined <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>'s last virgin rain forest.
   _<LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> earmarked about <MONEY>$80 million</MONEY> for saving tropical
forests.
   ``Without a coherent strategy for protecting the tropical forests
in which everyone concerned participates, we cannot master the vast
problems threatening the future of all mankind,'' said West German
Chancellor <PERSON>Helmut Kohl</PERSON>.
   ``We have to be ambitious. We're in trouble,'' said <PERSON>Randall
Hayes</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based Rainforest Action Network</ORGANIZATION>. ``If we
don't get the changes we need in the next five years, then we've
lost the rain forests.''
   The results could be catastrophic.
   Rain forests cover some 2.4 billion acres of the planet, about
half the original amount, ecologists say.
   Sometimes called the ``lungs of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,'' they act as a
carbon dioxide isn't removed from the atmosphere, it can trap heat,
which some scientists say causes a global warming trend called the
greenhouse effect. Burning the rain forests, a common way to create
arable land, also adds carbon to the atmosphere.
   Rain forests are storehouses of plant, insect and animal species,
some of which could prove useful for drugs and other scientific
endeavors. Scientists say only a small percentage of the 5 million
species in the forests, many of them unique to the tropical
environment, have been studied.
   In addition, 200 million people live in and around rain forests,
including indigenous tribes who depend on them for sustenance and
shelter.
   Nonetheless, preservation presents complexities that cut across
social and political boundaries. Many rain forests are in developing
countries that need to capitalize on their natural resources and
must borrow money for costly modernization projects, such as
highways and power plants.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, for example, has the developing world's largest foreign
debt at <MONEY>$115 billion</MONEY>. Two of its limited number of export products
are beef and timber _industries that cause major forest destruction.
Cattle ranchers burn forests to create grazing land; loggers clear
jungle in search of exotic hardwoods.
   Meanwhile, poor farmers burn small tracts to grow crops. The
soil, so fertile under the rain forest canopy, is then leached of
nutrients in seasonal heavy rains, forcing farmers to move on and
burn another patch every few years.
   Last fall, Brazilian President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> suspended tax benefits
for land developers and banned exports of unprocessed tropical
timber. ``We must create nationwide consciousness that we are all
passengers in the adventure of man on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. The era of unlimited
natural resources is over,'' he said.
   But environmentalists contend the harmful practices continue.
Now, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is balking at proposals to swap some of its foreign debt
for saving parcels of rain forest. Such plans would entail creation
of an international commission to watch over the preserved jungle.
   ``We can't turn the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> into a sort of national park for
humanity,'' <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s foreign minister, <PERSON>Roberto de Abreu Sodre</PERSON>, said.
``Our priority is economic development. We're open to international
suggestions, but not those that interfere in Brazilian sovereignty.''
   Industrial giants such as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and European
countries, which have little or no rain forest, have been the most
vocal about the developing nations' efforts to halt the destruction.
That causes particular resentment.
   A conference of eight nations in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region, including
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, earlier this month issued a declaration rejecting foreign
interference while saying development must preserve the environment
and wild resources.
   ``Part of the problem is that it's coming down to the developed
countries versus the developing countries,'' said a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> activist
who monitors the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, the largest source of aid to developing
nations.
   ``They (developing countries) say, `You raped your countries to
get developed, and now you're stopping us from doing it,''' said the
activist, who spoke on condition his name not be used.
   But <PERSON>N.F. Potter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s executive director at the <ORGANIZATION>151-nation
World Bank</ORGANIZATION>, said: ``There are ways of doing things without making
the same mistakes.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> has been criticized by environmentalists, who say
it ignores ecological issues when funding projects. At issue are
billions of dollars; in the <DATE>fiscal year ending June 30</DATE>, the bank
expects to loan a record <MONEY>$21 billion</MONEY>.
   ``These bankers are unbelievably ignorant. They are absolutely
reckless,'' said <PERSON>Brent Blackwelder</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based Environmental
Policy Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   Under increasing pressure from member nations and environmental
groups not to fund ecologically harmful projects, the bank set up a
department in <DATE>1987</DATE> to assess the potential damage of development
projects.
   ``You can see a lot more environmental consciousness than there
was two years ago,'' said an official with a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> agency that
monitors aid. ``There has been movement. I'm not saying there has
been all the movement necessary.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32645 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat030aa_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-030 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Portuguese-Speaking Countries Agree To Create Union </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY1102001494 Brasilia Voz do Brasil Network in Portuguese 
2100 GMT 10 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY1102001494 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Voz do Brasil Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by Arlete Milhomen] </F>
  [Text] The Portuguese-speaking countries community probably 
will be created before <DATE>July</DATE>. The foreign ministers of the seven 
Portuguese-speaking countries -- <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Guinea Bissau</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sao Tome</LOCATION> and Principe, and <LOCATION>Cape Verde</LOCATION> 
-- today signed a joint communique as the basis for the 
establishment of the community of Portuguese-speaking countries. 
The document has 13 points that are fundamental for the group's 
implementation. The main items are: social, cultural, and 
economic cooperation among the countries' inhabitants; the 
implementation in the short term of the <ORGANIZATION>Portuguese Language 
International Institute</ORGANIZATION>; and support for an immediate cease-fire 
in <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>, where a civil war is under way. 
  Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> said the community 
will be a great opportunity to intensify relations among the 
member countries. He added that it will not prevent them from 
participating in other groups: 
  [Begin recording] <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, for example, which is currently a 
<ORGANIZATION>UN Security Council</ORGANIZATION> member, has been acting in coordination with 
other countries. It is necessary, however, to make this 
coordination and common agreement more permanent then it is in 
other forums. In <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>, for example, we participate in 
the <ORGANIZATION>Rio Group</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is a <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> member. The African 
Portuguese-speaking countries are <ORGANIZATION>OAU</ORGANIZATION> members. Therefore, this 
association will allow us to make better use of our common 
efforts. [end recording] 
  The community of Portuguese-speaking countries will be 
comprised of more than 200 million people spread over three 
continents. In addition to the language, these peoples share 
historic and ethnic traits. The community will become official 
during a meeting of the member countries' chiefs of state, which 
probably will be held in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> before <DATE>July</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-31917 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat020_m_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-020 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Minister Seeks To Avoid U.S. Retaliation Over Patents </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY2801233294 Sao Paulo GAZETA MERCANTIL in Portuguese 27 Jan 
94 p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PY2801233294 </F>
<F P=104>  Sao Paulo GAZETA MERCANTIL </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <ORGANIZATION>Maria Helena Tachinardi</ORGANIZATION>] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION> -- A group headed by Ambassador <PERSON>Roberto 
Abdenur</PERSON>, secretary general of the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, 
will visit <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> in early <DATE>February</DATE> to try to prevent the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> from retaliating against <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, which will 
probably not be able to meet the 28 <DATE>February</DATE> deadline to approve 
a bill on industrial property rights (trademarks and patents). 
  The fatal deadline imposed by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is already 
the extension of an investigation into Brazilian industrial 
property law. Last <DATE>November</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Government</ORGANIZATION> decided to 
bring forward by three months its decision on whether to adopt 
restrictive measures on Brazilian exports. 
  This subject was discussed yesterday by Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> and 20 businessmen from the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Chamber of 
Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. The minister does not think there will be 
difficulties in the talks with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, because the 
Brazilian draft bill being discussed in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> "will be very 
similar to the intellectual property agreement" of the <ORGANIZATION>Uruguay 
Round of GATT</ORGANIZATION> talks which concluded last 15 <DATE>December</DATE>. 
  "An action that does not take into consideration what was 
attained bilaterally and multilaterally would be technically 
precipitate and politically inopportune. If <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> had wanted 
to, it would have hindered the <ORGANIZATION>GATT</ORGANIZATION> intellectual property 
agreement," <PERSON>Amorim</PERSON> said. 
  The main point of controversy in the Brazilian draft bill is 
the requirement that pharmaceutical products must be 
manufactured in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in order to obtain a license. The text 
of the <ORGANIZATION>GATT</ORGANIZATION> agreement on the subject is ambiguous, and has not 
yet been clarified within the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> Convention which deals with 
intellectual property rights. "The text of the agreement deals 
with the subject indirectly. Political vision is necessary to 
deal with this ambiguity, which will in time be resolved," <PERSON>Celso 
Amorim</PERSON> said. 
  The foreign minister also spoke with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Chamber of 
Commerce</ORGANIZATION> businessmen about the Common Market of the South, the 
<LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> Round of the <ORGANIZATION>GATT</ORGANIZATION> talks, and trade problems between 
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, such as problems in the iron and 
steel industry and in the shoe and tobacco sectors. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-31922 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat020_m_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-020 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Minister Announces Establishment of Free Trade Zone </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY2801170694 Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network in 
Portuguese 0900 GMT 28 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY2801170694 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> will support the establishment of a free 
trade zone encompassing the Mercosur [Common Market of the 
South] countries -- <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> -- and 
<LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>. This was announced by Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso 
Amorim</PERSON>, who added that the free trade zone should be established 
in <DATE>1994</DATE>. 
  The establishment of the free trade zone between <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> countries was decided during the presidential summit 
held <DATE>earlier this month</DATE> in the city of <LOCATION>Colonia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890628-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-89 2301EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     06-28 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0517</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel: Gold Mining, Settlements Killing Indians and Rain Forest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JORGE MEDEROS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of gold prospectors in the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> are devastating rain forests and killing off the world's
largest primitive Indian tribe, a panel of officials, scientists and
clerics said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Indian reservations are being ``physically, morally and
culturally destroyed'' by uncontrolled gold mining and settlement in
the region, said ``Action for the Citizens.''
   It is the first time government officials have spoken against
destruction of the Yanomami Indian tribe and the rain forest by gold
miners. In this nation where the frontier spirit is strong and
rugged prospectors are widely seen as folk heroes, the government
has rarely intervened.
   The commission of <ORGANIZATION>Justice Ministry</ORGANIZATION> officials, lawmakers, lawyers,
scientists, <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> members and missionaries said
whites disrupted Indian hunting, contaminated rivers with mercury
used to join gold dust particles and spread fatal diseases among the
Indian population.
   The Yanomamis are a tribe of about 9,000 in the far northern
states of Amazonas and <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>, near the Venezuelan border. The area
is rich in timber, gold, diamonds and other minerals and has been
invaded by an estimated 100,000 prospectors, despite a government
ban prohibiting whites from entering Indian reservations.
   ``Owing to the tolerance of the authorities before an invasion of
thousands of gold miners into the reserves, we are seeing the
genocide of the Yanomani Indians, devastation of nature,
contamination of rivers and a gigantic ecological disaster,'' <PERSON>Sen.
Severo Gomes</PERSON> of the centrist <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Democratic Movement Party</ORGANIZATION>
said in an interview.
   Gomes had joined <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> member <PERSON>Plinio Arruda Sampaio</PERSON> of the
leftist Workers' Party, Archbishop <PERSON>Aldo Mongiano</PERSON> and 15 other
members in a recent three-day trip to several <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION> reservations
in the far-off jungle state of <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>, some 3,720 miles northwest
of <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>.
   The delegation also visited territories of the <ORGANIZATION>Macuxi</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Wapixana</LOCATION>,
Ingarico, and Taurepang tribes, which have been invaded by ranchers
that burned off and cleared indigenous farmland.
   The 26-page report denounced a ``complete disregard for the law''
by the miners and the lack of government enforcement in the region,
which it said even led to contrabanding of gold.
   All gold is required by law to be sold to the government.
   ``The miners themselves, with their guns, resolve all legal
problems,'' said <PERSON>Senator Gomes</PERSON>.
   Prospectors illegally used jungle airstrips cut by the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian
Air Force</ORGANIZATION> ``every five minutes'' to transport cargo and manpower by
helicopter and planes, said <PERSON>Sampaio</PERSON>.
   ``The whole thing looks like <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> during the war,'' he said.
``The hellish noise of planes and helicopters sends the Indians
scattering.''
   Last year, the powerful <ORGANIZATION>Bishops Council</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic
Church</ORGANIZATION> warned that the Yanomamis faced extinction if their lands
were taken away. The council said the government reduced by <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> the tribe's 17.3 million acres of land, divided into 19
separate tracts.
   About 220,000 Indians are left in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, down from an estimated
5 million when the country was discovered by the Portuguese in <DATE>1500</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890914-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-89 2117EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     09-14 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0476</SECOND>
<HEAD>Amazon Indians March on Presidential Palace to Protest Invasion of
Lands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scores of <ORGANIZATION>Amazon Indians</ORGANIZATION> in war paint
marched on the presidential palace <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to demand the removal of
tens of thousands of gold miners who invaded tribal lands.
   Shouting ``Give back the stolen land!'' and ``We want peace, not
war!'' about 100 Indians of the <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Kayapo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Guarani</ORGANIZATION> and
Kaingang tribes advanced to the marble-and-glass palace.
   The protesters, wearing green parrot-feather headresses and
red-and-black war paint and carrying wooden clubs, sang tribal
chants and demanded to see President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON>.
   Sarney refused to receive the group, and an aide said the Indians
should lodge their complaints with the <ORGANIZATION>Interior Ministry</ORGANIZATION>.
   The protest was led by Chief <PERSON>Davi Kopenawa</PERSON> of the 9,000-member
Yanomami tribe. The Yanomamis live in the remote northern <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> on
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s border with <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, a region rich in timber, gold and
diamonds.
   Kopenawa said the Indians wanted to deliver a petition to <PERSON>Sarney</PERSON>
demanding the immediate removal of an estimated 40,000 gold
prospectors from the <LOCATION>Yanomami</LOCATION> reservation. The government said it
began removing prospectors from the region <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``Sarney should obey the constitution,'' said <PERSON>Kopenawa</PERSON>, who last
year won a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> award for his defense of the environment.
   He said <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of the Yanomamis' land _ originally covering
22 million acres _ have been converted into national parks and
forests. But the government has been unable or unwilling to keep
prospectors out of the mineral-rich area.
   Environmental and Indian protection groups claim the invasion of
gold miners has spread disease, made game scarce and contaminated
rivers.
   ``We don't want our families to go on dying,'' said <PERSON>Kopenawa</PERSON>,
adding that the Yanomamis wanted an emergency health plan.
   The chief threatened to return the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> award if the government
didn't take action against the prospectors.
   ``This medal, which I didn't ask for ... is not resolving
anything,'' he said.
   The Indians arrived in <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION> earlier this week and tried to
meet with presidential candidates. None of the leading candidates
would meet with them.
   Brazilians are to vote <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> in the first free election for
president since <DATE>1960</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has about 220,000 native Indians, down from an estimated 5
million when the nation was discovered by Portuguese explorers in
<DATE>1500</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Fernando Gabeira</PERSON>, the presidential candidate of the small <ORGANIZATION>Green
Party</ORGANIZATION> and a supporter of the Indians' cause, said ``there is no
consciousness in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> of the importance of Indian culture.''
   <PERSON>Ricardo Pedreira</PERSON>, the presidential press secretary, said the
government and federal police began <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to remove the first
group of 90 miners from <LOCATION>Yanomami</LOCATION> land.
   He said officials also would try to close an estimated 70
clandestine air strips on the reservation. Small planes ferry some
miners to the region.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33515 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat109_m_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-109 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Chilean Minister on Joining Mercosur </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Chilean Minister on Joining Mercosur </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PY0606143294 Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network in 
Portuguese 1000 GMT 6 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY0606143294 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network </F>
<F P=105>  Portuguese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> will probably be the fifth country to join the 
Common Market of the South, <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION>. Chilean Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Carlos Figueroa</PERSON> and Brazilian counterpart <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> reported 
this news in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Para State</ORGANIZATION> on the night of 5 <DATE>June</DATE>. Here is 
<PERSON>Antonia Marcia Vale</PERSON>'s report: 
  [Begin recording] [Vale] Since the beginning of the <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> 
negotiations, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has refused to participate. The Chilean 
foreign minister now states that his country's interest in 
joining <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> follows President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON>'s proposal, in 
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1993</DATE>, to establish a free-trade zone in <LOCATION>Latin 
America</LOCATION>. 
  Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> asserted that if 
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> joins Mercosur it will be advantageous and represent a 
door for Brazilian exports to the <LOCATION>Pacific Region</LOCATION> market. 
  [Amorim] This possibility is important for us, not just 
because <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has commercial and political importance or because 
of old ties that bind our two countries. Mercosur member 
countries have always considered the possibility of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> 
becoming a member. As the Chilean foreign minister said, this 
initiative is a result of the current <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Government</ORGANIZATION>, of 
President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON>'s proposal to establish a South American 
free-trade area. This shows we have indeed been working in the 
right direction. This possibility gives us enormous 
satisfaction. 
  [Vale] The foreign minister reported that <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s main 
concern about entering <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> had been the high taxes charged 
by <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> on imported items. Minister Amorim added that this 
difficulty has practically ceased because currently our custom 
fees average just <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10189 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat042_m_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-042 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Minister Tours Europe To Revive Foreign Policy </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY0203191494 Sao Paulo O ESTADO DE SAO PAULO in Portuguese 
26 Feb 94 p A8 </F>

<F P=103> PY0203191494 </F>
<F P=104>  Sao Paulo O ESTADO DE SAO PAULO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Article by Reali Junior] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> is giving up the passive diplomacy that has 
prevailed during the past few years in its relations with 
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. During his visit to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso 
Amorim</PERSON> has been trying to design a more dynamic position for 
Brazilian diplomacy and counter the self-restraint our country 
has been imposing on its foreign presence. High-level meetings 
have been scheduled for <DATE>April</DATE> when British Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Douglas Hurd</PERSON> visits <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>, and the Brazilian foreign minister 
will visit <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> at the invitation of his counterpart, <PERSON>Alain 
Juppe</PERSON>. Amorim will address the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Foreign Relations 
Committee</ORGANIZATION> then. 
  These bilateral meetings have not been held for some years. 
As just an example of the poor period being experienced by 
Brazilian diplomacy, the French foreign minister's visit to 
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has been postponed four consecutive times during the past 
few years. 
  The positive results of the foreign minister's visit to 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> foreshadow a new period. In <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> on 25 <DATE>February</DATE>, the 
Brazilian foreign minister himself announced these two important 
meetings with the British and French foreign ministers to O 
ESTADO DO SAO PAULO. Amorim said: "If <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> hopes to play a 
leading role in the international arena, it cannot give up these 
talks." The Brazilian foreign minister accused former President 
<PERSON>Fernando Collor</PERSON> of destroying our country's foreign policy and 
not replacing it. 
  The Brazilian foreign minister admitted that recently our 
country has been placing less emphasis than it should on its 
bilateral relations. This explains the new effort toward 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s three 
principal European partners, which represents a priority in 
<ORGANIZATION>Itamaraty</ORGANIZATION>'s strategy. The effort to further approach these <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> 
countries is obviously aimed at attracting technology and 
investments. Amorim emphasized: "To this end, however, it is 
necessary to hold political talks." 
  In the case of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, the Brazilian foreign minister 
explained: "The tripartite agreement's ratification was 
essential because diplomacy and development must work together." 
  Concerning specific projects, the minister confirmed the 
German interest in <ORGANIZATION>Sivam</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Amazon Region Surveillance System</ORGANIZATION>]. 
The Germans are interested in installing the air traffic 
control system in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> region. The French and Americans 
also have expressed interest in this project. The <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian 
Government</ORGANIZATION>'s decision on the submitted proposals must be made by 
late <DATE>April</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900405-0206 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-05-90 1243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-SavingtheAmazon Adv13   04-05 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Saving the Amazon, Adv 13,0820</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv13</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release PMs Friday April 13 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Ecologists Applaud Choice for New Environment Minister</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER MUELLO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>RIO DE JANEIRO, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Defenders of nature say the
appointment of <PERSON>Jose Lutzenberger</PERSON>, a noted ecologist, as <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
environment minister could signal an end to wanton destruction of
the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> rain forest.
   The choice of <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>, 63, was seen as a victory for
conservationists, who claim the government has done little to stop
slash-and-burn devastation of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>. He was named by President
<PERSON>Fernando Collor de Mello</PERSON>, who took office <DATE>March 15</DATE>.
   By <DATE>1988</DATE>, ranchers and farmers had destroyed about <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT> of
the rain forest in the 2 million square miles of <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> wilderness,
said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> researcher <PERSON>Philip Fearnside</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of
Research</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
   Carbon dioxide produced by the burning is believed to add to the
``greenhouse effect'' warming the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface.
   ``<PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> is the right man in the right place; nobody else
has his credibility,'' <PERSON>Johan Dalgas Frisch</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Preservation Association</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION>, said in an interview.
   Antonio <PERSON>Carlos de Oliveira</PERSON> of the ecology group <PERSON>Oikos</PERSON> said: ``He
is superimportant, a legend. We all have the greatest respect and
admiration for him.''
   Lutzenberger seeks radical changes in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s environmental
policy. He favors solar, wind and other natural forms of energy
over the huge hydroelectric complexes of recent decades.
   A Rio newspaper made the wry comment that <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> was so
radical about protecting nature that he even opposed lawn mowers.
   The new environment minister told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>: ``We
have to question the fundamental doctrines of modern industrial
society, which is geared to the needs of the powerful. We're not
saying give up technology, but go a different way.''
   In his first week on the job, <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> spoke out against the
controversial Northern Rim project, which would create army posts
to guard <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s vast jungle border.
   He also promised to review a decision that allowed gold miners
to settle on land claimed by the primitive <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami Indians</ORGANIZATION>.
   Prospectors have invaded <ORGANIZATION>Yanomami</ORGANIZATION> land in the remote western
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> state of <LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION>, devastating the forest and bringing
disease and death to the Indians.
   After consulting with <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> and visiting the area, <PERSON>Collor</PERSON>
ordered the dynamiting of clandestine air strips on tribal land and
said the Northern Rim project would be redirected toward protecting
the environment.
   ``We must remove the prospectors, but we also must give them
decent living conditions,'' <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> said. ``They are not there
because they're bad or want to destroy.''
   Lutzenberger, a descendant of German immigrants, is an
agronomist with a degree from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Louisiana</ORGANIZATION>. In the
<DATE>1970s</DATE>, he resigned as a chemical company executive to join the
ecology movement and helped found <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s first environmental
protection group.
   Later, <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> established an environmental consulting firm.
   He pushed for tougher laws on pesticide control and for
installation of anti-pollution filters at a cellulose plant in his
native <LOCATION>Rio Grande</LOCATION> do Sul state, in southern <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> was among the first to sound the alarm about the
<LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
   ``This problem concerns all of humanity,'' he told reporters
shortly after becoming environment secretary.
   ``It concerns the continuation of life on this planet. This
requires not just plans for preservation, protection or parks. It
requires fundamentally rethinking our economic programs.''
   He appealed for help from industrialized countries.
   ``We must establish now an intensive and continuing dialogue
between the governments of the <ORGANIZATION>First World</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION> on
how we can collaborate to save the last jungles,'' <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>
told the journalists.
   One way, he said, is to write off part of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s <MONEY>$114 billion</MONEY>
foreign debt against programs to preserve the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> has rejected such ``debt for nature'' swaps on grounds
they violate national sovereignty. Of that, <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON> said:
   ``The idea is to find ways to reduce the debt in exchange for
the preservation of <LOCATION>Amazonia</LOCATION> by our government. There is not the
slightest intention to `internationalize' the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION>.''
   A key test of his strength is likely to be a proposed highway
from the western <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> through <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   Lutzenberger opposes the highway, but <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> and governors of
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s Amazonian states say it is vital to economic development
in the region. Most of the governors supported <PERSON>Collor</PERSON> for president.
   ``The important thing to watch is how much power he has. Let's
see what happens when he conflicts with the highway lobby,''
<PERSON>Fearnside</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> researcher, said in a telephone interview from
<LOCATION>Manaus</LOCATION>, in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle 3,000 miles northwest of Rio.
   Some fear <PERSON>Lutzenberger</PERSON>'s well-known temper and firm convictions
could work against him.
   ``If he's very radical, <PERSON>Collor</PERSON> will be pressured to get rid of
him,'' <PERSON>Frisch</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PMs Friday April 13</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32210 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat024_m_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Minister Underlines Increased Trade Within Mercosur </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY0302150794 Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network in 
Portuguese 0900 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PY0302150794 </F>
<F P=104>  Brasilia Radio Nacional da Amazonia Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] In a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Deputies</ORGANIZATION> joint 
congressional committee for <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> [Common Market of the 
South], Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> will 
invest nearly <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> in trade with <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>, and 
<LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION> this year. 
  Amorim refuted criticism that the implementation of <ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> 
was being delayed. He added that the member countries are 
merely negotiating schedules with longer adjustment terms for 
the implementation of the common custom fee. 
  The minister told the congressmen that trade among the 
<ORGANIZATION>Mercosur</ORGANIZATION> member countries has increased from <MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8 
billion</MONEY> in the last three years. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0302 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 1423EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-Continent-Bolivia-Glance Adv28   05-22 0560</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Continent-Bolivia-Glance, Adv 28,0568</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv28</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday May 28 or Thereafter ^CONTINENT IN CRISIS: Bolivia
at a Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Continent in Crisis-Bolivia, b0519-b0520</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Sunday May 28</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32405 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat026_m_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-026 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Brazil </F>
<H3> <TI>   Foreign Minister Criticizes U.S. Embargo Against Cuba </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY0702142594 Sao Paulo GAZETA MERCANTIL in Portuguese 4 Feb 
94 p 2 </F>

<F P=103> PY0702142594 </F>
<F P=104>  Sao Paulo GAZETA MERCANTIL </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] AGENCIA BRASIL reported that Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso 
Amorim</PERSON>, indirectly referring to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, yesterday 
"without respect for international law and to the detriment of 
the development of countries such as <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> [no closing 
quotation mark as published]. The foreign minister said <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 
refuses "to admit the imposition of other countries' laws" 
within its territory, alluding to the Torricelli Law which 
punishes <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies that do business with <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, even though 
they are subsidiaries installed in other countries. 
  Amorim's observations came during a speech at a lunch 
offered 
in honor of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s Vice President <PERSON>Carlos Lage</PERSON> who began a 
two-day visit to <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION> today. Amorim expressed hope that the 
political changes being implemented in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> today will "help to 
facilitate, as we all wish, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s full reinsertion in the 
hemisphere's coexistence." 
  The Brazilian foreign minister said <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> can join 
forces "to overcome our weaknesses," citing as examples the 
benefits that might be derived from the recent bilateral 
agreement for the purchase of medicines in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>; exchanges in 
the agroindustrial field, particularly on sugar and alcohol; and 
bilateral scientific and technical cooperation. 
  The Cuban vice president said that during his conversation 
with Amorim the Brazilian foreign minister reiterated <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s 
position against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> embargo on <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. "The embargo has 
caused our country many difficulties and it is important that it 
is rejected by all Latin American countries," <PERSON>Carlos Lage</PERSON> said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-51725 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat016__a94009" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-016-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Belize </F>
<H3> <TI>   Castro's Invitation to Collor `Dipleases' President Franco </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PY2201190794 Rio de Janeiro JORNAL DO BRASIL in Portuguese 
22 Jan 94 p 16--FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> PY2201190794 </F>
<F P=104>  Rio de Janeiro JORNAL DO BRASIL </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Luiz Orlando Carneiro</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION>] </F>
  [Text] Cuban President <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON>'s invitation to former 
Brazilian President <PERSON>Fernando Collor</PERSON> to spend a few days in 
<LOCATION>Varadero</LOCATION>, a Cuban sea resort, has displeased Brazilian President 
<PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON> and has taken Itamaraty [<ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION>] by surprise. It is possible that <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> will eliminate 
from his agenda a meeting with Cuban Vice President [title as 
published] <PERSON>Carlos Lage Davila</PERSON>, who will be officially visiting 
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 2-7 <DATE>February</DATE>. 
  Cuban Ambassador to <PERSON>Brazil Jorge Bolanos</PERSON> went to Itamaraty 
on 
21 <DATE>January</DATE> and told Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> that 
<PERSON>Castro</PERSON>'s invitation to <PERSON>Fernando Collor</PERSON> was strictly personal. 
According to <ORGANIZATION>Itamaraty</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Luiz Fernando Benedini</PERSON>, the 
meeting between Minister Amorim and the Cuban ambassador had 
been scheduled in advance. Benedini denied that the ambassador 
had been summoned for an explanation. The spokesman refused to 
comment on behalf of the minister on the possible displeasure 
that <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>'s invitation to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s former president, found 
guilty of malfeasance in office, may have caused. 
  According to information on hand, the former president was 
supposed to go to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> as part of a business delegation together 
with his old friend, businessman <PERSON>Luiz Estevao</PERSON>. Collor was 
reportedly invited to stay at the official guest house in 
<LOCATION>Varadero</LOCATION> where his former wife <PERSON>Lilibeth Monteiro de Carvalho</PERSON> and 
his children <PERSON>Arnon Affonso</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joaquim Pedro</PERSON> have stayed in the 
past. The trip of the business delegation was postponed because 
the health of <PERSON>Luiz Estevao</PERSON>'s father took a turn for the worse, 
but <PERSON>Collor</PERSON> confirmed that he plans to spend a few days in <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON> -- who still maintains a personal relationship 
with the former Brazilian president -- was unable to withdraw 
his earlier invitation. 
  Vice President <PERSON>Carlos Lage</PERSON>'s official visit to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> had 
been arranged some time ago. Lage's agenda includes meetings 
with President <PERSON>Franco</PERSON>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON>, Finance 
Minister <PERSON>Fernando Henrique Cardoso</PERSON>, and Health Minister <PERSON>Henrique 
Santillo</PERSON>. 
  [<LOCATION>Sao Paulo</LOCATION> FOLHA DE SAO PAULO in Portuguese on 21 <DATE>January</DATE> on 
page A6 carries a 200-word report noting that "on 22 <DATE>January</DATE> 
Collor will be boarding a plane for <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, the first leg of a 
30-day vacation. Collor, who is traveling with his wife <PERSON>Rosane</PERSON>, 
will visit <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, then go to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and end up in the Cap Ferrat 
resort in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>."] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890125-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-25-89 2211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Brazil-Indians     01-25 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brazil-Indians,0317</SECOND>
<HEAD>Church Group Denounces Violence Against Native Indians</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BRASILIA, Brazil (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A church group on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> denounced the
slaying of 36 Indians during <DATE>1988</DATE> and blamed the government of
President <PERSON>Jose Sarney</PERSON> for ``increasing violence against native
populations'' in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   At least 28 of the deaths were linked to battles over land, and
in the majority of cases ``authorities took no measures to find or
punish the guilty parties,'' <ORGANIZATION>Antonio Brand</ORGANIZATION>, executive secretary of
the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Missionary Council</ORGANIZATION>, said in a press conference.
   Brand said the worst Indian massacre last year was the <DATE>March 28</DATE>
slaying of 14 <ORGANIZATION>Tikuna Indians</ORGANIZATION> in the far northern state of Amazonas
after a dispute over land with a wealthy wood dealer.
   In a press release, the council also mentioned the death of 25
Yanomami Indians through diseases transmitted by white men such as
malaria or poisoning by mercury, which is used by gold prospectors
to refine the precious metal.
   Brand said the government's refusal to remove the thousands of
gold prospectors from <LOCATION>Yanomami</LOCATION> territory in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> jungle region
``will allow the continued massacre of this people.''
   The Yanomami Indians are <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s most primitive tribe and live
almost without contact with the modern world close to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s
northern border with <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
   Brand said the government was ``responsible for the state of
chronic violence'' that exists in the rain forest, which is rich in
gold, diamonds, iron ore and uranium.
   Currently about 220,000 native Indians and 430 tribes remain out
of a population estimated at 5 million when <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> was discovered by
the Portuguese.
   About <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> has been destroyed by farming,
gold prospecting and mining, according to the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based Institute
for Policy Studies</ORGANIZATION>. An estimated 400,000 gold prospectors are
located throughout the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> and, along with farmers and
wood-cutters, often involve themselves in territory disputes with
Indians.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-19758 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drweu055_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-WEU-94-055 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> PORTUGAL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Soares Urges Formation of Lusophone Community </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  LD2103234594 Lisbon Radio Renascenca in Portuguese to Europe 
2200 GMT 21 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> LD2103234594 </F>
<F P=104>  Lisbon Radio Renascenca </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Portuguese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Excerpts] President <PERSON>Soares</PERSON> is in <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. He does not tire 
of advocating a good relationship between all peoples of the 
Lusophone countries, and he backs the community being prepared. 
Among other advantages, it will carry a significant weight at 
the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION>, which could help many people in the future. These were 
<PERSON>Soares</PERSON>' words in an exclusive interview with Renascenca. Ines 
Saldanha also spoke to President <PERSON>Soares</PERSON> about the political 
contacts he has been having and of <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON>'s visit to 
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>. 
  [Begin recording] [Soares] First of all, at the invitation 
of 
Vice President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON>, we are preparing a major meeting 
to be held in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> and a major meeting of Lusophone countries 
at a head-of-state level. [passage omitted] 
  [<LOCATION>Saldanha</LOCATION>] You place great importance on the <DATE>July</DATE> meeting of 
Lusophone countries, and I know that that is related to the 
importance you give to a greater weight of those countries in 
the <ORGANIZATION>UN</ORGANIZATION>. Do you think that could help <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in matters such 
as <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>? 
  [Soares] Of course. They all have come out, and even <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 
recently came out very clearly in favor of <LOCATION>East Timor</LOCATION> and in 
favor of its self-determination. This carries some weight. But 
I am thinking beyond the present. I am thinking of the future. 
  [<LOCATION>Saldanha</LOCATION>] Are you thinking of the community of Lusophone 
countries the Brazilian ambassador talks of? 
  [Soares] Exactly. I am thinking of a community, a 
Luso-Afro-Brazilian community that could have an important 
specific weight in the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Saldanha</ORGANIZATION>] And do you think that is viable considering the 
conditions in <LOCATION>Mozambique</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>? 
  [Soares] Precisely, what I want is a joint plan by <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> to help our African brothers, who are in a bad 
situation but will be great nations in the future. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Saldanha</ORGANIZATION>] Have you invited President Itamar to visit 
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> before the end of your mandate? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Soares] Naturally</ORGANIZATION>, it has been confirmed that he will visit 
in <DATE>June</DATE>. Before the summit of heads of state, he will come on a 
bilateral state visit to <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, and I will have the honor of 
receiving him in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>. [end recording] 

</TEXT>
