<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891205-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-12-05-89 1111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-The'80s-TenYears Adv16-3Takes   12-05 0863</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-The '80s-Ten Years, Adv 16 - 3 Takes,0923</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 16-17 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Year by Year, an Eventful Decade in Review</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1980</NOTE>
<NOTE>AMERICA HELD HOSTAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1981</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF ASSASSINS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1982</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF INVASION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1983</NOTE>
<NOTE>SUPERPOWER CHILL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891213-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-89 1308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-The'80s-TenYears 1stLd-Writethru   12-13 0914</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-The '80s-Ten Years, 1st Ld-Writethru,0979</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 16-17 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Year by Year, an Eventful Decade in Review</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads b0778-0779-0780, sent Dec. 5. UPDATES 1989 with new entries;
CORRECTS death tolls in 1980 MGM fire to 87 sted 84; in 1987 Dona Paz sinking
to more than 3,000 dead sted 1,600; CORRECTS damages in 1989 San Francisco
quake to $7 billion sted $17 billion.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1980</NOTE>
<NOTE>AMERICA HELD HOSTAGE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1981</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF ASSASSINS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1982</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF INVASION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1983</NOTE>
<NOTE>SUPERPOWER CHILL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1980s</DATE> began in crisis: the crisis of the hostages, the
crisis of <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, the crisis of striking shipyard workers in
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. The decade is now ending with the unexpected: the sight of
communism's walls crumbling, of new powers rising in the world, of
hostages still held.
   Here is a chronology of an eventful 10 years, years of tumult,
disaster and accomplishment:
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880912-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-88 0723EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv20   09-12 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv 20,0486</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv20</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Tuesday, Sept. 20</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<HEAD>By The Associated Press</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 20</DATE>, the 264th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are 102
days left in the year. Yom Kippur, the <ORGANIZATION>Jewish Day of Atonement</ORGANIZATION>,
begins at sunset.
   Today's highlight in history:
   In <DATE>1519</DATE>, Portuguese navigator <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION> set out from
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on a voyage to find a western passage to the Indies. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
was killed en route, but one of his ships eventually circled the
globe.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1870</DATE>, Italian troops took control of the <LOCATION>Papal States</LOCATION>,
leading to the unification of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1873</DATE>, panic swept the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in
the wake of railroad bond defaults and bank failures.
   In <DATE>1881</DATE>, <PERSON>Chester A. Arthur</PERSON> was sworn in as the 21st <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
president, succeeding <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON>, who was assassinated.
   In <DATE>1884</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Equal Rights Party</ORGANIZATION> was formed during a convention
of suffragists in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. The convention nominated <PERSON>Belva Ann
Bennett Lockwood</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> for president.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, former <ORGANIZATION>New York City Mayor Fiorello La Guardia</ORGANIZATION> died.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, <PERSON>James Meredith</PERSON>, a black, was blocked from enrolling in
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Mississippi</ORGANIZATION> by Gov. <PERSON>Ross R. Barnett</PERSON>. (<PERSON>Meredith</PERSON>
was later admitted.)
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> proposed a joint U.S.-Soviet
expedition to the moon in a speech to the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1973</DATE>, in their so-called battle of the sexes, tennis star
<PERSON>Billie Jean King</PERSON> defeated <PERSON>Bobby Riggs</PERSON> in straight sets, 6-4, 6-3,
6-3, at the <LOCATION>Houston Astrodome</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, Playboy magazine released an interview in which
Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> admitted he'd ``looked
on a lot of women with lust.''
   In <DATE>1977</DATE>, the first wave of Southeast Asian boat people arrived
in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> under a new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resettlement program.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, a car bomber attacked the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> annex in
suburban <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>. The explosion in front of the building killed more
than a dozen people, including the driver.
   Ten years ago: <PERSON>John Vorster</PERSON>, prime minister of white-ruled <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION> since <DATE>1966</DATE>, announced his resignation, saying he would seek
the ceremonial position of president.
   Five years ago: After a week of negotiations, President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
and congressional leaders reached a compromise authorizing the
1,200 <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Marines</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> to remain on their peacekeeping
mission for 18 more months.
   One year ago: Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> concluded an 11-day visit to
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> as he celebrated Mass for thousands of Indians at
<LOCATION>Fort Simpson</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>.
   Today's birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Boston Celtics President Red Auerbach</ORGANIZATION> is 71.
Singer <PERSON>Gogi Grant</PERSON> is 64. <ORGANIZATION>Psychologist Dr. Joyce Brothers</ORGANIZATION> is 60.
Actress-comedian <PERSON>Anne Meara</PERSON> is 59. Actress <PERSON>Sophia Loren</PERSON> is 54.
Former hockey player Guy <PERSON>LaFleur</PERSON> is 37.
   Thought for today: ``Misery is a communicable disease.'' _
<PERSON>Martha Graham</PERSON>, American modern dance pioneer.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881229-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-88 1450EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Chronology'88 2ndLd-Writethru   12-29 1056</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Chronology '88, 2nd Ld-Writethru,1130</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv00</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>
<HEAD>Politics, Tragedy, Triumph: 1988 As It Unfolded</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS Dec. 7 entry to reflect downward revision in official
death toll from earthquake; SUBS Dec. 21 entry to update with bomb
blamed for Pan Am crash and revised death toll. Last update moved
Dec. 22, under same b0962 number.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of the major events of <DATE>1988</DATE>:
   
   JAN. 2 _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> sign landmark free-trade agreement.
   JAN. 7 _ Record snowfall in the South, record cold across <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   <DATE>JAN. 28</DATE> _ Face-to-face negotiations begin between Contras and
Sandinistas. Polygamist 13-day siege ends in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   JAN. 30 _ <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins defeat Denver Broncos 42-10 in
Super Bowl.
   FEB. 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> aid voted down by <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Anthony Kennedy</PERSON>
confirmed as <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justice.
   FEB. 8 _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gephardt</PERSON> win <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> caucuses.
   <DATE>FEB. 13</DATE> _ Winter Olympics open in <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>FEB. 16</DATE> _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> win <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> primary.
   <DATE>FEB. 17</DATE> _ Marine Lt. Col. <PERSON>Richard Higgins</PERSON> kidnapped in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 21 _ <PERSON>Jimmy Swaggart</PERSON> steps down from pulpit in sex scandal.
   <DATE>FEB. 23</DATE> _ Nationalist protests begin in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 25 _ <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Delvalle</PERSON> fails in attempt to fire
armed forces chief <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, indicted on drug charges in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   MARCH 8 _ Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wins 16 of 17 contests, Democratic
results split.
   MARCH 16 _ <PERSON>Poindexter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Secord</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hakim</PERSON> indicted on
conspiracy charges in Iran-Contra affair.
   MARCH 23 _ Sandinistas, Contras sign cease-fire agreement.
   <DATE>MARCH 29</DATE> _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> drops out of presidential race.
   APRIL 4 _ <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Senate</ORGANIZATION> convicts, removes Gov. <PERSON>Mecham</PERSON>.
   APRIL 16 _ <PERSON>Khalil al-Wazir</PERSON>, senior <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> commander, assassinated in
<LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 20 _ Two-week Kuwaiti hijacking ends in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 26 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> clinches Republican nomination with win in
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. In South Korean election, government party loses
legislative majority to opposition groups.
   MAY 3 _ Three French hostages released in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   MAY 4 _ Deadline for illegal aliens in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to apply for amnesty.
   MAY 8 _ Mitterrand re-elected in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   MAY 15 _ Soviets begin Afghan troop withdrawal. Kentucky school
bus collision kills 27.
   MAY 19 _ Disturbed woman shoots one child dead, wounds five and
one adult at <LOCATION>Winnetka</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, elementary school.
   MAY 29 _ Reagan-Gorbachev summit begins in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   JUNE 7 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> clinches Democratic nomination with victories in
four primaries.
   JUNE 13 _ ``Cigarette lawsuit'' in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> decided in favor of
plantiff.
   <DATE>JUNE 28</DATE> _ Opening day of special Soviet Communist Party
conference that adopts sweeping reforms of Soviet system.
   JULY 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> cruiser <LOCATION>Vincennes</LOCATION> shoots down <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> Air
jetliner over <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing all 290 aboard.
   JULY 6 _ <ORGANIZATION>Piper Alpha</ORGANIZATION> oil platform explodes in <LOCATION>North Sea</LOCATION>, killing
167.
   JULY 11 _ Terrorist attack on Greek cruise ship kills nine,
wounds 98.
   <DATE>JULY 13</DATE> _ Principles of <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> settlement reached in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
talks.
   JULY 20 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> nominated for president by Democrats.
   <DATE>JULY 31</DATE> _ <PERSON>Hussein</PERSON> resigns <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>'s claim to <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 8 _ <ORGANIZATION>Perez de Cueller</ORGANIZATION> announces Iran-Iraq cease-fire.
   AUG. 17 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> nominated for president by Republicans. President
<PERSON>Zia</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Raphel</PERSON> killed in plane crash.
   <DATE>AUG. 27</DATE> _ Heavy flooding in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>; at least 1,000 perish.
   <DATE>AUG. 28</DATE> _ Italian precision-flying unit crashes into air show
crowd in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, killing 70.
   AUG. 31 _ Thirteen die in <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> crash at <LOCATION>Dallas-Forth Worth
Airport</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 8 _ Firestorm around Old Faithful in continuing <DATE>summer</DATE> of
fire in <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION> and elsewhere in <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. <DATE>12-16</DATE> _ Hurricane Gilbert strikes <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cayman Islands</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 12 _ West German hostage <PERSON>Rudolf Cordes</PERSON> freed in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 17</DATE> _ Summer Olympics open in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 29</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>_ Shuttle Discovery</ORGANIZATION> launched, resuming <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned space
program.
   OCT. 1 _ In major shakeup, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> becomes Soviet president,
<PERSON>Gromyko</PERSON> retires.
   OCT. 3 _ <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> hostage Mithileshwar Singh, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resident, freed.
   OCT. 5 _ President <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> loses Chilean referendum.
   OCT. <DATE>19-25</DATE> _ Hurricane Joan kills 184 in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 20</DATE> _ Dodgers defeat <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> A's to win World Series.
<LOCATION>Imelda</LOCATION>, indicted on racketeering charges in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 26</DATE> _ Trapped whales in Alaskan Arctic freed in combined
U.S.-Soviet effort.
   NOV. 1 _ <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> election, Likud gains slightly.
   NOV. 3 _ Computer virus strikes nationwide research network.
   NOV. 6 _ Soviet dissident <PERSON>Andrei Sakharov</PERSON> arrives in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> for
visit.
   NOV. 8 _ Bush-Quayle elected.
   <DATE>NOV. 15</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION> proclaims independent
Palestinian homeland. Soviet space shuttle Buran makes first flight,
unmanned.
   <DATE>NOV. 16</DATE> _ In <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION> declares ``sovereignty.''
   NOV. 21 _ Conservatives win Canadian election.
   DEC. 1 _ Supreme Soviet, national parliament, adopts government
reforms.
   DEC. 2 _ Space shuttle Atlantis launched on four-day mission;
<PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON> becomes <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> prime minister.
   DEC. 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> founder <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> indicted on fraud charges.
   DEC. 7 _ <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, at <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, announces troop
reductions. Devastating earthquake in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION>; initial
estimates of up to 55,000 killed but government later says under
25,000 confirmed dead.
   DEC. 8 _ <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> jet carrying ammunition crashes into
residential area of <LOCATION>Remscheid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, killing 5. Palestinians
in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s occupied territories mark one year since beginning of
intefadeh.
   DEC. 11 _ Soviet quake relief plane crashes, killing 79; Mexican
market explosion kills 68.
   DEC 12. _ <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> triple train crash kills 33; Yugoslav quake
relief plane crashes, killing 7.
   <DATE>DEC. 13</DATE> _ Yasser Arafat speaks to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> at session in
<LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> assets sold for <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY>.
   DEC. 14 _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> announces it will open dialogue with <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> after
Arafat says he will accept <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>DEC. 16</DATE> _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> holds first direct talks with <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION>; political
extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON> convicted of tax and mail fraud conspiracy.
   <DATE>DEC. 21</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747 crashes in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, killing at least
270 aboard and on the ground; terrorist bomb later blamed. <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s
right-wing Likud bloc and center-left <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> decide to form a
new national unity government. Two Soviet cosmonauts end history's
longest space flight _ a year in orbit.
   DEC. 22 _ <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> sign accords granting
independence to <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, a South African colony, and pledging to
withdraw 50,000 Cuban troops from <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Year-End Editions</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900514-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-90 0837EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv21   05-14 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv21,0498</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv21</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, May 21.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>May 21</DATE>, the 141st day of <DATE>1990</DATE>. There are 224
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <DATE>May 21</DATE>, the 141st day of <DATE>1990</DATE>. There are 224
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, May 21.</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890911-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-11-89 1254EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv20 1stLd-Writethru 09-11 0526</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv20, 1st Ld-Writethru, b0183,0542</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wednesday, Sept. 20</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 20th graf to CORRECT that LaFleur still active player.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 20</DATE>, the <DATE>263rd day of 1989</DATE>. There are
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 20, 1519</DATE>, Portuguese navigator <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION> set
out from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on a voyage to find a western passage to the Indies.
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was killed en route, but one of his ships eventually
circled the globe.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1870</DATE>, Italian troops took control of the <LOCATION>Papal States</LOCATION>, leading
to the unification of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1873</DATE>, panic swept the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in
the wake of railroad bond defaults and bank failures.
   In <DATE>1881</DATE>, <PERSON>Chester A. Arthur</PERSON> was sworn in as the 21st president of
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, succeeding <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON>, who was
assassinated.
   In <DATE>1884</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Equal Rights Party</ORGANIZATION> was formed during a convention of
suffragists in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. The convention nominated <PERSON>Belva Ann
Bennett Lockwood</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, for president.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, former <LOCATION>New York City Mayor Fiorello LaGuardia</LOCATION> died.
   In <DATE>1958</DATE>, civil rights leader <PERSON>Martin Luther King Jr.</PERSON> was seriously
wounded at a <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> department store when an apparently
deranged black woman stabbed him in the chest.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, <PERSON>James Meredith</PERSON>, a black, was blocked from enrolling in
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Mississippi</ORGANIZATION> by Gov. <PERSON>Ross R. Barnett</PERSON>. Meredith was
later admitted.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> proposed a joint U.S.-Soviet
expedition to the moon in a speech to the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1973</DATE>, in their so-called ``battle of the sexes,'' tennis star
<PERSON>Billie Jean King</PERSON> defeated <PERSON>Bobby Riggs</PERSON> in straight sets, 6-4, 6-3,
6-3, at the <LOCATION>Houston Astrodome</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, Playboy magazine released an interview in which
Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> admitted he'd ``looked
on a lot of women with lust.''
   In <DATE>1977</DATE>, the first wave of Southeast Asian ``boat people''
arrived in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> under a new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resettlement program.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, <PERSON>John Vorster</PERSON>, prime minister of white-ruled <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>
since <DATE>1966</DATE>, announced his resignation, saying he would seek the
ceremonial position of president.
   Ten years ago: <PERSON>Jean-Bedel Bokassa</PERSON>, the self-styled head of the
Central African Empire, was overthrown in a French-supported coup
while on a visit to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: A suicide car bomber attacked the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION>
annex in <LOCATION>north Beirut</LOCATION>, killing a dozen people. Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>
wrapped up his 12-day tour of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, appealing for action
against the nuclear arms race, economic injustice and abortion.
   One year ago: <PERSON>Greg Louganis</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> won the gold
medal in springboard diving at the Summer Olympics in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Korea</LOCATION>, one day after he struck and injured his head on the board in
the preliminary round.
   Today's birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Boston Celtics President Red Auerbach</ORGANIZATION> is 72.
Singer <PERSON>Gogi Grant</PERSON> is 65. Psychologist <PERSON>Dr. Joyce Brothers</PERSON> is 61.
Actress-comedian <PERSON>Anne Meara</PERSON> is 60. Actress <PERSON>Sophia Loren</PERSON> is 55.
Hockey player Guy <PERSON>LaFleur</PERSON> is 38.
   Thought for today: ``Envy is more irreconcilable than hatred.'' _
<ORGANIZATION>Duc Francois de la Rochefoucauld</ORGANIZATION>, French author (1613-1680).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881212-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-12-88 2120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Chronology'88 Adv00   12-12 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Chronology '88, Adv 00,0871</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv00</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>
<HEAD>Politics, Tragedy, Triumph: 1988 As It Unfolded</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of the major events of <DATE>1988</DATE>:
   
   JAN. 2 _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> sign landmark free-trade agreement.
   JAN. 7 _ Record snowfall in the South, record cold across <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   <DATE>JAN. 28</DATE> _ Face-to-face negotiations begin between Contras and
Sandinistas. Polygamist 13-day siege ends in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   JAN. 30 _ <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins defeat Denver Broncos 42-10 in
Super Bowl.
   FEB. 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> aid voted down by <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Anthony Kennedy</PERSON>
confirmed as <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justice.
   FEB. 8 _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gephardt</PERSON> win <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> caucuses.
   <DATE>FEB. 13</DATE> _ Winter Olympics open in <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>FEB. 16</DATE> _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> win <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> primary.
   <DATE>FEB. 17</DATE> _ Marine Lt. Col. <PERSON>Richard Higgins</PERSON> kidnapped in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 21 _ <PERSON>Jimmy Swaggart</PERSON> steps down from pulpit in sex scandal.
   <DATE>FEB. 23</DATE> _ Nationalist protests begin in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 25 _ <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Delvalle</PERSON> fails in attempt to fire
armed forces chief <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, indicted on drug charges in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   MARCH 8 _ Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wins 16 of 17 contests, Democratic
results split.
   MARCH 16 _ <PERSON>Poindexter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Secord</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hakim</PERSON> indicted on
conspiracy charges in Iran-Contra affair.
   MARCH 23 _ Sandinistas, Contras sign cease-fire agreement.
   <DATE>MARCH 29</DATE> _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> drops out of presidential race.
   APRIL 4 _ <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Senate</ORGANIZATION> convicts, removes Gov. <PERSON>Mecham</PERSON>.
   APRIL 16 _ <PERSON>Khalil al-Wazir</PERSON>, senior <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> commander, assassinated in
<LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 20 _ Two-week Kuwaiti hijacking ends in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 26 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> clinches Republican nomination with win in
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. In South Korean election, government party loses
legislative majority to opposition groups.
   MAY 3 _ Three French hostages released in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   MAY 4 _ Deadline for illegal aliens in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to apply for amnesty.
   MAY 8 _ Mitterrand re-elected in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   MAY 15 _ Soviets begin Afghan troop withdrawal. Kentucky school
bus collision kills 27.
   MAY 19 _ Disturbed woman shoots one child dead, wounds five and
one adult at <LOCATION>Winnetka</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, elementary school.
   MAY 29 _ Reagan-Gorbachev summit begins in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   JUNE 7 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> clinches Democratic nomination with victories in
four primaries.
   JUNE 13 _ ``Cigarette lawsuit'' in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> decided in favor of
plantiff.
   <DATE>JUNE 28</DATE> _ Opening day of special Soviet Communist Party
conference that adopts sweeping reforms of Soviet system.
   JULY 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> cruiser <LOCATION>Vincennes</LOCATION> shoots down <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> Air
jetliner over <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing all 290 aboard.
   JULY 6 _ <ORGANIZATION>Piper Alpha</ORGANIZATION> oil platform explodes in <LOCATION>North Sea</LOCATION>, killing
167.
   JULY 11 _ Terrorist attack on Greek cruise ship kills nine,
wounds 98.
   <DATE>JULY 13</DATE> _ Principles of <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> settlement reached in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
talks.
   JULY 20 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> nominated for president by Democrats.
   <DATE>JULY 31</DATE> _ <PERSON>Hussein</PERSON> resigns <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>'s claim to <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 8 _ <ORGANIZATION>Perez de Cueller</ORGANIZATION> announces Iran-Iraq cease-fire.
   AUG. 17 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> nominated for president by Republicans. President
<PERSON>Zia</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Raphel</PERSON> killed in plane crash.
   <DATE>AUG. 27</DATE> _ Heavy flooding in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>; hundreds perish.
   <DATE>AUG. 28</DATE> _ Italian precision-flying unit crashes into air show
crowd in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, killing 70.
   AUG. 31 _ Thirteen die in <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> crash at <LOCATION>Dallas-Forth Worth
Airport</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 8 _ Firestorm around Old Faithful in continuing <DATE>summer</DATE> of
fire in <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION> and elsewhere in <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. <DATE>12-16</DATE> _ Hurricane Gilbert strikes <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cayman Islands</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 12 _ West German hostage <PERSON>Rudolf Cordes</PERSON> freed in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 17</DATE> _ Summer Olympics open in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 29</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>_ Shuttle Discovery</ORGANIZATION> launched, resuming <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned space
program.
   OCT. 1 _ In major shakeup, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> becomes Soviet president,
<PERSON>Gromyko</PERSON> retires.
   OCT. 3 _ <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> hostage Mithileshwar Singh, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resident, freed.
   OCT. 5 _ President <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> loses Chilean referendum.
   OCT. <DATE>19-25</DATE> _ Hurricane Joan kills 111 in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 20</DATE> _ Dodgers defeat <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> A's to win World Series.
<LOCATION>Imelda</LOCATION>, indicted on racketeering charges in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 26</DATE> _ Trapped whales in Alaskan Arctic freed in combined
U.S.-Soviet effort.
   NOV. 1 _ <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> election, Likud gains slightly.
   NOV. 3 _ Computer virus strikes nationwide research network.
   NOV. 6 _ Soviet dissident <PERSON>Andrei Sakharov</PERSON> arrives in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> for
visit.
   NOV. 8 _ Bush-Quayle elected.
   <DATE>NOV. 15</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION> proclaims independent
Palestinian homeland. Soviet space shuttle Buran makes first flight,
unmanned.
   <DATE>NOV. 16</DATE> _ In <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION> declares ``sovereignty.''
   NOV. 21 _ Conservatives win Canadian election.
   DEC. 1 _ Supreme Soviet, national parliament, adopts government
reforms.
   DEC. 2 _ Space shuttle Atlantis launched on four-day mission;
<PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON> becomes <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> prime minister.
   DEC. 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> founder <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> indicted on fraud charges.
   DEC. 7 _ <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, at <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, announces troop
reductions. Earthquake in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION> kills up to 60,000, by
official estimate.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Year-End Editions</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900910-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-10-90 0831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv20   09-10 0549</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv20,0573</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv20</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thursday, Sept. 20</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>September 20th</DATE>, the 263rd day of <DATE>1990</DATE>. There
are 102 days left in the year. This is the Jewish New Year, <LOCATION>Rosh
Hashanah</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>September 20th, 1519</DATE>, Portuguese navigator <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
set out from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on a voyage to find a western passage to the
Indies. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was killed enroute, but one of his ships
eventually circled the globe.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1870</DATE>, Italian troops took control of the <LOCATION>Papal States</LOCATION>,
leading to the unification of <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1873</DATE>, panic swept the floor of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> in
the wake of railroad bond defaults and bank failures.
   In <DATE>1881</DATE>, <PERSON>Chester A. Arthur</PERSON> was sworn in as the 21st president of
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, succeeding <PERSON>James A. Garfield</PERSON>, who was
assassinated.
   In <DATE>1884</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Equal Rights Party</ORGANIZATION> was formed during a convention
of suffragists in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. The convention nominated <PERSON>Belva Ann
Bennett Lockwood</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Washington D.C.</LOCATION> for president.
   In <DATE>1947</DATE>, former <ORGANIZATION>New York City Mayor Fiorello La Guardia</ORGANIZATION> died.
seriously wounded at a <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> department store when an
apparently deranged black woman stabbed him in the chest.
   In <DATE>1962</DATE>, black student <PERSON>James Meredith</PERSON> was blocked from enrolling
in the <ORGANIZATION>University of Mississippi</ORGANIZATION> by Governor <PERSON>Ross R. Barnett</PERSON>.
Meredith was later admitted.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> proposed a joint U.S.-Soviet
expedition to the moon in a speech to the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1973</DATE>, in their so-called ``battle of the sexes,'' tennis star
<PERSON>Billie Jean King</PERSON> defeated <PERSON>Bobby Riggs</PERSON> in straight sets, 6-4, 6-3,
6-3, at the <LOCATION>Houston Astrodome</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, ``Playboy'' magazine released an interview in which
Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> admitted he'd ``looked
on a lot of women with lust.''
   In <DATE>1977</DATE>, the first wave of Southeast Asian ``boat people''
arrived in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> under a new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resettlement program.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, <PERSON>John Vorster</PERSON> (faws'-tur), prime minister of white-ruled
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> since <DATE>1966</DATE>, announced his resignation, saying he would
seek the ceremonial position of president.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, <PERSON>Jean-Bedel Bokassa</PERSON>, the self-styled head of the Central
African Empire, was overthrown in a French-supported coup while on
a visit to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, a suicide car bomber attacked the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> annex in
<LOCATION>north Beirut</LOCATION>, killing a dozen people.
   Ten years ago: ``Spectacular Bid,'' ridden by <PERSON>Bill Shoemaker</PERSON>,
ran as the only entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Woodward Stakes</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Belmont Park</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> after three potential challengers dropped out in horse
racing's first walkover since <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   Five years ago: A second major earthquake struck the <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>
area, one day after a devastating temblor.
   One year ago: Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> pulled off a
major shake-up of the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>, dropping three
Politburo members in a dramatic consolidation of power.
   Today's Birthdays: <ORGANIZATION>Boston Celtics President Red Auerbach</ORGANIZATION> is 73.
Singer <PERSON>Gogi Grant</PERSON> is 66. <ORGANIZATION>Psychologist Dr. Joyce Brothers</ORGANIZATION> is 62.
Actress-comedian <PERSON>Anne Meara</PERSON> is 61. Actress <PERSON>Sophia Loren</PERSON> is 56.
Former hockey player Guy <PERSON>LaFleur</PERSON> is 39.
   Thought for Today: ``Public opinion is stronger than the
legislature, and nearly as strong as the Ten Commandments.''
--<PERSON>Charles Dudley Warner</PERSON>, American author and editor (1829-1900).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thursday, Sept. 20</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881222-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-22-88 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-YE--Chronology'88 1stLd-Writethru   12-22 1043</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-YE--Chronology '88, 1st Ld-Writethru,1117</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv00</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release in Year-End Editions</NOTE>
<HEAD>Politics, Tragedy, Triumph: 1988 As It Unfolded</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS Aug. 27 entry to raise Bangladesh death toll to 1,000;
SUBS Oct. 19-25 entry to raise death toll from Joan-Miriam; SUBS
Dec. 7 entry to reflect revised official death toll from earthquake;
ADDS recent events.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a chronology of the major events of <DATE>1988</DATE>:
   
   JAN. 2 _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> sign landmark free-trade agreement.
   JAN. 7 _ Record snowfall in the South, record cold across <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   <DATE>JAN. 28</DATE> _ Face-to-face negotiations begin between Contras and
Sandinistas. Polygamist 13-day siege ends in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   JAN. 30 _ <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Redskins defeat Denver Broncos 42-10 in
Super Bowl.
   FEB. 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> aid voted down by <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Anthony Kennedy</PERSON>
confirmed as <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justice.
   FEB. 8 _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gephardt</PERSON> win <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> caucuses.
   <DATE>FEB. 13</DATE> _ Winter Olympics open in <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>FEB. 16</DATE> _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> win <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION> primary.
   <DATE>FEB. 17</DATE> _ Marine Lt. Col. <PERSON>Richard Higgins</PERSON> kidnapped in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 21 _ <PERSON>Jimmy Swaggart</PERSON> steps down from pulpit in sex scandal.
   <DATE>FEB. 23</DATE> _ Nationalist protests begin in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION>.
   FEB. 25 _ <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s President <PERSON>Delvalle</PERSON> fails in attempt to fire
armed forces chief <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, indicted on drug charges in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   MARCH 8 _ Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wins 16 of 17 contests, Democratic
results split.
   MARCH 16 _ <PERSON>Poindexter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Secord</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hakim</PERSON> indicted on
conspiracy charges in Iran-Contra affair.
   MARCH 23 _ Sandinistas, Contras sign cease-fire agreement.
   <DATE>MARCH 29</DATE> _ <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> drops out of presidential race.
   APRIL 4 _ <ORGANIZATION>Arizona Senate</ORGANIZATION> convicts, removes Gov. <PERSON>Mecham</PERSON>.
   APRIL 16 _ <PERSON>Khalil al-Wazir</PERSON>, senior <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> commander, assassinated in
<LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 20 _ Two-week Kuwaiti hijacking ends in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>.
   APRIL 26 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> clinches Republican nomination with win in
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. In South Korean election, government party loses
legislative majority to opposition groups.
   MAY 3 _ Three French hostages released in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   MAY 4 _ Deadline for illegal aliens in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to apply for amnesty.
   MAY 8 _ Mitterrand re-elected in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   MAY 15 _ Soviets begin Afghan troop withdrawal. Kentucky school
bus collision kills 27.
   MAY 19 _ Disturbed woman shoots one child dead, wounds five and
one adult at <LOCATION>Winnetka</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, elementary school.
   MAY 29 _ Reagan-Gorbachev summit begins in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   JUNE 7 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> clinches Democratic nomination with victories in
four primaries.
   JUNE 13 _ ``Cigarette lawsuit'' in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> decided in favor of
plantiff.
   <DATE>JUNE 28</DATE> _ Opening day of special Soviet Communist Party
conference that adopts sweeping reforms of Soviet system.
   JULY 3 _ <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> cruiser <LOCATION>Vincennes</LOCATION> shoots down <LOCATION>Iran</LOCATION> Air
jetliner over <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing all 290 aboard.
   JULY 6 _ <ORGANIZATION>Piper Alpha</ORGANIZATION> oil platform explodes in <LOCATION>North Sea</LOCATION>, killing
167.
   JULY 11 _ Terrorist attack on Greek cruise ship kills nine,
wounds 98.
   <DATE>JULY 13</DATE> _ Principles of <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> settlement reached in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
talks.
   JULY 20 _ <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> nominated for president by Democrats.
   <DATE>JULY 31</DATE> _ <PERSON>Hussein</PERSON> resigns <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>'s claim to <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 8 _ <ORGANIZATION>Perez de Cueller</ORGANIZATION> announces Iran-Iraq cease-fire.
   AUG. 17 _ <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> nominated for president by Republicans. President
<PERSON>Zia</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Raphel</PERSON> killed in plane crash.
   <DATE>AUG. 27</DATE> _ Heavy flooding in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>; at least 1,000 perish.
   <DATE>AUG. 28</DATE> _ Italian precision-flying unit crashes into air show
crowd in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, killing 70.
   AUG. 31 _ Thirteen die in <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> crash at <LOCATION>Dallas-Forth Worth
Airport</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 8 _ Firestorm around Old Faithful in continuing <DATE>summer</DATE> of
fire in <ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION> and elsewhere in <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. <DATE>12-16</DATE> _ Hurricane Gilbert strikes <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cayman Islands</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   SEPT. 12 _ West German hostage <PERSON>Rudolf Cordes</PERSON> freed in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 17</DATE> _ Summer Olympics open in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>SEPT. 29</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>_ Shuttle Discovery</ORGANIZATION> launched, resuming <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> manned space
program.
   OCT. 1 _ In major shakeup, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> becomes Soviet president,
<PERSON>Gromyko</PERSON> retires.
   OCT. 3 _ <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> hostage Mithileshwar Singh, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> resident, freed.
   OCT. 5 _ President <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> loses Chilean referendum.
   OCT. <DATE>19-25</DATE> _ Hurricane Joan kills 184 in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 20</DATE> _ Dodgers defeat <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> A's to win World Series.
<LOCATION>Imelda</LOCATION>, indicted on racketeering charges in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>OCT. 26</DATE> _ Trapped whales in Alaskan Arctic freed in combined
U.S.-Soviet effort.
   NOV. 1 _ <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> election, Likud gains slightly.
   NOV. 3 _ Computer virus strikes nationwide research network.
   NOV. 6 _ Soviet dissident <PERSON>Andrei Sakharov</PERSON> arrives in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> for
visit.
   NOV. 8 _ Bush-Quayle elected.
   <DATE>NOV. 15</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Palestine National Council</ORGANIZATION> proclaims independent
Palestinian homeland. Soviet space shuttle Buran makes first flight,
unmanned.
   <DATE>NOV. 16</DATE> _ In <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION> declares ``sovereignty.''
   NOV. 21 _ Conservatives win Canadian election.
   DEC. 1 _ Supreme Soviet, national parliament, adopts government
reforms.
   DEC. 2 _ Space shuttle Atlantis launched on four-day mission;
<PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON> becomes <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> prime minister.
   DEC. 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> founder <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> indicted on fraud charges.
   DEC. 7 _ <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, at <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, announces troop
reductions. Devastating earthquake in <LOCATION>Soviet Armenia</LOCATION>; official
estimates of up to 55,000 killed.
   DEC. 8 _ <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> jet carrying ammunition crashes into
residential area of <LOCATION>Remscheid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, killing 5. Palestinians
in <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s occupied territories mark one year since beginning of
intefadeh.
   DEC. 11 _ Soviet quake relief plane crashes, killing 79; Mexican
market explosion kills 68.
   DEC 12. _ <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> triple train crash kills 33; Yugoslav quake
relief plane crashes, killing 7.
   <DATE>DEC. 13</DATE> _ Yasser Arafat speaks to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> at session in
<LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> assets sold for <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY>.
   DEC. 14 _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> announces it will open dialogue with <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> after
Arafat says he will accept <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>DEC. 16</DATE> _ <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> holds first direct talks with <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION>; political
extremist <PERSON>Lyndon LaRouche</PERSON> convicted of tax and mail fraud conspiracy.
   <DATE>DEC. 21</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 747 crashes in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, killing at least
281 aboard and on the ground; sabotage is suspected. <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s
right-wing Likud bloc and center-left <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> decide to form a
new national unity government. Two Soviet cosmonauts end history's
longest space flight _ a year in orbit.
   DEC. 22 _ <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION> sign accords granting
independence to <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, a South African colony, and pledging to
withdraw 50,000 Cuban troops from <LOCATION>Angola</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Year-End Editions</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031989-0259 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 33453 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 19, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Real Estate; Part 8; Page 21; Column 2; Real Estate Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
163 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NIKKEN SEKKI OPENS 1ST U.S. OFFICES IN L.A. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Nikken Sekkei Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, one of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest architecture/engineering consulting 
firms with expertise in seismic engineering and earthquake research, has opened 
its first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> subsidiary in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Nikken America Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has opened offices at 333 <ORGANIZATION>S. Hope St.</ORGANIZATION>, 
Suite 2650. 
</P>
<P>
Its goal is "to develop a <LOCATION>Pacific Rim</LOCATION> architectural culture with influences 
from both countries' traditions." <PERSON>Katsumi Yano</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Nikken America</ORGANIZATION>, 
said, "We believe there will be growing demand for buildings that combine the 
cultures and technologies of our two countries." 
</P>
<P>
Hayahiko <ORGANIZATION>Takase</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Shinjiro Wachi</PERSON> will lead the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> office as senior 
vice presidents. 
</P>
<P>
The 89-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Nikken Sekkei</ORGANIZATION> has been providing access to the Japanese market 
for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> design firms, including <ORGANIZATION>Chaix &amp; Johnson of Los Angeles</ORGANIZATION>, which is 
designing the interiors of a 400-room hotel and convention center in <LOCATION>Yokahama</LOCATION> 
and has designed the interiors of several major department stores in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880311-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-88 1851EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Ariane 1stLd-Writethru a0725 03-11 0499</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ariane, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0725,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Rocket Lifts Off with French, U.S. Payload</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 3 grafs to UPDATE with Ariane lifting off</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KOUROU, French Guiana (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s Ariane 3 rocket lifted off
on schedule <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> for a mission to place French and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
communications satellites into orbit and reaffirm its role as the
<LOCATION>West</LOCATION>'s only active launcher.
   The rocket blasted off at <TIME>7:28 p.m.</TIME> from this jungle space
center on the northern coast of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> _ Ariane's 21st
launching and the first of eight planned for this year.
   <PERSON>Andre Payet</PERSON>, chief of mission, said no technical problems were
reported and weather conditions were good for the launch of the
rocket, owned by the <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   The launch was first scheduled for <DATE>December</DATE> but was delayed for
extra tests after anomalies were detected in the oxygen and liquid
hydrogen third-stage engine.
   ``We preferred to take the time to understand the problem,''
said <PERSON>Frederic d'Allest</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Arianespace</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>ESA</ORGANIZATION>'s commercial
arm.
   Third-stage engine failure was the cause of three of Ariane's
four failed launches _ in <DATE>September 1982</DATE>, <DATE>September 1985</DATE> and <DATE>May
1986</DATE>. The last failure, the 18th launch, left the rocket grounded
for more than a year.
   The other failed launch occurred in <DATE>May 1980</DATE> because of a
problem with the first-stage engine.
   Ariane produced a perfect 20th launch <DATE>Nov. 21, 1987</DATE>, but the
West German television satellite it placed into orbit developed
problems with its solar panels and is not fully operational.
   The 21st launch will thrust into orbit the American <ORGANIZATION>GTE Spacenet
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s fifth satellite, Spacenet III R-Geostar R01. The satellite
is aimed at increasing the company's wide-ranging
telecommunications services in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and help set up a
system of satellite communication with mobile units such as trucks,
cars and trains.
   Two transponders on <ORGANIZATION>Spacenet III</ORGANIZATION> purchased by <ORGANIZATION>The Associated
Press</ORGANIZATION> are to provide the New York-based news cooperative with
domestic satellite delivery services over the next 10 years. A
satellite being used is nearing the end of its operational service.
   The French Telecom IC, the third in a series of satellites owned
by <ORGANIZATION>France Telecom</ORGANIZATION>, the state-owned telecommunications system, is
used for telephones, radio and television transmissions as well as
military communications.
   The new satellite is to replace <ORGANIZATION>Telecom</ORGANIZATION> 1-B, which broke down
<DATE>Jan. 15</DATE>.
   With the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle grounded and Titan 4 and <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>
rockets not yet competitive, Ariane remains the only active
launcher for commercial satellites in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. However,
<ORGANIZATION>Arianespace</ORGANIZATION> is watching the return of the Americans to the
lucrative space market as well as competition from the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   Including <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s payload, <ORGANIZATION>Arianespace</ORGANIZATION> has 43 satellites on its
order books worth <MONEY>$2.36 billion</MONEY>, according to the company.
   To keep up with the orders, the <LOCATION>Kourou</LOCATION> space center has made two
launch pads available.
   Ariane's 21st launch is to be the first of eight this year, with
nine launches each planned for <DATE>1989</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, d'Allest said earlier
this week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891107-0239 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-07-89 2358EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-VirginIslands-Troops     11-07 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Virgin Islands-Troops,0293</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half of Troops from Hurricane-Battered St. Croix Return Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHRISTIANSTED, U.S. Virgin Islands (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly half the 1,100
federal troops sent to maintain order on <ORGANIZATION>St. Croix</ORGANIZATION> after Hurricane
Hugo have returned home following a presidential order to withdraw.
   About 250 troops returned home aboard C-141 transport planes
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the first 250 were flown back to the States,
said <ORGANIZATION>Joint Task Force</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Maj. <PERSON>Doug Foster</PERSON>.
   ``We should all be home for Thanksgiving,'' he said.
   The C-141 and C-130 transport planes were constantly flying in
and out of the island to evacuate heavy equipment and vehicles
brought by the soldiers when they arrived on <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE>, four days
after Hugo's ravaged the island.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> ordered the withdrawal last week following a
request by Gov. <PERSON>Alexander Farrelly</PERSON>, who said the troops, most of
them from <LOCATION>Fort Hood</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Fort Bragg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, were no longer
needed.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops were sent to curb looting and help local
authorities maintain order. Most stores had already been sacked of
food and other commodities by the time the soldiers arrived.
   ``It's important for the <ORGANIZATION>Virgin Islands National Guard</ORGANIZATION> and the
police to get back on their own feet now,'' Foster said.
   Farrelly's request for the pullout was criticized by three
business organizations, the <ORGANIZATION>St. Croix Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Board
of Realtors</ORGANIZATION> and a civic group called the <ORGANIZATION>United Concerned Citizens
of St. Croix</ORGANIZATION>.
   They charged the governor reneged on his promise to keep the
federal troops until all power and telephone services were restored.
   Hugo caused more than <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> in damage to the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin
Islands</LOCATION>, mostly on <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION>, where most of the 52,000 residents
were left homeless.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891205-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-12-05-89 1112EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-The'80s-TenYears Adv16-1stAdd   12-05 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-The '80s-Ten Years, Adv 16 - 1st Add,1001</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 16-17 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: Western Europe.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1984</NOTE>
<NOTE>MORNING IN AMERICA</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1985</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF TERRORISM</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1986</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF REVOLUTION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1987</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF SCANDAL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891122-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-89 1417EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon-Presidents     11-22 0468</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon-Presidents,0484</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lebanon's Political History Plagued By Violence</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Lebanon, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lebanon's political history has been
plauged by violence and turmoil.
   Since independence from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1943</DATE>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s nine
presidents have grappled with sectarian fighting, coup attempts and
invasion by foreign forces.
   The latest victim was <PERSON>Rene Mouawad</PERSON>, who was elected president by
an emergency session of Parliament <DATE>Nov. 5</DATE> in <LOCATION>Syrian-controlled
north Lebanon</LOCATION> and served only 17 days before his assassination
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The first president was <PERSON>Bishara Khoury</PERSON>, who was released from
his cell in a French prison when <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> elected him <DATE>Sept. 21,
1943</DATE>. The French-educated trial lawyer headed the <ORGANIZATION>Christian-Moslem
National Resistance</ORGANIZATION> against the French, who ruled <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> under a
<ORGANIZATION>League of Nations</ORGANIZATION> mandate from <DATE>1920</DATE> to <DATE>1943</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, forces loyal to <PERSON>Khoury</PERSON> and his Sunni Moslem prime
minister, <PERSON>Riyad Solh</PERSON>, suppressed a two-week revolt by the <ORGANIZATION>Syrian
Social Nationalist Party</ORGANIZATION> aimed at making <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> part of a
``greater <LOCATION>Syria</LOCATION>.'' Syrian nationalist leader <PERSON>Antoine Saadeh</PERSON> was
executed.
   A year later, <PERSON>Solh</PERSON> was assassinated on a visit to <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, <PERSON>Khoury</PERSON> resigned after protest demonstrations broke out
when he sought to amend the constitution to extend his term.
   Parliament elected <PERSON>Camille Chamoun</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> ambassador and
a Maronite Catholic chieftain who survived four assassination
attempts to complete his six-year term.
   Chamoun asked for American help in <DATE>1958</DATE> when he faced a Moslem
revolt inspired by Egyptian leader <PERSON>Gamal Abdel Nasser</PERSON>'s radical
pan-Arabism. President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> sent 10,000 <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Marines</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> in <DATE>July 1958</DATE> and the rebellion fizzled.
   Chamoun's successor, army Gen. <PERSON>Fuad Chehab</PERSON>, crushed a coup
attempt on New Year's Eve by pro-Syrian army officers in <DATE>1959</DATE>.
   Lawyer <PERSON>Charles Helou</PERSON>, elected in <DATE>1964</DATE>, ruled as <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>'s
Palestinian guerrillas built up their power base in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>. In
<DATE>1969</DATE>, the Lebanese army clashed with Arafat's fighters in street
battles in south <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   Helou's successor, pro-Syrian <PERSON>Maronite Suleiman Franjieh</PERSON>,
oversaw the clashes between Christians and Palestinians that
triggered the civil war in <DATE>April 1975</DATE>. More than 150,000 people
have died since then.
   Parliament came under shellfire when <PERSON>Elias Sarkis</PERSON>, a former
<ORGANIZATION>Central Bank</ORGANIZATION> governor, was elected in <DATE>1976</DATE> with strong Syrian
backing. During his term the Israelis invaded in <DATE>1978</DATE> and <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bashir Gemayel</PERSON>, the Israeli-backed commander of the Christians'
main militia was elected to replace him. Gemayel, 34, was
assassinated in an east <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> bombing <DATE>Sept. 14, 1982</DATE>, a week
before he was to be sworn in.
   Parliament unanimously elected his elder brother, Amin. His
reign saw the advent of Iranian-sponsored Shiite terrorism,
including the kidnapping of Westerners and the suicide bombings of
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and French military bases.
   Gemayel stepped down <DATE>Sept. 22, 1988</DATE>, with <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> unable to
elect a successor. He left <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> in shambles and now lives in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891213-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-89 1320EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-The'80s-TenYears 1stLd-Writethru 1stAdd 12-13 0940</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-The '80s-Ten Years, 1st Ld-Writethru, 1st Add, b0779,1000</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 16-17 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: Western Europe.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1984</NOTE>
<NOTE>MORNING IN AMERICA</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1985</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF TERRORISM</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1986</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF REVOLUTION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1987</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF SCANDAL</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <DATE>DEC. 20</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> mutiny forces evacuation of leader <PERSON>Yasser Arafat</PERSON>
and 4,000 followers from last stronghold in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890904-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-04-89 0859EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv14   09-04 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv14,0659</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv14</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Sept. 14</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Sept. 14</DATE>, the <DATE>257th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 108
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Sept. 14, 1814</DATE>, <PERSON>Francis Scott Key</PERSON> wrote his famous poem ``The
Star-Spangled Banner'' after witnessing the British bombardment of
<ORGANIZATION>Fort McHenry</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> during the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1807</DATE>, former Vice President <PERSON>Aaron Burr</PERSON> was acquitted of a
misdemeanor charge two weeks after he was found innocent of treason.
   In <DATE>1812</DATE>, the Russians set fire to <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> after an invasion by
<PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>'s troops.
   In <DATE>1847</DATE>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces under Gen. <PERSON>Winfield Scott</PERSON> took control of
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1901</DATE>, President <PERSON>William McKinley</PERSON> died in <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, of
gunshot wounds inflicted by an assassin. Vice President <PERSON>Theodore
Roosevelt</PERSON> became president.
   In <DATE>1927</DATE>, modern dance pioneer <PERSON>Isadora Duncan</PERSON> died in Nice,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, when her scarf became entangled in the wheel of her sports
car.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed the Selective Service Act, providing for
the first peacetime draft in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, a groundbreaking ceremony took place in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> at the
site of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>' world headquarters.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, <PERSON>Gerald R. Ford Jr.</PERSON> upset Rep. <PERSON>Bartel J. Jonkman</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s Fifth District Republican primary.
   In <DATE>1957</DATE>, President <PERSON>Dwight D. Eisenhower</PERSON> met in <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>,
with <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> Gov. <PERSON>Orval Faubus</PERSON>, who pledged to uphold court-ordered
school integration, but also pleaded for patience.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, the Soviet space probe Luna II became the first manmade
object to reach the moon as it crashed onto the lunar surface.
   In <DATE>1963</DATE>, <PERSON>Mary Ann Fischer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Aberdeen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, gave birth to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first surviving quintuplets, four girls and a boy.
   In <DATE>1964</DATE>, the third session of the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>21st
Ecumenical Council</ORGANIZATION> _ also known as <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> II _ convened in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1975</DATE>, Pope <PERSON>Paul VI</PERSON> declared Mother <PERSON>Elizabeth Ann Bayley Seton</PERSON>
the first U.S.-born saint.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Princess Grace</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Monaco</LOCATION>, who had gained fame as
American movie star <PERSON>Grace Kelly</PERSON>, died at age 52 of injuries she
suffered in a car crash the day before.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s president-elect, <PERSON>Bashir Gemayel</PERSON>, was killed by
a bomb that shattered the headquarters of his Lebanese Christian
Phalangist Party in east <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Shiite Moslem extremists in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> released the Rev.
<PERSON>Benjamin Weir</PERSON>, an American missionary, after holding him captive for
16 months.
   Ten years ago: Actress <PERSON>Jean Seberg</PERSON>, who committed suicide, was
buried in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the same day the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> admitted that in <DATE>1970</DATE>, it
spread rumors <PERSON>Seberg</PERSON> had become pregnant by a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Black
Panther Party</ORGANIZATION> in order to ``neutralize'' her support for black
militants.
   Five years ago: <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s new coalition government came into
being, with <PERSON>Shimon Peres</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> as prime minister and
<PERSON>Yitzhak Shamir</PERSON> of the Likud bloc as foreign minister promising to
exchange roles for the second half of their terms.
   One year ago: Hurricane Gilbert, one of the strongest storms on
thousands of residents to flee. Bad weather forced Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>
to make an unscheduled stop in <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> during a tour of
southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: ``Lone Ranger'' <PERSON>Clayton Moore</PERSON> is 75.
Television newscaster <PERSON>Hughes Rudd</PERSON> is 68. Actress <PERSON>Zoe Caldwell</PERSON> is 56.
Feminist author <PERSON>Kate Millett</PERSON> is 55. Actor <PERSON>Nicol Williamson</PERSON> is 51.
Singer-actress <PERSON>Joey Heatherton</PERSON> is 45. Actress <PERSON>Mary Crosby</PERSON> is 30.
   Thought for today: ``My country right or wrong, is a thing no
patriot would think of saying except in a desperate case. It is like
saying, `My mother, drunk or sober!''' _ <ORGANIZATION>G.K. Chesterton</ORGANIZATION>, English
poet and essayist (1874-1936), commenting on a sentiment originally
expressed by <PERSON>Stephen Decatur</PERSON>, American naval officer (1779-1820).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Advance for Thursday, Sept. 14</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890515-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-15-89 0821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv21   05-15 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv21,0501</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv21</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, May 21</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>May 21</DATE>, the <DATE>141st day of 1989</DATE>. There are 224
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>May 21, 1927</DATE>, <PERSON>Charles A. Lindbergh</PERSON> landed his ``Spirit of <LOCATION>St.
Louis</LOCATION>'' near <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, completing the first solo airplane flight
across the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. Lindbergh covered a distance of more
than 3,600 miles in 33{ hours.
   On this date:
   In <DATE>1542</DATE>, Spanish explorer Hernando de Soto died while searching
for gold along the <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1832</DATE>, the first <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION> got under way
in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>. The delegates would nominate President <PERSON>Andrew Jackson</PERSON>
for a second term.
   In <DATE>1840</DATE>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> was declared a British colony.
   In <DATE>1904</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Jazz</ORGANIZATION> musician <PERSON>Fats Waller</PERSON> was born.
   In <DATE>1919</DATE>, a proposed federal amendment to give women the right to
vote passed the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> by a vote of 304 to
89.
   In <DATE>1924</DATE>, 14-year-old <PERSON>Bobby Franks</PERSON> was murdered in a ``thrill
killing'' by <PERSON>Nathan Leopold Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard Loeb</PERSON>, two students at
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1941</DATE>, a German U-boat sank the American freighter SS <PERSON>Robin
Moore</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1948</DATE>, in a message to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, President <PERSON>Harry Truman</PERSON> urged
statehood for <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1956</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> exploded the first airborne hydrogen
bomb over Bikini Atoll in the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, the musical ``Gypsy,'' inspired by the life of stripper
<PERSON>Gypsy Rose Lee</PERSON>, opened on Broadway with <PERSON>Ethel Merman</PERSON> in the role of
<ORGANIZATION>Gypsy</ORGANIZATION>'s mother, Rose.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, the nuclear-powered submarine Scorpion, with 99 men
aboard, was last heard from. (The remains of the sub were later
found on the ocean floor 400 miles southwest of the <LOCATION>Azores</LOCATION>.)
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, Socialist <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> assumed office as
president of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Deputed Testamony</ORGANIZATION>, a 14-to-one shot, won the Preakness
Stakes in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, while <LOCATION>Kentucky Derby</LOCATION> winner Sunny's Halo
finished sixth.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <PERSON>Patti Frustaci</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, who was expecting
septuplets, gave birth to six live babies, three of whom died in
the following weeks.
   Ten years ago: Former <LOCATION>San Francisco City</LOCATION> Supervisor <PERSON>Dan White</PERSON>
was convicted in the shooting deaths of Mayor <PERSON>George Moscone</PERSON> and
Supervisor <PERSON>Harvey Milk</PERSON>.
   Five years ago: In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Jose Napoleon Duarte</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION> appealed to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to approve more aid without
attaching what he called ``degrading'' conditions.
   One year ago: The Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> reported that the
Communist Party leaders of <LOCATION>Armenia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Azerbaijan</LOCATION> were dismissed
after fresh outbreaks of ethnic tensions in the two southern Soviet
republics.
   Today's birthdays: Novelist <PERSON>Harold Robbins</PERSON> is 73. Actor <PERSON>Raymond
Burr</PERSON> is 72. Soviet human rights activist <PERSON>Andrei Sakharov</PERSON> is 68.
   Thought for today:
   ``Poverty is the great reality. That is why the artist seeks
it.'' _ <ORGANIZATION>Anais Nin</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891205-0184 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-PX-12-05-89 1113EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-The'80s-TenYears Adv16-2ndAdd   12-05 0879</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-The '80s-Ten Years, Adv 16 - 2nd Add,0934</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv16</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions Dec. 16-17 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>UNDATED: Heritage USA.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   MAY 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>Joint House-Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee hearings on Iran-Contra
affair open in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   MAY 8 _ Democratic front-runner <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON> quits presidential
race amid reports of extramarital affair with <PERSON>Donna Rice</PERSON>. Hart
re-enters race in <DATE>December</DATE>, then withdraws for good.
   MAY 17 _ Iraqi warplane fires missiles at frigate USS Stark on
patrol in <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing 37 sailors.
   MAY 28 _ West German teen-ager <PERSON>Mathias Rust</PERSON> lands small plane in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Red Square</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 7 _ Central American presidents sign peace pact calling for
democratic reforms, amnesties and end to outside support for
insurgencies.
   OCT. 14 _ Eighteen-month-old <PERSON>Jessica McClure</PERSON> falls into
abandoned well in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and is pulled out alive 58 hours later as
entire nation watches.
   <DATE>OCT. 19</DATE> _ Black <DATE>Monday</DATE> on Wall Street. Dow Jones average drops
record 508 points on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> stock exchanges; other world markets
decline.
   <DATE>OCT. 23</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> rejects nomination of <ORGANIZATION>Robert Bork to Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>NOV. 29</DATE> _ South Korean jetliner disappears over <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION> with 115
aboard; woman later confesses to planting bomb as part of North
Korean conspiracy.
   DEC. 8 _ <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> sign treaty to destroy 2,611
Soviet and American medium-range missiles.
   DEC. 9 _ Palestinian uprising begins in Israeli-occupied <LOCATION>West
Bank</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gaza Strip</ORGANIZATION>, with rioters protesting auto accident that
killed four Arabs.
   DEC. 20 _ Philippine passenger ferry Dona Paz collides with
tanker; more than 1,600 killed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1988</NOTE>
<NOTE>NATURE'S FURY</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   MAY 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>Joint House-Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee hearings on Iran-Contra
affair open in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   MAY 8 _ Democratic front-runner <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON> quits presidential
race amid reports of extramarital affair with <PERSON>Donna Rice</PERSON>. Hart
re-enters race in <DATE>December</DATE>, then withdraws for good.
   MAY 17 _ Iraqi warplane fires missiles at frigate USS Stark on
patrol in <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing 37 sailors.
   MAY 28 _ West German teen-ager <PERSON>Mathias Rust</PERSON> lands small plane in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Red Square</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 7 _ Central American presidents sign peace pact calling for
democratic reforms, amnesties and end to outside support for
insurgencies.
   OCT. 14 _ Eighteen-month-old <PERSON>Jessica McClure</PERSON> falls into
abandoned well in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and is pulled out alive 58 hours later as
entire nation watches.
   <DATE>OCT. 19</DATE> _ Black <DATE>Monday</DATE> on Wall Street. Dow Jones average drops
record 508 points on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> stock exchanges; other world markets
decline.
   <DATE>OCT. 23</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> rejects nomination of <ORGANIZATION>Robert Bork to Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>NOV. 29</DATE> _ South Korean jetliner disappears over <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION> with 115
aboard; woman later confesses to planting bomb as part of North
Korean conspiracy.
   DEC. 8 _ <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> sign treaty to destroy 2,611
Soviet and American medium-range missiles.
   DEC. 9 _ Palestinian uprising begins in Israeli-occupied <LOCATION>West
Bank</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gaza Strip</ORGANIZATION>, with rioters protesting auto accident that
killed four Arabs.
   DEC. 20 _ Philippine passenger ferry Dona Paz collides with
tanker; more than 1,600 killed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>1989</NOTE>
<NOTE>YEAR OF FREEDOM</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   MAY 5 _ <ORGANIZATION>Joint House-Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee hearings on Iran-Contra
affair open in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   MAY 8 _ Democratic front-runner <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON> quits presidential
race amid reports of extramarital affair with <PERSON>Donna Rice</PERSON>. Hart
re-enters race in <DATE>December</DATE>, then withdraws for good.
   MAY 17 _ Iraqi warplane fires missiles at frigate USS Stark on
patrol in <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, killing 37 sailors.
   MAY 28 _ West German teen-ager <PERSON>Mathias Rust</PERSON> lands small plane in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Red Square</LOCATION>.
   AUG. 7 _ Central American presidents sign peace pact calling for
democratic reforms, amnesties and end to outside support for
insurgencies.
   OCT. 14 _ Eighteen-month-old <PERSON>Jessica McClure</PERSON> falls into
abandoned well in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and is pulled out alive 58 hours later as
entire nation watches.
   <DATE>OCT. 19</DATE> _ Black <DATE>Monday</DATE> on Wall Street. Dow Jones average drops
record 508 points on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> stock exchanges; other world markets
decline.
   <DATE>OCT. 23</DATE> _ <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> rejects nomination of <ORGANIZATION>Robert Bork to Supreme
Court</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>NOV. 29</DATE> _ South Korean jetliner disappears over <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION> with 115
aboard; woman later confesses to planting bomb as part of North
Korean conspiracy.
   DEC. 8 _ <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> sign treaty to destroy 2,611
Soviet and American medium-range missiles.
   DEC. 9 _ Palestinian uprising begins in Israeli-occupied <LOCATION>West
Bank</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Gaza Strip</ORGANIZATION>, with rioters protesting auto accident that
killed four Arabs.
   DEC. 20 _ Philippine passenger ferry Dona Paz collides with
tanker; more than 1,600 killed.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Dec. 16-17</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881122-0203 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-22-88 0703EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     11-22 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0616</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The recently resigned head of Soviet space
research says his country's maiden space shuttle launch had
``absolutely no scientific value,'' and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet shuttle
programs are in ``deep trouble'' economically.
   <PERSON>Roald Z. Sagdeev</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>
for 15 years, said <DATE>last week</DATE>'s inaugural Soviet shuttle flight _
like the <DATE>1981</DATE> flight of the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle _ was an
``outstanding technological achievement.''
   The shuttle, however, ``is technology of the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. Why
should we pay <DATE>20th century</DATE> money for it?''
   ``My personal view is that American experience with the shuttle
indicates that from the point of view of cost efficiency, the
shuttle is in deep trouble,'' said <PERSON>Sagdeev</PERSON>, who has followed closely
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> decision-making process on the shuttle and is a key science
and arms control adviser to President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>PALMDALE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The recently resigned head of Soviet space
research says his country's maiden space shuttle launch had
``absolutely no scientific value,'' and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet shuttle
programs are in ``deep trouble'' economically.
   <PERSON>Roald Z. Sagdeev</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>
for 15 years, said <DATE>last week</DATE>'s inaugural Soviet shuttle flight _
like the <DATE>1981</DATE> flight of the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle _ was an
``outstanding technological achievement.''
   The shuttle, however, ``is technology of the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. Why
should we pay <DATE>20th century</DATE> money for it?''
   ``My personal view is that American experience with the shuttle
indicates that from the point of view of cost efficiency, the
shuttle is in deep trouble,'' said <PERSON>Sagdeev</PERSON>, who has followed closely
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> decision-making process on the shuttle and is a key science
and arms control adviser to President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The recently resigned head of Soviet space
research says his country's maiden space shuttle launch had
``absolutely no scientific value,'' and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet shuttle
programs are in ``deep trouble'' economically.
   <PERSON>Roald Z. Sagdeev</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>
for 15 years, said <DATE>last week</DATE>'s inaugural Soviet shuttle flight _
like the <DATE>1981</DATE> flight of the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle _ was an
``outstanding technological achievement.''
   The shuttle, however, ``is technology of the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. Why
should we pay <DATE>20th century</DATE> money for it?''
   ``My personal view is that American experience with the shuttle
indicates that from the point of view of cost efficiency, the
shuttle is in deep trouble,'' said <PERSON>Sagdeev</PERSON>, who has followed closely
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> decision-making process on the shuttle and is a key science
and arms control adviser to President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The recently resigned head of Soviet space
research says his country's maiden space shuttle launch had
``absolutely no scientific value,'' and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet shuttle
programs are in ``deep trouble'' economically.
   <PERSON>Roald Z. Sagdeev</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>
for 15 years, said <DATE>last week</DATE>'s inaugural Soviet shuttle flight _
like the <DATE>1981</DATE> flight of the first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle _ was an
``outstanding technological achievement.''
   The shuttle, however, ``is technology of the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. Why
should we pay <DATE>20th century</DATE> money for it?''
   ``My personal view is that American experience with the shuttle
indicates that from the point of view of cost efficiency, the
shuttle is in deep trouble,'' said <PERSON>Sagdeev</PERSON>, who has followed closely
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> decision-making process on the shuttle and is a key science
and arms control adviser to President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900412-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-90 1137EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-LetelierArrest 1stLd-Writethru a0495 04-12 0592</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Letelier Arrest, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0495,0602</SECOND>
<HEAD>FBI Arrests Man in Assassination of Chilean Ambassador</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS one graf after 4th graf, `U.S. officials...', to ADD
comment from Sen. Kennedy. Picks up 5th graf, `A former...'.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JAMES MARTINEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TAMPA, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fugitive arrested in the <DATE>1976</DATE> car bombing
that killed the former Chilean ambassador was being held without
bond awaiting trial in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   <PERSON>Jose Dionisio Suarez y Esquivel</PERSON>, 51, arrested at his <LOCATION>St.
Petersburg</LOCATION> home early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, waived his rights to a bond
hearing before a federal magistrate here on charges of conspiracy
to murder a foreign official.
   Suarez is accused of providing the explosives and detonating
devices in the explosion that killed former Chilean Ambassador
<PERSON>Orlando Letelier</PERSON> and business colleague <PERSON>Ronni Moffitt</PERSON> as they drove
to work in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 21, 1976</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said they expect the new Chilean government to
prosecute top intelligence officials of the former military
government of Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> on charges of planning
Letelier's assassination, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reported today. The
killings long have been a sore point in relations between the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, welcomed the
arrest and commended the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION>, but said, ``Unfortunately, the
masterminds of this atrocity remain at large in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>. I hope and
expect that the new democratic government in that nation will do
all in its power to bring them to justice.''
   A former Chilean diplomat, <PERSON>Jose Miguel Barros</PERSON>, testified in a
Chilean court last year that <ORGANIZATION>Letelier</ORGANIZATION>'s assassination was ordered
by Chilean army Gen. <PERSON>Juan Manuel Contreras Sepulveda</PERSON>, who headed
the <ORGANIZATION>Chilean National Intelligence Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pinochet stepped down as president last month after the election
of a civilian, <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> marhals said <PERSON>Suarez</PERSON> would be flown to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> as early
as <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. If convicted, he could face life in prison.
   <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> agents said <PERSON>Suarez</PERSON> had been leading a secretive, cautious
life in <LOCATION>St. Petersburg</LOCATION>, rarely even leaving the house.
   ``To our knowledge, he hasn't been employed in the <DATE>last 12</DATE> to 14
years,'' said Assistant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorney <PERSON>Terry Furr</PERSON>.
   But his 30-year-old wife <PERSON>Elizabeth</PERSON> said <PERSON>Suarez</PERSON> worked at home as
an artist and never realized his face had been plastered in post
offices and courthouses around the country for more than a decade.
   ``No one ever notified him he was a fugitive,'' said <PERSON>Mrs.
Suarez</PERSON>, a hospital administration employee and mother of a
15-month-old boy. She said they have lived either in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>St.
Petersburg</LOCATION> throughout their nine-year marriage.
   Letelier served as Chilean ambassador to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in
<DATE>1971-1973</DATE>, during the presidency of <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, who was
ousted by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in a coup. Letelier had begun to emerge as a
leading international critic of <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> when he and <PERSON>Moffitt</PERSON> were
assassinated.
   <PERSON>Michael V. Townley</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizen who also was an employee of
the Chilean intelligence agency, was arrested in <DATE>April 1978</DATE>.
Townley was extradited to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, confessed to planting
the bomb on the order of superiors and spent 40 months in prison.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Townley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Suarez</PERSON> and fugitive <PERSON>Virgilio
Pablo Paz</PERSON> built the bomb used in the assassination. Suarez
allegedly provided the explosives and detonators and purchased the
bomb parts.
   A federal grand jury also indicted three Chilean army personnel
in connection with the case.
   Maj. <PERSON>Armando Fernandez Larios</PERSON> pleaded guilty to being an
accessory after the fact to <ORGANIZATION>Letelier</ORGANIZATION>'s death and was sentenced to
22 months in custody. The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> has failed to obtain
the extradition of two others.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891125-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-25-89 1449EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Lebanon 1stLd-Writethru   11-25 0814</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Lebanon, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0508,0839</SECOND>
<HEAD>New President Dissolves Aoun Cabinet; Nation Mourns Mouawad</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: Insert graf after 15th, `But his...' with Hrawi, Hoss meeting
possibly to replace Aoun; Insert graf after 21st pvs, `Jumblatt and Berri...'
to UPDATE with candidate rejecting Cabinet post, and delete 24th pvs, `The
Greek...' to conform. Pickup 25th, `Also Saturday...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BEI1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FAROUK NASSAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BEIRUT, Lebanon (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Elias Hrawi</PERSON> declared the
Cabinet of the rebellious army chief, Gen. <PERSON>Michel Aoun</PERSON>, dissolved
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and named a new government to end 14 years of civil war.
His predeccesor, slain after 17 days in office, was buried.
   In a rare display of national unity, businesses in both Moslem
and Christian areas closed for a nationwide day of mourning for
<PERSON>Rene Mouawad</PERSON>, killed by a bomb <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Church bells rang and bands struck slow drum beats as his
flag-draped coffin inched through crowds in <LOCATION>Mouawad</LOCATION>'s hometown of
Zgorta. His widow, <LOCATION>Nayla</LOCATION>, and daughter Rima and son <PERSON>Michel</PERSON> walked
sobbing behind the cortege.
   Weeping women tossed roses and waved from balconies.
   Patriarch <PERSON>Nasrallah Sfeir</PERSON>, spiritual head of the Maronite
community, presided over the service, and <ORGANIZATION>Papal Nuncio Paolo Ponte</ORGANIZATION>
read a message from Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON>, saying the pontiff was
praying for <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s salvation.
   A 21-gun salute was fired as the coffin was put into a crypt at
<ORGANIZATION>St. Mary's Church</ORGANIZATION>, where it will remain until completion of a tomb
at the cemetery.
   <PERSON>Aoun</PERSON> said <PERSON>Hrawi</PERSON>'s election <DATE>Friday</DATE> was ``as unconstitutional as
that of Mouawad. Both have been elected under Syrian occupation.''
   ``They should have waited to find out who killed Mouawad before
appointing a new president,'' he said in a statement.
   No one has claimed responsibility for <ORGANIZATION>Mouawad</ORGANIZATION>'s assassination.
   Hrawi put himself on a collision course with <PERSON>Aoun</PERSON> by dismissing
the general's military Cabinet before dawn and forming a national
unity government with members from <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s seven major sects.
   The new government, under Sunni Moslem Prime Minister <PERSON>Salim
Hoss</PERSON>, is to oversee implementation of an Arab League-brokered plan
to introduce political reforms aimed at ending the civil war, which
has killed more than 150,000 people.
   Aoun rejects the accord, which was approved by parliamentarians
in <DATE>October</DATE> and which cleared the way for <ORGANIZATION>Mouawad</ORGANIZATION>'s election <DATE>Nov. 5</DATE>.
The military general said the plan is unacceptable because it does
not provide a timetable for the withdrawal of 40,000 Syrian troops
from <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>.
   Mouawad, 64, and 23 other people were killed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by a
remote-controlled bomb in Moslem west <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   It was not clear how <PERSON>Hrawi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hoss</PERSON> would go about removing <PERSON>Aoun</PERSON>
to head off final partition of the country. Aoun commands the
loyalty of a cohesive army of about 20,000 that stands as the
nation's mightiest fighting machine.
   But his troops are outnumbered and outgunned by the Syrians,
whose soldiers control <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of Lebanese territory under a
<DATE>1976</DATE> Arab League mandate to quell civil war fighting.
   State-run television in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> said <PERSON>Hrawi</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hoss</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION>
Minister <PERSON>Albert Mansour</PERSON> were meeting possibly to discuss dismissing
<PERSON>Aoun</PERSON> and appointing a new army commander.
   Aoun is holding out with his troops in the country's Christian
enclave, comprising east <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> and land to the north. He said his
Cabinet is <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s only legitimate government.
   The 54-year-old soldier, a Maronite Christian like <PERSON>Hrawi</PERSON>, was
named to head an interim Cabinet by outgoing President <PERSON>Amin Gemayel</PERSON>
on <DATE>Sept. 22, 1988</DATE>, because Parliament was unable to agree on a new
president.
   Lebanon had been without a president since then until
parliamentarians approved the peace plan and then elected Mouawad.
   Hoss, whom Mouawad selected to be prime minister, also was named
prime minister by <PERSON>Hrawi</PERSON>, in addition to foreign minister.
   He retained Druse warlord <PERSON>Walid Jumblatt</PERSON> as public works
minister, and Shiite Moslem militia chieftain <PERSON>Nabih Berri</PERSON> as
minister of electrical and water resources. Berri also was given
the housing and cooperatives portfolio.
   Jumblatt and <PERSON>Berri</PERSON> are <LOCATION>Syria</LOCATION>'s main allies in <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>. They
fielded the largest Moslem militias in the war against the
Christians.
   <PERSON>Michel Sassine</PERSON>, a Greek Orthdox offered the position of deputy
premier and labor minister, turned down the post and flew to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>
without explaining why, state-run television in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> reported.
   Hoss introduced <PERSON>George Saadeh</PERSON>, leader of the right-wing <ORGANIZATION>Phalange
Party</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION>'s largest Christian political force, into the new
   Saadeh, a Maronite based in the Christian enclave controlled by
<PERSON>Aoun</PERSON>'s army, said his participation must first be approved by his
party's Politburo.
   Also <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, Israeli jets blasted Palestinian targets in
eastern <LOCATION>Lebanon</LOCATION> for the second time in three days, wounding two
guerrillas, in the 16th such air raid on the country this year.
   The target was a <LOCATION>Bekaa</LOCATION> base of Ahmed Jibril's Popular Front for
   Police said at least two PFLP-GC fighters were wounded as two
fighter-bombers fired six rockets into the base in two runs at
<TIME>10:50 a.m.</TIME>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-49507 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi089_b_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-089 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> United States &amp; Canada </F>
<H3> <TI>   `China 21st Century Agenda' Delegation Visits U.S. </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    `China 21st Century Agenda' Delegation Visits U.S. </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0805094994 Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service in Chinese 0643 
GMT 7 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> OW0805094994 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service </F>
<F P=105>  Chinese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 
