<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06082216 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06082216 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Clarence Leo Fender, the electric guitar pioneer whose renowned "Stratocaster"
models have been revered and played by such rock 'n' roll legends as Buddy
Holly, Eric Clapton and Jimi Hendrix, died here Thursday, apparently of
natural causes.;    Mr. Fender, 81, was found unconscious in his home by his
wife, Phyllis, and died en route to a hospital, police said said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CLARENCE LEO FENDER, 81, ELECTRIC GUITAR
PIONEER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     While <PERSON>Mr. Fender</PERSON> did not invent the electric guitar, he did revolutionize
and perfect it. Called both the <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> and the <PERSON>Thomas Edison</PERSON> of the
instrument, <PERSON>Mr. Fender</PERSON>'s solid-body guitars and amplifiers set the industry
standard for excellence.;    "Fender was a phenomenon," said <PERSON>Peter Schuelzky</PERSON>,
general manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Guitar Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>. "He created the guitar (to)
which all other manufacturers try to conform. . . . Nobody has been quite as
successful.";    <ORGANIZATION>Electric</ORGANIZATION> guitars made <PERSON>Mr. Fender</PERSON>, a tinkerer and inventor by
nature, a millionaire.;    In <DATE>1954</DATE>, he created the <LOCATION>Stratocaster</LOCATION>, a
revolutionary instrument hailed as a near-perfect fusion of electronics,
ergonomics and technology on one side, and design and aesthetics on the
other.;    "The Stratocaster is like the <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION>," said <PERSON>Dick Dale</PERSON>, 53,
known as "king of the surf guitar" for pioneering the surf rock sound in
<LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> in the late-1950s and early '60s. "It can never be
surpassed."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Fullerton  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910322  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  218  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday March 22, 1991
00082216,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06098082 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06098082 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Los Angeles Times; Leo Fender, right, with his G&amp;L Musical
Products partner George Fullerton in 1982, with a bass.; PHOTO (Photo
Montage): Below, from left, Telecaster masters Albert Collins, Keith Richards
and Bruce Springsteen; and Stratocaster blasters Eric Clapton, Stevie Ray
Vaughan, Robert Cray and Jimi Hendrix.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  PLAYING a Fender guitar is somewhat like driving a very powerful car,
preferably American-made -- perhaps a 1967 Corvette.;    In the case of the
three-pickup Stratocaster model, you find that this sculpted piece of wood
with two curved teeth by the fingerboard -- an instrument built for Batman --
fits the human body surprisingly well. After you've plugged it into an
amplifier (perhaps a Fender Twin Reverb from the late '60s), you suddenly are
capable of producing the most alarming . . . sound.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LEO FENDER, MUSIC MAKER
THE ENGINEER OF ROCK 'N' ROLL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Pop Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Such was the legacy of <PERSON>Clarence Leo Fender</PERSON>, the force behind one of the
century's enduring American artifacts -- the solid-body electric guitar. If
rock 'n' roll was invented by <PERSON>Robert Johnson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Elvis Presley</PERSON> and <PERSON>Little
Richard</PERSON>, it was Fender and his company who launched the music's true machine.;
   Purists will argue that Fender, a <ORGANIZATION>Fullerton</ORGANIZATION> resident who died last month at
82, was not the first to make such a device. Claims are made for the
Rickenbacker company, and for the remarkable <PERSON>Les Paul</PERSON>, who also produced music
from a solid piece of wood in the <DATE>1940s</DATE> (eventually manufactured by <ORGANIZATION>Fender</ORGANIZATION>'s
American arch-rival, the <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Corp.</ORGANIZATION>). Acoustic guitars had been electrified
for jazz since the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, and perhaps before.;    It was Fender's genius,
though, to mass-produce the solid-wood design that not only made the raucous,
reverberating sounds of rock, but also managed to look the part.;    Like
<PERSON>Levi</PERSON>'s and <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Stratocaster</LOCATION> and its more basic cousin, the
Telecaster swept the world in the early '50s. Both have since been copied and
recopied by just about every guitar maker from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>. But if
their design can be found everywhere, nothing has quite duplicated the spirit
of the originals.;    <PERSON>Tom Wheeler</PERSON>, in his encyclopedic book "American
Guitars," perfectly catches their visual audacity: "Fender guitars were rock
and roll, jet-age, outrageous. They were as futuristic as <LOCATION>Sputnik</LOCATION>, or as tacky
as all the sequins in <PERSON>Webb Pierce</PERSON>'s wardrobe, depending on your point of view.
Before Fender, there were no turquoise musical instruments, no Candy Apple
Red, scoop-body dragsters with gold-plated hardware and white plastic knobs.";
   <ORGANIZATION>Fender</ORGANIZATION>'s creations became not only the sound of rock 'n' roll, but its
history. Such artists as <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Holly</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Eric Clapton</PERSON> became
inseparable from their Stratocasters (and, in some cases, from their onstage
demolition of them.);    Inevitably, anyone who admired these Strat players
(or Telecaster players such as <PERSON>Bruce Springsteen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Keith Richards</PERSON> and <PERSON>Danny
Gatton</PERSON>) would want to own such odd-looking, interesting instruments -- and
would treasure them.;    It is a wonderful aural coincidence that the words
Strad and Strat sound so much alike: A violinist will talk about his
Stradivarius with the same reverence that a rock guitarist will speak about
his Stratocaster.;    The father of the Strat was no great fan of rock.
Rather, <ORGANIZATION>Fender</ORGANIZATION> was fascinated by the way you could get sounds by placing
magnets under the metal strings of guitars.;    He experimented with coils of
different sizes and impedances -- more intrigued, perhaps, by capacitors than
by harmonies. He held dozens of patents, and so much attention was lavished on
his guitars that one could overlook the fact he made the world's first
electric bass in <DATE>1951</DATE> -- an instrument that also changed pop music forever.;  
 With astounding understatement, he once said, "I never had too much feeling
for the acoustic guitars. I had always felt that the guitar could do a much
better job if it wasn't limited by the properties of that vibrating top.";   
For him, the combinations of sound, once you were freed from the acoustic
limit, seemed infinite. With a revolutionary three pickups (the Stratocaster
version; <ORGANIZATION>Telecasters</ORGANIZATION> had only two) and the proper amplifier, musicians could
fill a large room. With enough amplification, they would discover soon enough,
their devices could fill a stadium.;    But even a beginner learns that with a
little experimentation, a mere flick of the wrist, the Fender sound can be
sustained, or vibrated -- and cranked up. It can be turned into Hendrix-like
feedback or <PERSON>Stevie Ray Vaughan-like</PERSON> blues or the <LOCATION>B.B.</LOCATION> King-like solos on those
Rolling Stones albums.;    This is not a guitar for "<PERSON>Michael</PERSON>, Row the Boat
Ashore." Even on the first test drive, you can imagine it assaulting <LOCATION>Jericho</LOCATION>'s
walls.;    In time, caught in the entropy of our century, things went
downhill. Fender sold the company to <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1965</DATE>, and since then connoisseurs
of Strats and Teles have looked for the phrase "pre-CBS" whenever one was
sold.;    Guitars that were traded routinely for under <MONEY>$200</MONEY> in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and
early <DATE>1960s</DATE> suddenly were going for thousands.;    "Fender Stratocaster, <DATE>1957</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Sunburst</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Been Through Hell</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>" is still a typical advertisement.
Eventually, the unthinkable happened: Fenders were made in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Some still
are, although the company's present owners again are making them in the <LOCATION>United
States.</LOCATION>;    Fender himself, the man <PERSON>Wheeler</PERSON> calls the "<PERSON>Henry Ford</PERSON> of electric
guitars," continued to build them. He founded <ORGANIZATION>G &amp; L Musical Products</ORGANIZATION>, and many
G &amp; L instruments are much prized.;    By most accounts, <PERSON>Fender</PERSON> was outwardly
the perfect nerd, absorbed by mechanical things until the end. "He rarely
wears a suit, and he's almost never without his little leather holster full of
screwdrivers," said a long-ago profile in Guitar Player. "In his shirt, he
keeps a plastic pocket protector stuffed with pens, pencils and a metal
ruler.";    He never learned to play the guitar. (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JEFFREY A. FRANK, Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910407  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  964  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 7, 1991
00098082,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06083056 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06083056 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; EQUIPMENT; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Clarence Leo Fender, the electric guitar pioneer whose famous Stratocaster
model has been played by such rock stars as Buddy Holly, Eric Clapton and Jimi
Hendrix, has died. He was 82.;    Mr. Fender was found unconscious Thursday in
his home by his wife, Phyllis, and died en route to St. Jude Medical Center
and Rehabilitation Center, said police Sgt. Mike Maynard.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  C.L. FENDER, 82, PIONEER IN ELECTRIC GUITARS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The death appeared to be from natural causes, <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> said.;    <PERSON>Mr. Fender</PERSON>
guitar designs at his shop.;    With its candy-colored curves, the
Stratocaster revolutionized music by making mass-produced electric guitars
that were affordable and had great sound.;    "He definitely was a pioneer.
It's still probably the No. 1 selling guitar in the world," said <PERSON>John
Carruthers</PERSON>, a guitar maker in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> who used to be a consultant to <PERSON>Mr.
Fender</PERSON>. "He was the <ORGANIZATION>Henry Ford</ORGANIZATION> of electric guitars. He basically turned it
into an assembly-line situation."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Fullerton  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910323  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  164  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 23, 1991
00083056,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0196 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 0709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:GuitarWizard Adv06   11-29 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Guitar Wizard, Adv06,0889</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv06</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thurs PMs, Dec. 6, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Texas Rocker Seeks To Push Guitar to Limits - With Elegance</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUZANNE GAMBOA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>EL PASO, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Minutes after mesmerizing an audience with
his electric guitar wizardry, rocker <PERSON>Eric Johnson</PERSON> is shyly greeting
fans and signing autographs.
   He talks with such humility and kindness that it's a tossup
which is more enchanting: the music he makes on stage or his boyish
friendliness backstage.
   Underneath the good humor lies a demanding perfectionism in a
musician on a quest for a brand-new sound from his '54 Fender
Stratocaster.
   ``The older I get, the more I listen to the guitar and go: `Oh
God. I need a new turn-on. It's got to do something more. Is this
all?''' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said in an interview. ``You can get a screechy,
nervous, jittery sound out of the electric guitar and it's like,
gah, it's got to go farther now.
   ``I'm trying to figure out a way. I want it to be real
rocked-out-and-buzz guitar, but I want it to have a little elegance
to it. And in its real <LOCATION>Neanderthal</LOCATION>, paleolithic way, I want it to
have a tuxedo on.''
   Elegance isn't a word often tied to the electric guitar. But
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> was schooled in classical piano and he's found ways to
bring the two together.
   ``I try to listen to more classical music because of the chord
changes and the breadth of the music. To me, classical in a way is
the most unassuming music,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   Johnson, 35, first hit the <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> music scene in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> at
age 15, mystifying musicians with his electric guitar mastery that
evoked images of rock revolutionary <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>.
   The late <PERSON>Stevie Ray Vaughan</PERSON> was among those awed by his talent.
Vaughan once said that by the time <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> reached his late teens,
he was so advanced it was difficult for him to find musicians to
keep up with him.
   Johnson's solo debut album, ``Tones,'' earned him a <DATE>1986</DATE> Grammy
nomination for ``Best Instrumental of the Year'' for the track
``Zap.'' However, the album had little commercial success.
   <DATE>Nearly four years later</DATE>, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> has poured his heart and
experience into a new album, ``Ah Via Musicom'' on <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>.
The album and its rich instrumental ``Cliffs of <LOCATION>Dover</LOCATION>'' have
received favorable response and substantial play on album-only rock
radio stations.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said the album has changed his audiences from the
musicians-only crowd to the fickle radio listeners eternally
searching for a new sound and new star.
   Some of the credit must go to <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>, which has heavily
promoted the album, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   But the album also is the embodiment of what makes <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>
great, his tireless perfectionism and insatiable search for a
different sound.
   ``I spent two months solid working on `Tones.' I spent 15 months
on this last record, not solid but close to it. I just did it over
and over and over, trying to figure out a way to get the guitar
tone like I wanted it,'' he said.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> recorded ``Ah Via
Musicom'' three times with two bass players, <PERSON>Kyle Brock</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roscoe
Beck</PERSON>; three drummer-percussionists, <PERSON>Tommy Taylor</PERSON>, <PERSON>James Ferner</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Paul Bissell</PERSON>; and several arrangements.
   <PERSON>Brock</PERSON>, who has played with <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> 20 years, and <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>,
formerly a drummer for <PERSON>Christopher Cross</PERSON>, are traveling with
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>. The three joined rock guitarist <PERSON>Joe Satriani</PERSON> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
in late <DATE>September</DATE> for three weeks of concerts on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>.
   ``I like to think <PERSON>Eric</PERSON>'s music is the music we're all involved
in,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. ``It's something a little promising and offers a
little alternative. So much of the music you hear is very
predictable. There's a freshness about what <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> does.''
   What <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> eternally seeks from his guitar and amplifiers and
electronic gizmos is what musician's call ``tone.''
   ``Tone is the colors you put together to create a certain hue of
sound of a particular instrument - the way you play the instrument,
the emotion you put behind it, the technique, phrasing, all the
things that are elements of your art or your music that create a
sound,'' he said.
   Johnson chooses to search for tone with more conventional
amplifiers and foot pedals from the <DATE>'60s</DATE> and <DATE>'70s</DATE> that lack the
computer chips found in today's equipment.
   In his live performances, he spreads a buffet of pedals before
his feet. While his fingers dance over the frets of his guitar, his
feet skip between the pedals, producing an energetic, intellectual
sound.
   ``There's kind of this side of me that treats it (the music)
like a laboratory where I work in the studio or I work in my
practice house and fiddle with all sorts of electronics and stuff,
trying to make the guitar sound better,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   ``I don't mean that with a negative connotation, but you play
for 20 years and it's the same old guitar sound. At this point, I'm
not reinventing the guitar, I don't have a whole new sound or
anything, but I'm trying to figure out a way to hone and perfect
the electrical guitar sound.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs PMs, Dec. 6</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Minutes after mesmerizing an audience with
his electric guitar wizardry, rocker <PERSON>Eric Johnson</PERSON> is shyly greeting
fans and signing autographs.
   He talks with such humility and kindness that it's a tossup
which is more enchanting: the music he makes on stage or his boyish
friendliness backstage.
   Underneath the good humor lies a demanding perfectionism in a
musician on a quest for a brand-new sound from his '54 Fender
Stratocaster.
   ``The older I get, the more I listen to the guitar and go: `Oh
God. I need a new turn-on. It's got to do something more. Is this
all?''' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said in an interview. ``You can get a screechy,
nervous, jittery sound out of the electric guitar and it's like,
gah, it's got to go farther now.
   ``I'm trying to figure out a way. I want it to be real
rocked-out-and-buzz guitar, but I want it to have a little elegance
to it. And in its real <LOCATION>Neanderthal</LOCATION>, paleolithic way, I want it to
have a tuxedo on.''
   Elegance isn't a word often tied to the electric guitar. But
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> was schooled in classical piano and he's found ways to
bring the two together.
   ``I try to listen to more classical music because of the chord
changes and the breadth of the music. To me, classical in a way is
the most unassuming music,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   Johnson, 35, first hit the <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> music scene in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> at
age 15, mystifying musicians with his electric guitar mastery that
evoked images of rock revolutionary <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>.
   The late <PERSON>Stevie Ray Vaughan</PERSON> was among those awed by his talent.
Vaughan once said that by the time <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> reached his late teens,
he was so advanced it was difficult for him to find musicians to
keep up with him.
   Johnson's solo debut album, ``Tones,'' earned him a <DATE>1986</DATE> Grammy
nomination for ``Best Instrumental of the Year'' for the track
``Zap.'' However, the album had little commercial success.
   <DATE>Nearly four years later</DATE>, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> has poured his heart and
experience into a new album, ``Ah Via Musicom'' on <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>.
The album and its rich instrumental ``Cliffs of <LOCATION>Dover</LOCATION>'' have
received favorable response and substantial play on album-only rock
radio stations.
   <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said the album has changed his audiences from the
musicians-only crowd to the fickle radio listeners eternally
searching for a new sound and new star.
   Some of the credit must go to <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>, which has heavily
promoted the album, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   But the album also is the embodiment of what makes <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>
great, his tireless perfectionism and insatiable search for a
different sound.
   ``I spent two months solid working on `Tones.' I spent 15 months
on this last record, not solid but close to it. I just did it over
and over and over, trying to figure out a way to get the guitar
tone like I wanted it,'' he said.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>Capitol Records</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> recorded ``Ah Via
Musicom'' three times with two bass players, <PERSON>Kyle Brock</PERSON> and <PERSON>Roscoe
Beck</PERSON>; three drummer-percussionists, <PERSON>Tommy Taylor</PERSON>, <PERSON>James Ferner</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Paul Bissell</PERSON>; and several arrangements.
   <PERSON>Brock</PERSON>, who has played with <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> 20 years, and <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>,
formerly a drummer for <PERSON>Christopher Cross</PERSON>, are traveling with
<PERSON>Johnson</PERSON>. The three joined rock guitarist <PERSON>Joe Satriani</PERSON> in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
in late <DATE>September</DATE> for three weeks of concerts on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>.
   ``I like to think <PERSON>Eric</PERSON>'s music is the music we're all involved
in,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. ``It's something a little promising and offers a
little alternative. So much of the music you hear is very
predictable. There's a freshness about what <PERSON>Eric</PERSON> does.''
   What <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> eternally seeks from his guitar and amplifiers and
electronic gizmos is what musician's call ``tone.''
   ``Tone is the colors you put together to create a certain hue of
sound of a particular instrument - the way you play the instrument,
the emotion you put behind it, the technique, phrasing, all the
things that are elements of your art or your music that create a
sound,'' he said.
   Johnson chooses to search for tone with more conventional
amplifiers and foot pedals from the <DATE>'60s</DATE> and <DATE>'70s</DATE> that lack the
computer chips found in today's equipment.
   In his live performances, he spreads a buffet of pedals before
his feet. While his fingers dance over the frets of his guitar, his
feet skip between the pedals, producing an energetic, intellectual
sound.
   ``There's kind of this side of me that treats it (the music)
like a laboratory where I work in the studio or I work in my
practice house and fiddle with all sorts of electronics and stuff,
trying to make the guitar sound better,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   ``I don't mean that with a negative connotation, but you play
for 20 years and it's the same old guitar sound. At this point, I'm
not reinventing the guitar, I don't have a whole new sound or
anything, but I'm trying to figure out a way to hone and perfect
the electrical guitar sound.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890721-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-89 1334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APArts:Woodstock-Hendrix Adv30   07-21 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Arts: Woodstock-Hendrix, Adv 30,0850</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv30</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, July 30 and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-AP Arts: Woodstock</HEAD>
<HEAD>Jimi Hendrix: Psychedelic Tour Guide for Woodstock Nation</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>STEVE BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Every other month, cemetery workers tending <LOCATION>Jimi
Hendrix</LOCATION>'s grave replace the lawn worn away by fans.
   Every day they take away the offerings left near his granite
marker the night before: marijuana butts, lighters, guitar picks.
   Twenty years after <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> _ and 19 years after <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> _
admirers still come to sit and think about the young man who helped
define psychedelic rock.
   When Hendrix cranked up his <PERSON>Fender Stratocaster</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
became ``The Third Stone From the Sun,'' and a nation of rebellious
youth grooved to ``The Star-Spangled Banner.''
   When he hit <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> in <DATE>August 1969</DATE>, his music and his career
were soaring. A year and a month later they crashed.
   He died in his sleep <DATE>Sept. 18, 1970</DATE>, while on a European tour.
The coroner's report said he choked on his own vomit. The trace of
barbituates in his blood was small, not enough to kill, the coroner
said.
   Hendrix was born in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>. He left <ORGANIZATION>Garfield High
School</ORGANIZATION> after his junior year to join the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> because he didn't
want to spend another <DATE>summer</DATE> mowing the lawns for his father's
landscape business.
   ``He wanted one of those screaming eagles on his shoulder,''
said <PERSON>James A.</PERSON> ``Al'' <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, referring to the patch worn by
paratroopers from the <ORGANIZATION>101st Airborne Division</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix served after <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and before <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, when lyrics from
his songs would be scribbled on soldiers' helmets.
   He went by <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> in those days and was shy, his father said. The
shortened name and stage antics, such as squirting lighter fluid on
his burning guitar, were just show business he adopted later.
   ``He was a good boy,'' the 70-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> said. ``He played
Little League, football, swimming. We called him `<PERSON>Buster</PERSON>' 'til he
was 9 or 10. Then he wanted to be called Jimmy.''
   Jimmy and his younger brother, <PERSON>Leon</PERSON>, were raised by their
father. His parents were divorced and his mother died when he was
10.
   The family's console record player filled the rooming house
where they lived with <PERSON>B.B. King</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Muddy Waters</ORGANIZATION>, and young <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>
mimicked the records, using a broom for a guitar.
   ``I had this old ukelele from one of my jobs,'' said his father,
a former musician in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>. ``I gave it to
him. Of course he couldn't get much music out of it.''
   So <ORGANIZATION>Al Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> paid a friend <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for his acoustic guitar and gave
it to <LOCATION>Jimmy</LOCATION>. The first electric guitar was bought at a music shop
along with a saxophone for dad. When they fell behind on payments,
the sax went back, but the electric guitar stayed.
   ``I told him he'd go farther with that guitar than I would with
the sax,'' <PERSON>Hendrix</PERSON> said with a laugh. ``I never did get him an amp.
He used to plug into his friends'. Still, he got music out of it.
The <PERSON>Peter Gunn</PERSON> theme was one of the first things I remember him
playing.''
   Hendrix didn't return to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> when a back injury from a
parachute jump ended his military career. Instead, he headed East
in search of the music scene, and played in backup bands for the
Supremes, the <ORGANIZATION>Isley Brothers and Little Richard</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix's guitar playing attracted a record producer who took
him to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. He became ``Jimi.'' <PERSON>Mitch Mitchell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Noel Redding</PERSON>
were added to make the <ORGANIZATION>Jimi Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>.
   The band conquered <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and played at the <ORGANIZATION>Monterey Pop
Festival</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE>, which led to a record contract and a tour with
the <ORGANIZATION>Monkees</ORGANIZATION>, the made-for-television pop group. Predictably, the
music styles clashed and the tour was cut short. By <DATE>August 1969</DATE>,
the Experience was finished but <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s music was taking off. He
formed the short-lived Band of Gypsies with <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Miles</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Billy
Cox</PERSON>, whom he'd met in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix left behind a rich musical legacy, influencing a
generation of musicians such as Prince and <PERSON>Eric Clapton</PERSON>. His
records still are among the best sellers at many stores. The heart
of his discography remains ``Are You Experienced?,'' ``Axis: Bold
as Love'' and ``Electric Ladyland.''
   <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> has been slow to honor <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, partly because his
reputation for drugs and sex didn't seem exemplary for young
citizens. <ORGANIZATION>Garfield High School</ORGANIZATION> put his bust in the second-floor
library and, when city fathers balked at a plaque in a city park,
the British director of <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s zoo volunteered a spot.
   Today, visitors must stand on the <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> memoril rocks for
the best view of the giraffes, zebras and gazelles in the zoo's
African savanna exhibit.
   A bronze sunburst marks the spot, and a sign in the shrubs
nearby reads: ``There's no telling how many lives your spirit will
go through _ die and be reborn.'' _ <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, May 30</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Every other month, cemetery workers tending <LOCATION>Jimi
Hendrix</LOCATION>'s grave replace the lawn worn away by fans.
   Every day they take away the offerings left near his granite
marker the night before: marijuana butts, lighters, guitar picks.
   Twenty years after <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> _ and 19 years after <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> _
admirers still come to sit and think about the young man who helped
define psychedelic rock.
   When Hendrix cranked up his <PERSON>Fender Stratocaster</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
became ``The Third Stone From the Sun,'' and a nation of rebellious
youth grooved to ``The Star-Spangled Banner.''
   When he hit <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> in <DATE>August 1969</DATE>, his music and his career
were soaring. A year and a month later they crashed.
   He died in his sleep <DATE>Sept. 18, 1970</DATE>, while on a European tour.
The coroner's report said he choked on his own vomit. The trace of
barbituates in his blood was small, not enough to kill, the coroner
said.
   Hendrix was born in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>. He left <ORGANIZATION>Garfield High
School</ORGANIZATION> after his junior year to join the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> because he didn't
want to spend another <DATE>summer</DATE> mowing the lawns for his father's
landscape business.
   ``He wanted one of those screaming eagles on his shoulder,''
said <PERSON>James A.</PERSON> ``Al'' <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, referring to the patch worn by
paratroopers from the <ORGANIZATION>101st Airborne Division</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix served after <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and before <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, when lyrics from
his songs would be scribbled on soldiers' helmets.
   He went by <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON> in those days and was shy, his father said. The
shortened name and stage antics, such as squirting lighter fluid on
his burning guitar, were just show business he adopted later.
   ``He was a good boy,'' the 70-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> said. ``He played
Little League, football, swimming. We called him `<PERSON>Buster</PERSON>' 'til he
was 9 or 10. Then he wanted to be called Jimmy.''
   Jimmy and his younger brother, <PERSON>Leon</PERSON>, were raised by their
father. His parents were divorced and his mother died when he was
10.
   The family's console record player filled the rooming house
where they lived with <PERSON>B.B. King</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Muddy Waters</ORGANIZATION>, and young <PERSON>Jimmy</PERSON>
mimicked the records, using a broom for a guitar.
   ``I had this old ukelele from one of my jobs,'' said his father,
a former musician in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>. ``I gave it to
him. Of course he couldn't get much music out of it.''
   So <ORGANIZATION>Al Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> paid a friend <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for his acoustic guitar and gave
it to <LOCATION>Jimmy</LOCATION>. The first electric guitar was bought at a music shop
along with a saxophone for dad. When they fell behind on payments,
the sax went back, but the electric guitar stayed.
   ``I told him he'd go farther with that guitar than I would with
the sax,'' <PERSON>Hendrix</PERSON> said with a laugh. ``I never did get him an amp.
He used to plug into his friends'. Still, he got music out of it.
The <PERSON>Peter Gunn</PERSON> theme was one of the first things I remember him
playing.''
   Hendrix didn't return to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> when a back injury from a
parachute jump ended his military career. Instead, he headed East
in search of the music scene, and played in backup bands for the
Supremes, the <ORGANIZATION>Isley Brothers and Little Richard</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix's guitar playing attracted a record producer who took
him to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. He became ``Jimi.'' <PERSON>Mitch Mitchell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Noel Redding</PERSON>
were added to make the <ORGANIZATION>Jimi Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>.
   The band conquered <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and played at the <ORGANIZATION>Monterey Pop
Festival</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1967</DATE>, which led to a record contract and a tour with
the <ORGANIZATION>Monkees</ORGANIZATION>, the made-for-television pop group. Predictably, the
music styles clashed and the tour was cut short. By <DATE>August 1969</DATE>,
the Experience was finished but <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s music was taking off. He
formed the short-lived Band of Gypsies with <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Miles</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Billy
Cox</PERSON>, whom he'd met in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>.
   Hendrix left behind a rich musical legacy, influencing a
generation of musicians such as Prince and <PERSON>Eric Clapton</PERSON>. His
records still are among the best sellers at many stores. The heart
of his discography remains ``Are You Experienced?,'' ``Axis: Bold
as Love'' and ``Electric Ladyland.''
   <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> has been slow to honor <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, partly because his
reputation for drugs and sex didn't seem exemplary for young
citizens. <ORGANIZATION>Garfield High School</ORGANIZATION> put his bust in the second-floor
library and, when city fathers balked at a plaque in a city park,
the British director of <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s zoo volunteered a spot.
   Today, visitors must stand on the <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> memoril rocks for
the best view of the giraffes, zebras and gazelles in the zoo's
African savanna exhibit.
   A bronze sunburst marks the spot, and a sign in the shrubs
nearby reads: ``There's no telling how many lives your spirit will
go through _ die and be reborn.'' _ <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910508-0012
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910508-0012.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Guitar-Pickers Are Making a Market
   ---
   Rock of Ages Spurs
   Old-Model Prices
   ----
   By Robert Tomsho
</HL>
<DATE>
05/08/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
TENNESSEE (TN)
</RE>
<LP>
   DALLAS -- Visitors to the Mandolin Brothers' booth at the
recent Greater Southwest Guitar Show found an eye-popping
price tag hanging from one instrument. "OK, so it's
$100,000," read a sign the Staten Island, N.Y., dealer had
placed nearby. "Go find another one."
   That would be hard to do. The rare 1958 Gibson "Flying V"
was one of only 81 shipped the year it was built. Amid a
recession that has driven down prices for Impressionist
paintings and folk art as well as many collectibles, vintage
guitars are hot -- especially those used by vintage rock 'n'
roll stars.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> auction last year, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>
sold a <DATE>1968</DATE> Fender Stratocaster used at <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Jimi
Hendrix</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$334,000</MONEY> -- nearly four times the expected price.
And actor <PERSON>Gary Busey</PERSON>, who portrayed <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Holly</ORGANIZATION> in a movie,
recently paid <MONEY>$242,000</MONEY> at a <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction in this country
for a <DATE>1945</DATE> Gibson J-45 acoustic once owned by the late
rocker.
   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, an unidentified buyer even paid <MONEY>$1,300</MONEY> for a
fragment of a guitar smashed by rock guitarist <PERSON>Pete Townshend</PERSON>
of the Who. "The guitar market has gone berserk," says
<LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> guitar dealer <PERSON>George Gruhn</PERSON>, also a columnist for
Guitar Player magazine.
   Some industry publications have begun tracking prices
monthly, and major manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Guitar Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fender Musical Instruments Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, are building high-priced "reissues" of their own
classics. <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>'s <DATE>1959</DATE> Les <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> reissues, named for the
legendary guitarist who originally designed the model, sell
for as much as <MONEY>$4,199</MONEY>, compared with about <MONEY>$1,699</MONEY> for a
similar new model.
   The original pre-1960 <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Les Paul</ORGANIZATION> models regularly
sell for more than <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>. And rare prewar Martin D-45
acoustics are going for as much as <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> -- nearly
quintuple the top price of just five years ago. Still, these
prices don't come near the cost of a Stradivarius; one of the
violins sold for <MONEY>$1.7 million</MONEY> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>last November</DATE>.
   The vintage guitar boom is being spurred on, in part, by
aging baby boomers seeking to recapture a piece of their
past. "We've got money to spend, and guitars, banjos and
fretted instruments are the instruments of our youth," says
<PERSON>Kerry Keane</PERSON>, a musical instrument appraiser for <ORGANIZATION>Skinner Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,
an auction house based in <LOCATION>Bolton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   As with most collecting fads, though, fortune hunters
should beware. Like cars, most used guitars still sell for
far less than they cost new, and dealers -- who pay top
dollar only for mint-condition guitars -- complain that many
would-be sellers expect any battered instruments they drag in
to be worth a small fortune.
   Moreover, with prices skyrocketing, guitar counterfeiters
are altering serial numbers and name plates, modifying
cheaper models, and even making pseudovintage instruments
from scratch. Some dealers now dismantle instruments before
buying to check for original paint, wiring and hardware.
"There is no such thing as a perfect forgery," says <ORGANIZATION>Mandolin
Brothers President Stanley Jay</ORGANIZATION>.
   As in so many other collecting areas, prices of vintage
guitars are being driven up by free-spending foreign
collectors and dealers. Many of them are Japanese, who prize
the American-made instruments for their tone, craftsmanship
and continuing status as the choice of most international
recording artists.
   Many <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitar dealers send their inventory lists
directly to foreign collectors and dealers, despite grumbling
from some musicians and dealers about the number of vintage
instruments leaving this country. While industry figures are
hard to come by in a largely cash-and-carry business, some
dealers say foreign buyers account for as much as <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of
their vintage sales.
   Overseas buyers have even hired <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> "brokers" to scour
pawnshops and newspaper want ads. "They're out in the
heartland looking for these guitars," says <PERSON>Mark Pollack</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Charley</LOCATION>'s Guitar Shop here.
   High-bidding Japanese buyers have become fixtures at the
growing number of guitar shows, which is why <PERSON>Mr. Pollack</PERSON> made
sure he had a Japanese-speaking employee in his booth at the
recent <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> show, the largest of its kind. Japanese
investors have been known to buy instruments by the truckload
for shipment back to their country, where even mass-produced
workhorses like 1970s-vintage Fender Stratocasters are
selling for as much as <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> -- nearly three times the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
price.
   "Mostly, it's the sound," says collector <PERSON>Mac Yasuda</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, an executive with <ORGANIZATION>Tsumura &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
large Tokyo-based manufacturer of pharmaceuticals and bath
additives. With the help of a toll-free <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> telephone
number, <PERSON>Mr. Yasuda</PERSON> buys instruments for both himself and
company President <PERSON>Akira Tsumura</PERSON>, who recently opened a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>
museum to display his huge collection. <PERSON>Mr. Yasuda</PERSON>'s own
collection includes 50 <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> J-200 acoustic guitars, 15
vintage <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Les Pauls</ORGANIZATION>, and seven out of the 91 D-45
acoustics made by <ORGANIZATION>C.F. Martin Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Nazareth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, before
World War II.
   A variety of factors make some guitars worth more than
others. Rarities such as the prewar D-45s -- first made for
cowboy crooner Gene Autry -- and the elegant jazz guitars
handmade by the late <PERSON>John D'Angelico</PERSON> have long been prized
for their tone and craftsmanship.
   Collectors seek out certain early Les Paul models because
of the "flame" patterns in the curly maple wood used to make
them. And the <ORGANIZATION>Fender Stratocasters</ORGANIZATION>' mystique is due largely
to their use by rock stars such as <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Eric
Clapton</PERSON>.
   Meanwhile, a small but growing nostalgia market has
developed for some instruments that never had much snob
appeal. Dealers say baby boomers, apparently recalling the
first budget-priced instruments that their parents bought
them, are paying as much as <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> for Danelectro electric
guitars once sold in <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Roebuck &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> catalogs for <MONEY>$59</MONEY>
and up.
   <PERSON>Dominick Montuoro</PERSON>, a disabled <LOCATION>New Rochelle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
construction worker, began collecting them after playing one
that belonged to a friend's son. "I just fell in love with
it," says <PERSON>Mr. Montuoro</PERSON>, who now has 90 of the homely
instruments, which feature Masonite tops with pickups, a
piece of electronic hardware, made from modified lipstick
tubes.
   With prices for many vintage guitars rising and falling on
such quirky factors as which model certain rockers used on
their last tour, appraisers caution that vintage guitars are
not for investors seeking huge profits. "For the most part,
it's a slow, steady increase," says <PERSON>Mr. Keane</PERSON>, the instrument
appraiser.
   Moreover, veteran dealers like <PERSON>Mr. Gruhn</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> warn
that prices could plummet if economic troubles beset <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
or <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. "If anything happens to reduce foreign demand, this
market will react as though it were struck in the solar
plexis," he says.
   Some professional musicians wouldn't mind seeing that
happen. "It's outrageous," says <ORGANIZATION>Warner Brothers</ORGANIZATION> recording
artist Ry Cooder, who attended one guitar show a few years
ago, but "crawled out" when he saw the prices. To musicians,
a guitar is a tool, says <PERSON>Mr. Cooder</PERSON>, adding that "a carpenter
wouldn't pay <MONEY>$100</MONEY> for a hammer."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06348260 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06348260 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Jeff Beck, one of the inventors of rock guitar, keeps
growing; PHOTO: Les Paul changed the way guitars were made, played.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  RECORD; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Pop; LES PAUL  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MASTERS AT PULLING STRINGS: THE LEGENDS OF THE
ELECTRIC GUITAR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  RECORDINGS; Each review is signed at the bottom  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  "Les Paul: The Legend; and the Legacy"; (<LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>; CDs and cassettes);
(star)(star)(star); The role of the electric guitar as the symbolic instrument
of pop is now undeniable. But its rise began at the cusp of the '50s with <ORGANIZATION>Les
Paul.</ORGANIZATION>;   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> not only redefined that role -- from a chugging member of the
rhythm section in jazz big bands to a solo instrument -- he provided it with
technical and technological innovations that have now become commonplace. He
designed the now famous "Les Paul" guitar and developed the multi-track
recording process and the echo pedal.;   None of these innovations would have
made much of an impact if he hadn't been such a dazzling guitarist. But he
was. And it is all to be had on this rollicking four-CD boxed set.;   From
such initial sparklers as "Lover" and "Caravan" to such hits as "How High the
Moon" he recorded with <PERSON>Mary Ford</PERSON>, his wife and vocalist, <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s fleeting
phrasings and his melodic meanderings, all recorded in multi-track mode with
one musical section topping another in layers of sound, are the stuff of pop
history in the making.;   The historical side is documented by <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> himself in
the enclosed booklet with comments by the master on a track-by-track basis.
The scrupulously constructed set also comes with 30 unreleased songs from
<PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s personal vaults and such rare selections as several radio programs and
even the commercials he recorded for Rheingold Beer.;   Much of the material
-- and <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s warbly vocals -- sound like period pop pieces from the <DATE>'50s</DATE>. But
his trebly tones and his acrobatic solos are constantly astounding and remind
us that it was <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> who set the stage for the work of such future guitar
heroes as <PERSON>Jeff Beck</PERSON>. And the sound and the innovations he achieved -- the echo
and the rest -- are the stuff on which all of modern pop is based.; -- <PERSON>Harry
Sumrall</PERSON>; Rock; <PERSON>JEFF BECK</PERSON>; "Beckology"; (Epic/Legacy; CD and cassettes);
(star)(star)(star)(star); Of the reigning triumvirate of Clapton-Beck-Page
that virtually invented the modern concept of rock guitar in the '60s, <PERSON>Jeff
Beck</PERSON> is arguably the most intriguing. While his two counterparts have pursued
somewhat static (if brilliant) creative courses (<PERSON>Clapton</PERSON> in the blues and Page
in heavy metal), <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> has been all over the musical map.;   "Beckology" charts
that course with the same sense of rollicking abandon that has characterized
<PERSON>Beck</PERSON>'s career. In the process, it encapsulates some of the wildest, noisiest,
most eccentric, idiosyncratic, wonderful, remarkable, low-down and dirty and
technically breathtaking guitar licks ever committed to record.;   It opens
with three previously unreleased cuts of <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> scratching out the blues with
the Tridents in <DATE>1963</DATE>. Astoundingly, the <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> sound with its whoops and
screeches and fleeting runs was there from the start, particularly on "Nursery
Rhyme.";   From there, the set is a non-stop roller coaster ride through
<PERSON>Beck</PERSON>'s revolutionary work with the Yardbirds on such hits as "Heart Full of
Soul" (in which he mimicked a sitar) to the epochal "I'm A Man" that begat
every garage and metal band that has come along since. (The set includes four
songs the group recorded live for the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> in its heyday in <DATE>1965</DATE>).;   And from
there it is on to selections of his performances with eight (!) versions of
the <ORGANIZATION>Jeff Beck Group</ORGANIZATION>, collaborations with the <ORGANIZATION>Jan Hammer Group</ORGANIZATION> and former
<ORGANIZATION>Vanilla Fudgers Appice</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Bogert</PERSON> and the solo efforts from the past decade.; 
 True to the inspired oddness of its namesake, "Beckology" comes in a box that
is made to look like an old Fender guitar case. (The cover of the enclosed
booklet with its scores of photos and Beck-related anecdotes is a guitar.) It
is, hands down, the best packaging of any of the boxed sets available.;   And
it's perfectly matched by the set's music.;   From the Martian take of <ORGANIZATION>Les
Paul</ORGANIZATION> on "<PERSON>Jeff</PERSON>'s Boogie" to the eloquent interpretation of <PERSON>Charles Mingus</PERSON>'
classic "Goodbye Pork Pie Hat" to the grandiose reading of "People Get Ready"
with old mate/nemesis <PERSON>Rod Stewart</PERSON>, "Beckology" proves that <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> has never
stuck with one genre or style. The only constant in his work has been the
uniqueness he has brought to every piece of music he has plucked.; -- <LOCATION>H.S.</LOCATION>;
JIMI <LOCATION>HENDRIX</LOCATION>; "Stages"; (Reprise; CDs and cassettes); (star)(star) 1/2; If
<PERSON>Beck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clapton</PERSON> and Page invented the modern rock guitar, it was Hendrix who
embraced their various innovations and wrapped them up in one all-encompassing
onslaught. The Page metal riffs and the <PERSON>Clapton</PERSON> blues and the <PERSON>Beck</PERSON> noises
became in <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>'s work a vast new world of sound.;   Much of that world
existed onstage, where he expanded on the sounds and songs of his studio
albums.;   While there are a number of "concert" records and CDs of <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>,
"Stages" is different in that it captures that world as it evolved over the
four years of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s legendary -- if brief -- career.;   Each of the set's
four CDs is drawn from individual shows (1967-1970) and comparisons of those
performances are variously redundant and illuminating. The <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION> show from
<DATE>1967</DATE> comes with notably straight renditions of the initial <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> hits as the
newly formed Experience feels its way through the material.;   The <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> shows (<DATE>1968</DATE>, <DATE>1969</DATE>) are much looser, with the interplay between the
guitarist and bassist <PERSON>Noel Redding</PERSON> and drummer <PERSON>Mitch Mitchell</PERSON> expanding in
various "psychedelic" directions. And the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> show of <DATE>1970</DATE> (with bassist
<PERSON>Billy Cox</PERSON>) is a mostly sloppy performance that reveals the boredom that had
set in on <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s part with the sound that had become his signature.;  
Songs such as "Purple Haze" and "Fire" appear on all the discs, with new
slants on each as <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s sound evolved. And there are moments of inspired
spontaneity at various points.;   But none of this is new. Hendrix's volatile
shows have been documented on other records. And his real innovations, most of
which were accomplished in the studio, are obviously not included.;   This is
a set for true fans only. Anyone else who would like a full plate of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s
career should consult the excellent <DATE>1990</DATE> set "Lifelines: The Jimi Hendrix
Story," also released by Reprise.; -- <LOCATION>H.S.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>TEXAS</LOCATION>; "Mother's Heaven";
(<ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>; CD and cassette); (star)(star)(star); Don't let the name fool you.
This Scottish dance-pop outfit is about as Texan as a cowboy in a plaid skirt.
Lead singer <PERSON>Sharleen Spiteri</PERSON> has a great big, sultry voice and a bravura,
Annie Lennox-style delivery that really lights up the often-unremarkable
material on the band's second album. The band's booming, epic-scale Euro-soul
melodies will spark comparisons with classic Eurythmics and the dance-floor
ravers Primal Scream. Instrumentally, the group borrows much from the lush,
seamless, keyboard-driven style of <PERSON>Bruce Hornsby</PERSON>. This stuff is an arresting
alternative to the din of hip-hop and house. "Mother's Heaven," "Why Believe
In You" and "Alone With You" are all rock-solid pop singles that deserve to be
played at red-line volume. It would be a pity to see a talent as big as <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
get lost in the crowd of emerging pop groups.; -- <PERSON>David Plotnikoff</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Staff Writers  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911213  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  21  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,220  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, December 13, 1991
00348260,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06092178 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06092178 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Country and Western guitarists Shorty Robbins, Eddie Dean and the Desert Rose
Band's John Jorgenson joined approximately 200 mourners this weekend to
remember electric guitar pioneer Clarence Leo Fender.;    Mr. Fender died
March 21 of complications related to Parkinson's disease. He was 81.;    Dean
wiped away tears as he played guitar and sang two western ballads at a
Saturday service at Temple Baptist Church.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GUITARIST C.L. FENDER EULOGIZED  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries;  SETTING THE RECORD STRAIGHT (publ. 4/2/91, pg. 5B);  Because of
an editor's error, a headline in Monday's Mercury News incorrectly identified
Clarence Leo Fender, a guitar maker who died March 21.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "I'll treasure his guitar as long as I shall live," Dean said.;    Other
musicians, including steel guitarist <PERSON>Alvino Rey</PERSON>, performed at the ceremony to
thank the man who invented the famed Telecaster and Stratocaster guitars
despite being unable to read music or play instruments.;    <PERSON>Mr. Fender</PERSON>'s
guitars first were favored by country and western musicians who were persuaded
to try them out in the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>. Some at the service said they owed their
careers to him.;    "He has contributed more to the music industry than any
other individual," said <PERSON>Hank Penny</PERSON>, longtime friend and western band leader.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Fullerton  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910401  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  194  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, April 1, 1991
00092178,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900918-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-18-90 1232EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HendrixRemembered     09-18 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hendrix Remembered,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>20 Years After His Death, Hendrix Fans Keep Guitar Great's Memory
Alive</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto SE3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>RENTON, Wash. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twenty years after his death, legendary
rock guitarist <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> still packs 'em in.
   They don't come in large numbers at any one time, but they come.
Some bring guitars, some bring flowers. Visitors might spend a
little time at his grave, strumming tunes.
   ``The crowds here have mellowed a bit, as has the mood of the
country,'' said <PERSON>Hank Kerns</PERSON>, general manager of <ORGANIZATION>Greenwood Memorial
Park</ORGANIZATION>, where <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> is buried.
   ``Once in a while they'll leave a beer can, but we're careful to
get it picked up right away.''
   <PERSON>Kerns</PERSON> said the number of visitors to <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>'s grave has
increased during the past few years, and the Goodwill Games brought
more than usual. One national magazine, he said, listed visiting
the gravesite as one of the things to do in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> while attending
the international athletic contest.
   Hendrix died in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 18, 1970</DATE>. According to coroner's
records, he died when he choked on his vomit. A non-lethal amount
of barbituate drugs was found in his system.
   ``Forever in our hearts,'' reads his headstone, which includes
an electric guitar carved in bas-relief. There is little to
indicate he was the king of acid rock, but by the time of his death
at age 27 he had forged a lasting legacy.
   ``I heard he was buried around here. I needed to make the
pilgrimage,'' <PERSON>Peg Wood</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> during a visit to the cemetery.
   The 26-year-old recently moved to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> to begin
an internship with the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Administration</ORGANIZATION> as she pursues a
Ph.D. in psychology. Her ``other life'' is playing rock guitar.
   ``My parents named me <PERSON>Peggy Sue</PERSON>, for God's sake. I was destined
for a life of decadent rock 'n' roll,'' she said, laughing.
   Hendrix, who grew up in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s predominantly black <ORGANIZATION>Central
Area</ORGANIZATION>, was about 14 when he talked his father into buying him a <MONEY>$5</MONEY>
used guitar, according to <LOCATION>Al Hendrix</LOCATION>.
   ``He wore that thing out,'' the father said. ``Later on I got
him his first electric guitar and I got a sax. I didn't know much
about the sax and he didn't know much about the guitar. So we'd
make quite a bit of noise.''
   At first, the young <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> was content to play along with
recordings of blues greats <PERSON>B.B. King</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Muddy Waters</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``So I told him, `Come up with something original,' and he
did,'' recalled <PERSON>Al Hendrix</PERSON>. ``The first time I heard `Are You
Experienced?' (the first Jimi Hendrix Experience album), it was
something altogether different than what I was used to listening
to.''
   It didn't take long for the elder <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> to become one of his
son's biggest fans. Innovative, sometimes outrageous and blaring
with his music, <PERSON>Jimi</PERSON> was quiet and unassuming offstage, his father
said.
   <PERSON>Al Hendrix</PERSON> still goes to his son's grave about once a month,
still gets a kick out of recalling the times he has found fans
sitting around the grave with guitars in hand.
   Fans frequently leave small items. Peg Wood added a guitar pick
to the collection there.
   ``He was the most inventive guitar player I ever heard,'' she
said. ``I like the blues. But I felt he rewrote them. He changed
the rules so that there weren't any rules. He freed me up.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880720-0268 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-88 1335EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Paul Adv28   07-20 0896</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Paul, Adv 28,0913</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv28</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thu AMs, July 28 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Guitar Great Les Paul Still Plucks The Strings at 73</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL MORAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Les <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> sat on a stool at a basement jazz club
on the <LOCATION>Lower East Side</LOCATION>, the fingers of his left hand cascading down
the neck of his guitar in soft, precise steps.
   At 73, the greatness of his guitar still draws laughs, sighs and
applause from audiences at Fat <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s.
   For the past four years he and his three-piece group have been
playing clubs, performing the same mellow standards <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> has done
for decades. Some of them _ ``Via Con Dios,'' ``How High the Moon''
_ were songs made famous during his long partnership with his
ex-wife, the late singer <PERSON>Mary Ford</PERSON>, from whom he was divorced in
<DATE>1962</DATE>.
   Younger musical stars such as <ORGANIZATION>Led Zeppelin</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jimmy Page</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Dire
Strait</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Mark Knopfler</PERSON> and Dutch guitarist <PERSON>Eddie Van Halen</PERSON> come to
pay tribute and sit in with a musician who did it first and who
many believe still does it best.
   ``In my lifetime, the guitar hasn't changed enough to put in
your hat,'' <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said, picking an imaginary guitar. ``Whether
you're Segovia or <PERSON>Van Halen</PERSON>, you can't do anything unless you can
do it here.''
   <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, a musician-composer-designer-inventor, is the acknowledged
father of electronic music. In <DATE>1937</DATE>, he became the first major
artist to play electric guitar when the 65 members of <PERSON>Fred Waring</PERSON>'s
Pennsylvanians big band voted unanimously to let <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> play his
amplified contraption.
   ``Suddenly it was recognized that power was a very important
part of music,'' he said in an interview. ``To have the dynamics,
to have the way of expressing yourself beyond the normal limits of
an unamplified instrument, was incredible. Today a guy wouldn't
think of singing a song on a stage without a microphone and a sound
system.
   ``But <DATE>today</DATE>, there are a lot of parents who blame Les <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> for
all the racket going on in their basement,'' he said with a smile,
a reference to the thousands of teen-agers whose love affair with
the guitar is expressed in decibels.
   For seven years in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> broadcast a TV show
from their home in <LOCATION>Mahwah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, which the <ORGANIZATION>Listerine Co.</ORGANIZATION> _ sponsor
of the show _ bought for the couple to get them to move to <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   It was with <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> that <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> developed two-track recording, known
today as dubbing, a process that revolutionized recording in the
<DATE>'40s</DATE> and is the backbone of studio work today.
   The guitar that bears his name, the <PERSON>Les Paul</PERSON>, is a legend in its
own right made by the <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>. The list of rock and
fusion jazz musicians who choose to play it reads like a who's who
of modern popular music: blues master <PERSON>B.B. King</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pete Townsend</PERSON> of
The Who, <PERSON>Steve Howe</PERSON> of Yes, jazz great <PERSON>Al DiMeola</PERSON>, Led <ORGANIZATION>Zeppelin</ORGANIZATION>'s
Page and <PERSON>Paul McCartney</PERSON>, who with <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>'s help designed his own
custom version of the guitar.
   In turn, two generations of aspiring guitarists have saved their
money for <ORGANIZATION>Les Pauls</ORGANIZATION>. The most popular model today sells for between
<MONEY>$800</MONEY> and <MONEY>$900</MONEY>.
   It is the <ORGANIZATION>Les Pauls</ORGANIZATION>' bigger, ``fatter'' sound that attracted
musicians back in the late '50s, when the first of the classically
inspired guitars was produced. The <ORGANIZATION>Les Pauls</ORGANIZATION>' innovation was the
use of two, double-coiled pick-ups that reduced the twang of other
guitars and gave the musician a broader range of sounds as the
change the tone or volume on each pick-up.
   <PERSON>Paul Jernigan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>'s marketing director, said sales figures
for the guitar are kept confidential but the 12 <ORGANIZATION>Les Paul</ORGANIZATION> models
continue to grow in popularity and the company now has six months
worth of back orders.
   The instrument's main competition for nearly two decades has
been the <PERSON>Fender Stratocaster</PERSON>, a lighter guitar with a dramatic
molded body. The Stratocaster, or Strat, as it is commonly known,
has its own claim on guitar aristocracy: <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> played a
Strat (and burned several on stage); <PERSON>Eric Clapton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robin Trower</PERSON>
both prefer the Fenders.
   Ironically, <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> said, most kids these days know what a Les <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>
is, but not who he is. He also has mixed feelings about today's
rock 'n' roll and the way his guitar is now being used. He hates
distortion and electronic gimmicks. ``They're just ways of hiding
what the guitarist can't do with these,'' he said, wiggling his
fingers.
   ``The first rock stuff, I mean in the early '60s, it was bad _
bad singers, bad players, bad everything. But they went from three
chords on guitar and by <DATE>1988</DATE> we now have some fantastic musicians
in all fields. There are some kids who can go into a music store
and pick up a guitar today and play anything; it's shocking.''
   But one thing <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> has not done is stop learning.
   <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> has agreed to market a ``super-guitar'' he is now
designing, which he said would sell for nearly <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY>. He also is
expecting a visit from <PERSON>McCartney</PERSON> at Fat <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s for a
performance, though a date has not been set.
   ``You can do anything in music as long as you can think it up,''
he said. ``That's a very exciting thing.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thu AMs, July 28</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891212-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-12-89 0101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HendrixInstitute     12-12 0564</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hendrix Institute,0580</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Jimi Hendrix Management Institute' Keeps Purple Haze Spreading</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By F.N. D'ALESSIO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ken Voss</PERSON> never saw <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> perform live. But
he's spent the 19 years since the death of the counterculture
guitarist keeping his music alive for later generations.
   ``It's funny when I go on tour with <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> material or stage
concerts devoted to his music,'' <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> said recently. ``We get the
14-year-olds and the 34-year-olds, but the 24-year-olds don't seem
to know who <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> was.
   ``There's sort of a gap there _ part of a generation apparently
doesn't realize what a force Hendrix exerted on the music performed
today.''
   Voss is trying to close the gap, spreading the word about the
acid rocker who used his teeth on the guitar strings in an
unsettling, feedback-laden rendition of the national anthem at the
<LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> music festival.
   A former music journalist, <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> is founder of the <ORGANIZATION>Jimi Hendrix
Information Management Institute</ORGANIZATION> (JIMI), curator of a mobile museum
of the star's memorabilia and editor of a quarterly newsletter
titled ``Voodoo Child,'' a name taken from a <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> hit.
   He's become a one-man clearinghouse of information about the
Seattle-born <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> since his drug-related death in a British
ambulance <DATE>Sept. 18, 1970</DATE>.
   ``As my wife says, I'm a fan turned fanatic, I spend 12 to 20
hours a week on <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Voss</PERSON>, 38, said in a telephone
interview from his <LOCATION>Des Plaines</LOCATION> home.
   The newsletter has about 1,500 subscribers, including one fan in
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> who has heard only bootlegged recordings of such
Hendrix selections as ``Foxy Lady'' and ``Purple Haze.''
   A recent edition lists the latest appearances of former members
of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s various backup bands and the going prices for <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>
memorabilia, ranging from <MONEY>$4</MONEY> for a mass-printed poster to <MONEY>$4,495</MONEY>
for a framed and autographed color photograph of the musician.
   ``I've also got a guitar authenticated as having been used by
<LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, but I don't dare exhibit that because it's worth from
<MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY>,'' <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> said.
   ``That particular model of electric guitar from those years (a
Fender Stratocaster) would bring <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> in its own right now, but
the value goes up tenfold if it can be proved that Jimi touched
it.''
   Hendrix touched a lot of guitars during his last years. That's
when he would smash his instrument at the climax of a performance,
douse it with lighter fluid and leave the stage with the guitar
lying in feedback-shrieking flames.
   ``I don't know how many guitars Jimi destroyed, but I do know
that his road men would salvage the parts and try to reassemble new
guitars from the pieces,'' <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> said.
   When <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> takes his mobile museum to nightclubs, concert halls
and college campuses around the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, he notices many visitors
staring at one exhibit _ a copy of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>' death certificate,
which ends with the words: ``Insufficient evidence of circumstances
_ open verdict.''
   ``Too many people these days only know <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> as a `victim' of
drugs, they don't know about his genius as a musician,'' <PERSON>Voss</PERSON> said.
   ``The fact is that although his death was drug-related, <PERSON>Jimi
Hendrix</PERSON> did not die of an overdose. He was not even known among the
musicians of his day as a particularly heavy drug user _ although I
must admit that drug use was more widely tolerated then than it
would be now.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901228-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-28-90 0839EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APArts:Hendrix Adv09   12-28 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP Arts: Hendrix, Adv 09,1079</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv 09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wed PMs, Jan 9 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Foxy Legacy: The Lingering Impact of Jimi Hendrix</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SPENCER BRIGHT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> is dead and selling jeans in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Still selling records, too, 20 years after his death; still
unmatched by all would-be imitators of his furious, blazing mastery
of the electric guitar.
   ``The Hendrix phenomenon has never really gone away,'' says
<PERSON>George McManus</PERSON>, marketing executive at <ORGANIZATION>Polydor Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two decades gone, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> is a briskly moving product. Polydor's
``Cornerstones'' album hit the top five and will shortly go
platinum in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. Wrangler adopted ``Crosstown Traffic'' for a
jeans commercial.
   Bass player <PERSON>Noel Redding</PERSON> and drummer <PERSON>Mitch Mitchell</PERSON>, the
survivors of the <ORGANIZATION>Jimi Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>, each published books this
year.
   ``Jimi's death was the most lucrative act of his sad career,''
according to <LOCATION>Redding</LOCATION>, whose book is partly a diatribe against the
<LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> estate.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION>, which counts Hendrix as an alumnus, kicked off
the year by including his ``Voodoo <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'' as part of its amplified
get-out-of-that-refuge concert in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> for Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON>.
   The anniversary may be a melancholy event for anyone who
remembers the first ear-boggling encounter with ``Foxy Lady,''
``Manic Depression'' or ``Purple Haze'' - ``'Scuse me, while I kiss
the sky'' - from the ``Are You Experienced?'' LP in <DATE>1967</DATE>.
   Serious craziness was the <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> experience: a stoned banshee
swathed in psychedelic foppery, caressing and bullying and
battering his guitar; bending ``The Star-Spangled Banner'' into
weird shapes at <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION>; amazing the plaster casters; fleeing a
concert in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> in a cloud of tear gas; taking too many downers
and choking to death on his own vomit.
   Born in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> found fame in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, and
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is where he died, in his <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> apartment on <DATE>Sept. 18,
1970</DATE>.
   His records have always sold well, but his impact wasn't widely
recognized until the Wrangler jeans company commissioned a survey
into British teen-age musical tastes. Hendrix's name ranked high
alongside living rock stars.
   Wrangler decided to feature <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Crosstown Traffic'' in
what became a highly effective TV commercial. Filmed in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
it showed a handsome young taxi driver who dumps his cab in the
middle of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> and takes off to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. Wrangler followed up
with another commercial including footage of <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> in concert.
   ``His appeal is partly his rebel image and partly his short
life, the <PERSON>James Dean</PERSON> factor,'' Polydor's <PERSON>McManus</PERSON> said. ``But deeper
than that, I believe it is because he is the source of so much of
today's music. People like <LOCATION>Bon Jovi</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Def Leppard</ORGANIZATION> will readily
admit to the debt they owe him. You can hear 20 seconds of a guitar
and know it is <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>. Very few people had that ability.''
   One of the most successful new British bands to cite <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> as
an influence is The Stone Roses from the thriving Manchester scene,
whose ``indie dance'' music combines psychedelia with disco-derived
``house'' music.
   Hendrix's influence can be detected on their two recent Top 10
singles, ``One Love'' and ``Fools Gold''
   ``Hendrix is top for me,'' says <ORGANIZATION>Stone Roses</ORGANIZATION> guitarist <PERSON>John
Squire</PERSON>. ``He was trying to expand peoples' minds in the '60s and
we're trying to do the same thing for the '90s. He had an extrovert
approach which we share. He is one of the few people we can relate
to.''
   The two men most closely related to <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> have contrasting
stories to tell.
   Redding, who was sacked from the band, emphasizes financial
matters. His book, ``Are You Experienced?'' is about the <MONEY>millions
of dollars</MONEY> worth of royalties he claims to be owed.
   <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>'s book, ``The Hendrix Experience,'' is full of pictures
and generally happier.
   Hendrix, according to <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>, ``was far from a tragic
character. For one thing, he had a wicked sense of humor. That's
why the women, in particular, really liked him, because we're
talking about a man who was funny.''
   One of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s secrets as a guitar technician, <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>
writes, were his thumbs, ``nearly as long as his fingers.''
   <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> also complains about his treatment by the estate, but
he had one lucrative gift from <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>: a Fender Stratocaster that
sold for <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> at auction in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   One important figure who has not written his memoirs is <PERSON>Chas
Chandler</PERSON>, former bass player of The Animals who saw <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> in a
<LOCATION>Greenwich Village</LOCATION> club, brought him to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and formed The <ORGANIZATION>Jimi
Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I considered writing a book now and again, but I never had the
time, and anyway I enjoy books too much,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said in a rare
interview.
   He has returned to his roots in a coastal village in the
northeast of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> where he lives with his family and manages a
local rock outfit, The <PERSON>Steve Graham</PERSON> Band.
   Chandler produced the first two Hendrix albums, ``Are You
Experienced?'' and ``Axis: Bold as Love,'' but quit halfway through
``Electric Ladyland,'' frustrated with the hangers-on and endless
rerecording of tracks.
   ``My only obvious regret is I wonder if I didn't walk out maybe
he would still be alive. He is a loss; he was a good friend.
Otherwise, I certainly have no regrets,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said.
   ``I do think there is a death cult around <LOCATION>Jimi</LOCATION>. There is
something black about all this brooding over his death. He is
typified as some sort of brooding genius. But when he was alive he
was a very funny guy, full of laughter. He was quite a gentle lad,
quiet but witty and a good mimic.
   ``You would have thought he went everywhere and burned his
guitar. But he only did it twice.''
   <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said that when he met him, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> hadn't written a
song. ``But I knew there was a place in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for him through the
sheer potential of his guitar. The music audiences in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> had
become quite sophisticated. ... The Beatles were pushing the
boundaries of what was acceptable and audiences were quite willing
to grasp something that was experimental.''
   Chandler also believes <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s appeal endures because of his
imitators.
   ``Most of the riffs played by a lot of guitar bands have their
origins in <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>. He was an originator of sounds, the greatest
guitar player to have lived,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv PM Wed Jan. 9</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> is dead and selling jeans in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   Still selling records, too, 20 years after his death; still
unmatched by all would-be imitators of his furious, blazing mastery
of the electric guitar.
   ``The Hendrix phenomenon has never really gone away,'' says
<PERSON>George McManus</PERSON>, marketing executive at <ORGANIZATION>Polydor Records</ORGANIZATION>.
   Two decades gone, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> is a briskly moving product. Polydor's
``Cornerstones'' album hit the top five and will shortly go
platinum in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. Wrangler adopted ``Crosstown Traffic'' for a
jeans commercial.
   Bass player <PERSON>Noel Redding</PERSON> and drummer <PERSON>Mitch Mitchell</PERSON>, the
survivors of the <ORGANIZATION>Jimi Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>, each published books this
year.
   ``Jimi's death was the most lucrative act of his sad career,''
according to <LOCATION>Redding</LOCATION>, whose book is partly a diatribe against the
<LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> estate.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Army</ORGANIZATION>, which counts Hendrix as an alumnus, kicked off
the year by including his ``Voodoo <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'' as part of its amplified
get-out-of-that-refuge concert in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> for Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON>.
   The anniversary may be a melancholy event for anyone who
remembers the first ear-boggling encounter with ``Foxy Lady,''
``Manic Depression'' or ``Purple Haze'' - ``'Scuse me, while I kiss
the sky'' - from the ``Are You Experienced?'' LP in <DATE>1967</DATE>.
   Serious craziness was the <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> experience: a stoned banshee
swathed in psychedelic foppery, caressing and bullying and
battering his guitar; bending ``The Star-Spangled Banner'' into
weird shapes at <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION>; amazing the plaster casters; fleeing a
concert in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> in a cloud of tear gas; taking too many downers
and choking to death on his own vomit.
   Born in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> in <DATE>1942</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> found fame in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, and
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> is where he died, in his <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> apartment on <DATE>Sept. 18,
1970</DATE>.
   His records have always sold well, but his impact wasn't widely
recognized until the Wrangler jeans company commissioned a survey
into British teen-age musical tastes. Hendrix's name ranked high
alongside living rock stars.
   Wrangler decided to feature <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Crosstown Traffic'' in
what became a highly effective TV commercial. Filmed in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
it showed a handsome young taxi driver who dumps his cab in the
middle of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> and takes off to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>. Wrangler followed up
with another commercial including footage of <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> in concert.
   ``His appeal is partly his rebel image and partly his short
life, the <PERSON>James Dean</PERSON> factor,'' Polydor's <PERSON>McManus</PERSON> said. ``But deeper
than that, I believe it is because he is the source of so much of
today's music. People like <LOCATION>Bon Jovi</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Def Leppard</ORGANIZATION> will readily
admit to the debt they owe him. You can hear 20 seconds of a guitar
and know it is <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION>. Very few people had that ability.''
   One of the most successful new British bands to cite <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> as
an influence is The Stone Roses from the thriving Manchester scene,
whose ``indie dance'' music combines psychedelia with disco-derived
``house'' music.
   Hendrix's influence can be detected on their two recent Top 10
singles, ``One Love'' and ``Fools Gold''
   ``Hendrix is top for me,'' says <ORGANIZATION>Stone Roses</ORGANIZATION> guitarist <PERSON>John
Squire</PERSON>. ``He was trying to expand peoples' minds in the '60s and
we're trying to do the same thing for the '90s. He had an extrovert
approach which we share. He is one of the few people we can relate
to.''
   The two men most closely related to <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION> have contrasting
stories to tell.
   Redding, who was sacked from the band, emphasizes financial
matters. His book, ``Are You Experienced?'' is about the <MONEY>millions
of dollars</MONEY> worth of royalties he claims to be owed.
   <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>'s book, ``The Hendrix Experience,'' is full of pictures
and generally happier.
   Hendrix, according to <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>, ``was far from a tragic
character. For one thing, he had a wicked sense of humor. That's
why the women, in particular, really liked him, because we're
talking about a man who was funny.''
   One of <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s secrets as a guitar technician, <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>
writes, were his thumbs, ``nearly as long as his fingers.''
   <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> also complains about his treatment by the estate, but
he had one lucrative gift from <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>: a Fender Stratocaster that
sold for <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> at auction in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   One important figure who has not written his memoirs is <PERSON>Chas
Chandler</PERSON>, former bass player of The Animals who saw <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> in a
<LOCATION>Greenwich Village</LOCATION> club, brought him to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and formed The <ORGANIZATION>Jimi
Hendrix Experience</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I considered writing a book now and again, but I never had the
time, and anyway I enjoy books too much,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said in a rare
interview.
   He has returned to his roots in a coastal village in the
northeast of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> where he lives with his family and manages a
local rock outfit, The <PERSON>Steve Graham</PERSON> Band.
   Chandler produced the first two Hendrix albums, ``Are You
Experienced?'' and ``Axis: Bold as Love,'' but quit halfway through
``Electric Ladyland,'' frustrated with the hangers-on and endless
rerecording of tracks.
   ``My only obvious regret is I wonder if I didn't walk out maybe
he would still be alive. He is a loss; he was a good friend.
Otherwise, I certainly have no regrets,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said.
   ``I do think there is a death cult around <LOCATION>Jimi</LOCATION>. There is
something black about all this brooding over his death. He is
typified as some sort of brooding genius. But when he was alive he
was a very funny guy, full of laughter. He was quite a gentle lad,
quiet but witty and a good mimic.
   ``You would have thought he went everywhere and burned his
guitar. But he only did it twice.''
   <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said that when he met him, <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION> hadn't written a
song. ``But I knew there was a place in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for him through the
sheer potential of his guitar. The music audiences in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> had
become quite sophisticated. ... The Beatles were pushing the
boundaries of what was acceptable and audiences were quite willing
to grasp something that was experimental.''
   Chandler also believes <ORGANIZATION>Hendrix</ORGANIZATION>'s appeal endures because of his
imitators.
   ``Most of the riffs played by a lot of guitar bands have their
origins in <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>. He was an originator of sounds, the greatest
guitar player to have lived,'' <PERSON>Chandler</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040989-0082 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 41672 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 9, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 5; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1757 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RICKENBACKER GUITARS ARE HIP -- AGAIN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL FLAGG, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It was <DATE>1964</DATE>, the movie theater was showing "A Hard Day's Night," and five young 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> rockers strained to read the names on the guitars the Beatles were 
playing. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>George Harrison</PERSON> had a Rickenbacker," recalled <PERSON>Roger McGuinn</PERSON>, who still 
remembers every guitar in the movie. A few days later, <PERSON>McGuinn</PERSON> traded in his 
folk guitar for a gleaming new Rickenbacker electric. 
</P>
<P>
In fact, he played it the next year on the Byrds' first hit record. 
</P>
<P>
Long since out of fashion, Rickenbackers are suddenly the rage again. With a 
reputation for expensive quality -- a sort of guitar version of the <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> -- 
they're big with yuppies and with foreign buyers these days. 
</P>
<P>
Until the Beatles, <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION> was just another guitar maker with an unlikely 
home in conservative <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. The company -- once an innovator -- became 
too conservative, even stodgy, some critics say. Rickenbacker, they contend, 
wasn't adroit enough to adapt to changes in taste and technology in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> 
and the invasion of foreign-made instruments. 
</P>
<P>
Rickenbacker didn't really seem to care about selling a million guitars or 
becoming a giant like Fender or <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>, so it has maintained its reputation for 
quality. And, unlike other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitar makers, it has refused to move its 
manufacturing overseas. 
</P>
<P>
After making guitars for nearly 60 years, <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION> has yet to hit sales of 
<MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> a year, or about what three busy T.G.I. Friday-type restaurants 
would do. 
</P>
<P>
Now the nondescript factory in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> is swamped with orders for the first 
time since the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, and <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION> is wrestling with problems it hasn't had 
since then: How to make all those guitars without getting sloppy and tarnishing 
its reputation as a small, quality manufacture. 
</P>
<P>
The people who buy Rickenbackers may be dentists and lawyers now, but they were 
adolescents in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> when the Beatles, the Byrds and the Who played 
Rickenbackers. 
</P>
<P>
"A lot of the British rock groups in the '60s used them, and nostalgia's a big 
part of their appeal now," said <PERSON>Richard R. Smith</PERSON>, a guitar collector and author 
of <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION>'s official history. 
</P>
<P>
The guitars' sound is so distinct that guitar players can often instantly 
identify one on a record. And even non-experts know there's something different 
about the sharp, scratchy guitar on the first few seconds of the Beatles' 
"Ticket to Ride," or the 12-string guitar that sounds like chimes on the Byrds' 
first hit, "<PERSON>Mr. Tambourine</PERSON> Man." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Convinced Guitar Was a Fad 
</P>
<P>
The guitars' unusually high, clear, jangly tone also makes them popular now 
with younger bands evoking a 1960s sound. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Adolph Rickenbacker</PERSON> was a Swiss immigrant who patented the first solid-body 
electric guitar in <DATE>1935</DATE>, the forerunner of today's electric guitars. The 
company was named to capitalize on the fame of World War I flying ace <PERSON>Eddie 
Rickenbacker</PERSON>, said to be a distant relative. 
</P>
<P>
By the time <PERSON>Adolph Rickenbacker</PERSON> was ready to retire, he was convinced the 
electric guitar was a fad. He sold the company in <DATE>1953</DATE> to <PERSON>F. C. Hall</PERSON>, a 
distributor of radio parts who moved it from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to be near his home in 
<LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In the early <DATE>1960s</DATE>, when an obscure young British rocker named <PERSON>John Lennon</PERSON> 
bought one, <PERSON>Rickenbacker</PERSON> was almost as well-known for its older Hawaiian 
guitars, which were played on the guitarist's lap. 
</P>
<P>
"When the Beatles came along, we went from selling thousands of guitars a year 
to tens of thousands," said <PERSON>John Hall</PERSON>, 38, son of <PERSON>F. C. Hall</PERSON> and now 
<ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION>'s president. 
</P>
<P>
"The Beatles," said <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, "put the company on the map." 
</P>
<P>
The guitars sold well even though they cost more than <MONEY>$300</MONEY>, by no means cheap 
then. 
</P>
<P>
But by the end of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, the first Rickenbacker boom was over. The Beatles 
had broken up, and most rock had assumed a bluesier, grittier sound. Guitar 
players emerged from anonymity, and every kid wanted the same kind of guitar 
his idol played, or at least one that looked like it. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Tried 'Dirtier Sound' 
</P>
<P>
The new stars of the guitar -- such as <PERSON>Eric Clapton</PERSON> -- usually played a <ORGANIZATION>Gibson 
Les Paul</ORGANIZATION>, which could get the rougher sound. 
</P>
<P>
With <ORGANIZATION>Fender</ORGANIZATION>'s Stratocaster -- played by another innovative musician, <LOCATION>Jimi 
Hendrix</LOCATION> -- Gibsons were guitars to have in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>. Their sales soared; 
Rickenbacker sales went off a cliff. 
</P>
<P>
The company tried to change the guitars, but it was never really able to. 
</P>
<P>
"We tried to put in a dirtier sound," said <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>, who bought the company from 
his father <DATE>four years ago</DATE>. "It didn't really work." 
</P>
<P>
By the mid-1970s, things weren't going too well for the rest of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitar 
industry, either. Sales of electric and "folk" guitars and other fretted 
instruments had jumped from 400,000 in <DATE>1960</DATE> -- before folk music and rock hit 
it big -- to 2.5 million in <DATE>1972</DATE>. But the manufacturers would never again sell 
that many. 
</P>
<P>
Why? Well, the baby boomers started to age, and there were fewer teen-agers to 
buy guitars. The late <DATE>1970s</DATE> were rather directionless musically; sales of 
records also suffered. By the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, video games and other distractions 
competed for kids' attention. By <DATE>1987</DATE>, the latest available figures, sales of 
new guitars had dipped to 1.2 million. 
</P>
<P>
Not only was the boom over, but first the Japanese and then the <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION> had 
ridden it right into the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitar market. 
</P>
<P>
Now guitars manufactured abroad dominate what was once an industry as unique to 
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as rock 'n' roll. Of the 1.2 million fretted instruments sold 
last year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, just 123,000 were made in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Even some of the bigger and more prestigious <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> companies have moved much of 
their manufacturing offshore to cut costs. Fender, for instance, now makes <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> 
of its guitars abroad, and once quit manufacturing in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
altogether. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Unknowledgeable Executives 
</P>
<P>
Some legendary names in the guitar business got hurt by imports, weak 
management and bad moves. Most had been bought by bigger companies dazzled by 
the glamour of the business. The cash that the new parent companies brought to 
the table sometimes helped soften the blow from imports. But, some critics say, 
the new owners often didn't know much about the business and hadn't the 
faintest idea how to compete with the imports. 
</P>
<P>
"Some of them had a succession of executives who didn't know how to tune a 
guitar," said <PERSON>George Gruhn</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> dealer in vintage guitars who has 
written extensively about the industry. "The Japanese often showed a better 
knowledge of the American market than the Americans did." 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1987</DATE>, for instance, all guitar manufacturers foreign and domestic shipped 
only <MONEY>$328 million</MONEY> worth of guitars at retail in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. By contrast, 
computer makers shipped <MONEY>$3.9 billion</MONEY> worth of home computers. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Similar Looks 
</P>
<P>
Rickenbacker is small even by the standards of this matchbox-sized industry. 
What saved the company in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> was its basses. As the guitars became 
unfashionable, the basses just as suddenly became hip. They were prized for 
their own bright, clear sound. It lifted the instrument out of the rhythm 
section in some groups -- such as the art rock combo Yes, whose bassist played 
a Rickenbacker -- and made the bass another solo instrument. 
</P>
<P>
When the guitars began to come back a few years ago, it wasn't terribly 
surprising that they still looked pretty much the same as they did 25 years 
ago, since a large part of their appeal is based on nostalgia. And they still 
make the same limited -- though distinct -- range of sounds. 
</P>
<P>
Nostalgia is not cheap: A new Rickenbacker starts at around <MONEY>$500</MONEY> and goes up to 
<MONEY>$2,700</MONEY>. That's without an amplifier or a case, both essential to the complete 
rock 'n' roller. And it's by no means the most expensive guitar these days. 
</P>
<P>
A <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> -- a rakish semi-custom guitar often painted in garish reds or blues 
-- starts at <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> and goes up to <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY>. It's the guitar of choice for heavy 
metal bands these days. 
</P>
<P>
Compared to the heavy metal types, a Rickenbacker is quieter and often older 
professional rockers who tend to play Rickenbackers, such as <PERSON>Tom Petty</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Jackson Browne</PERSON>. Some newer groups are playing them too, including REM and the 
Bangles. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
It's on <ORGANIZATION>MTV</ORGANIZATION>? It's Hot 
</P>
<P>
But the guitar market is fickle. <PERSON>Doc Pittillo</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> guitar repairman, 
said, "What's really hot is usually what the kids saw on <ORGANIZATION>MTV</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last week</DATE>. That's 
why I'm in business." 
</P>
<P>
What happens when the Rickenbacker fad wanes again, as some experts say it 
surely must? 
</P>
<P>
The younger <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> seems more willing to change with the times, to some extent. A 
guitar player, unlike his father, and a friend to some of his more renowned 
customers like <PERSON>McGuinn</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> has mostly tinkered with a few changes in the 
company's marketing strategy. 
</P>
<P>
Of new models, however, there are few, and critics say the company could get 
caught flat-footed when fashion and technology change again. The last new 
guitars came out four years ago and aren't selling particularly well compared 
to the more classic models because -- in a classic Catch 22 -- the new models 
"don't look like Rickenbackers," said <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>. The company is working on some new 
guitars it will unveil this year. 
</P>
<P>
In marketing its guitars, <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION> has finally deigned to use one of the 
oldest ploys in the guitar industry: Get a famous guitar player to endorse your 
product. But <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION>'s pitch is still largely nostalgic: Its deals are 
with older rockers such as the Byrds' <PERSON>McGuinn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pete Townshend</PERSON> of the Who. 
Rickenbacker is selling new models of the guitars <PERSON>McGuinn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Townshend</PERSON> played 
in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and making them only in limited editions so it can charge more. 
</P>
<P>
The company has also taken to sticking "Made in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>" labels on its guitars. 
That's mostly for foreign buyers. It doesn't really make much difference to the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mass market now that guitars from abroad are as good as most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitars. 
The international market is important to Rickenbacker: Almost half the 10,000 
guitars the company says it usually makes each year are sold abroad. 
</P>
<P>
There's also a plan to manufacture better and more expensive amplifiers, which 
the company has been making for an indifferent public for 60 years. 
</P>
<P>
Otherwise, <ORGANIZATION>Rickenbacker</ORGANIZATION> still sticks stubbornly to a nondescript section of 
