<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-10194</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CG4BOAE9FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920731
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 JUL 92 / Taxman set to drive a hard bargain: The Inland Revenue's
proposals for company cars
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GRIFFITHS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE Inland Revenue says some 1.2m drivers would benefit under its proposals
to restructure company car taxation - but the 700,000 losers would face
higher tax demands running to thousands of pounds a year in some cases.
The Revenue emphasised yesterday that the proposals were only the start of a
3 1/2 -month consultative process.
It can expect to be inundated, for the issue is important for manufacturers,
which make nearly a third of sales to business users, and for the
government, which receives Pounds 1.4bn annually in income tax from the
company car benefit scale charges, as well as for the nearly 2m company car
users.
The proposals aim to make fairer what is essentially a crude banding system,
unchanged in all essentials since it was introduced <DATE>16 years ago</DATE>. But they
are also intended to take account of criticisms, including some by the
<ORGANIZATION>Monopolies and Mergers Commission</ORGANIZATION>, that the combined price and engine
capacity thresholds of the company car taxation system distort the market,
obliging manufacturers to produce 'tax break specials' causing market
bunching and potentially putting specialist manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> at
a disadvantage.
There are about 1,200 car models available in the UK, but the present scale
system divides them into only five categories, using both price and engine
size. That means, to use the Revenue's own example, that the driver of a
sub-Pounds 9,000 <ORGANIZATION>Ford Fiesta</ORGANIZATION> diesel pays the same as the driver of a Pounds
19,000 <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> 520i if their business mileages are similar.
The Revenue says its proposals to base the tax charge mainly on price is
fairer and more easily understood than the present system.
The Revenue has resisted pressure to abandon banding in favour of basing the
scale charge on a percentage of the list price of the car. The Revenue
wished to avoid the need for individual tax calculations and PAYE recodings
each time a car is changed.
The Revenue is proposing 12 price bands, each higher band covering a
successively wider range of car prices. The advantage seen in such a
structure is that it would be sensitive in the Pounds 10,000-Pounds 19,500
region where company cars are concentrated.
Business car buyers will have to wait until the final scheme is set out in
next year's Budget for the exact detail. But to generate the same revenue
yield as the present system, the document indicates a scale representing two
ninths of a car's value for drivers covering 2,500-18,000 business miles a
year; one third for low-mileage (below 2,500 miles) users and only one ninth
for those covering more than 18,000 business miles a year. The document
proposes no changes to the business mileage bands.
The effects of the change are likely to be uneven. The Revenue says more
than half of the 750,000 company car drivers in the existing 1.4 litre to 2
litre engine band would gain modestly, most with a tax charge cut by about
10 per cent, and about 70,000 drivers of most basic cars by up to 25 per
cent.
But even the Revenue acknowledges that better-equipped saloons in the Pounds
12,500-Pounds 16,000 range would attract increases of more than 10 per cent,
affecting an estimated 360,000 drivers. The typical middle-ranking
executive, driving a high-specification car of just under 2 litres and just
under the present Pounds 19,250 threshold, would be among those worst
affected, facing a typical increase in tax of about 40 per cent.
Cars now costing between Pounds 19,250 and Pounds 29,000 would be split into
two bands. The 60,000 cars in the lower half of the current band would have
the tax charge cut by 15 per cent on average; those costing more than Pounds
24,500 - involving about 20,000 cars - would be modest losers.
For the most expensive cars, priced now at more than Pounds 29,000, those at
the bottom of the range - up to Pounds 39,000 - would have a tax charge
reduced by more than 30 per cent, a benefit to companies such as <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>.
Above Pounds 39,000, the tax charge would rise, by 35 per cent for cars
costing between Pounds 50,000 and Pounds 60,000.
<PERSON>Mr Brian Friedman</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Stoy Benefit Consulting</ORGANIZATION>, said the
system 'will inevitably hit senior executives driving the most expensive
cars'. He suggested that, since many of these drivers were user-choosers,
'the logical result will be a general downsizing of company cars'.
The scheme also aims to minimise incentives to drive thirsty cars. And while
there are no specific provisions to encourage economical diesel cars, they
will be encouraged indirectly by the proposals.
Diesel cars need larger engines than petrol equivalents in order to have
acceptable power and are therefore often put into a higher band under the
present scale structure. A price-only band would end such discrimination, as
well as tending in general to favour cheaper - and generally more
fuel-efficient - cars.
There is a strong administrative argument for the Revenue's proposals:
whereas the whole business car sector usually waits on tenterhooks each
Budget to see what changes in scale charges are announced, a multi-band
price system would be broadly self-correcting and require no Budgetary
attention. Cars would simply drift up through the price bands, depending on
inflation.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-10347</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CG4BOAA0FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920731
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  31 JUL 92 / Taxman set to drive a hard bargain: The Inland Revenue's
proposals for company cars
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GRIFFITHS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE Inland Revenue says some 1.2m drivers would benefit under its proposals
to restructure company car taxation - but the 700,000 losers would face
higher tax demands running to thousands of pounds a year in some cases.
The Revenue emphasised yesterday that the proposals were only the start of a
3 1/2 -month consultative process.
It can expect to be inundated, for the issue is important for manufacturers,
which make nearly a third of sales to business users, and for the
government, which receives Pounds 1.4bn annually in income tax from the
company car benefit scale charges, as well as for the nearly 2m company car
users.
The proposals aim to make fairer what is essentially a crude banding system,
unchanged in all essentials since it was introduced <DATE>16 years ago</DATE>. But they
are also intended to take account of criticisms, including some by the
<ORGANIZATION>Monopolies and Mergers Commission</ORGANIZATION>, that the combined price and engine
capacity thresholds of the company car taxation system distort the market,
obliging manufacturers to produce 'tax break specials' causing market
bunching and potentially disadvantaging specialist manufacturers such as
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>.
There are about 1,200 car models available in the UK, but the present scale
system divides them into only five categories, using both price and engine
size. That means, to use the Revenue's own example, that the driver of a
sub-Pounds 9,000 <ORGANIZATION>Ford Fiesta</ORGANIZATION> diesel pays the same as the driver of a Pounds
19,000 <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> 520i if their business mileages are similar.
The Revenue says its proposals to base the tax charge mainly on price is
fairer and more easily understood than the present system.
The Revenue has resisted pressure to abandon banding altogether, in favour
of basing the scale charge on a percentage of the list price of the car. The
Revenue wished to avoid the need for individual tax calculations and PAYE
recodings each time a car is changed.
The Revenue is proposing 12 price bands, each higher band covering a
successively wider range of car prices. The perceived advantage of such a
structure is that it would be sensitive in the Pounds 10,000-Pounds 19,500
region, where company cars are concentrated.
Business car buyers will have to wait until the final scheme is set out in
next year's Budget for the exact detail. But to generate the same revenue
yield as the present system, the document indicates a scale representing two
ninths of a car's value for drivers covering 2,500-18,000 business miles a
year; one third for low-mileage (below 2,500 miles) users and only one ninth
for those covering more than 18,000 business miles a year. The document
proposes no changes to the business mileage bands.
The effects of the change are likely to be uneven. The Revenue says more
than half of the 750,000 company car drivers in the existing 1.4-2-litre
engine band would gain modestly, most with a tax charge reduced by about 10
per cent, and about 70,000 drivers of most basic cars by up to 25 per cent.
But even the Revenue acknowledges that better-equipped saloons in the Pounds
12,500-Pounds 16,000 range would attract increases of more than 10 per cent,
affecting an estimated 360,000 drivers. The typical middle-ranking
executive, driving a high-specification car of just under 2 litres and just
under the present Pounds 19,250 threshold, would be among those worst
affected, facing a typical increase in tax of about 40 per cent.
Cars currently costing between Pounds 19,250 and Pounds 29,000 would be
split into two bands. The 60,000 cars in the lower half of the current band
would have the tax charge cut by 15 per cent on average; those costing more
than Pounds 24,500 - involving about 20,000 cars - would be modest losers.
For the most expensive cars, priced now at more than Pounds 29,000, those at
the bottom of the range - up to Pounds 39,000 - would have a tax charge
reduced by more than 30 per cent, a benefit to companies such as <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>.
Above Pounds 39,000, the tax charge would rise, by 35 per cent for cars
costing between Pounds 50,000 and Pounds 60,000.
<PERSON>Mr Brian Friedman</PERSON>, managing director of <ORGANIZATION>Stoy Benefit Consulting</ORGANIZATION>, said the
system 'will inevitably hit senior executives driving the most expensive
cars'. He suggested that, since many of these drivers were user-choosers,
'the logical result will be a general downsizing of company cars'.
The scheme also aims to minimise incentives to drive thirsty cars. And while
there are no specific provisions to encourage economical diesel cars, they
will be encouraged indirectly by the proposals.
Diesel cars need larger engines than petrol equivalents in order to have
acceptable power and are therefore often put into a higher band under the
present scale structure. A price-only band would end such discrimination, as
well as tending in general to favour cheaper - and generally more
fuel-efficient - cars.
There is a strong administrative argument for the Revenue's proposals:
whereas the whole business car sector usually waits on tenterhooks each
Budget to see what changes in scale charges are announced, a multi-band
price system would be broadly self-correcting and require no Budgetary
attention. Cars would simply drift up through the price bands, depending on
inflation.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891020-0259 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-89 0057EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Jaguar-GM     10-20 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Jaguar-GM,0471</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jaguar Hopes To Make Less Expensive Car in GM Deal</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar PLC</ORGANIZATION>, a British luxury automaker, is looking
to produce a less expensive model appealing to business executives
if plans for cooperation with <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> go through, a
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> executive said.
   ``An association with a large company like <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> would enable us to
look at the possibility of introducing a smaller <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>, an area in
which as a small independent company we cannot consider as the
investment and components-cost would be too high,'' <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>David
Boole</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``We want to look at other market opportunities and one of those
is a downsized model in the <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> range,'' <ORGANIZATION>Boole</ORGANIZATION> said
in a telephone interview from his home near the <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> plant at
<ORGANIZATION>Coventry</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>English Midlands</LOCATION>.
   ``Because we are small we are somewhat constrained in what we
can do,'' <ORGANIZATION>Boole</ORGANIZATION> added.
   <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> cars are known for their sleek lines and high-quality
interior trim. The highest-priced model costs around <MONEY>$64,000</MONEY>.
   Sir <PERSON>John Egan</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at the opening
of the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Motorfair he hoped within one month to present his
stockholders with a plan outlining cooperation with <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>.
   The plan would thwart a merger bid by <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> domestic
rival, which <DATE>this week</DATE> disclosed it has built a stake of <PERCENT>10.4
percent</PERCENT> in <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>. Egan is set against a merger that would
undermine his rule over one of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s most famous companies.
   He told reporters that negotiations with <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>, the world's biggest
automaker, could lead to <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> receiving a huge cash injection and
guarantee his company's independence.
   British auto industry reporters said <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> would probably
propose to its stockholders that <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> sell <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> a <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> stake
in the company in return for about <MONEY>$237 million</MONEY> cash.
   <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> currently produces 50,000 cars a year and <PERSON>Egan</PERSON> said the
<ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> deal would enable <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> to invest immediately in new models and
cut spending on components by as much as <MONEY>$950 million</MONEY> a year.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> has been a supplier for decades of gear boxes to <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>,''
said <ORGANIZATION>Boole</ORGANIZATION>. ``The most important thing for us in an association
with <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> would be access to low-cost components and to <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s advanced
research. That would mean developing our current range of cars and
making them more cost effective.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Boole</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> would concentrate on ``critical items'' in its
cars like body style, engines and the interior trim _ ``what the
customer sees and touches.''
   He said the company would look to <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> for the ``not-so-critical,
out-of-sight background technology'' of wiring harness, axles,
backup systems and air bags _ ``the areas in which a small company
like ours finds it isn't cost effective to spend time and money.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-1312</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CFWA9AE1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920623
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 JUN 92 / Fastest Jaguar road car sets off
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GRIFFITHS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
DELIVERIES are beginning this week of the fastest and, at Pounds 350,000
each, the most expensive roadgoing <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> cars ever built.
However, growing environmentalist sentiment and the difficulties some
customers apparently face in paying for their cars make it almost certain
that the 500-plus horsepower 212mph XJ220 is likely to be the first and last
of its type to be offered under the <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> badge.
'We all recognise that a long-term shift is taking place in what will appeal
to buyers. No one can afford to ignore the environmental issues,' according
to <PERSON>Mr Bill Donnelly</PERSON>, sales and marketing director of <ORGANIZATION>JaguarSport</ORGANIZATION>, which is
based at <ORGANIZATION>Bloxham</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oxfordshire</LOCATION>, where the XJ220 is being built.
JaguarSport, which has engineered and is producing the cars, is a 50-50
joint-venture company set up in <DATE>1988</DATE> between <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> - itself now owned by
<ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> - and <PERSON>Mr Tom Walkinshaw</PERSON>'s racing organisation to develop
high-performance versions of <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>'s mainstream models as well as to
undertake special projects.
The XJ220, said <PERSON>Mr Donnelly</PERSON>, 'will probably turn out to be the ultimate
roadgoing <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>. We'll take a different slant in the future; something
smaller and lighter, with the emphasis very much on weight-saving.'
The XJ220 plant is to be taken over by another <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Aston
Martin</ORGANIZATION>, to make a new <ORGANIZATION>Aston Martin</ORGANIZATION> model - expected to be priced below
Pounds 100,000 - at a rate of 625 a year as soon as XJ220 production ends in
early <DATE>1994</DATE>.
The car's debut could hardly be worse timed, coming when the UK and other
once buoyant markets for expensive cars are still struggling to emerge from
the recession, and when cars in general are being increasingly pilloried
over environmental issues such as exhaust emissions, energy conservation,
congestion and pedestrian safety. The XJ220 may meet all emissions standards
envisaged until at least <DATE>1994</DATE>, but its speed and inevitably high - but so
far undisclosed - fuel consumption make it a likely focus for anti-car
campaigners.
JaguarSport is not alone. Several other 200mph-plus 'supercars' conceived on
their creators' computer screens in the boom period of the late <DATE>1980s</DATE> have
also been announced in the past few weeks. They include the Pounds 530,000
McLaren F1, a car based on the Surrey racing group's grand prix technology;
and the <ORGANIZATION>Yamaha</ORGANIZATION> OX99-11, a 200mph single-seater to be produced for the
Japanese vehicle manufacturer at its <ORGANIZATION>Ypsilon Technology</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary at <PERSON>Milton
Keynes</PERSON>.
According to <ORGANIZATION>JaguarSport</ORGANIZATION>, 1,500 would-be owners applied to buy the cars,
backing their orders with a Pounds 50,000, non-returnable deposit when the
project was first announced in the <DATE>autumn of 1989</DATE>. But with the market for
very expensive cars having suffered a spectacular collapse, there is growing
speculation within the investment-car market about whether 'supercar' sales
confidence may be misplaced.
According to <PERSON>Mr Robert Brooks</PERSON>, principal of the international auction house
which has sold many of the world's most valuable cars, the present
investment value of virtually all 'supercars' is well below their new
purchase price. 'The investment money is simply not there,' he says. 'How
many cars like this can the market absorb, particularly at a time when the
speculative investment buyer has gone out of the market?'
Under the XJ220's order terms, options are tradable. Originally seen as
offering the potential for a premium, the recession has meant some option
sales have been made simply to recoup the Pounds 50,000 and escape payment
of a second Pounds 50,000 instalment required before a car's construction
starts.
JaguarSport has yet to try and test the veracity of another speculation
circulating among collectors of cars: that a few option owners looking to
escape from purchase but finding difficulty in selling their options have
'sold' them to asset-less shell companies which it would be pointless for
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> to pursue for payment. If that is happening, said <PERSON>Mr Donnelly</PERSON>, the
instalment payment system means that JaguarSport will get warning at least
six months before construction of a particular car starts.
'If there are problems, it simply won't get built - at least not until
another firm buyer is found,' he added.
Technology, Page 12
German car industry, Page 18
<ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> US sales, Page 21
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 10
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT931-7874</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DBVBWAEKFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930222
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 FEB 93 / Survey of Vehicle Fleet Management (2): Wait for the tax
changes - Drivers on business face a new regime
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GRIFFITHS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN his budget speech next month <PERSON>Mr Norman Lamont</PERSON>, the chancellor, is
expected to indicate the extent to which the Inland Revenue's proposals for
the reform of company car taxation, first outlined last <DATE>summer</DATE>, have been
amended by criticism invited from the motor industry and other interested
parties.
The legislation to implement the revised tax regime will then be introduced
in this year's Finance Act. But such are the complexities of change - to
PAYE systems, car makers' production and marketing strategies, for example -
that there will almost certainly be no attempt to introduce the changes
before the start of the 1994-95 tax year. If the switch- over seems likely
to cause more complications than expected, it could even be postponed until
later.
Despite, or perhaps because of, the wide range of responses to and
criticisms of the Revenue's draft, there appear few signs that there will be
significant departures from the scheme as originally proposed.
The Revenue has declared four principal aims in restructuring the way
personal taxation of the company car benefit is assessed: greater fairness,
reduced distortion of the new car market caused by manufacturers producing
'tax break specials' within the current price and engine capacity 'banding'
system, to promote fuel efficiency and to simplify the administration of
company car taxation.
Central to the Revenue's proposed new regime are a dozen new bands, based
wholly on price and stretching up to Pounds 60,000. The current regime,
which the Revenue itself has described as outdated and crude, has only two
price thresholds, of Pounds 19,250 and Pounds 29,000, above which the
assessed tax benefit to the user rises sharply.
These, however, currently are assessed in combination with three engine
capacity bands, of under 1.4 litres, 1.4-2 litres and over <MONEY>2 litres</MONEY>. One of
the long-standing criticism of these capacity bands is that they do not
differentiate between petrol and much less powerful but more economical
diesel engines, which require more cubic capacity for a given level of
performance.
The proposals favour using the manufacturer's list price as the basis for
the bandings, but leave open actual cost to purchasers after discounts, and
estimates of original market value for a particular category of car, as
alternatives.
The Revenue has done its own calculations about the expected effect on some
2m company car drivers and asserts that 1.2m drivers would benefit from the
revised structure, with their tax bills falling by up to 25 per cent.
However, it also acknowledges that there would be 700,000 losers. About
500,000 of these, with cars currently in the Pounds 13,000-Pounds 15,000
bracket, would be less than 10 per cent worse off. But about 200,000 drivers
of high specification cars with prices just under the current two 'break'
points face a 40 per cent tax rise.
Launching the proposed scheme, <PERSON>Mr Stephen Dorrell</PERSON>, financial secretary to
the <ORGANIZATION>Treasury</ORGANIZATION>, said that it was designed to end the unfair situation whereby,
for example, the presumably low-paid driver of a basic 1.8 litre Ford Fiesta
diesel, using mainly for business, paid the same tax as the driver of a
Mercedes 190 for equivalent business mileages.
What the new regime apparently does not seek to do is increase the total tax
burden by more than the current scheme would impose in the normal course of
annual adjustments.
In a foreword to the proposals, <PERSON>Mr Lamont</PERSON> signalled that the swingeing
annual increases in scale charges that have quadrupled tax payable by
company car users in less than a decade are at an end: 'The government
recognises that company cars are an important feature of modern business
Exchequer.'
While not spelling it out precisely, <PERSON>Mr Lamont</PERSON> indicated that, in the
government's view, company cars are now just about tax neutral - neither
encouraging nor discouraging their provision. Currently, the Exchequer's
receipts from the tax are around Pounds 1.4bn.
The proposed dozen price bands are: under Pounds 5,000, Pounds 5,000-Pounds
6,499, Pounds 6,500-Pounds 7,999, Pounds 8,000-Pounds 9,999, Pounds
10,000-Pounds 12,499, Pounds 12,500-Pounds 15,499, Pounds 15,500-Pounds
19,499, Pounds 19,500-Pounds 24,499, Pounds 24,500-Pounds 30,999, Pounds
31,000-Pounds 38,999, Pounds 39,000-Pounds 49,999, Pounds 50,000-Pounds
62,500, and over Pounds 62,500. The advantage seen in this successively
wider banding is that it would be particularly sensitive in the Pounds
10,000-Pounds 19,500 region where company cars are concentrated.
To generate the same revenue yield as the present system, the proposals
suggest a scale representing two-ninths of a car's value for drivers
covering 2,500-18,000 business miles a year, one third for low-mileage
(below 2,500 miles) users and only one-ninth for those covering more than
18,000 business miles a year. The document proposes no changes to the
business mileage bands, despite widespread criticism that essential car
users are heavily penalised if they do not cover more than 18,000 business
miles.
Cars now costing between Pounds 19,250 and Pounds 29,000 would be split into
two bands. The 60,000 cars in the lower half of the current band would have
the tax charge cut by 15 per cent on average. In the case of cars costing
more than Pounds 24,500 - affecting about 20,000 - the drivers would be
modest losers.
For the most expensive cars, priced now at more than Pounds 29,000, those at
the bottom of the range - up to Pounds 39,000 - would have a tax charge
reduced by more than 30 per cent. This would benefit companies such as
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>.
Above Pounds 39,000, the tax charge would rise by 35 per cent for cars
costing between Pounds 50,000 and Pounds 60,000.
By using the price mechanism more strongly, the scheme also aims to
encourage the use of more economical cars. In that context, the regime, if
adopted largely unchanged, should give a significant boost to diesel cars.
The administrative argument in favour of the Revenue's proposals is widely
seen as a strong one. Whereas, at budget time each year, car makers and
fleet users alike have traditionally waited on tenterhooks for the revised
scale charges in each Budget, to assess the likely impact on both car users
and car sales, the Revenue's proposed new system would be broadly
self-correcting. Each year, cars could be expected to drift up through the
price bands, depending on prevailing rates of inflation.
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
                  CAR BENEFIT SCALE CHARGES 1992-93
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
    Original                                      High business
     market                        Engine       mileage (18,000
     value                      size (cc)        miles or  more)
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
                        Cars under four years old
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Up to Pounds 19,250                0-1400         Pounds 1,070
Up to Pounds 19,250             1401-2000         Pounds 1,385
Up to Pounds 19,250                 <DATE>2001</DATE>+         Pounds 2,220
Pounds 19,251 to Pounds 29,000      2,875         Pounds 5,750
Over Pounds  29,000                   All         Pounds 4,650
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
                        Cars over four years old
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Up to Pounds 19,250                0-1400         Pounds   730
Up to Pounds 19,250             1401-2000         Pounds   940
Up to Pounds 19,250                 <DATE>2001</DATE>+         Pounds 1,490
Pounds 19,251 to Pounds 29,000        All         Pounds 1,935
Over Pounds 29,000                    All         Pounds 3,085
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
                                      Average business   Low business
                                       mileage (2,501    mileage (2,500
                                      to 17,999 miles)   miles or less)
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  2,140     Pounds  3,210
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  2,770     Pounds  4,155
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  4,440     Pounds  6,660
Pounds 19,251 to Pounds 29,000         Pounds  5,750     Pounds  8,625
Over Pounds  29,000                    Pounds  9,300     Pounds 13,950
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
                        Cars over four years old
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  1,460     Pounds 2,190
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  1,880     Pounds 2,820
Up to Pounds 19,250                    Pounds  2,980     Pounds 4,470
Pounds 19,251 to Pounds 29,000         Pounds  3,870     Pounds 5,805
Over Pounds 29,000                     Pounds  6,170     Pounds 9,255
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
Source: Inland Revenue
 -----------------------------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5511 New and Used Car Dealers.
    P99   Nonclassifiable Establishments.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>GOVT  Taxes.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870226-0039 </DOCNO>
<HL> Most Midsized Cars
Incur Over $1,000
Of Damage in Test
---
By Laurie McGinley
<DD> 02/26/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GM F HMC TOYOY
AUTOS, AUTO PARTS (AUT) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   All but two of 22 midsized cars put through four low-speed test crashes designed to gauge bumper strength sustained damages exceeding <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>, a highway group backed by the insurance industry said. 

   The cars were crashed four times at five miles per hour. 
"As a group," said <PERSON>Brian O'Neill</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Insurance Institute for Highway Safety</ORGANIZATION>, the Washington-based group that tested the cars, "they did very poorly. 
There should be only minimum damage in such tests." 

   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s new <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Corsica</ORGANIZATION> incurred the least amount of damage -- <MONEY>$419</MONEY> -- in the four crashes, the institute said. 
The next best competitor, the <ORGANIZATION>Toyota Camry</ORGANIZATION>, sustained damages totaling <MONEY>$866</MONEY>, while the <ORGANIZATION>Honda Accord DX</ORGANIZATION>, which did the worst, had <MONEY>$2,030</MONEY> in damages. 

   Many of the more expensive cars tested had the more costly damages. 
All of the six worst performers had a manufacturer's suggested base price exceeding <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>. 
The suggested base price for the <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> Accord, for example, is <MONEY>$10,625</MONEY>, while the <LOCATION>Pontiac</LOCATION> 6000, which sustained a total of <MONEY>$2,004</MONEY> in damages in the tests, costs <MONEY>$10,499</MONEY>. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Ford Taurus GL</ORGANIZATION>, which has a manufacturer's recommended price of <MONEY>$11,622</MONEY>, sustained damages totaling <MONEY>$1,945</MONEY>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Mercury Sable GS</ORGANIZATION>, which has a <MONEY>$12,340</MONEY> price tag, had damages of <MONEY>$1,571</MONEY>. 

   Priced at <MONEY>$8,995</MONEY>, the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Corsica</ORGANIZATION> was one of the least expensive cars tested. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Toyota Camry</ORGANIZATION> is priced at <MONEY>$10,998</MONEY>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Buick Skylark</ORGANIZATION>, which had damages of <MONEY>$1,024</MONEY>, and carries a suggested base price of <MONEY>$9,915</MONEY>, had the third-lowest damage total. 
Next was the Oldsmobile Firenza, which sustained damages of <MONEY>$1,125</MONEY>, and has an <MONEY>$8,449</MONEY> base price. 

   The four tests were a frontal crash into a barrier, a rear crash into a barrier, a frontal crash into a barrier at an angle and a rear crash into a pole. 
All the cars tested were <DATE>1987</DATE> models, except for the <LOCATION>Corsica</LOCATION>, which was a <DATE>1988</DATE> model. 

   <PERSON>Mr. O'Neill</PERSON> said the extensive damage that resulted from the tests underscores the need for tougher federal bumper standards. 
In <DATE>1982</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Highway Traffic Safety Administration</ORGANIZATION> eased a requirement that cars be able to withstand damage to the vehicle and suffer only minimal damage to the bumper at 5 mph. 
Its action lowered the standard to 2.5 mph. 

   Officials at the safety agency say the weaker rule, on balance, benefits consumers. 
They argue that bumpers required by the 5 mph standard add to the car price, are more expensive to replace and increase fuel costs because they are heavier than less damage-resistant bumpers. 

   In <LOCATION>Dearborn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Robert H. Munson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s director of automotive safety, said "the best evidence" of the strength of the bumpers on the Taurus and <ORGANIZATION>Sable</ORGANIZATION> and of the cars' overall damage resistance is "the fact that the two largest auto insurance companies . . . and most other insurance companies offer significant discounts for collision and comprehensive coverage on <DATE>1987</DATE> Taurus and Sable models." 

   In a prepared statement, he added that "actual accident statistics compiled by the <ORGANIZATION>Highway Loss Data Institute</ORGANIZATION>, which is funded by the <ORGANIZATION>Insurance Institute for Highway Safety</ORGANIZATION>, show that loss payments for Taurus and Sable are <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>, respectively, below the average loss payments for all 1986-model passenger cars." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Munson</PERSON> said the Taurus and Sable "five-miles-an-hour bumpers" performed "as expected" in the <ORGANIZATION>Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s tests, noting that they "incurred no damage during the five-miles-an-hour perpendicular barrier-crash portions of the test." 
He added, "The <ORGANIZATION>IIHS</ORGANIZATION> bumper test results are distorted, however, by the five-miles-an-hour '<ORGANIZATION>McDonald's</ORGANIZATION> pole test,' which simulates a kind of accident that is relatively rare in the real world." 

   A <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> spokesman in <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> said the No. 1 auto maker was "pleased with the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Corsica</ORGANIZATION>'s performance" and noted that "four of the top five performers" in the test were <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> products. 
He declined to comment on the performance of the <ORGANIZATION>Century</ORGANIZATION> and <DATE>6000</DATE>. 

   In <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> spokesman declined to comment. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881007-0125 </DOCNO>
<HL> Marketing and Media: Mercedes U.S. Unit Strives to Weather Expected Two-Year Flat Sales Period </HL>
<AUTHOR> Bradley A. Stertz (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<DATELINE> GROSSE POINTE, Mich.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz of North America Inc.</ORGANIZATION> is testing new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> marketing programs to get it through a stagnant sales period that is expected to last at least two more years. 

   One program the West German auto maker is testing is aimed at buyers who can't afford the <MONEY>$30,980</MONEY> base price of the least expensive 1989-model <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>. 
Under a pilot program in 21 cities, <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes</ORGANIZATION> is giving consumers an incentive to buy used models by offering a comprehensive, "bumper-to-bumper," factory warranty on used cars with less than 100,000 miles. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> unit of <ORGANIZATION>Daimler-Benz AG</ORGANIZATION> is also trying to build up its leasing operations and is considering more extensive advertising programs. 
And it adopted only modest price increases on its most popular <DATE>1989</DATE> models. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION> officials in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> said that such steps are necessary because they don't expect demand for luxury cars to grow significantly before the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 
They said that over the <DATE>last two years</DATE>, sales of all cars costing more than <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> have leveled off to about 140,000 a year. 
About <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the cars Mercedes sells in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fall in that price range and it controls about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of that market. 

   <PERSON>Erich Krampe</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, said he expects to sell about 80,000 cars in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> by yearend, and about the same number in <DATE>1989</DATE>. 

   "We are confident this particular segment of the market provides prospects for future growth," <PERSON>Mr. Krampe</PERSON> said at the Mercedes 1989-model preview before reporters here. 
"But coming close to our boom year in <DATE>1986</DATE> {when Mercedes sold 99,314 cars in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>} is not in our vision for the next five years," he said, since <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes</ORGANIZATION> won't cut prices to sell more cars. 

   Mercedes has tried to protect its dealers' profits by tightening inventories in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to less than a 40 days supply. 
Mercedes had enough cars in dealer inventories a year ago to handle sales for 70 days, which caused price wars in some cities. 
Mercedes officials also said bigger inventories greatly increase costs for dealers, who must finance the expensive, unsold cars. 

   Base prices of its <DATE>1989</DATE> models have been increased an average <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT>, <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes</ORGANIZATION> said. 
It lowered the price on one of its least expensive cars, the 190E sedan, by <MONEY>$1,910</MONEY> or <PERCENT>5.7%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$31,590</MONEY>. 
It lowered that price because it eliminated a similar 190 model that came with a less powerful engine. 
However, <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1989</DATE> won't have any cars costing less than <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>. 
The base price of its cheapest model, the 190D diesel sedan, increased <MONEY>$1,020</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$30,980</MONEY>. 

   The company also raised prices on the 300 series cars, the most popular, by <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT>. 
The price of the 300E sedan, for example, went up <MONEY>$450</MONEY> to <MONEY>$44,850</MONEY>. 
The biggest price increases came on its top-of-the-line models. 
The most expensive Mercedes, the 560 <ORGANIZATION>SEC</ORGANIZATION> coupe, went up <MONEY>$2,775</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>3.6%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$79,840</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880112-0017 </DOCNO>
<HL> Honda Raises Prices For Its Cars, Citing Slide in U.S. Dollar </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> HMC </CO>
<IN> AUT MON </IN>
<DATELINE> GARDENA, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Honda Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> said it raised base prices on its <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> division cars an average of <PERCENT>2.2%</PERCENT> and its Acura division cars an average of <PERCENT>2.8%</PERCENT> to compensate for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar's slide against the Japanese yen. 

   The price boosts took effect yesterday upon their announcement by <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales arm, <ORGANIZATION>American Honda Motor Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
They marked the ninth time <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> has raised its prices since the yen began its climb against the dollar in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
Prices of <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> division cars have gone up an average of <PERCENT>29.2%</PERCENT> in that time, while Acura prices have increased an average of <PERCENT>18.4%</PERCENT> since their <DATE>May 1986</DATE> introduction in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 

   The price of <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s least expensive car, the Honda Civic hatchback, increased <MONEY>$100</MONEY> to <MONEY>$6,195</MONEY>, a rise of <PERCENT>1.6%</PERCENT>. 
The base price of the least expensive sporty CRX model went up <MONEY>$250</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$8,545</MONEY>. 
The base price for the Accord, <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s bestselling model, jumped <MONEY>$390</MONEY> a car, or <PERCENT>3.7%</PERCENT>, to <MONEY>$10,925</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s most expensive car, the Prelude, will increase in price <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$145</MONEY>, to <MONEY>$13,640</MONEY> for a base model. 

   Prices on the upscale <ORGANIZATION>Acura</ORGANIZATION> division's base model cars jumped even higher than the <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> division's prices. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Acura Integra</ORGANIZATION> jumped <PERCENT>3.5%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$370</MONEY>, to <MONEY>$10,915</MONEY>. 
The luxury Legend sedan increased in price <PERCENT>2.5%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$525</MONEY>, to <MONEY>$23,675</MONEY>. 
And the Legend coupe rose <PERCENT>2.5%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$579</MONEY>, to <MONEY>$23,675</MONEY>. 

   At a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> news conference, <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION>'s president, <PERSON>Tadashi Kume</PERSON>, said he thought <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> wouldn't lose market share in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> because of the price boosts. 
Honda accounted for <PERCENT>7.2%</PERCENT> of the cars sold in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, up from <PERCENT>6.1%</PERCENT> a year earlier. 

   Separately, <PERSON>Mr. Kume</PERSON> said the Japanese company's home-market auto sales will grow in <DATE>1988</DATE>, while exports will be little changed. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Kume</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Honda</ORGANIZATION> aims to sell 1,310,000 of its Japanese-built passenger cars, including so-called minicars, in <DATE>1988</DATE>, up <PERCENT>5.8%</PERCENT> from last year. 
Of the total, 620, 000 units are expected to be sold in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>13.3%</PERCENT>. 
The company expects exports to total 690,000 units, almost unchanged from 690,946 units in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-18233</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJDDVAHZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941004
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 OCT 94 / Survey of World Car Industry (27): Design a high priority in
the luxury market - Stuart Marshall assesses the new models on offer
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STUART MARSHALL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Will a radical change in construction materials and techniques put <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> up
among the front runners in the luxury car stakes in <DATE>1995</DATE>? Its new A8 quattro
saloon's light alloy space frame and panels save weight and fuel; Tiptronic
transmission gives drivers the benefits of automatic or manual shifting; and
four-wheel drive allows them to make full use of its 4.0-litre, multi-valve
V8s 300 horsepower on wet or dry surfaces.
But by itself, this technology may not be enough to ensure sales success.
When it comes to styling and mechanical layout, status conscious luxury car
drivers are remarkably conservative. Thus the new <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> 7-Series has classic
rear-wheel drive and lines remarkably like those of its predecessor, while
the new <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> XJ saloon, roomier inside yet slimmer looking, has even
reverted to the twin round headlamps of an earlier model.
In business motoring's middle reaches, <ORGANIZATION>General Motors</ORGANIZATION> has stayed faithful to
rear-wheel drive for its <ORGANIZATION>Opel</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Vauxhall</ORGANIZATION> in the UK) <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION>, as has <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> with
its heavily revamped Scorpio.
Drivers of these classes of car know what they want - smoothness and
silence, ample power and air conditioning, automatic transmission and a
built-in telephone, airbags and anti-lock brakes.
Next year the list will extend to satellite navigation, to be offered in
<ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>'s most prestigious S-Class, <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s 7-Series and, probably the
successor to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s trend-setting luxury car, the Lexus LS400.
In the medium/large class most of the past year's newcomers - the <ORGANIZATION>Renault
Laguna</ORGANIZATION> is typical - have conformed to a pattern; front-wheel drive
(occasionally with an all-wheel drive option), space-saving
transversely-mounted engines, standard airbags and anti-lock brakes and the
easy availability of air-conditioning and automatic transmission.
Choice of a diesel as an alternative to a petrol engine has become
essential. Only two European business car providers of any consequence -
<ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> - do not have diesels in their product ranges. Both are
likely to add diesels, with engines bought-in rather than developed in-
house, within the next two or three years.
Great strides are being made in car diesel technology. For now, <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s
in-line turbocharged and intercooled six-cylinder units have no peers for
urgent and near silent power delivery.
<ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION>, with the world's first four valves-per-cylinder passenger car
diesels, and <ORGANIZATION>PSA Group</ORGANIZATION>'s latest 2.5-litre diesels with twin balancer shafts,
have brought diesel smoothness close to petrol engine standards while
benefiting from higher torque at low revolutions and cleaner exhaust
emissions.
<ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s just introduced four-cylinder diesel is raising the stakes in the
market for less expensive, fuel efficient business cars. For fuel economy
combined with acceptable refinement, VW-Audi's direct-injection diesels, as
fitted in <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> 80 and 100 and <ORGANIZATION>VW</ORGANIZATION> Golf and Passat models, lead the pack.
Rover's direct-injection engined 600 diesel saloon will soon rival their
standards.
Sales of on-off road 4x4s have maintained their impetus. The vehicles have
become civilised, if rather thirsty, on-road car substitutes and rarely
venture on to the rough terrain which they were designed to tackle.
Land Rover's latest Range Rover with height-adjustable air suspension is put
forward as an alternative to conventional luxury cars in the <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION> class.
Although its two beam axles cannot reasonably be expected to equal the ride
comfort of a sophisticated all-independent system, it is a most urbane
performer on the road and remains capable off it.
One of the attractions of on-off road vehicles such as Range Rover is their
so-called command driving position. It gives users a feeling of superiority
and allows them to see over the tops of normal cars ahead.
Similar benefits are offered by multi-purpose vehicles (MPVs) which lack the
high-slung 4x4s largely unused off-road capability.
Their market penetration is forecast to grow substantially in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> as new
models such as the joint Portugese-produced Ford-VW project come on stream.
Whether this will be at the expense of on-off road 4x4s or conventional
estate cars remains to be seen.
In the <DATE>past eight years</DATE>, sales of MPVs such as the <ORGANIZATION>Renault Espace</ORGANIZATION> (still
market leader in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>) have risen by an average 80 per cent per annum.
By the <DATE>end of the century</DATE> it is expected that 700,000 MPVs will be sold in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> each year.
This forecast makes the introduction of a range of MPVs built by <ORGANIZATION>PSA</ORGANIZATION> but
which will be sold badged as Citroens, Peugeots, Fiats and Lancias among the
most significant motoring events of <DATE>1994</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>XAZ  World.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P3711 Motor Vehicles and Car Bodies.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page X
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-32</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EF3D2AGVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940630
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  30 JUN 94 / Survey of Executive Cars (4): The Revenue gnashes its teeth
/ An examination of UK suppliers' changing price strategies
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN GRIFFITHS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Car makers were uneasy two years ago when the Inland Revenue unveiled its
proposals for a new company car tax regime, based on a simple percentage of
cars' list prices.
In previous years considerable effort had gone into producing 'tax break
specials' under the old tax regime, which heavily favoured high-earning
executives compared with lower-paid essential users of company cars.
The old system, based on price and engine capacity bands, meant that an
executive driving a highly-specified 'perk' car of fractionally under 2
litres and Pounds 19,250 paid only the same personal tax on his company car
as an essential user of a utilitarian vehicle of just over 1.4 litres,
provided their marginal tax rates were the same.
Under the new system, effective from <DATE>April 6</DATE>, the same executive would have
to swap his Pounds 19,000 car for a model costing a mere Pounds 12,500 so
that the tax bill would be the same. Car makers feared that many executives
would be tempted to downsize and downprice, thus sapping revenue from one of
the most profitable sectors of the new car market. Vehicles with many
executive 'extras' provide disproportionately higher profit per unit
compared with mainstream fleet cars.
It will take two or three years before the effect of the new system, in
terms of vehicle choice, can be fully assessed. Nevertheless, there is
little sign so far of executives opting for less tax-burdensome cars,
according to <PERSON>Mr Michael Banner</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Vauxhall</ORGANIZATION>'s director of fleet sales, and
researchers at <ORGANIZATION>Henley Management College</ORGANIZATION> who have studied the executive and
fleet car market on <ORGANIZATION>Vauxhall</ORGANIZATION>'s behalf.
While some preference is being shown for smaller cars - but only ones
equipped to executive standards - there is only a very slight trend towards
downpricing, the researchers maintain.
<PERSON>Mr Banner</PERSON> observes that 'the typical executive driving a car priced at the
old Pounds 19,250 tax threshold has looked at the changes, realised that his
current car is going to cost him only another Pounds 20 or Pounds 30 a month
and has decided 'I'll cope'.'
Similar views are being voiced by other manufacturers. But that does not
mean that significant changes in manufacturers' model mixes and marketing
policies are not under way. One major effect of the new tax system was to
eliminate entirely the engine capacity bands which previously had
discriminated severely against larger units.
Particularly badly hit under the old system was the diesel engine. Though
likely to be favoured by many fleet managers because of its one-third
greater fuel economy compared with a petrol unit, it typically reqires
larger capacity to provide comparable on-road performance.
The new tax system is already seeing the introduction of new versions of
mainstream business cars with larger, high-performing V6 engines of 2.5
litres, as well as giving a further boost to the buoyant diesel car sector,
sales of which in the first four months of this year were running 60 per
cent higher than in the same period of <DATE>1993</DATE>.
The diesel sales go on despite two learned reports in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, which argue
that diesel exhaust emissions - including particulates suspected of causing
cancer - could contaminate the air in cities if the diesel car population
continues to expand.
One in four new cars sold in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> is now a diesel. Business car users and
fleet managers, increasingly impressed by the cost advantages, appear to be
taking comfort from the fact that commercial vehicles - many of them elderly
buses - account for at least two-thirds of the diesel exhaust pollution
being created in urban areas.
It is not only at the Pounds 19,250 tax break point that the tax system
changes are having an effect. The scrapping of the second threshold of
Pounds 29,000, above which an executive's personal tax on his company car
rose sharply, has eliminated model range 'bunching' around the breakpoint
while the capping of the new system at a Pounds 60,000 list price means that
the expensive car makers such as <ORGANIZATION>Rolls-Royce</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Aston Martin</ORGANIZATION> are not
significantly disadvantaged.
It is in pricing structures and strategies that the new tax system has had
some of its most notable effects - at least in terms of the notional prices
which are paid for executives' cars. Traditional UK pricing policies - with
a few exceptions such as Mercedes and <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> - have been based on a relatively
high list price which few customers in the business sector actually pay.
There are widespread discounts - <DATE>30</DATE> per cent or more in a few notorious
deals to particularly large fleet operators. The new list price-based tax
regime makes such policies untenable because they would maximise an
executive's personal tax burden. So manufacturers have been cutting the
profit margins they allow their dealers. Once typically 15-16.5 per cent,
plus the chance of cash bonuses from manufacturers for meeting sales
targets, these 'official' margins have been cut to 10 per cent and in some
cases - over the past few weeks in the executive sector - to 5 per cent.
Indeed, <ORGANIZATION>Vauxhall</ORGANIZATION>'s new <ORGANIZATION>Omega</ORGANIZATION> executive car range was launched with a 5 per
cent margin. In a few cases, the margin has been dispended with altogther in
favour of a fixed 'handling' charge payable to the dealer. Some <ORGANIZATION>Renault</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Volvo</ORGANIZATION> models fall into this category. So do some of the cheapest Rover 800
models with a Pounds 500 fee, while <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> is allowing a Pounds 1,500 handling
fee on its US-built Probe coupe and is giving only a token margin on its
Granada/Scorpio executive cars.
The changes have been accompanied by much trumpeting about lower prices.
This is convenient in view of the pan-EU car price comparisons now published
twice a year at the behest of the <ORGANIZATION>European Commission</ORGANIZATION>, which wants to see
price convergence between <ORGANIZATION>EU</ORGANIZATION> new car markets and tends to regard the UK as a
high-priced market.
But transaction prices have not changed a lot because dealers were already
giving away much of their official margin and relying on incentive bonuses
from manufacturers to make a return on mainstream executive cars. They now
merely have less room to haggle.
The approach does mean a lower company car tax burden for executives - and a
lower tax take for the Inland Revenue. At the moment, the Revenue can only
stand by gnashing its teeth. How it might react, in the longer term, to an
entrenched system of zero profit margins and 'handling charges' is another
matter altogether.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5012 Automobiles and Other Motor Vehicles.
    P3711 Motor Vehicles and Car Bodies.
    P3714 Motor Vehicle Parts and Accessories.
    P5511 New and Used Car Dealers.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    MKTS  Market shares.
    MKTS  Sales.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page II
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891103-0276 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-03-89 1528EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Ford-Jaguar Bjt   11-03 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ford-Jaguar, Bjt,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ford Could Close Jaguar Deal by Year's End</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FREDERICK STANDISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Auto Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>DEARBORN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> could complete its <MONEY>$2.5
billion</MONEY> acquisition of the British luxury car maker <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> by the
end of the year, the head of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s European arm said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>L. Lindsey Halstead</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Ford of Europe Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said in a
video news conference from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> that a <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> shareholders
meeting could be called by the end of this month. The transaction
could be completed within days after that if shareholders approved
the deal.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>, the No. 2 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> automaker after <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>,
announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> its agreement to buy <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>, which has suffered
from declining earnings due to dropping sales in its important <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
market.
   The buyout must win approval from <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>'s 182
million outstanding shares, which will vote whether to lift a
restriction barring anyone from owning more than <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> of
<ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> owns a <PERCENT>13.2 percent</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>.
   Halstead and <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Bert Serre</PERSON> said financing for the
deal was undetermined. Technically, <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> could pay for <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> out
of its <MONEY>$5.8 billion</MONEY> in cash reserves, but that seemed unlikely for
tax reasons, analysts have said.
   Shortly after the announcement <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp; Poors</ORGANIZATION> put
some of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s securities on its CreditWatch negative list _ a
possible prelude to a slight downgrading of their credit ratings _
citing concern about the frenzied pace of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s acquisitions in
the face of a softening <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> car market.
   Recent acquisitions have included last month's <MONEY>$3.35 billion</MONEY>
purchase of <ORGANIZATION>The Associates Corp.</ORGANIZATION> financial company from <ORGANIZATION>Paramount
Communications Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   Because of the pending shareholders' vote, <PERSON>Halstead</PERSON> declined to
answer specific questions about how <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> production would be
affected by a possible merger with <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>. Shared components may be
the most likely place a consumer would notice the partnership.
   However, he said, ``We are looking for an opportunity to expand
volume substantially. One of the first items on the agenda is
defining how that will proceed.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>'s factory in <LOCATION>Coventry</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, makes about 50,000 cars
annually and can produce up to 80,000.
   There has been speculation that if <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> came up with a totally
new model under <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> ownership, the car would be priced near or
below the current <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> XJ6 four-door sedan, which has a base
price of <MONEY>$39,700</MONEY>.
   Ford's most expensive car is the Lincoln Town Car Cartier with a
base price of <MONEY>$33,364</MONEY>.
   Halstead turned aside a suggestion that with the <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>
acquisition, Lincoln no longer would be the company's luxury car
division. He said the character of the two cars, with <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> being
more of a performance vehicle than <LOCATION>Lincoln</LOCATION>, would keep them
separate.
   ``I don't ever expect to see <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> cars in <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> showrooms and
no Jaguars in <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> showrooms,'' <PERSON>Halstead</PERSON> said.
   Ford recently stopped importing the West German-made Merkur,
which was sold through the company's <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln-Mercury</ORGANIZATION> dealerships.
   There are about 140 <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION> dealerships in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12732</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJTB8AAGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 92 / Survey of World Car Industry (25): Safety for the driver and
his planet - Stuart Marshall explores the environmental and other features
of Europe's latest models
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STUART MARSHALL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE new models that will be entering European showrooms over the next 12
months will reflect the industry's success in meeting environmental needs as
well as consumer demands.
From next <DATE>January</DATE>, every new petrol-engined car must have a catalytic
converter to clean up the exhaust. Some sections of the industry perceived
the <ORGANIZATION>EC</ORGANIZATION> requirement as a politically inspired expedient. But they faced up to
the challenge, equipping even the smallest and cheapest of their cars with
the electronic fuel injection needed for a catalyser to work properly.
Multi-valve engines have for some years been widely used by all Japanese
makers on high volume production, as opposed to specialised high
performance, cars. This was not the case in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, though <ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION> and Rover
were among the few honourable exceptions as multi-valve pioneers.
Now, however, they are being adopted by European manufacturers across the
whole price spectrum as a means of improving power outputs without
increasing cylinder capacity.
Among the latest multi-valve models are a wide range of <ORGANIZATION>Ford Escorts</ORGANIZATION> and the
<ORGANIZATION>Mercedes Benz</ORGANIZATION> 200-300 cars, due to be joined early next year by the
replacement for the best selling 190.
V6 engines are enjoying a vogue because of the space they save compared with
in-line designs, which do not fit transversely into front-wheel driven cars.
An alternative solution, seen in the latest <ORGANIZATION>Volvo</ORGANIZATION> 850GLT, is to mount a
5-cylinder in-line engine east-west combined with an ultra-compact manual or
automatic transmission.
The most space-saving conventional piston engine of all is the narrow angle
V6, first used more than 60 years ago by <ORGANIZATION>Lancia</ORGANIZATION>. Audi and <ORGANIZATION>Volkswagen</ORGANIZATION> are
employing two different narrow angle V6s occupying hardly any more space
than in-line 4-cylinder engines of far less cylinder capacity in a number of
models, including the <ORGANIZATION>VW Golf</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Vento</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> 80 and 100.
This illustrates another growing trend - the fitting of comparatively large
displacement and high power output engines into cars of modest size. These
provide the performance, and offer all the luxury equipment, expected of
products in the next size class. Big is no longer beautiful among many
motorists who spend much of their time driving on their own in crowded
traffic conditions.
Availability from early next year of the mid-sized <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Vauxhall
Cavalier</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Opel Vectra</ORGANIZATION> in most European markets) with a new British-built,
narrow angle 2.5 litre V6 engine is a straw in the wind. So, too, is <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s
decision to offer its new V8 engines, originally introduced in the big
7-Series and intended to power its forthcoming replacement, in the 5-Series
as well.
<ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION>, also <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> controlled, is expected soon to be using the British-made 2.5
V6 but has its own ideas for improving performance and minimising emissions.
The <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> link has given <ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION> access to 32-bit microprocessor technology. It is
combined with a direct ignition system having a mini-coil per cylinder and
no high-tension leads or distributor. This 32-bit component (most other
makers use 8-bit or 16-bit microprocessors) provides exceptionally precise
monitoring and control of transient state conditions within the engine.
So exactly does the <ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION> Trionic system, with its 2m calculations each
second, control combustion that it is claimed to make the 2.3 litre,
turbocharged 4-cylinder engine of <DATE>1993</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Saab</ORGANIZATION> 9000CS and CD models one of the
world's cleanest. In the foreseeable future, the Trionic system will allow a
petrol engine to be run on less polluting alternative fuels such as ethanol
or methanol without any adjustment.
Two-stroke engines, far smaller and lighter than four-strokes of the same
power output, are being developed by many car makers on both sides of the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> and in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> is monitoring the performance of a fleet of two-stroke powered Fiestas
in service with a British police force.
<ORGANIZATION>Toyota</ORGANIZATION> has demonstrated an ultra-light and fuel efficient two-stroke powered
concept town car. <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> also has some promising two-stroke engines at an
advanced development stage in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
The Japanese motor industry has an unnerving habit of rapidly turning
concept cars into production models. For example, both <ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi</ORGANIZATION> 3000GT and
Subaru SVX were on sale within two years of being unveiled to the public at
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> motor show. Even so, the Japanese do not expect two-stroke engines to
be in the showrooms in <DATE>1993</DATE> but a mid-decade timescale looks more promising.
But for the time being, there is agreement among major European
manufacturers that the diesel engine, preferably with turbocharging,
intercooling and direct injection, provides the best fuel economy.
Although there is a public perception that diesels are dirty - and
ill-maintained heavy lorries and buses undoubtedly are - a diesel car is at
least as environmentally acceptable as one with a petrol engine and
three-way catalytic converter.
There is a clear relationship between atmospheric pollution and fuel
consumption. The diesel engine, especially when operating at less than full
power and at constantly changing revolutions - as it does in traffic - has a
much lower specific fuel consumption than a petrol engine. Hence its carbon
dioxide emissions are proportionately lower and its efficient combustion
process also creates less carbon monoxide.
Now that inherent noise problems have been overcome by two-stage injectors
and other means, the direct-injection car diesel is pointing to fuel economy
beyond the capability of petrol engines.
Without any special preparation, a new <ORGANIZATION>Audi</ORGANIZATION> 100 TDI saloon with 6-speed
gearbox recently gained an entry in the <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of Records</ORGANIZATION> by being
driven further on a single tankful than any other car. In showroom trim, it
went from <PERSON>John o</PERSON>' Groats to Lands End and then back again north of the
Scottish border on 17.62 gallons (80.17 litres) of fuel, giving a
consumption of 75.94 mpg (3.72 l/100 km).
The industry is now concentrating on further reducing the diesel car
engine's particulate emissions (visible exhaust smoke), the only area in
which it is significantly worse than a petrol engine.
The main line of attack is to refine the fuel injection and combustion
process and clean the exhaust gases by a simple oxidation catalyser.
Automatic transmissions are gaining ground as urban driving in particular
becomes more stressful. There can be no argument that a car with two pedals
makes fewer demands on the driver in heavy traffic than one with three.
Safety can only benefit. Just as 4-speed automatics have virtually taken
over from the old 3-speed types, those with 5-speeds are making steady
headway in cars of medium price and above.
This kind of technological advance always spreads downward. When ABS brakes
were first introduced, they were costly extra equipment on the most
expensive cars. Now buyers expect them to be standard on modestly priced
cars, particularly those of higher than average performance potential.
In the same way, traction control systems have become increasingly popular
on executive-class cars. They make use of the ABS brake system's electronic
sensors to eliminate the risk of wheelspin and consequent loss of control
when accelerating by matching engine output to tyre grip.
Full-time four wheel drive performs a similar function but traction control
has been found to provide most of the benefits without the weight and cost
penalties.
On the safety front, enhanced protection for the occupants in side impacts
is now a feature of many high volume production cars. Similarly, airbags
which inflate in severe frontal impacts and reduce risk of facial injury to
drivers and front seat passengers are spreading down market. They cost extra
 -usually over Pounds 500 - but as demand grows, prices must fall.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870519-0143 </DOCNO>
<HL> GM Moves Up Date
For Idling Of Plant,
Citing Slow Sales
---
By Dale D. Buss
<DD> 05/19/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GM
AUTOS, AUTO PARTS (AUT) </IN>
<DATELINE> DETROIT  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to close temporarily most of its assembly plant here more than a month earlier than previously planned because of slow sales of several luxury-car models built at the factory. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said it now plans tentatively to shut down its state-of-the-art, two-year-old factory here, known as the "Poletown" plant, on <DATE>June 26</DATE>, idling about 2,500 workers until its reopening in late <DATE>August</DATE>. 
During the closure, the company will retool the plant for styling changes in the new fall model of the <LOCATION>Cadillac Eldorado</LOCATION>, which the plant builds in addition to several other <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> luxury models, including the <LOCATION>Cadillac Seville</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Oldsmobile Toronado</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Buick Riviera</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Stopping production of these <DATE>1987</DATE> models earlier than planned represents a setback for the company. 
When <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> introduced the front-wheel-drive models in the <DATE>fall of 1985</DATE>, they were hailed as vehicles that would keep <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> strong in the expensive-car market for years. 
But many consumers ignored the new products, partly because their styling was similar to less expensive <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> cars and they were smaller. 
They have sold at roughly only half the rate of the models they replaced. 

   Besides underscoring the continuing problems of these cars, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement also shows that the No. 1 auto maker's recent problems in generating sales across its product line aren't easing much. 
Just <DATE>last week</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to close temporarily six other assembly plants and to lay off about 30,000 hourly workers because of slow sales, in the latest of its frequent rounds of plant shutdowns this year. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> had opened the Poletown plant with much fanfare about laser-inspection systems and other high-technology devices that it was introducing there. 
But in addition to encountering resistance to the cars built there, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> also soon saw the plant run into a variety of technical snafus, which the company has spent the last year correcting. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890824-0091 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890824 </DD>
<AN> 890824-0091. </AN>
<HL> GM Increases Price
@  Of New Lumina Car </HL>
<DD> 08/24/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> GM C </CO>
<IN> AUTOS, AUTO PARTS (AUT) </IN>
<DATELINE> DETROIT  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Just five months after its introduction, <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is raising the price of its <DATE>1990</DATE> Chevrolet Lumina sedan, the first of a new line of four-door sedans <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> is counting on to boost its sagging car-market share. 

   The least expensive <ORGANIZATION>Lumina</ORGANIZATION> will sell for <MONEY>$12,340</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>3.8%</PERCENT> from the original base price of <MONEY>$11,883</MONEY>. 
The base price of the <ORGANIZATION>Lumina Euro</ORGANIZATION> sedan, which <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> expects to be the more popular version, will rise <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$14,240</MONEY> from <MONEY>$13,776</MONEY> currently. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> appears to be boosting the Lumina prices in step with its prime competitor, the <ORGANIZATION>Ford Taurus</ORGANIZATION>. 
The <DATE>1990</DATE> Taurus will start at <MONEY>$12,594</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$254</MONEY> more than <ORGANIZATION>Lumina</ORGANIZATION>, and up <PERCENT>6.9%</PERCENT> from the <DATE>1989</DATE> Taurus base price of <MONEY>$11,778</MONEY>. 
But the <DATE>1990</DATE> Taurus will have a standard driver-side air bag. 
Chevy's <ORGANIZATION>Lumina</ORGANIZATION> will not. 

   So far, <ORGANIZATION>Lumina</ORGANIZATION> hasn't set the market on fire. 
At the end of <DATE>July</DATE>, dealers had an 82-day supply of the sedans; a 60 to 65-day supply is considered desirable. 
In mid-August, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> sold 2,865 Luminas. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>, by comparison, sold 8,363 Taurus sedans. 

   Meanwhile, Chevrolet set the price for its top-of-the-line image car, the Corvette ZR-1, at <MONEY>$58,995</MONEY>. 
That sticker could make the ZR-1 the most expensive car <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> sells, depending on the final price of <ORGANIZATION>Cadillac</ORGANIZATION>'s Allante model. 
The <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Allante</ORGANIZATION> sells for <MONEY>$57,183</MONEY>. 
Cadillac hasn't announced a final price for the <DATE>1990</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Allante</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Overall, <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> officials said they expect the division to increase its combined <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> car and truck market share to roughly <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1990</DATE> model year from an estimated <PERCENT>18%</PERCENT> for <DATE>1989</DATE>. 

   Chevrolet general manager <PERSON>J.C. Perkins</PERSON> forecast <DATE>1990</DATE> Chevy sales at about 2.9 million vehicles, including more than 1.4 million trucks. 
That's up from 2.8 million currently estimated for the model year that ends next month. 

   Division marketing executives said the new car advertisements will focus on product and features, rather than image. 

   Truck advertising will accent image, however, with lots of quick shots in one television version of men hard at work in factory settings. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910409-0083
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910409-0083.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Ford Increases
   Its Base Prices
   On 1991 Models
   ---
   General Motors Boosts Cost
   Of Certain Options Amid
   Lower Sales Volumes
   ----
   By Krystal Miller
</HL>
<DATE>
04/09/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   F GM
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
</IN>
<RE>
MICHIGAN (MI)
</RE>
<LP>
   Ford Motor Co., in an attempt to bolster profit in a
sagging market, quietly raised base prices on all 1991 model
cars as much as $582.
   Separately, General Motors Corp. boosted prices on certain
widely purchased options. The No. 1 and No. 2 auto makers'
actions come in the wake of price increases by Chrysler Corp.
and several Japanese auto makers. The moves suggest that
despite consumer resistance to high vehicle prices, the
industry is continuing a strategy of pushing prices up to
offset the impact of lower sales volumes.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Dearborn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, told dealers in <DATE>February</DATE>
it would increase sticker prices on most of its models. But
<ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> didn't announce the action to the public. The increases
were reported in yesterday's <ORGANIZATION>Automotive News</ORGANIZATION>, a trade
journal.
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> said it moved to add an average <MONEY>$50</MONEY> a car to sticker
prices to offset higher operating and product development
costs. The increases could generate an additional <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>
for every 100,000 vehicles sold. With <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and European auto
sales soft, the company has signaled it expects to post a
"substantial loss" for the <DATE>first quarter</DATE> and may not be
profitable for the full year.
   The biggest price rise came on the Taurus L and GL models,
which were given V-6 engines as standard equipment. The
Taurus L sedan now costs <MONEY>$13,934</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>4.4%</PERCENT> from <MONEY>$13,352</MONEY>. The
Taurus GL starts at <MONEY>$14,163</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$581</MONEY> from <MONEY>$13,582</MONEY>. The price
of <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s least-expensive car, the <LOCATION>Festiva</LOCATION>, which is made in
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, rose <MONEY>$28</MONEY> to <MONEY>$6,648</MONEY>. Meanwhile, the price of the
least-expensive <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-made Ford</ORGANIZATION>, the Escort Pony, was pushed
<MONEY>$40</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8,016</MONEY>.
   "The cost of business continues to rise" despite slow
sales, a <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said. "There's a laundry list of
costs that continues to go up." Ford didn't announce the
increases because they were "insignificant," the spokesman
said.
   <PERSON>George Hoffer</PERSON>, a professor of economics at <ORGANIZATION>Virginia
Commonwealth University</ORGANIZATION>, said the price increases shouldn't
have a major impact on buyers because <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> could use rebates
to adjust prices. "Auto makers use rebates to fine tune
prices to adjust to market demand," contends <PERSON>Mr. Hoffer</PERSON>. "The
cars don't normally sell at list price because of the
manipulation of rebates."
   Still, the increases mean consumers will start negotiating
from higher base prices. Moreover, because <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> no longer
offers direct-to-customer incentives, shoppers may not know
how much of a discount they can get. Instead, dealers could
pocket part of the rebate unless customers work hard to get
the best deal.
   Ford raised <DATE>1991</DATE> model prices an average of <PERCENT>1.9%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$312</MONEY>,
in <DATE>September</DATE>, the last month of the auto industry's <DATE>1990</DATE>
model year. Since that time, this has been <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>'s only price
rise.
   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s price increase for options could raise the cost of
cars equipped with air conditioning and automatic
transmissions by as much as <MONEY>$85</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> announced the increases in <DATE>January</DATE> to dealers only. A
<ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the company raised option prices "to
partially recover higher production costs." The No. 1 auto
maker said it hasn't raised base sticker prices so far this
year.
   The increases affect such widely ordered optional
equipment as automatic transmissions, air conditioning and
power windows and locks. The price increases for automatic
transmissions range from <MONEY>$10</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30</MONEY>. Prices for air
conditioning will rise between <MONEY>$15</MONEY> and <MONEY>$55</MONEY>. Buyers of <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>
trucks will pay between <MONEY>$5</MONEY> and <MONEY>$25</MONEY> more for certain optional
equipment. <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said its <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Cadillac divisions aren't
affected by the increases.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900629-0117
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900629-0117.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Heard on the Street:
   Porsche and BMW Stocks Seen Underpriced
   As Sales of Specialty Cars Move Into Overdrive
   ----
   By David B. Hilder
</HL>
<DATE>
06/29/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C2
</SO>
<CO>
   G.POR G.BMW
</CO>
<IN>
HEARD ON THE STREET (HRD)
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
AUTOMOBILES (AUT)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Because of Wall Street's continuing slump, far
fewer traders and investment bankers are lining up to buy
high-powered, high-priced cars such as Porsches and BMWs.
   But in the rest of the U.S. -- and in Japan and Europe --
sales of these performance cars are shifting into overdrive.
Several European auto analysts say shares of Porsche and
Bayerische Motoren Werke are underpriced, even if Americans
have to search a bit to find ways to buy those stocks.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>, which is much smaller than <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> and makes more
expensive cars, gets more enthusiastic reviews for its adroit
recovery from a sales slump in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Porsche shares trade at
a price-earnings ratio of about 17.5, close to that of
<ORGANIZATION>Daimler Benz</ORGANIZATION>, the giant of German auto makers. Several
analysts believe <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> will someday command a higher
multiple, however, because it's the only remaining publicly
traded specialty car maker.
   "We really do believe <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> is the last of its kind
remaining in the world" after <ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor</ORGANIZATION>'s purchase of
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Jaguar</ORGANIZATION>, says <PERSON>Stephen M. Reitman</PERSON>, a London-based
analyst with <ORGANIZATION>UBS Phillips &amp; Drew</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> and other analysts also recommend <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>,
which trades at a significantly lower price-earnings ratio
than <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Daimler Benz</ORGANIZATION>, they fear that <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> shares may
get stuck in neutral because of fears about increasing
Japanese competition in the lower end of the luxury-car
market.
   "I think <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> is cheap and that one should probably buy
it," says <PERSON>Philip Ayton</PERSON>, a London-based analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Barclays
de Zoete Wedd</ORGANIZATION>. But he adds that <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s stock "has performed
badly and I'm not sure even now whether there's going to be a
change in sentiment."
   Several analysts cite <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>'s swift recovery from the
gear-grinding changes of <DATE>1987</DATE> as evidence of a management
that recognized the company's problems and acted decisively.
   Through <DATE>1986</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> rode the big luxury-car boom in the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and allowed <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales to claim <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of its peak
production of about 53,500 cars a year. Porsche "stepped
right into the dollar trap by getting a little too greedy and
selling too many cars in the States," says <PERSON>Dagmar
Bottenbruch</PERSON>, a European auto analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Credit Suisse First
Boston</ORGANIZATION>. "Then the currency halved and the bottom fell out of
the luxury-car market" in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, she adds.
   But now, <PERSON>Ms. Bottenbruch</PERSON> says, <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> "has its destiny
under control." Production has been cut to about 31,000 cars
a year. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales now represent only about one-third of
<ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>'s total, with an equal amount in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the rest
concentrated in other European countries and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> also eliminated its cheapest and least profitable
model in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, the 924, which had been priced at about
<MONEY>$24,000</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> says. Now, the lowest-price <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> sold
in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is the 944, at <MONEY>$43,350</MONEY>.
   The most profitable models for <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> are the various
versions of its classic 911, descendants of the original
<ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> which resembled an upside-down bathtub.
   Porsche sales in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> have been rising this
year, up <PERCENT>19%</PERCENT> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> through <DATE>May</DATE> and up <PERCENT>62%</PERCENT> in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>
through <DATE>April</DATE>. But <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> doesn't expect big increases
in either production or prices. Porsche "trades on having a
cache, on their rarity and desirability. They will accept
waiting lists," he believes.
   One slightly hidden asset, <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> says, is <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>'s
research and development facility in <LOCATION>Weissach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>,
which does work for many other auto makers, including <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION>,
and is run as a profit center. During the 1987-88 period the
center took on additional work that should produce more
profits in the next few years, he says.
   <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> also has net cash of <MONEY>459 million marks</MONEY> (<MONEY>$275.8
million</MONEY>) and no debt; analysts expect the company to be able
to continue to fund its development from cash flow.
   <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>'s fiscal year ends <DATE>July 31</DATE>; <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> expects
the company to report a profit of about <MONEY>70 marks</MONEY> (<MONEY>$42</MONEY>) a
share; <PERSON>Ms. Bottenbruch</PERSON> expects profit of 72 to <MONEY>75 marks</MONEY> a
share. For next year, <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON> forecasts <MONEY>80 marks</MONEY> a share
but says that could be low; <PERSON>Ms. Bottenbruch</PERSON> looks for <MONEY>85
marks</MONEY> to <MONEY>90 marks</MONEY> a share.
   At yesterday's closing price of <MONEY>1232 marks</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> is
trading at about 17.5 times its expected <DATE>1990</DATE> earnings. The
<ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> shares that trade on the <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> exchange are
non-voting preference shares; voting control is held by
members of the <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Piech</PERSON> families.
   <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>, which closed yesterday at <MONEY>584.50 marks</MONEY>, trades at
only about 10 times analysts' estimates of its <DATE>1990</DATE> earnings;
<ORGANIZATION>Daimler Benz</ORGANIZATION> is trading at about 17 times estimated <DATE>1990</DATE>
earnings. That price/earnings gap, asserts <PERSON>Mr. Reitman</PERSON>, is
"totally unjustified."
   <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> can be bought in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> as an American Depositary
Receipt; <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION> stock trades only in German markets.
   <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> shares have sagged on fears that new Japanese-made
luxury cars, such as Infiniti and Lexus, will steal some
market share from <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>, whose lowest priced 318is model has a
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> base price of <MONEY>$21,500</MONEY>. <PERSON>Mr. Ayton</PERSON> concedes that the
Japanese will grab some part of the luxury market, but says:
"I'm not convinced that it will be fully at <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s expense or
at the expense of <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s margins."
   There's some concern that <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>'s profit may ebb next year
as it revises the models in its best-selling 3-series. <PERSON>Ms.
Bottenbruch</PERSON>, who has a neutral rating on <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION>, says the shares
may get a boost once the new models are introduced. "The car
press already says this is going to be a real blockbuster,"
she notes.
   One additional issue for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> investors in either <ORGANIZATION>Porsche</ORGANIZATION>
or <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> is how the mark fares against the dollar. A falling
mark would diminish potential capital gains. Though many
economists expect the mark to thrive against the dollar
long-term, there is some concern that the mark will weaken
during the next few months because of the costs of German
reunification.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880815-0149 </DOCNO>
<HL> GM Increases '89 Model Prices From 4% to 8% --- Company Says Rise Is 2.9%, Listing Former Options As Standard Equipment </HL>
<AUTHOR> Joseph B. White (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GM </CO>
<IN> AUT </IN>
<DATELINE> DETROIT  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is raising the base prices of most <DATE>1989</DATE> cars and light trucks between <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT>, and is pressing a strategy that makes it more attractive to buy cars that are relatively loaded with options. 

   The No. 1 auto maker, in an announcement <DATE>Friday</DATE>, billed the average price increase for <DATE>1989</DATE> cars as <PERCENT>2.9%</PERCENT>. 
But <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> adjusted for the inclusion as standard equipment of features that were sold as options last year, and also adjusted for the fact that it isn't raising the prices of equipment that remains optional. 

   Excluding this latter adjustment, the actual prices of many popular <DATE>1989</DATE> models will go up considerably more than <PERCENT>2.9%</PERCENT>, even when allowances are made for new standard equipment. 

   For example, the lowest priced <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Pontiac Grand Prix</ORGANIZATION> will cost <MONEY>$13,899</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>10.8%</PERCENT>, or <MONEY>$1,360</MONEY>, from the <DATE>1988</DATE> base model price of <MONEY>$12,539</MONEY>. 
The Grand Prix, the best-selling of <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s new line of midsized cars, will now have air conditioning as standard equipment. 
Last year, <PERCENT>99%</PERCENT> of Grand Prix customers bought air conditioning as a <MONEY>$775</MONEY> option, a <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said. 
So on a comparably equipped basis, the Grand Prix's base price is up <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> for <DATE>1989</DATE>. 

   The base price for the <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Buick Regal</ORGANIZATION>, the Grand Prix's sister car, will rise <PERCENT>14.1%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$14,214</MONEY>. 
Adjusting for new standard equipment, the <DATE>1989</DATE> Regal's base price is still <MONEY>$518</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>3.8%</PERCENT>, higher than the base <DATE>1988</DATE> model. 

   The <DATE>1989</DATE> Corsica sedan, one of <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s best-selling cars, will have a base price of <MONEY>$9,985</MONEY>, up <PERCENT>4.5%</PERCENT> from last year's base price, and up <PERCENT>3.6%</PERCENT> from the <MONEY>$9,642</MONEY> price of the comparably equipped <DATE>1988</DATE> model. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> is cutting the prices on a few models, such as the compact <ORGANIZATION>Oldsmobile Cutlass Calais</ORGANIZATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Cutlass Calais</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1989</DATE> base price of <MONEY>$9,995</MONEY> is <PERCENT>3.1%</PERCENT> less than the base <DATE>1988</DATE> version. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> said its price increases reflect "the partial recovery of higher material, labor and other costs." 
But <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1989</DATE> pricing strategy also is aimed at two broader goals. 
It cuts the number of variations of each model the company has to build, and therefore helps <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> cut manufacturing costs. 
And it helps <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> push customers toward buying more profitable options. 

   For instance, a <DATE>1989</DATE> Camaro RS with a package of options that includes air conditioning, four-speed automatic transmission, power door locks, AM/FM-cassette stereo, tinted glass and rear window defogger will list for <MONEY>$12,227</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>5.3%</PERCENT> less than the comparably equipped <DATE>1988</DATE> model. 

   But a buyer who wants a base <DATE>1989</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Camaro RS</ORGANIZATION> will pay <PERCENT>4.5%</PERCENT> more for that car than for the base <DATE>1988</DATE> Camaro RS. Even adjusting for the additional equipment added to the <DATE>1989</DATE> base car, the <MONEY>$11,495</MONEY> price represents a <PERCENT>3.8%</PERCENT> increase over the comparably equipped <DATE>1988</DATE> model. 

   In addition to the base price increases, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> is also adding <MONEY>$25</MONEY> to the destination charges it tacks on to each vehicle delivered. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s price disclosure follows announcements by <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Corp.</ORGANIZATION> that it expects to raise base prices an average of <PERCENT>3.9%</PERCENT>, or about <PERCENT>2.3%</PERCENT> when adjusted for additional standard equipment. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ford Motor Co.</ORGANIZATION> earlier this month said it is raising the base prices of a half-dozen older models an average of <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> hasn't announced its final prices yet. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1989</DATE> pricing strategy builds on moves last year to justify higher prices by building more standard equipment into the base models. 

   Company officials say building popular options in as standard equipment will mean that base model prices more honestly reflect the prices customers actually will pay for cars. 

   "Under <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> buy base cars. 
That's an artifact, and customers know that," <PERSON>Shirley Young</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president for consumer market development, said in a recent interview. 

   But for <DATE>1989</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> officials are conceding that some of the price increases are simply "economic adjustments." 
The base price of the full-size <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> pickup truck, for instance, will rise <PERCENT>4.5%</PERCENT> in <DATE>1989</DATE> to <MONEY>$10,335</MONEY>, compared with <MONEY>$9,894</MONEY> in <DATE>1988</DATE>. 
No new equipment is included, a <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said. 

   <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> isn't raising the base prices of its least expensive and most expensive cars, the <LOCATION>Pontiac</LOCATION> LeMans and the <ORGANIZATION>Cadillac Allante</ORGANIZATION>. 
The Allante, the flagship of the <ORGANIZATION>Cadillac</ORGANIZATION> division, has a base price of <MONEY>$56,533</MONEY>, and hasn't sold well. 
The LeMans, made in <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, has a base price of <MONEY>$6,399</MONEY>. 

   The base price of a domestically built entry level model, the two-door <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet Cavalier</ORGANIZATION>, will increase <PERCENT>5.4%</PERCENT> in <DATE>1989</DATE> to <MONEY>$7,375</MONEY> from <MONEY>$6,995</MONEY>, the <ORGANIZATION>Chevrolet</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said. 

   Because <ORGANIZATION>GM</ORGANIZATION> announced its <DATE>1989</DATE> prices to the public <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> before giving details to its dealers, dealers late last week said they needed to know more before making any comment. 
