<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06011160 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06011160 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Depardieu, left, and MacDowell face a tough INS interrogation in 'Green
Card'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AMERICAN filmmakers do many things well, but the sophisticated romance isn't
one of them. For this, Hollywood must defer to the French, and on very rare
occasion to the British, who brought us such four-hankie classics as "Brief
Encounter" and "The Go-Between.";    Touchstone's brand new "Green Card" isn't
up to those standards, mind you, but it is something quite special -- a
smartly written and performed relationship picture that assumes a certain
level of intelligence on the part of the viewer. We'll go one further: "Green
Card" makes "Pretty Woman" and "Ghost" look positively arthritic in their
plotting. Why, it even has a continental feel. Translation: the principals
lead interesting lives, have a sense of humor about themselves and can banter
without resorting to profanity.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HOLLYWOOD CONTINENTAL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Film Reviews  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Before rushing to clap Hollywood on the back, we should also add that
"Green Card" stars the great French actor <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> and was directed by
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON>, best known for "Dead Poets Society" and "Witness"
(remember <PERSON>Harrison Ford</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kelly McGillis</PERSON> cheek-to-cheeking to <PERSON>Sam Cooke</PERSON>'s
"Wonderful World"). <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s love interest is played with just the right
air of mock indifference by <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>, the more conventional sister of
"sex, lies &amp; videotape.";    Together, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>, <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> have
fashioned a slick, spunky little fable about a marriage of convenience that
becomes something more, though not by the same predictable route taken by two
decades of <PERSON>Neil Simon</PERSON> lovebirds.;    <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> plays <PERSON>George</PERSON>, a con
man/composer from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> is <LOCATION>Bronte</LOCATION>, an uptown kind of woman who's
big on horticulture and chic environmental causes. He wants to stay in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>; she wants to stay in her apartment building, which has strict rules
about not renting to singles. They decide to get married -- to get <PERSON>George</PERSON> his
work permit (a green card) and to keep <PERSON>Bronte</PERSON> in her dream home, which comes
complete with a Victorian greenhouse and miniature rain forest.;    It's a
business arrangement, see? Nothing personal. No lingering attachments after
the proper documents are signed. Both shrug nervously and go their separate
ways -- until immigration officers start sniffing around and <PERSON>George</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bronte</PERSON>
must play out a more elaborate charade for the government, her parents and
neighbors.;    Inevitably, just by virtue of their proximity, the two become
better acquainted. In one of the funnier sequences, they go to great lengths
to fabricate a wedding album, complete with Polaroids of winter and tropical
vacations. It's all great fun, but hardly the stuff of lasting romance. After
all, she's kind of uptight and comes with a perfectly predictable beau (<PERSON>Gregg
Edelman</PERSON>), and <PERSON>George</PERSON> is a live-for-the-moment kind of guy with "a past."
Bronte's friends find the hulking, refreshingly blunt foreigner charming;
<LOCATION>Bronte</LOCATION>, in keeping with her Victorian namesake, finds him loud and uncouth.;  
 Granted, there isn't a great deal going on here. The script at best is a
reversal of the old boy-meets-girl, boy-loses-girl, boy-gets-girl formula.;   
What makes "Green Card" special is <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>'s jumpy pacing and <ORGANIZATION>Depardieu</ORGANIZATION>'s lusty
portrayal. Weir constantly throws his hero into impossible situations, and
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>, that bear with the little-boy grin, improvises with great gusto.
His impromptu  piano recital before a roomful of uptown swells is hilarious.
It, like this movie, is a reminder that we'll buy just about anything,
provided it's delivered with charm and energy.; Green Card;
(star)(star)(star); Rated: PG-13 (slight profanity); Cast: <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>; Director-writer: <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENN LOVELL, Mercury News Film Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910111  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  591  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, January 11, 1991
00011160,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1310EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--MacDowell Adv04-06   12-24 0673</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--MacDowell, Adv04-06,0908</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv04</NOTE>
<NOTE>$Adv05</NOTE>
<NOTE>$Adv06</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Weekend Editions, Jan. 4-6, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Star Watch: From `sex, lies and videotape' to `Green Card'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: `Green Card' will open wide on Jan. 11.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From Tarzan's mate to <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON>'s
leading lady - that's the amazing range of <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>'s
fast-rising movie career.
   The <LOCATION>South Carolinian</LOCATION> made her film debut in <DATE>1984</DATE> opposite
<PERSON>Christopher Lambert</PERSON> in ``Greystoke: The Legend of <LOCATION>Tarzan</LOCATION>, Lord of
the Jungle.'' The movie didn't do much for either performer, and
<ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>'s career languished until last year's ``sex, lies and
videotape.'' The film brought prestigious offers, including one
from <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> (``Witness,'' ``Dead Poets Society'') to co-star
opposite <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in ``Green Card.''
   Touchstone Pictures released ``Green Card'' in limited
engagements before year's end in time for Academy Award
consideration, and the movie will open nationally <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE>.
   Weir wrote, directed and produced the story of a Frenchman
(<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>) who lacks a green card to take a job in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. The solution: get married to an American. MacDowell needs
to be married in order to rent the ``perfect apartment'' in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>. Voila!
   MacDowell, a rare beauty whose screen presence belies a basic
shyness, admits she was scared to death at her first meeting with
<PERSON>Weir</PERSON>. ``I wanted to do this film so badly, and I wanted to make the
proper impression. Any time you want to make the proper impression,
you usually don't,'' she said with a laugh.
   ``I left that meeting going over every word that I had uttered,
every movement that I had made. I guess it worked. I got the job.''
   Her first meeting with <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> was easier: ``<PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> said in an
interview that I was nervous, and I was. I was more nervous meeting
with <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> than with <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON>. He's very charming, you know, and you
can see immediately how easy and comfortable he is with himself.''
   About the language problem: ``I can get by in French. I would
say that <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> speaks better English than I speak French. We did
all right. A lot of times he would speak French to me, because I
can understand it. Peter speaks perfect French.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> was born in the small mill town of <LOCATION>Gaffney</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, and grew up on both sides of the border between the
<LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>. The urge to act came early.
   ``Even as a child I loved to entertain. I loved to make people
laugh. I used to put on shows in my garage. I danced in front of
the TV - `Look at me! Look at me!' A little bit of a ham, I guess.
I did theater when I was in college,'' she said.
   ``My mother, who is no longer alive, was very happy that I
wanted to act, and she gave me great confidence. She sustained me.
My father, I think at the beginning was a bit frightened, only
because of the possibility of danger that I was going to the big
city. He had plans for his daughter: he wanted me to be a nurse,
get my education, marry a doctor and have children. Now he seems
very proud that I'm happy.''
   MacDowell did go to the big city, where she studied in a
repertory theater. Playing <PERSON>Jane to Lambert</PERSON>'s Tarzan seemed like a
star-making turn, but it wasn't. Her only memorable role afterward
was an unobtainable love in the yuppie melodrama ``St. Elmo's
Fire.'' Then came ``sex, lies and videotape,'' in which she played
the frustrated wife of a philandering husband.
   ``I would say it was the beginning of my career,'' she
commented. ``I didn't know how it would turn out. It was such a
low-budget film with a new director (<PERSON>Stephen Soderbergh</PERSON>). When I
met him, I had complete trust in him.
   ``But you just don't know. It might get made and never
distributed. That was my fear. I thought I would have something on
tape to show casting directors what I was capable of. I knew that I
finally had a role that I could do very well.
   ``I had confidence in myself as far as the role. I didn't think
that anybody knew her as well as I knew her. It touched me in a
very deep place.''
   She feared that people might be narrow-minded about the film's
explicit talk. Not until ``sex, lies'' won first prize at the <LOCATION>Park
City</LOCATION> film festival did she think that it might be distributed after
all. Then it won big at <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION>, and she thought, ``Well, it really
will get distributed!''
   MacDowell lives with her husband, <PERSON>Paul Qualley</PERSON>, and their two
children in a farmhouse outside <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>. ``I wanted to move
further into the country and live on a farm,'' she said, ``but this
career has sort of taken over my life. This year I lived in
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. I did three films.
   ``I don't think I plan to do three films next year. After so
many years of wanting to do good work, to all of a sudden have the
opportunity to work on three such interesting and different
projects, it was too tempting to pass up. I hope I don't do that
again.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Weekend Editions, Jan. 4-6</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   From Tarzan's mate to <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON>'s
leading lady - that's the amazing range of <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>'s
fast-rising movie career.
   The <LOCATION>South Carolinian</LOCATION> made her film debut in <DATE>1984</DATE> opposite
<PERSON>Christopher Lambert</PERSON> in ``Greystoke: The Legend of <LOCATION>Tarzan</LOCATION>, Lord of
the Jungle.'' The movie didn't do much for either performer, and
<ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>'s career languished until last year's ``sex, lies and
videotape.'' The film brought prestigious offers, including one
from <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> (``Witness,'' ``Dead Poets Society'') to co-star
opposite <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in ``Green Card.''
   Touchstone Pictures released ``Green Card'' in limited
engagements before year's end in time for Academy Award
consideration, and the movie will open nationally <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE>.
   Weir wrote, directed and produced the story of a Frenchman
(<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>) who lacks a green card to take a job in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>. The solution: get married to an American. MacDowell needs
to be married in order to rent the ``perfect apartment'' in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>. Voila!
   MacDowell, a rare beauty whose screen presence belies a basic
shyness, admits she was scared to death at her first meeting with
<PERSON>Weir</PERSON>. ``I wanted to do this film so badly, and I wanted to make the
proper impression. Any time you want to make the proper impression,
you usually don't,'' she said with a laugh.
   ``I left that meeting going over every word that I had uttered,
every movement that I had made. I guess it worked. I got the job.''
   Her first meeting with <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> was easier: ``<PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> said in an
interview that I was nervous, and I was. I was more nervous meeting
with <PERSON>Peter</PERSON> than with <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON>. He's very charming, you know, and you
can see immediately how easy and comfortable he is with himself.''
   About the language problem: ``I can get by in French. I would
say that <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> speaks better English than I speak French. We did
all right. A lot of times he would speak French to me, because I
can understand it. Peter speaks perfect French.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> was born in the small mill town of <LOCATION>Gaffney</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, and grew up on both sides of the border between the
<LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>. The urge to act came early.
   ``Even as a child I loved to entertain. I loved to make people
laugh. I used to put on shows in my garage. I danced in front of
the TV - `Look at me! Look at me!' A little bit of a ham, I guess.
I did theater when I was in college,'' she said.
   ``My mother, who is no longer alive, was very happy that I
wanted to act, and she gave me great confidence. She sustained me.
My father, I think at the beginning was a bit frightened, only
because of the possibility of danger that I was going to the big
city. He had plans for his daughter: he wanted me to be a nurse,
get my education, marry a doctor and have children. Now he seems
very proud that I'm happy.''
   MacDowell did go to the big city, where she studied in a
repertory theater. Playing <PERSON>Jane to Lambert</PERSON>'s Tarzan seemed like a
star-making turn, but it wasn't. Her only memorable role afterward
was an unobtainable love in the yuppie melodrama ``St. Elmo's
Fire.'' Then came ``sex, lies and videotape,'' in which she played
the frustrated wife of a philandering husband.
   ``I would say it was the beginning of my career,'' she
commented. ``I didn't know how it would turn out. It was such a
low-budget film with a new director (<PERSON>Stephen Soderbergh</PERSON>). When I
met him, I had complete trust in him.
   ``But you just don't know. It might get made and never
distributed. That was my fear. I thought I would have something on
tape to show casting directors what I was capable of. I knew that I
finally had a role that I could do very well.
   ``I had confidence in myself as far as the role. I didn't think
that anybody knew her as well as I knew her. It touched me in a
very deep place.''
   She feared that people might be narrow-minded about the film's
explicit talk. Not until ``sex, lies'' won first prize at the <LOCATION>Park
City</LOCATION> film festival did she think that it might be distributed after
all. Then it won big at <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION>, and she thought, ``Well, it really
will get distributed!''
   MacDowell lives with her husband, <PERSON>Paul Qualley</PERSON>, and their two
children in a farmhouse outside <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>. ``I wanted to move
further into the country and live on a farm,'' she said, ``but this
career has sort of taken over my life. This year I lived in
<LOCATION>Budapest</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. I did three films.
   ``I don't think I plan to do three films next year. After so
many years of wanting to do good work, to all of a sudden have the
opportunity to work on three such interesting and different
projects, it was too tempting to pass up. I hope I don't do that
again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910110-0105
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910110-0105.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Film: Weir's Slight but Sweet Love Story
   ----
   By Julie Salamon
</HL>
<DATE>
01/10/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   The director Peter Weir has built a distinguished career
making intelligent, romantic films that enable audiences to
feel both entertained and enlightened. Though he is
Australian, films like "The Year of Living Dangerously,"
"Witness" and, certainly, "Dead Poets Society," fit within a
Hollywood tradition of entertainment as teaching tool.
   The lessons of Mr. Weir's latest film, "Green Card," are
very slight, and that lightness turns out to be the picture's
virtue. Little more than air -- and Gerard Depardieu, and the
pretty lighting on Andie MacDowell's gorgeous face -- hold
this romantic comedy together. You won't find yourself
discussing this bit of ephemera for hours, or even minutes
once it's over.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But "Green Card" is quite pleasant to watch mainly because
<PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> hasn't disturbed its simple virtues with undue
portent. Sometimes a plate of spaghetti with a simple tomato
sauce is just the thing, and this is the movie equivalent of
that.
   Or perhaps I should say it's the equivalent of a simple
hamburger. <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> -- who wrote and produced as well as
directed the film -- takes great delight in vegetarian
bashing. <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> plays a rough sensualist who is
horrified by the sanctimonious people the woman he loves
associates with. "Get out vegetarian]" he screams at her
boyfriend. "You . . . cucumber." The burly French actor's
earthy charms are so convincing that he makes the idea of a
meal without red meat and red wine seem sinful.
   <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> plays <PERSON>George Faure</PERSON>, a Frenchman who wants to
emigrate to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> but who doesn't have legal immigrant
status. A friend urges him to cut through the red tape by
marrying a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizen. The friend just happens to have a
woman friend who also needs a quickie marriage. She's a
horticulturist who's found an apartment with a greenhouse --
in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>; however, the co-op board wants a married couple
in the place. Though they plan to separate immediately
following their marriage, suspicious immigration officials
force them to spend time together so they can prove they are
really married.
   <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> has filmed <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> with the friendly warmth of
the outsider who's been charmed rather than dismayed by what
you might call the city's energy. This isn't the knowing
vision of <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>, who romanticizes <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> with the
tenderness of a lover who has never lost his sense of that
initial enchantment. <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> isn't particularly
familiar; it's just a pretty urban backdrop.
   Indeed, this isn't a picture for those who find prettiness
annoying. The first image of <PERSON>Ms. MacDowell</PERSON> shows a pretty
woman sniffing a rose. Many of the shots in the picture
seemed to have been staged simply for the purpose of creating
a tableau centering on the actress's face. Her vivid
portrayal of the repressed housewife in "sex, lies and
videotape" made a lot of people forget that she tended to
ruin her performances when she opened her mouth. In this film
her acting is once again dodgy; she frequently conveys more
with her complexion than with her characterization. Her
complexion, however, is charming.
   <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON>, on the other hand, proves here that he is a
great actor in at least two languages. Because he has become
so identified as the contemporary French actor, it was
difficult to imagine what it would be like to hear him
speaking English. Would the nuance of his performance be
diluted by the fact that he was forced to carry on in
English? Not at all. In fact, <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> frequently seems
more at ease handling points of irony than <PERSON>Ms. MacDowell</PERSON>
does, and she's speaking her own language.
   Except for a small part in an obscure movie years ago, <PERSON>Mr.
Depardieu</PERSON> has never before acted in an English-language
picture. I suspect this won't be his last.
   ---
   <PERSON>Penelope Ann Miller</PERSON> is emerging as one of the freshest and
most engaging young actresses working today. At the moment
she is starring in "Awakenings" and in "Kindergarten Cop."
Her appeal is so strong that she has inspired <PERSON>Arnold
Schwarzenegger</PERSON> to appear sincere in a love scene.
   <PERSON>Mr. Schwarzenegger</PERSON> is otherwise predictable in
"Kindergarten Cop," and that is meant as a compliment. He
plays an undercover policeman who must teach kindergarten for
a while in order to catch a vicious killer. Though the film
never quite lives up to the joke of its concept -- big man
overwhelmed by small children -- it makes for an amiable
backdrop to a box of popcorn. Unfortunately, the film makers
have tacked on an ending sequence whose violence seems too
graphic for small children who would otherwise enjoy the
picture.
   Perhaps parents could use the tactic my friend <PERSON>Sara</PERSON>'s mom
came up with at "Old Yeller" many years ago. She had taken a
bunch of kids to the movies to celebrate <PERSON>Sara</PERSON>'s birthday. But
when she realized the picture was unspooling inexorably
toward the dog's death, she told the children the picture was
over and herded them out of the theater. For years <PERSON>Sara</PERSON> was
convinced "Old Yeller" had a happy ending and would have been
content to believe that forever.
   ---
   VIDEO TIP: When I praised <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> for his
performance in the film "Cyrano de Bergerac," a number of
readers chastised me later for not mentioning the <DATE>1950</DATE>
version of the film, starring <PERSON>Jose Ferrer</PERSON>, which is also
available on video. Fans of another contemporary film,
"Dances With Wolves," might like to compare that overlong
<PERSON>Kevin Costner</PERSON> buffalo opera with a classic film of a similar
story, "Broken Arrow." It stars <PERSON>James Stewart</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jeff
Chandler</PERSON>, and it offers many glimpses of Debra Paget in her
toothsome prime.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06010200 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06010200 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: (Gerard Depardieu) (color); PHOTO: Gerard Depardieu and
Andie MacDowell play a married couple dodging immigration laws in the upcoming
movie 'Green Card.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FRANCE; MOVIE; CELEBRITY; MAN; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  JUST as European audiences once thought of Hollywood action pictures as
synonymous with Steve McQueen and Charles Bronson, Americans have come to
associate quality French films with the name Gerard Depardieu. Just roll it
off your tongue -- JAY-rard DE-par-dew -- and you feel as if you're speaking
French.;    Do a quick scroll of the great French films of the last 15 years
-- "Get Out Your Handkerchiefs," "The Return of Martin Guerre," "Danton" and
"Jean de Florette," among them -- and you're bound to come up with a Depardieu
vehicle or two. Since making his screen debut in 1965 in a short and an
unfinished adaptation of "Christmas Carol" by Agnes Varda, the actor has
appeared in, by his own estimation, "almost 80 films." And he's only 42! Not
even the old-time Hollywood greats -- the Cagneys and the Bogarts -- could
boast of such filmography.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE THINKING WOMAN'S SEX SYMBOL
FRANCE'S BURLY GERARD DEPARDIEU POISED FOR
STATESIDE STARDOM  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Depardieu -- the very personification of the bearish bohemian -- obviously
likes to work. And over the years he has sought out and been sought out by his
country's best  filmmakers, including <PERSON>Claude Berri</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alan Resnais</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bertrand
Blier</PERSON> and the late <PERSON>Francois Truffaut</PERSON>, for whom he made "The Last Metro" and
"The Woman Next Door.";    And yet, for all his notoriety, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> has
remained a hero of the art-house cognoscenti. <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s burly man of the street
-- part poet, part stevedore -- hasn't caught on with Mr. and Mrs. Average
Filmgoer.;    But that could change in '91.;    <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> is now appearing in
the thinking man's swashbuckler, "Cyrano de Bergerac," and is making his
Hollywood debut in a robust romantic comedy called "Green Card" (arriving
locally <DATE>Friday</DATE>). As Cyrano, he brings his energy and signature bullheadedness
to a whole new audience. There is even talk of an Oscar nomination. As <PERSON>George
Faure</PERSON>, the French composer in "Green Card" who marries a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> botanist to
get around immigration laws, he gets to speak broken English and work his
mulish charm on co-star <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> (of "sex, lies &amp; videotape").;    <PERSON>Then
Depardieu</PERSON> is set to return in early <DATE>February</DATE> in the restored, five-hour
version of "1900," directed by <PERSON>Bernardo Bertolucci</PERSON> and first released in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
Depardieu co-starred opposite <PERSON>Robert De Niro</PERSON>, <PERSON>Donald Sutherland</PERSON> and <PERSON>Burt
Lancaster</PERSON>. (The epic celebration of Italian socialism, to be rated NC-17 in
its new form, begins a limited run at <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s Castro Theater <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE>.);
   Liked film's simplicity;  With an occasional assist from a young
translator, the actor talked recently about his unusual work methods and the
decision to at long last "go Hollywood." He was drawn to "Green Card" because
of its simplicity and because it had been tailor-designed for him (by
director-writer <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> of "Dead Poets Society"). "It's a beautiful
situation," he began, reaching for another pungent Gitane. "I like the idea of
a man who goes to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and has to marry a woman to stay in the country. It
is simple, uncomplicated. Also, I love <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON>. I was very impressed that
this man who didn't know me wrote a script for me on the other side of the
planet.";    Actually, <PERSON>Australian Weir</PERSON> rewrote the script with <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in
mind. The romantic comedy had been gathering dust in a bottom drawer for
several years. It wasn't until <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> saw <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in "Danton" and <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>'s wife
suggested a few changes (the protagonist was originally a British film buff in
<LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>) that the project was resurrected. The character may be named <PERSON>George
Faure</PERSON>, but he's really <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>, right down to the provincial upbringing, the
dagger tattoo on his right forearm, the early scrapes with gendarmes and time
in reform school.;    The shady past <PERSON>George</PERSON> describes to <PERSON>McDowell</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Bronte</LOCATION> is
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s past.;    "I got this when I was 12 years old," the actor said,
pulling up his sleeve to reveal the dagger tattoo. "I wanted to be strong,
tough. I was angry about everything. All of my tattoos mean something. The
knife tattoo means that you were reported by someone and have sworn to have
revenge.";    Weighty issue;  There are even references to <ORGANIZATION>Depardieu</ORGANIZATION>'s
considerable waistline. In the movie, a joke is made of <ORGANIZATION>George</ORGANIZATION>'s refusal to
own up to his weight. Depardieu isn't as vain. "I am now 200 pounds. I weighed
250 during 'Cyrano.' I had trouble moving in the sword fights. It's the wine.
The wine opens your appetite. Now I eat steamed vegetables and a little
chicken.";    "Originally, the concept for '<ORGANIZATION>Green Card</ORGANIZATION>' didn't work," <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>
explained later. "It was neither funny nor romantic, but labored, contrived.
When I changed the setting to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and made the hero a Frenchman, it
started to come together. I constructed <PERSON>George</PERSON> to reflect the qualities I've
loved most in <LOCATION>Gerard</LOCATION>'s work -- the humor, the roughness, the physicality. It
was purely and simply written for <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON>.";    Six weeks later <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> had a
script but doubted that <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> would be attainable. "If he hadn't made a
picture in English at age 40, I reasoned, he either didn't want to or he
didn't speak English well enough.";    Not fluent in English;  <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> discussed
the project with <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> by phone, then sent him the script, which was
translated and recorded on an audio cassette. They talked again.;    "I put
the phone down with clammy hands," the director recalled. "His English was
pretty bad and my French wasn't much better. But at least we could
communicate. He said he liked the fact that the character was a foreigner, not
an American, and that he would only have to speak enough English to seesaw
thorough the language.";    So they met in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and "sealed the deal . . . We
got on immediately," said Weir.;    Unfortunately, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s legendary
workload got in the way. Besides the upcoming "Cyrano," he had two other
feature commitments. He wouldn't be free for another 18 months. "It was a
major disappointment," <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> recalled. "I had no option but to say, 'I'll
wait.' ";    <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> went on to "Dead Poets Society" and further acclaim.
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> did <PERSON>Blier</PERSON>'s "Thanks, Life," <PERSON>Berri</PERSON>'s "Uranus" (about the French
resistance in the last days of World War II) and "Cyrano," which was filmed in
four months in <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and earned <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> the best actor award at last
year's <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> festival. "Cyrano," at <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>, is the most expensive French
production to date. Typically, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> was involved years before the cameras
started rolling.;    That's how he prefers it. He sees himself as packager and
creative producer as well as star.;    "I'm not just an actor," he said. "The
acting is the last part I have to do. It's a piece of cake. More exciting for
me is the development. I propose an idea and give writers the money to develop
it. Sometimes I work for years with a writer and nothing happens. I
commissioned a writer to give me a treatment of <LOCATION>Balzac</LOCATION>'s 'Colonel Chabert.' He
went away for a year and returned with a treatment we didn't use.";   
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> said he works so much because "I am -- how do you say? -- hungry at
life. I eat the life.";    And it's this near-feverish zest that comes through
in "Cyrano" and "Green Card." Depardieu's specific appeal can be chalked up to
one element -- "unpredictability, both in life and on screen," said <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>.
"That's his greatest quality. You're never certain what he might do next. . .
. There are some very funny things that aren't in the film because they tilted
the character toward the buffoonish. There was a whole thing in the shower
with <PERSON>Bronte</PERSON>'s potted plants that was hysterical.";    <ORGANIZATION>Depardieu</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest
laugh-getter -- wherein he literally pounds out an impromptu composition on a
grand piano -- did make it to the final cut. It's the actor at his most
roguish and resourceful.;    In <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>'s mind, the rather light and predictable
"Green Card" could only have worked with two actors -- <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> or the
middle-aged <PERSON>Spencer Tracy</PERSON>. "But Tracy is dead and I don't know if he could
have mastered the accent.";    <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> shrugs off <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s awe over his
immense body of work. He points to <LOCATION>Gene Hackman</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nick Nolte</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael Caine</PERSON>
as other actors who keep busy. "I don't think (the amount of work) is so
amazing," he went on. "Except for 'Cyrano' and 'Jean de Florette,' I make
small movies. It's not the same way Americans make movies. When they accept
movies they have beaucoup travail -- they work much more.";    <ORGANIZATION>Depardieu</ORGANIZATION>
doesn't have time to ponder such things. He must return to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> to oversee
production on a farce called "Mon Pere." He plays a single father on vacation
with his precocious teen-age daughter. "It's a little comedy, but a good one .
. . a very good concept. Everyone thinks my 14-year-old daughter is my
lover.";    <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> thinks he's a long shot for an Oscar nomination this
year. He does note, however, that <PERSON>Jose Ferrer</PERSON> won in <DATE>1950</DATE> for his portrayal of
<ORGANIZATION>Cyrano de Bergerac</ORGANIZATION> and that version was a lot less popular than the new French
adaptation. "That was very stagy, claustrophobic . . . the audience was not
into classics then. In mine, I didn't wear the long, exaggerated nose because
I didn't want to be a caricature. Ours is closer to a romantic epic, like
Hollywood makes.";    <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> is more optimistic about <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s chances. "I
think he'll be nominated for 'Cyrano,' but '<ORGANIZATION>Green Card</ORGANIZATION>' will keep the
spotlight on him. Each movie will stimulate the other. 'Cyrano' is the grander
work; it's an Academy film.";    Even if the <ORGANIZATION>Academy</ORGANIZATION> does smile on the
foreigner (no actor in a foreign-language film has ever won in the best-actor
category), don't expect him to file for a green card work permit. "Maybe if I
were more fluent in English. For now I think I will just visit when I see
something I really want to do."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENN LOVELL, Mercury News Film Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Hollywood  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910110  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,671  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, January 10, 1991
00010200,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901221-0123
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901221-0123.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Movies:
   Disney's Star Is Foreign to U.S. Audiences
   ----
   By Richard Turner
</HL>
<DATE>
12/21/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   DIS
</CO>
<IN>
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
</IN>
<LP>
   HOLLYWOOD -- What Pele was to soccer, Gerard Depardieu is
to movies. In much of the world, particularly in Western
Europe, he is acclaimed as the greatest living screen actor,
a French Brando, a legend.
   But in the U.S., people ask "Who?"
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Moreover, as <ORGANIZATION>Walt Disney Co.</ORGANIZATION> film executives found when
testing brief TV ads with audiences, many Americans' initial
impression of the shaggy, beefy, big-nosed actor was that he
was a "fat slob."
   The female lead in the coming film "Green Card" has the
same reaction, but after a while she falls madly in love.
Disney's vaunted marketing machine must ensure that audiences
do the same.
   But first, they have to get people to show up. The main
thing people ask when they hear that a film is a love story
is "Who's in it?" But the movie's co-star, <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> of
"sex, lies, and videotape," is also relatively unknown.
   The subject matter of this small-scale romantic comedy
won't help sell it either, even if the idea is easy to sum up
on a poster: "The story of two people who got married, met,
and then fell in love." Hollywood generally loves concepts
that can be explained in a sentence: Two strangers, a scruffy
Frenchman and a slightly priggish American horticulturist,
get married, he to gain residency status, she to get an
apartment she covets. But however packageable the idea seems,
it doesn't hold any special allure.
   "It's outside most people's experience," concedes <PERSON>Peter
Weir</PERSON>, who wrote, produced and directed "Green Card."
   The marketing difficulties are especially frustrating
because Disney executives are proud of the film. <ORGANIZATION>Disney
Studios</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Jeffrey Katzenberg</PERSON> has taken it as a
personal challenge to successfully open the movie, which some
<ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> wags are calling "`Pretty Woman' for people who
think." The poster for "Green Card" bears more than a passing
resemblance to the one used for "Pretty Woman," <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s
biggest hit ever.
   Christmas is a crowded, competitive time, especially for
fragile movies, but "Green Card" is being released <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to
qualify it for <ORGANIZATION>Academy Award</ORGANIZATION> consideration. Most reviews
aren't out yet, but they're likely to be generally favorable.
Rolling Stone called it "captivating" but with "all the heft
of a potato chip." <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON>, the Australian director who made
"The Year of Living Dangerously" and "Witness," is highly
regarded. Disney gets prestige points no matter what, but a
success would help redeem a winter season when <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s
"Three Men and a Little Lady" and "Rescuers Down Under" were
snowed under by <ORGANIZATION>Fox</ORGANIZATION>'s "Home Alone."
   It would surpass <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> executives' wildest dreams if the
film won the kind of audience attracted by other urban fare
like "Moonstruck" and "When Harry Met Sally." But the
marketing of the film is a slow and arduous process; it's
definitely not just a matter of buying the right TV time. <PERSON>Mr.
Katzenberg</PERSON> has criss-crossed the country to be the host at
upscale screenings followed by receptions at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s 21
Club, <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Morton</PERSON>'s and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles County</LOCATION> Museum
of Art.
   This is an effort to reach "opinionmakers," says <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>
marketing chief <PERSON>Robert Levin</PERSON>. Through word-of-mouth, he hopes
the film will do well in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, then build
gradually as it goes to a still-selective 100 screens Jan 11.
If any kind of buzz continues and if other Christmas movies
wither, <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> hopes theater owners will make room for "Green
Card" on more and more screens.
   Disney is walking a tightrope. It needs <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON>'s
tiny art-house following to help launch the picture, but if
the film is perceived as too arty, it could turn off wider
segments of the audience.
   "When someone is confronted with a piece of material, they
can say, `I get it, but I think you have to be smart,'" says
<PERSON>Mr. Levin</PERSON>. "They're afraid that they're going to wind up in
the audience and not get the joke when everyone else does."
   So the TV spots and theatrical trailer rather mundanely
explain the idea and show a little romance and comedy. <PERSON>Mr.
Levin</PERSON> says the only reason the trailer even mentions that <PERSON>Mr.
Depardieu</PERSON> is "the most acclaimed actor in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>" is so the
handful of people who know this will be reassured that <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>
is aware of it. "The rest of the people will say, `Big
deal.'"
   Disney hasn't been too proud to try some Hollywood
gimmicks, but they, too, have been problematic. The marketing
people placed classified ads seeking couples who got married
so one partner could get a green card to stay in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>,
thinking they would be fodder for talk shows that would also
mention the film. "But it appears only to have generated the
interest of the <ORGANIZATION>INS</ORGANIZATION>," says <PERSON>Mr. Levin</PERSON>. As in the film, the
<ORGANIZATION>Immigration and Naturalization Service</ORGANIZATION> doesn't care if the
couple are in love and want to live happily ever after; the
initial act is still fraud.
   <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> thought up the movie's premise three years ago
after returning to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to take a year off, licking his
wounds from the disappointing opening of "The Mosquito
Coast." He wound up writing the script with <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> in
mind, even though he had never met him and didn't know
whether <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> could speak English. (He can, sort of.)
   Disney has an aggressively hands-on attitude about its
films and generally steers clear of renowned directors for
this reason, but <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Katzenberg</PERSON>, who did "Dead
Poets Society" together, get along well. Although <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON>
says <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> shows "excessive zeal" about enforcing budgetary
constraints and can be "bureaucratic," he was left alone on
"Green Card" because the <MONEY>$12 million</MONEY> film was independently
produced. <PERSON>Mr. Depardieu</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> accepted reduced fees to
meet the budget, nothing new for the French actor who once
starred in a movie for a struggling director in return for a
bottle of wine. (He did stipulate that it be a very good
bottle.)
   Disney executives seemed resigned to allowing <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> to
make the film his way. They couldn't get him to cast a bigger
name than <PERSON>Ms. MacDowell</PERSON> or to broaden the comedy elements.
They didn't push too hard about <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON>'s refusal to give
the film a "Pretty Woman" fairy-tale ending. They would just
say, "Don't you realize that if you recut this, you could buy
a new house?" <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> recalls.
   But now <PERSON>Mr. Weir</PERSON> needs <ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION> to get people into theaters,
and the director sees some irony in this. The movie industry,
he says, "has trained audiences to respond to a siren song:
`Come and get it, you'll like it,' and it's turned into a
Frankenstein monster. They release all these dumb movies, and
then when they have one they like -- one everybody likes,
that's simple and honest -- it turns out to be difficult to
sell."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06014097 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06014097 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Director Peter Weir is known for giving credit to crew members and actors for
their contributions to his films. But he's bemused by the attention he gets
for just being sensible.;    "I don't know why everybody makes such a big deal
out of my generosity," the Australian director told reporters in L.A. "If
you're the conductor of the orchestra and somebody can twiddle the flute
better than you, you pay them.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DIRECTOR'S GENEROSITY IS JUST COMMON SENSE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  People.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "It doesn't bother me who gets the credit as long as it helps the finished
movie.";    In "Dead Poet's Society," a hit for <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>, he used a few lines of
poetry written on the spot by <PERSON>Robin Williams</PERSON> for a crucial scene.;    On
<PERSON>Weir</PERSON>'s newest film, "Green Card," starring <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Andie
MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>, assistant cameraman <PERSON>Eric Swanek</PERSON> came up with the idea of shooting
through a door's peephole to show one character's distorted view of another.; 
  The director said he also relied heavily on the French film star <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>
to flesh out his character, a French national who needs a green card to remain
in the <LOCATION>United States.</LOCATION>;    "We sat down and he told me actual stories of his
life, as well as hypothesizing on what might have been if he hadn't gone into
acting."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Compiled from Mercury News wire services.  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910114  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  207  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, January 14, 1991
00014097,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06021096 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06021096 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  "No matter how hopeless the situation, you can't give up," says composer Harry
Stewart, 27, until recently a member of New York City's homeless community.;  
 Stewart was in the right place -- a New York City subway station -- at the
right time . . . when director Peter Weir was looking for street musicians to
provide music for his movie, "Green Card."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HE TOOK A SUBWAY TO FIND AN OSCAR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  People.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Stewart got the job -- and his life changed.;    Not only was he paid well
for composing and performing his spirited song, "Eyes on the Prize" -- which
<PERSON>Touchstone</PERSON> has submitted for Oscar consideration -- <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> is cleaning up
some bad habits in a <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> rehab center.;    The "beautiful, haunting"
voices that <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> says he heard in the subway were those of <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> and his
<ORGANIZATION>Emmaus The Group</ORGANIZATION> singers, which <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> had organized while living at <LOCATION>Harlem</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Emmaus House</ORGANIZATION> for the homeless.;    After <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> inquired about the film's
story line -- a man and woman pretend to be married for individual reasons,
then fall in love -- he composed the song especially for the film. Then he
surprised <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> with it when the group auditioned in <LOCATION>Central Park.</LOCATION>;    As soon
as he heard it, <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> says, he knew he wanted it -- as a parable for the
seemingly insurmountable obstacles faced by the film's two main characters,
played by <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell.</ORGANIZATION>;    "The song throws the
message to the audience to keep your eyes on the prize," <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> says. "There's a
lot of hopelessness in the world. . . . Yes, it's just a movie, but it gives
you hope.";    Before his lucky break, <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> says, he was "throwing his
faith away," a lyric from another of his songs. "That's what I was doing. I
became homeless and I stayed that way because of an addiction to drugs.";   
"I got the inspiration from seeing the homeless. If I encourage one person who
is homeless, then I've done something," he added.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Compiled from Mercury News wire services.  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910121  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  317  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday January 21, 1991
00021096,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901231-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-31-90 1329EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--FilmReview Adv00   12-31 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Film Review, Adv00,1112</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv00</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Anytime</NOTE>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>At the Movies: `The Long Walk Home'; `Green Card'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Films are currently in limited release nationwide, and will
open in more theaters.</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ``The Long Walk Home'' (New Visions Pictures)
   
   Like ``<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> Burning'' in <DATE>1988</DATE>, ``The Long Walk Home'' has
been assailed by some black leaders as being a distortion of the
struggle for civil rights in the South. Both films are told from
the white point of view, though ``The Long Walk Home'' appears to
offer more balance between the races.
   Taken on its artistic merits alone, ``The Long Walk Home'' is an
earnest, often affecting, curiously anticlimactic film. Its major
assets are two fully realized performances by accomplished
actresses, <PERSON>Sissy Spacek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Whoopi Goldberg</PERSON>.
   The setting of <PERSON>John Cork</PERSON>'s script is <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1955</DATE>,
when municipal buses were segregated and blacks were forced to sit
in the back. A seamstress named <PERSON>Rosa Parks</PERSON> decided one day that she
was too tired and took a seat at the front of the bus. She was
arrested, and <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> blacks staged a one-day boycott that grew
into a movement led by <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Buses were integrated
a year later following a federal court order.
   In ``The Long Walk Home,'' nothing has changed in the social
structure of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> since the institution of <PERSON>Jim Crow</PERSON> laws
following the Civil War and Reconstruction.
   The back-of-the-bus mentality prevails among the city's white
leaders, and the blacks are expected to know their place. The
decades of degradation well up, and blacks call a strike on the
municipal bus system, a prime source of revenue.
   Enter two reluctant heroines.
   <PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> (Spacek) is a well-to-do matron who accedes to
the wishes of her good ol' boy husband (<PERSON>Dwight Schultz</PERSON>). Odessa
<PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> (<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>) is her dutiful domestic, a woman who has never
challenged the social system.
   But <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> believes the bus strike is the right thing to do. She
is willing to walk the nine long miles to and from work. <PERSON>Mrs.
Thompson</PERSON> sympathizes with <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> and is increasingly appalled by
how her husband is influenced by his racist brother (<PERSON>Dylan Baker</PERSON>).
   The strike escalates into violence, and <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s house is bombed.
<PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> decides to drive <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> to work. Her act brings a
climax in her marriage and in the community.
   Inexpensively but caringly produced by <PERSON>Howard W. Koch Jr.</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Dave Bell</PERSON>, ``The Long Walk Home'' carries an emotional impact.
Spacek deftly portrays the ethical dilemma of Southern wife and
mother. In her most restrained performance, <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> again
impresses as one of the best actresses around. The other
performances are first-rate, especially <PERSON>Schultz</PERSON> as the husband who
is incensed to find his values questioned.
   <PERSON>Richard Pearce</PERSON> directs with a firm touch on the personal scenes,
which could have been overwrought. Only in the climax does he
stumble, reducing the issues to a simplistic level and mishandling
crowd scenes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Miramax Films</ORGANIZATION> release of a New Visions Picture is rated PG
for language and intensity. Running time: 97 minutes.
   By <PERSON>Bob Thomas</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
   ---
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   ``The Long Walk Home'' (New Visions Pictures)
   
   Like ``<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> Burning'' in <DATE>1988</DATE>, ``The Long Walk Home'' has
been assailed by some black leaders as being a distortion of the
struggle for civil rights in the South. Both films are told from
the white point of view, though ``The Long Walk Home'' appears to
offer more balance between the races.
   Taken on its artistic merits alone, ``The Long Walk Home'' is an
earnest, often affecting, curiously anticlimactic film. Its major
assets are two fully realized performances by accomplished
actresses, <PERSON>Sissy Spacek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Whoopi Goldberg</PERSON>.
   The setting of <PERSON>John Cork</PERSON>'s script is <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1955</DATE>,
when municipal buses were segregated and blacks were forced to sit
in the back. A seamstress named <PERSON>Rosa Parks</PERSON> decided one day that she
was too tired and took a seat at the front of the bus. She was
arrested, and <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> blacks staged a one-day boycott that grew
into a movement led by <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Buses were integrated
a year later following a federal court order.
   In ``The Long Walk Home,'' nothing has changed in the social
structure of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> since the institution of <PERSON>Jim Crow</PERSON> laws
following the Civil War and Reconstruction.
   The back-of-the-bus mentality prevails among the city's white
leaders, and the blacks are expected to know their place. The
decades of degradation well up, and blacks call a strike on the
municipal bus system, a prime source of revenue.
   Enter two reluctant heroines.
   <PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> (Spacek) is a well-to-do matron who accedes to
the wishes of her good ol' boy husband (<PERSON>Dwight Schultz</PERSON>). Odessa
<PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> (<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>) is her dutiful domestic, a woman who has never
challenged the social system.
   But <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> believes the bus strike is the right thing to do. She
is willing to walk the nine long miles to and from work. <PERSON>Mrs.
Thompson</PERSON> sympathizes with <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> and is increasingly appalled by
how her husband is influenced by his racist brother (<PERSON>Dylan Baker</PERSON>).
   The strike escalates into violence, and <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s house is bombed.
<PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> decides to drive <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> to work. Her act brings a
climax in her marriage and in the community.
   Inexpensively but caringly produced by <PERSON>Howard W. Koch Jr.</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Dave Bell</PERSON>, ``The Long Walk Home'' carries an emotional impact.
Spacek deftly portrays the ethical dilemma of Southern wife and
mother. In her most restrained performance, <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> again
impresses as one of the best actresses around. The other
performances are first-rate, especially <PERSON>Schultz</PERSON> as the husband who
is incensed to find his values questioned.
   <PERSON>Richard Pearce</PERSON> directs with a firm touch on the personal scenes,
which could have been overwrought. Only in the climax does he
stumble, reducing the issues to a simplistic level and mishandling
crowd scenes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Miramax Films</ORGANIZATION> release of a New Visions Picture is rated PG
for language and intensity. Running time: 97 minutes.
   By <PERSON>Bob Thomas</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
   ---
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   ``The Long Walk Home'' (New Visions Pictures)
   
   Like ``<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> Burning'' in <DATE>1988</DATE>, ``The Long Walk Home'' has
been assailed by some black leaders as being a distortion of the
struggle for civil rights in the South. Both films are told from
the white point of view, though ``The Long Walk Home'' appears to
offer more balance between the races.
   Taken on its artistic merits alone, ``The Long Walk Home'' is an
earnest, often affecting, curiously anticlimactic film. Its major
assets are two fully realized performances by accomplished
actresses, <PERSON>Sissy Spacek</PERSON> and <PERSON>Whoopi Goldberg</PERSON>.
   The setting of <PERSON>John Cork</PERSON>'s script is <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1955</DATE>,
when municipal buses were segregated and blacks were forced to sit
in the back. A seamstress named <PERSON>Rosa Parks</PERSON> decided one day that she
was too tired and took a seat at the front of the bus. She was
arrested, and <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> blacks staged a one-day boycott that grew
into a movement led by <ORGANIZATION>Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. Buses were integrated
a year later following a federal court order.
   In ``The Long Walk Home,'' nothing has changed in the social
structure of <LOCATION>Montgomery</LOCATION> since the institution of <PERSON>Jim Crow</PERSON> laws
following the Civil War and Reconstruction.
   The back-of-the-bus mentality prevails among the city's white
leaders, and the blacks are expected to know their place. The
decades of degradation well up, and blacks call a strike on the
municipal bus system, a prime source of revenue.
   Enter two reluctant heroines.
   <PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> (Spacek) is a well-to-do matron who accedes to
the wishes of her good ol' boy husband (<PERSON>Dwight Schultz</PERSON>). Odessa
<PERSON>Cotter</PERSON> (<PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON>) is her dutiful domestic, a woman who has never
challenged the social system.
   But <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> believes the bus strike is the right thing to do. She
is willing to walk the nine long miles to and from work. <PERSON>Mrs.
Thompson</PERSON> sympathizes with <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> and is increasingly appalled by
how her husband is influenced by his racist brother (<PERSON>Dylan Baker</PERSON>).
   The strike escalates into violence, and <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s house is bombed.
<PERSON>Miriam Thompson</PERSON> decides to drive <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION> to work. Her act brings a
climax in her marriage and in the community.
   Inexpensively but caringly produced by <PERSON>Howard W. Koch Jr.</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Dave Bell</PERSON>, ``The Long Walk Home'' carries an emotional impact.
Spacek deftly portrays the ethical dilemma of Southern wife and
mother. In her most restrained performance, <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> again
impresses as one of the best actresses around. The other
performances are first-rate, especially <PERSON>Schultz</PERSON> as the husband who
is incensed to find his values questioned.
   <PERSON>Richard Pearce</PERSON> directs with a firm touch on the personal scenes,
which could have been overwrought. Only in the climax does he
stumble, reducing the issues to a simplistic level and mishandling
crowd scenes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Miramax Films</ORGANIZATION> release of a New Visions Picture is rated PG
for language and intensity. Running time: 97 minutes.
   By <PERSON>Bob Thomas</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press Writer</ORGANIZATION>.
   ---
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121790-0091 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 323631 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 17, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
GERARD DEPARDIEU 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1755 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FRANCE'S WORKING-CLASS HERO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PATRICK GOLDSTEIN, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It seems like only yesterday that <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> was the enfant terrible of 
French film, startling filmgoers with his portrayal of an amoral delinquent in 
"Going Places," <PERSON>Bertrand Blier</PERSON>'s outrageous <DATE>1974</DATE> sex comedy. 
</P>
<P>
Nibbling on pasta at a cozy Hollywood eatery, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> is grumpily bemoaning 
the new generation of lazy, empty-headed French actors. "The young French 
actors are total egomaniacs," he growls in halting English. "These acting 
schools they go to -- all they do is turn them inward, not outward." 
</P>
<P>
Searching for an appropriately scathing image, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> abruptly switches to 
his native tongue. "They've become so self-absorbed," he says in torrid French 
through an interpreter. "In my time, we read the classics. Moliere. 
Shakespeare. Anything we could get our hands on. 
</P>
<P>
"Now, if you ask a French actor to recite from <LOCATION>Racine</LOCATION>, they wouldn't know what 
to do. All they know is Stanislavsky. When I started out 20 years ago, the 
great actors all had a strong theater background. But the young actors today 
only think about film." 
</P>
<P>
He frowns, running a meaty hand through his long mane of hair. "Now our actors 
do one or two movies and -- voila -- they're stars. They want everything 
without doing anything. 
</P>
<P>
"I get letters all the time from parents saying, 'My son loves the acting 
profession.' " 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu flashes a triumphant smile. "So I reply, 'That's wonderful, but does 
the acting craft love him?' " 
</P>
<P>
It's no secret that the camera loves <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>. At 41, he is the working-class 
hero of French cinema, as honored and beloved as <PERSON>Jean Gabin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michel Simon</PERSON>, <PERSON>Yves 
Montand</PERSON> or any other titans of past eras. It's perhaps a sign of his screen 
magnetism that when <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> needed a burst of inspiration to finish his 
script for "Green Card," he simply put a photo of <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> on display at his 
desk as he wrote. 
</P>
<P>
Though <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> made his mark with <PERSON>Blier</PERSON>'s raffish satires, the bulky actor 
has played everything from a 16th-Century wanderer in "The Return of Martin 
Guerre" to a baffled modern-day husband in "Get Out Your Handkerchiefs." 
</P>
<P>
It's hard to imagine many actors who have ranged so far and wide in the cinema. 
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> was <PERSON>Danton</PERSON> in <PERSON>Andrzej Wajda</PERSON>'s compelling account of the French 
Revolution and <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON> in <PERSON>Bruno Nuytten</PERSON>'s "<PERSON>Camille Claudel</PERSON>." He also picked up 
best-actor prizes in such films as "The Last Metro" (his only movie with 
<PERSON>Francois Truffaut</PERSON>) and <PERSON>Maurice Pialat</PERSON>'s "Police." 
</P>
<P>
American audiences will soon be seeing <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in two of his most formidable 
challenges. He opens <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as the eloquent swordsman hero of "Cyrano de 
Bergerac," which won him the best-actor prize at the <ORGANIZATION>Cannes Film Festival</ORGANIZATION>. On 
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, he opens in "Green Card," <PERSON>Weir</PERSON>'s romantic comedy, which features 
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> in his first major English-language film as a Frenchman who engineers 
a marriage of convenience so he can move to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
As it turns out, language was just as much a barrier making "Cyrano" as it was 
in "Green Card." The film, adapted from <PERSON>Edmond Rostand</PERSON>'s classic play, was shot 
on location in both <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, using 2,000 actors and extras. Most of 
the extras were Hungarian. 
</P>
<P>
"That made it very difficult to coordinate everyone's movements during the big 
crowd scenes," he explains. "Since the extras didn't speak French, they didn't 
always know where I was going next. They all look very impressed by my 
speeches, but most of them didn't understand a word I was saying!" 
</P>
<P>
Since the film's dialogue is delivered in Alexandrine verse, which contains 12 
syllables in each line (English verse is commonly 10-syllable iambic 
pentameter), <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> found himself choreographing sweeping physical movements 
and sword play to fit the extended lines of verse. 
</P>
<P>
"We rehearsed the film like we would a play," says <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>, who spent an hour 
each day having his already ample nose enlarged for the part. "We all sat 
around a table for two weeks and practiced, so we could visualize how it would 
work." 
</P>
<P>
With 60 films to his credit in less than 20 years, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> is an actor who 
seems obsessed with keeping busy. A chunky man with a torso that looks like it 
could support a freeway overpass, he says he enjoys carousing at night -- but 
insists he's always ready for work every morning. 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu jokes that the only time he has free time is when he's making a 
movie. "I know it sounds strange, but I like a strict schedule. That's when I 
really feel free." 
</P>
<P>
He's certainly not enthusiastic about doing in-depth interviews to promote his 
films. Out with a reporter on a brief visit here, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> only allows an 
occasional glimpse of the playfulness he displays on movie sets. (He does joke 
about <PERSON>Warren Beatty</PERSON>'s legendary sexual exploits, but quickly adds that the jest 
was "in parentheses," apparently a rough translation for off-the-record.) 
</P>
<P>
He apologizes about missing a previous interview, saying he had been worn out 
from a long day of media encounters. "I was exhausted," he says. "And probably 
drunk too." 
</P>
<P>
This time around, accompanied by a pretty young girlfriend who was flying with 
him to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, he sticks to mineral water. "It's great for jet lag," he 
advises. 
</P>
<P>
Apparently peeved about a recent Interview feature that he says misquoted him 
as bad-mouthing <PERSON>Robert De Niro</PERSON> ("that's so untrue -- he is a hero to me!"), 
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> is all business. An hour into his interview, he becomes bored and 
restless, signaling an end to the chat by abruptly heading off to his 
limousine. 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu may find his publicity labors trying, but it was a series of 
interviews he did in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> several years ago that got him his part in 
"Green Card." 
</P>
<P>
"I'd been writing a romantic comedy about an Englishman who comes to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> 
and has to get a green card," explains <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> in a separate interview. "And 
when it wasn't going very well, my wife suggested that I use <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> as the 
model for the character. So, almost completely on a whim, I wrote the entire 
movie for him. 
</P>
<P>
"After I got started, <PERSON>Gerard</PERSON> came to <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> for a film festival. I thought of 
calling him up, but I was afraid he might say no. So instead, I took a picture 
of him that ran with an interview he gave in the local paper and kept it on my 
desk as I wrote." 
</P>
<P>
Too nervous to simply send <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s agent the completed script, <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> got on 
a plane, flew to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and spent a weekend with the actor at his country house. 
Weir says that the two men took long walks in the fields surrounding 
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s home, getting to know each other. The fact that <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> speaks French 
with as little confidence as <ORGANIZATION>Depardieu</ORGANIZATION> handles English was hardly an impediment 
once the creative juices began flowing. 
</P>
<P>
"We had a real rapport from the start," <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> says. "When we had trouble finding 
the right words to explain something, we simply pooled our two languages and 
made them one. We were never embarrassed to use whichever language expressed 
what we were trying to say." 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu prefers to work with strong-minded directors who can provide him with 
rich, provocative material. His favorite remains longtime collaborator <PERSON>Blier</PERSON>, 
with whom he has made four films, including "Going Places," "Menage" and "Too 
Beautiful for You." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> was born in a small town in central <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> that had a nearby <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air 
Force</ORGANIZATION> base. Fascinated by American culture, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> went to see rock 'n' roll 
movies, stole blue jeans from laundry lines and hung out at the local train 
station, perfecting his James Dean impression. 
</P>
<P>
"When I was young I loved <PERSON>James Dean</PERSON> and <PERSON>Marlon Brando</PERSON>," he recalls. "But I 
liked so many American stars -- <PERSON>Gary Cooper</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert Mitchum</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alan Ladd</PERSON>." He 
grins mischievously. "Even Victor Mature!" 
</P>
<P>
He insists he was extremely shy as a teen-ager. In fact, he believes his 
youthful timidity served him well as a performer. 
</P>
<P>
"There have been many great actors who stuttered in real life, but once they 
were on stage, they were completely relaxed," he says. "Certain kinds of 
obstacles can be assets, not just defects. There is something in the art of 
acting that transforms these difficulties into strengths and beauties." 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu taps his fork on the table. "If you are only macho, like some actors 
you see today, you can't ever be shy. But if you are shy, you can still act 
macho. I am not afraid to show my feminine side -- it's part of what makes me a 
man." 
</P>
<P>
He waves the fork in the air. "Our society wants us to be men with (guts). But 
the greatest thing you can have as a man is to have the (guts) -- and the 
vulnerability too." 
</P>
<P>
Talk of success and celebrity bores him. "Who knows what success is anyway," he 
says. "I'm not a sportsman, trying to better my record. I try to make good 
movies, regardless of whether they make money or not. A good flop is better 
than two ordinary hits anyway." 
</P>
<P>
But are actors held in high regard in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, at least when compared to other 
artists? "The most respected artists are writers," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> concludes after a 
thoughtful silence. "Then come the composers and musicians. After that, the 
film directors. The only actors who really matter are the ones who come along 
and release creative energy." 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu throws his hands into the air, mimicking a bomb blast. "They are the 
detonators. They inspire writers to release a blast of creative energy, which 
can make great movies." 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu is, of course, too modest to describe himself as such a detonator. 
But hearing him detail his relationship with <PERSON>Blier</PERSON>, it seems that he relishes 
just such a role. 
</P>
<P>
"We make movies together, the way Scorsese does with De Niro," he says. "I 
don't like to just take a script and say, 'OK, I'll do it.' Blier and I are so 
close that he doesn't even have to explain anymore. We know what each other is 
thinking." 
</P>
<P>
Could <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> ever reach such instinctive harmony with <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> (who hopes to do 
another film with him) or an American filmmaker? "I hope so," he says. "But 
when it comes to American movies, I have a long way to go, not just because I 
don't understand the language, but because I need to understand the spirit of 
the language. 
</P>
<P>
"But what makes film so beautiful is that it helps you discover so much about 
different cultures. If you see a Bunuel film, you learn about the Spanish and 
their problems with God. If you see a French film, you understand we have our 
problems with sex." 
</P>
<P>
And what has <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> discerned about Hollywood films and their vision of 
Americans? "Ah," he says with mock gravity. "You Americans. Your trouble is 
with guilt." 
</P>
<P>
Guilt but not sex? "Oh yes, sex too," he says with a laugh. "But only because 
it makes you feel so guilty!" 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Gerard Depardieu has made 60 films in less than 20 years. GARY FRIEDMAN 
/ Los Angeles Times; Photo, His two latest are "Cyrano de Bergerac," top, in 
which he woos Anne Brochet ... ; Photo, ... and "Green Card," above, in which 
he enters into a marriage of convenience with Andie MacDowell. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Interview 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ACTORS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032590-0038 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 194522 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 25, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Page 43; Calendar Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
308 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE MOVIE CHART: FILMS GOING INTO PRODUCTION: 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By David Pecchia 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Edward Scissorhands</PERSON> (Fox). Shooting in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>. "Batman" director <PERSON>Tim Burton</PERSON> 
takes on this cutting story of a young man (<PERSON>Johnny Depp</PERSON>) who has scissors in 
lieu of hands. 
</P>
<P>
The official press summary labels it "a fantastic tale shorn out of ordinary 
suburbia and dangerous creativity." Executive producer <PERSON>Richard Hashimoto</PERSON>. 
Producers <PERSON>Burton</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Denise Di Novi</ORGANIZATION>. Screenwriter <PERSON>Caroline Thompson</PERSON>. Also stars 
<PERSON>Dianne Wiest</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The Five Heartbeats (Five Heartbeats). Shooting in <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> "Hollywood Shuffle's" 
<PERSON>Robert Townsend</PERSON> again stars, directs and co-scripts. The film, titled after a 
fictitious '60s black singing group, chronicles the efforts of group manager 
<PERSON>Townsend</PERSON> and wife <PERSON>Diahann Carroll</PERSON> as they stick by the guys through both thick 
and thin. Producers <PERSON>Townsend</PERSON> and <PERSON>Loretha Jones</PERSON>. Screenwriters <PERSON>Townsend</PERSON> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Keenen Ivory Wayans</ORGANIZATION>. Distributor Fox. 
</P>
<P>
Green Card (<ORGANIZATION>Green Card</ORGANIZATION>). Shooting in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> produces, directs and 
writes this romantic comedy starring <PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> and "sex, lies, and 
videotape's" <ORGANIZATION>Andie MacDowell</ORGANIZATION>. Depardieu's first English language feature 
features him as a Frenchman who marries American botanist <ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> in order to 
obtain his green card. She's in it to be able to inhabit a rooftop apartment 
and grow things. Executive producer <PERSON>Edward S. Feldman</PERSON>. Also stars <PERSON>Bebe Neuwirth</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Gregg Edelman</PERSON>. Distributor Buena Vista (domestic). 
</P>
<P>
True Colors (<ORGANIZATION>Paramount</ORGANIZATION>). Shooting in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Herbert Ross</PERSON>, hot off "Steel 
Magnolias," directs <PERSON>John Cusack</PERSON> and <PERSON>James Spader</PERSON> in a tale of friendship, 
betrayal and revenge. Messrs. <PERSON>Cusack</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spader</PERSON> meet in law school and over 
course of a decade become involved with the same women which puts a strain on 
things. Producers <PERSON>Laurence Mark</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ross</PERSON>. Screenwriter "Working Girl's" <PERSON>Kevin 
Wade</PERSON>. Also stars <PERSON>Imogen Stubbs</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mandy Patinkin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard Widmark</PERSON>. Fall 
release. <PERSON>David Pecchia</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; List 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900131-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-31-90 0446EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DirectorsGuild     01-31 0457</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Directors Guild,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Directors Guild Nominees Mix Popular Films With More Personal
Projects</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WEST HOLLYWOOD, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rob Reiner</PERSON>, <PERSON>Phil
Alden Robinson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Oliver Stone</PERSON> and <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> are the <ORGANIZATION>Directors Guild
of America</ORGANIZATION>'s nominees for <DATE>1989</DATE> directorial achievement.
   <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> was nominated for ``Crimes and Misdemeanors,'' <PERSON>Reiner</PERSON> for
``When Harry Met Sally ... ,'' <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> for ``Field of Dreams,''
Stone for ``Born of the Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>'' and <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> for ``Dead Poets
Society.''
   ``I'm just stunned,'' said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, a first-time nominee. ``I
didn't think I stood a chance.''
   ``I think we have some interesting choices this year,''
commented <PERSON>Barry Levinson</PERSON>, last year's winner for ``Rain Man,'' as
he announced the nominees <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Reiner, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> were somewhat surprising choices,
since several critics have overlooked their achievements in favor
of such films as <PERSON>Paul Mazursky</PERSON>'s ``Enemies, A Love Story,'' <PERSON>Edward
Zwick</PERSON>'s ``Glory,'' <PERSON>Bruce Beresford</PERSON>'s ``Driving Miss Daisy'' and
<PERSON>Spike Lee</PERSON>'s ``Do the Right Thing.''
   Said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>: ``<PERSON>Bruce Beresford</PERSON> deserved a nomination. I'm
surprised <PERSON>Ed Zwick</PERSON> didn't get a nomination. And a lot of people
were pulling for <PERSON>Paul Mazursky</PERSON>.''
   ``Crimes and Misdemeanors'' is an alternately funny and haunting
story of infidelity, starring <PERSON>Allen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Alan Alda</PERSON> and <PERSON>Anjelica Huston</PERSON>.
``When Harry Met Sally ...'' is perhaps the lightest movie in
competition, a romantic comedy with <ORGANIZATION>Billy Crystal</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Meg Ryan</PERSON> as
best friends who become lovers.
   ``Field of Dreams,'' set in an <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> corn field, features <PERSON>Kevin
Costner</PERSON> as a baseball fan who recaptures the past by building a
ballpark on his farm. ``Born on the Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>'' is Stone's
account of the life of <PERSON>Ron Kovic</PERSON> (played by Tom Cruise), a
patriotic soldier whose life is shattered in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   ``Dead Poets Society'' casts <PERSON>Robin Williams</PERSON> as an unconventional
teacher working within the confines of a conventional boys boarding
school.
   The guild says its awards have deviated from the <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>
only three times since <DATE>1949</DATE>.
   Three years ago, <PERSON>Steven Spielberg</PERSON> won the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> award for ``The
Color Purple,'' but <ORGANIZATION>Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences</ORGANIZATION>
members didn't nominate him for an Oscar. The directing Oscar that
year went to <PERSON>Sydney Pollack</PERSON> for ``Out of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>.''
   Some observers believe the guild's 9,000 members, all of whom
have a vote, represent a more divergent electorate than the <ORGANIZATION>Academy</ORGANIZATION>.
   Four of the <DATE>1989</DATE> nominees have been up for the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> award before.
<PERSON>Allen</PERSON> was nominated for ``Annie Hall'' (<DATE>1977</DATE>), ``<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>'' (<DATE>1979</DATE>)
and ``Hannah and Her Sisters'' (<DATE>1986</DATE>); <PERSON>Reiner</PERSON> for ``Stand By Me''
(<DATE>1986</DATE>); Stone for ``Platoon'' (He won in <DATE>1986</DATE>); and <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> for
``Witness'' (<DATE>1985</DATE>).
   The awards will be presented at the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION>'s 42nd annual dinner, to
be held simultaneously in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 10</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121289-0106 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 147451 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 12, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
<P>
Correction Appended 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 4; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1171 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CRITIC AT LARGE: DEPARDIEU: A FRENCHMAN'S PASSION FOR FILM 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES CHAMPLIN, TIMES ARTS EDITOR 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Gerard Depardieu</PERSON> had finished "Cyrano de Bergerac" in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> at 5 the previous 
afternoon and hopped a plane to <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, where his film "Too Beautiful for 
You" was the opening-night attraction at the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Film Festival. 
</P>
<P>
He was still wearing the long hair and a mustache grown for Cyrano, just in 
case retakes would be needed. Lumberjack-large and in a smock-like black shirt 
and black trousers, he suggested <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>'s sculpture of Balzac more than <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>, 
whom he plays in "<PERSON>Camille Claudel</PERSON>," which opens <DATE>Dec. 22</DATE> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In "Too Beautiful for You," which will be released here in <DATE>February</DATE>, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> 
plays a car dealer torn between his love for his exquisitely beautiful wife and 
a plain, frumpy but passionately devoted mistress. It is a reordering of the 
classic triangle, with sharp and wounding corners however it's turned. 
</P>
<P>
The film is also his fifth with writer-director <PERSON>Bertrand Blier</PERSON>. Their first 
collaboration, "Going Places" ("Les Valseuses") in <DATE>1974</DATE>, established <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> 
as a star. He and the late <PERSON>Patrick Dewaere</PERSON> played a pair of layabouts who meet 
up, with fateful consequences, with <PERSON>Jeanne Moreau</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I was young, unconscious and very dangerous," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> said in his hotel 
suite the afternoon after the festival opening. "My father saw the film and 
said, 'Ah, yes, that's Gerard all right.' " 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu spoke through a translator, with tentative bursts of English. He will 
make his second film in English in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> starting in 
<DATE>February</DATE>. It is "The Green Card," which director <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> ("Dead Poets 
Society") wrote especially for <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
His first venture in English, "I Want to Go Home," directed by <PERSON>Alain Resnais</PERSON> 
from a script by <PERSON>Jules Feiffer</PERSON>, was a success at the <ORGANIZATION>Venice Film Festival</ORGANIZATION> 
earlier this year. In it, lyricist <ORGANIZATION>Adolph Green</ORGANIZATION> plays a temporarily expatriate 
cartoonist, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> a Flaubert scholar. 
</P>
<P>
Depardieu somewhat resembles <PERSON>Michael Caine</PERSON> in his apparently compulsive drive 
to work constantly, but money does not seem to be the immediate object. 
</P>
<P>
"Sometimes, I make a film for two bottles of good wine," he says. "I made three 
films without being paid at all, and none is a success. I make no money yet 
from 'Too Beautiful for You.' But," he explains with a devastating smile, "I 
have a sympathetic banker." 
</P>
<P>
In fact, he produces or co-produces all his own films now. "Truffaut told me 
how to get more involved," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> says. "It's better not to get paid a lot. 
I don't want to have to make movies just to pay taxes." He admits he is in the 
<PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> bracket. "Anyway, it stifles interesting projects to ask for a lot of money 
at the beginning." 
</P>
<P>
But even so, no benefits will be required for him. A few years ago, he bought a 
castle, with vineyards, in <LOCATION>Anjou</LOCATION>. Joan of Arc is said to have slept there. 
</P>
<P>
"The '89 vintage is very good, great," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> says. He loves the land and 
watching the vines and, occasionally, he adds, he feels some of the resonances 
of "Jean de Florette," one of the films in which he achieved a great critical 
success and in which feelings about land was a central theme. 
</P>
<P>
If he hints of <PERSON>Caine</PERSON> in his constant employment, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> also has a parallel 
with <PERSON>Steve McQueen</PERSON> as a man whose early teen-age years could have as easily led 
him to jail as to fame and fortune. 
</P>
<P>
He grew up in the small city of <LOCATION>Chateauroux</LOCATION> in central <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, with an American 
air base just outside town. "I saw rock 'n' roll movies. It was a big taste of 
American culture." He fell in love with blue jeans and T-shirts and kept 
himself supplied, he says, by stealing them from laundry lines. He admits that 
he was a juvenile delinquent in training. 
</P>
<P>
He also saw his first blacks -- GIs who were, he says, "received like gods" 
because of their unfamiliarity. He had a casual black girlfriend and was 
kissing her when a French friend angrily told him off. "It was my first 
experience with racism," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> says, "so of course I kept on kissing her, 
as my personal blow against racism." 
</P>
<P>
He and his pals hung out at the train station, watching with envy as people 
left for the mysterious glamour of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. One pal who was studying acting in 
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> came home on a visit and it did not take much urging to persuade 
<PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> to come back with him. 
</P>
<P>
"It was easier to leave home then," <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON> explains. He was 15. He joined a 
workshop and his life and education began again. At 16, already working in 
theater, he met <PERSON>Elizabeth Guignot</PERSON>, who became his wife and still is. 
</P>
<P>
"I discovered immediately that I am never afraid on stage. I am nervous in 
sports, but I am at peace on the stage." With his first money, he bought an 
alarm clock and a book. "I learned again how to read, to decipher tragedy, to 
understand things I didn't really understand." 
</P>
<P>
Not yet 17, he made his first film, a small documentary by <PERSON>Roger Lennart</PERSON>, "the 
patron of my new life," about <PERSON>Socrates</PERSON> as the first beatnik. He started 
"Christmas Carol" with <PERSON>Agnes Varda</PERSON> but it was never finished. ("People started 
living and stopped shooting," he says cryptically.) 
</P>
<P>
On stage, he did <PERSON>David Storey</PERSON>'s "Home" and was offered a role in the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 
production of "One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest" but turned it down because he 
thought the translation failed to do justice to the material. 
</P>
<P>
He made his first feature at 22 in <DATE>1970</DATE> and has hardly paused since. He 
appeared in <PERSON>Marguerite Duras</PERSON>' "<PERSON>Nathalie Granger</PERSON>" in <DATE>1972</DATE> and in <DATE>1974</DATE> the 
significant "Going Places," which his aura of smoldering danger helped make an 
international success. 
</P>
<P>
The work since is an anthology of the best contemporary French and European 
cinema: <PERSON>Blier</PERSON>'s "Get Out Your Handkerchiefs," <PERSON>Resnais</PERSON>' "My Uncle in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>," 
<PERSON>Truffaut</PERSON>'s "The Last Metro," <PERSON>Daniel Vigne</PERSON>'s "The Return of <PERSON>Martin Guerre</PERSON>," 
<PERSON>Andrzej Wajda</PERSON>'s "Danton," <PERSON>Bernardo Bertolucci</PERSON>'s "1900," <PERSON>Maurice Pialat</PERSON>'s "Under 
the Sign of Satan" (best film at the <DATE>1987</DATE> Cannes festival) and <PERSON>Claude Berri</PERSON>'s 
"Jean de Florette." It is a partial list. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Blier</PERSON>'s "Too Beautiful for You" is frequently funny and just as frequently 
baffling, not least to <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>. "After seven weeks of shooting, I said, 'I 
don't know what we're doing.' Blier and I were pacing around a courtyard and he 
looked pale and terrible. He said it was the food we had yesterday. I said, 
'No, it's the film.' " 
</P>
<P>
In "<PERSON>Camille Claudel</PERSON>," which was directed by veteran cinematographer <PERSON>Bruno 
Nuytten</PERSON>, <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Rodin</LOCATION> is inevitably overshadowed by <PERSON>Isabelle Adjani</PERSON>'s 
extraordinary performance as the young protegee (sister of the poet <PERSON>Paul 
Claudel</PERSON>) who went mad for the lost love of him. But his <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON> -- imperious, 
self-centered, driven, leaning close to models and materials because of acute 
myopia, pushing and tugging to arrange the masses he could see in the mind's 
eye -- is a remarkable characterization. In an actor's magical mathematics, it 
is all <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>, and all <PERSON>Depardieu</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I like playing historic personages," he says. "I learn more of my own 
history." Contemplating <PERSON>Rodin</PERSON>, he confesses, "The one trap I've fallen into is 
playing characters who are a little bit cowardly. I've made a true career of 
masochism." 
</P></TEXT>
<CORRECTION-DATE>
<P>
December 13, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</CORRECTION-DATE>
<CORRECTION>
<P>
FOR THE RECORD 
</P>
<P>
Film opening -- "Camille Claudel" with French film star Gerard Depardieu will 
open Dec. 21 in Los Angeles. An incorrect date was reported in Tuesday's 
Calendar. 
</P>
</CORRECTION>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Gerard Depardieu is in "Camille Claudel" opening Dec. 22 in L.A. b: 
"Sometimes, I make a film for two bottles of wine." ELENA SEIBERT 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ACTORS; DEPARDIEU, GERARD 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA013190-0103 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 169573 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 31, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
908 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DGA NOMINATIONS FURTHER MUDDLE OSCAR RACE; 
</P>
<P>
MOVIES: DIRECTORS GUILD REMEMBERS SPRING/SUMMER FILMS FOR ITS TOP AWARD BUT 
FORGETS SPIKE LEE AND PAUL MAZURSKY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JACK MATHEWS, TIMES FILM EDITOR 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The ad line that <ORGANIZATION>Universal Pictures</ORGANIZATION> has been using in its Oscar campaign for 
<PERSON>Phil Alden Robinson</PERSON>'s "Field of Dreams," a fantasy baseball-theme picture 
released last <DATE>spring</DATE>, is "Remember the feeling." Enough members of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Directors Guild of America</ORGANIZATION> remembered to give <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> the feeling of being a 
nominee for the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1989</DATE> best-director award. 
</P>
<P>
Enough members also remembered "Dead Poets Society" and "When <PERSON>Harry Met Sally</PERSON>," 
two early <DATE>summer</DATE> releases, to put their directors -- <PERSON>Peter Weir</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rob Reiner</PERSON> 
-- on a list that also included previous <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> winners <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON> ("Crimes and 
Misdemeanors") and <PERSON>Oliver Stone</PERSON> ("Born on the Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>"). 
</P>
<P>
Weir was a previous <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> nominee in <DATE>1985</DATE> for "Witness." Reiner was nominated for 
the <DATE>1986</DATE> "Stand By Me." <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> won the award in <DATE>1977</DATE> for "Annie Hall" and was a 
subsequent nominee for both "<LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>" in <DATE>1979</DATE> and "Hannah and Her Sisters" in 
<DATE>1986</DATE>. Stone won in <DATE>1987</DATE> for "Platoon." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION>, the bulk of whose 9,000 members are not feature-film directors, has 
had a spotty record of presaging the full list of nominations made by the 
been nearly perfect in aligning its winner with the eventual Oscar winner. Only 
three times in the 41-year history of the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> awards has the guild's winner not 
gone on to win the <ORGANIZATION>Academy Award</ORGANIZATION> as well. 
</P>
<P>
For weeks, veteran Oscar watchers have been calling this one of the most 
wide-open races in years, and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s announcement, made by <DATE>1988</DATE> winner <PERSON>Barry 
Levinson</PERSON> ("Rain Man"), did little to put it into focus. Previously honored 
directors <PERSON>Spike Lee</PERSON> (winner of the <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> critics' best-director award for "Do 
the Right Thing"), <PERSON>Paul Mazursky</PERSON> (the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> winner for "Enemies, a Love 
Story"), <PERSON>Kenneth Branagh</PERSON> (the <ORGANIZATION>National Board of Review</ORGANIZATION>'s pick for "Henry V"), 
and <PERSON>Gus Van Sant</PERSON> ("Drugstore Cowboy," selected by the <ORGANIZATION>National Society</ORGANIZATION> of Film 
Critics) were all left off the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> list. 
</P>
<P>
A number of other directors of well-reviewed films who were overlooked by the 
<ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> ("Driving Miss Daisy's" <PERSON>Bruce Beresford</PERSON>, "The War of the Roses" ' <PERSON>Danny 
DeVito</PERSON>, "Glory's" <PERSON>Ed Zwick</PERSON>, "sex, lies, and videotape's" <PERSON>Steven Soderbergh</PERSON>, 
"Music Box's" Costa-Gavras) are still in the running for <LOCATION>Oscars</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Of this year's <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> slate, only <PERSON>Oliver Stone</PERSON> seems certain to be among the 
academy's best-director nominees. Oscar nominations will be announced <DATE>Feb. 14</DATE>; 
balloting closes <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In the meantime, the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> nominations underscore the changing release patterns 
of major studios and undermine the conventional wisdom that films released 
before the fall are forgotten by winter. 
</P>
<P>
"Field of Dreams," the story of a corn farmer who builds a baseball field for 
his father's post-World War I idols, then watches the flanneled ghosts play 
ball, opened in <DATE>March</DATE>, a month that had traditionally been better for teen-age 
high-jinks movies than for those aimed at adults. It played all the way through 
the most competitive <DATE>summer</DATE> in history and grossed more than <MONEY>$62 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The movie seemed to strike a nerve with audiences, especially men tweaked by 
memories of their own relationships with their fathers, and enjoyed the kind of 
word-of-mouth that made such films as "Chariots of Fire" and "Peggy Sue Got 
Married" easy to remember at awards time. 
</P>
<P>
"Dead Poets Society" fits the same mold. The movie, about a free-spirited 
English teacher at a conservative prep school, was a risky summer entry by 
<ORGANIZATION>Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s Touchstone division but easily held its own and has grossed more than 
<MONEY>$94 million</MONEY>. The <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> nomination bodes well for both <PERSON>Weir</PERSON> and the film's star, 
<PERSON>Robin Williams</PERSON>, in the Oscar race. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Rob Reiner</PERSON>'s "When <PERSON>Harry Met Sally</PERSON>," a romantic comedy about a couple who seem 
to prove the notion that friendships between men and women are sooner or later 
subverted by sexual attraction, was an instant box-office hit, propelled by the 
most talked-about scene of the year (<PERSON>Meg Ryan</PERSON>'s faked orgasm in <LOCATION>Katz Deli</LOCATION>) and 
has taken in <MONEY>$92 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON>'s "Crimes and Misdemeanors" divided critics and audiences but found 
enough fans within the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION>. A funny-sad meditation on the relativity of sin in 
God's eyes, it has faced the usual resistance from moviegoers to <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> films -- 
particularly those that veer into the epistemological zone. "Crimes and 
Misdemeanors" has grossed just <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY> and was pretty much ignored by 
critics groups. 
</P>
<P>
Stone's "Born on the Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>," adapted from the autobiography of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
veteran <PERSON>Ron Kovic</PERSON>, is on a roll at the box office (it grossed more than <MONEY>$30 
million</MONEY> during its first month in release) and seems the odds-on favorite to 
dominate the <LOCATION>Oscars</LOCATION>. Stone is that rare film maker who, in one of <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s 
most timid eras, has managed to both make films with heavy social themes and 
turn studio executives lightheaded with their box-office success. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION>'s nominations figure to be more populist than the academy, which in 
turn figures to be more populist than critics. There are 270 feature-film 
directors in the academy's directors branch, while the <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> membership includes 
directors of film and TV dramas and their assistants, directors of TV news and 
sports programs, unit production managers and stage production managers. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>DGA</ORGANIZATION> will announce its nominees in TV categories next week. All 9,000 
members vote on the final ballot and the winners will be announced by <PERSON>Levinson</PERSON> 
at the guild's annual dinner <DATE>March 10</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hilton Hotel</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Beverly 
Hills</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Woody Allen "Crimes" ; Photo, Rob Reiner "Harry/Sally" ; Photo, Phil 
Alden Robinson "Field of Dreams" ; Photo, Oliver Stone "Fourth of July" ; 
Photo, Peter Weir "Dead Poets" ; Photo, Spike Lee "Right Thing" ; Photo, Paul 
Mazursky "Enemies" ; Photo, Kenneth Branagh "Henry V" 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MOTION PICTURE DIRECTORS; DIRECTORS GUILD OF AMERICA; ACADEMY AWARDS; MOTION 
PICTURES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06027104 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06027104 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Bebe Neuwirth, left, is the slightly wilder friend of an uptight Andie
MacDowell in the new romantic comedy 'Green Card.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; CELEBRITY; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ANDIE MacDowell, face framed by a cascade of chestnut curls flowing past her
shoulders, tucks one slim leg under her on the sofa as she gets comfortable.; 
  Nominated (but not picked) for a Golden Globe Award for best actress for her
starring role in "Green Card," playing nationwide, MacDowell is enjoying a
longed-for hiatus from moviemaking. (The movie won the Golden Globe for best
comedy and co-star Gerard Depardieu was named best actor in that category.)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A MODEL FOR MODERN HAPPINESS
THE SUNNY SIDE OF ANDIE MACDOWELL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Personality
Burke-Block is a free-lance writer based in New York.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The 32-year-old actress also stars in two upcoming films, "Object of
Beauty" (with <PERSON>John Malkovich</PERSON>) -- which is set for nationwide release <DATE>Feb. 22</DATE>
-- and the action thriller "Hudson Hawk," co-starring <PERSON>Bruce Willis</PERSON>, set for
release this summer.;    In between films, <ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> has continued to fulfill
her modeling contract with the cosmetics company L'Oreal.;    Down-home
glamour; Sitting in her publicist's office, dressed in pleated gray trousers
and a fitted black riding coat with an embroidered collar, <ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> looks
very relaxed.;    Even without any makeup she has the beauty that has made her
an internationally known and admired model.;    In addition to two careers,
<ORGANIZATION>MacDowell</ORGANIZATION> has a husband (ex-model <PERSON>Paul Qualley</PERSON>) and two young children, <PERSON>Justin</PERSON>
