<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880831-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-31-88 0231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CaliforniaSlug Bjt   08-31 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-California Slug, Bjt,0557</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Governor Squashes Proposed State Mollusk</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHLEEN GRUBB</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When it comes to representing
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the banana slug just won't do, Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON>
said in vetoing a bill that designated the slimy, slothful creature
the state's official mollusk.
   The veto by the image-conscious governor, announced <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>,
squashed the hopes of a group of <ORGANIZATION>Blue Birds</ORGANIZATION> and Camp Fire girls
from the <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> area who led the campaign to make the
banana slug a state mascot.
   ``I feel really bad that he vetoed it,'' says <PERSON>Grace Moses</PERSON>, 9,
whose Blue Bird troop worked six weeks lobbying. ``I mean, why did
he have to do that? He didn't know anything about it. I hope he
watched the news about it.''
   <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> said he vetoed the bill because the large, brilliant
yellow mollusk, which can eat poison oak without getting a rash,
isn't a true Californian.
   ``If there is a need to designate a state mollusk, it would be
more appropriate to select one that is indigenous to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and
perhaps one that is more representative of the international
reputation that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> enjoys,'' he said in his veto message.
   The governor added that the dubious honor of being the banana
slug's home state may belong to wetter neighbors to the north,
since the species was first identified near the mouth of the
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia River</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and lives as far north as <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>.
   But members of the <ORGANIZATION>Redwood City Dynamite Blue Birds</ORGANIZATION> and the
office of the legislator who carried their slug bill said the
governor is misinformed about the banana slug, which has the
scientific name Ariolimax columbianus and lives in damp coastal
forest areas throughout the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Janice Hopcraft</PERSON>, an aide to Democratic Assemblyman <PERSON>Bryon Sher</PERSON>,
said four of five kinds of banana slugs are native to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   ``I think basically the banana slug has gotten a bad rap,'' said
<PERSON>Hopcraft</PERSON>, who wore a yellow armband <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in memory of Sher's
bill. ``They're obviously easy to look down upon and they do have
some odd habits. Perhaps, the governor looked too much at that and
not their good side.
   ``As far as its representative qualities, it's absolutely a
unique example of the diversity of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s wildlife.''
   Deukmejian, a Republican who's made a personal campaign of
promoting <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> trade nationally and overseas, suggested the
<ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION> may not need an official slug at all.
   And if <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> must have a mollusk, he'd prefer the pismo
clam, black abalone, red abalone, turban shell, two-spotted
octupus, common squid or another breed of mussel unique to the
state.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has several official mascots, including a tree, a
fossil, a reptile, a fish, a rock and even a state insect in
addition to the usual bird, animal and flower. The Legislature sent
a bill to the governor <DATE>Monday</DATE> that would designate the square dance
as the official folk dance, and the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> swing, or jitterbug,
as the official dance.
   Deukmejian has not acted on that measure.
   The banana slug gained notoriety a few years ago when students
at the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz</ORGANIZATION> chose it as the
official school mascot over the sea lion, despite the objections of
the university's president.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880830-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-88 2245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BananaSlug     08-30 0413</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Banana Slug,0426</SECOND>
<HEAD>A Bad Day for the Banana Slug</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
vetoed a bill to make the banana slug the state mollusk, leaving a
troop of Blue Birds singing the blues.
   Deukmejian explained in his veto message that the slug isn't
Californian enough and that its reputation just doesn't fit with
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s image.
   But members of the <ORGANIZATION>Redwood City Blue Birds</ORGANIZATION> say the governor's
grasp of mollusk lore is a bit slippery.
   <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> said the species was first identified in <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and
ranges as far north as <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, so it's not a true-blue Californian.
   Besides, the yellowish mollusk has an image that isn't befitting
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION>, he said. He suggested that native <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
fauna such as the pismo clam, the black abalone, the red abalone or
the turban shell would make a better choice.
   ``If there is a need to designate a state mollusk, it would be
more appropriate to select one that is indigenous to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and
perhaps one that is more representative of the international
reputation that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> enjoys,'' <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> said.
   The Blue Birds who sponsored the campaign and the bill's author
said the governor was all wet.
   Four of five types of banana slug are native to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, said
<PERSON>Janice Hopcraft</PERSON>, an aide to Assemblyman <PERSON>Bryon Sher</PERSON>. <PERSON>Hopcraft</PERSON> and
her co-workers wore yellow armbands <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to mark the bill's
demise.
   ``I think basically the banana slug has gotten a bad rap,'' she
said. ``They're obviously easy to look down upon, and they do have
some odd habits. Perhaps the governor looked too much at that and
not their good side.
   ``As far as its representative qualities, it's absolutely a
unique example of the diversity of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s wildlife.''
   ``Yeah, he didn't know all the facts,'' said 9-year-old <PERSON>Susanna
Farley</PERSON>, whose Blue Bird troop worked six weeks on the bill.
   ``I feel really bad that he vetoed it,'' said her friend, <PERSON>Grace
Moses</PERSON>, also 9. ``I mean, why did he have to do that? He didn't know
anything about it. I hope he watched the news about it.''
   <PERSON>Hopcraft</PERSON> said the veto is a disappointing end for the bill's
young supporters.
   ``I think this is basically the ultimate lesson for the Dynamite
Blue Birds and Camp Fire kids, that not all things have a happy
ending.''
   Gubernatorial vetoes can be overturned by two-thirds majorities
in the Assembly and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, but Assembly Republicans have vowed to
block any attempts to override <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON>'s vetoes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870408-0117 </DOCNO>
<HL> REVIEW &amp; OUTLOOK (Editorial):
Sour Grapes in California</HL>
<DD> 04/08/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   An editorial writer for the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>) 
<PERSON>News-Press</PERSON> expressed sadness recently that Rose Bird found it necessary to spruce herself up with a visit to the hairdresser just before <DATE>last November</DATE>'s elections. 
We had a little trouble getting the point at first. 
Why shouldn't the former <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> chief justice, a handsome woman, have a new hairdo? 
So we read on. 

   As most everyone knows by now, <PERSON>Ms. Bird</PERSON> was ousted from the <ORGANIZATION>California Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> by the state's voters, new hairdo notwithstanding. 
Two other justices identified with her views were thrown out as well. 
Three new justices appointed by Gov. <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON> and vetted by a three-member judicial commission were installed last month. 

   The editorial complaint about <PERSON>Ms. Bird</PERSON> having to fix her hair just to try to make a good impression on the voters was by way of leading up to a proposed amendment to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Constitution. 
A <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> politician named <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON> -- not the <PERSON>Gary Hart</PERSON>, but certainly a Democrat and a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> state senator -- is offering the amendment. 
It would change <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s system of selecting and, more importantly, disposing of <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> justices, a system that dates back to a <DATE>1934</DATE> initiative. 

   The fundamental change would be interesting. 
Currently justices are appointed by the governor, vetted by the <ORGANIZATION>Commission on Judicial Appointments</ORGANIZATION> and put on the ballot for public approval or disapproval at the next general election. 
They serve 12-year terms, after which they go before the voters again. 
Ms. Bird and her two colleagues were the first justices ever voted out of office. 
Voters had become fed up with their predisposition toward leniency for violent criminals, among other things. 

   <PERSON>Sen. Hart</PERSON> would take the voters out of the picture. 
Justices would be appointed by the governor, confirmed by the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and be limited to a single 12-year term. 
No justice would have to fix her, or his, hair to try to win reconfirmation. 
The <PERSON>Hart</PERSON> argument is that this would make appointments less "political." 

   We've noticed how apolitical <PERSON>Sen. Joe Biden</PERSON> and other Democrats in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Senate have been when it comes time to confirm President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s judicial appointees. 
<PERSON>Sen. Hart</PERSON> presumably intends that the Democrats who dominate the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> will be less partisan, but we are not much encouraged by the highly charged testimony presented by the <ORGANIZATION>National Organization for Women</ORGANIZATION> and other liberal groups when Gov. <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON>'s latest appointees were up before the judicial commission. 
NOW thought appointee <PERSON>Marcus Kaufman</PERSON> "hostile" toward anti-discrimination laws. 

   In <PERSON>Sen. Hart</PERSON>'s view the current system is too political because the voters, rather than professional politicians, do the confirming. 
What do voters know about such matters, the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Barbara News-Press</ORGANIZATION> wants to know. 
Well, the voters apparently knew they didn't like Rose Bird. 
We suspect that is what really grates in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>. 
The voters threw out Rose Bird. 
So <PERSON>Sen. Hart</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>News-Press</ORGANIZATION> want to throw out the voters. 

   The governor has a thought or two on this subject. 
In a recent interview he observed that in <DATE>1934</DATE> the people of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> reserved for themselves the confirmation right. 
"I don't see any reason to change that and I would not favor taking away from the people the right to make that decision." 

   We rather like the idea of popular democracy ourselves. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880308-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-88 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     03-08 0440</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0456</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright and Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FAIRBANKS, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At the <ORGANIZATION>Pike</ORGANIZATION>'s Landing bar, the regulars
have a curious way of telling <DATE>spring</DATE> is near _ they wait for the
first truck or car to break through the ice of the <LOCATION>Chena River</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Gary Halmstad</PERSON> earned that dubious distinction <DATE>Monday</DATE>. His <DATE>1979</DATE>
van broke through 8 inches of ice as he started across an ice
bridge used as a winter shortcut by many residents.
   ``I hate being this kind of harbinger of <DATE>spring</DATE>,'' he said.
   The ice cracked between the front and back tires, and he
summoned a small wrecker to pull him off. Instead, the tow truck
pulled the front tires off a supporting shelf of ice, and the front
of the van plunged into about 5 feet of water. He planned to call a
larger wrecker to pull the van out the rest of the way.
   ``I'm glad it wasn't in the middle,'' he said. ``I suppose I
should giggle. All I have to do is pay money for a tow truck and
drain the engine.''
   The dunking was the earliest that bar patrons could recall.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At the <ORGANIZATION>Pike</ORGANIZATION>'s Landing bar, the regulars
have a curious way of telling <DATE>spring</DATE> is near _ they wait for the
first truck or car to break through the ice of the <LOCATION>Chena River</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Gary Halmstad</PERSON> earned that dubious distinction <DATE>Monday</DATE>. His <DATE>1979</DATE>
van broke through 8 inches of ice as he started across an ice
bridge used as a winter shortcut by many residents.
   ``I hate being this kind of harbinger of <DATE>spring</DATE>,'' he said.
   The ice cracked between the front and back tires, and he
summoned a small wrecker to pull him off. Instead, the tow truck
pulled the front tires off a supporting shelf of ice, and the front
of the van plunged into about 5 feet of water. He planned to call a
larger wrecker to pull the van out the rest of the way.
   ``I'm glad it wasn't in the middle,'' he said. ``I suppose I
should giggle. All I have to do is pay money for a tow truck and
drain the engine.''
   The dunking was the earliest that bar patrons could recall.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080390-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 256492 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 3, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
699 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S THE LEAST THEY COULD DO FOR THE TERNS, NAVY FIGURES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HAROLD MAASS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ALAMEDA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Jets roar to a takeoff and scream over the <LOCATION>Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, making the 
<ORGANIZATION>Alameda Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION> runway seem one of the most unlikely places for a 
nature preserve. 
</P>
<P>
But each <DATE>summer</DATE> the air station is transformed into a sort of maximum-security 
bird sanctuary when nesting pairs of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least terns begin to breed in a 
fenced-in some 75 yards from a runway flanked by land-based cannons and armed 
warships. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least tern, an endangered species more commonly found in the 
southern part of the state, has no other fertile nesting grounds in <LOCATION>Northern 
California</LOCATION>. About 100 nesting pairs -- a local record, up from 72 in <DATE>1989</DATE> -- 
are breeding at the base this year, making the military installation home to 
more than <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the least tern population in the north. 
</P>
<P>
"It is critical to keeping them breeding in <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Laura 
Collins</PERSON>, caretaker at the four-acre Alameda breeding area. "We really don't 
have any big success stories anywhere else." 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least tern has bounced back fairly well since the bird -- a 
cousin to the sea gull, about nine inches from tail to bill -- was included 20 
years ago on the first federal list of endangered species. From a low of about 
300 breeding pairs 30 years ago, the least tern population had increased to 
1,250 pairs by <DATE>1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In part because of open spaces and fenced-off beaches on military bases, more 
than half of the least tern population heads to one of the installations at 
breeding time, said <PERSON>Barbara Massey</PERSON>, an ornithologist who studies a least tern 
breeding colony program in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the state's least terns nest on beaches in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> -- about 
350 pairs at <LOCATION>Camp Pendleton</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Oceanside</LOCATION>, another 250 pairs at <LOCATION>Venice Beach</LOCATION>, 
and about 250 more at <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica State Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Huntington Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But the <ORGANIZATION>Alameda Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION> least terns are not the only ones with a 
penchant for airports. Although the birds naturally seek beach nesting spots, 
they have been known to look elsewhere. About 10 pairs of the birds make their 
nests at the <ORGANIZATION>Metropolitan Oakland International Airport</ORGANIZATION>, and another small 
group nests between two runways at a <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> airfield, <PERSON>Massey</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The sharing of Tarmac and airspace by 200 birds and two reserve squadrons of 
attack jet aircraft -- not to mention four squadrons of helicopters and other 
military planes -- requires some adjustments. For example, <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> sets a 
period in late <DATE>summer</DATE> when the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> shuts down its 3,000-foot main runway and 
directs traffic to another airstrip at the base. 
</P>
<P>
During this period, a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said, fledglings' first short flights 
often land them in the middle of the runway. 
</P>
<P>
"At a certain time during the growing process . . . these least terns have a 
tendency to run out on the runways, and they try to hide on the white and 
yellow paint strips," said <PERSON>Bill Valente</PERSON>, the base's assistant public affairs 
officer. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> has taken other steps to protect the birds. <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> builders surrounded 
the breeding area with an electrified fence, capable of jolting predators with 
a harmless but discouraging shock from six-volt batteries. This year, the base 
hired federal animal control workers to come in and catch cats and rival birds 
that threaten the least terns and their eggs, <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>David Kashimba</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
For breeding birds, the problems associated with airstrip nesting don't end 
there. At especially noisy times -- when jet pilots practice touch-and-go 
landings, for example -- the birds sometimes do fly away. But they keep coming 
back. Theoretically, steady high noise levels could pose problems for the 
birds, which bring food only to chicks that recognize and return their call. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't know how they manage to teach their chicks their calls when there's 
the roar of jets everywhere all the time," <PERSON>Massey</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But the birds manage so well that some of the people who help protect them say 
the air station colony could anchor a <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION> comeback that could 
eventually link up with the southern colonies and spread the birds throughout 
the state. 
</P>
<P>
"The least tern is one of the success stories, in terms of managing endangered 
species," <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Caretaker Laura Collins inspects a least tern nest at Alameda air field. 
Below, the rare bird's distinctive speckled eggs and a baby tern on the base. 
GARY FRIEDMAN / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ENDANGERED SPECIES; ALAMEDA NAVAL AIR STATION; BIRDS; ANIMAL BREEDING; 
CONSERVATION; MIGRATION; ANIMAL CONTROL; NOISE; MILITARY AIRPLANES; NAVY 
(U.S.); TERNS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910903-0118
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910903-0118.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   California Rejects Bid for Protection
   For Coastal Songbird, Stirring Debate
   ----
   By Charles McCoy
</HL>
<DATE>
09/03/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<IN>
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
</IN>
<NS>
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
</NS>
<GV>
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT (FDL)
</GV>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   California state officials' rejection of recommendations
that they grant protection to a small songbird sets up
another bitter court fight over the fate of a troubled
species.
   Late Thursday, the California Fish and Game Commission
declined to grant the California coastal gnatcatcher
protection under the Endangered Species Act.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The commission, which consists of four members appointed
by the state's governor, rejected the recommendation of the
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Game Department</ORGANIZATION>, which after a year of
review of the gnatcatcher's condition had strongly
recommended listing the bird as endangered in order to avert
its possible extinction. The commission has rarely gone
against state biologists' findings on a species in the past,
but the panel, by a vote of 3 to 1, held that it wasn't
convinced that the bird's condition is dire enough to warrant
protections.
   Environmentalists, led by the <ORGANIZATION>Natural Resources Defense
Council</ORGANIZATION>, attacked the commission's decision and vowed to
challenge it in court as early as this week.
   Federal officials are also considering whether to grant
the gnatcatcher protection under the federal Endangered
Species Act. The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
field scientists have recommended that it be listed as
endangered under the act. The federal agency's decision on
the bird is due later this month.
   The gnatcatcher dispute is shaping up as an important test
case in the increasingly bitter clash over how far to go to
protect wildlife. The gnatcatcher lives in the low scrub that
dots the southern <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> coast; much of its habitat has
been plowed under to make way for housing tracts in
fast-growing counties such as Orange, <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. State and federal scientists believe there are only
about 2,000 pairs of gnatcatchers left in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   Thousands of acres of the remaining coastal scrub are
owned by big developers, such as <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Cos.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Baldwin Co.</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Margarita Co</ORGANIZATION>. The companies, which are among the
biggest Republican campaign contributors in the nation, have
spent <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> on a lobbying blitz aimed at
blocking any listing of the bird as endangered under either
state or federal wildlife laws. The developers contend that
they're already voluntarily setting aside enough gnatcatcher
habitat to ensure the bird's survival, and that listing it as
endangered would paralyze housing construction and road
projects, costing billions of dollars and thousands of jobs.
   The commission in early <DATE>August</DATE> had delayed its decision on
the gnatcatcher, after developers produced a new study they
maintained refuted scientific findings that the gnatcatcher
was headed for extinction. But at <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s commission
meeting in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Pete Bonadelli</PERSON>, head of the
state Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Game Department</ORGANIZATION>, reported that the new
information in some ways only strengthened his agency's
belief that the gnatcatcher is imperiled and should be listed
under the state's endangered species statute. As is often the
case with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> environmental laws, the state's
endangered species statutes are in some respects tougher than
federal laws.
   The commission still voted against listing the
gnatcatcher. One reason may have been a last-minute appeal
from <PERSON>Michael Mantell</PERSON>, deputy director of the state's
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Resources</ORGANIZATION>, which is trying to persuade
developers to cooperate voluntarily with its own plan for
preserving coastal habitat. Many environmentalists support
the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Resources</ORGANIZATION> plan, but they contend the plan
is many months, if not years, away from bearing fruit and say
the gnatcatcher can't wait that long.
   Environmentalists accused the state commission of caving
in to political pressure on the gnatcatcher. "The
commission's position is absurd," said <PERSON>Joel Reynolds</PERSON>, a
"They clearly have allowed politics to supplant science." <PERSON>Mr.
Reynolds</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>NRDC</ORGANIZATION> will file a suit in state court
alleging that the commission's action violates state law,
perhaps as early as this week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880831-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-31-88 0538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-DigestBriefs     08-31 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digest Briefs,0830</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>CORKSCREW, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>JERUSALEM (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SACRAMENTO, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some state and local Democratic leaders say
that while <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' Republican rivals have made their grab
for the national spotlight, his campaign has been making important
organizational gains in the field.
   Around the country, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> field leaders and Democratic Party
state and local leaders contend the appearance of flagging momentum
on the part of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign is at worst a temporary problem
_ a part of the ups and downs of a campaign that will balance in
the end.
   Dukakis campaign officials have said they were devoting much of
their <DATE>summer</DATE> efforts to building organization in the states, and
party officials in some key states point to organizational gains.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121090-0089 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 320372 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 10, 1990, Monday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
222 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VENTURA COUNTY NEWS ROUNDUP: VENTURA; 
</P>
<P>
PARK RANGERS SHARE TALES OF SEA BIRDS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KIRSTEN LEE SWARTZ 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Raising babies can be stressful. Consider the adult Western gull. When chicks 
want to eat they peck at a red mark on one of their parents' bills until mom or 
dad regurgitates a meal. 
</P>
<P>
"It is kind of fun to go out to <LOCATION>Anacapa Island</LOCATION> and watch them do that," said 
<PERSON>Jean Van Tatenhove</PERSON>, a ranger for <ORGANIZATION>Channel Islands National Park</ORGANIZATION>. "It's a little 
gross, but it's fun too." 
</P>
<P>
For the adult Xantus Murrelet, chick-rearing includes forcing the young birds 
to tumble down cliffs on <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Island</LOCATION> for a life at sea two days after 
they hatch. 
</P>
<P>
Calling sea birds the last frontier for bird watchers, Van Tatenhove, an 
ornithologist, told the stories of some of the area's lesser known sea birds at 
park headquarters at <LOCATION>Ventura Harbor</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Each month the <ORGANIZATION>National Park 
Service</ORGANIZATION> features free lectures on park wildlife. Talks on sea birds will 
continue through <DATE>December</DATE>. In <DATE>January</DATE>, rangers will begin discussions on whales 
to mark the mammals' migration through the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara Channel</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Van Tatenhove displayed five of the 11 birds monitored by rangers, including 
the endangered brown pelican. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>West Anacapa Island</LOCATION> serves as the largest breeding colony in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> brown pelicans. Centuries ago Chumash Indians made coats from 
the pelicans' finely marked feathers, she said. KIRSTEN LEE SWARTZ 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Ranger Jean Van Tatenhove holds stuffed cormorant during a talk on sea 
birds. JAMES RUEBSAMEN / For The Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880822-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-88 1002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AndeanCondors     08-22 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Andean Condors,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condor Dies En Route to Experiment for California Condor
Recovery</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One zoo-hatched Andean condor died in transit
to a wilderness area but three others survived for an experiment
intended to show the best way to reintroduce endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors into the wild.
   The surviving birds were safely placed in secret holding pens
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>Los Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION>, and more Andean condors
will be taken to the area in <DATE>October</DATE>, said <PERSON>Joe Dowhan</PERSON>, condor
recovery coordinator for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   The dead bird was sent to <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> for an autopsy, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   He said its death will have little effect on the program. ``In
some ways, you kind of want things to go wrong now instead of
later,'' he said.
   The South American birds, all females to prevent breeding in the
wild, are being used to test techniques biologists hope to use to
begin returning the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor to the wild after their
numbers are increased in a captive breeding program.
   Only 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are known to survive, all in
captivity at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The Andean condor was chosen for the experiment because it is
the closest living relative to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. Though the
Andean condors are also endangered, they number in the thousands.
   Scientists are conducting the experiment to see how birds
hatched in captivity adapt to freedom and fend for themselves
without native birds of their species to serve as examples.
   The 3- and 4-month-old birds will spend several weeks in mesh
enclosures in the forest 75 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   When the Andean birds are able to fly, around <DATE>November</DATE>,
scientist will fit them with radio transmitters, release them and
monitor their progress.
   The Andean birds will remain in the wild until it's time to
release <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, perhaps as early as <DATE>1992</DATE> if the captive
breeding program continues to succeed, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06034141 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06034141 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: Illustration by Wilfred Spoon; (California condor)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CALIFORNIA; BIRD; POLITICS; CONSERVATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BEAUTIFUL, BABE, BEAUTIFUL. Let's do carrion real soon.;    The condor is an
authentic Californian who's been around for 2.5 million years, but -- let's be
honest -- Gymnogyps californianus is not Golden State glamorous.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  West  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE CALIFORNIA CONDOR
THE BIG BALD UGLY BIRD WHO DEVELOPED POLITICAL
CLOUT.  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  WEST PRIMER
JOANNE JACOBS is a Mercury News columnist.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It's a big bird. Along with its Andean cousin, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor is the
largest soaring bird in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, with a nine-foot wing span and a weight
up to 22 pounds. The condor is black, with white highlights on the wings, a
bald yellow head and a red neck.;    Landed, it's a bit of a klutz. In the
air, the condor can cruise for hours, checking out the coastal range for newly
dead meat. Basically, this is a recovering vulture.;    Coastal Indians saw
the high-flying condor as a symbol of freedom, and believed that the end for
the condor would mean the end of the world as we know it, and a time of
purification.;    That time almost came. Condors grew sick from pesticides,
poisoned coyote bait and lead-filled corpses left by hunters. Some were run
down by cars while snacking on road kill. Others flew into power lines. The
spread of humans destroyed much of the big birds' habitat -- they hang in the
<LOCATION>San Rafael Mountains</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor became the most
endangered avian in the world.;    Unfortunately, the condors are avid
practitioners of planned parenthood. In the wild, they wait to mate till the
relatively (for a bird) mature age of five or six, and lay only one egg every
other year.;    It looked like a bird that's been around since prehistoric
times wouldn't survive the 20th century.;    But as the condor became a symbol
of environmental destruction, it developed "great political clout," says <PERSON>Bill
Toone</PERSON>, curator of birds at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. "The condor is a
useless piece of trash in a lot of ways. You have this creature that's nothing
more than a vulture who vomits, burps and eats dead things, and you've turned
it into something incredible.";    The threat to the condor set off a fierce
debate among environmentalists. The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> began
putting radio transmitters on condors and then moved on to egg-napping, hoping
to improve the fledglings' survival rate by raising them in captivity on
minced mouse. The <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> argued the interference was necessary; the
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club</ORGANIZATION> and Friends of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> believed it was better to let the condor
live and die out in the wild.;    <PERSON>David Brower</PERSON>, founder of Friends of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, wrote: "What if the (condor), watching <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> sprawl toward its
last hills, has simply decided it is time to go? Perhaps feeding on ground
squirrels, for a bird that once fed on mastodons, is too steep a fall from
glory?";    Finally, in <DATE>1987</DATE>, researchers grabbed the last wild condors --
only 27 were left -- and started breeding them at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> zoos. Thirteen condors have joined the flock.;    Despite the breeding
success, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor is still tops on the endangered list; survival
will be assured when several 100-bird flocks are flying in the wild, with
another flock breeding in captivity.;    Researchers hope the condors of the
future will soar over the <ORGANIZATION>Sespe Condor Sanctuary</ORGANIZATION>, 53,000 acres in the <ORGANIZATION>Los
Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION>, plus condor country in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Animas Mountains</LOCATION>
purchased by the <ORGANIZATION>Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>, and possibly the <LOCATION>Grand Canyon</LOCATION> as well.;  
 The first step will be taken in late <DATE>1991</DATE>: Scientists plan to let three young
zoo-born birds fly wild in the <LOCATION>Los Padres</LOCATION> habitat.;    Condors who have
cruised <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> for 2.5 million years will be around for the <DATE>21st century</DATE>
as well.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Joanne Jacobs  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910203  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  626  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday February 3, 1991
00034141,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880823-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-88 0338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AndeanCondors     08-23 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Andean Condors,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stress Blamed On Rare Bird's Death</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LYNN ELBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stress is believed to have killed a zoo-hatched
Andean condor that was on its way to freedom in an experiment to
see how its endangered North American cousin will adapt to the wild.
   Three other transplanted Andean condors in the program were
doing well <DATE>Monday</DATE>, officials said.
   The Andean birds were chosen for the experiment because it is
the closest living relative to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. Though the
Andean species is also endangered, they number in the thousands.
Only 28 of its North American cousins exist and all in captivity.
   The Andean condors, which are also endangered, were transported
to <ORGANIZATION>Los Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION> in airline-style animal shipping
crates and placed in secret holding pens <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   One died while being transported.
   Preliminary results of an autopsy show the death was
stress-related, although infection has not been ruled out, said <PERSON>Joe
Dowhan</PERSON>, condor recovery coordinator for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   Final test results are expected by <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   He said it was premature to say how officials might have handled
the move differently or what changes might be implemented to
prevent other deaths.
   ``This is a learning process. Right now there are all kinds of
scenarios we could consider changing,'' he said.
   Scientists are conducting the experiment to see how birds
hatched in captivity adapt to freedom, fending for themselves in a
region without native birds of their species to serve as examples.
   The first group of the 3- and 4-month-old birds are scheduled to
spend several weeks in mesh enclosures in the forest 75 miles
northeast of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   Two came from the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>; one was from the
Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> center in <LOCATION>Patuxent</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>; and the one that
died came from the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   Scientists will prepare the birds for their first flights over
the dry mountains and foothills that once supported a large
population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors.
   The condors are being exposed to other young condors for the
first time because they were raised singly, as in the wild, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON>
said.
   More Andean condors will be brought to the area in <DATE>October</DATE>.
   In <DATE>December</DATE>, when the birds should be able to fly, scientists
will fit them with radio monitors, release them, and follow their
progress.
   The Andean birds will remain in the wild until it's time to
release <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, perhaps as early as <DATE>1992</DATE> if officials
have continued success in captive breeding programs at the Wild
Animal Park and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   Blood tests on the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor conceived in
captivity determined the bird is a female, officials said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The 4-month-old bird, named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, also was determined to be
``in perfect health,'' said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman at the Wild
Animal Park. The bird, which weighed in at 6} ounces when born
<DATE>April 29</DATE>, now weighs 16 pounds.
   Fourteen of the 27 other <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are females. Park
officials say further tests will determine which of the birds are
related and how they will be separated for breeding.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06052143 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06052143 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  CALIFORNIA; STATE; HISTORY; ARTS; MINERAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The days are warm, the state budget is thin, the Legislature is moving slowly.
It must be time for, you guessed it, another "Official State" item battle.;   
Remember those? Official state bird: valley quail; official tree: redwood;
official gem: benitoite, whatever that is.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  OFFICIAL STATE ARTIFACT? MEET THE STONE BEAR  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Now comes the revelation that we have no official state prehistoric
artifact. SB 404 by <PERSON>Sen. Ralph Dills</PERSON>, D-Gardena, would close that gap. Make
way for the chipped stone bear.;    <ORGANIZATION>Dills</ORGANIZATION>' arguments are simple: Stones
chipped to look like bears go far, far back in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s history. It would
be a tribute to the artistic contributions of American Indians. And the bear
is pretty darn prominent on <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s official list. The grizzly bear,
after all, is the official animal.;    The artifact movement, if it can be
called that, started in <DATE>1985</DATE> when <ORGANIZATION>Cypress College</ORGANIZATION> students discovered an
8,000-year-old bear-shaped carving in <LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION>. A committee was
formed. Eventually a pitch was made. The <DATE>1985</DATE> find, which is about 2 1/2
inches long, would serve as the model for the official artifact under the
plan.;    But reasonable or not, don't expect this to be simple. This, after
all, has to pass the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Legislature.;    Remember, if you will, the
historic battle in <DATE>1988</DATE> over an official state mollusk. The proposal, muscled
along by the ultra-cute lobbying of a troop of <LOCATION>Redwood City</LOCATION> Camp Fire kids,
was to give that prestigious honor to the banana slug.;    The banana slug
eventually won in the Legislature but was vetoed by then-Gov. <PERSON>George
Deukmejian</PERSON>, who apparently was in a less humorous mood than lawmakers. The
banana slug, he said, is "not representative of the international reputation
that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> enjoys." To the Camp Fire kids, that translated into
"harrumph.";    That might be a bad sign for <ORGANIZATION>Dills</ORGANIZATION>. He has the backing of
college students and scientists, hardly as adorable a group as the pack of
fourth-graders carrying around their pet slugs.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  McClatchy News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Sacramento  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910221  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  326  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday February 21, 1991
00052143,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880820-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-88 0130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AndeanCondors 1stLd-Writethru a0680 08-20 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Andean Condors, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0680,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condors to Scout Way for Return of California Condors</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE with trip under way, picking up
7th graf pvs, `The Andean ....'
^By GEORGE GARTIES</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Andean condors that will serve as scouts
for reintroduction of the gravely threatened <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor into
the wild are headed for temporary pens in a rugged mountain range.
   The 3- and 4-month-old avian pioneers, hatched and reared in
zoos, will spend several weeks in mesh enclosures as scientists
prepare them for their first flights over the dry mountains and
foothills that once supported a thriving population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> species _ a black, vulture-like carrion eater
with a wingspan up to 9{ feet _ has dwindled to a mere 28, all in
captivity.
   Two Andean condors from the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> were
loaded into airline-style animal shipping crates <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> for
a 200-mile trip to the secret holding pens in the <LOCATION>Los Padres
National Forest</LOCATION>, 75 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the animal park, said in a telephone interview <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``They want to arrive and put the birds in their new home in the
dark of night so the birds awaken the next morning thinking they
are in the same place they were before,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said as his crew
was ready to depart at <TIME>6:45 p.m.</TIME> for the six-hour drive.
   The birds were not drugged, but were captured and wrapped in
blankets by familiar handlers, he said.
   ``By moving them in the dark it basically minimizes the
stress,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   A third Andean condor hatched at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo will join
the contingent, along with a fourth, flown in from a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> center in <LOCATION>Patuxent</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>, the
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo biologist overseeing the program.
   The Andean birds, all females to prevent breeding in the wild,
will be used to test techniques biologists hope to use _ perhaps as
soon as <DATE>1992</DATE> _ to begin returning the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor to nature.
More Andean condors will be added to the test flock later.
   In a <MONEY>$440,000</MONEY> program overseen by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Service</ORGANIZATION>, the birds will be taken to a special mesh enclosure,
measuring about 20 feet by 40 feet and 15 feet high, in rugged
territory. The exact spot is secret to deter the curious or the
malicious.
   About <DATE>November</DATE>, when the birds are able to fly, they will be
fitted with radio monitoring gear and released. It's expected they
will cover much of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor's five-county range, a
land of bare grassy hills dotted with occasional oaks, and rugged,
rocky cliffs and canyons in the mountains that ring the southern
end of the <LOCATION>San Joaquin Valley</LOCATION>.
   The purpose of the test, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said, is twofold: To see how
birds hatched in captivity adapt to freedom; and to see if such
birds can learn to fend for themselves in a region without native
birds of their species to serve as examples.
   The program also will help scientists spot such possible hazards
as poison bait illegally left for coyotes or lead shot in animal
carcasses left by hunters, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The Andean birds will be captured from the wild when it's time
to release their <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> cousins, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said. The first
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> birds could be released as early as <DATE>1992</DATE> if breeding
programs are successful, he said.
   The Andean condor was chosen for the experiment because it is
the closest living relative to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. Though the
Andean species is endangered, they number in the thousands.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land bird, once
roamed widely along the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, but its numbers had shrunk to
40 when the Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> launched a rescue effort in
<DATE>1976</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880430-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-88 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorChick     04-30 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Chick,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>Only Condor Chick Conceived In Captivity Eats First Meals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hungry bundle of fluff named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, the
only <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick conceived in captivity, gobbled minced
mice <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and keepers of the endangered species were
encouraged by its appetite.
   The newly hatched chick, which raised the condor population to
28, ate its first meal from the fingertips of a handler at <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
and ate again at hourly intervals, said <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON>, spokeswoman
for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   ``The chick was hungry and ate everything it was offered,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Baker</PERSON> said. ``Everyone seems very pleased with the progress of the
chick. But the first 10 days are critical, for anybody, human or
animal.''
   The chick's diet was a combination of minced baby mice and
chicken egg yolk, she said. The meals fed to the chick, which is
slightly larger than a person's fist, amounted to about two
tablespoons of food each time.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Interior Secretary <PERSON>Donald Hodel</PERSON> congratulated the Wild
Animal Park staff for the successful hatching.
   ``The hatching of the world's first captive-bred condor is a
milestone that we've been awaiting for years,'' <PERSON>Hodel</PERSON> said in a
statement released in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Interior Department</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
recovery program.
   ``This small chick represents a big step back from the brink of
extinction and a big step forward for recovery of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor,'' he said.
   Keepers delicately wielding tweezers helped the chick break free
of its avocado-size egg at <TIME>5:38 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, ending a 61{-hour
hatching process that began when the chick first pecked cracks in
the shell <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The laborious process of helping the bird get free, led by
biologist <PERSON>Cyndi Keuhler</PERSON>, took nearly eight hours.
   Molloko is an Indian word for the giant condor species. The name
originates from the <LOCATION>Sacramento Valley Maidu</LOCATION> tribe and was chosen by
a council of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> tribes last week, <PERSON>Ms. Baker</PERSON> said.
   After hatching, the chick was swaddled in a towel and put in the
same type of incubator used for premature infants. The chick
weighed about 6{ ounces.
   Its sex won't be determined for about a month because it must be
strong enough for a blood sample to be drawn.
   The chick will be reared by keepers using a hand puppet that
resembles an adult condor. The puppet is used to feed the chick and
help it identify with its species.
   The chick hatched from an egg laid <DATE>March 3</DATE> by the only pair of
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to be actively breeding. The egg was taken
from the parent birds and placed in the incubator in hope that the
parents would produce a second egg. That has not happened so far.
   All 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in captivity: 15 at
the Wild Animal Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. Fourteen birds
are female.
   The captive flock includes 13 condors hatched from eggs taken in
the wild over the past five years. Molloko was the first addition
since <DATE>April 1986</DATE>, when a chick named <PERSON>Nojoqui</PERSON> was hatched at the
park from an egg laid in the wild.
   Efforts to save the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, which has a wingspan of
up to 10 feet at maturity, rest with the captive breeding program.
The last known wild <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor was captured a year ago.
   The goal of the program is to rebuild the population until
condors can be sent back into the wild. The earliest anticipated
release would be <DATE>1992</DATE>, authorities have said. The oldest bird
hatched in captivity is 5 years old. Condors reach sexual maturity
at about age 7.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081290-0208 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 261263 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 12, 1990, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
469 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ENVIRONMENT: NOTES ABOUT YOUR SURROUNDINGS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Banner Year -- The numbers are coming in on the recently concluded breeding 
season for the endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least tern, and <DATE>1990</DATE> shaped up as a banner 
season at the <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica Ecological Reserve</ORGANIZATION>. Last season, 115 pairs of least 
terns nested there; this year, 239 total nests were counted. 
</P>
<P>
Because some birds build more than one nest for various reasons, the number of 
breeding pairs this season was probably slightly less than 239. But the most 
important number is how many successful fledglings were produced: 150, compared 
to last year's 45. 
</P>
<P>
The news on the small, gull-like bird was mixed at the <ORGANIZATION>Huntington State Beach</ORGANIZATION> 
colony. Last year, 70 pairs nested there, a number that dropped to 40 pairs 
this season. The good news is that 20 fledglings were produced, up from a 
disastrous five last season. The chicks at <LOCATION>Huntington</LOCATION> continued to fall prey to 
kestrels, while no predation problems were noted at <LOCATION>Bolsa Chica</LOCATION> this season. 
</P>
<P>
Estimated numbers for least terns at <ORGANIZATION>Upper Newport Bay Ecological Reserve</ORGANIZATION> 
remained relatively steady, between 60 and 70 pairs compared to last year's 74. 
About 50 fledglings are likely, according to state Fish and Game biologist 
<PERSON>Esther Burkett</PERSON>. She has not received numbers for the colony at <ORGANIZATION>Seal Beach 
National Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Overall, I would say that we had a really, really good year," <PERSON>Burkett</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
This is the first season that all the least terns nested on <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica</ORGANIZATION>'s south 
island, having been pushed off the reserve's north island by the continuing 
success of larger tern species that have moved northward in recent years. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica</ORGANIZATION> this season, counts estimate 1,000 elegant tern nests, 100 
Caspian tern nests and 100 <ORGANIZATION>Forster</ORGANIZATION>'s tern nests. Black skimmers are at 295 
nests, up from 170 <DATE>last year</DATE>, and their breeding season continues. The breeding 
success of the skimmers comes despite the fact that many received some oil 
damage in the <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE> American Trader spill off <LOCATION>Huntington Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
We're With the Band -- The state Fish and Game department is continuing to band 
many of the tern chicks that fledge at <LOCATION>Bolsa Chica</LOCATION>, particularly elegant tern 
and black skimmers. Chicks hatched this season have pink bands; <DATE>1989</DATE> birds have 
blue bands and <DATE>1988</DATE> birds have yellow bands. 
</P>
<P>
If you spot birds with these bands, you can help biologists by noting the date 
and location of the sighting, the number of birds with bands, the color of the 
bands and the species. Call <PERSON>Esther Burkett</PERSON> with the information: (714) 
537-0696. 
</P>
<P>
Museum News -- <ORGANIZATION>The Museum of Natural History and Science</ORGANIZATION>, which recently closed 
its doors in <LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>, has announced a <DATE>Nov. 17</DATE> opening date for its new 
interim site in <LOCATION>Aliso Viejo</LOCATION>. Exhibits planned for the new facility include 
space exploration, robotic dinosaur models, local Indian artifacts and local 
marine mammal fossils. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, California least terns nested in Bolsa Chica in record numbers during 
1990. Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900324-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-90 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorHatching     03-24 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Hatching,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condor Comeback Takes Wing with Two More Hatchings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hatchings of two healthy <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors late last week and the possibility of eight to 10 chicks in
all this breeding season could accelerate the program to return the
endangered species to the wild, a zoo official said.
   A 5.8-ounce bird named Kareya, from the Karok Indian word
meaning ``creator of all things,'' emerged at <TIME>4:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the
first of the vulturelike chicks to hatch at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>,
said spokeswoman <PERSON>Cindy Richardson</PERSON>. Its gender won't be known for
about three months.
   Kareya's hatching came only a little more <DATE>than 24 hours after
the second chick of the 1990</DATE> breeding season, <PERSON>Honsi</PERSON>, was hatched
early <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   It was <DATE>less than two years ago</DATE> that the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor
chick was hatched after being bred in captivity. A chick named
<PERSON>Molloko</PERSON> was hatched at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 29, 1988</DATE>, amid national
fanfare.
   The latest hatchings nudged the total population of the species
to 35, all in the two zoos. There were only 27 known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors when all were taken into captivity for breeding in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Scientists are trying to breed enough of the birds, which can
have a wingspan of nearly 10 feet, to begin returning some to their
natural habitat.
   Wildlife officials had planned on releasing the first of the
condors sometime between <DATE>1993</DATE> and <DATE>1995</DATE>. But <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>,
curator for birds at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, said the captive breeding
program has achieved such success that the first birds could be
released in the <LOCATION>Los Padres National Forest</LOCATION> next year.
   Officials hope to establish a wild flock there while they keep a
healthy captive flock, he said. Other release areas could include
the Grand Canyon or <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>.
   Two eggs are under incubation in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, and four in <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION>, making for a possible record breeding season, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
The incubation period for condor eggs is about two months.
   Under the captive breeding program, four chicks were hatched
last year, in addition to the one hatched in <DATE>1988</DATE>. The condor's
breeding season runs from <DATE>January</DATE> through <DATE>April</DATE>. In <DATE>1984</DATE>, eight
eggs were taken from the wild and hatched.
   ``We're hoping for between eight to 10 youngsters this year,''
<PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
   Kareya, like <PERSON>Honsi</PERSON>, appeared healthy and hungry, zoo officials
said.
   ``It's had its first feeding of minced mice,'' <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880430-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-88 0123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CondorEgg 3rdLd-Writethru a0892 04-30 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Egg, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0892,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condor Chick Hatches With Help From Its Keepers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 5 grafs to UPDATE with comments from news conference.
Picks up 5th graf pvs, `A recording...' Edits to conform.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor conceived in
captivity hatched <DATE>Friday</DATE>, its keepers using tweezers and their
fingertips to help the newest member of the nearly extinct species
break free from its shell, officials said.
   ``It's alive and it looks healthy,'' said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. ``It's resting now.
We don't have any other details.''
   The hatching represents a tremendous boost to efforts to save
the species. It brings the known population of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s
largest land bird to 28, all in captivity _ 15 at the park here and
13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The squawking infant, named Molloko, an Indian word for
``condor,'' was swaddled in a towel and placed in the same type of
incubator used for premature infants.
   ``Early <TIME>this morning</TIME> there were 27 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors left in
the world,'' said <PERSON>Bill Toone</PERSON>, curator of birds at the park. ``This
afternoon there's 28 of them, and we couldn't be more excited about
that.
   ``When the numbers are so low, one bird is seen as a very big
step away from extinction,'' <PERSON>Toone</PERSON> added.
   Although the tiny bird was not brought forth to ``meet the
press,'' its history-making birth was recorded on videotape and
shown at a press conference <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Earlier, the chick had become stuck in dried membrane and
albumen and could no longer rotate in the shell to peck its way
out. Its keepers removed it cautiously because of the danger of
rupturing blood vessels linked to egg membranes.
   A recording of vultures making hissing and grunting sounds was
played at intervals to duplicate the sounds the chick would hear in
a natural setting.
   Park officials had said they intended to intervene by <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
if the chick, which began hatching <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, hadn't emerged from
the shell. Allowing the hatching struggle to continue would
overexhaust the bird.
   The chick, conceived by the only known activing breeding pair of
the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, was expected to weigh about 9 ounces,
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. The species has a wingspan of up to 10 feet at
maturity.
   The 10-ounce blue-green egg, about 5 inches long, had been under
a 24-hour watch since <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, when keepers noticed ``pip''
cracks in one end signaling the start of hatching, which can take
three days.
   After the egg was laid <DATE>March 3</DATE>, it was taken away from the
parent birds and incubated artificially in hopes that the female
bird would produce a second egg. So far, this has not happened.
   It will be a while before the sex of the bird can be determined
through a blood test, officials said.
   Hanscom said that representatives of the Chumash Indian tribe
had been enlisted to select the name for the chick upon hatching.
   The tribe inhabited the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> area that most recently
served as <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor habitat, and the bird figures
prominently in the tribe's religion.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890421-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-89 1059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     04-21 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Alert' Condor Chick Takes First Feeding</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newborn <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick gobbled down
its first meal of minced mice and egg yolk and was pronounced alert
and healthy by its anxious keepers.
   An eyedropper was used <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to give the bird its first meal,
said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. The
bird, hatched <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, is the second <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor to be
conceived and produced in captivity and the 29th known member of
the critically endangered species.
   The initial feeding was withheld until <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to give the
chick, named <LOCATION>Mandan</LOCATION>, time to rest and build an appetite while being
monitored by keepers for signs of a working digestive system.
   ``It gobbled it down. It did so well with the first feeding that
it took two minced mice'' about an hour later, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. ``The
chick is alert and active and gives every appearance of a healthy
baby condor.''
   The 6.9-ounce chick was named after an Indian tribe native to
the eastern Rockies where condors lived hundreds of years ago. It
is the offspring of the same condor couple that produced <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>,
the year-old condor that was the first of the species conceived and
born in captivity.
   Mandan's sex will be determined in several weeks when it's
strong enough to undergo a blood test. Its hatching gives hope for
the future of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land birds, which have
wingspans up to 9{ feet, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Three other fertile condor eggs incubating at the park are
expected to hatch at various times within the next six weeks.
   All <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in the state's two
condor breeding stations. Fifteen birds are at the Wild Animal Park
and 14 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032990-0184 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 196714 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 29, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
539 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DOING A GOOD TURN; 
</P>
<P>
CREWS LAY TILE HOMES FOR ENDANGERED LEAST TERNS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HUNTINGTON BEACH 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Carrying a red clay tile that looked as if it belonged on an <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> roof, 
<PERSON>Elizabeth McBride</PERSON> looked for a bare spot on a sandy island in the <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica 
Ecological Reserve</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
McBride and six colleagues from the <ORGANIZATION>California Conservation Corps</ORGANIZATION> roamed the 
wildlife refuge on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, searching for spots to place the tiles that the 
endangered least tern will use to shelter its chicks. 
</P>
<P>
"I was just trying to see where another good place for a house might be," said 
<PERSON>McBride</PERSON>, 21, of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. "I was just thinking, 'If I were a bird, where 
would I want to live?' " 
</P>
<P>
The work of the <ORGANIZATION>Conservation Corps</ORGANIZATION> members is part of an effort to protect the 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least tern, a tiny gull-like bird that migrates from Central and 
<LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> and is expected to arrive at the reserve in about two weeks. "The 
Bolsa Chica area breeds <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of least terns left on the face of this <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>," 
said <PERSON>Curt Taucher</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>California Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game. 
"If we let that get away from us, we won't have any terns left." 
</P>
<P>
Environmentalists are encouraging <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> taxpayers to make a donation for 
endangered species such as the least tern on state tax forms. About <MONEY>$910,000</MONEY> 
was raised through this campaign last year to benefit rare, threatened and 
endangered species. 
</P>
<P>
As a flock of sandpipers waded in the nearby marsh, <ORGANIZATION>Conservation Corps</ORGANIZATION> workers 
scanned the ground, stepping lightly to avoid crushing the nests of other birds 
and scouting spots for tiles. 
</P>
<P>
Even though most of the hand-picked team of workers didn't know what a least 
tern was before this assignment, they enthusiastically installed the artificial 
nests for the gray-and-white terns. 
</P>
<P>
"I feel all the animals should be able to live," said <PERSON>Robert Bolton</PERSON>, 19, of <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION>. "They have the same right we do." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Chrystie Clark</PERSON> said she had helped clean up oil that washed up on beaches after 
the <ORGANIZATION>American Trader</ORGANIZATION> spill. She recalled seeing the rescue of an oil-coated 
gull. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm glad I could come out here again," said <PERSON>Clark</PERSON>, 20, of <LOCATION>Pleasanton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. 
"You want to do something for (the birds) besides clean up what a human did." 
</P>
<P>
Nature used to take care of sheltering the birds, providing driftwood in which 
fledgling least terns could hide from natural predators such as sparrow hawks, 
crows and red foxes. But the tern is not doing well in its competition with 
humans for open space. 
</P>
<P>
"These birds nest traditionally on bare sand beaches," said <PERSON>Charles Collins</PERSON>, a 
<LOCATION>Cal State Long Beach</LOCATION> biology professor who specializes in ornithology. "And 
since there's competition for space on the beach for a small bird and lots of 
humans, birds tend to lose out." 
</P>
<P>
After the volunteers finished laying down the tiles on the reserve's northern 
island, they set out for an island to the south, where they cleared land for 
bird nesting. 
</P>
<P>
The effort might seem like a lot of effort for a bird that weighs about 45 
grams when it reaches maturity, but wildlife biologists such as <PERSON>Esther Burkett</PERSON> 
say the endangered species must be preserved. 
</P>
<P>
"If the least tern were to disappear, the world wouldn't necessarily stop," 
<PERSON>Burkett</PERSON> said. "(But) at some point, we will lose too many species. You start 
losing one and there are repercussions that start going down the food chain." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Wildlife biologist Esther Burkett leads workers across Bolsa Chica 
reserve where they placed tiles for California least terns. ; Photo, A 
California least tern nests with her chick. California Department of Fish and 
Game; Photo, Two cormorants survey Bolsa Chica from atop a utility pole. Below, 
killdeer eggs at island in ecological reserve. ; Photo, Worker's boots slosh 
through the Bolsa Chica Ecological Reserve. ; Photo, Worker heads to an island 
to prepare shelters for least terns. ; Photo, One Good Tern. . .: Members of 
the California Conservation Corps prepared the Bolsa Chica wildlife refuge in 
Huntington Beach for the return of migrating least terns. The terns are 
exprected to arrive in about two weeks. Above, Chrystie Clark and others clear 
land on refuge. KEN HIVELY / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BIRDS; ENDANGERED SPECIES; WILDLIFE MANAGEMENT; BOLSA CHICA ECOLOGICAL RESERVE; 
HABITATS; NATURE RESERVES; WILDLIFE REFUGES; TAX FORMS; TAXES -- CALIFORNIA; 
CONTRIBUTIONS; VOLUNTEERS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081789-0024 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 95553 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 17, 1989, Thursday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 8; Column 6 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
664 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PLANNERS SAY NO TO WIND FARM IN HILLS NEAR GORMAN; 
</P>
<P>
PANEL CITES HARM TO BIRDS, RUSTIC SCENERY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVE PADILLA, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Los Angeles County</LOCATION> planners on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> rejected a proposal to build the 
county's first power-generating wind farm in the hills northeast of <PERSON>Gorman</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The five-member <ORGANIZATION>Regional Planning Commission</ORGANIZATION> said the project would destroy the 
rustic beauty of the area, promote erosion and harm wildlife, after one 
protester warned that the spinning blades of giant turbines would slice up 
passing birds "like they went through a Cuisinart." 
</P>
<P>
The commission unanimously voted down the proposal after a five-hour hearing 
attended by more than 150 people at <LOCATION>Santa Clarita City Hall</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Zond Systems</ORGANIZATION>, the largest producer of wind energy in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, had hoped to 
erect more than 300 windmills -- some as high as 150 feet -- on vacant, 
mountainous land near the tiny community best known as a truck stop along 
Interstate 5, south of the <LOCATION>Kern County</LOCATION> line. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Zond</ORGANIZATION>'s proposal drew opposition from a broad coalition that included the 
<ORGANIZATION>California Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game, the <ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club</ORGANIZATION>, a citizens group called Save the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain Committee</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Tejon 
Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, a wealthy landowning corporation with 200,000 acres in the area. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Ralphs Family 
</P>
<P>
Tehachapi-based <ORGANIZATION>Zond</ORGANIZATION> had the backing of the influential <ORGANIZATION>Ralphs</ORGANIZATION> family, a 
pioneer <PERSON>Gorman</PERSON> clan that founded the supermarket chain. The proposal had 
divided the small town -- <PERSON>Gorman</PERSON> has only 65 registered voters -- for months. 
The Save the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain Committee</ORGANIZATION> circulated petitions throughout the county and 
submitted more than 3,000 signatures opposing the windmills. 
</P>
<P>
The commissioners heard often-conflicting testimony during the hearing. 
</P>
<P>
Zond officials cited an environmental impact report that declared that the 
<MONEY>$100-million</MONEY> project would not significantly harm wildlife or the environment. 
The report said the proposed site was outside the routes usually traveled by 
the endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. The giant condor is now confined to 
captivity, but scientists hope to reintroduce the birds to the region in the 
early <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Linda Blum</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> said the windmills would raise a 
dangerous barrier in a former condor "flyway." <PERSON>Sherry Teresa</PERSON>, a wildlife 
biologist with the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game, said the environmental 
impact report was deficient. She said it failed to note that three endangered 
species -- the bald eagle, peregrine falcon and <PERSON>Swainson</PERSON>'s hawk -- have been 
sighted at the proposed wind farm site. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Russell Hemsath</PERSON>, speaking for the <ORGANIZATION>California State Racing Pigeon Organization</ORGANIZATION>, 
said, "Our birds would look like they went through a Cuisinart." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Steven W. Carothers</PERSON>, an environmental consultant for <ORGANIZATION>Zond</ORGANIZATION>, countered that 
the number of birds killed by windmills statewide is "relatively 
insignificant." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Zond</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>James Dehlsen</PERSON> tried to persuade the commissioners by touting 
windmills as clean producers of energy that would reduce pollution and the use 
of gas and oil. 'We like to think we're practicing environmentalists," he said. 
</P>
<P>
But commissioners rejected his argument, saying their concern was land use, not 
utility bills. 
</P>
<P>
Zond had originally proposed building 458 windmills but scaled that proposal 
down to 350. Dehlsen offered to cut back the proposal to 319 so that none of 
the giant machines would be visible from Interstate 5, a common complaint by 
the project's critics. 
</P>
<P>
Commissioners were not swayed. 'I really have a problem with this project," 
Commissioner <PERSON>Betty Fisher</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Commissioner Lee Strong agreed that the site was ill-suited to a wind farm but 
said that much of the opposition probably came from landowners with their own 
development plans. Referring to the parade of paid experts who testified for 
the opponents, Strong said: 'You can't tell me that the money that has been 
spent comes strictly from the people. It's coming from people who are concerned 
about 'what is going to happen to my piece of property?' " 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Dehlsen</PERSON> said it was too soon to predict whether <ORGANIZATION>Zond</ORGANIZATION> would appeal the 
commission's decision to the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Supervisors</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Planners voted down wind farm proposal after five-hour hearing attended 
by more than 150 people. RICARDO DeARATANHA / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06092182 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06092182 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; A chick, the world's 42nd California condor,
comes out of its shell  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  LOS-ANGELES; ANIMAL; PARK; BIRD; BIRTH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The world's 42nd California condor celebrated Easter with a meal of pureed
mice after emerging from its shell at the Los Angeles Zoo -- the latest
success story in an attempt to return the endangered birds to the wild.;   
The healthy chick emerged from its pale blue shell at 10:13 p.m. Saturday --
two hours too early for the zoo's public-relations department, said Mike
Wallace, director of the zoo's California Condor Recovery Project.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CONGRATULATIONS, IT'S A CONDOR
CHICK HATCHES IN L.A. ZOO'S CAPTIVE BREEDING
PROGRAM  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "You could tell our PR department was really trying to get us to slow this
bird down so he would hatch on Easter," chuckled <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>, who noted it would
have been the zoo's second Easter hatching in a row.;    "But as long as they
are healthy, we don't care when they hatch," he said.;    The new chick --
whose gender won't be known for three months or so -- was named Pawoko, a
Kawaiisu Indian word for condor drawn from a list provided by the state <ORGANIZATION>Native
American Commission.</ORGANIZATION>;    "We're feeling really good," said <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>. "This was
a really healthy hatch. The chick came out unassisted and weighed around 6
ounces.";    Pawoko is the sixth condor to be hatched in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> since the
zoo's participation in the joint program with the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park
began two years ago. Wallace has hopes it will be among the first of more than
a dozen birds to emerge this year.;    If the condors continue to breed as
successfully as they have in the past, it's possible that a small number could
be released into the wild by the end of the year -- almost two years ahead of
schedule, he said.;    In <DATE>1987</DATE>, when biologists rounded up the last of the 27
wild condors known to exist, they hoped their controversial captive breeding
program would enable them to increase the species sufficiently to re-introduce
them into a remote <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> sanctuary.;    With a 9 1/2-foot wingspan
that makes them <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest bird, the condors in prehistoric times
ranged up and down the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION>. The bird's decline is believed to be a
result of the introduction of man into their habitat.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Daily News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910401  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  369  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 1, 1991
00092182,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880502-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-88 0455EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     05-02 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doing Well and Eating Lots</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor born to captive
parents is downing about 30 minced mice a day and slowly gaining
weight, say keepers who are watching the bald, fluffy chick for
infection.
   ``So far so good,'' <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>
Wild Animal Park, said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``We're not through the most
critical period, which is 72 hours.''
   The chick, named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, an Indian word condor, was hatched
with human help <DATE>Friday</DATE>, boosting the endangered species' numbers to
28.
   It ate 28 mice <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and 30 more by <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>Ms.
Baker</PERSON> said.
   ``The appetite of the bird is very good,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Baker</PERSON>,
adding that the chick had regained its birth rate of 6} ounces. As
adults, the birds have a wingspan up to 10 feet.
   The chick had very bright eyes and its bodily functions seemed
to be operating correctly, she said.
   The fist-sized bird's attachment to its yolk sac, similar to a
human infant's umbilical cord, was healing well.
   Molloko hatched from an egg laid by the only pair of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors known to be actively breeding.
   All 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in captivity: 15 at
the Wild Animal Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. Fourteen birds
are female. The chick's sex has not been determined.
   The flock includes 13 condors hatched from eggs taken in the
wild during the past five years. Molloko was the first addition
since <DATE>April 1986</DATE>, when a chick hatched at the park from an egg laid
in the wild.
   Efforts to save the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor from extinction rest with
the captive breeding program. The last known condor in the wild was
captured last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100290-0168 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 286552 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 2, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 2; Column 4; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
279 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CLIPBOARD; 
</P>
<P>
BREEDING BIRD: WESTERN KINGBIRD (TYRANNUS VERTICALIS) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Description: Lemon yellow belly and ashen gray head; distinctive black tail 
with narrow white edging on outer feathers. Dark wings contrast with paler 
olive back and bill is shorter than other similar species. 
</P>
<P>
Orange-red crown patch is usually concealed. Juvenile has paler yellow belly 
and brownish tinge on breast as well as buffy edged wing coverts. Length: 8 
inches. 
</P>
<P>
Habitat: Roadsides, savanna, dry open country, agricultural lands, wires. 
</P>
<P>
Diet: Berries and insects. 
</P>
<P>
Displays: In frenetic courtship flight, male darts into air, fluttering, 
vibrating feathers, and trilling. 
</P>
<P>
Nest: Usually on horizontal branch near tree trunk or on man-made structure; 
lined with plant down, cotton or hair. 
</P>
<P>
Eggs: White, creamy, pinkish hues blotched with brown, lavender or gray; 1 inch 
long. 
</P>
<P>
Notes: The Western <PERSON>Kingbird</PERSON> is the most widespread of its species in 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Voice: Shrill, bickering calls; common call is a sharp whit or whit-ker-whit. 
</P>
<P>
Breeding bird atlas: To report bird breeding activity in your neighborhood, or 
to get information on the breeding bird atlas (now in its fifth and final 
year), call Sea and <ORGANIZATION>Sage Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> members <PERSON>Sylvia Gallagher</PERSON>, (714) 
962-8990, or <PERSON>Nancy Kenyon</PERSON>, (714) 786-3160. 
</P>
<P>
Note: Map is divided into 5-kilometer squares so that <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> 
volunteers can more easily survey areas on a regular basis. 
</P>
<P>
Sources: Sea and Sage Audubon Society; "The Birder's Handbook," <PERSON>Ehrlich</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dobkin</PERSON> 
and Wheye, Fireside Books (<DATE>1988</DATE>); "Field Guide to the Birds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>," 
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1987</DATE>); "Birds of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>: Status and 
Distribution," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1981</DATE>). 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Drawing, WESTERN KINGBIRD (Tyrannus verticalis) ; Map, Southern California, 
DORIS SHIELDS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA062390-0010 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 237521 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 23, 1990, Saturday, Ventura County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 2; Column 3 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
585 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VENTURA COUNTY NEWS ROUNDUP: SANTA CLARA RIVER; 
</P>
<P>
BIRD WATCHERS HELP TERNS NEST IN PEACE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CAROL WEINSTOCK 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Armed with signs, two-way radios and portable fences, <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> 
bird-watchers are helping safeguard a small gray-and-white bird species that 
faces extinction. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> least tern, listed as being at risk since <DATE>1970</DATE>, nests along the 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> coastline between the months of <DATE>May</DATE> and <DATE>August</DATE>. Nesting sites in 
<LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> include a section of the <LOCATION>Santa Clara River</LOCATION> estuary in <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Point Mugu</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ormond Beach</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oxnard</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The birds lay their purple-and-brown speckled eggs near the water and must be 
protected from beach-goers, who could easily trample them, said <PERSON>Don Davis</PERSON>, vice 
president of the western <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The birds scrape a spot in the sand and lay their eggs, which are well 
camouflaged. 
</P>
<P>
The birds are protected at their breeding grounds at Point Mugu because the 
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> property is off-limits to most people. And the <LOCATION>Ormond Beach</LOCATION> nesting area, 
a favorite for off-road vehicles, has been partially sealed off and is 
patrolled by the <ORGANIZATION>Oxnard Police Department</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But at the <LOCATION>Santa Clara River</LOCATION> estuary, the terns nest in an increasingly popular 
area. So for the past five years, the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> -- with help from the 
city of <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Ventura Port District</LOCATION>, the state Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Game Commission</ORGANIZATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>McGrath State Beach</ORGANIZATION> rangers -- fences a 500-by-200-foot area of beach as a 
breeding ground from <DATE>late April</DATE> to late <DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The four-foot-high chain-link fence cuts the area off to foot traffic and is 
surrounded by signs informing people that it is a nesting area. 
</P>
<P>
On weekends, about 45 <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> members rotate shifts from noon until 
dark, answering questions and keeping people at a distance from the birds, who 
make a distinctive sound like a Kewpie doll squeaking, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"People are understanding and cooperative," said monitor <PERSON>Bobbe Dorsey</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But unleashed dogs have to be chased away, she said. 
</P>
<P>
Monitors carry two-way radios to notify rangers or police if they need help but 
have not had to use them, <PERSON>Dorsey</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The fence also protects the terns from wild cats, foxes and weasels that live 
nearby. 
</P>
<P>
The terns themselves handle threats from aerial predators. 
</P>
<P>
When a sea gull flies over the nesting area, the colony of about 45 terns takes 
flight and harasses it. 
</P>
<P>
"Terns are very agile and can fly loops around a poor old lumbering gull," 
<PERSON>Davis</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
This season, the colony is larger than usual, in part because the Point Mugu 
nesting ground was washed out by a storm Memorial Day weekend. 
</P>
<P>
It is now mating season for the gray-and-white birds, which are about nine 
inches long with a 20-inch wing span. In the birds' mating ritual, the male 
first presents the female with a fish and bobs his head repeatedly. After they 
mate, the female lays one to four eggs within a couple of days. Incubation 
lasts 3 1/2 weeks with parents taking turns on the nest. 
</P>
<P>
Within a day of breaking from the shell, the speckled chicks can scurry to hide 
under the short dune plants. 
</P>
<P>
Both parents catch minnows and sticklebacks from nearby ponds or smelt from the 
ocean to feed their hungry brood. 
</P>
<P>
As chicks grow feathers, the family leaves the nest to live by various ponds in 
the county, including those at golf courses. 
</P>
<P>
In the <DATE>fall</DATE>, the terns fly south to winter in southern <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1989</DATE>, about 1,233 pairs of least terns bred at 28 sites between <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> 
and the <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay Area</LOCATION>, according to a field study by the state 
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game. <PERSON>CAROL WEINSTOCK</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mary Jane Davis, left, and Linda O'Neill, members of the Tern Watch 
group, carefully observe the rare birds. SCOTT HARRISON / For The Times; Photo, 
California least tern sits on a nest. The birds come to local beaches to mate. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880722-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-88 1250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Condors     07-22 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condors,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condors To Be Released As Forerunners To California Condors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAUREN BLAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four young Andean condors are going to be
introduced to the <ORGANIZATION>Los Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION> in an experiment that
wildlife experts hope will lead the way to eventually returning
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors to the wild.
   Scientists said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they believe the information they get
from monitoring the Andean condors will help them avoid problems
when they begin releasing <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors in the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>.
   There are only 28 known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, the largest flying
birds in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, and all of them are at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo
and the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. Scientists hope to save the
species by breeding the birds in captivity to build up the
population and later releasing them.
   The last free <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor was captured in <DATE>April 1987</DATE>.
   Although the Andean condors, which are native to <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>,
are considered endangered, there are thousands of them.
   Researchers in the two-year, <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> program will start with
newborn condors that haven't developed any domesticated habits.
   Nine zoos have sent eggs to the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and the wild
animal park. After hatching, the chicks will be kept in captivity
for three months, using puppets that resemble adult condors to feed
them, said <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>, curator of birds at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo
and the project's field coordinator.
   ``We have to make sure the birds have some fear of humans to
protect them,'' <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said. ``When they see a human on the
horizon, it may be a hunter.''
   At the age of three months the birds will be taken to a large
outdoor cage, and they will be released when they are about 7
months old, the age they would normally leave the nest, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>
said.
   The first chicks will be three months old next month and are
tentatively scheduled to be moved the weekend of <DATE>Aug. 19</DATE> to a spot
near the <ORGANIZATION>Hopper Mountain Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION> in northern <LOCATION>Ventura
County</LOCATION>, northwest of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   A group of eight scientists and technicians and 200 volunteers
will monitor the birds' moves by radio transmitters to distinguish
eating patterns and other habits. Scientists said they will provide
food for the birds throughout the experiment.
   The observers will periodically recapture the birds to monitor
their health and check their transmitters, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>, the lead agency in the
program, will provide protection for the birds, wildlife inspector
<PERSON>Ron Drifka</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880304-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-88 0634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorEgg     03-04 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Egg,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Condor Egg Breeds Hope For Species</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first egg produced by a pair of captive
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors is a huge success for biologists trying to save
the endangered species, even if it proves to be infertile, a
curator says.
   The egg, laid <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>, will be
inspected for fertility <DATE>Monday</DATE>, officials said.
   ``If it's not fertile, we would still remain happy,'' said <PERSON>Bill
Toone</PERSON> curator of birds for the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, which is affiliated
with the park. ``We (now) know they will breed in captivity.''
   Only 27 of the giant birds exist, all in captivity at the park
or the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The 10-ounce, pale blue-green egg was moved from a nest to an
electronic incubator, said park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>. If fertile,
the egg is expected to hatch within two months.
   The egg may be infertile because the female is old and her mate
may be sexually immature, park officials said.
   By taking the egg from its parents at an early point, scientists
hope to induce the pair to produce a second egg to replace the one
they lost.
   The incubator will maintain a constant temperature and humidity
for the egg. Handlers will turn it 180 degrees twice a day,
imitating the behavior of a mother condor's care in the wild.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, which have a wingspan of about 9 feet, are
dark reddish-brown, with a curved beak. They were decimated in the
wild by lead poisoning from eating lead shot in animal carcasses,
biologists said.
   The last one living in the wild was captured and brought to the
Wild Animal Park <DATE>last April</DATE> in the effort to save the species.
   Since <DATE>1981</DATE>, scientists have successfully hatched 13 condors in
captivity from eggs taken in the wild.
   Wildlife biologists hope to breed sufficient numbers of the
condor in captivity and release the captive-bred birds into a safe
