<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880430-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-88 1646EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorChick     04-30 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Chick,0626</SECOND>
<HEAD>Only Condor Chick Conceived In Captivity Eats First Meals</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hungry bundle of fluff named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, the
only <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick conceived in captivity, gobbled minced
mice <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and keepers of the endangered species were
encouraged by its appetite.
   The newly hatched chick, which raised the condor population to
28, ate its first meal from the fingertips of a handler at <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
and ate again at hourly intervals, said <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON>, spokeswoman
for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   ``The chick was hungry and ate everything it was offered,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Baker</PERSON> said. ``Everyone seems very pleased with the progress of the
chick. But the first 10 days are critical, for anybody, human or
animal.''
   The chick's diet was a combination of minced baby mice and
chicken egg yolk, she said. The meals fed to the chick, which is
slightly larger than a person's fist, amounted to about two
tablespoons of food each time.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Interior Secretary <PERSON>Donald Hodel</PERSON> congratulated the Wild
Animal Park staff for the successful hatching.
   ``The hatching of the world's first captive-bred condor is a
milestone that we've been awaiting for years,'' <PERSON>Hodel</PERSON> said in a
statement released in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Interior Department</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
recovery program.
   ``This small chick represents a big step back from the brink of
extinction and a big step forward for recovery of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor,'' he said.
   Keepers delicately wielding tweezers helped the chick break free
of its avocado-size egg at <TIME>5:38 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, ending a 61{-hour
hatching process that began when the chick first pecked cracks in
the shell <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The laborious process of helping the bird get free, led by
biologist <PERSON>Cyndi Keuhler</PERSON>, took nearly eight hours.
   Molloko is an Indian word for the giant condor species. The name
originates from the <LOCATION>Sacramento Valley Maidu</LOCATION> tribe and was chosen by
a council of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> tribes last week, <PERSON>Ms. Baker</PERSON> said.
   After hatching, the chick was swaddled in a towel and put in the
same type of incubator used for premature infants. The chick
weighed about 6{ ounces.
   Its sex won't be determined for about a month because it must be
strong enough for a blood sample to be drawn.
   The chick will be reared by keepers using a hand puppet that
resembles an adult condor. The puppet is used to feed the chick and
help it identify with its species.
   The chick hatched from an egg laid <DATE>March 3</DATE> by the only pair of
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to be actively breeding. The egg was taken
from the parent birds and placed in the incubator in hope that the
parents would produce a second egg. That has not happened so far.
   All 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in captivity: 15 at
the Wild Animal Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. Fourteen birds
are female.
   The captive flock includes 13 condors hatched from eggs taken in
the wild over the past five years. Molloko was the first addition
since <DATE>April 1986</DATE>, when a chick named <PERSON>Nojoqui</PERSON> was hatched at the
park from an egg laid in the wild.
   Efforts to save the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, which has a wingspan of
up to 10 feet at maturity, rest with the captive breeding program.
The last known wild <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor was captured a year ago.
   The goal of the program is to rebuild the population until
condors can be sent back into the wild. The earliest anticipated
release would be <DATE>1992</DATE>, authorities have said. The oldest bird
hatched in captivity is 5 years old. Condors reach sexual maturity
at about age 7.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880304-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-88 0634EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorEgg     03-04 0328</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Egg,0340</SECOND>
<HEAD>California Condor Egg Breeds Hope For Species</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first egg produced by a pair of captive
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors is a huge success for biologists trying to save
the endangered species, even if it proves to be infertile, a
curator says.
   The egg, laid <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>, will be
inspected for fertility <DATE>Monday</DATE>, officials said.
   ``If it's not fertile, we would still remain happy,'' said <PERSON>Bill
Toone</PERSON> curator of birds for the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, which is affiliated
with the park. ``We (now) know they will breed in captivity.''
   Only 27 of the giant birds exist, all in captivity at the park
or the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The 10-ounce, pale blue-green egg was moved from a nest to an
electronic incubator, said park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>. If fertile,
the egg is expected to hatch within two months.
   The egg may be infertile because the female is old and her mate
may be sexually immature, park officials said.
   By taking the egg from its parents at an early point, scientists
hope to induce the pair to produce a second egg to replace the one
they lost.
   The incubator will maintain a constant temperature and humidity
for the egg. Handlers will turn it 180 degrees twice a day,
imitating the behavior of a mother condor's care in the wild.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, which have a wingspan of about 9 feet, are
dark reddish-brown, with a curved beak. They were decimated in the
wild by lead poisoning from eating lead shot in animal carcasses,
biologists said.
   The last one living in the wild was captured and brought to the
Wild Animal Park <DATE>last April</DATE> in the effort to save the species.
   Since <DATE>1981</DATE>, scientists have successfully hatched 13 condors in
captivity from eggs taken in the wild.
   Wildlife biologists hope to breed sufficient numbers of the
condor in captivity and release the captive-bred birds into a safe
environment in the wild.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880502-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-88 0455EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     05-02 0291</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doing Well and Eating Lots</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor born to captive
parents is downing about 30 minced mice a day and slowly gaining
weight, say keepers who are watching the bald, fluffy chick for
infection.
   ``So far so good,'' <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>
Wild Animal Park, said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``We're not through the most
critical period, which is 72 hours.''
   The chick, named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, an Indian word condor, was hatched
with human help <DATE>Friday</DATE>, boosting the endangered species' numbers to
28.
   It ate 28 mice <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and 30 more by <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>Ms.
Baker</PERSON> said.
   ``The appetite of the bird is very good,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Baker</PERSON>,
adding that the chick had regained its birth rate of 6} ounces. As
adults, the birds have a wingspan up to 10 feet.
   The chick had very bright eyes and its bodily functions seemed
to be operating correctly, she said.
   The fist-sized bird's attachment to its yolk sac, similar to a
human infant's umbilical cord, was healing well.
   Molloko hatched from an egg laid by the only pair of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors known to be actively breeding.
   All 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in captivity: 15 at
the Wild Animal Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. Fourteen birds
are female. The chick's sex has not been determined.
   The flock includes 13 condors hatched from eggs taken in the
wild during the past five years. Molloko was the first addition
since <DATE>April 1986</DATE>, when a chick hatched at the park from an egg laid
in the wild.
   Efforts to save the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor from extinction rest with
the captive breeding program. The last known condor in the wild was
captured last year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890202-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-89 0211EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Condors Bjt   02-02 0678</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condors, Bjt,0695</SECOND>
<HEAD>Captive California Condors Court; Eagles Divebomb Andean Condor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Love is in the air at two zoos where
scientists hope the world's last 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors will mate
themselves away from the brink of extinction, a biologist says.
   Meanwhile, one of seven Andean condors freed into the wilderness
chickened out of a dogfight with two golden eagles half her size.
   ``We've got all sorts of great things happening with the Andeans
and some equally exciting things happening with the captive
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors. We're very encouraged,'' <PERSON>Joseph Dowhan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> condor recovery coordinator, said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Only 28 endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors remain, 14 in captivity at
the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and 14 others at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>
in <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>. Scientists hope the vulture-like creatures, which are
<LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land birds with 9{-foot wingspans, will
reproduce enough so that some can be returned to the wild in five to
10 years.
   Courtship started in early <DATE>January</DATE> among four pairs of the birds
at <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> and two pairs in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said during a
phone interview from his office in <LOCATION>Ventura</LOCATION>.
   One of the courting pairs in <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, male condor AC-4 and
female UN-1, started mating early in <DATE>January</DATE>, he added. Last <DATE>April</DATE>,
the same pair produced a female chick named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, the first
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor conceived and hatched in captivity.
   Scientists believe condors lay eggs 30 to 35 days after
fertilization, but mating doesn't necessarily result in
fertilization, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   The seven Andean condors, donated by zoos across the nation, were
freed into rugged mountains 50 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in an
experiment meant to help biologists learn the best way to handle,
release and monitor <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors once they reproduce in
adequate numbers. About 1,000 to 2,000 of the wild Andean birds
remain in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   The most recent release was <DATE>Jan. 21</DATE>, when biologists removed
netting from a roost box and feeding platform that housed four
Andean condors in the <ORGANIZATION>Sespe Condor Sanctuary</ORGANIZATION>.
   On the same day, a hostile encounter occurred between two golden
eagles and one of three other Andeans, which had been freed <DATE>Dec. 17</DATE>
from the nearby <ORGANIZATION>Hopper Mountain National Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON>
said.
   The 10-month-old Andean, condor Y1, flew from <ORGANIZATION>Hopper Mountain</ORGANIZATION>
onto the eagles' turf, where ``the eagles made several `stoops,' or
aggressive drives, toward the condor and forced it to the ground,''
said a Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> news release.
   Dowhan said the condor soon returned to the air and ``made a
beeline to the security of its home (roost box). It was intimidated
by the eagles,'' which have 5-foot wingspans.
   The Andean condors, which will be recaptured and re-released in
<LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> when the experiment ends next year, will encounter a
number of other birds in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s mountains and ``recognize some
will be territorial and others may serve as pilots to where food is
present,'' he said.
   There hasn't been much flight activity among the four Andeans
released <DATE>Jan. 21</DATE>, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   Condor R4 immediately flew 120 feet into a brushy thicket and
couldn't figure out how to get back to her roost box. Biologists
caught her <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and returned her to the box, where <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said
``she ate right away _ carcasses of stillborn calves.''
   Dowhan said it will be months before the biologists place food
for the carrion-eating condors away from their roost boxes in an
effort to teach them to forage.
   Two of the three Andeans freed from <ORGANIZATION>Hopper Mountain</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>December</DATE>
flew about three miles on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and passed over the Sespe roost
box, but the four condors there ``didn't notice them. They were
sleeping,'' <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   Back at the zoos, the six males court the females by arching
their necks, looking at the ground, and trying to encircle the
females with their outstretched wings. Dowhan said each female
``will try to come up under the male and nibble at his beak. That's
a positive reaction.''
   Dowhan said the breeding season runs from <DATE>January</DATE> to <DATE>April</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880303-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-03-88 2238EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorEgg     03-03 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Egg,0272</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Egg Laid by Rare California Condors</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor <DATE>Thursday</DATE> laid the first egg
ever produced in captivity by a pair of the endangered birds,
boosting efforts to save the species, the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal
Park</LOCATION> said.
   If the egg hatches at the end of its two-month incubation, it
will be the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor ever conceived in captivity,
officials said. Only 27 of the birds exist, all in captivity, said
park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>.
   Biologists moved the egg from the nest to an incubator,
according to plan, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said. The egg may not produce an
offspring because the female is old and her mate, a young male, may
be sexually immature, park officials cautioned.
   By taking the egg from its parents at an early point, scientists
hope to induce the pair to ``double-clutch,'' or produce a second
egg to replace the lost one.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors have been decimated in the wild by lead
poisoning, caused by eating lead shot in animal carcasses,
biologists said.
   The last <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor in the wild was captured and brought
to the Wild Animal Park on <DATE>April 3, 1987</DATE> in a last bid to restore
the vanishing species.
   Fourteen of the birds are kept at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> park in
enclosures not on view to the public. The 13 others are similarly
housed at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   Since <DATE>1981</DATE>, scientists have hatched 13 condors in captivity from
eggs taken in the wild. The birds, which have a wingspan of about 9
feet, are dark reddish-brown with a curved beak.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900324-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-90 1235EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorHatching     03-24 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Hatching,0427</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condor Comeback Takes Wing with Two More Hatchings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES ANDERSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The hatchings of two healthy <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors late last week and the possibility of eight to 10 chicks in
all this breeding season could accelerate the program to return the
endangered species to the wild, a zoo official said.
   A 5.8-ounce bird named Kareya, from the Karok Indian word
meaning ``creator of all things,'' emerged at <TIME>4:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the
first of the vulturelike chicks to hatch at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>,
said spokeswoman <PERSON>Cindy Richardson</PERSON>. Its gender won't be known for
about three months.
   Kareya's hatching came only a little more <DATE>than 24 hours after
the second chick of the 1990</DATE> breeding season, <PERSON>Honsi</PERSON>, was hatched
early <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   It was <DATE>less than two years ago</DATE> that the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor
chick was hatched after being bred in captivity. A chick named
<PERSON>Molloko</PERSON> was hatched at <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 29, 1988</DATE>, amid national
fanfare.
   The latest hatchings nudged the total population of the species
to 35, all in the two zoos. There were only 27 known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors when all were taken into captivity for breeding in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Scientists are trying to breed enough of the birds, which can
have a wingspan of nearly 10 feet, to begin returning some to their
natural habitat.
   Wildlife officials had planned on releasing the first of the
condors sometime between <DATE>1993</DATE> and <DATE>1995</DATE>. But <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>,
curator for birds at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, said the captive breeding
program has achieved such success that the first birds could be
released in the <LOCATION>Los Padres National Forest</LOCATION> next year.
   Officials hope to establish a wild flock there while they keep a
healthy captive flock, he said. Other release areas could include
the Grand Canyon or <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>.
   Two eggs are under incubation in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, and four in <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION>, making for a possible record breeding season, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
The incubation period for condor eggs is about two months.
   Under the captive breeding program, four chicks were hatched
last year, in addition to the one hatched in <DATE>1988</DATE>. The condor's
breeding season runs from <DATE>January</DATE> through <DATE>April</DATE>. In <DATE>1984</DATE>, eight
eggs were taken from the wild and hatched.
   ``We're hoping for between eight to 10 youngsters this year,''
<PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
   Kareya, like <PERSON>Honsi</PERSON>, appeared healthy and hungry, zoo officials
said.
   ``It's had its first feeding of minced mice,'' <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881123-0069 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-23-88 0709EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Condors     11-23 0621</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condors,0640</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condors Await Test Release</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to remove Bjt designator</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SESPE CONDOR SANCTUARY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Six Andean condors are
napping and munching on beef and chopped rats as they await release
into the wild in an experiment aimed at saving their <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor cousins from extinction.
   ``It will be a credit to humankind if we can preserve the animals
of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, and the condor is but one animal facing dire
straits,'' said <PERSON>Jeff Opdycke</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>
official who toured the Andean condor release site with reporters
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Of thousands of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors that once soared in the early
<DATE>1800s</DATE>, only 28 of the vulture-like, carrion-eating birds remain
alive. With 9-1@2-foot wingspans, they are <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest
bird.
   All the survivors are in captive breeding programs at the <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   In five to 10 years, after enough of them have produced offspring
in captivity, some of the young birds will be re-introduced into the
wild in another attempt to avoid extinction.
   To learn the best way to release the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors and
assure their survival, researchers are using young Andean condors
donated by various zoos as stand-ins for their more endangered
relatives. One thousand to 2,000 Andean condors remain in the wilds
of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>.
   ``These are surrogates,'' said <PERSON>Joseph Dowhan</PERSON>, condor recovery
coordinator for the Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``We're going to test
release techniques, release sites, and train people.''
   Seven of the Andean birds will be freed in <DATE>December</DATE> and <DATE>January</DATE>
into the 53,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>Sespe Condor Sanctuary</ORGANIZATION>, 50 miles northwest of
downtown <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   Along with up to 10 others to be freed late next year, they will
be rounded up when the <MONEY>$440,000</MONEY> study is done in two or three years,
then released permanently in their native <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>.
   About a dozen reporters were allowed to observe three of the
birds on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in a tour led by officials of the Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Service</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The three young female condors, all about five months old and
weighing 19 to 21 pounds, sat in the shade, napping in the
net-enclosed half of their 35-by-16-foot roosting box, which sits
atop sawed-off telephone poles 10 feet above the ground to protect
them from black bears and coyotes.
   Biologists sneak into the cage at night to deliver meals of calf
meat, ground horse meat and chopped rats, said <PERSON>Mike Wallace</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo's curator of birds.
   The condors displayed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> will be released in <DATE>January</DATE>, along
with a fourth bird that had not yet arrived.
   Scientists hope that once released, the birds will stay in the
sanctuary and away from areas where wild <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors died
from what officials believe was lead poisoning. They were poisoned
by eating the carcasses of coyotes that were trapped and shot, or
the remains of wounded deer that died after escaping hunters,
scientists said.
   <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said others probably were shot, and some may have been
killed by colliding with power lines.
   Development along <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s coast and <LOCATION>San Joaquin Valley</LOCATION> also
gradually destroyed much condor habitat, researchers believe.
   So far, only one <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick has been hatched in
captivity. That is the seven-month-old <PERSON>Moloko</PERSON>, who resides at the
<LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. Dowhan hopes one to five more chicks
will hatch next year.
   Four of the last five wild breeding pairs of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors
vanished in <DATE>1984-1985</DATE>. In <DATE>1986</DATE>, the Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> made a
controversial decision to round up the last six wild birds to
prevent their demise.
   So far, attempts to save the condors have cost about <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890421-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-21-89 1059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     04-21 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0304</SECOND>
<HEAD>`Alert' Condor Chick Takes First Feeding</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A newborn <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick gobbled down
its first meal of minced mice and egg yolk and was pronounced alert
and healthy by its anxious keepers.
   An eyedropper was used <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to give the bird its first meal,
said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. The
bird, hatched <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, is the second <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor to be
conceived and produced in captivity and the 29th known member of
the critically endangered species.
   The initial feeding was withheld until <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to give the
chick, named <LOCATION>Mandan</LOCATION>, time to rest and build an appetite while being
monitored by keepers for signs of a working digestive system.
   ``It gobbled it down. It did so well with the first feeding that
it took two minced mice'' about an hour later, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. ``The
chick is alert and active and gives every appearance of a healthy
baby condor.''
   The 6.9-ounce chick was named after an Indian tribe native to
the eastern Rockies where condors lived hundreds of years ago. It
is the offspring of the same condor couple that produced <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>,
the year-old condor that was the first of the species conceived and
born in captivity.
   Mandan's sex will be determined in several weeks when it's
strong enough to undergo a blood test. Its hatching gives hope for
the future of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land birds, which have
wingspans up to 9{ feet, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Three other fertile condor eggs incubating at the park are
expected to hatch at various times within the next six weeks.
   All <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to exist are in the state's two
condor breeding stations. Fifteen birds are at the Wild Animal Park
and 14 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022589-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 23294 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 25, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 1; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
679 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
A FIRST FOR BIRD BORN IN CAPTIVITY; 
</P>
<P>
CONDOR HATCHED IN ZOO LAYS MILESTONE EGG 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TOM GORMAN, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Wildlife officials on <DATE>Friday</DATE> heralded the laying of yet another <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
condor egg in captivity -- the third in a week -- and proclaimed the newest egg 
especially significant because it was the first laid by a condor which itself 
was hatched in captivity and has never known the wild. 
</P>
<P>
"This is a behavioral milestone," said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman for the <LOCATION>San Diego 
Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>, which is home to 15 of the 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors now in 
captivity. The rest live at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, and none is believed still in 
the wild. 
</P>
<P>
Of the 28 condors, 14 were born in captivity, either at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo or 
the Wild Animal Park. But 13 of those came from eggs taken from the wild, and 
the 14th was an egg that was conceived in captivity by a breeding pair that was 
taken from the wild. 
</P>
<P>
The newest egg, however, was laid by a condor named Almiyi, which was hatched 
in captivity. 
</P>
<P>
"We now know that a condor who has only known a captive life is capable of 
reproducing, and that will have to be the case if we hope to keep the species 
alive," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. "We can't keep relying on condors taken from the wild 
laying eggs, because they will eventually die off, and we will only have birds 
hatched in captivity." 
</P>
<P>
He cautioned that, although the egg-laying itself is significant, there is 
concern that the egg may not be fertile because <PERSON>Almiyi</PERSON> is 6 years old, and 
condors are generally not sexually mature until age 7. 
</P>
<P>
The newest egg was laid between dusk <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and dawn <DATE>Friday</DATE> in the Wild 
Animal Park's so-called "condorminium" away from public view, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
Gestation lasts 55 to 60 days, but officials hope to determine within 4 to 10 
days whether the egg is fertile by placing a high-intensity lamp behind it and 
looking for development. 
</P>
<P>
Almiyi's breeding partner was Paxa, who was born in the wild in <DATE>1981</DATE> and 
captured in <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The newest addition is the third <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor egg to be laid in recent 
days. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo officials discovered that one of their captive pairs 
of condors -- Cuyama and <LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION> -- had produced an egg, and it was whisked on 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to the Wild Animal Park east of <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>, because of its experience in 
handling <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor eggs. 
</P>
<P>
That breeding pair also is about 6 years old, and officials say their egg may 
also prove infertile. It was the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor egg laid at the <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. 
</P>
<P>
Also on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, two condors at the Wild Animal Park laid their second egg in 
captivity. The pair, known as UN1 and AC4, are the same that produced the 
female chick Molloko from the first egg laid in captivity last <DATE>March</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Hanscom said that, although the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> egg and the most recent egg may 
both be infertile, because of the youth of the breeding pairs, "we're 
encouraged by the fact that they're giving it a try." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
7 <ORGANIZATION>Males Give Courtship Displays 
</P>
<P>
Officials</ORGANIZATION> note that, between the two animal facilities, at least seven males 
are giving courtship displays this season. 
</P>
<P>
For each of the three breeding pairs, officials took the egg with the hope that 
the pairs would double-clutch, or try to replace the missing egg with another 
one, before the end of their breeding season. In the wild, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors 
produce and raise, on the 
</P>
<P>
average, one chick every two years. 
</P>
<P>
The fact that birds taken from the wild would produce eggs in captivity was the 
significant milestone reached with the birth last <DATE>March of Molloko</DATE>, <LOCATION>Hanscom</LOCATION> 
noted. But the newest lesson has even farther-reaching ramifications, because 
it offers behavioral proof that birds that have never experienced the wild 
still will breed. 
</P>
<P>
Besides trying to promote double-clutching, handlers take eggs from parents to 
help ensure their successful hatching. Officials say they are concerned that 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors have little experience at parenting, and they want to take 
as few chances as possible. 
</P>
<P>
Wild Animal Park officials noted, for instance, that after UN1 and AC4 produced 
their egg on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the male, AC4, lunged at the egg, striking it with its 
beak. The egg was removed by technicians before any damage was done. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890522-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-22-89 1037EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     05-22 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0266</SECOND>
<HEAD>Year's Third Condor Hatching Ups Species Count to 31</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Wildlife officials believe the endangered
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor is on the rebound after the hatching of a fourth
bird bred in captivity.
   Kaduku, whose Konkow Indian name means ``very strong being, both
physically and spiritually,'' became the 31st known condor when it
popped out of its shell <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>
without much help from keepers.
   The chick weighed in at 5.8 ounces. Its aqua-colored egg was
laid on Easter.
   ``This is the first time in two decades that there have been
more than 30 of the birds,'' said park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>. ``We
expect a lot more hatches next year.''
   All known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, which are <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest
land birds with wingspans up to 9{ feet, have been captured in
hopes of rebuilding their numbers to the point where the species
can be reintroduced in the wild.
   Seventeen of the birds are at the Wild Animal Park; the 14
others are at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   Molloko, the first captive-bred condor, which hatched last year,
remains in good health, as do all three chicks produced <DATE>this year</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Another egg is expected to hatch in about two weeks. Next year's
mating season, more of the condors will have reached sexual
maturity.
   Handlers feed the chicks using lifelike condor puppets to keep
the birds from becoming attached to humans.
   The number of the black carrion-eaters dwindled dangerously low
because of shooting and pesticide poisoning.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890521-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-21-89 2036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorChick     05-21 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Chick,0455</SECOND>
<HEAD>Year's Third Endangered Condor Chick Coaxed From Egg</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick was coaxed from its
egg <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as keepers clucked over the year's third successful
hatching in an ongoing effort to save the giant vulture from
extinction.
   The chick, named <PERSON>Kaduku</PERSON>, was the first conceived by a pair of
6-year-old birds at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, changing biologists'
notions about when condors reach sexual maturity, said <LOCATION>San Diego
Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>.
   ``It previously was not known if <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors achieved
full sexual maturity at age 6 or 7,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. ``It was
thought to be 7 but these birds proved us wrong.''
   The sparsely feathered bird, hatched from a pale aqua-colored
egg laid on <DATE>Easter Sunday</DATE>, weighed 5.8 ounces after it was helped
from the shell by handlers at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> park around <TIME>11:20 a.m.</TIME>,
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   ``It was our Easter egg,'' said <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo spokeswoman
<PERSON>Cindy Richardson</PERSON>. ``It looks really healthy and is doing great.''
   The baby, whose Konkow Indian name means ``very strong being,
both physically and spiritually,'' joined two other chicks at the
park's so-called ``condorminium'' and was scheduled to take its
first meal of minced mouse meat <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   The baby bird, conceived by a pair of birds named Cayuma and
<LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION>, was the fourth captive-bred condor chick successfully
hatched, bringing the world's <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor population to 31.
   All remaining wild condors, which are <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest
land birds, have been captured in hopes of building their numbers
in captivity.
   Seventeen condors are housed at the animal park in northern <LOCATION>San
Diego County</LOCATION>, about 30 miles northeast of downtown <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, and
the other 14 live at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s hatching followed one on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and the year's first
on <DATE>April 19</DATE>. The first captive-bred chick, named Molloko, hatched
in <DATE>1988</DATE> and remains in good health as do the other chicks.
   Like all previous captive condor chicks, <PERSON>Kaduku</PERSON> was brought to
the ``condormimium'' in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> as soon as the egg was laid in
hopes the parents would produce another egg to replace it.
   The female Cachuma previously produced another egg, but it was
infertile.
   Los Angeles Zoo officials have been encouraged by the pair's
continued affectionate behavior, saying they hoped the birds would
become productive members of the breeding program.
   The chicks are raised by handlers who use lifelike
condor-replica puppets to feed the birds, allowing for close
scrutiny of their daily progress by while maintaining the chicks'
identification with their own kind.
   The captive-breeding program was established when numbers of the
black carrion-eaters dwindled because of shooting and pesticide
contamination.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880820-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-88 0130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-AndeanCondors 1stLd-Writethru a0680 08-20 0646</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Andean Condors, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0680,0656</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condors to Scout Way for Return of California Condors</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE with trip under way, picking up
7th graf pvs, `The Andean ....'
^By GEORGE GARTIES</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four Andean condors that will serve as scouts
for reintroduction of the gravely threatened <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor into
the wild are headed for temporary pens in a rugged mountain range.
   The 3- and 4-month-old avian pioneers, hatched and reared in
zoos, will spend several weeks in mesh enclosures as scientists
prepare them for their first flights over the dry mountains and
foothills that once supported a thriving population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condors.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> species _ a black, vulture-like carrion eater
with a wingspan up to 9{ feet _ has dwindled to a mere 28, all in
captivity.
   Two Andean condors from the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> were
loaded into airline-style animal shipping crates <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> for
a 200-mile trip to the secret holding pens in the <LOCATION>Los Padres
National Forest</LOCATION>, 75 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the animal park, said in a telephone interview <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``They want to arrive and put the birds in their new home in the
dark of night so the birds awaken the next morning thinking they
are in the same place they were before,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said as his crew
was ready to depart at <TIME>6:45 p.m.</TIME> for the six-hour drive.
   The birds were not drugged, but were captured and wrapped in
blankets by familiar handlers, he said.
   ``By moving them in the dark it basically minimizes the
stress,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   A third Andean condor hatched at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo will join
the contingent, along with a fourth, flown in from a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> center in <LOCATION>Patuxent</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>, the
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo biologist overseeing the program.
   The Andean birds, all females to prevent breeding in the wild,
will be used to test techniques biologists hope to use _ perhaps as
soon as <DATE>1992</DATE> _ to begin returning the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor to nature.
More Andean condors will be added to the test flock later.
   In a <MONEY>$440,000</MONEY> program overseen by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Service</ORGANIZATION>, the birds will be taken to a special mesh enclosure,
measuring about 20 feet by 40 feet and 15 feet high, in rugged
territory. The exact spot is secret to deter the curious or the
malicious.
   About <DATE>November</DATE>, when the birds are able to fly, they will be
fitted with radio monitoring gear and released. It's expected they
will cover much of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor's five-county range, a
land of bare grassy hills dotted with occasional oaks, and rugged,
rocky cliffs and canyons in the mountains that ring the southern
end of the <LOCATION>San Joaquin Valley</LOCATION>.
   The purpose of the test, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said, is twofold: To see how
birds hatched in captivity adapt to freedom; and to see if such
birds can learn to fend for themselves in a region without native
birds of their species to serve as examples.
   The program also will help scientists spot such possible hazards
as poison bait illegally left for coyotes or lead shot in animal
carcasses left by hunters, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The Andean birds will be captured from the wild when it's time
to release their <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> cousins, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said. The first
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> birds could be released as early as <DATE>1992</DATE> if breeding
programs are successful, he said.
   The Andean condor was chosen for the experiment because it is
the closest living relative to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. Though the
Andean species is endangered, they number in the thousands.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land bird, once
roamed widely along the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, but its numbers had shrunk to
40 when the Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> launched a rescue effort in
<DATE>1976</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890221-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-21-89 0920EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Condors     02-21 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condors,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condors Lay Egg At Los Angeles Zoo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD DE ATLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After weeks of amorous but clumsy courting, a
female <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor laid an egg scientists hope will prove
fertile and produce a condor chick for the endangered species'
captive breeding program.
   The egg was noticed <DATE>Monday</DATE> after <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo researchers
reviewed a videotape of activity in the condor's plywood nest box
and briefly saw it as the condors traded places from the nest to the
outside.
   The couple, a male condor named Cuyama and a female named
<LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION>, had piqued the interest of observers on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when they
showed signs indicating an egg-laying was near.
   ``They were showing great interest in each other, nibbling each
other and following each other around to the nest box and scraping
around as though making a nest in the sand,'' said <PERSON>Mike Wallace</PERSON>,
curator of birds at the zoo and supervisor of its captive condor
breeding program.
   He said the egg was the first for the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo program. A
condor egg laid in captivity was hatched last year in the program at
the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>.
   Only 28 of the endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors remain alive, 14 in
captivity at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and 14 more in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>.
Scientists hope the vultures, which are <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land
birds with 9{-foot wingspans, will reproduce enough so that some can
be returned to the wild in five to 10 years.
   The breeding program has removed all known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors
from the wild. Environmentalists have complained that other captive
breeding programs have met with only limited success.
   The egg will be removed from the nest and placed in incubation
sometime <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said. As part of the breeding program,
scientists hope to have the birds produce as many as three
fertilized eggs during the <DATE>January</DATE> to <DATE>April</DATE> mating season.
   ``If you remove the first egg as soon as it's laid, they will
recycle and go into another mating ritual, and within 30 days lay
another egg,'' he explained.
   Experts will know in seven to 10 days whether the egg placed in
the incubator is fertilized, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said. If it is, the chick
should hatch in 55 to 66 days.
   Cuyama and <LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION>, both 6 years old and new to the courting
ritual, have shown an interest in each other for the past few weeks,
with Cuyama waltzing around <LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION> with outstretched wings, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>
said.
   ``We had seen attempts on (<LOCATION>Cuyama</LOCATION>'s) part to copulate, but they
were not good ones because it's his first time and he's learning
how,'' <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
   The other six condor couples at the zoo also have been in
courtship over the past week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890606-0146 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-89 2111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorChick     06-06 0319</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Chick,0327</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condor Hatching Climaxes Productive Breeding Season</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick emerged from its shell
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, marking the fourth captive hatching in the most productive
breeding season for the critically endangered bird since <DATE>1984</DATE>,
officials said.
   Named Shasta for the volcanic <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> mountain that was once a
range for <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land bird, the chick was helped
out of its shell by keepers at <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>, said park
spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>.
   The egg was removed from its nest at the park's ``condorminium''
soon after it was produced <DATE>April 9</DATE> by the parents of Molloko and
<LOCATION>Mandan</LOCATION>, the first and second <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors to be born and bred
in captivity.
   The bird's gender will be determined by a blood test, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>
said.
   The hatching process began <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, when the chick pecked a hole
in its shell. During the final seven minutes, keepers cracked away
bits of shell until the 6.8-ounce chick was freed.
   ``This is the most productive year since <DATE>1984</DATE>, when eight condor
eggs were taken from the wild and six successfully hatched,'' said
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>. He said a seventh condor was born in the wild that year,
but five condor deaths in the wilderness reduced the net population
gain to two.
   Shasta's hatching raised the species' population to 32. It also
represented the first successful ``double-clutch'' in captivity,
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Condors naturally produce a single egg each year but often lay a
replacement egg if the first is lost early in the egg-laying season.
   All condors known to exist are in captivity _ 18 at the <LOCATION>San Diego
Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> and 14 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo. The goal of the
program is to rebuild the population to the point where condors can
be reintroduced into the wild.
   Hanscom said keepers hope to release an initial group of condors
in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880823-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-88 0338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AndeanCondors     08-23 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Andean Condors,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stress Blamed On Rare Bird's Death</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LYNN ELBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Stress is believed to have killed a zoo-hatched
Andean condor that was on its way to freedom in an experiment to
see how its endangered North American cousin will adapt to the wild.
   Three other transplanted Andean condors in the program were
doing well <DATE>Monday</DATE>, officials said.
   The Andean birds were chosen for the experiment because it is
the closest living relative to the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor. Though the
Andean species is also endangered, they number in the thousands.
Only 28 of its North American cousins exist and all in captivity.
   The Andean condors, which are also endangered, were transported
to <ORGANIZATION>Los Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION> in airline-style animal shipping
crates and placed in secret holding pens <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   One died while being transported.
   Preliminary results of an autopsy show the death was
stress-related, although infection has not been ruled out, said <PERSON>Joe
Dowhan</PERSON>, condor recovery coordinator for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   Final test results are expected by <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   He said it was premature to say how officials might have handled
the move differently or what changes might be implemented to
prevent other deaths.
   ``This is a learning process. Right now there are all kinds of
scenarios we could consider changing,'' he said.
   Scientists are conducting the experiment to see how birds
hatched in captivity adapt to freedom, fending for themselves in a
region without native birds of their species to serve as examples.
   The first group of the 3- and 4-month-old birds are scheduled to
spend several weeks in mesh enclosures in the forest 75 miles
northeast of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   Two came from the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>; one was from the
Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> center in <LOCATION>Patuxent</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>; and the one that
died came from the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   Scientists will prepare the birds for their first flights over
the dry mountains and foothills that once supported a large
population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors.
   The condors are being exposed to other young condors for the
first time because they were raised singly, as in the wild, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON>
said.
   More Andean condors will be brought to the area in <DATE>October</DATE>.
   In <DATE>December</DATE>, when the birds should be able to fly, scientists
will fit them with radio monitors, release them, and follow their
progress.
   The Andean birds will remain in the wild until it's time to
release <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, perhaps as early as <DATE>1992</DATE> if officials
have continued success in captive breeding programs at the Wild
Animal Park and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dowhan</PERSON> said.
   Blood tests on the first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor conceived in
captivity determined the bird is a female, officials said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The 4-month-old bird, named <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, also was determined to be
``in perfect health,'' said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, spokesman at the Wild
Animal Park. The bird, which weighed in at 6} ounces when born
<DATE>April 29</DATE>, now weighs 16 pounds.
   Fourteen of the 27 other <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are females. Park
officials say further tests will determine which of the birds are
related and how they will be separated for breeding.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880307-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-88 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-CondorEgg     03-07 0427</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Egg,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keepers Detect The Beginnings Of A Condor Chick</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor egg produced by
captive breeding is fertile and contains the makings of a chick,
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park officials said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``You can't actually see an embryo yet, but what you can see is
the beginnings of circulatory development, which appears as a dark
dime-sized dot toward the top of the yolk,'' park spokesman <PERSON>Tom
Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The egg was laid <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the product of a male condor known as
AC-4 and a female condor called UN-1. It was removed immediately
from its nest in the park's ``condorminium'' and placed in an
incubator.
   Keepers peeked inside the egg by holding it up to a
high-intensity lamp in a process known as ``candling.'' The egg
then was returned to its incubator, where it will be kept until the
hatching expected between <DATE>April 28</DATE> and <DATE>May 3</DATE>, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   ``Now, we incubate the egg according to the parameters that have
worked so well in the past and hope ... we can hatch a healthy
condor chick,'' he said.
   All 27 living <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are in captivity. Fourteen are
kept at the Wild Animal Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   Thirteen of the 27 birds were hatched in captivity in an effort
to build a breeding flock to save the rare birds from extinction.
Each of those eggs were taken from nests in the wild.
   The breeding program has been conducted at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> and
its affiliate, the Wild Animal Park, since <DATE>1983</DATE> in cooperation with
state and federal wildlife officials.
   The last known wild condor was captured in <DATE>April 1987</DATE> by
government biologists after it was determined the carrion-eating
birds' existence was threatened by lead poisoning in their food
supply and human encroachment upon their central <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> habitat.
   ``Our success or failure has pivoted on the captive production
of a fertile egg and that's what we've got,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said of the
4-day-old egg.
   Meanwhile, the parents of the egg were said to be doing well.
Keepers removed the shell from its nest soon after it was laid to
stimulate more breeding activity by the pair, which <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said
has begun.
   ``That's real positive,'' he said. ``That would lead us to hope
for the production of a second egg, which could come as early as 30
days after the first egg.
   ``The parents are doing fine, the egg is doing fine and the
keepers are doing fine.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890222-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-22-89 0821EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Condors     02-22 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condors,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoo Finds Second Egg Laid By Endangered Birds</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two eggs laid by captive pairs of endangered
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors have been placed in incubation while anxious
scientists wait to learn whether either one is fertile, zoo
officials said.
   The newest egg, discovered <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal
Park</LOCATION>, was produced by condors UN1 and AC4 one day after an egg was
found at the state's other breeding station at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>,
park spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   ``We've had in hand 18 eggs and this one is on the small side,
but we've seen healthy birds hatch from smaller eggs,'' he said.
   Both eggs must incubate for about a week before keepers will be
able to tell whether they're fertile. If so, a chick could hatch in
about two months if there are no complications, officials said.
   The egg found <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo was removed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
from the plywood nest box of male <LOCATION>Cuyama</LOCATION> and female <LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION> when
both vultures were away from it, zoo spokeswoman <PERSON>Lora LaMarca</PERSON> said.
   The 8{-ounce egg, about 5 inches long and 3 inches wide, was
placed in a padded wooden box with hot water bottles to keep it warm
during the trip to the state's other condor breeding station at the
Wild Animal Park.
   The egg was transferred to the northern <LOCATION>San Diego County</LOCATION> park
because the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION> is installing new incubation facilities,
<PERSON>LaMarca</PERSON> said.
   Dr. <PERSON>Mike Wallace</PERSON>, curator of birds at <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, said after
the egg was laid <DATE>Monday</DATE> that he hoped to collect as many as three
eggs from <LOCATION>Cuyama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Cachuma</LOCATION> during the <DATE>January</DATE> through <DATE>April</DATE> laying
season.
   The condors recycle their mating habits if their nest loses an
egg, and the female usually takes a month to produce another egg, he
said.
   All 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to remain alive are in captivity,
half at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and half at the Wild Animal Park near
<LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION>. The condor eggs discovered this week are among the only
three laid in captivity.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880428-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-88 1139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorEgg     04-28 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Egg,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Recordings of Bird Sounds Inspire Chick On To Freedom</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick, inspired by
recordings of vulture hisses and grunts, was slowly chipping its
way out of its shell today, <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park officials
said.
   ``Everything is proceeding fine,'' park spokeswoman <PERSON>Martha Baker</PERSON>
said <TIME>this morning</TIME>. ``The chick is moving around inside the shell
and the condor keepers can hear the chick tapping.''
   ``What we're trying to do is provide a natural stimulus to the
bird to assist it in hatching,'' spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The chick, the first ever of the nearly extinct species to be
conceived in captivity, began its three-day struggle to break free
of its blue-green egg early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   A successful hatching would raise the population to 28. All 27
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are in captivity, 14 at the Wild Animal Park and
13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said park officials still expect the chick to hatch <DATE>Friday</DATE>
or <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. If the chick hasn't emerged from its shell by <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, keepers likely will help it out, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Meanwhile, keepers are playing recordings of bird noises and
gently tapping the egg with a light metal rod every two hours to
simulate what condor parents would do to encourage the youth, he
said.
   The chick has settled into a rhythm of pecking and resting,
punctuated by cheeps, and appears to be strong and healthy, said
<PERSON>Bill Toone</PERSON>, curator of birds at the park.
   ``At this point, it will continue to push at the pip hole and
situate itself so that it will attempt to cap the egg,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>
said, referring to the chick's chipping all the way around the egg
so it can push the upper third of the shell away from the rest.
   The egg is being watched on a remote television monitor but
keepers are reluctant to help the chick because of the danger that
blood vessels linked to a surrounding membrane will rupture, which
could cause fatal bleeding.
   Since <DATE>1983</DATE>, there have been 14 successful condor hatchings at
the Wild Animal Park and the affiliated <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo involving
eggs taken from the wild. All of those hatchings occurred with
human help, although one of those chicks died of an infection 24
hours after birth.
   The egg was laid <DATE>March 3</DATE> at the park's ``condorminium'' after
its parents engaged in the first captive mating in the history of a
15-year program aimed at saving <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land bird.
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, which are scavengers, have wing spans of up to
10 feet.
   State and federal wildlife officials overseeing the condor
program decided to remove the remaining condors in the wild to
focus efforts on a captive breeding flock. The last known
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor in the wild was captured in <DATE>April 1987</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880430-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-88 0123EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CondorEgg 3rdLd-Writethru a0892 04-30 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condor Egg, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0892,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>Condor Chick Hatches With Help From Its Keepers</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 5 grafs to UPDATE with comments from news conference.
Picks up 5th graf pvs, `A recording...' Edits to conform.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DENNIS GEORGATOS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor conceived in
captivity hatched <DATE>Friday</DATE>, its keepers using tweezers and their
fingertips to help the newest member of the nearly extinct species
break free from its shell, officials said.
   ``It's alive and it looks healthy,'' said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. ``It's resting now.
We don't have any other details.''
   The hatching represents a tremendous boost to efforts to save
the species. It brings the known population of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s
largest land bird to 28, all in captivity _ 15 at the park here and
13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
   The squawking infant, named Molloko, an Indian word for
``condor,'' was swaddled in a towel and placed in the same type of
incubator used for premature infants.
   ``Early <TIME>this morning</TIME> there were 27 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors left in
the world,'' said <PERSON>Bill Toone</PERSON>, curator of birds at the park. ``This
afternoon there's 28 of them, and we couldn't be more excited about
that.
   ``When the numbers are so low, one bird is seen as a very big
step away from extinction,'' <PERSON>Toone</PERSON> added.
   Although the tiny bird was not brought forth to ``meet the
press,'' its history-making birth was recorded on videotape and
shown at a press conference <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Earlier, the chick had become stuck in dried membrane and
albumen and could no longer rotate in the shell to peck its way
out. Its keepers removed it cautiously because of the danger of
rupturing blood vessels linked to egg membranes.
   A recording of vultures making hissing and grunting sounds was
played at intervals to duplicate the sounds the chick would hear in
a natural setting.
   Park officials had said they intended to intervene by <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
if the chick, which began hatching <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, hadn't emerged from
the shell. Allowing the hatching struggle to continue would
overexhaust the bird.
   The chick, conceived by the only known activing breeding pair of
the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, was expected to weigh about 9 ounces,
<PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. The species has a wingspan of up to 10 feet at
maturity.
   The 10-ounce blue-green egg, about 5 inches long, had been under
a 24-hour watch since <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, when keepers noticed ``pip''
cracks in one end signaling the start of hatching, which can take
three days.
   After the egg was laid <DATE>March 3</DATE>, it was taken away from the
parent birds and incubated artificially in hopes that the female
bird would produce a second egg. So far, this has not happened.
   It will be a while before the sex of the bird can be determined
through a blood test, officials said.
   Hanscom said that representatives of the Chumash Indian tribe
had been enlisted to select the name for the chick upon hatching.
   The tribe inhabited the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> area that most recently
served as <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor habitat, and the bird figures
prominently in the tribe's religion.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880507-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-07-88 0520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CondorChick     05-07 0380</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Chick,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keepers Treat Condor's Leg Development Problem</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Condor keepers hobbled the legs of a newly
hatched <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor by wrapping them with a tiny gauze
bandage in an effort to straighten out the chick's limbs, the <LOCATION>San
Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> said.
   The bandage was applied to Molloko on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, six days after
the hatching of the first captive-bred condor, to correct a leg
development problem known as splayed legs, park spokesman <PERSON>Tom
Hanscom</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Hanscom said the condition is not serious but it could become a
hindrance to the bird if allowed to become permanent.
   The same problem occurred in an Andean condor chick born at the
park and was successfully corrected by use of a gauze strip. Andean
condors are closely related to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors.
   ``What we do is hobble the chick's legs. This simply entails
tying the leg above the feet with a strand of gauze'' that prevents
the legs from spreading out to the side, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The gauze was expected to remain in place through today.
   Molloko, the first of the endangered species to be conceived in
captivity, is otherwise in excellent health, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Keepers are using a hand puppet built to resemble an adult
condor to feed the chick. Molloko consumes some 15 diced baby mice
during each feeding.
   The splayed-leg condition occurs in chicks that are raised on a
hard surface or, as with <PERSON>Molloko</PERSON>, on a towel, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. They
are unable to gain traction as they attempt to stand, unlike condor
chicks in the wild that move on sandy surfaces.
   Because the chick's bones are still soft and the joints have yet
to set, the condition would become permanent if not attended to, he
said.
   Keepers could correct the problem by placing the bird on sand
instead of a towel, but that approach would be dangerous.
   ``Many birds raised on sand die of sand impaction,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>
said, in which sand ingested by the bird creates a fatal blockage
in the intestine.
   The hatching <DATE>April 29</DATE> of Molloko raised the known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor population to 28. All of the rare condors, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s
largest land birds, are in captivity, with 15 at the Wild Animal
Park and 13 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880427-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-27-88 1130EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-CondorEgg 1stLd-Writethru a0510 04-27 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Condor Egg, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0510,0705</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Condor Conceived in Captivity Pecks Hole in Shell</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with chick chipping hole in
shell; picks up in 11th graf pvs, ``Exhaustion from...''</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto GO1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LYNN ELBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN DIEGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tiny <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor chick that scientists
say represents the salvation of its species pecked a hole in its
eggshell today, officials said.
   Keepers at <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> are keeping a
round-the-clock vigil over the egg, the first produced by captive
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors under a program started 15 years ago to save the
nearly extinct species, spokesman <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The chick should win its struggle to break out of the the
blue-green shell within the next three days, he said. It began
using its lungs for the first time <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when it pushed its beak
into an air pocket at the egg's narrow end.
   The chipping of a small hole in the shell, or pipping, begins a
critical phase in the bird's development, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   ``We have a remote TV camera on the egg, monitoring it
constantly,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. ``And every hour the egg is physically
tapped by a keeper to provide the same outside stimulation one
might expect from a natural mother in the nest.''
   If the chick fails to hatch itself by <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, keepers
and veterinarians will step in and help it get out, <PERSON>Hansom</PERSON> said.
The chick will be hand-raised by keepers using a puppet resembling
an adult condor for feeding.
   The chick is especially susceptible to infection and exhaustion
now that it has broken through the eggshell, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest land bird with a
wing span of up to 10 feet, once ranged along the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> coast
from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Only 27 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors are known to exist today, all in
captivity at the wild animal park and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, the last
wild bird having been captured last year.
   The fertile egg, laid <DATE>March 3</DATE>, was the culmination of an
elaborate courtship dance and mating of a young male designated AC4
and his older mate, UN1. The egg was removed from the park's
``condorminium'' and placed in an incubator.
   Exhaustion from trying to break the shell could kill the chick,
but keepers must allow 72 hours to pass before intervening, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON>
said. If they step in too early, they could cause the chick to
bleed to death by rupturing a membrane of blood cells that the
condor needs to absorb, he said.
   ``We don't want to be pessimistic, but we are very anxious at
this time,'' <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said.
   Thirteen of 14 condor eggs taken from nests in the wild have
hatched in captivity, all with human assistance, he said.
   The chick's parents have continued to mate, raising hopes for a
second egg. At the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>, two other potential mating
pairs have failed to begin the courtship dance.
   Hanscom said the pairs may not have adjusted to captivity or may
be incompatible.
   ``These birds mate for life and here we are chosing mates
artificially for them,'' he said. ``That might not always take. The
birds may not always decide to follow our magic making.''
   Scientists sought to begin the condor capture-breeding program
during the <DATE>1950s</DATE> but were delayed by opposition by the <ORGANIZATION>National
Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> and others.
   The opponents eventually were pacified by assurances that the
condors' natural habitat would be protected and that a wild
population eventually would be re-established.
   Federal and state agencies have joined the multimillion-dollar
effort to regenerate the birds.
   The success of the program won't be known for years, as the
oldest bird hatched in captivity is 5 years old and condors reach
maturity at age 7, <ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The egg's parents were taken from the wild, and the male only
reached maturity last <DATE>summer</DATE>. But Hanscom is convinced condors born
in captivity also will produce eggs such as the one now watched
intently.
   ``The chick that hatches from this egg represents the
regeneration of this species,'' he said. ``Captive breeding is
their only hope for survival.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880722-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-88 1250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Condors     07-22 0419</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Condors,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condors To Be Released As Forerunners To California Condors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAUREN BLAU</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four young Andean condors are going to be
introduced to the <ORGANIZATION>Los Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION> in an experiment that
wildlife experts hope will lead the way to eventually returning
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors to the wild.
   Scientists said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they believe the information they get
from monitoring the Andean condors will help them avoid problems
when they begin releasing <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors in the early <DATE>1990s</DATE>.
   There are only 28 known <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors, the largest flying
birds in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, and all of them are at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo
and the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION>. Scientists hope to save the
species by breeding the birds in captivity to build up the
population and later releasing them.
   The last free <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor was captured in <DATE>April 1987</DATE>.
   Although the Andean condors, which are native to <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>,
are considered endangered, there are thousands of them.
   Researchers in the two-year, <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> program will start with
newborn condors that haven't developed any domesticated habits.
   Nine zoos have sent eggs to the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo and the wild
animal park. After hatching, the chicks will be kept in captivity
for three months, using puppets that resemble adult condors to feed
them, said <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>, curator of birds at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo
and the project's field coordinator.
   ``We have to make sure the birds have some fear of humans to
protect them,'' <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said. ``When they see a human on the
horizon, it may be a hunter.''
   At the age of three months the birds will be taken to a large
outdoor cage, and they will be released when they are about 7
months old, the age they would normally leave the nest, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>
said.
   The first chicks will be three months old next month and are
tentatively scheduled to be moved the weekend of <DATE>Aug. 19</DATE> to a spot
near the <ORGANIZATION>Hopper Mountain Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION> in northern <LOCATION>Ventura
County</LOCATION>, northwest of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
   A group of eight scientists and technicians and 200 volunteers
will monitor the birds' moves by radio transmitters to distinguish
eating patterns and other habits. Scientists said they will provide
food for the birds throughout the experiment.
   The observers will periodically recapture the birds to monitor
their health and check their transmitters, <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>, the lead agency in the
program, will provide protection for the birds, wildlife inspector
<PERSON>Ron Drifka</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022689-0132 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 23704 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 26, 1989, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 9; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
344 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CONDOR EGGS' FERTILITY UNCLEAR IN INITIAL TESTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GENE YASUDA, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Three <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor eggs laid earlier this week are now being watched by 
wildlife officials as carefully as the Soviets guard their bejeweled Faberge 
eggs. 
</P>
<P>
Hoping that the eggs will soon boost the endangered species numbers, caretakers 
at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal Park</LOCATION> examined the eggs <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to determine 
whether the eggs are fertile, said <PERSON>Tom Hanscom</PERSON>, a park spokesman. 
</P>
<P>
"This was the first time we checked them specifically to see if they were 
fertile," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. "We looked at all three of them, but unfortunately, the 
tests were inconclusive." 
</P>
<P>
The fertility test is conducted by placing a high-intensity lamp behind the egg 
and looking for signs of embryo development. 
</P>
<P>
"Within 4 to 10 days, if the egg is fertile, we will be able to note a dark, 
opaque spot toward one edge of the yolk," <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. "That's a sign of cell 
division . . . that an embryo is growing. We couldn't see anything today." 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, an egg born to a captive pair of condors at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Zoo was 
moved to the Wild Animal Park in <LOCATION>Escondido</LOCATION> because of its expertise in handling 
condor eggs. Of the 28 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors now in captivity, 14 were born either 
at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Zoo or the Wild Animal Park. No condors are believed to exist 
in the wild. 
</P>
<P>
Two other egg layings quickly followed. Also on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, two condors at the 
Wild Animal Park that produced a chick last <DATE>March</DATE> laid their second egg, and on 
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, a 6-year-old park condor, named <PERSON>Almiyi</PERSON>, produced an egg as well, 
<ORGANIZATION>Hanscom</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
There is some concern that the eggs laid by <PERSON>Almiyi</PERSON> and the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> condors, 
also about 6 years old, will not hatch because condors normally do not reach 
sexually maturity until age 7, <PERSON>Hanscom</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"If we don't see any signs by the end of the 10-day mark, we'll have to say 
they're infertile. But we have every reason to believe that the other egg will 
be fertile because it came from the same pair that was successful the last 
time." 
</P>
<P>
The breeding pair, known as UN1 and AC4, produced the female chick Molloko from 
the first egg laid in captivity last <DATE>March</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06163010 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06163010 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (6); PHOTO: Humans can handle a newly hatched chick, like this one at
the Los Angeles Zoo, because of its poor eyesight. But after chicks are a few
days old, PHOTO: a puppet that looks like the real adult at far left takes
over parenting. The chicks become so attached to their puppet that if another
is introduced, they will hiss and snap at it.; PHOTO: Photos by Los Angeles
Zoo; Los Angeles Zoo; A field worker walks toward the site in Los Padres
National Forest in Ventura County where Andean condors were first released.
(Color); PHOTO: Los Angeles Zoo; Cachuma, a female hatched in the wild and
raised in captivity, stands on a scale. (Color); PHOTO: Los Angeles Zoo --
Special to the Mercury News; A juvenile female Andean condor named Y-1, above
and PHOTO: at top, with radio transmitters on its wings, was one of the first
birds released in the wild (Both Color Photos)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MAJOR-STORY; CALIFORNIA; BIRD; INCREASE; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  NOT LONG AGO, Mike Wallace was sleeping on the cages of the Los Angeles Zoo's
California condors, after the last of the 27 birds had been captured. Wallace,
bird curator and a specialist in endangered scavengers, wanted to protect the
condors at his zoo from activists threatening to free them.;    Now, just four
years since Adult Condor-9 became the last bird captured, Wallace again spends
his nights at the zoo. This time, he's awake with those earlier birds'
hatching chicks. And now, there's a chance that one or more of them -- maybe a
chick of AC-9's -- will be released this fall to start re-establishing the
species in the wild.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NEW DAWN FOR THE CONDOR
BIOLOGISTS WEIGH THE RISKS OF RETURNING SOME
TO WILD  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Strategies for helping the condor, Page 2E  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     A decision on the historic step, two years ahead of schedule, is expected
this week and depends on the answers to two questions:;    Have scientists
gained enough expertise, from a release program using more populous Andean
condors, to ensure a likelihood of success with the Californians? And has
high-speed breeding, which nearly doubled the population to 53, yielded enough
chicks to risk releasing any in the wild without weakening the limited gene
pool?;    <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>, who took up hang gliding to better understand some of what
"the kids" will face, is unflappable days before the decision: "The worst that
could happen is we'd wait another year.";    Eventually, planners hope to
establish populations of at least 100 birds each in three parts of the
country. The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> is looking at the <LOCATION>Grand Canyon</LOCATION>, a
prehistoric <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor habitat, as a possibility.;    "If we pull this
off," <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> says, fairly glowing, "it will be a major coup.";    The
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor is not adept at surviving in today's world.;    "They have
incredible curiosity," says <PERSON>David Clendenen</PERSON>, lead biologist for the <ORGANIZATION>Fish &amp;
Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>'s condor recovery program.;    American Indian Chumash legend
says the dark birds were white until they flew too close to campfire. More
recently, their curiosity-driven brushes with humanity have led to power-line
collisions, shooting deaths and lead poisoning. Poking around in carcasses for
bone bits, needed for calcium, the carrion-eaters often latch onto bullet
fragments. The lead destroys digestive nerves, starving the birds to death.;  
 Their natural mortality rate ranges from 5 to <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> a year, but by the
mid-1980s it had skyrocketed to as high as <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT>. Meanwhile, the birds
were producing just one egg per pair every two years.;    Their survival in
the wild now depends on the skills of the species that brought them to the
brink of extinction. A complex breeding and release program will cost about
<MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> this year; the cost is expected to fall as the program becomes more
efficient.;    The breeding in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and at the <LOCATION>San Diego Wild Animal
Park</LOCATION> has established mirror populations in case disease or disaster should
strike one site.;    Meanwhile, a team of biologists is experimenting with
releasing Andean condors in a 53,000-acre sanctuary in <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Los
Padres National Forest</ORGANIZATION>. For three years, they have practiced stealthy
manipulations to help the birds -- whose behavior is virtually the same as the
Californians' -- without their knowledge.;    "We're sneaky," <PERSON>Clendenen</PERSON> says.;
   Here in <LOCATION>Los Padres</LOCATION>, where the birds soar over rugged hillsides of chaparral
and traditional nesting places in sandstone cliffs, it's easy to see why
Indians have held them in such esteem. Legends hold that the birds' nearly
10-foot wingspans carry human spirits to the afterlife.;    Popular perception
may be that condors are ugly, with feeding habits that hardly enhance their
image. But that perception is lost in their remarkable grace in flight, their
wings separating the air with a faint, unearthly whir.;    The captive
Andeans' odyssey in the wild begins one night when they are about 4 months
old, "around the time they'd be peeking out of a cave," <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> says. Three or
four birds are brought at night from the zoo to a wooden, hillside roost.
"We're trying to trick them into thinking they were always there," <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>
says.;    Unseen biologists open the roost's door at daybreak to reveal a
rocky pen about 20 feet long by 15 feet wide, with 10-foot-high protective
netting. The birds are secretly watched around the clock, and then one night,
when they are about 8 months old, the pen's netting is removed. The next
morning, the birds can begin to learn to fly.;    "When they first leave, you
can see the uncertainty," <PERSON>Clendenen</PERSON> says. "You can see them stand there, with
their wings out. They know that's what they want to do and should do. But you
can see the ambivalence." The birds need wind currents or thermal drafts to
soar and, as their explorations take them farther -- as far as 100 miles --
biologists track them with small radio transmitters on their wings.;    Most
crucial to the birds' re-establishment is their feeding program. The <ORGANIZATION>Fish &amp;
Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> will provide the condors with food for years, if necessary,
to keep them from foraging in dangerous areas and feeding on deadly
carcasses.;    The biologists secretly bring stillborn dairy calves to a
series of feeding platforms, high off the ground to keep the area's black
bears at bay. Because the condors have a poor sense of smell, they don't pick
up human scent. They rely on vision to determine whether an animal is food,
sometimes watching it for hours to see its lack of movement and other animals
feeding on it.;    When the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor release begins, it will follow
the patterns developed with the Andeans. Some young Andeans also may be
released for the safety and social development of the first Californians. And
the four carefully selected older Andeans now in the wild may be kept on to
serve as teachers.;    "When we release the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, we don't want a
bird out there that's going to take him to downtown <LOCATION>Ojai</LOCATION>," says <PERSON>Robert Mesta</PERSON>,
coordinator of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> program. The program is ready,
<PERSON>Mesta</PERSON> says. "All we need now is the condors.";    Just last week, another
chick hatched in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, bringing the total hatched there and in <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION> to 13 this year. In the wild, mating pairs produced just one egg every
two years.;    But "multiple clutching," or removal of a newly laid egg,
provokes renewed mating and can yield up to six eggs in two years. The chicks
then are raised by puppets resembling adult condors. (A pair that produced
three eggs in one year was rewarded with an Andean egg, substituted when the
pair's last egg was removed, to hatch and rear.;    While the Californians'
fates are decided, the chicks are swaddled in a seamless blanket of security,
just small bundles of fuzz with ungainly heads and feet, oblivious to their
urban surroundings.;    "We're not pushing it," the <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> Zoo's <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> says of
this <DATE>fall</DATE>'s possible release. But eventual recovery of the species would have
enormous impact.;    Elsewhere in the world, he says, "people say, if we can't
even save our own species, who are we to tell them what to do with their rain
forest? . . . It's become a real symbol for conservation."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAMELA KRAMER, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910611  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,356  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 11, 1991
00163010,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--RareSpecies Adv06-1stAdd   12-24 0520</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Rare Species, Adv06-1st Add,0665</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv06</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release Sunday, Jan. 6</NOTE>
<HEAD>BALTIMORE: wildlife refuge.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> Zoo has bred the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, a small tropical
bird that resembles a sandpiper. The <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Zoo implanted an
embryo from an endangered Indian desert cat into a surrogate mother
- a domestic house cat that nursed the kitten as if it were her
own.
   At the aquarium in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>'s redeveloped Inner Harbor, still
one of the most polluted areas of the <LOCATION>Chesapeake Bay</LOCATION>, a collection
of crickets, wax worms, fruit flies and other insects are kept in
rows of bottles on a shelf in a cramped, pungent work area behind
the rain forest exhibit.
   Above the bottles is a sign reading, ``Time flies like an arrow,
fruit flies like a banana.''
   What blue poison dart frogs like is a diet high in calcium and
phosphorous, humidity and privacy. The three-quarter-inch,
blue-and-black frog is so-named because it secretes a deadly
alkaloid similar to curare, which <ORGANIZATION>South American Indians</ORGANIZATION> use to
make poison darts.
   ``In the wild they lay their eggs under large jungle leaves,''
Cover says. ``We've found the bottom of 2-liter soda bottles are a
real good breeding hut. We put a plastic leaf in a petri dish and
put the bottle over the top.
   ``The male does a courtship dance. The female, if receptive,
follows him in and does an elaborate courtship dance with all kinds
of stroking and spinning. Then she lays her eggs and he'll
fertilize them.''
   Cover and his colleagues are still working on how to get the
frogs to produce the toxin medical researchers want to study.
Herpetologists and others have tried several unorthodox methods.
   Special diets didn't work, nor did daily handling of the frogs.
They thought cold baths, which would simulate the dangers of the
wild, might be the key.
   ``We actually tested that hypothesis,'' Cover says. ``But in the
wild the frog would already have to have the poison the first time
a predator comes down. There wouldn't be a second chance. So,
danger doesn't seem like it would stimulate production.''
   Perhaps the mostnown endangered species is the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor, the largest land bird in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, which has a
wingspan of up to 10 feet. There are 40 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to
exist and all are in captivity - <DATE>21</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal
Park and 19 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   The last condor known to exist in the wild was captured in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
Before <DATE>1985</DATE>, scientists had hoped to breed them in captivity and in
the wild, but between <DATE>1984</DATE> and <DATE>1985</DATE>, four of the last five breeding
pairs in the wild were lost and presumed dead. In <DATE>1985</DATE>, federal
officials decided to capture all remaining wild condors in a
last-ditch effort to save the species.
   That effort drew criticism from several environmental groups,
but it appears to have been the right choice.
   ``When we first hatched birds in captivity, it was pretty
exciting,'' says <PERSON>Dr. Michael Wallace</PERSON>, curator of birds at the <LOCATION>Los
Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>. ``We were under a lot of pressure from outside groups
to release the birds. It's good to see we could not only do it, but
do it fairly well.''
   Four of the vulture-like chicks were hatched this year at the
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> park and four at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>. That success has
enabled zoologists to consider reintroducing some of the condors
into the wild as early as next year, several years ahead of
schedule.
   Despite their successes, zoologists are quick to remind that
breeding programs are only part of the solution.
   ``Zoos are looking at being part of a holistic program,''
<PERSON>Hutchins</PERSON> says. ``If we are going to save species, we just can't
save them in zoos. But at least having these populations in
captivity provides us with the option of reintroducing them.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday Jan. 6</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> Zoo has bred the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, a small tropical
bird that resembles a sandpiper. The <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Zoo implanted an
embryo from an endangered Indian desert cat into a surrogate mother
- a domestic house cat that nursed the kitten as if it were her
own.
   At the aquarium in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>'s redeveloped Inner Harbor, still
one of the most polluted areas of the <LOCATION>Chesapeake Bay</LOCATION>, a collection
of crickets, wax worms, fruit flies and other insects are kept in
rows of bottles on a shelf in a cramped, pungent work area behind
the rain forest exhibit.
   Above the bottles is a sign reading, ``Time flies like an arrow,
fruit flies like a banana.''
   What blue poison dart frogs like is a diet high in calcium and
phosphorous, humidity and privacy. The three-quarter-inch,
blue-and-black frog is so-named because it secretes a deadly
alkaloid similar to curare, which <ORGANIZATION>South American Indians</ORGANIZATION> use to
make poison darts.
   ``In the wild they lay their eggs under large jungle leaves,''
Cover says. ``We've found the bottom of 2-liter soda bottles are a
real good breeding hut. We put a plastic leaf in a petri dish and
put the bottle over the top.
   ``The male does a courtship dance. The female, if receptive,
follows him in and does an elaborate courtship dance with all kinds
of stroking and spinning. Then she lays her eggs and he'll
fertilize them.''
   Cover and his colleagues are still working on how to get the
frogs to produce the toxin medical researchers want to study.
Herpetologists and others have tried several unorthodox methods.
   Special diets didn't work, nor did daily handling of the frogs.
They thought cold baths, which would simulate the dangers of the
wild, might be the key.
   ``We actually tested that hypothesis,'' Cover says. ``But in the
wild the frog would already have to have the poison the first time
a predator comes down. There wouldn't be a second chance. So,
danger doesn't seem like it would stimulate production.''
   Perhaps the mostnown endangered species is the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
condor, the largest land bird in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, which has a
wingspan of up to 10 feet. There are 40 <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condors known to
exist and all are in captivity - <DATE>21</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal
Park and 19 at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>.
   The last condor known to exist in the wild was captured in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
Before <DATE>1985</DATE>, scientists had hoped to breed them in captivity and in
the wild, but between <DATE>1984</DATE> and <DATE>1985</DATE>, four of the last five breeding
pairs in the wild were lost and presumed dead. In <DATE>1985</DATE>, federal
officials decided to capture all remaining wild condors in a
last-ditch effort to save the species.
   That effort drew criticism from several environmental groups,
but it appears to have been the right choice.
   ``When we first hatched birds in captivity, it was pretty
exciting,'' says <PERSON>Dr. Michael Wallace</PERSON>, curator of birds at the <LOCATION>Los
Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>. ``We were under a lot of pressure from outside groups
to release the birds. It's good to see we could not only do it, but
do it fairly well.''
   Four of the vulture-like chicks were hatched this year at the
<LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> park and four at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>. That success has
enabled zoologists to consider reintroducing some of the condors
into the wild as early as next year, several years ahead of
schedule.
   Despite their successes, zoologists are quick to remind that
breeding programs are only part of the solution.
   ``Zoos are looking at being part of a holistic program,''
<PERSON>Hutchins</PERSON> says. ``If we are going to save species, we just can't
save them in zoos. But at least having these populations in
captivity provides us with the option of reintroducing them.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06092182 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06092182 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; A chick, the world's 42nd California condor,
comes out of its shell  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  LOS-ANGELES; ANIMAL; PARK; BIRD; BIRTH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The world's 42nd California condor celebrated Easter with a meal of pureed
mice after emerging from its shell at the Los Angeles Zoo -- the latest
success story in an attempt to return the endangered birds to the wild.;   
The healthy chick emerged from its pale blue shell at 10:13 p.m. Saturday --
two hours too early for the zoo's public-relations department, said Mike
Wallace, director of the zoo's California Condor Recovery Project.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CONGRATULATIONS, IT'S A CONDOR
CHICK HATCHES IN L.A. ZOO'S CAPTIVE BREEDING
PROGRAM  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "You could tell our PR department was really trying to get us to slow this
bird down so he would hatch on Easter," chuckled <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>, who noted it would
have been the zoo's second Easter hatching in a row.;    "But as long as they
are healthy, we don't care when they hatch," he said.;    The new chick --
whose gender won't be known for three months or so -- was named Pawoko, a
Kawaiisu Indian word for condor drawn from a list provided by the state <ORGANIZATION>Native
American Commission.</ORGANIZATION>;    "We're feeling really good," said <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON>. "This was
a really healthy hatch. The chick came out unassisted and weighed around 6
ounces.";    Pawoko is the sixth condor to be hatched in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> since the
zoo's participation in the joint program with the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> Wild Animal Park
began two years ago. Wallace has hopes it will be among the first of more than
a dozen birds to emerge this year.;    If the condors continue to breed as
successfully as they have in the past, it's possible that a small number could
be released into the wild by the end of the year -- almost two years ahead of
schedule, he said.;    In <DATE>1987</DATE>, when biologists rounded up the last of the 27
wild condors known to exist, they hoped their controversial captive breeding
program would enable them to increase the species sufficiently to re-introduce
them into a remote <LOCATION>Ventura County</LOCATION> sanctuary.;    With a 9 1/2-foot wingspan
that makes them <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest bird, the condors in prehistoric times
ranged up and down the <LOCATION>Pacific Coast</LOCATION>. The bird's decline is believed to be a
result of the introduction of man into their habitat.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Daily News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910401  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  369  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 1, 1991
00092182,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880822-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-88 1002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AndeanCondors     08-22 0337</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Andean Condors,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Andean Condor Dies En Route to Experiment for California Condor
Recovery</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL FLEEMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
