<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06212094 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06212094 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  (box)Today, all day.; Junior Halter &amp; Showmanship Classes, Horse Arena.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SANTA CLARA COUNTY FAIR
WHAT'S DOING
AT THE FAIR?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Events  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, noon to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Kids' Day Continuous Contests, Demo Green.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, noon to <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Kids' Day Art Experience, 4H-FFA-Juniors.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; Kids<DATE>' Day</DATE> Planters-Make Your Own, K101 Garden Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Brenda Lee Dancers</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>,
<TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Lindsey Johnson</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; Asleep
At The Wheel with <ORGANIZATION>Stratton &amp; Christopher</ORGANIZATION>, Amphitheater.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>;
<LOCATION>Los Danzantes</LOCATION> De Aztlan, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7-10 p.m.;
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Square Dancers Association</ORGANIZATION>, Variety Square.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>,
<TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; Daddy-O, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910730  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  111  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday July 30, 1991
00212094,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06220111 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06220111 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing at the fair?; (box)Today, all day.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  Livestock Judging: Senior Beef Cattle, Livestock Arena.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, noon to
<TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Seniors' Day Booth Displays, <ORGANIZATION>Vennum</ORGANIZATION> Garden.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>12:15
p.m.</TIME>; Special Show for Seniors, K101 Garden Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>;
Seniors' Day Contests, K101 Garden Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 4 to <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Joe
Ferrari Big Band Concert</ORGANIZATION>, K101 Garden Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; Eternal
Peace, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Youth <PERSON>Talent
Showcase</PERSON>, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Los Danzantes</LOCATION> De Aztlan,
KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; The <LOCATION>Lettermen</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Amphitheater.</LOCATION>; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; The Charms, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910807  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  107  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday August 7, 1991
00220111,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06222111 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06222111 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  (box)Today, 7 and 9 p.m.; Little Anthony, The Shirelles and Johnny Baron,
Amphitheater.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SANTA CLARA COUNTY FAIR
WHAT'S
DOING
AT THE FAIR?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Events  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Town &amp; Country Dog Training</ORGANIZATION>, Demo Green.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>American Dance Academy</ORGANIZATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>;
<PERSON>Freddie Jackson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Grandstand.</LOCATION>; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Hydro Matics</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA
Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, all day.; Open Western Horse Show, Horse
Arena.; (box)<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, all day.; Open Western Horse Show, Horse Arena.;
(box)<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, all day.; <ORGANIZATION>American Begonia Society Show &amp; Sale</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Vennum</ORGANIZATION>
Gardens.; (box)<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Cracker Eat &amp; Whistle and Egg &amp; Spoon Race
Contests</ORGANIZATION>, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; The Temptations,
<LOCATION>Grandstand.</LOCATION>; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910809  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  104  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday August 9, 1991
00222111,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06221085 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06221085 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing at the fair?; (box)Today, all day.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  Livestock Judging: <ORGANIZATION>Senior Beef Cattle &amp; Super Steer</ORGANIZATION> (<TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>), Livestock
Arena.; (box)Today, all day.; Livestock Judging: Senior Sheep and Senior Swine
(<TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>), Sheep &amp; Swine.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; Creating Bonsai, K101 Garden
Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Cornerstone</LOCATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Youth <PERSON>Talent Showcase</PERSON>, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>,
<TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Lindsey Johnson</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>;
Blood, <ORGANIZATION>Sweat &amp; Tears</ORGANIZATION>, Amphitheater.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 to 10 p.m.; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara
Valley Square Dancers Association</ORGANIZATION>, Variety Square.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>;
<PERSON>Nikki Love</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910808  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  103  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday August 8, 1991
00221085,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06218079 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06218079 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing; at the fair?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day.; <ORGANIZATION>Fruit &amp; Vegetable Weight/Number Guessing</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fiesta Hall.</LOCATION>;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>California Natives For The Dry Landscape</ORGANIZATION>, K101 Garden
Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Orange Peel &amp; Eat</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hula Hoop Contests</ORGANIZATION>, KNTV
Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; Shining Light, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Youth <PERSON>Talent Showcase</PERSON>, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>,
<TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Jensen Performing Arts</ORGANIZATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9
p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Williams &amp; Ree</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Amphitheater.</LOCATION>; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7-10 p.m.; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley
Square Dancers Association</ORGANIZATION>,Variety Square.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Kenny
Anderson Band</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910805  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  101  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday August 5, 1991
00218079,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06214121 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06214121 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing; at the fair?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day; 4-H English Horse Review.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day; Livestock
Judging: <ORGANIZATION>Junior Dairy Goats &amp; Junior Pygmy Goats</ORGANIZATION>, Sheep East Tent.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; Creating a Garden Habitat for Wildlife, K101 Garden
Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Leslie Ann Sine</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Licorice Rope-Off and <ORGANIZATION>Obstacle Course Contests</ORGANIZATION>, KNTV
Contest Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; Watermelon Feed and Hog Calling Contests,
KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)Today, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>South Bay School/Variety Show</LOCATION>,
KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; Tower of Power,
<LOCATION>Amphitheater.</LOCATION>; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; Some Assembly Required, International
Village Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Hydro Matics</PERSON>, KSFO/KYA Community
Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910801  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  117  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday August 1, 1991
00214121,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06219089 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06219089 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing; at the fair?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SANTA CLARA COUNTY FAIR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Events  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, noon to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Kids' Day Continuous Contests, Demo Green.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, noon to <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Kids' Day Art Experience, 4H-FFA-Juniors.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 2 to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Bay Area Freestyle Arm Wrestling Junior Championship,
KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; Stenciling, KSFO/KYA Community
Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Water Balloon Toss and Bubble Gum Blowing
Contests, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME>; Youth <PERSON>Talent Showcase</PERSON>,
KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Rob Hanna</PERSON>'s Salute to <PERSON>Rod
Stewart</PERSON>, Amphitheater.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; Daddy-O, KSFO/KYA Community
Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910806  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  100  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday August 6, 1991
00219089,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06215082 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06215082 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's doing; at the fair?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day; <ORGANIZATION>Gymkhana Horse Show</ORGANIZATION>, Horse Arena.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day;
Early Day Gas Engines, Sheep &amp; Swine-West Lawn.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>; Designing
With <ORGANIZATION>Garden Flowers</ORGANIZATION>, K-101 Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Cracker Eat &amp; Whistle</ORGANIZATION>
and Egg Toss Contests, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Starlite
Express</ORGANIZATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; (box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; Preserving Pictures,
Home Arts Demo Area.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; Tower of Power, <LOCATION>Amphitheater.</LOCATION>;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Junior Division Lad &amp; Ladies Lead</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Sheep &amp; Swine.</ORGANIZATION>;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Frankie Valli</PERSON> and the Four Seasons, <LOCATION>Grandstand.</LOCATION>;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; The Charms, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara
County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910802  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  112  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday August 2, 1991
00215082,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06213030 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06213030 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  What's; doing  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVENTS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>  at the fair?; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day; Junior Horse Performance Classes,
HorseArena.; (box)Today, noon; <ORGANIZATION>Sewing Machine Center-Knitting</ORGANIZATION>, Home Arts Demo
Area.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; Dancing Grandmothers Plus 1, KSFO/KYA Community
Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME>; Pie-Eating and Balloon Bust Contests, KNTV Contest
Stage.; (box)(box) <DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; Water Balloon Toss and Bubble Gum Blowing
Contests, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>; Stray Cats,
<LOCATION>Amphitheater.</LOCATION>; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Vallezano</LOCATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, 7-10 p.m.; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Square Dancers Association</ORGANIZATION>, Variety
Square.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; The Substitutes, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>; Daddy-O, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.; Source: <LOCATION>Santa Clara
County Fair</LOCATION>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910731  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  108  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday July 31, 1991
00213030,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06223120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06223120 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  (box)Today, all day.; American Begonia Society Show &amp; Sale, Vennum Gardens.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHAT'S DOING AT THE FAIR?  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Events  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, all day.; Open Western Horse Show, Horse Arena.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4
p.m.</TIME>; Diaper Derby, KNTV Contest Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>; The
Temptations, <LOCATION>Grandstand.</LOCATION>; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; Zamar, International Village
Stage.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; <ORGANIZATION>Kamaaina Dancers</ORGANIZATION>, KSFO/KYA Community Stage.;
(box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>; Little <PERSON>Joe y</PERSON> <LOCATION>La Familia</LOCATION>, Amphitheater.; (box)<DATE>Today</DATE>, <TIME>9
p.m.</TIME>; <PERSON>Joe Goodwin Band</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>International Village Stage</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Source: Santa Clara County Fair  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910810  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  71  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday August 10, 1991
00223120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06207094 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06207094 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COUNTY; FESTIVAL; FLOWER; PLANT; GARDEN  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  GARDENING seminars, plant sales, a drought display center and more than 600
flower and vegetable displays will be featured at the 47th annual Santa Clara
County Fair opening Friday at the Fairgrounds, 344 Tully Road, San Jose.;   
Floriculture exhibits will include flower arrangements, indoor and potted
plant displays, cut flowers and African violets. Fairgoers also can view the
agriculture and horticulture exhibits, which range from corn and cabbage to
plums and peaches.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COUNTY FAIR DIGS INTO GARDENING TOPICS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Happenings  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     A drought resource center, coordinated by the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Water
District</ORGANIZATION>, will be in place in the garden area. Vendors will have water-saving
plants for sale.;    Seminar presentations will be given on the Garden Stage
unless otherwise noted. They include:; (box)  <DATE>Friday</DATE>: Dahlias by <PERSON>Harrison
Elleard</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>John E. Stowell Dahlia Society</ORGANIZATION>,  <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Saturday</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Nite
Bloomers African Violet Club</ORGANIZATION> show and sale, all day next to <ORGANIZATION>Orchid House</ORGANIZATION>;
raising African violets by <PERSON>Doreen Hassan</PERSON>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Sunday</DATE>: Cactus and
<ORGANIZATION>Succulent Society of San Jose</ORGANIZATION> show and sale, all day next to Patio Area; talk
by <PERSON>Albert Wilson</PERSON>, noon; Floriculture Day and awards presentation, <TIME>2:30 p.m.</TIME>;  
 (box)  <DATE>Monday</DATE>: Fuchsias by <PERSON>Elsie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Al Sydnor</PERSON>  of <LOCATION>San Jose Branch</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American
Fuchsia Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: Kids day planters, "Make Your
Own," by <PERSON>Nancy Homen</PERSON> and members of <ORGANIZATION>Las Jardineras Garden Club</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;   
(box)  <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>: Low-water grasses by <PERSON>Wes Foster</PERSON>, garden writer and master
gardener, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>: Creating a garden habitat for wildlife by
<PERSON>Phil</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Vi Nisonger of Santa Clara County Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box) 
<DATE>Aug. 2</DATE>: Designing with garden flowers by <PERSON>Ruth Holmstrom</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Garden
Club</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Furyu  Floral Designers</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>: Malahini Orchid
Society show and sale, all day next to <ORGANIZATION>Orchid House</ORGANIZATION>; talk by <PERSON>Albert Wilson</PERSON>,
noon; orchid growing, <PERSON>Ken Matheson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Santa Clara Valley</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Malahini Orchid
Societies</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Bromeliad Study Group of Northern
California</ORGANIZATION> show and sale, all day next to Orchid House.;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 5</DATE>:
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> natives for the dry landscape by <PERSON>Glenn Rogers</PERSON>, landscape architect,
and <ORGANIZATION>California Native Plant Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>: Kids day
planters, "Make Your Own," <PERSON>Dorothy Goble</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dorothy Dorenus</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Las Jardineras 
Club</ORGANIZATION> members, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 7</DATE>: Orchids by <PERSON>Weegie  Caughlan</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Peninsula Orchid Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 8</DATE>: Bonsai by <PERSON>Les Steele</PERSON>
and <PERSON>John Thompson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Midori Bonsai Club</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 9</DATE>: Cactus and
succulents by <PERSON>Don Cravalho</PERSON> of the Cactus and <ORGANIZATION>Succulent Society</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <TIME>2
p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>: <PERSON>Clara B. Rees Iris Society</PERSON> show and sale, all day
next to <LOCATION>Patio Area</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Branch of American Begonia Society</ORGANIZATION> show
and sale, all day next to <ORGANIZATION>Orchid House</ORGANIZATION>; talk by <PERSON>Albert Wilson</PERSON>, noon;
propagating begonias by <PERSON>Mary Ann Leer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Malvina Rendler</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Begonia Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara County Rose Society</ORGANIZATION>
show and sale, all day next to Patio Area; rose talk by <PERSON>Lorrie Freeman</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara County Rose Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    Information: (408) 295-3050.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910725  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  511  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday July 25, 1991
00207094,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06214029 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06214029 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  GARDEN; SHOW; LIST; SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  GARDENERS will find seminars, plant sales, a drought display center and more
than 600 flower and vegetable displays at the 47th annual Santa Clara County
Fair under way at the Fairgrounds, 344 Tully Road, San Jose.;    Floriculture
exhibits include flower arrangements, indoor and potted plant displays, cut
flowers and African violets. The agriculture and horticulture exhibits range
from corn and cabbage to plums and peaches.;    Seminar presentations will be
given on the Garden Stage unless otherwise noted. They include:  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FAIR-GOING GARDENERS FIND A LOT TO DIG  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Events  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (box)  Today: Creating a garden habitat for wildlife by <PERSON>Phil</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Vi
Nisonger of Santa Clara County Humane Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Friday</DATE>:
Designing with garden flowers by <PERSON>Ruth Holmstrom</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Garden Club</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Furyu  Floral Designers</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Saturday</DATE>: Malahini Orchid Society
show and sale, all day next to <ORGANIZATION>Orchid House</ORGANIZATION>; talk by <PERSON>Albert Wilson</PERSON>, noon;
orchid growing, <PERSON>Ken Matheson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Santa Clara Valley</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Malahini Orchid
Societies</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Sunday</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Bromeliad Study Group of Northern
California</ORGANIZATION> show and sale, all day next to Orchid House.;    (box)  <DATE>Monday</DATE>:
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> natives for the dry landscape by <PERSON>Glenn Rogers</PERSON>, landscape architect
and <ORGANIZATION>California Native Plant Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>: Kids day
planters, "Make Your Own," <PERSON>Dorothy Goble</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dorothy Dorenus</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Las Jardineras 
Club</ORGANIZATION> members, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>: Orchids by <PERSON>Weegie  Caughlan</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Peninsula Orchid Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 8</DATE>: Bonsai by <PERSON>Les Steele</PERSON>
and <PERSON>John Thompson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Midori Bonsai Club</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 9</DATE>: Cactus and
succulents by <PERSON>Don Cravalho</PERSON> of the Cactus and <ORGANIZATION>Succulent Society</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, <TIME>2
p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>: <PERSON>Clara B. Rees Iris Society</PERSON> show and sale, all day
next to <LOCATION>Patio Area</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Branch of American Begonia Society</ORGANIZATION> show
and sale, all day next to <ORGANIZATION>Orchid House</ORGANIZATION>; talk by <PERSON>Albert Wilson</PERSON>, noon;
propagating begonias by <PERSON>Mary Ann Leer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Malvina Rendler</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Begonia Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    (box)  <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>: <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara County Rose Society</ORGANIZATION>
show and sale, all day next to Patio Area; rose talk by <PERSON>Lorrie Freeman</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara County Rose Society</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>;    Information: (408) 295-3050.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910801  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  349  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday August 1, 1991
00214029,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06208012 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06208012 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); PHOTO: The Temptations: They'll give you sunshine on a cloudy day;
PHOTO: Freddie Jackson; PHOTO: Frankie Valli; Photo: Kathy Mattea  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE Santa Clara County Fair's musical slate could best be likened to the menu
of a favorite neighborhood eatery -- nothing fancy, just tried-and-true fare
for the entire family. A careful musical gourmet should be able to find some
top-drawer blues, country and soul acts on the fair's two main stages. All the
acts on the 8,000-seat grandstand and 4,000-seat amphitheater stages are free
with fair admission.;    On the grandstand stage: Vaqueros Musical teams with
six other Hispanic acts for Noche de Estrellas III at 7 p.m. Saturday. The
rockin' oldies act Flash Cadillac has a concert -- complete with fireworks --
slated for 8:30 p.m. Sunday. Frankie Valli and the Four Seasons trot out those
memories with an 8 p.m. performance next Friday. Country diva Kathy Mattea,
who's been a major-league draw ever since she hit in '88 with "18 Wheels and a
Dozen Roses," has an 8 p.m. concert Aug. 3. The Bay Area's own living blues
legend, John Lee Hooker, teams with veteran rocker Elvin Bishop and jump-blues
specialists Little Charlie &amp; the Nightcats for an 8 p.m. show Aug. 4. Soul
crooner Freddie Jackson checks in for an 8 p.m. concert Aug. 9. The
Temptations, Motown's veteran stars, work at 4 and 8 p.m. Aug. 10.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FAIR'S MUSICAL FARE OFFERS SOMETHING FOR
EVERYONE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See related articles on pages 3 and 27
FRONT LINES  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     On the amphitheater stage (where all acts perform at 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>),
versatile country rockers the <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Tucker Band</ORGANIZATION> boogie on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Former
<PERSON>Springsteen</PERSON> sax man (and recent Bay Area emigre) <PERSON>Clarence Clemons</PERSON> blows up a
storm <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Asleep at the <ORGANIZATION>Wheel</ORGANIZATION> brings its unbeatable brand of Western swing
to the grandstand <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Local soul warhorses Tower of Power light up the
house <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and next <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Tex-Mex giants <ORGANIZATION>Little Joe y la Familia</ORGANIZATION> bring
their barn-burning brand of country and Mexican folk music to the grandstand
<DATE>Aug. 10.</DATE>;    Other grandstand acts include: <PERSON>Chris Le Doux</PERSON> (today), the Stray
Cats (<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>), the Jets (<DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>), the Little River Band (Aug. 4), comedians
<ORGANIZATION>Williams &amp; Ree</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>Aug. 5</DATE>), <PERSON>Rod Stewart</PERSON> impersonator <PERSON>Rob Hanna</PERSON> (Aug. 6), the
Lettermen (<DATE>Aug. 7</DATE>), Blood, <ORGANIZATION>Sweat &amp; Tears</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>Aug. 8</DATE>) and <PERSON>Little Anthony</PERSON>, the
Shirelles and Elvis impersonator <PERSON>Johnny Baron</PERSON> (Aug. 9).;    There are
non-musical attractions, too. Like rowdy bookends, the fair begins and ends
with <ORGANIZATION>Big Tires</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Big Engines</ORGANIZATION>. Tonight, it's Monster Truck Madness at 8; on
<DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>, it's the Destruction Derby at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> (the latter carries an
additional admission charge). You want tamer fare? Show up for the fireworks,
this <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at dusk.;    In addition to the big (or at least bigger)
name acts and attractions, there are loads of other diversions every day. They
include:;    (box) <PERSON>Jeff Allen</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magic Windows</ORGANIZATION>, a 3D laser holography exhibit
in the Bicentennial hall, 3-9 p.m. weekdays, noon-9 p.m. weekends.;    (box)
Last Laugh Comedy Showcase, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> nightly on the <ORGANIZATION>KNTV</ORGANIZATION> comedy and contest
stage.;    (box) The Harmonics Caribbean Steel Band, 6 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> nightly at
<ORGANIZATION>Eleanor Vennum</ORGANIZATION> Gardens.;    (box) Aztec Indian Dancers, 3, 6 and <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>
weekdays, with an additional show at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> on weekends, at the <ORGANIZATION>International
Village Stage.</ORGANIZATION>;    (box) Gold Heist Stunt Show, at the carnival entrance, 2,
4, 6:30 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> weekdays, with an additional noon performance on weekends.;
   (box) Petting zoo, near the Arch entrance, <TIME>noon-9 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>weekdays</DATE>, 11 a.m.-9
p.m. weekends.;    (box) <LOCATION>Bingo</LOCATION>, sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>South Valley Swim Club</ORGANIZATION>, <TIME>2-8
p.m.</TIME> every day in the grandstand terrace.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- David Plotnikoff  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910726  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  27  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  608  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 26, 1991
00208012,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06203217 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06203217 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Visit the Connoisseur's Marketplace, left, in Menlo Park
today, where food from 25 restaurants will be available; Vicky Merz, on the
left, and Debbie Merz sample some of the cuisine during last year's festival.;
PHOTO: Next Sunday, see Nancy Wilson, below, at the Summer Symphony Pops in
the Park at Stanford.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; RECREATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THIS is a big week with the Santa Clara County Fair opening Thursday and the
Gilroy Garlic Festival starting Friday.;    But for today try the
Connoisseur's Marketplace in Menlo Park featuring, along Santa Cruz Avenue,
culinary samplings from 25 restaurants and California wines and beers.
Entertainment runs 10 a.m. to 6 p.m. today at the El Camino Stage, corner of
El Camino Real and Santa Cruz Avenue and the Fremont Park Stage, corner of
University and Santa Cruz avenues. Both stages will be surrounded by white
umbrella tables and chairs. Two hundred artisans will show their creations.
Also featured are a petting zoo, clowns, face painting and art demonstrations.
Free admission and parking.;    (check) Also on tap is the California Country
Music Association, giving a family-oriented country barbecue and picnic from 2
to 6 p.m. today at Pleasure Living Connection, a new Western theme park on
Felter Road, Milpitas. Activities and live music, with a special appearance by
the Country Travelers. Admission is $5 and the chicken barbecue is $5.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GOOD DAY FOR FAIR PLAY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard
Things to do  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (check) A sneak preview of the <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION> opens from 5 to <TIME>11
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> with two hours of free carnival rides from 5 to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> Admission
for all ages is <MONEY>$4</MONEY> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> only. <PERSON>Greg Kihn</PERSON> Band entertains at 7 and <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the amphitheater; Monster Truck Madness can be seen at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the grandstand. "Childhood Memories" is the theme for this year's
edition, which has many new attractions including the Gold Heist Stunt Show, a
Kids' Korral, <PERSON>Jeff Allen</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magic Windows</ORGANIZATION> and elephant rides.;    Nightly
fireworks, animals, foods, a petting zoo, carnival and kiddie rides, contests
and entertainment will keep the fairgrounds hopping through <DATE>Aug. 11.</DATE>;   
Special dates to remember: kids<DATE>' days July 30</DATE> and <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>, when kids 16 and
under are free from noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; and noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Tuesdays</DATE> through
<DATE>Fridays</DATE>, when park admission plus <MONEY>$9</MONEY> buys unlimited carnival rides.;   
Regular fair hours are noon to <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>weekdays</DATE>, <TIME>11 a.m. to 11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturdays</DATE>
and <DATE>Sundays</DATE> and <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday, Aug. 11</DATE>. Admission is <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> general
(ages 17-59), <MONEY>$4</MONEY> seniors (60 and over) and children (5 and under) and <MONEY>$20</MONEY>
family (admits up to six members). Uniformed military are free. The
fairgrounds are at 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Call (408) 295-3050 for details.;
   (check) The Gilroy Garlic Festival opens <DATE>Friday</DATE> for a three-day run of
gourmet garlic dishes, four stages of entertainment, demonstrations, exhibits,
mariachis, clowns and puppets. Hours are 10 a.m. to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and <TIME>10 a.m.
to 6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Located at <LOCATION>Christmas Hill Park</LOCATION>, Tenth and
<PERSON>Miller</PERSON> avenues, <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>. Admission <DATE>Friday</DATE> is <MONEY>$7</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2 children</MONEY> and
seniors, and on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <MONEY>$8</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> seniors and children.;   
(box) Other family activities this week include:;    Events; An All You Can
Eat Ice Cream Social  will be held 1:30 to <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>next Sunday</DATE> at the
<ORGANIZATION>Community School of Music</ORGANIZATION> and Arts, 253 <ORGANIZATION>Martens Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. Featured
will be samplings from <PERSON>Dreyer</PERSON>'s, <ORGANIZATION>Double Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>, Baskin-Robbins, yogurt from
<PERSON>J. Higby</PERSON>'s, toppings from <ORGANIZATION>Smucker</ORGANIZATION>'s, a children's art exhibit and a sound
sampler for kids to try out musical instruments. Advance tickets are <MONEY>$4</MONEY>
adults, <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> children; at the gate, <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children, with family
attendance not to exceed <MONEY>$15</MONEY>. (415) 961-0342.;    Summer Dog Show.  The <ORGANIZATION>San
Mateo Kennel Club</ORGANIZATION> will hold its show <TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Cow
Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Geneva Avenue</LOCATION> and Santos Street, <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. Free admission.;    <ORGANIZATION>The
Summer Symphony Pops</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Park</LOCATION>  is slated for next <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Frost
Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Nancy Wilson</PERSON> will be featured this year
with <PERSON>Denis</PERSON> De Coteau conducting the <LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet Orchestra</LOCATION> in a
benefit for the <ORGANIZATION>Children's Health Council</ORGANIZATION>. Gates open at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> for picnic
goers. Live music by Take Four, a barbershop quartet, and Zigzag Walk, a jazz
band. The symphony program starts at <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> Box lunches and refreshments will
be available. <MONEY>$15</MONEY> lawn seating, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> chair seating with <MONEY>$3</MONEY> off for children and
seniors or a <MONEY>$35</MONEY> sponsor ticket. Tickets are available at the gate next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
or in advance by calling (415) 326-0643.;    Entertainment; "The Princess and
the Magic Pea."  A musical adaptation of a popular fairy tale. Performers are
ages 9-16. Curtain times are <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Saturday</DATE>,
and 4:30 next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the last day of the play's run. Alameda Children's
Musical Theatre, <DATE>1912</DATE> Central Ave., <LOCATION>Alameda</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$7</MONEY>; <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for seniors,
teens, military personnel and disabled people; <MONEY>$4</MONEY> children under 12. For
reservations call (415) 521-6965.;    Exhibits;  <ORGANIZATION>Children's Discovery Museum</ORGANIZATION> 
announces new <DATE>summer hours of</DATE> <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturdays</DATE>;
to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursdays</DATE>; and noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sundays</DATE> through <DATE>Aug. 27</DATE>. Tuesdays the
museum is open to pre-booked youth groups only. The museum features hands-on
exhibits and programs. Located at Woz Way and Auzerais Street, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
Admission is <MONEY>$6</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3 children</MONEY> (ages 4-18); 3 and under are free. (408)
298-5437.;    Upcoming; <LOCATION>Ringling Bros.</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus</ORGANIZATION>  is
scheduling its <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> appearances for <DATE>Aug. 20-27</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> and
<DATE>Aug. 29-Sept</DATE>. 2 at the <ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. Tickets range from <MONEY>$8.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$12.50</MONEY>,
available by calling (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910721  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  960  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 21, 1991
00203217,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06210024 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06210024 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: The San Jose Police Department Mounted Units, left, will be
making appearances throughout the run of the Santa Clara County Fair. PHOTO:
Below, 'Bye Bye Birdie' with, from left, Jennifer Panetto, John Panetto, Tori
Stewart, opens this week at the Montgomery Theater in San Jose.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; CHILDREN; ENTERTAINMENT; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  FAMILY entertainment is in the air this week heralded by nightly fireworks
from the Santa Clara County Fair and the pungent fragrance of the Gilroy
Garlic Festival.;    The 47th annual Santa Clara County Fair is now open daily
through Aug. 11 with many new attractions, including the Gold Heist Stunt
Show, a Kids' Korral, Jeff Allen's Magic Windows and elephant rides.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FIREWORKS AND GARLIC GALORE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard
Things to do  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     There also are animals, a petting zoo, carnival and kiddie rides, foods,
displays, exhibits, contests and entertainment.;    Special dates to remember:
Kids' days are <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>, when those 16 and under are free from noon
to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; and all <DATE>Tuesdays</DATE> through <DATE>Fridays</DATE> from noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>, when park
admission plus <MONEY>$9</MONEY> buys unlimited carnival rides.;    Regular fair hours are
noon to <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>weekdays</DATE>, <TIME>11 a.m. to 11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturdays</DATE> and <DATE>Sundays</DATE>, and 11
a.m. to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday, Aug. 11</DATE>. Admission is <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> general (ages 17-59), <MONEY>$4</MONEY>
seniors (60 and over) and children (5 and under), and <MONEY>$20 family</MONEY> (up to six
members). Uniformed military are free. The fairgrounds are at 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Call (408) 295-3050 for details.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Gilroy Garlic Festival</ORGANIZATION> is
open from <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, ending a three-day run of gourmet garlic
dishes, four stages of entertainment, demonstrations, exhibits, mariachis,
clowns and puppets. Festival site is <LOCATION>Christmas Hill Park</LOCATION>, Tenth and <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>
avenues, <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>. Take Highway 101 to <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>, exit at the Tenth Street off-ramp
and follow the signs. Admission is <MONEY>$8</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> seniors and children.;   
Other family activities this week include:;    Events;  An All You Can Eat Ice
Cream Social  will be held from 1:30 to <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Community
School of Music</ORGANIZATION> and Arts, 253 <ORGANIZATION>Martens Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. Featured will be
samplings from <PERSON>Dreyer</PERSON>'s, <ORGANIZATION>Double Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>, Baskin-Robbins, yogurt from <PERSON>J.
Higby</PERSON>'s, toppings from <ORGANIZATION>Smucker</ORGANIZATION>'s, a children's art exhibit, hands-on
activities and a sound sampler for kids to try out musical instruments.
Tickets at the gate are <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children. (415) 961-0342.;   
Entertainment;  "Bye Bye Birdie"  will be presented by the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Children's
Musical Theater</ORGANIZATION>, opening at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and continuing at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, 2
and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and 2 and <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>next Sunday</DATE>. All performances will be
held in the <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery Theater</ORGANIZATION>, Market and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> streets, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
Admission is <MONEY>$8</MONEY>-<MONEY>$9</MONEY> reserved. (408) 288-5437.;    "Fiddler on the Roof"  will
be presented by the <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow Theater</ORGANIZATION> youth this week at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, and 1 and <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, 457 <ORGANIZATION>E. Calaveras
Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION>. The show continues through <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. Tickets are <MONEY>$3</MONEY>, <MONEY>$1</MONEY>
seniors and children. (408) 942-2470.;    "Oklahoma!"  The <PERSON>Rodgers</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Hammerstein</ORGANIZATION> classic will be performed by the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View Recreation
Division</ORGANIZATION>'s Junior Theater late this week. Performances are slated for <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, 2 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>next Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION>,
201 S. Rengstorff Ave., Mountain View. Admission is <MONEY>$4</MONEY>, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> for seniors and
children under 16. (415) 903-6331.;    "Sacramento Fifty Miles"  is being
presented by the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara University Department of Theater and Dance</ORGANIZATION>
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the <ORGANIZATION>Fess Parker Studio Theater</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Franklin</PERSON> and
<LOCATION>Lafayette</LOCATION> streets, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. The musical comedy is loosely based on "The
Brementown Musicians." Set in the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gold fields, it follows four
animal friends who outfox a pair of villainous prospectors and win a lovely
home for themselves. Performance times are 11 a.m. Tickets are <MONEY>$4</MONEY>, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> students
and seniors. Call (408) 554-4015 for reservations.;    The Summer Symphony
Pops in the <LOCATION>Park</LOCATION>  is slated today at <ORGANIZATION>Frost Amphitheater</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Nancy Wilson</PERSON> will be featured this year with <PERSON>Denis</PERSON> De Coteau conducting the
<LOCATION>San Francisco Ballet Orchestra</LOCATION> in a benefit for the <ORGANIZATION>Children's Health Council</ORGANIZATION>.
Gates open at <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME> for picnickers. Live music by Take Four, a barbershop
quartet, and Zigzag Walk, a jazz band. The symphony program starts at <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>
Box lunches and refreshments will be available. <MONEY>$15</MONEY> lawn seating; <MONEY>$20</MONEY> chair
seating with <MONEY>$3</MONEY> off for children and seniors or a <MONEY>$35</MONEY> sponsor ticket. Tickets
are available at the gate. (415) 326-0643.;    Upcoming; Snowman Building
Contest.  For children ages 2-12. Divided into age groups. Six tons of snow to
work with. Bring decorations from home to dress up snowmen. Register from noon
to <TIME>1:45 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Happy Hollow Park</ORGANIZATION> and Zoo, <PERSON>1300 Senter Road</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.
<MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2 seniors</MONEY> (ages 65-80) and children (ages 2-14). (408)
295-8383.;    <LOCATION>Walden Marionettes</LOCATION>.  "A Spooky Affair" and "The Danse Macabre."
<TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 8</DATE>, <PERSON>Albert L. Schultz Jewish</PERSON> Community Center, 655 Arastradero
Road, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$5</MONEY>, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children. (415) 493-9400.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910728  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  842  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 28, 1991
00210024,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06257175 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06257175 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; Dancers from Los Lupenos will
perform in Fiestas Patrias  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ENTERTAINMENT; FESTIVAL; SOUTH-BAY; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  From San Jose's huge Mexican Independence Day Parade to Pleasanton's Pasta
Festival, there's fun, food and entertainment to suit any taste this weekend.
Admission to all is free, though there are charges for food and other items.
Here are some of the highlights:; Fiestas Patrias  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A FESTIVE WEEKEND  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>   Celebrates <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s independence; (box)Key events:  Parade, food, arts,
crafts, entertainment.; (box)Where:  Parade begins at <ORGANIZATION>Ninth</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>
streets in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; other events at <LOCATION>Almaden Boulevard</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Fernando
Street.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  Parade begins at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>; booths open at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>; entertainment at four stages <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>; art exhibit 6
to <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the Old Convention Center
at <LOCATION>Park Avenue</LOCATION> and Market Street.; <ORGANIZATION>Garin Apple Festival</ORGANIZATION>  (box)Key events: 
Cider tasting, old-fashioned games, square dancing, blacksmith demonstrations
and apple orchard tours.; (box)Where:  <LOCATION>Garin Regional Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hayward.</LOCATION>;
(box)When:  <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Participants may bring homemade pies for
judging from 12:30 to <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME>; <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> Art; and Wine Festival  (box)Key
events:  Wines from <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> wineries, arts and crafts booths, foods, music,
games, and "Kids' Kingdom" with petting zoo, face painting and more.;
(box)Where:  Central Park, on <ORGANIZATION>Kiley Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> north of Homestead Road in <LOCATION>Santa
Clara.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and Sunday.; <PERSON>Aki Matsuri</PERSON> 
(box)Key events:  Traditional Japanese-American outdoor festival, including
children's activities, costumed dancers, Taiko drummers, singers, food.;
(box)Where:  <PERSON>Wesley Methodist Church</PERSON>, 566 <ORGANIZATION>N. Fifth St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; (box)When: 
Noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>American Indian Summer Festival</ORGANIZATION>  (box)Key events: 
Dancing, singing, food, crafts, fun run, Indian village contests.; (box)Where:
 Spartan Stadium, Seventh and Alma streets, <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  Noon to <TIME>11
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>; noon to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Sunday.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Willow Glen</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Founders</ORGANIZATION>' Day  (box)Key
events:  10K run, 5K walk, parade, food, arts and crafts, wine tasting,
entertainment. Run or walk costs <MONEY>$18.</MONEY>; (box)Where:  Lincoln Avenue between
<LOCATION>Minnesota Avenue</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Willow Street</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  Run begins at <TIME>8
a.m.</TIME>, walk at <TIME>8:15</TIME>; other activities 9 a.m to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> Sunday.; Almaden Art; and
Wine Festival  (box)Key events:  130 artists and artisans, wine- and
ale-tasting, entertainment.; (box)Where:  <LOCATION>Parma Park</LOCATION>, next to the <ORGANIZATION>Almaden
Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>6445 Camden Ave.</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  10 a.m. to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>
Sunday.; <ORGANIZATION>Newark Days</ORGANIZATION>  (box)Key events:  Parade featuring championship horses,
antique autos; food and game booths; pet contest.; (box)Where:  Parade starts
at <ORGANIZATION>City Hall on Newark Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Thornton Avenue</LOCATION> and goes north to the
community center on <LOCATION>Cedar Boulevard</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION> boulevards, where other events
will be.; (box)When:  Parade begins at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Booths open noon to <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Pet contest at <TIME>1:30 p.m.</TIME> Sunday.; (box)<LOCATION>Pleasanton</LOCATION>
Pasta; Festival  (box)Key events:  Food, arts and crafts, beer and wine
garden, cooking demonstrations.; (box)Where:  Main Street, <LOCATION>Pleasanton.</LOCATION>;
(box)When:  10 a.m. to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Sunday.</LOCATION>; Mall
anniversary; <ORGANIZATION>Eastridge Mall</ORGANIZATION>'s 20th anniversary; (box)Key events:  Hands-on
space and science exhibit sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Engineering Careers Council</ORGANIZATION> and
NASA.; (box)Where:  <ORGANIZATION>Eastridge Mall</ORGANIZATION>, on <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION> west of <LOCATION>Capitol Expressway</LOCATION>
in <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; (box)When:  <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and Sunday.; Trail
dedication; Dedication of <LOCATION>Almaden Valley</LOCATION> leg of <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Ridge Trail</ORGANIZATION>; (box)Key
events:  Hiking, biking, horseback riding.; (box)Where:  <LOCATION>Santa Teresa County
Park</LOCATION>. For specific locations, call (408) 268-8220.; (box)When:  Events begin
at <TIME>9:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>; dedication ceremony at 12:30 p.m; barbecue at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910913  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  582  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, September 13, 1991
00257175,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06217196 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06217196 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Jack Fredricks, right, and his son Christopher along with their
Walden Marionettes will be performing Thursday in Palo Alto.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; CHILDREN; ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THERE'S plenty of family entertainment this week with two area county fairs
running concurrently. The Santa Clara County Fair will run daily through next
Sunday and the San Mateo County Fair and Floral Fiesta opens Tuesday and runs
through Aug. 18. Both have displays, exhibits, petting zoos, extensive
carnival rides and headliner entertainment. And both have discount days.
Taking advantage of these discounts can amount to a tidy savings if you're
escorting a number of children to the events.;    The 47th annual Santa Clara
County Fair has all the old favorites and many new attractions, including the
Gold Heist Stunt Show, a Kids' Korral, Jeff Allen's Magic Windows and elephant
rides.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FAIR-THEE-WELL THIS WEEK  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard
Things to do  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Dates to remember this week: Kids' day is <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, when kids 16 and under
are admitted free from noon to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; seniors' day is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, with those
60 and over admitted free all day; and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE> from noon to <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME>, park admission plus <MONEY>$9</MONEY> buys unlimited carnival rides for all ages.;   
Regular fair hours are <TIME>11 a.m. to 11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, noon to <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Monday-Friday, 11 a.m. to</DATE> <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>next Sunday</DATE>,
closing day. Admission is <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> general (ages 17-59), <MONEY>$4</MONEY> seniors (60 and over)
and children (5 and under), and <MONEY>$20</MONEY> family (admits up to six members).
Uniformed military are admitted free. The fairgrounds are at 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Call (408) 295-3050 for details.;    The <LOCATION>San Mateo County Fair</LOCATION> and
Floral Fiesta opens <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Hours are noon to 10 p.m. Mondays-Thursdays, noon
to <TIME>11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Fridays</DATE>, <TIME>10 a.m. to 11 p.m. Saturdays and 10 a.m. to 10 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Sundays</DATE> at the <LOCATION>San Mateo County Fairgrounds</LOCATION>, <DATE>2495</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. Delaware St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Mateo</LOCATION>.
Carnival rides will be <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY> each on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>; on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, all rides for
all ages all day will be <MONEY>$12</MONEY>. On <DATE>Friday</DATE> a pass for all rides between noon and
<TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> costs <MONEY>$7</MONEY>. Regular admission is <MONEY>$6</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$4</MONEY> seniors and children ages
6-12. Children's and family contests include a father-son look-alike, rooster
crowing, freckle count, marble and leap frog, diaper derby (<TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> next
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>), rug crawlers for 9 months and under, yo-yo fun, paper airplane
fly-off, fruit and vegetable sculpture, and farm animal sounds. (415)
574-3247.;    (box) Other family activities this week include:;    Events;
Make(*)A(*)Circus  is starting its <DATE>summer</DATE> swing around the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>. On
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it will appear at <TIME>12:30 p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Red Morton Park</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1120</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Roosevelt Ave.</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Redwood City</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> it will perform at <TIME>12:30 p.m.</TIME> at <LOCATION>Kennedy Park</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Hesperian</ORGANIZATION> and A streets, <LOCATION>Hayward</LOCATION>. On <DATE>Thursday</DATE> it will appear at <TIME>12:30 p.m.</TIME> in
<LOCATION>San Ramon Central Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alcosta Boulevard</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bollinger</PERSON> street, <LOCATION>San Ramon</LOCATION>. And
on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at noon it will be in <LOCATION>Callaghan Park</LOCATION>, 255 Sudden St., <LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION>.
Admission is free. (415) 776-8470.;    <ORGANIZATION>Summer Carnival</ORGANIZATION>  featuring children's
games, songs, magic, fun and food is open from <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>3:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
at <LOCATION>Rinconada Park</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Newell</PERSON> and Embarcadero streets, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. There will be a
children's penny carnival, storytelling, folk singing and Jay the Juggler.
Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Palo Alto Recreation Department</ORGANIZATION>. Admission is free. (415)
329-2380.;    Entertainment; "Bye Bye Birdie"  will be performed by the San
<PERSON>Jose Children</PERSON>'s Musical Theater at 2 and <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> in the <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery
Theater</ORGANIZATION>, Market and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> streets, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$8</MONEY>-<MONEY>$9</MONEY> reserved.
(408) 288-5437.;    "Fantastic Classics"  fairy tales will be performed by the
<ORGANIZATION>Fun City Show Company</ORGANIZATION> as part of the Family Series' <DATE>Saturday</DATE> programs
sponsored by <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Stage Company</ORGANIZATION>. The Fun City Show Company uses
versatility, mime, music and circus skills in its storytelling. The show
starts at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at 490 <ORGANIZATION>S. First St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$4</MONEY>.
Call (408) 283-7142 for tickets.;    "Fiddler on the Roof"  will be presented
by the <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow Theater Youth</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday-Friday</DATE> and <DATE>1</DATE> and <TIME>7:30 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, 457 <ORGANIZATION>E. Calaveras Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION>. Tickets
are <MONEY>$3</MONEY>, <MONEY>$1</MONEY> seniors and children. Call (408) 942-2470.;    "<PERSON>Heidi</PERSON>,"  a
presentation by the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Children's Musical Theater</ORGANIZATION>, opens at <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Friday</DATE> in downtown <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. The play will repeat at 2 and <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and
2 and <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>next Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery Theater</ORGANIZATION>, Market and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION>
streets. Admission is <MONEY>$5</MONEY>-<MONEY>$6</MONEY>. (408) 288-5437.;    "<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>!,"  the <PERSON>Rodgers</PERSON> and
Hammerstein classic, will be performed by the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View Recreation
Division</ORGANIZATION>'s Junior Theater this week. The final performance is at <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>
at the <ORGANIZATION>Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, 201 S. Rengstorff Ave., Mountain View. Admission is
<MONEY>$4</MONEY>, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> for seniors and children under 16. Call (415) 903-6331 for details.;   
"A Spooky Affair" and "The Danse Macabre"  will be enacted by the <ORGANIZATION>Walden
Marionettes</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Albert L. Schultz Jewish Community
Center</ORGANIZATION>, 655 Arastradero Road, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. Tickets at the door are <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY>
for children. (415) 493-9400.;    Upcoming; <ORGANIZATION>Ringling Bros.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnum &amp; Bailey
Circus</ORGANIZATION>  has scheduled its Bay Area appearances for <DATE>Aug. 20-27</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> and <DATE>Aug. 29-Sept</DATE>. 2 at the <ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. Tickets will be
<MONEY>$8.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$12.50</MONEY>, available by calling (408) 998-2277, (415) 762-2277.;    <ORGANIZATION>Snowman
Building Contest</ORGANIZATION>.  For children ages 2-12. Divided into age groups. Six tons
of snow to work with. Bring decorations from home to dress up snowmen.
Register from noon-1<TIME>:45 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Happy Hollow Park</ORGANIZATION> and Zoo, <PERSON>1300 Senter
Road</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2 seniors</MONEY> (ages 65-80) and children (ages
2-14). (408) 295-8383.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910804  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  964  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday August 4, 1991
00217196,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06208027 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06208027 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Jenny Anderson - Mercury News; Santa Clara County Fairgrounds  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SANTA-CLARA; COUNTY; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  When: Now through Aug. 11.;    Where: Santa Clara County Fairgrounds, 344
Tully Road, San Jose. (See parking map. Or take the light rail to the Curtner
Station and catch the No. 26 bus to the fairgrounds.)  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHEN TO GO, WHAT TO DO AND HOW TO EAT YOURSELF
SILLY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See related articles pages 3 and 27  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Hours: <TIME>Noon-11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>weekdays</DATE>, 11 <TIME>a.m.-11 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>weekends</DATE>, 11 <TIME>a.m.-8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Aug.
11</DATE> (closing day).;    Admission: <MONEY>$6.50 general</MONEY> (ages 17-59); <MONEY>$4</MONEY> juniors (ages
6-16) and seniors (ages 60 and over), <MONEY>$20 family</MONEY> (admits up to six members).
Various discounts are available; see below.;    Daily schedules: Highlights of
each day's schedule will appear Monday-Saturday in the Living section of the
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION>, and <DATE>Sundays</DATE> in the Local section, starting today and continuing
through closing day, <DATE>Aug. 11.</DATE>;    Discounts: Many businesses and organizations
offer free or reduced-price admission to the fair. In addition, here are the
bargain days:;    (box) Both <DATE>Mondays</DATE>, <DATE>July 29</DATE> and <DATE>Aug. 5</DATE>: All gate admissions
and carnival rides are half-price.;    (box) Both <DATE>Tuesdays</DATE>, <DATE>July 30</DATE> and <DATE>Aug.
6</DATE>: All kids ages 6-16 are admitted free from <TIME>noon-5 p.m.</TIME>;    (box) <DATE>Tuesdays</DATE>
through <DATE>Fridays</DATE>, <TIME>noon-5 p.m.</TIME>: All-you-can-ride for <MONEY>$9</MONEY> (plus fair admission).; 
  (box) Every day: Admission free to members of the military, in uniform.;   
More discounts: Combo discount coupons offer <MONEY>$2</MONEY> off gate admission and <MONEY>$2</MONEY> off
the <MONEY>$9</MONEY> all-you-can-ride pass. They may be used from <TIME>noon-5 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Tuesday-Friday</DATE>, days when the fair is less crowded. They are available on
<ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> products in participating locations, at <ORGANIZATION>Round Table Pizza</ORGANIZATION> locations
and county transit buses and light-rail vehicles.;    Even more discounts:
"Feature Days" honor individuals, groups and communities with reduced gate
prices. They include: <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION> Day; <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <LOCATION>San Jose Day</LOCATION>; <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Service Club</ORGANIZATION> Day; <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, Peace Officers Day; Next <DATE>Friday</DATE>, Teacher
Recognition Day; <DATE>Aug. 3</DATE>, Gilroy/Morgan Hill Day; <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>, Grange Day; <DATE>Aug. 5</DATE>,
<LOCATION>Los Gatos Day</LOCATION>, Special Olympics Day; <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>, Mountain View/Cupertino Day; <DATE>Aug.
7</DATE>, Seniors' Day; <DATE>Aug. 8</DATE>, <LOCATION>Santa</LOCATION> Clara/Campbell Day; <DATE>Aug. 9</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Union Labor</ORGANIZATION> Day;
<DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>, Firefighters Day; <DATE>Aug. 11</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Armed Services/Veterans/United Veterans
Council Day.</ORGANIZATION>;    Food: Hey, go crazy. It's the fair. Load up on everything
from fried artichoke hearts to gyros to menudo to <LOCATION>Philly Cheesesteaks</LOCATION> to
Indian tacos to English bangers to good ol' peanut butter sandwiches. Lots of
things are served on sticks so you can have a hand free to play the carnival
games.;    Details: (408) 295-3050.;    Entertainment recording: (408)
295-3050, extension 336.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910726  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  27  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  428  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday July 26, 1991
00208027,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06361003 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06361003 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  GARDEN; EDUCATION; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IF you need to prune trees and shrubs, but aren't quite sure where to make the
cuts, the following pruning demonstrations are scheduled.;   (box)  Home Depot
stores: Free clinic on bare-root roses and trees Saturday at 10 a.m. with
repeat sessions on Saturdays through Jan. 18.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Garden  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DEMONSTRATIONS SIMPLIFY PRUNING  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classes  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     (box)  <LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION> Rose Society: Free rose pruning demonstrations
<DATE>Jan. 4</DATE> and 5 from <TIME>1-3 p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Municipal Rose Garden</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Naglee</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dana</PERSON>
streets, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; and <DATE>Jan. 18 from 10</DATE> <TIME>a.m.-noon and 1-3 p.m.</TIME> at the <ORGANIZATION>Santa
Clara County Superior Courthouse Rose Garden</ORGANIZATION>, First and <LOCATION>St. James</LOCATION> streets, <LOCATION>San
Jose</LOCATION>. Information: (408) 251-3740.;   (box)  <ORGANIZATION>Yamagami</ORGANIZATION>'s Nursery: Rose pruning
seminars <DATE>Jan. 9</DATE> at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE> at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>, and <DATE>Jan. 12</DATE> at <TIME>10
a.m.</TIME> Fruit tree pruning seminars are scheduled <DATE>Jan. 16</DATE> at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>; <DATE>Jan. 18</DATE> at
<TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME>, and <DATE>Jan. 19</DATE> at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> Classes will be held at the
nursery, <DATE>1361</DATE> S. Saratoga-Sunnyvale Road, <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>. Registration is required.
Fee: <MONEY>$15</MONEY> with <MONEY>$5</MONEY> credit toward merchandise. Information: (408) 252-3347.;  
(box)  <PERSON>Carman</PERSON>'s Nursery: Free kiwi pruning demonstrations at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE>
and <DATE>Jan. 18</DATE>. The nursery is located at 16201 <LOCATION>Mozart Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>.
Information: (408) 356-0119.;   (box)  <LOCATION>Peninsula</LOCATION> Rose Society: Free rose
pruning demonstration <DATE>Jan. 12 from</DATE> <TIME>1-3 p.m.</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Roger Reynolds Nursery</ORGANIZATION>, 133
<LOCATION>Encinal Ave.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>. Information: (415) 323-5612.;   (box)  <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s
Morcom Amphitheater of Roses: Site for free rose pruning demonstration <DATE>Jan. 12</DATE>
from 1-4 p.m, sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland Office of Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Recreation and the
<LOCATION>East Bay Rose Society</LOCATION>. In case of rain, it's rescheduled <DATE>Jan. 26 from 1-4</DATE> p.m.
Information: (510) 273-3090.;   (box)  University of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>,
Botanical Gardens: Workshop on bud grafting and other grafting techniques <DATE>Jan.
12</DATE> from <TIME>1-4 p.m.</TIME>, at the garden on <ORGANIZATION>Centennial Drive</ORGANIZATION> behind the campus. Cost:
<MONEY>$8 members</MONEY>, <MONEY>$12</MONEY> non- members; also, pruning demonstration of old-fashioned
roses, 10 a.m.-noon <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE>. Cost: <MONEY>$10</MONEY> members; <MONEY>$15</MONEY> non-members. Information:
(510) 642-3343.;   (box)  <PERSON>Symons</PERSON> Nursery: Free seminar <DATE>Jan. 18</DATE> at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> on
pruning, grafting, sprays and fertilizers for roses, fruit trees and vines at
806 <ORGANIZATION>W. San Carlos St.</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Sunol</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>;   (box)  Gamble Garden Center:
Fruit tree pruning workshop <DATE>Jan. 25 from 9</DATE> <TIME>a.m.-12:30 p.m.</TIME>; also, a class on
rose pruning and winter care, <DATE>Feb. 1</DATE> from <TIME>9:30-11 a.m.</TIME> at 1431 <LOCATION>Waverley  Ave.</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>. Cost for each workshop: <MONEY>$15 members</MONEY>, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> non-members. Information:
(415) 329-1356.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911226  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  430  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, December 26, 1991
00361003,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06224070 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06224070 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Children's music performer Joanie Bartels will be at the San
Jose Kids Fair '91 Saturday and next Sunday.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; RECREATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  COUNTY fairs are still in the limelight today with the San Mateo County Fair
and Floral Fiesta in full swing as the Santa Clara County Fair comes to a
close.;    It may sound hokey, but county fairs still provide the best family
entertainment package around. The San Mateo fair is in mid-run, with Maria
Muldaur and a Hispanic celebration featured tonight to cap a day of exhibits,
carnival rides and other special fair attractions.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BAY AREA STILL FAIRING WELL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The Diaper Derby -- which pits the wits and patience of parents who try to
entice their little ones to crawl along a 10-yard carpet -- will be at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>today</DATE>. Rug crawlers 9 months and under are eligible to compete. The <ORGANIZATION>Diaper
Derby</ORGANIZATION> is among many children's and family contests scheduled during the fair;
others include a father-son look-alike contest, rooster crowing, a freckle
count, marble and leapfrog competitions, balloon races, yo-yo contests, a
paper airplane fly-off, small-engine trouble-shooting, fruit and vegetable
sculpture, clay carving and farm animal sounds. Call (415) 574-3247 for
complete details.;    <LOCATION>San Mateo County</LOCATION> Fair admission is <MONEY>$6</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$4 seniors</MONEY>
(age 62 and over) and children (6-12). The fairgrounds are at <DATE>2495</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>S. Delaware
St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Mateo.</LOCATION>;    The <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fair</LOCATION> ends its run today, opening at
<TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> and closing at <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> Admission is <MONEY>$6.50 general</MONEY> (ages 17-59), <MONEY>$4</MONEY>
seniors (60 and over) and children (5 and under) and <MONEY>$20</MONEY> family (admits up to
six members). Uniformed members of the military are admitted free. The
fairgrounds are at 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Call (408) 295-3050 for details.;
   Other family activities this week include:; Events; Movies in the Round 
will be shown from <TIME>8:30 to 10:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> to children floating on inner
tubes at the <ORGANIZATION>Milpitas Sports Center Complex</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1325</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>E. Calaveras Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION>. Popcorn and inner tubes will be provided at <MONEY>$1</MONEY> per person. For ages
12 and up. (408) 942-2470.;    <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> Kids Fair '91  will be from <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to
<TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>next Sunday</DATE> at the San <ORGANIZATION>Jose Convention Center</ORGANIZATION>, 150 <PERSON>W. San
Carlos St. Ernie Reyes Jr.</PERSON>, who plays <PERSON>Leonardo</PERSON>, one of the <ORGANIZATION>Teenage Mutant
Ninja Turtles</ORGANIZATION>, will star in a live stage show on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at 12:15 and <TIME>4:30
p.m.</TIME> Also on the entertainment bill for the weekend will be <PERSON>Joanie Bartels</PERSON>, a
children's music performer, and <PERSON>J.D. Roth</PERSON>, host of the children's television
show "Fun House." Also featured will be Make(*)A(*)Circus, puppet shows,
storytellers and games and crafts and interactive displays sponsored by the
<ORGANIZATION>Children's Discovery Museum</ORGANIZATION> and The Garage. In addition, Bay Area Parent
magazine will host its "cover kids contest." The Kids Fair is sponsored by TV
station KNTV; admission is <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$1.50</MONEY> children. (408) 977-4309.;   
Entertainment; Children's show,  "The <PERSON>Nina</PERSON>, the Pinta and the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>,"
will be presented by the <ORGANIZATION>Flamenco Society of San Jose</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at
490 <ORGANIZATION>S. First St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Dancers, singers and guitarists will commemorate
the 500th anniversary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' arrival in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, and children will be
taught dance steps as they participate in the musical voyage from <LOCATION>Cadiz</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>. Tickets are <MONEY>$4</MONEY>. (408) 283-7142.;    "<PERSON>Heidi</PERSON>,"  by the
San <PERSON>Jose Children</PERSON>'s Musical Theater, will be presented at 2 and <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>
at the <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery Theater</ORGANIZATION>, Market and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> streets. Admission is <MONEY>$5</MONEY>-<MONEY>$6</MONEY>.
(408) 288-5437.;    Exhibits;  <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Discovery Museum</ORGANIZATION>.  The Folk Art '91
exhibit features displays and workshops on carousel animals and
carousel-related activities. At the museum, <PERSON>William Dentzel</PERSON> is building a
manually operated Mexican-style carousel. Foot pedals power the carousel and
set its animals spinning. The hand-carved creatures include four horses with
horse hair tails, a rabbit, frog, pig and a cat. On <DATE>Sept. 15</DATE>, the museum will
hold a carousel festival commemorating the end of the summer-long project. The
museum, open 10 a.m.-5 p.m. Tuesdays-Sundays, features hands-on interactive
exhibits and programs. Located in Building 557 <LOCATION>East Fort Baker</LOCATION>, northeast end
of the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate Bridge</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Sausalito</LOCATION>. Admission is <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3 children</MONEY>
(ages 2-17), <MONEY>$4</MONEY> seniors (65 and older) and students over 17. (415) 332-9646.; 
  Sharks.  This special exhibit exploring the myths and realities of sharks
continues at the <LOCATION>Monterey Bay Aquarium</LOCATION> through <DATE>Oct. 20</DATE>. The exhibit features
live species, hands-on activities and video presentations. Free with regular
aquarium admission of <MONEY>$9</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> students and seniors, and <MONEY>$4 children</MONEY>
(ages 3-12). Sea otters, touch pool and a three-story kelp forest are all
regular exhibits at the aquarium, 886 <ORGANIZATION>Cannery Row</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Monterey</ORGANIZATION>. Open daily from
<TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> (408) 648-4888.;    Upcoming; <ORGANIZATION>Gilroy Hispanic Cultural
Festival</ORGANIZATION>  will be <DATE>Aug. 24-25</DATE> at <LOCATION>Christmas Hill Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>. Mariachis,
folkloric dancers and South American musicians will fill three stages of
entertainment with Sha-boom and <PERSON>Dr. Loco</PERSON>'s Rockin' Jalapeno Band headlining.
Food and cultural displays will be featured. Admission will be <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$1</MONEY>
children ages 7-12. (408) 842-1411.;    <ORGANIZATION>Ringling Bros.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnum &amp; Bailey
Circus</ORGANIZATION>  is scheduling its <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> appearances for <DATE>Aug. 20-27</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Oakland
Coliseum</ORGANIZATION> and <DATE>Aug. 29-Sept</DATE>. 2 at the <ORGANIZATION>Cow Palace</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Daly City</LOCATION>. Tickets will range
from <MONEY>$8.50</MONEY>-<MONEY>$12.50</MONEY> and are available by calling (408) 998-2277, (415)
762-2277.;    Snowman building contest.  Children ages 2-12 will be divided
into age groups for this unusual contest in which they'll have six tons of
snow to work with. Participants should bring decorations from home to dress up
their snow creations. Register from noon-1<TIME>:45 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Happy Hollow Park</ORGANIZATION>
and Zoo, <PERSON>1300 Senter Road</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2 seniors</MONEY> (ages 65-80) and
children (2-14); those under 2 and over 80 are free. (408) 295-8383.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910811  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  993  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday August 11, 1991
00224070,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06355038 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06355038 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; RANKING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Bugsy.; (box)    Reviewed, this page.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Eye  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  OPENING TODAY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  MOVIES  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Father of the Bride.; (box)    Reviewed, Page 7.;   Rhapsody in August.;
(box)    Reviewed, Page 8.;   JKF.; (box)    Reviewed, Page 10.;   COMING UP;
High Heels.; (box)<PERSON>Marisa Paredes</PERSON>  and <PERSON>Victoria Abril</PERSON> are mother and daughter
sharing unpleasant memories of the same lover. Directed by <PERSON>Pedro Almodovar</PERSON>. 
Opens Christmas day.;   <ORGANIZATION>Fried Green</ORGANIZATION> Tomatoes.; (box)<PERSON>Jessica Tandy</PERSON>  and <PERSON>Kathy
Bates</PERSON> -- consecutive best-actress Oscar winners -- star in this story based on
the hilarious <ORGANIZATION>Fanny Flagg</ORGANIZATION> novel.  Coming in <LOCATION>January.</LOCATION>;   The Prince of Tides;
(box)<LOCATION>Barbra Streisand</LOCATION>'s  adaptation of the <PERSON>Pat Conroy</PERSON> novel, with <PERSON>Nick Nolte</PERSON>
as a <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> football coach who falls for his suicidal sister's <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> shrink (played by Streisand).  Opens Christmas day.;   Grand Canyon;
(box)<PERSON>Lawrence Kasdan</PERSON>  weighs in with what is being called a "Big Chill" for
the '90s. Starring <PERSON>Steve Martin</PERSON> (busy guy!), <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON> and <PERSON>Danny Glover</PERSON>. 
Opens <DATE>Jan. 10.</DATE>;   TOP MONEY-MAKERS; (box)1. "Hook"  TriStar.;   (box)2. "The
Last Boy Scout"  <ORGANIZATION>Warner Bros.</ORGANIZATION>;   (box)3. "Star Trek VI: The Undiscovered
Country"  Paramount;   (box)4. "The Addams Family"  Paramount;   (box)5.
"Beauty and the <LOCATION>Beast</LOCATION>"  Disney;   (box)6. "My Girl"  <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>;   (box)7. "Cape
Fear"  Universal;   (box)8. "For the Boys"  20th Century Fox;   (box)9. "An
American Tail: Fievel Goes West"  Universal;   (box)10. "Curly Sue"  <ORGANIZATION>Warner
Bros</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911220  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  206  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, December 20, 1991
00355038,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06112129 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06112129 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Clowns Jeremy and Julietta, left, perform today at the
Milpitas Community Center.; PHOTO: Next weekend is the grand-opening
celebration of the Bay Area Discovery Museum in Sausalito, with plenty of
entertainment for kids, above.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FAMILY; CHILDREN; RECREATION; ENTERTAINMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SPRING has sprung when cherry blossom festivals are under way, especially the
big parade in San Francisco at 1 p.m. today. It begins at City Hall and
travels 15 blocks to the Japan Center, Post and Buchanan streets, for the
final activities in the two-weekend event.;    (box) San Jose's cherry blossom
festival, "Nikkei Matsuri," will be held 9:30 a.m. to 4 p.m. next Sunday at
Fifth and Jackson streets, San Jose. Call (408) 298-4303 for details.;   
(box) Two major cat shows are in progress today in San Jose. The Aristicats
Cat Club is holding "A Feline Coronation" in a 12-ring all-breed championship
and household pet show 9:30 a.m. to 5 p.m. today at the Santa Clara County
Fairgrounds, 344 Tully Road, San Jose. $4 adults, $10 family (two adults and
two children), $2 children ages 12 to 15, and $1 seniors.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CHERRY BLOSSOMS ON PARADE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Family Clipboard
Things to do  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Cat Fanciers</ORGANIZATION> show will be 10 a.m. to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at
the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose Civic Auditorium Exhibit Hall</ORGANIZATION>, 291 S. Market St., <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. More
than 300 cats, representing all breeds and household pets, will compete. <MONEY>$4</MONEY>
adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> children and seniors.;    (box) The Bay Area Discovery Museum, a
new children's museum beneath the Golden Gate Bridge in <LOCATION>Sausalito</LOCATION>, is hosting
its grand opening party <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and next <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. From 10 a.m. to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> both
days, kids can make wooden toy boats, draw sidewalk chalk murals, paint an
underwater scene and more. Continuous music, entertainment and face painters.
Tickets, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> and <MONEY>$5</MONEY>, are available at the museum. Take Hwy. 101 north to the
Alexander Avenue exit and follow signs. (415) 332-7674.;    (box)  "Animal
Crackers" is the theme for the Downtown Mountain View Parade set for noon
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>. More than 1,500 participants will dance, march, juggle and sing
their way from <PERSON>Evelyn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> streets, up <PERSON>Castro</PERSON>, past Mercy Street and the
new Civic Center Plaza for a post-parade celebration at <LOCATION>Pioneer Park</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION>
and <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> streets. Contemporary big-band jazz by <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> Night Live, food and
carnival booths will be at the park. Free admission.;    (box) <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION> Young
Artists' Fair will be <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, with live entertainment,
workshops in visual and performing arts, exhibits and food. Community Center,
457 <ORGANIZATION>E. Calaveras Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION>. (408) 942-2470.;    Other family activities
this week include:; EVENTS; <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>'s 43rd Anniversary  will be celebrated
12:30 to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> with <PERSON>Joel Nelson</PERSON>'s orchestra, folk songs, a petting zoo,
game booths, food and carnival rides. <ORGANIZATION>Jewish Community Center</ORGANIZATION>, 14855 Oka Road,
<LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>. Free admission.;    <PERSON>Clowns Jeremy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Julietta</PERSON>  entertain with
juggling, acrobatics and magic at <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Milpitas Community
Center</ORGANIZATION> auditorium, 457 <ORGANIZATION>E. Calaveras Blvd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION>. Sponsored by a grant from
the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Milpitas</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Young Audiences of San Jose</ORGANIZATION>. Free.;    Senior Expo, 
a fair for seniors and their families, takes place 11 a.m. to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> at
the <LOCATION>Santa Clara County Fairgrounds</LOCATION>, 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Entertainment,
how-to demonstrations, arts and crafts, medical screening tests and food. Free
admission. (408) 295-3050.;    Entertainment; <PERSON>Linda Arnold</PERSON>  appears in concert
at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> and <TIME>2 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the Little Theater, School for the Deaf,
39350 <ORGANIZATION>Gallaudet Drive</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>. Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Weibel Elementary School PTA</ORGANIZATION>.
<MONEY>$7.50</MONEY>. (408) 998-3400.;    A Concert for Children  will be given by <PERSON>Vicki
Neville Coffis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Steve Palazzo</PERSON> at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the Kuumbwa Jazz
Center, 320-2 Cedar St., <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. A benefit for Planned Parenthood of <LOCATION>Santa
Cruz County</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$5</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$3</MONEY> children. (408) 425-1551.;    Exhibits;  Sharks. 
This special exhibit exploring the myths and realities of sharks continues at
the <LOCATION>Monterey Bay Aquarium</LOCATION> through <DATE>Oct. 20</DATE>. Live species, hands-on activities
and video presentations are featured. Free with regular aquarium admission of
<MONEY>$9</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$6.50</MONEY> students and seniors, and <MONEY>$4 children</MONEY> (ages 3 to 12). Sea
otters, touch pool and a three-story kelp forest are all regular exhibits at
the aquarium, 886 <ORGANIZATION>Cannery Row</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Monterey</ORGANIZATION>. Open daily 10 a.m. to <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> (408)
648-4888.; UPCOMING; <PERSON>Lorrie Morgan</PERSON>,  a rising country-western singing star,
will perform at <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> at an all-day <DATE>spring</DATE> outing next <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Santa
Clara County Fairgrounds</LOCATION>, 344 <ORGANIZATION>Tully Road</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. From noon to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME> there
will be pony rides, a puppet show and refreshments. The outing is a
fund-raiser for the <ORGANIZATION>Community Coordinated Child Development Council of Santa
Clara County</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$8</MONEY> adults, <MONEY>$2</MONEY> children 12 and under, <MONEY>$20</MONEY> family ticket (two
adults and unlimited children).;    <PERSON>Keith Terry</PERSON>,  a body musician,
percussionist and rhythm dancer, has scheduled two family performances, <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>May 3</DATE> and <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>May 4</DATE>, at the Center for the Performing Arts, <PERSON>Castro</PERSON> and
Mercy streets, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$18</MONEY>. For tickets, call (415) 903-6000.;   
"Little Shop of Horrors"  will be presented <DATE>May 3</DATE> through 5 at the <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery
Theater</ORGANIZATION>, Market and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> streets, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>. Performances by the <ORGANIZATION>San Jose
Children</ORGANIZATION>'s Musical Theater are <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>May 3</DATE>, 2 and <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>May 4</DATE>, and 2 and <TIME>7
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>May 5</DATE>. <MONEY>$8</MONEY>-<MONEY>$9</MONEY>. (408) 288-5437.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DOROTHY PRIES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910421  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  893  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 21, 1991
00112129,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06329151 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06329151 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  HOLIDAY; CHARITY; ORGANIZATION; FOOD; PROGRAM; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Here are some of the charitable organizations that need donations of food or
money to provide Thanksgiving Day meals or food boxes to needy people.; SANTA
CLARA COUNTY  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHERE TO GIVE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See related story page 1B of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)CityTeam Ministries, 44 <PERSON>W. Julian St.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; (408) 998-4770. Needs
turkeys and stuffing mix, pumpkin pies, canned cranberry sauce and vegetables.
Will accept donations at the <ORGANIZATION>Julian Street Rescue Mission</ORGANIZATION> seven days a week
from <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> Checks can be mailed to CityTeam at P.O. Box 143, <LOCATION>San
Jose 95103.</LOCATION>; (box)<ORGANIZATION>Loaves &amp; Fishes</ORGANIZATION>, 389 <ORGANIZATION>E. Santa Clara St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, behind
<LOCATION>St. Patrick</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Cathedral</LOCATION>; (408) 293-4505. Need turkeys and canned goods,
pumpkin pies, potatoes, salad greens. Accepting donations weekdays from <TIME>10:30
a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>, and <DATE>today</DATE> from <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>; (box)<ORGANIZATION>Sacred Heart
Community Service</ORGANIZATION>, 803 S. First St., <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; (408) 283-5800. Need turkeys
and trimmings, hams, canned goods, cranberry sauce, pumpkin pies, and staples
such as rice, beans and tomato products. Open for donations from <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME> weekdays. Checks for financial donations can be mailed to the above
address, ZIP 95110.; (box)<ORGANIZATION>Second Harvest Food Bank of Santa Clara</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>San
Mateo Counties</LOCATION>, 297 Commercial St., <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; (408) 286-9170. Needs turkeys,
chickens and canned goods. Will accept donations weekdays from <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5
p.m.</TIME>; (box)<LOCATION>St. Joseph</LOCATION>'s Family Center, <ORGANIZATION>7950-A Church St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Gilroy</LOCATION>; (408)
842-6662. Needs canned, frozen or fresh hams and turkeys, fresh vegetables,
fruit and canned goods. Donations accepted from <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> to noon and from 1 to <TIME>4
p.m.</TIME> weekdays.; (box)<LOCATION>San Jose Urban Ministry</LOCATION>, 44 <ORGANIZATION>S. Fifth St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; (408)
292-4286. Donations of turkeys, hams and coffee will be accepted at the <ORGANIZATION>Julian
Street Inn</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Julian</PERSON> and <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> streets, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, daily from <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5:30
p.m.</TIME>; (box)The <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army</ORGANIZATION>, 359 <ORGANIZATION>N. Fourth St.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; (408) 998-4400.
Needs turkeys, hams, canned, bottled and packaged fruit and vegetables. Open
for donations at either the front office or Room 202, from 8 to <TIME>11:45 a.m.</TIME> and
12:30 to <TIME>4:15 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Contribution checks can be mailed to
the <ORGANIZATION>Salvation Army</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 2-D, <LOCATION>San Jose 95109.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>SAN MATEO</LOCATION> COUNTY;
(box)Ecumenical Hunger Program, <DATE>1934</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>University Ave.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>East Palo Alto</LOCATION>; (415)
323-7781. Accepting food, clothing and furniture donations weekdays from <TIME>9
a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>; (box)<LOCATION>St. Anthony</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Padua</LOCATION> Dining Room, 3500 <LOCATION>Middlefield Road</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>; (415) 365-9664. Needs turkeys, vegetables and baked goods. Accepts
donations <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturday</DATE> from <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> at the dining room,
or at the parish rectory after hours until <TIME>8 p.m.</TIME>; SOUTHERN ALAMEDA COUNTY;
(box)LOV-Newark, 37400 Central Court, <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>; (510) 793-5683. Needs turkeys
and ingredients for stuffing and other trimmings, canned hams, fruits and
vegetables, pies, roasting pans, paper plates, plastic utensils, other dinner
supplies, cash donations and volunteers. Donations accepted from <TIME>8 a.m. to 11
p.m.</TIME> daily.; (box)<ORGANIZATION>Tri-City Volunteers Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, 37350 <PERSON>Joseph St.</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>; (510)
793-4583. Needs turkeys, hams, canned meats and vegetables. Accepting
donations from <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> weekdays.; <LOCATION>SANTA</LOCATION> CRUZ COUNTY; (box)River
Street Shelter, 733 River St., <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>; (408) 425-3437. Needs frozen
turkeys, canned vegetables, staples. Donations accepted from 3 to <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> seven
days a week.; (box)Veterans of Foreign Wars Bill Motto Post 5888, 846 Front
St., <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>; (408) 429-8345. Needs turkeys, canned hams and vegetables and
other staples. Donations can be brought to the Veterans Memorial Building, 846
Front St., from <TIME>10 a.m. to 5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, and from <TIME>8 a.m. to 10 p.m.</TIME> weekdays.
Financial contributions to buy produce can be mailed to the VFW post at P.O.
Box 664, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> 95061.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911124  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  618  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, November 24, 1991
00329151,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
