<DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880408-0107 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex Outlines Shared Exchange In Merger Plan </HL>
<AUTHOR> Gary Lamphier (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GLVAF T.MSG LCNAF T.ICR T.RGM </CO>
<IN> STK PCS CMD TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said that its proposed merger with three affiliates and a large Royex holder would be implemented through an exchange of shares and that the new company will be called <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Royex has proposed to merge with affiliates <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s second-largest holder, <ORGANIZATION>Galveston Resources Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 
If approved at planned shareholder meetings in <DATE>June</DATE>, the resulting company would be one of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest and lowest-cost gold producers. 

   Under terms of the proposed merger, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s share capital would consist mainly of Class A shares, with one vote each, and Class B shares, with 100 votes each. 
Royex Chairman <PERSON>Ned Goodman</PERSON> said certain Royex executives and directors would receive Class B shares with a combined voting stake of more than <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> in <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Royex said the merger plan, approved by the directors of each company <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, provides that Royex holders would receive 0.61 Class A share of <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for each <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> common share; <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> holders would receive one <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Class A share for each of their common shares; Lacana holders would receive 1.32 Class A shares of the new company for each Lacana share; and Mascot holders would receive 1.11 Class A shares for each <ORGANIZATION>Mascot</ORGANIZATION> share. 

   Galveston holders would receive 0.43 Class A share for each <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> Class A share, and 0.43 Class B share in the new company for each <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> Class B share. 

   The shares of the five companies are expected to resume trading today on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 
They were halted prior to the opening <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 

   Royex closed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at <MONEY>6.125 Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$4.94</MONEY>), Corona closed at <MONEY>9.75 dollars</MONEY>, Lacana at <MONEY>13.125 dollars</MONEY>, Mascot at <MONEY>11.25 dollars</MONEY>, and <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>'s Class A and B shares each closed at <MONEY>4.60 dollars</MONEY>. 
The share values give the concerns a combined indicated market capitalization of about <MONEY>2.52 billion dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$2.03 billion</MONEY>). 

   The merger plan also specifies that all intercompany holdings between Royex, its affiliates and <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> be canceled. 
Royex currently holds a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> stake in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION> and <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> of Lacana, which in turn owns <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of Mascot. 
Corona and <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> are <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s largest holders, with interests of about <PERCENT>41%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT>, respectively. 
All companies are based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> but <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, based in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>. 

   Royex's <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> will be chairman of the new concern, and <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, Royex president and chief executive officer, would retain his posts. 
<ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is expected to have <DATE>1988</DATE> gold output of about 465,000 ounces, annual cash flow of about <MONEY>200 million dollars</MONEY>, and interests in industrial minerals and oil and gas as well as gold. 
Four new gold mines are expected to be added by the end of <DATE>1989</DATE> to the five concerns' present eight mines. 

   Royex, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> would also issue warrants to purchase new <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION> shares, and <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said holders of its preferred shares and all warrants, options and convertible securities of the merging companies would be issued securities of <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION> at the proposed merger ratios. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880407-0129 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex, 3 Affiliates And Large Holder Propose a Merger </HL>
<AUTHOR> Gary Lamphier (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.RGM T.ICR LCNAF T.MSG GLVAF </CO>
<IN> TNM PCS CMD </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, three of its affiliates and <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s second-largest holder proposed a merger that would create one of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s biggest gold producers. 

   <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s president and chief executive officer, said directors of Royex, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Galveston Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> were to vote yesterday on the proposed merger. 
He said he expected the boards to approve the plan. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> wouldn't disclose terms of the proposed merger or the name of the company that would result from it. 
He said further details would be provided today. 

   Royex holds a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> stake in Corona and a <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> interest in <LOCATION>Lacana</LOCATION>, which in turn owns <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of Mascot. 
Corona and <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> are <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s largest holders, with interests of about <PERCENT>41%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>14%</PERCENT>, respectively. 
All the companies are based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> except <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, which is based in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said the merger would simplify Royex's complex corporate structure and result in the formation of a "significant" gold mining concern. 
He said the proposed company would have gold output of 450,000 ounces in <DATE>1988</DATE> and 650,000 ounces in <DATE>1989</DATE>, at an average cash operating cost of <MONEY>$170</MONEY> an ounce. 
This would make the company the fifth-largest North American producer and one of the continent's lowest-cost gold mining concerns, according to <ORGANIZATION>Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

   Trading in the companies' shares was halted prior to the opening yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Royex closed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at <MONEY>6.125 Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$4.93</MONEY>), up <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>. 
Corona closed at <MONEY>9.75 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>37.5 cents</MONEY>; Lacana at <MONEY>13.125 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>, and Mascot at <MONEY>11.25 dollars</MONEY>, unchanged. 
<LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>'s Class A shares closed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at <MONEY>4.60 dollars</MONEY>, up <MONEY>five cents</MONEY>, and its Class B shares closed unchanged at <MONEY>4.60 dollars</MONEY>. 

   Based on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s share values, the concerns have a combined indicated market capitalization of about <MONEY>2.52 billion dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$2.03 billion</MONEY>). 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said his gold production estimates for the proposed company include output from the disputed Page-Williams mine, ownership of which is being contested by <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Canada</ORGANIZATION> is expected to end the lengthy legal battle after it hears an appeal by LAC, scheduled for <DATE>October</DATE>. 
An <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> court previously awarded the mine to Corona. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870311-0056 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex Gold to Raise
Its Stake in Affiliate,
Sell Mascot Interest</HL>
<DD> 03/11/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.RGM T.MSG T.ICR LCNAF
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it intends to raise its stake in its affiliate <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>. 

   Royex, a Toronto-based gold mining concern, said it also has agreed to sell its <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> to an affiliate for a total of <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> in cash, notes and preferred shares. 

   <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer of Royex, said it wants to increase its investment in <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> "to make it abundantly clear that we control the company." 
International Corona is being sued by a director, <PERSON>Murray Pezim</PERSON>, who is seeking to replace five of the company's 10 directors. 
Royex would have to buy about 2.4 million <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> shares to raise its stake to <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT>, and yesterday's closing price gives the additional shares an indicated value of <MONEY>$94.8 million</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> is in discussions with investment advisers to arrange financing for the <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> stock purchase. 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> hasn't decided whom it will buy the shares from. 

   Royex is selling the stake in <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mines</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in order to reduce <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s bank debt and to help finance the purchase of <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> shares. 

   Lacana Mining, which is <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> owned by <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>, has agreed to buy the <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mining</ORGANIZATION> shares for <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY> cash, a <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> promissory note and <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> in preferred shares of a Lacana subsidiary. 
Lacana and Mascot are gold mining concerns based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. 

   International Corona is a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> mining concern. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870206-0103 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex Gold to Buy
36% Stake in Lacana
For $52.3 Million</HL>
<DD> 02/06/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.RGM LCNAF T.WMI
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to purchase a <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> interest in <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> for about <MONEY>$52.3 million</MONEY> (Canadian). 

   Royex said it will purchase 4,751,009 Lacana common shares at <MONEY>$11</MONEY> a share, and that the transaction is scheduled to close <DATE>Feb. 13</DATE>. 
Royex also said it plans no follow-up offer to the remaining shareholders of <LOCATION>Lacana</LOCATION>, which is based here. 

   Most of the shares will be purchased from <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>, Alberta-based <ORGANIZATION>Westmin Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, with the balance from other shareholders, <PERSON>Royex</PERSON> said. 
<ORGANIZATION>Westmin</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to sell its block of 3.2 million shares to Royex for <MONEY>$34.7 million</MONEY>. 

   Royex said it will operate <LOCATION>Lacana</LOCATION>, which has interests in precious metals mining in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, as a separate unit. 
Royex operates gold mines in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Westmin</ORGANIZATION> is an energy and mining concern. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> trading yesterday, Lacana closed at <MONEY>$10.50</MONEY>, down <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>. 
Westmin closed unchanged at <MONEY>$9.125</MONEY>, and <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> common closed at <MONEY>$4.15</MONEY>, up <MONEY>5 cents</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880606-0064 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Corona Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.RGM GLVAB T.ICR LCNAF T.MSG GLVAF </CO>
<IN> TNM PCS </IN>
<TEXT>
   Shareholders of <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and four affiliates approved a merger to create <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s fifth-largest gold producer. 

He said <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s average cash operating cost is about <MONEY>$170</MONEY> an ounce, ranking it among the world's lowest-cost gold producers. 

   In addition to <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>, companies involved in the merger are <ORGANIZATION>Galveston Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mascot Gold Mines Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 
All but <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, British Columbia-based <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> are based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. 

   The merger was carried out through an exchange of securities of the five concerns, which have a combined indicated market capitalization of about <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Ned Goodman</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>, said its shares would begin trading <DATE>July 4</DATE> on Canadian exchanges. 
The merging companies will continue to trade under their own listings until <DATE>July 1</DATE>, he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870303-0024 </DOCNO>
<HL> 

Feisty Pezim Only Wants a Gold Mine
-- And International Corona's Top Job
--
By Leonard Zehr and Alan Bayless
<DD> 03/03/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.ICR </IN>
<TEXT>
   Canadian mining promotor <PERSON>Murray Pezim</PERSON> has begun a messy corporate fight to get his gold mine back. 

   Last week, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> said it would discontinue the positions of vice chairmen, held by the "Pez," as he is called, and <PERSON>Ned Goodman</PERSON>. 
The <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> gold-mining company said the two could remain as directors. 
In addition, two of <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s nominees to the 10-member board failed to win reelection. 

   Next <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Ontario</ORGANIZATION> will hear <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s request to have five Corona directors removed and replaced with his nominees or with court-appointees. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, who helped found the company, vowed to press his feud against management, saying the board broke an agreement under which he was to have continued to serve in an "executive position." 

   "Even if we don't win <DATE>Monday</DATE>, I'm going to call a special shareholders meeting and vote <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> of the stock for a new board," <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said. 
"My people are buying a lot of (<ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>) stock. 
I want to be chairman again." 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> became vice chairman several years ago when he gave up the post as chairman because of illness. 

   In the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> was a fledgling mining exploration company that was effectively controlled by <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>. 
Under his leadership, the company discovered <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s richest gold deposit at <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> arranged the initial financing that led to the discovery of the <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION> ore body. 

   Officials of Corona couldn't be reached for comment on the issue of dropping <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> as vice chairman, but in a previous statement, the company said it was "disturbed about statements purportedly made to the media by <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> concerning proposed transactions that have not been recommended by <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s management, nor considered by the Corona board." 

   His fight began six weeks ago when <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> asked <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s chief executive officer, for 40 Corona annual reports to give to his clients in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> refused. 
"<PERSON>Steen</PERSON> told me they don't want me representing the company," <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> recalled. 

   A <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman said that <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Theodore Rhenius</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s chief financial officer, were in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> <DATE>last September</DATE> speaking to potential investors. 
"<PERSON>Peter</PERSON> felt things might get confused having two groups speaking for the company," she added. 
<PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> couldn't be reached for comment. 

   "I've had indications for the past year that (<ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> and its largest single shareholder, <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>) have wanted to get rid of me," <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said. 
"They totally shafted us at the Corona annual meeting, when they proposed a new board. 
We didn't have the faintest idea that two of my people weren't going to be reappointed." 

   The Corona spokeswoman says <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> "started making noises" in <DATE>January</DATE> about gaining control of Corona. 
She said Royex, which owns <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT> of Corona, supported the new slate of directors "to lessen <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s influence on the board." 
Corona owns about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of Royex. 

   One of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s most colorful executives, the 66-year-old <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> currently promotes a stable of about 40 Vancouver Stock Exchange-listed mining companies. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> claims he made and lost a total of more than <MONEY>$150 million</MONEY> (Canadian) from various ventures. 

   He said he lost control of Corona in <DATE>1984</DATE> after two ill-fated ventures -- Pezzaz greeting cards, which featured audiocassette messages from Hollywood personalities, and <ORGANIZATION>Swensen's Ice Cream Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. 
"Every time I get involved in something other than gold mining, I get burned," he said. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s current chairman, bailed out Corona and <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, who owed his stockbrokers about <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> estimated his stake to have been about <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>, a portion of which he sold to <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>. 

   According to <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, the two had a verbal agreement to retain <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> as a senior officer of Corona and a member of the executive committee. 
He also said they agreed that the <PERSON>Goodman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pezim</PERSON> groups would have equal representation on the Corona board. 

   Now, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> thinks <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> is behind the moves to push him out of Corona. 
<PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> "is my sworn enemy now. 
I'm going to dig up everything I can on him. 
I'm a street fighter. 
I don't quit once I start something." 
<PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> wasn't available for comment. 

   In addition to owning a <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> interest in one of the three gold mines at <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> won a court decision last year against <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which also operates a mine at <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION>. 
The court ordered LAC to hand over its mine, valued by some specialists at more than <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>, to Corona. 
An appeals court is expected to rule soon. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, who launched the suit against LAC, said he wants to have more influence at Corona. 
He also said he disagreed with many of Corona's recent decisions, including a <MONEY>$45 million</MONEY> warrant financing last year. 

   Moreover, he says he wasn't consulted when Royex paid about <MONEY>$52 million</MONEY> earlier this year to acquire effective control of <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> mining and oil and gas concern. 
While he isn't a director of Royex, he said Royex probably plans to use proceeds to buy more Corona shares to tighten the interlocking ownership among the three companies. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871029-0076 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief:
Royex Gold Mining Corp.</HL>
<DD> 10/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.RGM GLVSF T.ICR
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to buy about 1.1 million warrants in a Royex affiliate from <ORGANIZATION>Galveston Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> for 10 million new Royex common shares and <MONEY>3 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$2.3 million</MONEY>). 

   In trading yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, Royex closed at <MONEY>5.50 dollars</MONEY>, unchanged. 

   Royex said each warrant entitles it to acquire for <MONEY>7 dollars</MONEY> one common share of <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, in which <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> is currently a holder. 
On the <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> exchange, Corona closed yesterday at <MONEY>47.25 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>1.25 dollars</MONEY>. 

   Royex said the purchase would raise its stake in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION> to <PERCENT>42.4%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT>, on a fully diluted basis. 
Royex and <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>, both based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, are gold mining concerns. 

   Royex said the proposed transaction is subject to approval by shareholders of <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, a <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, British Columbia-based gold exploration concern. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880325-0047 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Rayrock Yellowknife Resources Inc. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.RAY SFX LCNAF PDG </CO>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Rayrock Yellowknife Resources Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to build a gold mine at its <PERCENT>23.3%</PERCENT>-owned Marigold property in <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> at a cost of at least <MONEY>30 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$24.1 million</MONEY>). 

   The <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> gold mining and energy concern said it expects the mine to begin production in early <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
It forecasts annual output of 55,000 to 60,000 ounces, and it said reserves are adequate to support production for 10 years. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Rayrock</ORGANIZATION>'s partners include <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific Mining Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which holds a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> interest, <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, with <PERCENT>23.3%</PERCENT>, and a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, with <PERCENT>23.3%</PERCENT>. 
Lacana and <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION> are <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> goldmining concerns. 
<ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Pacific</ORGANIZATION> is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Santa Fe Southern Pacific Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, a railroad and energy concern. 

   In trading yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Rayrock</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>9.625 dollars</MONEY>, unchanged. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870310-0092 </DOCNO>
<HL> Galveston Resources
Plans to Make Offer
Of Bonds and Stock</HL>
<DD> 03/10/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.GAL T.ICR T.RGM
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON) </IN>
<DATELINE> VANCOUVER  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Galveston Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold exploration concern, plans a <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> (Canadian) bond offering and a <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> equity offering, <PERSON>Murray Pezim</PERSON>, chairman, said. 

   Proceeds will be used for general purposes, "possibly including the purchase of securities of certain gold mining companies," <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said. 

   He declined to say if he would use the funds to purchase stock of <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a Toronto-based gold mining concern. 
As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> is seeking to replace <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s board. 

   Interest on the bonds will be paid semi-annually in shares of Corona from <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>'s holdings of the stock, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said. 
Based on a price of <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a Corona share, the interest payment would be <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, he said. 
On the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, Corona closed yesterday at <MONEY>$41</MONEY>, down <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said the payout of Corona shares wouldn't hurt his corporate fight because he expects the battle to be completed within six months. 
He declined to disclose the number of Corona shares held by <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, but said it was sufficient to cover the interest payments. 

   The <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> bonds will have a three-year maturity and will be convertible into <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> common shares at <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a share, the company said. 
The offer is subject to regulatory approval. 
Agents are <ORGANIZATION>Midland Doherty Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Maison Placements Canada Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The equity issue involves one million shares and one million warrants, to be offered in units of one share and one warrant at <MONEY>$20</MONEY> each, <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION> said. 
Each warrant allows the holder to purchase an additional share for <MONEY>$22</MONEY> within two years. 

The shares closed yesterday at <MONEY>$25</MONEY> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, down <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>. 
Corona, which has about 21.5 million shares outstanding, is <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT>-owned by <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900619-0111
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900619-0111.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Goodman Is Still Mining for Golden Deals
   ----
   Larry M. Greenberg
</HL>
<DATE>
06/19/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B11
</SO>
<CO>
   T.SKZ PDG ICRA PLDS
</CO>
<IN>
BIOGRAPHY (BIO)
DIVIDENDS (DIV)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<LP>
   TORONTO -- "We've never had any cash," says Corona Corp.'s
Ned Goodman. "When you get into a situation where your
opposition is dealing with cash, you've got to become more
creative."
   Creative financing is the Corona chairman's hallmark.
Mainly by issuing new securities and trading them for assets,
he has built Toronto-based Corona into one of North America's
10 biggest gold mining companies. Through a special class of
shares, he and a few friends have solid control with only
7.6% of the equity. His penchant for complex deals and
ultimate control has given rise to what analysts call the
"Ned Factor," a sort of bewilderment discount that they say
sometimes affects the share prices of his companies.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Despite this, Corona shareholders have done better over
the years than those of most other Canadian gold companies.
   Now <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>, 52 years old, has proposed a typically
complex series of transactions, entirely paid for with paper,
that could win Corona control of two companies that own
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s hottest new gold property. The <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> property
in <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION> has estimated reserves of 4.8 million
ounces, worth about <MONEY>US$1.66 billion</MONEY> at current prices.
   But Corona, and <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>'s paper-shuffling style, are
challenged by a <MONEY>230 million Canadian dollar</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$196 million</MONEY>),
all-cash offer by <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for one of the target
companies, <ORGANIZATION>Stikine Resources Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. Most analysts agree that
<PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>'s paper probably has more long-term value than
<ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION>'s cash, and <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> also has locked up a huge
block of shares in <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION>. But recent declines in the price
of gold, along with the Ned Factor, have pushed down the
price of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s shares and, therefore, the value of its
planned offer. The contest won't be over until <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>British Columbia-based Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION>'s bid expires today.
   <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>'s style has deep roots. Born in <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>, he
was trained as a geologist and later moved into investment
counseling. He became involved with a sleepy copper producer
called <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Chibougamau Mines Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. After a <DATE>1979</DATE> proxy
fight, <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> took over as chairman and went on a
shopping binge in the resource sector.
   By <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> had run up lots of debt, and <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>
was outnumbered when the board decided to sell the company's
interest in <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp</ORGANIZATION>. He quit the <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION>
board and bought the Royex stake in a transaction that even
<PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> says was complex.
   "I said that I'd never put myself in a position again of
working for a company where someone else is going to make the
decisions," <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> says.
   Royex's main asset was its holding in <ORGANIZATION>International Corona
Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which in turn held a controlling stake in
Royex. Over the next three years, Royex acquired major
interests in other resource outfits, financing the deals in
part by transferring investments between units.
   "We were getting an awful lot of criticism because we had
a complicated company. I didn't like it either. (But) we had
no choice," <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> says. To simplify matters, he merged
Royex with four related companies to form Corona in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   In his latest proposal, <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> plans to spin off
Corona's gold assets into a separately listed company. Some
shares of the new company, to be called <ORGANIZATION>Corona Gold Corp.</ORGANIZATION>,
will be distributed to current Corona holders. He also has
offered a combination of Corona and <ORGANIZATION>Corona Gold</ORGANIZATION> shares to the
owners of <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources Group
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which would then be merged with <ORGANIZATION>Corona Gold</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> says the Corona restructuring, which would
leave the parent holding a mixed basket of resource
interests, is meant to still the "moans and groans" of
holders who disapproved of the company's branching out from
precious metals.
   But the restructuring plan hasn't satisfied all of <PERSON>Mr.
Goodman</PERSON>'s critics, who complain that he freely spends
<ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s Class A shares, which carry one vote apiece, while
leaving intact the number of Class B shares, which have 100
votes apiece and are largely held by <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> and four
other directors.
   A study of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s past share price performance indicates
that backing <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> has been wise. <PERSON>Barry Allan</PERSON>, an
analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Prudential-Bache Securities Canada Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>,
calculates that an investor buying a Royex share in <DATE>January
1987</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> became <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman, would have
seen a <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT> appreciation in his money. This compares with a
<PERCENT>9.9%</PERCENT> drop in the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> gold index over the
same period and a decline of <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> in the price of gold
bullion.
   Nevertheless, "there are a lot of people who don't want to
have anything to do with the guy (<PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>). I sometimes
wonder whether people are afraid of him because he's two
steps ahead of them," says <PERSON>John Embry</PERSON>, a vice president of
Toronto-based <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank Investment Management</ORGANIZATION>, which holds
about <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> of the Corona Class A shares.
   Although he backs <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>'s proposals to acquire <LOCATION>Eskay
Creek</LOCATION> and restructure Corona, <PERSON>Mr. Embry</PERSON> says he remains
concerned <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> will continue to control the new gold unit
with a <PERCENT>50.2%</PERCENT> holding.
   <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> plans to remain at the helm of the Corona
parent, which will concentrate on building up its interests
in base metals, oil and gas, industrial minerals and
financial services. Meantime, <ORGANIZATION>Corona Gold</ORGANIZATION>, if it succeeds in
its plan to merge with the current owners of <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION>,
will focus on developing that ore body. <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> estimates
the addition of <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> would boost <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s production
to about 1.2 million ounces of gold in <DATE>1994</DATE> from 700,000
ounces expected this year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871005-0060 </DOCNO>
<HL> 
 </HL>
<DD> 10/05/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LAC T.ICR T.RGM TEK.A CANDA
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A gold mine developed by <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> that is expected to become <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s biggest producer belongs to <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, an <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Court of Appeal</ORGANIZATION> ruled. 

   In a long-awaited decision, a panel of four judges unanimously upheld a <DATE>1986</DATE> ruling by the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Ontario</ORGANIZATION> and dismissed LAC's appeal to overturn it. 
LAC declined to say whether it would seek a further appeal. 

We feel that justice has been done." 
As a result of the added production from the disputed mine, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> expects to more than double its gold output this year and <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which holds a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> interest in <LOCATION>International Corona</LOCATION>, expects its gold output to increase about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said he will soon meet with Vancouver-based <ORGANIZATION>Teck Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to discuss their plans to jointly operate the mine and one next to it at <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION> gold district. 
Together, the two mines are expected to produce about 700,000 ounces of gold annually by <DATE>1990</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>David Thompson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION>'s vice president, finance, said <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> is "very pleased." 
<ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> acquired half of Page-Williams in <DATE>1986</DATE> and its share of the mine output is expected to double <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION>'s gold production this year. 

   LAC must hand over the mine once <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> pays it <MONEY>154 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$117.8 million</MONEY>) to help cover the mine's development costs, unless LAC can obtain a court order deferring the transfer. 
An <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> lawyer said he expected <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> to pay LAC the funds this week. 

   In return, LAC must pay <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> an amount equal to the mine's earnings since it opened in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>. 
The mine, which was expected to provide about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of LAC's gold production in <DATE>1987</DATE>, earned about <MONEY>24.3 million dollars</MONEY> <DATE>during the 18 months ended June 30</DATE>. 

   In their 126-page ruling, delayed because of the death in <DATE>June</DATE> of one of their members, the appeal court judges said they found "ample evidence" to support the conclusions of <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Supreme Court Justice</ORGANIZATION> <PERSON>R.E. Holland</PERSON>, who heard the original court trial. 

   The appeal court upheld the conclusions of <ORGANIZATION>Justice Holland</ORGANIZATION>. 
It cited LAC for breaching a trust with <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> when the two talked about a joint venture in <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
The panel agreed LAC used confidential information given to it by <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION>, then a tiny exploration company, to acquire the property where the PageWilliams mine now operates. 

   Analysts say they expect the ruling to have a positive effect on <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> share prices. 

   <PERSON>Paul Esquivel</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Davidson Partners Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, said he believes <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s shares are valued at about <MONEY>60 dollars</MONEY> if one includes the Page-Williams mine. 

   In trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>47.50 dollars</MONEY>, up <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>. 
Royex shares closed at <MONEY>5.50 dollars</MONEY>, up <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>; <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>33.75 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>. 

   <PERSON>Amy Gassman</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said she expects a "moderately negative" short-term impact on <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION>'s share price. 
In trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, LAC closed at <MONEY>18 dollars</MONEY>, up <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870401-0028 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex Makes Offer
To Raise Stake
In Mining Affiliate</HL>
<DD> 04/01/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.RGM T.ICR
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it is offering a package of securities and cash with an indicated value of about <MONEY>$234.4 million</MONEY> (Canadian) under its previously reported plan to raise its stake in <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold mining affiliate based here. 

   Under the offer, mailed yesterday to shareholders of <LOCATION>International Corona</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Royex</PERSON> said it is offering to purchase four million <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> common shares for <MONEY>$4</MONEY> each in cash and <MONEY>$47.50</MONEY> of new Royex preference shares and warrants. 
Royex currently holds about 8.2 million, or <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s 21.6 million issued common shares. 

   Royex said it is also offering one Royex preference share and one Royex warrant, with a combined indicated value of <MONEY>$42.50</MONEY>, for each of 711,053 International Corona warrants that expire <DATE>Aug. 31</DATE>. 

   Royex said the offer, if successful, would effectively raise its interest in <LOCATION>International Corona</LOCATION> to <PERCENT>58%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT> on an undiluted basis, or to <PERCENT>44%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>24%</PERCENT> on a fully diluted basis. 
Royex said its voting interest in <LOCATION>International Corona</LOCATION> would be raised to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>. 

   Under the offer, which is scheduled to expire <DATE>April 22</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said its two new series of Royex preference shares will initially be convertible into 3.33 Royex common shares, subject to a one-time adjustment to reflect the outcome of litigation between <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lac Minerals Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 
The adjustment will be made after the litigation is resolved, or not later than <DATE>April 30, 1990</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   The litigation relates to a dispute between <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> and Lac over a large northern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> gold mine. 

   Royex said its offer for <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> common shares isn't conditional on any minimum acceptance level, but if fewer than 2.7 million <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> common are deposited, <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s share and warrant holders will be entitled to withdraw from the offer within two days after its expiration. 
If more than four million <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> shares are tendered, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said it will pay for the shares on a pro-rata basis. 

   Trading in <ORGANIZATION>International Corona</ORGANIZATION> and Royex shares was halted yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 
In trading <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>$43.125</MONEY>, up <MONEY>62.5 cents</MONEY>, and Royex common closed at <MONEY>$6.125</MONEY>, down <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870414-0110 </DOCNO>
<HL> Corona Waits to Judge
Bid From Royex Gold</HL>
<DD> 04/14/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.ICR T.RGM
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> said its board decided to make no recommendation to holders concerning <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s offer for <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> shares and warrants because a pending court ruling could affect <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s share price. 

   Corona said its financial adviser, <PERSON>Dean Witter Reynolds</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Canada) Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, determined that the Royex offer had a market value of <MONEY>$52.625</MONEY> per <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> share, and <MONEY>$40.875</MONEY> per Corona warrant, based on market prices before the <DATE>March 31</DATE> offer was made. 
But it said <PERSON>Dean Witter</PERSON> also determined that a ruling in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>'s dispute with <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> over ownership of a gold mine could drive the price of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s common to as low as <MONEY>$25</MONEY> or as high as <MONEY>$92</MONEY>. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> trading yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>, a mining and exploration company, closed at <MONEY>$54.50</MONEY>, up <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY>; Royex closed at <MONEY>$7.75</MONEY>, up <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY>. 

   Royex -- which is <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s largest shareholder, controlling about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> -- made the offer to strengthen its hand against <PERSON>Murray Pezim</PERSON>, a dissident <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> director who has filed suit seeking to replace five of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s 10 directors. 

   In a dissenting opinion, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> rejected the Royex offer. 

   Both Royex and <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> are based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871218-0009 </DOCNO>
<HL> LAC Cleared to Appeal
Ruling to Give Mine
To Corona Resources</HL>
<DD> 12/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LAC T.ICR T.RGM TEK.A CANDA
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Canada</ORGANIZATION> agreed to let <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> appeal a decision that would have forced it to hand over a big <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> gold mine to <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The court didn't offer its reasons for the decision. 
A <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said the appeal might not be heard until <DATE>1989</DATE>. 

It followed a decision in <DATE>October</DATE> by an <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Court of Appeal</ORGANIZATION> to award the Page-Williams mine, in <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION> district, to <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, upholding a <DATE>1986</DATE> court ruling. 
The appeals court agreed that LAC used confidential information given to it by Corona to acquire the property where the Page-Williams mine now operates. 

   Corona said it plans a cross-appeal to the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Canada</ORGANIZATION> regarding the company's claim that it shouldn't have to pay <MONEY>LAC 154 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$117.8 million</MONEY>) to help compensate it for developing the Page-Williams property. 

   The outcome of the legal battle will significantly affect both Toronto-based companies and their affiliates. 
Page-Williams is expected to become <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s biggest gold mine. 
It would have accounted for more than half of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s gold output and about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of LAC's gold output this year. 

   In trading yesterday on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>14 Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$10.71</MONEY>), up <MONEY>87.5 cents</MONEY>, and <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>49.875 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>12.5 dollars</MONEY>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which holds a <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> stake in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, closed at <MONEY>6.50 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>1.375 dollars</MONEY>. 

   Vancouver-based <ORGANIZATION>Teck Corp.</ORGANIZATION> had agreed with Corona to jointly operate the Page-Williams mine and one next to it. 
<ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION>'s Class B shares closed at <MONEY>35.25 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>5.75 dollars</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880707-0016 </DOCNO>
<HL> Corona Agrees to Sell Oil, Gas Assets to Unit Of Poco Petroleum </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> IRAFV T.POC I/PET I/LNG </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to sell its oil and gas assets to a unit of <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>, Alberta-based <ORGANIZATION>Poco Petroleums Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> for Poco stock with an indicated market value of <MONEY>72.6 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$59.9 million</MONEY>). 

   The planned sale to <ORGANIZATION>Poco</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERCENT>89%</PERCENT>-owned <ORGANIZATION>Central Explorers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit would result in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION> becoming Poco's largest holder, with a <PERCENT>25.4%</PERCENT> fully diluted stake. 

   Poco is a fast-growing oil and gas producer. 
Toronto-based Corona, formed last week through the merger of five affiliated mining concerns, is among <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s top five gold producers. 

   Under the proposed transaction's terms, the companies said <ORGANIZATION>Central</ORGANIZATION> will acquire <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Lacana Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> unit's oil and gas assets, which are mainly in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. 
They include about 6.4 million barrels of oil reserves, 56.8 billion cubic feet of natural gas reserves, 78,000 acres of undeveloped land and related working capital of more than <MONEY>C$20 million</MONEY>. 

   Central will incur a debt to Poco for the assets and <ORGANIZATION>Poco</ORGANIZATION> will issue to Corona five million new common shares and two million new preferred shares that would be convertible to an equal number of <ORGANIZATION>Poco</ORGANIZATION> common shares. 

   In <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading yesterday, Poco's common shares closed at <MONEY>$10.375</MONEY>, up <MONEY>37.5 cents</MONEY>. 

   Corona, which will have three nominees on <ORGANIZATION>Poco</ORGANIZATION>'s board, said it currently doesn't plan to raise its stake in <LOCATION>Poco</LOCATION>. 
A Corona official said the Poco investment would assign a market value to <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s oil and gas assets, which the company believed weren't recognized previously by investors. 

   The transaction is expected to close this <DATE>summer</DATE>, subject to regulatory approvals. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880602-0092 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief: Royex Gold Mining Corp. </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.RGM </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> management group intends to strengthen its long-term control of <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a proposed new gold mining company, by restricting the sale of members' multiple-voting shares in the new concern. 

   <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer of Toronto-based Royex, said management group members would be required under a planned agreement to offer to one another any Corona Class B multiple-voting shares they intend to sell. 
If the shares aren't sold, they would be converted to Royex Class A shares and sold on the open market, he said. 

   Shareholders of Royex and four other mining companies are scheduled to vote tomorrow on a proposed merger that would result in the creation of Corona. 
If approved, the company would rank among <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s biggest gold producers. 

   Under the planned merger's terms, <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s management group would emerge with a <PERCENT>55.6%</PERCENT> voting stake and <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> equity interest in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>. 
Royex said Corona would have outstanding about 116.3 million Class A shares, with one vote each, and 8.7 million Class B shares, with 100 votes each. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880415-0068 </DOCNO>
<HL> Royex Slates Output At Saskatchewan Site Before End of Year </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.RGM </CO>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Royex Gold Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said it plans to begin gold production at its <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>-owned Jolu property in <LOCATION>Saskatchewan</LOCATION> before year end. 

   Royex projected annual gold output at Jolu of about 50,000 ounces, beginning in <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
The property is <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT>-owned by <ORGANIZATION>Vancouver-based Mahogany Minerals Resources Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold exploration concern. 

   Royex said it expects to spend about <MONEY>20 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$16.2 million</MONEY>) to complete construction of a mine and mill at the site. 
Financing will be arranged through a gold loan, the company said. 

   Royex said the mine would be operated by <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, pending the result of <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION>'s merger with four other Canadian gold mining concerns. 
Corona is the name of the company that would result from the planned merger, which <ORGANIZATION>Royex</ORGANIZATION> said it expects to complete early in <DATE>July</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870424-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief:
Royex Gold Mining Corp.</HL>
<DD> 04/24/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> T.RGM T.ICR
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM) </IN>
<TEXT>
   ROYEX <ORGANIZATION>GOLD MINING CORP.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, lifted its interest in <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>38%</PERCENT> under an offer. 
Royex also settled its differences with a dissident Corona holder, <PERSON>Murray Pezim</PERSON>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> agreed to drop a legal action that sought to replace five of <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s 10 directors, and he agreed to place the Corona shares he owns or controls in a voting trust that Royex controls. 
Royex received right of first refusal to buy <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s Corona shares or securities convertible into <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> shares. 
<PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, who remains a Corona director, confirmed the details of the agreement. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880629-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> Corona Corp. Chief Hints at Flexibility In Settling LAC Suit </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> LAC T.ICR T.FN CANDA </CO>
<IN> CEO TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said the company remains "receptive to examining an out-of-court settlement" with <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> regarding the disputed <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION> mine at <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>. 

   Still, the sides haven't discussed the issue since a meeting earlier this year, he said. 

   "That's the only meeting that I have had, and that's the only meeting that <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> has had" with LAC, <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said in an interview. 
Asked if Corona is willing to reopen talks, he said: "I think we're waiting for {LAC's president and chief executive, <PERSON>Peter Allen</PERSON>} to make his move." 

   A <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said "nothing substantial was discussed" at the <DATE>spring</DATE> meeting, and that LAC doesn't plan to resume talks. 

   <ORGANIZATION>International Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, one of five affiliated companies that agreed earlier this month to merge to form <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, was awarded ownership of the <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION> mine in <DATE>1986</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Ontario</ORGANIZATION>. 
The decision was upheld on appeal and the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Canada</ORGANIZATION> will hear a final appeal <DATE>Oct. 11</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said Corona, whose merger takes effect <DATE>Friday</DATE>, doesn't believe its case will be affected by other litigation in progress involving the <ORGANIZATION>Hemlo</ORGANIZATION> claims. 

   Neither <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> nor Corona Vice President and Treasurer <PERSON>Tony Walsh</PERSON> would offer specific earnings or revenue projections. 
Nevertheless, <PERSON>Mr. Walsh</PERSON> described as "reasonable" an analyst's forecast that <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> will earn about <MONEY>77 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$63.8 million</MONEY>), or <MONEY>53 cents</MONEY> a share, on revenue of <MONEY>C$264 million</MONEY> for the fiscal year ending <DATE>Sept. 30</DATE>, and <MONEY>C$111 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY> a share, on revenue of <MONEY>C$376 million</MONEY> for fiscal <DATE>1989</DATE>. 

   The forecast is based on gold output of 466,000 ounces this year and 630,000 ounces for fiscal <DATE>1989</DATE> and an average gold price of <MONEY>$450</MONEY> an ounce. 
Corona previously forecast output of 465,000 ounces for <DATE>1988</DATE> and 650,000 ounces for <DATE>1989</DATE> at an average cash production cost of <MONEY>$170</MONEY> an ounce. 

   <PERSON>Igor Levental</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s newly appointed director, acquisitions and evaluations, said <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> "could take on a <MONEY>C$400</MONEY>-<MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> company" with its current financial resources. 
<PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said the company is considering an offer for Toronto-based <ORGANIZATION>Franco-Nevada Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, in which <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> holds a <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> stake. 
"It's on the market, and we are taking a look at it," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890814-0110 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890814 </DD>
<AN> 890814-0110. </AN>
<HL> Corona Corp. Wins
@  Ontario Gold Mine
@  Developed by LAC
@  ----
@  By Larry M. Greenberg
<DD> 08/14/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> ICRA LAC CANDA TEK.A </CO>
<IN> PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<DATELINE> OTTAWA  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court of Canada</ORGANIZATION> awarded the country's richest gold mine to <ORGANIZATION>Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, ending an acrimonious eight-year legal battle between <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> and the mine's developer, <ORGANIZATION>LAC Minerals Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The court ruled that Toronto-based LAC must hand over the Page-Williams mine in northern <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION> and that Corona must pay <MONEY>LAC 154 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$131.6 million</MONEY>) for past development costs. 
With interest, the payment would amount to more than <MONEY>C$210 million</MONEY>. 

   Corona, also based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, said the payment is to come equally from it and from <ORGANIZATION>Teck Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>, which plans to operate the mine in an equal partnership with Corona. 
The two companies also will split about <MONEY>C$80 million</MONEY> in profit from the mine that has been held in a trust account since <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   The ruling upholds the findings of the <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1986</DATE> and the <ORGANIZATION>Ontario Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>a year later</DATE>, saying that <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION> had "breached a duty of confidence" with <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s predecessor company when it talked with <ORGANIZATION>LAC</ORGANIZATION> about a possible joint venture in <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
The high court said LAC used confidential information given to it by <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s predecessor to acquire the property where the Page-Williams mine operates. 

   The Page-Williams mine, which last year produced 379,000 ounces of gold, should produce 490,000 ounces this year, said <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s president and chief executive officer. 
He said <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s half-share of the output would boost the company's production this year by <PERCENT>64%</PERCENT> to an expected 625,000 ounces, advancing the company's transformation from a small exploration outfit in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE> to one of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s top gold producers. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON> said the companies plan to accelerate the exploration of little-known areas of the mine. 
The reserves already discovered contain nearly seven million ounces of gold, he said. 
<ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> said its operations, without Page-Williams, are expected to produce about 150,000 ounces of gold this year. 

   LAC's chief financial officer, <PERSON>Rolly Francisco</PERSON>, said he was disappointed with the court's ruling but said LAC will abide by the decision and work closely with <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> to ensure an orderly handover of the mine. 
LAC hasn't included earnings from the Page-Williams mine in its own accounts since <DATE>1986</DATE>. 

   LAC's defeat in court could leave the company vulnerable to a takeover attempt, analysts said. 

   With the company currently holding cash of about <MONEY>C$250 million</MONEY> plus the payment due for the Page-Williams mine, "I think it becomes a real attractive takeover candidate if the share price dropped. 
You would be able to finance much of the takeover cost with the company's own cash," said <PERSON>Julian Baldry</PERSON>, a senior mining analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Nesbitt Thomson Deacon Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Before the court decision was announced, LAC shares closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <ORGANIZATION>New York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading at <MONEY>$11.375</MONEY> each, down <MONEY>12.5 cents</MONEY>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Baldry</PERSON> estimated the company could become vulnerable to takeover if its stock falls below <MONEY>C$10</MONEY> (<MONEY>$8.54</MONEY>) a share. 

<ORGANIZATION>Teck</ORGANIZATION> Class B shares closed at <MONEY>C$22.625</MONEY>, down <MONEY>C$1.375</MONEY>, on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870803-0154 </DOCNO>
<HL> Yellowknife
Bids for 19.99%
Of Dome Mines
---
Purchase, for $313.1 Million,
Could Dash Plan to Build
A Big Gold Mining Firm
---
By Gary Lamphier
<DD> 08/03/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> DM GYK FALCF CRK PLC
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
MINING, METALS (NON-PRECIOUS) (MIN)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS) </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> said it offered to buy <PERCENT>19.99%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>417.1 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$313.1 million</MONEY>). 

   The transaction could thwart <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>' plan to form <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s biggest gold mining company through a merger with two other concerns. 

   Giant <PERSON>Yellowknife</PERSON> said it offered <MONEY>21.50 dollars</MONEY> a share to <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> for about 19.4 million of the 20.9 million <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> shares that the oil and gas company owns. 
If the sale goes through, <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION> said it would vote the shares against a proposal to combine <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> with <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Red Lake Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Placer Development Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Shareholders of the three companies are to vote on the merger proposal <DATE>Aug. 12</DATE>. 
In trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> closed at <MONEY>21 dollars</MONEY>, up one dollar. 

   <PERSON>David Emery</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION>, declined to say why his company would oppose the merger. 
But a <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION> insider said the company prefers a major stake in <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> to a smaller one in the combined company, since the two concerns could benefit from "synergies" in their gold mining operations. 
The companies operate several gold mines and mills near <LOCATION>Timmins</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>. 

   The insider said <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION> is also interested in <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>' <PERCENT>21.4%</PERCENT> stake in Toronto-based <ORGANIZATION>Falconbridge Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which has zinc, copper and gold mines in the area. 
Giant <LOCATION>Yellowknife</LOCATION> is a gold producer, but it is indirectly controlled by <ORGANIZATION>Ariadne Australia Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, which has interests in other metals. 

   Giant <PERSON>Yellowknife</PERSON> said it would offer to buy <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION>'s remaining 1.5 million shares in <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> if certain regulatory approvals can be obtained or waived. 
Under Ontario securities regulations, such approval is usually required if a buyer wishes to purchase <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> or more of a company without extending the offer to all shareholders. 
<ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION>'s shares represent about <PERCENT>21.5%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <LOCATION>Calgary</LOCATION>, Alberta-based <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> said it expects to respond to the offer by <DATE>Friday</DATE>, which is when it expires. 
The sale would need approval from creditors whose loans to <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> are secured by its <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> shares. 
The creditors would receive about <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of the proceeds if the offer were accepted, <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>, Toronto-based <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> and Vancouver-based <LOCATION>Placer</LOCATION> said they still intend to proceed with the proposed merger. 

   Analysts were generally negative toward <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION>'s offer. 
<PERSON>John Lydall</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>First Marathon Securities Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, said the price offered to <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> for its <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> shares is no higher than the price <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> would receive in the form of stock from the merger of the three companies. 

   Giant <PERSON>Yellowknife</PERSON> said it plans no follow-up offer to <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>' remaining holders. 
It said that if its offer is accepted by <ORGANIZATION>Dome Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> and the gold company merger is approved, it will consider exercising certain rights under Canadian law that could force Dome Mines to buy back <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION>'s holdings in the company. 
The merger plan requires approval by two-thirds of <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>' holders. 

   Giant <PERSON>Yellowknife</PERSON> said it would finance purchase of the <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION> stake by borrowing from <ORGANIZATION>Giant Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <LOCATION>Ariadne Australia</LOCATION>. 
It said it planned to retire the debt through a rights issue to its shareholders. 
It also said it has arranged, subject to regulatory approval, for a private placement of 1.4 million <ORGANIZATION>Giant Yellowknife</ORGANIZATION> shares with <ORGANIZATION>Giant Resources</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>28.25 dollars</MONEY> each. 

   Giant Yellowknife currently has 6.9 million shares outstanding. 
Its shares closed at <MONEY>27.25 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>75 cents</MONEY>, in trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Giant <LOCATION>Yellowknife</LOCATION>, which expects to produce about 200,000 ounces of gold from five mines this year, was indirectly acquired by Ariadne earlier this year. 
Ariadne, through <ORGANIZATION>Giant Resources</ORGANIZATION>, since has acquired a zinc and lead mine in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s Yukon. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Dome Mines</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Placer</LOCATION> had <DATE>1986</DATE> combined gold production of 825,000 ounces, more than any single producer outside <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. 
Analysts estimate output of the amalgamated company would rise to 1.1 million ounces by <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
Placer also has copper, silver and oil and gas interests. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900705-0001
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900705-0001.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Corona to Pursue
   Talks With Placer
   On Gold Prospect
   ----
   By Larry M. Greenberg
</HL>
<DATE>
07/05/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   ICRA PDG T.SKZ PLDS
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
</IN>
<LP>
   TORONTO -- Corona Corp. radically altered its plans to
secure control of Canada's hottest gold prospect and said it
would pursue talks with rival Placer Dome Inc. Analysts and
some Corona officials expect the talks will result in joint
ownership of the rich ore deposit.
   Corona said it was pressured to change its plans after
Murray Pezim, a Corona director and honorary chairman,
refused to deliver to Corona his shares in Prime Resources
Group Inc. under a previous agreement. Mr. Pezim also is
chairman of Prime Resources, which owns, together with
Stikine Resources Ltd., the Eskay Creek gold property in
northwestern British Columbia.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> has estimated reserves of about 4.8 million
ounces of gold, worth about <MONEY>$1.73 billion</MONEY> at current market
prices.
   Under its revised proposal, Toronto-based <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> said it
dropped plans to spin off its gold assets into a separately
listed subsidiary and to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION> by swapping
shares in the subsidiary.
   Corona also said it improved the terms of an offer to
<ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION>'s major shareholders, who had committed to Corona
their <PERCENT>42%</PERCENT> stake. For each <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> share, holders will receive
one new Corona preferred share that will be redeemable at a
later date into either 8.5 Corona Class A subordinate voting
shares or <MONEY>70 Canadian dollars</MONEY> (US$60.14) in cash. Corona said
it plans to offer, subject to regulatory approval, the same
terms to other <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> holders to increase its stake to <PERCENT>55%</PERCENT>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>, gold mining
concern, has offered C$67.50 a share for <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION>, valuing the
company at about <MONEY>C$225 million</MONEY>. The bid by <LOCATION>Placer</LOCATION>, which
already owns <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION>'s shares, expired yesterday, but
the company said it wouldn't have final bid results until
today.
   Corona said it agreed to acquire a <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Prime
Resources</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION> financier <PERSON>Jim Pattison</PERSON>. The purchase
price is one Corona Class A share and an amount in cash to
bring the value of the transaction to <MONEY>C$9</MONEY> a share. Corona
said it also obtained voting rights over the rest of <PERSON>Mr.
Pattison</PERSON>'s holdings in <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION>, bringing <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s
voting control in Prime to <PERCENT>34%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> currently.
   As previously reported, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, the Corona director,
refused to turn over his shares to <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s offer unless the
terms were improved. <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s latest offer "is
what we wanted in the first place."
   But Corona spokesman <PERSON>Brian Hay</PERSON> said the company hadn't
made any new offers for <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s holdings. He said <PERSON>Corona</PERSON>
decided not to take <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> to court over the previous
agreement to deliver his <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION> shares because of
the cost of such a procedure.
   On the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, Corona Class A shares
closed unchanged yesterday at <MONEY>C$7.625</MONEY> after rising <MONEY>25
Canadian cents</MONEY> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> following the <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> announcement.
<ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> shares closed yesterday at C$70, down C$2, after
closing unchanged a day earlier. <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION> shares rose <MONEY>50
Canadian cents</MONEY> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <MONEY>12.5 Canadian cents</MONEY> yesterday to
finish at <MONEY>C$18.50</MONEY>. On the <ORGANIZATION>Vancouver Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Prime
Resources</ORGANIZATION> shares closed yesterday at <MONEY>C$8.50</MONEY>, up <MONEY>37.5 Canadian
cents</MONEY>, after losing <MONEY>87.5 Canadian cents</MONEY> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Hay</PERSON> said he expects talks between Corona and <ORGANIZATION>Placer
Dome</ORGANIZATION> to result in a merger of <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION>
into an operating company to develop the <LOCATION>Eskay</LOCATION> creek ore
deposit. Production at <ORGANIZATION>Eskay Creek</ORGANIZATION> isn't expected to begin
before <DATE>1993</DATE>.
   "I see a joint venture between <LOCATION>Placer</LOCATION> and Corona on this
thing," <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Hugh Leggatt</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION> spokesman, said, "We'd like to
reach an agreement with them {<PERSON>Corona</PERSON>} on the disposition of
the <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> assets. In principle we're quite prepared to
speak with them."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870219-0145 </DOCNO>
<HL> Who's News:
Royex Gold Mining Corp.</HL>
<DD> 02/19/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> WNEWS T.RGM </IN>
<DATELINE> ROYEX GOLD MINING CORP. (Toronto)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    <PERSON>Ned Goodman</PERSON>, 49 years
old, a director of this gold mining concern, was named
chairman. <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> succeeds <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, 56, who remains
Corona Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a gold mining concern that owns <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> of
Royex.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910730-0004
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910730-0004.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   International Corona to Split Company,
   Loosen Financier's Hold on Gold Assets
   ----
   By Larry M. Greenberg
</HL>
<DATE>
07/30/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C11
</SO>
<CO>
   ICR.A ICRA PDG T.D T.PDG T.POC
</CO>
<MS>
BASIC MATERIALS (BSC)
ENERGY (ENE)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVIDENDS (DIV)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
OIL-SECONDARY (OIS)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
PETROLEUM (PET)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
DIVIDENDS (DIV)
PETROLEUM MARKET (PET)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
CANADA (CN)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
</RE>
<LP>
   VANCOUVER, British Columbia -- International Corona Corp.
announced a plan that would split Corona into two companies
and loosen mining financier Ned Goodman's control over its
gold assets.
   Under terms of the plan, Corona would keep the gold
assets, but its two classes of stock would be replaced with a
single class of shares with equal voting rights. Holders also
would get shares in Dundee Bancorp Inc., a Corona subsidiary
based in Toronto. Corona would spin off Dundee, and transfer
to the subsidiary its interests in oil and gas, industrial
minerals and merchant banking.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Corona put a value of <MONEY>281.4 million Canadian dollars</MONEY>
(<MONEY>US$244.8 million</MONEY>) on its non-gold assets.
   Analysts said the restructuring likely would bolster the
market valuation of Corona's gold assets, making it easier
for the company to raise equity financing to develop its next
big gold project, the <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> deposit in northern <LOCATION>British
Columbia</LOCATION>. They said the improved investor opinion would
reflect in part the company's plans to abandon its
much-criticized multiple-share structure, which gives <PERSON>Mr.
Goodman</PERSON> and a few associates control of <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of the votes in
<LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION> with less than <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> of the equity.
   Shares in <ORGANIZATION>Dundee Bancorp</ORGANIZATION>, however, likely would suffer, as
the subsidiary would maintain a two-tiered share structure
that keeps <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> and others firmly in control of voting
rights, analysts said. <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON> would serve as chairman
and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Dundee Bancorp</ORGANIZATION>, whose assets
would include a one-third stake in <ORGANIZATION>Poco Petroleums Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, a
Canadian oil and gas concern. Dundee also would be the
biggest shareholder in <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, with a <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> stake.
   In late trading on the <ORGANIZATION>American Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> yesterday,
Corona Class A shares were quoted at <MONEY>$7.50</MONEY>, down <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> a
share. The Class B multiple voting shares finished on the
<ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> at <MONEY>C$9.375</MONEY>, down <MONEY>87.5 Canadian cents</MONEY>.
   The restructuring will allow investors to choose between
<ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s gold assets and <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>'s enterprising style,
said <PERSON>Barry Allan</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Deacon Barclays de Zoete Wedd
Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> "You can either play gold or you can play <PERSON>Ned</PERSON>, who has
demonstrated that he can put deals together," he said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Goodman</PERSON>, with little cash but a knack for creative
financing, helped build Corona from a hodgepodge of small
mining outfits into a major concern that produces about 700
ounces of gold annually.
   Under terms of the plan, which is subject to regulatory
and shareholder approvals, shareholders would exchange 100
Corona shares of either class for 70 new Corona shares and 30
shares and 25 warrants of <ORGANIZATION>Dundee Bancorp</ORGANIZATION>. Dundee would pay
<ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> <MONEY>C$100 million</MONEY> in cash, which the company said it would
completed in <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> said.
   Separately, <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s president and chief
executive officer, said the company had resumed talks with
<ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION> about jointly developing the
<LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION> deposit, which contains an estimated 3.2 million
ounces of gold. The two concerns have been at loggerheads
since <DATE>last year</DATE> when they launched competing bids to acquire
the companies that own the property.
   "I think we're getting to the point where we feel we'll
have a suitable arrangement" with <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Steen</PERSON>
said.
   Although <PERSON>Corona</PERSON> has the dominant ownership position at
<LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION>, it has large debts and little cash. Placer
Dome's deep pockets could be invaluable in financing the
development of the mine, which analysts estimate will cost
some <MONEY>C$200 million</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900604-0047
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900604-0047.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Pezim Says Corona
   Is Set to Improve
   Offer for Stikine
   ----
   By Larry M. Greenberg
</HL>
<DATE>
06/04/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B5
</SO>
<CO>
   ICRA T.SKZ PLDS PDG
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
DIVIDENDS (DIV)
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
</IN>
<LP>
   TORONTO -- Corona Corp. director Murray Pezim said the
company will announce today an improved offer for Stikine
Resources Ltd., upping the ante in a battle for control of a
Canadian gold property.
   Mr. Pezim also said Corona, based here, will announce
plans to spin off its gold assets into a separately listed
company that would offer to acquire all the shares of Prime
Resources Group Inc. Prime Resources is Stikine's partner and
the operator of the promising Eskay Creek gold project in
northwestern British Columbia. Corona already owns 20% of the
stock in Prime Resources, of which Mr. Pezim is chairman.
Prime Resources and Stikine are both based in Vancouver.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s disclosure unravels efforts by <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s
management to keep the news under wraps until <TIME>this morning</TIME>.
Trading in shares of <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> and Prime has been
halted since last week.
   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, who is also honorary chairman of <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, has
been in hot water before with the company's management. In a
fiery <DATE>1987</DATE> boardroom battle, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, commonly known as
"the Pez," was ousted from an executive position amid
management charges that he had talked to the media about
proposed Corona transactions that hadn't been considered by
the Corona board.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> spokesman wouldn't comment on the accuracy of the
latest disclosures, but said <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Ned Goodman</PERSON> was
"very concerned" about <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>'s statements. "<PERSON>Murray</PERSON> talked
when he shouldn't have," the spokesman said.
   According to <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> will offer 6.5 Corona Class
A shares and two <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION> shares for each share of
<ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION>.
   The revised Corona offer would have an indicated value of
<MONEY>C$75.69</MONEY> a <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> share, based on market prices before the
trading halt went into effect. This is higher than a rival
bid by <ORGANIZATION>Placer Dome Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, which has offered
<MONEY>C$229.5 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>C$67.50</MONEY> for each <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> share. Placer is
offering cash with a share alternative.
   Despite a possibly higher offer from <LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION>, analysts
weren't convinced that the <LOCATION>Placer</LOCATION> bid would be the less
favorable of the two. The gap between the bids "is quickly
closed when one considers one {offer} is cash and the other
isn't," said <PERSON>Egizio Bianchini</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Nesbitt Thomson
Deacon Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   Corona's previous offer involved a complex plan under
which it would acquire a <PERCENT>44.6%</PERCENT> stake in a company that was to
be formed from the merger of <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION>. In
exchange, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> was to issue to <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> holders a package of
securities that analysts valued at anywhere from <MONEY>C$65</MONEY> to <MONEY>C$70</MONEY>
a <ORGANIZATION>Stikine</ORGANIZATION> share.
   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said that under <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s plan to spin off its
gold assets, shareholders will receive one share in the new
gold company for every 2.27 Corona shares currently held.
   Corona is one of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s biggest gold-mining
concerns, with production last year of about 680,000 ounces
of gold. The company also has interests in industrial
minerals and oil and gas.
   "At the end, Corona will control <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT>" of the new gold
company, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said. He said the gold subsidiary will be
based in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, with <PERSON>Peter Steen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION>'s president and
chief executive, serving as chairman of the new company. <PERSON>John
Ivany</PERSON>, president and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION>, will
serve in the same roles at the new company, <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Mr. Pezim</PERSON> said the new gold company will then bid to
acquire <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION>, offering one share of the new gold
company for each <ORGANIZATION>Prime Resources</ORGANIZATION> share.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900423-0009
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900423-0009.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Business Brief -- Corona Corp.:
   Stock Deal Set for Stake
   In Stikine-Prime Resources
</HL>
<DATE>
04/23/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A16
</SO>
<CO>
   CANDA ICRA T.SKZ
</CO>
<IN>
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
COMMODITY MARKETS FOR METALS (MIN)
</IN>
<LP>
   Corona Corp., Toronto, said it will acquire a 44.6% stake
in a new company to be formed through the proposed merger of
two mining companies, Stikine Resources Ltd. and Prime
Resources Group Inc., both based in Vancouver, British
Columbia.
   Corona said it will acquire the stake in exchange for 16.6
million new Class A shares, giving the transaction an
indicated value of about 128.7 million Canadian dollars
(US$110.7 million).
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Corona said the proposed transaction "represents a
potential <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> increase in gold and equivalent reserves, and
approximately a <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> dilution in outstanding common equity."
Corona has about 141.9 million Class A shares outstanding. On
the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the Class A shares closed
at <MONEY>C$7.75</MONEY>, down <MONEY>50 Canadian cents</MONEY>, in heavy trading.
   Stikine and Prime each hold <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> stakes in the <LOCATION>Eskay Creek</LOCATION>
property in <LOCATION>Northern British Columbia</LOCATION>. The property has
created much speculation in the mining industry as a possible
major new precious-metal and base-metal find.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910308-0174
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910308-0174.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Gulf Canada Begins
   New Effort to Sell
   Asamera Operation
</HL>
<DATE>
03/08/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   GOU T.GOU T.AUA ICR.A ICRA BWRLF T.BWR
</CO>
<IN>
PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
EARNINGS (ERN)
</IN>
<LP>
   CALGARY, Alberta -- Gulf Canada Resources Ltd. said it was
again seeking a buyer for its 92% stake in Asamera Minerals
Inc., a precious-metal concern, as part of an effort to
reduce debt.
   Gulf Canada, controlled by Toronto's Reichmann family,
pulled the Asamera stake off the market last spring because
of low gold prices. The gold price has barely changed since
then, but a Gulf spokesman said the company recently has been
contacted by parties wondering if the stake still was for
sale. He said there aren't any formal discussions currently
taking place.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The spokesman said that <ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION> doesn't fit with <LOCATION>Gulf
Canada</LOCATION>'s strategy of concentrating on its principal business
of oil and gas production and development. He said <LOCATION>Gulf
Canada</LOCATION> wants to reduce its long-term debt to about <MONEY>500
million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$431.2 million</MONEY>) by the end of this
year from <MONEY>C$902 million</MONEY> at <DATE>Dec. 31, 1990</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION>'s main asset is a <PERCENT>51%</PERCENT> stake in the Cannon gold and
silver mine at <LOCATION>Wenatchee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, which last year produced
149,330 ounces of gold. Analysts estimate <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>'s
holding in <ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION> could fetch between <MONEY>C$50 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>C$75
million</MONEY>.
   <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>British Columbia-based Corona Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a big gold
producer that indirectly holds an interest in the Cannon mine
through an affiliate, <ORGANIZATION>Breakwater Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, said it
would "take another look" at the <ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION> stake. Corona last
year ended a pact to purchase the stake for about <MONEY>C$100
million</MONEY> in stock.
   Vancouver-based Breakwater, in which <ORGANIZATION>Corona</ORGANIZATION> holds a <PERCENT>27%</PERCENT>
interest, owns <PERCENT>49%</PERCENT> of the Cannon mine.
   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION> reported a loss for <DATE>1990</DATE> of <MONEY>C$5.2
million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>21 Canadian cents</MONEY> a share, after writing down
<MONEY>C$6.9 million</MONEY> in deferred exploration costs. A year earlier,
<ORGANIZATION>Asamera</ORGANIZATION> had net income of <MONEY>C$2 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>eight Canadian
cents</MONEY> a share. Revenue rose to <MONEY>C$37.6 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>C$37
million</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880201-0090 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sherritt Gordon Says Newmont Mining's 33.5% Stake for Sale </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> T.SE NEM T.SG T.HRI </CO>
<IN> TNM </IN>
<DATELINE> TORONTO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon Mines Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is seeking a buyer for its <PERCENT>33.5%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The approximately 7.5 million <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION> shares held by <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> have a current market value of about <MONEY>39.2 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$30.7 million</MONEY>). 
In trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION> shares closed at <MONEY>5.25 dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$4.11</MONEY>), down <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>. 

   Sherritt <PERSON>Gordon</PERSON> said the possible sale of the stake is one of several steps <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> is taking to reduce debt. 
Officials at <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>, a New York-based mining concern, couldn't be reached for comment. 
<ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> is <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION>'s biggest holder. 

   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION> said it agreed to sell its <PERCENT>58%</PERCENT> interest in <ORGANIZATION>SherrGold Inc.</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Hayes Resources Inc.</ORGANIZATION> for about <MONEY>23.2 million Canadian dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>$18.2 million</MONEY>) in cash and stock. 

   SherrGold's chief asset is the <PERSON>MacLellan</PERSON> gold mine in <PERSON>Lynn Lake</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Manitoba</LOCATION>, which produced about 40,000 ounces of gold last year. 

   Under the agreement, <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> will pay <ORGANIZATION>Sherritt Gordon</ORGANIZATION> <MONEY>17 million dollars</MONEY> in cash and 2.4 million new Hayes shares. 
The shares would represent an <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> interest in <LOCATION>Hayes</LOCATION>, a small Toronto-based exploration concern controlled by a group that includes <ORGANIZATION>American Barrick Resources Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a major gold producer also based in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Sherritt Gordon</PERSON>, a mining, metal refining, fabricating and fertilizer concern, said the proposed sale of the SherrGold interest would improve its balance sheet and reduce consolidated debt about <MONEY>14 million dollars</MONEY>. 

   In trading <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> exchange, SherrGold shares closed at <MONEY>1.75 dollars</MONEY>, down <MONEY>14 cents</MONEY>, and <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> shares closed at <MONEY>2.20 dollars</MONEY>, unchanged. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880125-0168 </DOCNO>
<HL> Newmont Mining, Banks Are Negotiating Million-Ounce Gold Loan, Sources Say </HL>
<AUTHOR> Jacquie McNish and Gary Lamphier (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> NEM NGC </CO>
<IN> PCS CMD </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Mining Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is negotiating with a syndicate of international banks to arrange a million-ounce gold loan, more than twice the size of any existing gold-based loan, bank and investment executives said. 

   In trading late <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> Metal Exchange the spot price of gold was quoted at <MONEY>$477</MONEY> an ounce, giving <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>'s planned loan an indicated value of <MONEY>$477 million</MONEY>. 
If <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> obtains the gold loan, banking and gold mining executives say its unprecedented size will enhance the popularity and credibility of this low-cost financing technique that is helping to fuel a boom in <LOCATION>North American</LOCATION> and Australian gold production. 

   <PERSON>Peter Munk</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>Toronto-based American Barrick Resources Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, said a million-ounce gold loan "could be a turning point" for the gold mining industry. 
Banks have been cautious about lending large amounts of gold and haven't lent more than 400,000 ounces to any one borrower. 
American <ORGANIZATION>Barrick</ORGANIZATION> borrowed 264,000 ounces of gold last fall. 

   "It would certainly add a lot of credence to the market," said <PERSON>Anthony Walsh</PERSON>, treasurer and vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Toronto-based Royex Gold Mining Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   T. <PERSON>Peter Philip</PERSON>, senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>New York-based Newmont Mining</ORGANIZATION>, declined to comment. 
Banking and investment executives said <ORGANIZATION>Bank of Nova Scotia</ORGANIZATION> is leading the syndicate and <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> plans to create a new holding company to borrow the gold. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> is expected to use the loan to refinance some of the <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> it borrowed last <DATE>September</DATE> when it paid a special dividend of <MONEY>$33</MONEY> a share to thwart a takeover bid from a group led by <PERSON>T. Boone Pickens Jr</PERSON>. Bank executives said the gold loan probably will have a five-year term with an annual interest rate of about <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT>. 
<ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION> would repay the loan with gold produced by its <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT>-owned <ORGANIZATION>Newmont Gold Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>'s largest gold producer. 

   Gold loans have tended to have terms of less than three years and are used primarily to fund working capital. 
<ORGANIZATION>Newmont</ORGANIZATION>'s planned five-year loan apparently signals banks' willingness to lend gold for long-term uses. 

   Gold loans are gaining popularity because of their low cost and diminishing investor appetite for new gold shares in the wake of the stock market crash. 
"If the stock market isn't available, gold loans are the best alternative," said <PERSON>Ray Jenner</PERSON>, treasurer of <LOCATION>Edmonton</LOCATION>, Alberta-based <ORGANIZATION>Echo Bay Mines Ltd</ORGANIZATION>. 

   "There's going to be a lot of new gold mines coming into production and more of the financing will come from gold loans," said <PERSON>Gordon Hawke</PERSON>, a senior manager with <ORGANIZATION>Royal Bank of Canada</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Typically, when a mining company borrows gold from a bank it agrees to repay the gold in installments to the bank with gold produced at its mines. 
Borrowers can receive cash for a gold loan by selling the borrowed gold. 

   Banks have lent small amounts of gold for decades to borrowers such as jewelers, who use gold in their business. 
But it was only in <DATE>1985</DATE> that gold mining companies began to borrow significant amounts of gold to help finance their operations. 
Echo <ORGANIZATION>Bay Mines</ORGANIZATION> says it was the first in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> to use the technique in <DATE>March 1985</DATE> when it borrowed 100,000 ounces. 

   Since then, investment officials estimate the equivalent of about <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> has been lent in gold to mining companies. 
Gold loans are an attractive form of debt because annual interest rates of between <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> are significantly lower than those charged on bank loans or bonds. 
Gold loans would be highly risky for nongold producers because gold prices could rise when the loan has to be repaid. 
Mining companies are protected from such risks as long as they can produce gold. 

   Rates are so low on gold loans because financial institutions are lending gold that would otherwise sit in vaults. 
Most commercial banks borrow gold from financial companies that own gold bullion or from central banks that act as agents for their governments' gold reserves. 
The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> doesn't lend its gold to commercial banks, but <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and certain European and Asian countries do through their central banks. 
