<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900304-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-04-90 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Mexico-Allende     03-04 0198</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Allende,0203</SECOND>
<HEAD>Allende Widow Leaves Mexico For Chile</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MEXICO CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of former Chilean President
<PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> left <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, where she has lived in
exile for 16 years, to return to live in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, the Mexican news
agency said.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Hortensia Bussi de Allende</PERSON> left for <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> after thanking
the Mexican government for giving her asylum and suporting
democracy in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, said the state-run news service Notimex. Mexico
broke diplomatic relations with <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> after the overthrow of
Allende's elected Marxist government.
   ``Now we need more than ever the support and the unity of the
Chilean people and international help for the democratic transition
to be successful,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>Notimex</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>'s
international airport.
   ``Chileans want to live in peace, with justice, liberty and
dignity,'' she added.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> after the <DATE>Sept. 1973</DATE> coup that brought
to power the military dictatorship of <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>. Allende
died of a gunshot wound during the overthrow.
   The <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> government is being replaced <DATE>March 11</DATE> by the
elected presidency of <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON>, 75, has visited <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> several times since <DATE>1988</DATE>,
when the government lifted a ban on the return of exiles.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890716-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-16-89 1722EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Chile-Campaign     07-16 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Campaign,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>United Opposition Opens First Presidential Campaign in 19 years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, CHILE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Thousands of people filled a large arena
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> for an enthusiastic opposition rally that opened <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s
first presidential election campaign in 19 years.
   Voters in <DATE>December</DATE> will pick a succeessor to military President
<PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, who took power in a bloody military coup in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, the candidate put forward by a coalition of 17
opposition parties, spoke to the estimated 10,000 people who crammed
the Caupolican Theatre. About 5,000 more listened to loudspeakers
set up in nearby streets.
   Aylwin stressed the need for a united opposition to restore
democracy in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   ``My government will not be the government of my own party, the
Christian Democracy, nor the government of the opposition
coalition,'' the 70-year-old law professor and former senator said.
``I want to be the president of all Chileans.''
<DATE>Dec. 14</DATE>. The new government is to take office on <DATE>March 11, 1990</DATE>. It
will be the first presidential election since Chileans chose
<PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, an avowed Marxist, in <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   Gen. <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> called the elections after losing an <DATE>October</DATE>
referendum in which voters rejected a proposal to extend his rule
until <DATE>1997</DATE>. Pinochet, has said, however, he intends to remain as
army commander after the election.
   The opposition has united behind <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, and opinion polls show
him leading government candidates by a wide margin.
   Pinochet supporters have become increasingly divided and have
failed to agree on a presidential candidate; two former ministers in
<LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION>'s Cabinet are vying for the spot.
   National Renewal, the largest conservative party, nominated
<PERSON>Sergio Jarpa</PERSON>, 68, a former interior minister, while the <ORGANIZATION>Independent
Democratic Union</ORGANIZATION> chose <PERSON>Hernan Buchi</PERSON>, 40, a former finance minister.
   <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> said at the rally that if elected, his government's
economic policies would emphasize aid to the nation's poor.
   Although the civilian government in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> will inherit an economy
that is one of the strongest in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, wages have dropped by
<PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> since <DATE>1981</DATE>. About <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT> of the country's 12 million
people live below the poverty line and <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT> live in extreme
poverty, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Studies on Development</ORGANIZATION>, a
private resesarch institute.
   <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> said he also would seek ``truth and justice,'' not
revenge, for human rights violations under <ORGANIZATION>Pinochet</ORGANIZATION>'s military
regime.
   After seizing power, the military began a harsh repression of
leftists who supported the Allende government. Church and human
rights groups have said at least 750 people disappeared after being
arrested following the coup.
   Aylwin on <DATE>Monday</DATE> was to fly to <LOCATION>Arica</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>northern Chile</LOCATION>, where he
was to begin a campaign tour of the provinces.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090590-0066 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 271574 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 5, 1990, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 19; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
448 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHILE, 'REPAIRING AN INJUSTICE,' REBURIES ALLENDE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SANTIAGO, Chile 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> unearthed the remains of former <ORGANIZATION>Marxist President Salvador Allende</ORGANIZATION> from a 
humble grave <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and reburied his body in the capital in a solemn ceremony 
17 years after his death in a military coup. 
</P>
<P>
and portraits to pay homage to <LOCATION>Allende</LOCATION>, who 20 years ago <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> became the 
first Marxist president freely elected in the Western hemisphere. 
</P>
<P>
His remains were placed in a marble mausoleum at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s main cemetery, 
where other Chilean presidents and dignitaries are buried. The military, which 
toppled Allende in the bloody <DATE>1973</DATE> coup, was conspicuously absent from the 
ceremonies. 
</P>
<P>
The event was marked by appeals to preserve <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s newly restored democratic 
rule. 
</P>
<P>
"We express our will to favor the future of our country, which demands from us 
to unite beyond the disputes that separated us in the past," President <PERSON>Patricio 
Aylwin</PERSON> said in a speech at the cemetery. 
</P>
<P>
Aylwin, an elected civilian who was a political foe of Allende, succeeded Gen. 
<PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> last <DATE>March</DATE>, putting an end to 16 1/2 years of authoritarian 
military rule. Pinochet, who led the coup against <ORGANIZATION>Allende</ORGANIZATION>, remains commander in 
chief of the army. 
</P>
<P>
Allende died during an attack on his presidential palace on <DATE>Sept. 11, 1973</DATE>. The 
military said he committed suicide rather than surrender. 
</P>
<P>
Allende's remains were unearthed early in the day from a modest family tomb in 
the city of <ORGANIZATION>Vina del Mar</ORGANIZATION>. In <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, thousands of people lined the streets to 
view the flag-draped coffin. The procession drove past the presidential palace, 
the Catholic cathedral and, finally, the cemetery. 
</P>
<P>
Right-wing politicians said the ceremony was an attempt to gain political 
advantage for the government and the left. But the government said the reburial 
was "repairing an injustice toward a man who was a legitimate president of 
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Aylwin was booed when he recalled in his speech that he had opposed the Allende 
government. 
</P>
<P>
Raising his voice, the 71-year-old president replied: "To those who are booing, 
I say: The only language that will allow us to understand each other is the 
language of truth. 
</P>
<P>
"The horror and suffering that <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has gone through should never happen 
again," he added. "It's a task for all Chileans to prevent it, and we will be 
able to do so only if we reject hatred and violence." 
</P>
<P>
Allende's widow, <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi</PERSON>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s ceremonies "should be seen as 
a contribution to reconciliation." 
</P>
<P>
Security around the ceremonies was tight. Four bombs went off overnight in 
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, causing minor damage to two military monuments and two shops, but no 
injuries. A right-wing group claimed responsibility. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, People salute Allende coffin. Agence France-Presse 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CHILE -- GOVERNMENT; GOVERNMENT REFORM; CHILE -- GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS; AYLWIN, 
PATRICIO; ALLENDE, SALVADOR; BURIALS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900310-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-90 2033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Missing 1stLd-Writethru a0516 03-10 0431</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Missing, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0516,0442</SECOND>
<HEAD>Widow of Protagonist in Movie `Missing' Returns to Chile</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with more quotes, details; no pickup.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Chile, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of an American whose arrest and
slaying in a <DATE>1973</DATE> military coup inspired the movie ``Missing''
returned to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to witness the end of Gen. <PERSON>Augusto
Pinochet</PERSON>'s 16{-year rule.
   ``It's not the <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> of my nightmares,'' said <PERSON>Joyce Horman</PERSON>, who
was invited by the elected government that takes power <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
no longer expects any new information on her husband's death.
   ``I think it would be a very special circumstance for anyone
with direct knowledge to step forward at this time,'' she said. But
she added: ``I haven't ruled it out.''
   ``But the most important thing is that democracy is established
for Chileans, that there is respect for human rights.''
   Her husband, <PERSON>Charles Horman</PERSON>, then 29, was among thousands of
people arrested when <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> seized power in a bloody coup on
<DATE>Sept. 11, 1973</DATE>. It toppled the elected government of President
<PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, a Marxist. Horman, a free-lance journalist, and
his wife were living in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> at the time.
   According to the family and testimony collected by human rights
groups, <PERSON>Horman</PERSON> was among many suspected dissidents held and
executed at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Stadium</ORGANIZATION>. The military government
has denied the allegations.
   Horman's father, <PERSON>Ed Horman</PERSON>, pressed for years for details on his
son's death and wrote a book about his efforts. The book provided
the story for the movie ``Missing,'' starring <PERSON>Sissy Spacek</PERSON> as
<PERSON>Horman</PERSON>'s wife and <PERSON>Jack Lemmon</PERSON> as the father.
   The movie is officially banned in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>. ``Maybe now they'll
show it,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Horman</PERSON> said.
   In the AP interview, she said she found the country much more
open and friendly than it was when she and her father-in-law were
ushered out by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> diplomats and military authorities on <DATE>Oct. 18,
1973</DATE>.
   ``The air feels lighter. It's a different place,'' she said.
``It's not the place I remember.''
   Both <PERSON>Mrs. Horman</PERSON>, a 45-year-old computer specialist, and
<PERSON>Horman</PERSON>'s father live in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>. Horman's father is not
attending the inauguration.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Stadium</ORGANIZATION> will be the site of a massive
celebration to mark the end of <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION>'s rule.
   <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, a 71-year-old Christian Democrat, was the
candidate of a center-left coalition that defeated <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in <DATE>Dec.
14</DATE> national elections, winning <PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT> of the vote.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Horman</PERSON> was one of about 400 people invited by <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> to
witness the change of government.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090690-0002 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 271762 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 6, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 6; Column 3; Editorial Writers Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
339 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
FINALLY, A DIGNIFIED BURIAL; 
</P>
<P>
AFTER 17 YEARS, ALLENDE TAKES HIS PLACE NEXT TO OTHER CHILEAN PRESIDENTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Prior to the military coup that ushered in the rigid rule of Gen. <PERSON>Augusto 
Pinochet</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> was widely admired in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> for its political 
tolerance. That honorable tradition was revived <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when Chileans finally 
gave a dignified burial to <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, the democratically elected 
president <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> overthrew in <DATE>1973</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
That was no easy, symbolic gesture for the new government of President <PERSON>Patricio 
Aylwin</PERSON>. For Allende is a controversial figure even in death, and many of the 
men who overthrew him are still alive and still powerful enough to cause 
political problems. Not least among them is Pinochet himself, still the chief 
of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s armed forces and publicly unhappy at the decision to hold a formal 
funeral for the late Marxist president. 
</P>
<P>
Allende died in the final hours of fighting around <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s presidential palace 
in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> 17 years ago next week. It is generally believed that he committed 
suicide rather than surrender to <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s forces. He was quietly buried in an 
unmarked grave and his family sent into exile. 
</P>
<P>
Allende's survivors were present when his body was disinterred. They were 
joined by <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> and most of his Cabinet for a funeral procession along 
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s widest thoroughfare to a funeral mass in the national cathedral and 
burial in the cemetery where other Chilean presidents are buried. Even the date 
chosen for <ORGANIZATION>Allende</ORGANIZATION>'s funeral was a symbol of reconciliation. Allende's family 
did not choose the anniversary of the coup, but instead the date <PERSON>Allende</PERSON> was 
elected president, <DATE>Sept. 4</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
At the funeral, <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, a Christian Democrat, admitted with candor and grace 
that he would still oppose Allende's policies if the circumstances were the 
same today as they were 17 years ago. "But the drama lived by <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> since <DATE>1973</DATE> 
has taught us that those circumstances should never repeat themselves," he 
added. "It is the duty of all Chileans to avoid them." It was a fitting tribute 
to a man who -- whatever his faults or mistakes -- devoted his life to 
peaceful, democratic politics. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Salvador Allende in 1973. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Editorial 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880901-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-01-88 2140EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile 1stLd-Writethru a0786 09-01 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0786,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pinochet Lifts Ban on Political Exiles</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 12 grafs with Isabel Allende arriving in Chile,
quotes, REVISES number of exiled affected upward, picks up graf 11
pvs `The Roman...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> announced
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> he has lifted a ban on the return from exile of hundreds
of leftists, including some of his fiercest Marxist critics.
   Within hours of the announcement, a formerly exiled daughter of
Marxist former President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, whose elected government
was ousted by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in a bloody <DATE>1973</DATE> coup, arrived in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>.
   Four hours after <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s announcement, <PERSON>Isabel Allende</PERSON>, 44,
arrived at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s international airport on a flight from <PERSON>Buenos
Aires</PERSON>. She had planned the trip days earlier as a challenge to ban
against her return, but <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s announcement allowed for her
re-entry to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> without problems.
   Asked why she returned, she told reporters at the airport:
``Because it's my legitimate right.''
   She said her mother, <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi</PERSON>, the exiled widow of
Allende, also plans to return. ``We are going to prepare a grand
entrance, through the front door, as we've always said.''
   Allende's widow <PERSON>Hortensia</PERSON> said in a telephone interview in
<LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> after learning of <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION>'s announcement: ``I am very
happy to be returning to my country. I left in the <DATE>spring</DATE> and I
will return in the <DATE>spring</DATE>.'' Winter is now ending in the <LOCATION>Southern
Hemisphere</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> and her daughter <PERSON>Carmen</PERSON> have lived in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> since
the coup.
   It was the first time she had stepped on Chilean soil since she,
her mother and other members of Allende's immediate family took
refuge in the <ORGANIZATION>Mexican Embassy</ORGANIZATION> the day of the coup, departing on a
flight specially arranged by <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s president at the time, <PERSON>Luis
Echeverria</PERSON>. Allende died in a siege of the government palace during
the takeover.
   Also <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the leader of a 16-party opposition coalition
challenged Gen. <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> to a televised debate during the campaign
for the <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> referendum in which the president seeks voter
approval for another eight-year term.
   <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> said in announcing the measure to Chilean reporters:
``The prohibitions are lifted. All of them. I have spoken this
morning with the interior minister and have given instructions with
respect to exile that totally solves this problem.''
   It was the latest of several relaxations in political
restrictions before the ``yes or no'' presidential referendum.
Pinochet's name will be the only one on the ballot.
   Interior Ministry Subsecretary <PERSON>Alberto Cardemil</PERSON> told reporters
the lifting of exile applies to all government opponents previously
banned from returning. He said they were 430 in number.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> human rights agency puts the total
political exiles at 504, but its list includes Chileans who changed
nationality in order to establish foreign residence or obtain work.
   Prominent exiles affected include <PERSON>Luis Corvalan</PERSON>, a former
senator and leader of the outlawed Communist Party who lives in
<LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Carlos Altamirano</PERSON>, a former leader of Allende's Socialist
Party; <ORGANIZATION>Anselmo Sule</ORGANIZATION>, a leading figure in the <ORGANIZATION>International
Socialist Movement</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Volodia Teitelboim</PERSON>, a ranking <ORGANIZATION>Communist
Party</ORGANIZATION> official.
   After taking power, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s military government arrested
thousands of leftist opponents and exiled them. According to police
figures, more than 9,000 have been authorized to return since <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   Last week, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> lifted all states of emergency for the first
time, and on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he won the formal backing of fellow military
commanders as the sole candidate in the upcoming referendum.
   <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, president of the centrist <ORGANIZATION>Chrisitian Democratic
Party</ORGANIZATION>, the country's largest, and spokesman for the coalition
challenged <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> to the televised debate.
   ``An open and free debate is indispensable,'' he said, and would
enable <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> ``to contrast his ideas with those of the
opposition.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900905-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-05-90 0554EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Allende     09-05 0550</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Allende,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>Huge Crowd Witnesses Reburial Of Allende</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an outpouring of emotion, tens of
thousands of Chileans lined the streets to view the casket of
toppled Marxist President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, whose remains were
unearthed from a humble grave for an honorable burial.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s solemn ceremony, organized by the new democratic
government, came 17 years after <PERSON>Allende</PERSON>'s death in a bloody
military coup.
   The military was conspicuously absent from the ceremonies. Gen.
<PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> led the coup against Allende and still heads the
armed forces.
   The day was chosen because it marked 20 years since Allende
became the Western hemisphere's first freely elected Marxist
president.
   As the crowd dispersed after the observances, riot police
blocked small groups who attempted to march to the city center.
   Interior Minister <PERSON>Enrique Kraus</PERSON> said 92 people were detained in
sporadic clashes with police in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> and five in <PERSON>Vina del Mar</PERSON>,
but all were released <DATE>three hours later</DATE>. <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> was reported calm
at dusk.
   The official observances were marked by appeals to preserve
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s newly restored democratic rule.
   ``We express our will to favor the future of our country, which
demands from us to unite beyond the disputes that separated us in
the past,'' President <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON> said in a speech at the
cemetery.
   Allende's remains, which had been buried outside the capital,
were placed in a marble mausoleum at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s main cemetery,
where other Chilean presidents and dignitaries are buried.
   Aylwin, an elected civilian who was a political foe of Allende,
succeeded <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in <DATE>March</DATE>, putting an end to 16{ years of
authoritarian military rule.
   Allende died during an attack on his presidential palace on
<DATE>Sept. 11, 1973</DATE>. The military said he committed suicide rather than
surrender.
   Allende's remains were unearthed early in the day from a modest
family tomb in <ORGANIZATION>Vina del Mar</ORGANIZATION>. In <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, thousands of people lined
the streets to view the flag-draped coffin.
   The procession drove the presidential palace, the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic
Cathedral</ORGANIZATION> and finally the capital's main cemetery.
   Right-wing politicians said the ceremony was a bid to gain
political advantage for the government and the left.
   But the government said the reburial was ``repairing an
unjustice toward a man who was a legitimate president of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.''
   Aylwin was booed when he recalled in his speech that he had
opposed the Allende government.
   Raising his voice, the 71-year-old president replied: ``To those
who are booing, I say: The only language that will allow us to
understand each to other is the language of truth.''
   ``The horror and suffering that <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has gone through should
never happen again,'' he continued. ``It's a task for all Chileans
to prevent it, and we will be able to do so only if we reject
hatred and violence.''
   Allende's widow, <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi</PERSON>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s ceremonies
``should be seen as a contribution to reconciliation.''
   French Prime Minister <PERSON>Michel Rocard</PERSON>, speaking on behalf of
foreign dignitaries attending the ceremony, stressed the importance
of preserving democracy.
   He said restoration of democracy in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> ``shows that freedom
can be momentarily supressed, but it can never be defeated.''
   Security around the ceremonies was tight.
   Four bombs went off overnight in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, causing minor damage
to two military monuments and two shops but no injuries. A
right-wing group claimed responsibility.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881006-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-88 2106EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Reax     10-06 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Reax,0631</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Watches, Applauds Chile After Pinochet Defeat</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Chile, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet television on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> celebrated the defeat of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s
right-wing President <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, saying voters' rejection of
his bid to rule until <DATE>1997</DATE> proved ``power can be seized by
bayonets, but they cannot keep it.''
   Since <DATE>1973</DATE>, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> ``played the role of the firm but just
`father of the nation,' trying to make Chileans forget the bloody
history of his ascension to the throne, his betrayal of the
Constitution, the murder of Salvador Allende,'' Soviet political
observer <PERSON>I. Fesynenko</PERSON> said on the TV.
   But <PERSON>Fesynenko</PERSON> noted that: ``First of all, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> will be in
power until <DATE>March 1990</DATE>, and only in <DATE>December 1989</DATE> will presidential
elections be held in the country, if the dictatorship does not
abolish them first.''
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, said the people
of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> ``have spoke eloquently, convincingly and courageously.
After 15 years of military rule, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has said `No' to
dictatorship and `Yes' to democracy.
   ``We congratulate the people of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> for having given the world
such an impressive demonstration of the power of the ballot box,''
   The West German government called on <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s military leaders to
abide by terms for the nation's democratization.
   ``We hope that the government will now hold to its own promised
timetable and continue on a course to allow open and free
elections,'' government spokesman <PERSON>Herbert Schmuelling</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>George Foulkes</PERSON>, a foreign affairs spokesman for the British
opposition <ORGANIZATION>Labor Party</ORGANIZATION> and one of 500 foreigners who visited <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>
to view the balloting, said, ``It's a tremendous triumph for
democracy in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, a totally unique situation where a dictator has
been voted out in a plebiscite.''
   Foulkes added, ``It is absolutely crucial now to ensure that
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> fully accepts the decision of the Chilean people.''
   Some Latin leaders reacted with restrained pleasure.
   InArgentina, President <PERSON>Raul Alfonsin</PERSON> said, ``The people of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>
have expressed their inalienable right to decide their own future.
The results of plebiscite open the way toward the restoration of
democracy.''
   Foreign Minister <PERSON>Roberto de Abreu Sodre</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> said,
``Defeating a dictatorship is not easy, but when a government stays
a long time in office it becomes a heavy burden to the people.''
   Mexican Foreign Minister <PERSON>Bernardo Sepulveda Amor</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
for the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, said: ``We congratulate the Chilean
people for this proof of civic maturity, for this capacity to
transform their own political lives in an orderly manner.''
   The Mexican government, which broke relations with <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> after
the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup, gave asylum to many Chileans, including <PERSON>Hortensia
Bussi</PERSON>, President Allende's widow. Bussi recently returned to
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> after the military government allowed exiles to return.
   President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> said he learned ``with a
profound joy of the results of the referendum in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and of the
perspectives opening up for the re-establishment of democracy,
suffocated 15 years ago in this country.''
   In <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, legislators rose to their feet in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> to applaud
the news of <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION>'s defeat. The government immediately named a
new ambassador to <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, a post long vacant in a sign of protest.
   <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Office</ORGANIZATION> said, ``We hope that the plebiscite
result, which appears to reflect the will of the Chilean people,
will represent an important first step on the path back toward full
democracy.''
   Spanish Foreign Minister <PERSON>Francisco Fernandez Ordonez</PERSON> said ``the
people of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> have given a great lesson of political maturity.''
   Added <PERSON>Laurent Fabius</PERSON>, speaker of the <ORGANIZATION>French National Assembly</ORGANIZATION>,
``It's a country that suffered terribly for 15 years ... and now,
all of a sudden, there is light and hope again.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900911-0192 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-11-90 2223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile 1stLd-Writethru a0749 09-11 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0749,0614</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pinochet, on Coup Anniversary, Says Would Stage Takeover Again</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with seven grafs to UPDATE with police reporting
arrests and injuries in clashes between pro- and anti-Pinochet
groups. Pickup 6th graf pvs, `Pinochet led...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, marking the 17th
anniversary of the coup he led in <DATE>1973</DATE>, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he would stage
another takeover again if confronted with similar circumstances.
   ``Should the circumstances of <DATE>1973</DATE> repeat, I would act in the
same manner,'' the 74-year-old army commander and former president
said.
   ``My only goal then was to rescue <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'' from ``a Marxist
government that was working to disintegrate the country,'' he told
a group of right-wing politicians.
   Meanwhile, police said three people were injured, one of whom
was shot in the arm, and 48 arrested in scattered clashes
throughout the city linked to the anniversary.
   Most of the incidents occurred when rival groups celebrating or
denouncing the anniversary clashed in the streets. Police used
water cannon to disperse people, and the government said calm had
been restored by midafternoon.
   Police said they were investigating the wounding of a
21-year-old man who was shot as he left <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s main cemetery
after visiting the tomb of <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, the man <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>
toppled in the coup.
   Pinochet spoke briefly to the leaders of the <ORGANIZATION>Independent
Democratic Union</ORGANIZATION>, a rightist group, who visited him at his home to
``thank him'' for the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup that ousted <PERSON>Allende</PERSON>, a Marxist who
was elected president by the Chilean populace.
   Pinochet led the armed forces in the coup, which took place
during a time of deep social, political and economic crisis.
   Pinochet stayed in power for 16{ years until <DATE>March 11</DATE>, when he
was succeeded by President <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, an elected civilian.
   After relinquishing the presidency to <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> remained
commander in chief of the army, sheltered by a special clause in
the <DATE>1980</DATE> constitution written by his government that prevents
<PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> from firing him.
   The coup anniversary was marked by the military with a series of
private ceremonies at barracks throughout the country.
   The civilian government ignored the celebrations, but ministers
and officials attended a Catholic Mass at the presidential palace
for the hundreds of people who died in the coup and in the severe
repression that followed it.
   Among those who died was Allende, who was killed the day of the
coup as his presidential palace in downtown <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> came under
heavy ground and air attack.
   Leftist politicians and relatives of the victims visited
cemeteries to pay tribute to the dead.
   Hundreds paraded in front of the new marble mausoleum where
Allende's remains were reburied one week ago at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s main
cemetery. They were led by <ORGANIZATION>Allende</ORGANIZATION>'s widow, <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi</PERSON>, his
daughters and other relatives and aides of his government.
   In <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, police used water cannons to scatter small groups
of demonstrators both celebrating and denouncing the coup
anniversary. Twelve people were briefly detained, according to
deputy Interior Minister <PERSON>Belisario Velasco</PERSON>.
   Also in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, two bombs went off during the night, police
said, causing no victims but damaging a bank and the office of a
right wing party. No victims were reported.
   Several hundred people gathered early in the morning in front of
<LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION>'s house in a fashionable <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> neighborhood, to cheer
the former president as he left for a ceremony and Mass at the
<ORGANIZATION>Military Academy</ORGANIZATION>.
   Many of the demonstrators later marched through the <LOCATION>Providencia</LOCATION>
district streets chanting slogans against the <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> government.
They also chanted ``Pinochet will come back, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> will come
back.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881001-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-01-88 2053EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Rally 2ndLd-Writethru   10-01 0502</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Rally, 2nd Ld - Writethru,a0663,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Huge Crowd Rallies Against Government</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS penultimate 15th graf `Pinochet, meanwhile,...' with 2
grafs to UPDATE with Pinochet speaking at stadium; picks up last
graf `The government...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of thousands of people jammed a
broad avenue <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to call for the rejection of President
<PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> in a nationwide referendum this week.
   Organizers said 1.2 million people packed a working class
neighborhood about five miles south of the center of <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> for
the demonstration marking the official close of the opposition's
campaign.
   After the rally ended, small groups marched downtown and clashed
with police, who dispersed them with water cannons. Police said
more than 20 people were arrested.
   Police did not give an estimate of the size of the crowd at the
rally, but reporters on the scene said it was in excess of 350,000.
   Chileans are to vote <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to approve or reject <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>,
the 72-year-old president and army commander who seized power in a
bloody <DATE>1973</DATE> coup. Elected President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, a Marxist,
was ousted and died in the coup.
   Pro- and anti-government forces have been waging ardent but
relatively peaceful campaigns.
   The opposition gathering was the largest of the campaign and one
of the biggest gatherings in memory in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>. Long columns of
people marched from various points of the city, many carrying
Chilean flags and opposition signs and chanting anti-government
slogans.
   <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, leader of a 16-party coalition opposing
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in the referendum, told the festive rally that an
opposition victory would pave the way to ``a peaceful, fast and
   Aylwin called on the military to ``facilitate the respect to the
people's will,'' if the opposition wins the presidential vote.
   He promised that if the government wins and the vote is fair,
the opposition will accept the result.
   ``We are going to win, and that will bring us democracy,'' said
<PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, president of the centrist Christian Democratic party.
   If a majority approve <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> as president, he will begin a new
eight-year term in <DATE>March</DATE>. If he is rejected, democratic elections
are to take place in <DATE>December 1989</DATE>, with <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> remaining in
power until a new president takes office.
   In either case, elections for congress, suspended since <DATE>1973</DATE>,
are planned for <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   Virtually all opposition figures from left to right attended the
rally, including <PERSON>Hotensia Bussi de Allende</PERSON>, widow of the former
president.
   Pinochet on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> traveled to the agricultural city of
<LOCATION>Rancagua</LOCATION>, 50 miles south of <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, and led a rally by thousands
of supporters in a local stadium.
   At the stadium he told the crowd the opposition was directed by
``the same people who in the past tried to destroy the patrimony
and who halted our development, relegating thousands of Chilean to
poverty.''
   The government forces were preparing their own campaign closing
rally for <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. According to election law, all
campaign activities must cease by <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120790-0123 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 319054 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 7, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 28; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
751 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BUSH HAILS CHILE'S 'FAR-REACHING' DEMOCRATIC REFORMS; 
</P>
<P>
SOUTH AMERICA: ON THE FOURTH LEG OF HIS TRIP, HE MEETS WITH PRESIDENT AYLWIN 
AND CHATS WITH FORMER DICTATOR AUGUSTO PINOCHET. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JAMES GERSTENZANG, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SANTIAGO, Chile 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Seventeen years after a coup overthrew a democratically elected government 
strongly opposed by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> saluted the 
re-establishment of Chilean democracy, which he said has been "every bit as 
far-reaching" as the revolutions that overthrew Communist governments in 
<LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION> last year. 
</P>
<P>
"In <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, once more, the people shall govern," <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said in a speech to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Chilean Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For the President, it was a day of symbolism -- one in which, as in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> a 
day earlier, the elements of newly inaugurated democracy barely covered up 
reminders of the time when military regimes tightly controlled political life 
and economic activity. 
</P>
<P>
He met at lunch with President <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, elected last <DATE>December</DATE> and 
inaugurated in <DATE>March</DATE> -- and he shook hands and chatted briefly with <PERSON>Augusto 
Pinochet</PERSON>, the military dictator for 16 1/2 years. Pinochet has continued in a 
position of influence, as chief of the Chilean army. 
</P>
<P>
Throughout the week, as <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has traveled from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and over the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, he has drawn attention to 
the renewal of democracy throughout the hemisphere and, in particular, the move 
toward less government control over debt-ridden economies. 
</P>
<P>
The President, who winds up the tour with an overnight stop tonight in 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, told the legislators: "Every year under autocratic rule served only 
to deepen your devotion to freedom and tolerance and respect for human rights, 
to strengthen <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s collective resolve to make this return to democracy 
permanent and to make it irreversible." 
</P>
<P>
On the other hand, he saluted the economic progress <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has made over the 
past five years, as a result of <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s free-market policies and their 
acceptance by <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Those policies, along with the political stability that the repressive Pinochet 
government imposed upon <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> by tightly controlling dissent, figured in the 
creation of an economic climate that began attracting foreign investors back to 
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>. In the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, nationalization of key industries under the 
government of Marxist President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON> resulted in economic and 
political turmoil. 
</P>
<P>
"Since <DATE>1985</DATE>, about <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY> in new investment has flowed into <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>," the 
President said. "Capital flight, which has sapped the economic strength of so 
many Latin nations, has now reversed itself, turned around with returning funds 
spurring new investment here." 
</P>
<P>
He spoke at the starkly modern legislative building, still under construction 
in the seaside city of <LOCATION>Valparaiso</LOCATION>, which he reached by a 40-minute ride aboard 
his Marine One helicopter. 
</P>
<P>
At a state dinner <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told Chileans: "You deserve 
your reputation as an economic model for other countries in the region and the 
world. Your economic growth is the pride of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
The dinner was held at <ORGANIZATION>La Moneda</ORGANIZATION>, the presidential palace in downtown <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> 
where Allende took his life as tanks and aircraft attacked in the <DATE>September, 
1973</DATE>, coup. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>White House Press</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Marlin Fitzwater</PERSON> described the reception <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has 
been given here and at the three previous stops on his journey as "a love fest" 
compared with the unease with which <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> has often regarded the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> -- and with the rocky reception some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> politicians have received. 
</P>
<P>
But the reception was not entirely friendly. 
</P>
<P>
A decoy limousine driven just ahead of the President's armored car in a 
motorcade was hit by an egg. And at least six bombs exploded in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> during 
the night <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, before <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> arrived midday <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Police reported that 
no one was injured. 
</P>
<P>
Before the visit, the <ORGANIZATION>Bush Administration</ORGANIZATION> worked to ease some of the sore 
points in U.S.-Chilean relations. Last <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> lifted a ban on military 
aid and sales to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> that was imposed in <DATE>1976</DATE> after former Chilean Foreign 
Minister <PERSON>Orlando Letelier</PERSON>, a prominent foe of <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, and an American aide, 
<PERSON>Ronni Moffit</PERSON>, were killed in a car bombing in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In another move also intended to patch up differences, in late <LOCATION>November Chile</LOCATION> 
was allowed back into the Generalized System of Preferences, which grants 
tariff concessions. 
</P>
<P>
As a result, Finance Minister <PERSON>Alejandro Foxley</PERSON> has said, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> will be able to 
increase exports to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by approximately <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> from the 
present <MONEY>$1.45 billion</MONEY> a year. The <ORGANIZATION>Reagan Administration</ORGANIZATION> had excluded <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> from 
the system in <DATE>1988</DATE> to protest <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s repression of the Chilean labor 
movement. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Salute to Democracy: President Bush hailed Chile as South America's 
newest democracy on the fourth leg of a five-nation goodwill tour. "In Chile, 
once more, the people shall govern," Bush said in a speech to the Chilean 
congress. Bush, above, talked with Chilean President Patricio Aylwin after a 
press conference. Agence France-Presse 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BUSH, GEORGE; OFFICIAL VISITS; CHILE -- GOVERNMENT; UNITED STATES -- FOREIGN 
RELATIONS -- CHILE; DEMOCRACY; HUMAN RIGHTS -- CHILE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900514-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-90 0221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-US-Chile     05-14 0469</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Chile,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>US-Chile Agreement a Major Step, State Department Negotiator Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One more step remains before US-Chilean
relations can be normalized, now that <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> has agreed to pay
compensation for the <DATE>1976</DATE> slaying in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> of a Chilean
opposition figure and his aide, a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> negotiator says.
   The ``agreement in principle'' was concluded last week following
talks between Chilean and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> negotiators in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION> legal adviser <PERSON>Abraham D. Sofaer</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   He said the second step toward normalizing relations is to see
that the killers of Chilean exile leader <PERSON>Orlando Letelier</PERSON> and his
aide, <PERSON>Ronni Moffitt</PERSON>, are brought to justice. Letelier and <PERSON>Moffitt</PERSON>
died in a car bombing in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   ``Once we have both those things done, relations between both
these two countries can be completely normalized,'' <PERSON>Sofaer</PERSON> said.
``So it is very significant. It has taken us years to get here.''
   The agreement with the new government of Chilean President
<PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON> marks a reversal of the stance taken by <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>'s
predecessor, right-wing Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, who seized power in
the <DATE>1973</DATE> overthrow.
   Aylwin, who defeated a Pinochet-backed candidate in elections to
replace the military government, has promised full cooperation with
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials in the case. Aylwin took power in <DATE>March</DATE>.
   Sofaer underscored that <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> would make payments without
conceding any government liability for the death of Letelier, who
served in the government of <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, a Marxist president
who died in a <DATE>1973</DATE> coup in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   ``We have agreed in principle to arbitration, in effect, to set
an amount of compensation to be paid to those people damaged by the
bombing,'' he said. The amount would be set by an international
tribunal.
   At the time of the <DATE>Sept. 21, 1976</DATE>, bombing, Letelier and <PERSON>Ms.
Moffitt</PERSON> were working for the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Policy Studies</ORGANIZATION>. The
survivors include <ORGANIZATION>Letelier</ORGANIZATION>'s widow and <PERSON>Ms. Moffitt</PERSON>'s husband.
   A federal judge in <DATE>1980</DATE> concluded that the <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> government
and its agents were responsible for the deaths of Letelier and
<PERSON>Moffitt</PERSON> and ordered the Chilean government to pay <MONEY>$2.9 million</MONEY> in
compensation to the survivors.
   But the relatives have been unable to collect, and the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> is expected to ask the tribunal to award at least the <MONEY>$2.9
million</MONEY> and 10 years' interest, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   In <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, the issue of reparations has been seen as key battle
between <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, who remains as army commander and has
promised to block human rights investigations of the military.
   Letelier served as ambassador to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and was foreign
minister during the Allende rule. In exile after the coup, he
became a severe critic of <ORGANIZATION>Pinochet</ORGANIZATION>'s rule.
   <PERSON>Sofaer</PERSON> said the issue of civil payments is wholly separate from
criminal cases in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> against former officials of the
Chilean secret police indicted in the killings.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900305-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-05-90 1934EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Allende     03-05 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Allende,0356</SECOND>
<HEAD>Widow of Allende Moves Back to Chile</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of former President <PERSON>Salvador
Allende</PERSON> returned for good to her homeland <DATE>Monday</DATE> and said she would
attend the weekend ceremony in which Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, who led
the coup that toppled her husband's government, gives up power.
   ``I want to spend my last years here,'' <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi de
Allende</PERSON>, 75, told reporters at <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s international airport.
She arrived from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, where she lived for more than a decade in
exile.
   She was met by <ORGANIZATION>Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION> officials and by a daughter,
<LOCATION>Isabel</LOCATION>, and granddaughter, <PERSON>Marcia</PERSON>. A small crowd cheered her
arrival, which was virtually unpublicized.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> said she would attend <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s inaugural ceremony,
in which <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> hands over the presidency to an elected
successor, <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, in the port city of <LOCATION>Valparaiso</LOCATION>.
   Asked if she planned to participate in the new government, she
replied: ``No. I've always said we have to make way for the younger
people.''
   Aylwin, a Christian Democrat, is backed by a coalition of 17
centrist and leftist parties, including the Socialist Party that
Allende once led.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> said she would lobby to have her husband's remains
moved to ``a deserved spot in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, where everyone can pay him
homage, and to have a grand monument built.''
   Allende died in the presidential palace while it was being
bombarded by the military during a coup on <DATE>Sept. 11, 1973</DATE>.
According to witnesses, he committed suicide with a machine gun
when it became evident his leftist government was falling.
   He was buried in the unpretentious plot of a brother-in-law, in
the coastal resort of <ORGANIZATION>Vina del Mar</ORGANIZATION>, near <LOCATION>Valparaiso</LOCATION>. The military
kept the grave unmarked for many years.
   The military forced <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> to leave the country within
days of the coup.
   She first returned in late <DATE>1988</DATE> after <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, campaigning for
an eight-year extension of his rule, ordered an end to her exile
and that of hundreds of other dissidents. Voters in an <DATE>October 1988</DATE>
referendum rejected the extension for <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, forcing him to call
elections.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880902-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-88 0049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Chile Bjt   09-02 0604</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Chile, Bjt,0633</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pinochet Lifts Ban on Exiles; Opponents Dismiss Move As
Self-Interest</HEAD>
<BYLINE>BY EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Right-wing President <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>
announced that hundreds of his critics living in exile may return
to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, but opponents said the move, and others like it, are
aimed only at winning votes in a presidential referendum.
   Four hours after <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s announcement, <PERSON>Isabel Allende</PERSON>, 44,
the daughter of former President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, flew to
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. She has been living in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> since her father, a
self-proclaimed Marxist, died during a bloody coup led by <DATE>Pinochet
15 years ago</DATE>.
   Asked why she returned, she told reporters at the airport,
``Because it's my legitimate right.''
   She said her mother, <PERSON>Hortensia Bussi</PERSON>, the exiled widow of
Allende, also plans to return. ``We are going to prepare a grand
entrance, through the front door, as we've always said,'' <PERSON>Ms.
Allende</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Jose Oyarce</PERSON>, a Communist who was labor minister in the Allende
government, returned to his homeland on the same flight as <PERSON>Ms.
Allende</PERSON>.
   Pinochet lifted a ban on the return of 430 Chileans who had
opposed him, including some of the fiercest leftist opponents of
his military government.
   ``The prohibitions are lifted. All of them,'' the president told
reporters. ``I have spoken this morning with the interior minister
and have given instructions with respect to exile that totally
solves this problem.''
   Opponents said the army general is only trying to lure voters in
an <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE> presidential referendum in which <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> is the sole
candidate.
   His nomination for the referendum was made <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>
himself and the commanders of the <ORGANIZATION>navy</ORGANIZATION>, air force and national
police. It sparked nationwide anti-government protests.
   If the majority of Chileans vote ``no'' in the ballot, an open
election is to be held. If they vote ``yes,'' <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> would begin
an eight-year term as president in <DATE>March</DATE>.
   ``The regime is trying to change (<ORGANIZATION>Pinochet</ORGANIZATION>'s) image on the eve
of the referendum,'' said <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, leader of a 16-party
opposition coalition.
   Aylwin challenged <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> to a ``free and open'' debate on
national television, ``so he can have the opportunity to contrast
his ideas with those of the opposition.''
   In another move opponents say was aimed at winning the
referendum, <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> lifted the state of emergency that
has suppressed civil liberties since the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup.
   The president also ordered a <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> reduction in the price of
gasoline.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> made a conciliatory gesture toward his
critics, appealing for their support in a nationally televised
speech.
   ``There is a new democracy ahead of us. We must work together to
make it efficient,'' the 72-year-old general said. ``Our democracy
has a place for everybody.''
   The tone of the speech contrasted sharply with <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s past
references to opposition leaders, whom he has called ``traitors''
and ``bandits'' who ``sell out their motherland.''
   Pinochet told reporters at the government palace <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that
he is not shifting his style in an effort to change his
authoritarian image.
   ``What happens is that a person must act according to the
circumstances,'' he said.
   Supporters praised <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s moves as proof of his intention to
hold an honest referendum.
   ``The decision of ending exile is part of the President's appeal
to peace and unity of all Chileans,'' said Interior Minister <PERSON>Sergio
Fernandez</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Carlos Cabello</PERSON>, leader of an independent organization supporting
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, said ``the move shows the President's deep democratic
conviction.''
   But <PERSON>Jose Sanfuentes</PERSON>, a spokesman for the outlawed <ORGANIZATION>Communist
Party</ORGANIZATION>, said: ``Pinochet will take other measures to try to buy out
the consciences of Chileans, but these measures will not prevent
the collapse of his dictatorship.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881219-0160 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-88 1958EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Novelist     12-19 0496</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Novelist,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Best-Selling Novelist Allende Visits Homeland for First Time in 13
Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Novelist <PERSON>Isabel Allende</PERSON> declared <DATE>Monday</DATE>
that the defeat of military President <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON> in a
political referendum was ``an historic moment'' and that democracy
has been restored to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   She made the comments at a news conference in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> during her
first trip back to her homeland after 13 years of self-imposed exile.
   The author of the best-selling ``House of the Spirits'' also said
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> is a dictator like others who have ruled Latin American
countries.
   ``I'm not really interested in talking about him personally
because he's no different from other cases and is not a particularly
interesting person.''
   However, she said she wept when she learned in <DATE>October</DATE> that
Chileans rejected by 3.9 million to 3.1 million a proposal that Gen.
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> remain in power until <DATE>1997</DATE>.
   ``I believe the silent decision that every Chilean made on <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>
is an historic moment in the return of democracy,'' she said.
   She was in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> at the time and telephoned <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> to
discuss the results with <PERSON>Hortensia Allende</PERSON>, widow of ousted civilian
President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>. ``We couldn't talk, we just cried,'' she
said.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON>'s father was a cousin of <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, the
Marxist who died when <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> toppled his elected government in a
bloody <DATE>1973</DATE> coup.
   Pinochet's referendum defeat obliged him to call elections for
next <DATE>December</DATE>. He is to hand over power in <DATE>March 1990</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON>, 46, has written three novels since she left <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>
in <DATE>1975</DATE> for self-exile in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, where she remained for 13
years. This year, she moved to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   She returned to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for a two-week visit with
family and said of her homeland: ``It feels the same, like not a day
has passed.''
   But she said she had no plans to re-establish residence in the
country.
   She said that while abroad ``every time I've had a chance to talk
publicly about <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and condemn the dictatorship I've done so.''
   ``I believe my mission ends with the arrival of democracy in
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,'' she said, adding: ``I believe it has arrived.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allende</PERSON> said she now is preparing a book of short stories,
including material culled from her third and latest novel, ``<PERSON>Eva
Luna</PERSON>.'' The book describes the experiences of an uneducated but
savvy peasant girl who seeks her fortune in a Venezuelan city.
   ``House of the Spirits,'' which was published in more than a
dozen languages, is the saga of several generations of a Chilean
family living in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>.
   Asked to comment on critics who compare her work with that of
renowned Colombian author <PERSON>Gabriel Garcia Marquez</PERSON>, she quipped:
``This must make <PERSON>Garcia Marquez</PERSON> unhappy.''
   She said she is influenced by <PERSON>Garcia Marquez</PERSON> and <PERSON>Pablo Neruda</PERSON>,
the late Nobel Prize-winning Chilean poet. She said her work and
<PERSON>Garcia Marquez</PERSON>' share only a style known as ``magical realism''
which mixes fantasy with reality.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880902-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-88 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i Chile-Exiles     09-02 0531</FIRST>
<SECOND>Chile-Exiles,0547</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exiled Chilean Artists Now Can Work at Home</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics accused President <PERSON>Augusto
Pinochet</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> of lifting the exile ban only to gain votes, but
whatever the motive, many Chilean artists and performers will be
able to work in their own country.
   Gen. <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, who seeks to win eight more years in office as
the sole candidate in a presidential referendum <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>, announced
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> that all 430 remaining political exiles may come home.
   One daughter of the late President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, overthrown
in the coup led by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in <DATE>September 1973</DATE>, already has returned
and <ORGANIZATION>Allende</ORGANIZATION>'s widow and other daughter have said they will come
back.
   Among other people affected is <PERSON>Miguel Littin</PERSON>, an acclaimed movie
maker whose ``Acts of Marusia'' was nominated for an Academy Award
as the best foreign film of <DATE>1985</DATE>. Littin and thousands of other
Chileans went into exile soon after the coup.
   It will not be Littin's first return. He spent several weeks
here in <DATE>1986</DATE> shooting scenes for a documentary on <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, but he was
disguised, used an assumed name and posed as a member of an Italian
television crew.
   That film, ``General Act of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,'' is critical of the <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>
militry regime and has been shown at several European movie
festivals.
   An account of the secret visit was written later by Colombian
author <PERSON>Gabriel Garcia Marquez</PERSON>, a Nobel laureate and close friend of
Littin.
   <PERSON>Garcia Marquez</PERSON> wrote that Littin visited several Chilean cities
and on one occasion stood only a few yards from <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION> while
filming a ceremony.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> newspaper La Epoca quoted Littin as
saying by telephone from his home in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> that he would return to
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> ``in the next few hours, or in a week.''
   Littin now is shooting ``Sandino,'' a film about the late
Nicaraguan revolutionary leader <PERSON>Cesar Augusto Sandino</PERSON> with American
actor <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON> playing the role of Sandino.
   Also expected to return is <PERSON>Helvio Soto</PERSON>, a movie maker who has
had been working in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Two folk groups noted for protest songs, <PERSON>Inti Illimani</PERSON> and
Quilapallun, have performed successfully in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for years.
   <PERSON>Inti Illimani</PERSON>, now based in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, was on a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour when
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> made his announcement.
   Quilapallun is based in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. It was not known if either group
planned to return.
   <PERSON>Patricio Manns</PERSON>, a folk musician who lives in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, also
can come back. In <DATE>1986</DATE> he became an ``international spokesman'' for
the <ORGANIZATION>Manuel Rodriguez Patriotic Front</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s main leftist
guerrilla group.
   Manns announced in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> that the guerrillas claimed
responsability for the <DATE>Sept. 6, 1986</DATE>, attempt to assasinate
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, the army commander. The president escaped harm in the
ambush of his motorcade on a road in the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION> foothills near
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> but six bodyguards were killed and 11 wounded.
   La Epoca quoted <PERSON>Manns</PERSON>, also a poet and author, as saying he had
not decided whether to return and wanted ``security guarantees''
from the government.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Chilean Journalists Association</ORGANIZATION> said 32 journalists are
among the exiles affected. They include <PERSON>Jose Miguel Varas</PERSON>, a
communist who lives in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> and broadcasts a daily radio program,
``The Voice of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880902-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-88 2031EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile-Exiles 1stLd-Writethru a0752 09-02 0542</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile-Exiles, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0752,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Exiled Chilean Artists Now Can Work at Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Retransmitting a0752 to include AM cycle designation</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EDUARDO GALLARDO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics accused President <PERSON>Augusto
Pinochet</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> of lifting the exile ban only to gain votes, but
whatever the motive, many Chilean artists and performers will be
able to work in their own country.
   Gen. <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, who seeks to win eight more years in office as
the sole candidate in a presidential referendum <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>, announced
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> that all 430 remaining political exiles may come home.
   One daughter of the late President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, overthrown
in the coup led by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in <DATE>September 1973</DATE>, already has returned
and <ORGANIZATION>Allende</ORGANIZATION>'s widow and other daughter have said they will come
back.
   Among other people affected is <PERSON>Miguel Littin</PERSON>, an acclaimed movie
maker whose ``Acts of Marusia'' was nominated for an Academy Award
as the best foreign film of <DATE>1985</DATE>. Littin and thousands of other
Chileans went into exile soon after the coup.
   It will not be Littin's first return. He spent several weeks
here in <DATE>1986</DATE> shooting scenes for a documentary on <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, but he was
disguised, used an assumed name and posed as a member of an Italian
television crew.
   That film, ``General Act of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,'' is critical of the <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>
militry regime and has been shown at several European movie
festivals.
   An account of the secret visit was written later by Colombian
author <PERSON>Gabriel Garcia Marquez</PERSON>, a Nobel laureate and close friend of
Littin.
   <PERSON>Garcia Marquez</PERSON> wrote that Littin visited several Chilean cities
and on one occasion stood only a few yards from <LOCATION>Pinochet</LOCATION> while
filming a ceremony.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> newspaper La Epoca quoted Littin as
saying by telephone from his home in <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> that he would return to
<LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> ``in the next few hours, or in a week.''
   Littin now is shooting ``Sandino,'' a film about the late
Nicaraguan revolutionary leader <PERSON>Cesar Augusto Sandino</PERSON> with American
actor <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON> playing the role of Sandino.
   Also expected to return is <PERSON>Helvio Soto</PERSON>, a movie maker who has
had been working in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
   Two folk groups noted for protest songs, <PERSON>Inti Illimani</PERSON> and
Quilapallun, have performed successfully in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for years.
   <PERSON>Inti Illimani</PERSON>, now based in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, was on a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour when
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> made his announcement.
   Quilapallun is based in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. It was not known if either group
planned to return.
   <PERSON>Patricio Manns</PERSON>, a folk musician who lives in <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, also
can come back. In <DATE>1986</DATE> he became an ``international spokesman'' for
the <ORGANIZATION>Manuel Rodriguez Patriotic Front</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s main leftist
guerrilla group.
   Manns announced in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> that the guerrillas claimed
responsability for the <DATE>Sept. 6, 1986</DATE>, attempt to assasinate
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, the army commander. The president escaped harm in the
ambush of his motorcade on a road in the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION> foothills near
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> but six bodyguards were killed and 11 wounded.
   La Epoca quoted <PERSON>Manns</PERSON>, also a poet and author, as saying he had
not decided whether to return and wanted ``security guarantees''
from the government.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Chilean Journalists Association</ORGANIZATION> said 32 journalists are
among the exiles affected. They include <PERSON>Jose Miguel Varas</PERSON>, a
communist who lives in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> and broadcasts a daily radio program,
``The Voice of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891214-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-14-89 2255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Chile 7thLd-Writethru a0732 12-14 1008</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Chile, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0732,1037</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition's Aylwin Trounces Buchi in Vote for Civilian Government</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs with 93 percent of returns in, Aylwin victory
speech, street celebrations, details. Picks up 12th pvs, `Voters also ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos SCL1,6,7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN NOBLET</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTIAGO, Chile (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Opposition candidate <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>
trounced Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>'s former finance minister <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
in elections to end the right-wing military president's 16-year
rule.
   Official election results from <PERCENT>93 percent</PERCENT> of the country's 7.5
million registered voters showed <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> with 3.58 million votes, or
<PERCENT>55.2 percent</PERCENT>, enough for an absolute majority.
   Interior Ministry returns had <PERSON>Hernan Buchi</PERSON>, the former finance
minister credited with designing a policy of economic growth and
low inflation from <DATE>1985</DATE> until <DATE>May</DATE>, finishing a distant second with
1.9 million votes, or <PERCENT>29.4 percent</PERCENT>.
   At <TIME>midnight</TIME>, Interior Minister <PERSON>Carlos Caceres</PERSON> formally
recognized <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>'s victory and pledged the government will abide
by the result.
   Under Chilean law, <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> is to take office for four years
beginning <DATE>March 11</DATE>.
   Earlier <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, <PERSON>Buchi</PERSON> conceded defeat, declaring, ``We
have returned to democracy. <PERSON>Mr. Patricio Aylwin</PERSON> has been elected
president of the republic by the people of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.''
   Motorists honked their horns in celebration and supporters of
the 71-year-old <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, a moderate Christian Democrat, rushed into
the streets of this capital to hail the victory. Fireworks dotted
the sky and lines of flag-waving citizens crammed the main
thoroughfares early <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   On one large white banner was painted a portrait of ex-President
<PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>, a Marxist whose elected 3-year-old government was
toppled by <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> in a <DATE>1973</DATE> coup. The banner quoted one of the
final statements of <LOCATION>Allende</LOCATION>, who died during the coup: ``I have
faith in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and its future.''
   In a victory speech delivered shortly after <TIME>midnight</TIME> (<TIME>10 p.m.
EST</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>) from a downtown hotel balcony, <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> declared: ``The
people of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> have taken their future destiny back into their own
hands.''
   He then asked the crowd to return peacefully to their homes and
prepare for an official street celebrations <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>.
   A long-shot third candidate, populist businessman <PERSON>Francisco
Errazuriz</PERSON>, also conceded defeat, saying, ``<PERSON>Mr. Aylwin</PERSON> has won an
absolute majority.'' Errazuriz had 998,000 votes or <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>,
according to the count. There were 114,000 null and blank ballots,
the <ORGANIZATION>Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>late Thursday</DATE>.
   In his first public reaction, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> applauded the
peacefulness and normality of the voting, and attributed the margin
of victory to a better organized opposition.
   One serious voting day incident was reported in this nation of
12 million people: police said a gunman fled after killing a
23-year-old officer guarding a polling station in a working-class
district in southern <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>. No details were given.
   Voters also elected 38 Senators and 120 <ORGANIZATION>House of Deputies</ORGANIZATION>
members, but results were not immediately available. Scattered
returns reported by local radio and television networks showed the
opposition coalition leading in most of the races.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> also will include up to 10 members appointed by,
among others, the president, <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court and National Security
Council</ORGANIZATION>.
   While a funereal atmosphere was evident at <PERSON>Buchi</PERSON> campaign
headquarters, across town <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> campaign official <PERSON>Enrique Krauss</PERSON>
said with a smile, ``The results show the unquestionable victory of
<PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>.''
   Aylwin, who represented an alliance of 17 centrist and leftist
parties, had been heavily favored in most pre-election surveys.
   The presidential count included returns from all of <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s 12
official regions. In only one, the southern 11th region, did <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>
win less than in absolute majority _ <PERCENT>46 percent</PERCENT>.
   With an absolute majority, <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> avoided a two-candidate
runoff, which the constitution required if no nominee won more than
<PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the total.
   <PERSON>Buchi</PERSON>, 40, was backed by pro-government parties. Errazuriz, a
47-year-old millionaire, had been expected to run a distant third.
   Pinochet and other top military officials claimed responsibility
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> for leading <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> back to democracy. It was a model in
<LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> before <DATE>1973</DATE>, and economically has done well in recent
years exporting wine, copper, fish, fruit and lumber.
   Aylwin, surrounded by bodyguards supplied by the government,
voted early at a school near his home in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, and was cheered
by bystanders as he pushed through a crush of journalists.
   When <PERSON>Buchi</PERSON> voted, he was greeted by <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON> backers who taunted
him with chants of ``Aylwin, president!'' He did not respond.
   Voting is mandatory in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> and people failing to vote can be
fined <MONEY>$95</MONEY>. For nearly half of the 7.5 million registered voters,
this was their first real election.
   Some people arrived before dawn at the polling places and waited
in lines that stretched for blocks to receive their three paper
ballots: one each for president, <ORGANIZATION>Senate and House of Deputies</ORGANIZATION>.
   The peaceful atmosphere mirrored that of <DATE>October 1988</DATE>, when
Chileans rejected a referendum proposal that <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> lead the
country until <DATE>1997</DATE>, forcing him to schedule elections.
   Hundreds of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and European observers are in the country,
allowed them in as tourists, saying no foreign supervision of the
vote was needed.
   Pinochet complained bitterly <DATE>Thursday</DATE> about their presence,
saying they came ``to control the pesos they gave to politicians.''
   Pinochet's right-wing administration frequently has accused the
political opposition of selling out to foreign political parties
and pro-democracy groups that donated money.
   Pinochet, meeting with reporters at the presidential palace,
said he was angered by two things: ``One, because they come to
control the pesos they gave to politicians and political parties.
Second, they come to meddle believing that there will be
irregularities, bad things, and this isn't so.''
   Among the polling stations <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was <ORGANIZATION>National Stadium</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, which became a symbol of political repression after the
<DATE>1973</DATE> coup. The military penned up thousands of dissidents in the
stadium and, according to human rights groups, killed or tortured
many.
   Similar roundups occurred elsewhere in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   Although he must step down as president, <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> has said he
will retain command of the 60,000-man army. A provision of the
constitution written by his regime prohibits the new president from
dismissing him until <DATE>1998</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900412-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-90 2325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-Chile     04-12 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Chile,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Moving to Restore Relations With Democratic Chile</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAWRENCE L. KNUTSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is moving to quickly
normalize relations with <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s new democratic government, the
<ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   This could include the lifting of economic sanctions and the end
of restrictions on military aid and arms sales.
   ``The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> applauds the return to democracy in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,''
the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement. ``We hope to normalize
quickly all of our relations with the new government in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>,
including economic, political and defense relations.''
   The department's statement comes one month after the
inauguration of President <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON> to replace dictator Gen.
<PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>.
   Pinochet ruled <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> with an iron hand after the coup that
ousted Socialist President <PERSON>Salvador Allende Gossens</PERSON> in <DATE>September
1973</DATE>. Thousands of Allende's supporters were rounded up and many
were tortured or killed.
   Pinochet remains head of the Chilean armed forces.
   But Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, who attended <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>'s <DATE>March 11</DATE>
inauguration in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> assured him he would follow
the policies of the new civilian government.
   The <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said a review will open soon on <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s
petition for the restoration of easier tariff treatment of its
exports and its request for renewed participation in the programs
of the <ORGANIZATION>Overseas Private Investment Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> was suspended from participation in these programs in <DATE>1987</DATE>
due to workers' rights issues, the department said.
   Organized labor in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> now strongly supports the ending of the
sanctions, the department said.
   Military aid and arms sales to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> have been restricted since
<DATE>1976</DATE>. The department noted <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> law bars their restoration until
the Chilean government meets these two conditions:
   _Restores respect for human rights.
   _Cooperates with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in bringing to justice those
Chilean intelligence officials suspected of complicity in the <DATE>1976</DATE>
murders in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> of former Chilean diplomat <PERSON>Orlando Letelier</PERSON>
and an American colleague, <PERSON>Ronni K. Moffitt</PERSON>.
   ``We are confident that the new government of <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>
will make every effort to meet those conditions,'' the department
statement said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-4930</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DIGCFAAXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930907
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  07 SEP 93 / No easing of general's grip in 'free' Chile: The coming 20th
anniversary of Pinochet's coup
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID PILLING
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THERE IS a little copper coin in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, the 10 peso piece, which depicts the
angel of liberty snapping the chains of repression that for so long have
bound her wrists. It does not commemorate <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s return to democracy in
<DATE>1990</DATE>, after 17 years of military rule, but the coup of <DATE>1973</DATE> that brought the
generals, led by <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, to power.
As <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> approaches the <DATE>20th anniversary of the coup of September 11</DATE>, the
coin remains a small but significant reminder of the fragile balance that
exists between the civilian government and the military forces. The
authority of the transitional administration, led by President <PERSON>Patricio
Aylwin</PERSON>, is still strictly circumscribed by the armed forces and by <PERSON>Gen
Pinochet</PERSON>'s <DATE>1980</DATE> constitution which remains largely intact.
Relations with the military, alternately civil and strained during the
democratic transition, have become tense over the past few months. The low
point was <DATE>May 28</DATE> when the military took advantage of President <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>'s
absence abroad to put on a show of strength on <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s streets. Troops
appeared in full combat gear, sporting automatic weapons and rocket
launchers, as the generals - still headed by <PERSON>Gen Pinochet</PERSON> - held a meeting.
The sabre-rattling of <DATE>May</DATE> was largely provoked by the one issue that has
dogged civilian-military relations since the <DATE>1990</DATE> handover - the matter of
human rights abuses committed during the military regime. Most leaders of
the armed forces believe that the issue has dragged on for too long. Many
still argue that during the <DATE>1970s</DATE> the military was engaged in a legitimate
war against Marxism, and that their actions should not be criticised.
Furthermore, since few, if any, torturers and assassins are to be punished -
because of an amnesty promulgated in <DATE>1978</DATE> - most in the military feel that
to pursue trials is a waste of time which can only further sully the armed
forces' reputation.
President <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>'s recent attempt to bring the trials to a conclusion ended
in disaster last week when divisions within the governing Concertacion
coalition killed off the president's bill. The so-called 'Aylwin Law',
presented to the nation in an emotional speech last month, had sought to
appoint special judges to hear human rights trials in secret. The hope was
largely to unearth fresh information that might have led to the discovery of
bodies 'disappeared' by the military.
The president was last week forced to halt the bill's progress through
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> after parties within his own coalition voted against the secret
clause which they argued denied the nation its right to know. It seems clear
that, during months of discussions with <PERSON>Gen Pinochet</PERSON>, the president had
reached agreement with the military, but had not squared the deal within his
own government.
His retreat, seen in <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> as a personal political defeat, shows the
difficulty of trying to appease politicians and soldiers when they are
pulling in different directions.
The bickering within the Concertacion mirrors the no less public debate over
commemoration of the <DATE>20th anniversary of the 1973</DATE> coup, still a public
holiday after the government's failed attempt to shift it to a less
controversial day. The failure to do so in itself highlights the
restrictions imposed by the <DATE>1980</DATE> constitution which, among other things,
enabled <PERSON>Gen Pinochet</PERSON> to stack the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> with nine of his non-elected
supporters.
The Concertacion has insisted that the military not conduct its celebrations
within four blocks of the Moneda presidential palace, the building which was
bombed during the final stages of the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup that overthrew the left-wing
government of President <PERSON>Salvador Allende</PERSON>.
<PERSON>Mr Aylwin</PERSON> has called on the armed forces to show restraint and to remember
the families of those who suffered repression. He has also urged Chileans
not to organise demonstrations in favour of or against the coup, but instead
to strive for reconciliation.
Traditionally, government employees have demonstrated their disapproval of
the holiday by refusing to take the day off work. But this method of protest
has been denied them this year since <DATE>September 11 falls</DATE> on a <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. The
possibility of clashes between opponents and supporters of the coup remains,
in spite of the president's attempt to defuse matters.
Gen <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON> feels the nation has forgotten what he sees as the service
performed by the military in overthrowing <PERSON>Mr Allende</PERSON>'s Marxist government.
'Everybody in this country has forgotten,' he said in a recent speech. 'It
is as though a shadow of amnesia has passed over the minds of the people.'
He remains a combative defender of the new role carved out for the armed
forces under what has been called a 'protected democracy'. He cannot be
dismissed by the government and is guaranteed to remain commander in chief
until <DATE>1998</DATE>. The president also has no power to reduce the huge armed forces
budget which is inflation-proofed and supplemented by 10 per cent of the
state copper company's earnings.
<PERSON>Mr Eduardo Frei</PERSON>, the presidential candidate of the Concertacion almost
certain to win <DATE>December</DATE>'s general election, has pledged to tackle what he
regards as the military's excessive power. After the armed forces' recent
flexing of muscles, it seems his task will be far from easy.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CLZ  Chile, South America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P971  National Security.
    P9721 International Affairs.
    P9199 General Government, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091190-0126 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 274534 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 11, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
EDGARDO BOENINGER 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
World Report; Part H; Page 2; Column 1; World Report 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1664 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PROFILE ; 
</P>
<P>
A VOICE FROM CHILE'S PAST PLAYS KEY ROLE IN ITS FUTURE; 
</P>
<P>
EDGARDO BOENINGER WAS ONE OF MANY EJECTED FROM NATIONAL LIFE WHEN SALVADOR 
ALLENDE WAS OUSTED AND KILLED. NOW, HE HAS BRIDGED THE GAP OF TIME AND MILITARY 
RULE TO PARTICIPATE IN THE COUNTRY'S NEW DEMOCRACY. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM R. LONG, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SANTIAGO, Chile 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The tall, slim man in the comfortable corner office on the ground floor of <ORGANIZATION>La 
Moneda</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s historical government house, has materialized there like a time 
traveler from long ago. His name, <PERSON>Edgardo Boeninger</PERSON>, has a familiar ring, 
echoing the faded urgency of bygone newscasts, resounding with the drama of 
past struggles for power. 
</P>
<P>
Seventeen years have passed since a military coup interrupted Chilean 
democracy, ejecting Boeninger and others from the nucleus of national life. 
Now, many have returned to the thick of things; their names reign once more in 
the headlines as they wield the trappings of office. 
</P>
<P>
Foremost among them, of course, is <PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Christian 
Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> at the time of the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup and now <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s elected civilian 
president. Then there are former congressmen, former ministers, longtime party 
leaders and other figures from the past who are among the people Aylwin relies 
on to help run the revived democracy. 
</P>
<P>
By most accounts, the president relies on no one more than <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON>, 65, whose 
official title is "minister secretary general of the presidency." A kind of 
right-hand man to <PERSON>Aylwin</PERSON>, he is a prime example of the political veteran who 
has bridged the gap of time and military rule to assume a key position in the 
new democratic order. 
</P>
<P>
In fact, <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> played a major role in formulating the political strategy 
that carried the country through a remarkably smooth transition from military 
to civilian rule. In his ministerial position, he is a combination chief of 
staff, strategist, trouble-shooter and mediator whose intellectual prowess is 
sometimes said to make him indispensable to the president. 
</P>
<P>
"There is no doubt in my mind that he is the closest adviser and the one the 
president pays most attention to," said an opposition politician. 
</P>
<P>
"Aylwin would not be viable without Boeninger," commented another politician 
who has known both men for many years. 
</P>
<P>
Chileans recall other, more turbulent times when <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON>'s formidable 
political skills were in play. In <DATE>1973</DATE>, before the coup, the chants of marching 
youths and clouds of tear gas often rose over <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> streets as rival 
political parties contended for power at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chile</ORGANIZATION>. Boeninger was 
at the center of the fray as the university's elected rector. 
</P>
<P>
With the support of conservative parties and center-straddling Christian 
Democrats, he had won university elections three times in the previous four 
years, defeating leftist forces that supported Chilean President <PERSON>Salvador 
Allende</PERSON>, a socialist. 
</P>
<P>
Asked in a recent interview if he was against the coup on <DATE>Sept. 11, 1973</DATE>, 
<PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> said he "shared the feeling that the situation had come to a point of 
crisis beyond return" but favored another solution. "We were working on the 
proposal that both the president and <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> resign, to have elections all 
over again, to start from scratch." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> was deeply involved in the political process at the time, he 
did not belong to a party. After the coup, he joined the Christian Democrats, 
just as the military junta, led by army Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>, banned all 
parties. 
</P>
<P>
"I was the last man to be admitted into a political party," <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> recalled. 
"I requested the president of the party at the time, which precisely was 
<PERSON>Patricio Aylwin</PERSON>, to admit me into the party. . . . It was my way of protesting 
the shutting down of the political system by the military." 
</P>
<P>
When the new regime intervened in the university administration, <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> 
resigned his post as rector, abruptly ending that phase of his career in public 
service. 
</P>
<P>
Like a number of prominent Chileans, Boeninger comes from German stock. His 
father, a white-collar worker, immigrated to <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> after World War 
I, and his mother was also of German descent. 
</P>
<P>
Boeninger attended some of <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s best secondary schools, then earned a 
degree in civil engineering at the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic University of Chile</ORGANIZATION>. He taught 
calculus and analytical geometry at the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic University School of 
Engineering</ORGANIZATION> for two years before serving for a decade as <LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION>'s first 
traffic engineer. 
</P>
<P>
Meanwhile, he completed a degree in business and economics at the <ORGANIZATION>University of 
Chile</ORGANIZATION>, where he became dean of economics in <DATE>1959</DATE>. Under President <PERSON>Eduardo Frei</PERSON>, 
from <DATE>1964</DATE> to <DATE>1969</DATE>, <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> was the national budget director. He was elected 
rector of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Chile</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1969</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
After the <DATE>1973</DATE> coup, he worked as a consultant to international organizations 
such as the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION>. In <DATE>1975</DATE>, he spent half a year at 
<ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> teaching a seminar and studying political science. 
</P>
<P>
He continued to study social sciences at private Chilean research institutions, 
"trying to sort of bring together economic thinking and political thinking," he 
said. "And that got me gradually involved in, first of all, bridging the gap of 
people who had been on different sides of the fence in the previous political 
conflicts." 
</P>
<P>
As a Christian Democrat, <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> formed a close association with <PERSON>Patricio 
Aylwin</PERSON> and became a party vice president in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Boeninger is often credited 
with devising the formula for an intricate alliance between the Christian 
Democrats and other parties, including the socialists, that won the elections 
last <DATE>October</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Using a favorite engineering metaphor, he told The Times that his earlier work 
in think tanks with both leftists and conservatives had helped prepare him for 
his political role. 
</P>
<P>
"I had helped build the initial bridges, so it was easy for me to make a 
contribution in doing this same bridge-building thing now in the political 
field," he said. 
</P>
<P>
was also Boeninger's strategy that won struggles within the party and within 
the electoral alliance to give Aylwin the nomination. 
</P>
<P>
"The mastermind of that was Boeninger," said <PERSON>Arriagada</PERSON>. As a result, he said, 
<PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> took his pick of posts in the administration that began <DATE>March 11</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"He is perhaps the only Aylwin minister who could choose for himself where he 
would be," <PERSON>Arriagada</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
He called Boeninger "profoundly analytical, rational" and "morally impeccable," 
capable of resisting pressure but bent on avoiding conflicts that could 
jeopardize the democratic process. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Miguel Otero</PERSON>, a vice president of the conservative <ORGANIZATION>National Renovation Party</ORGANIZATION>, 
described Boeninger as "muy simpatico," but calculatedly so. 
</P>
<P>
"Boeninger never loses his calm, never," <PERSON>Otero</PERSON> said. "He knows exactly where he 
is going and how, and he uses all of the charm in his power to get there." 
</P>
<P>
Boeninger said an important part of his job is to mediate between parties and 
the government, between the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the government and between ministries 
within the government. On a bookshelf, within his reach as he spoke in his La 
Moneda office, was a book entitled "The Resolution of Conflict." 
</P>
<P>
Boeninger is a voluminous reader. "I read all sorts of novels," he said. Once 
he favored authors of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>'s literary "boom" generation of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, 
such as <PERSON>Gabriel Garcia Marquez</PERSON>, but lately he has been exploring Japanese and 
Egyptian literature, he said. 
</P>
<P>
He also relaxes with jogging and <ORGANIZATION>Ping-Pong</ORGANIZATION>. "I'm fond of the theater, I'm fond 
of the movies, I like to dance," he added. "I've never been bored in my life. 
Too many things interest me." 
</P>
<P>
He and his wife, <PERSON>Marta</PERSON>, have been married 22 years. He has two grown children 
from a previous marriage and she has four. 
</P>
<P>
Boeninger makes a distinction between his political and private lives. "His 
house is not the politician's house where everyone comes," said Christian 
Democrat Arriagada. "His friends come, and that's it." 
</P>
<P>
What Boeninger does most, however, is work, according to those who know him. He 
is capable, according to the newsmagazine Hoy, "of working until 2 in the 
<TIME>morning</TIME> and returning to work at <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> with a memo ready containing a proposal 
for solving the problem under discussion." 
</P>
<P>
A major problem faced by the administration Boeninger serves is what to do 
about human rights violations that took place under <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s military 
government. Many Chileans want punishment for violators, but others, including 
<PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>, oppose it. 
</P>
<P>
"The issue of human rights is the only one in which you cannot expect to reach 
a consensus," <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> said. "What you can do is ride a narrow path to finally 
get to what I call the grudging acceptance of all the parties involved. 
</P>
<P>
"What does that really mean? That the expectations of punishment for violators 
of human rights will be limited. . . ." 
</P>
<P>
He said Chileans will have to accept a small number of human rights trials for 
crimes that took place after <DATE>1978</DATE>. Violations before that are pardoned by an 
amnesty, decreed under <PERSON>Pinochet</PERSON>'s regime. 
</P>
<P>
"We will not try to change the amnesty law," <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> said. "We think that 
would produce a conflict hardly manageable." 
</P>
<P>
Boeninger predicted that the armed forces will not interfere with the 
government's overriding goal of consolidating democracy. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think that the authoritarian temptation is any risk now in this 
country," he said. "I don't think that anyone believes that there could be a 
regression to any kind of authoritarian regime." 
</P>
<P>
When the current four-year term is over, <PERSON>Boeninger</PERSON> will end his public service 
