<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911213-0015
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911213-0015.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Retailing:
   This Christmas May Be One for the Books
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
12/13/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
SPECIALTY RETAILERS OF LIMITED PRODUCT LINES (OTS)
PUBLISHING, INFORMATION SERVICES COMPANIES (PUB)
ALL SPECIALTY RETAILERS (RTS)
</IN>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Despite the recession, Santa Claus's bag will be heavy
this year.
   While retailers in general report little holiday cheer,
many booksellers are ringing up sales that are comfortably
ahead of last year's. Pricey coffee-table books have suffered
in the recession and book buyers are choosy, but they aren't
leaving stores empty-handed.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "The combination of my instinct and the pattern so far
tells me Christmas is going to be very good for books," says
<PERSON>Edward Morrow</PERSON>, owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Northshire Bookstore</ORGANIZATION> in
<ORGANIZATION>Manchester Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, and former chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Booksellers Association</ORGANIZATION>. "Sales of nonbook items like records
and toys are down in my store, but books are up. It tells me
that people look upon books as items of substance worth
having in times of stress."
   Besides the search by financially stressed consumers for
reasonably priced gifts, booksellers cite an unusually broad
selection of high-quality and popular titles in many
categories. "We're a product-driven business, and the product
is wonderful right now," says <PERSON>Jeff Rogart</PERSON>, vice president of
merchandising for <ORGANIZATION>Waldenbooks</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Kmart Corp.</ORGANIZATION> "I've
been in this business 20 years, and this is the best season
for books I can remember. Almost every major novelist has a
book out; then you throw in `<PERSON>Scarlett</PERSON>' and <PERSON>Katharine
Hepburn</PERSON>'s memoirs, and there is even a new <PERSON>Betty Crocker</PERSON>
cookbook."
   Booksellers say there isn't a single "must-have" title
this year, like the <MONEY>$50</MONEY> "Civil War" book that sold more than
half a million copies last year. While "Scarlett" continues
to rack up impressive sales, a wide range of novels by
popular favorites like <PERSON>Tom Clancy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON> are
selling briskly, as are practical, basic nonfiction books
like cookbooks and home-improvement guides. "The Best
Treatment," a home reference guide on treatments for various
ailments, is a major how-to hit since <PERSON>Ann Landers</PERSON> plugged it
in a column recently.
   Price is clearly a factor in consumers' book shopping.
"There isn't a lot of impulse buying," says <PERSON>Brian Weese</PERSON>,
general manager of Encore Books, a chain of 83 stores in the
mid-Atlantic region. "There isn't one book selling in what I
call floor-stack quantities, where we stack it on the floor
in waist-high piles and the stacks just melt."
   "We definitely feel the effects of the recession in the
high-ticket coffee-table books," says <PERSON>Robert Teicher</PERSON>, a book
buyer for <ORGANIZATION>Book Inventory Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which supplies books
for several dozen extra-large, upscale bookstores. A photo
collection by <PERSON>Annie Leibovitz</PERSON>, at <MONEY>$60</MONEY>, is a top seller in its
category, he adds, though not doing as well as expected. And
in areas like cookbooks, old standbys are selling faster than
newer models: the revised 40th anniversary edition of <PERSON>Betty
Crocker</PERSON>'s cookbook "is a classic and also a great buy at
<MONEY>$22</MONEY>," <PERSON>Mr. Teicher</PERSON> says.
   <PERSON>Shanna Hamilton</PERSON>, manager of a <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON> bookstore in
<LOCATION>Dearborn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, says, "People will ask for something cheaper
in the same category, or they'll buy something off the
bargain table. A lot of people balk at paying <MONEY>$25</MONEY> for a
hardcover novel, so even for gifts they'll ask `What do you
have by that author in paperback?'"
   Catering to consumers' interest in bargain basics, <PERSON>B.
Dalton</PERSON> is running a tie-in program called "Master Value,"
which gives a <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> discount on 20 popular titles to anybody
charging at least <MONEY>$55</MONEY> on their <ORGANIZATION>MasterCard</ORGANIZATION>. This has given an
extra boost to such favorites as "The Joy of Cooking" and
<PERSON>Shel Silverstein</PERSON>'s "A Light in the Attic." Also courtesy of
the special deal, "Civil War" has shot back to No. 1 on <PERSON>B.
Dalton</PERSON>'s list of best-selling coffee-table books.
   The sticker shock caused by full-size hardcover books is
one of the factors boosting sales of small, cleverly packaged
gift books ranging from the silly to the inspirational. One
of the sleeper hits of <DATE>last Christmas</DATE> was a palm-sized <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY>
paperback called "Meditations for Women Who Do Too Much."
This year there are dozens of tempting little tomes under
<MONEY>$10</MONEY>, but nothing has sold like "French For Cats," a tiny
hardcover featuring a cartoon cat wearing a beret.
   So far, more than 170,000 copies of the book are in print,
and it's selling big at both chain stores and independent
bookstores. At the classy <ORGANIZATION>Brentano</ORGANIZATION>'s chain, "French For Cats"
is outselling "Scarlett." <ORGANIZATION>Henry Beard</ORGANIZATION>, the book's author, did
well previously with "Miss <ORGANIZATION>Piggy</ORGANIZATION>'s Guide to Life" and "Latin
for All Occasions," but the cat book is his biggest hit to
date.
   This silly book purports to portray a cat's thoughts, with
English expressions like "I think I'm going to cough up a fur
ball" translated into French. It has captivated book buyers,
and its publisher, <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Villard Books</ORGANIZATION> division,
says it was all by design.
   "We knew people were resisting high book prices, and we
noticed that small books were selling, selling, selling,"
says <PERSON>Diane Reverand</PERSON>, publisher of <ORGANIZATION>Villard</ORGANIZATION>. "I think the cute
packaging is a big selling point, and it's a level of whimsy
people need at the moment, with things so bleak. You can't
even say the title aloud without smiling." At this rate, a
sequel seems likely. Perhaps "Italian for Dogs," says <PERSON>Ms.
Reverand</PERSON>.
   Children's books, meanwhile, continue to boom, almost
regardless of price. At <ORGANIZATION>Books &amp; Books</ORGANIZATION>, a bookstore in <LOCATION>Coral
Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, the most popular children's book is "Pish Posh
Said <PERSON>Hieronymus Bosch</PERSON>," an illustrated book selling for
<MONEY>$18.95</MONEY>. The favorite children's book nationwide seems to be
"The Jolly Christmas Postman," a <MONEY>$16.95</MONEY> picturebook with
letters and postcards that can be removed and read. It's the
sequel to "The Jolly Postman," also by <PERSON>Janet</PERSON> and <PERSON>Allan
Ahlberg</PERSON>.
   Books in every price range tied to <ORGANIZATION>Walt Disney</ORGANIZATION>'s new movie
"Beauty and the <LOCATION>Beast</LOCATION>" are also big sellers. And sales have
been strong for many titles by the recently deceased <PERSON>Dr.
Seuss</PERSON>. Publisher <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> combined six <PERSON>Seuss</PERSON> favorites in
a <MONEY>$25</MONEY> hardcover book that is a big gift item.
   Even in tough times, there are still enough big spenders
out there to make a success of <ORGANIZATION>Alfred A. Knopf</ORGANIZATION>'s two-volume
set on "The Sistine Chapel," priced at <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>. Produced with
<ORGANIZATION>Nippon Television Network Association</ORGANIZATION>, which funded the
chapel's restoration, the set's lavish 740 pages feature 600
color photographs.
   "We published a limited edition of 2,500, and only 500 are
still in the warehouse; I expect those to be gone by
Christmas," says <PERSON>Bruce Harris</PERSON>, an executive vice president of
<ORGANIZATION>Knopf parent Random House Inc.</ORGANIZATION> "About <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> have sold to
institutions like libraries and museums, but the rest are
being bought by individuals. Many bookstores have said to us,
`I'll take two or three, and I know exactly who I'm going to
sell them to.'"
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06140068 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06140068 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; SALE; AWARD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ASK James Mason why the anthology "When I Am an Old Woman I Shall Wear Purple"
has sold 200,000 copies, an astounding number for a book from a small
publisher, and he'll tell you it's certainly not because Watsonville-based
Papier-Mache Press has a large advertising budget.;    "Firstly, it taps a
very much neglected and increasingly vast senior citizen market," says Mason,
marketing manager for Papier-Mache Press, which three years ago published the
anthology of stories, poems and photographs about growing old. "And the
combination of simple, evocative language and photographs has given the book
an astonishing word-of-mouth promotion."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHEN LITTLE BOOKS HIT IT BIG  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Books  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Professional word-of-mouth promotion, when booksellers recommend their
favorites to customers, is known in the industry as "hand selling," and over
time it often can turn a little-known book such as "When I Am an Old Woman I
Shall Wear Purple" into something of a best seller.;    It's that kind of
word-of-mouth promotion the <ORGANIZATION>American Booksellers Association</ORGANIZATION> wants to
encourage with its first-ever ABBY award, announced early this month. The
<MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> award, voted on by ABA-member bookstores, will be presented at the
association's <DATE>June</DATE> meeting in <LOCATION>New York.</LOCATION>;    "When I Am An Old Woman I Shall
Wear Purple" was named one of three runners-up in the competition. Another
steady seller that seemed unlikely to make the leap to best seller, "The
Education of Little Tree," got top honors as the American Booksellers Book of
the Year.;    "The Education of Little Tree" is Forrest <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>'s
autobiographical account of his <DATE>1930s</DATE> boyhood spent with his Cherokee
grandparents in the <LOCATION>Appalachian Mountains</LOCATION> of Tennessee.;    <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, who died
in <DATE>1979</DATE> at the age of 53, also wrote the novel "Gone to <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>," which was made
into the <PERSON>Clint Eastwood</PERSON> film "The Outlaw Josey Wales." Still, his name was
hardly a household word on a par with <PERSON>Sidney Sheldon</PERSON> or <PERSON>Louis L'Amour</PERSON> when
"The Education of Little Tree" was published by Delacorte in <DATE>1976.</DATE>;    The
book was warmly if not widely reviewed. The <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> noted that, "Some of it
is sad, some of it is hilarious, some of it is unbelievable and all of it is
charming.";    A paperback edition was published by <ORGANIZATION>Dell/Laurel Leaf</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
Word spread and, over the years, "The Education of Little Tree" became a cult
classic, even though the book went out of print.;    Five years ago, though,
the <ORGANIZATION>University of New Mexico Press</ORGANIZATION> brought out a <MONEY>$10.95</MONEY> trade paperback
edition that has sold almost a quarter of a million copies. It has been the
press's best-selling book for two straight years and sales show no sign of
abating; more than 25,000 copies were shipped out in <DATE>January</DATE> and February.;   
Similarly, Papier-Mache Press plans to publish a hardcover edition of "When I
Am an Old Woman I Shall Wear Purple" in <DATE>July</DATE>. The hardcover book, which will
sell for <MONEY>$16</MONEY>, will be issued simultaneously with an updated paperback version
priced at <MONEY>$10.</MONEY>;    Other runners-up for the ABBY award were the best-selling
"The Civil War," by <PERSON>Geoffrey Ward</PERSON> with <PERSON>Ric Burns</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ken Burns</PERSON>, the companion
volume to the popular PBS series; "The Shell Seekers," a novel by <PERSON>Rosamunde
Pilcher</PERSON> that also made best-seller lists; and "Cold Sassy Tree," the late
Olive <PERSON>Ann Burns</PERSON>' novel about family relationships in a small <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> town.;   
The awards process began in <DATE>January</DATE>, when booksellers nominated the five books
they most enjoyed hand selling in <DATE>1990</DATE>. Any book in print, fiction or
non-fiction, was eligible. In <DATE>February</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> announced the 10 ABBY
finalists as culled from the 2,000 nominations made by more than 400
booksellers. Final voting took place in <LOCATION>March.</LOCATION>;    In the weekly <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION>
newsletter, executive director <PERSON>Bernie Rath</PERSON> noted that one of the intentions of
the ABBY award program was to generate a list for bookstores of titles that
sell steadily over time, the so-called midlist books.;    The other five
finalists for the ABBY were <PERSON>Barbara Kingsolver</PERSON>'s novels "Animal Dreams" and
"The Bean Trees"; <ORGANIZATION>Fannie Flagg</ORGANIZATION>'s funny novel "Fried Green Tomatoes at the
Whistle Stop Cafe"; <PERSON>Kazuo Ishiguro</PERSON>'s critically acclaimed novel "The Remains
of the Day"; and <PERSON>Jill K. Conway</PERSON>'s memoir of her Australian girlhood, "Road
from Coorain."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Staff and Wire Reports  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910519  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  26  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  705  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday May 19, 1991
00140068,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900508-0089
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900508-0089.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing &amp; Media:
   Doubleday Pulls Out All the Stops
   For Reissue of Stephen King Novel
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
05/08/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B7
</SO>
<CO>
   G.BRT
</CO>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- In 1978, "The Stand" was Stephen King's first
best seller, selling fewer than 100,000 copies in hardcover.
A new, longer version of the novel is now for sale at nearly
double the price, and publisher Doubleday has printed one
million copies.
   The original "Stand" hit the New York Times best seller
list at 15th place and climbed no farther than No. 13: The
new version of the novel will start on the New York Times
list Sunday, in first place. A signed, limited edition of
1,250 copies in black leather stamped with gold is sold out
at $325 each; book collectors have offered the publisher as
much as $1,200 for a copy.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Reflected in this episode are the vast changes in the
market for hardcover books over the past decade, but the
principal factor is the singular phenomenon of <PERSON>Mr. King</PERSON>'s
popularity. Also, <ORGANIZATION>Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>, a division of <ORGANIZATION>Bertelsmann AG</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Bantam Doubleday Dell Publishing Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, has
pulled out all promotional stops to incite the fans.
   In addition to the deluxe edition, Doubleday got
bookstores across the country to take "reservations" for the
book (which sometimes resulted in a discount) and set up a
special "Stand Hotline" with the details of what's included
in the book. About 200 people a day still call the hotline,
though the book has arrived at most stores in recent weeks.
   When <PERSON>Mr. King</PERSON> approached Doubleday in the mid-80s about
re-issuing the novel, the publisher was skeptical, despite
<PERSON>Mr. King</PERSON>'s record for the most best sellers of the past
decade. Doubleday had originally cut about 400 pages from the
book because production costs would have mandated a hardcover
price of <MONEY>$12.95</MONEY>, which seemed too high in <DATE>1978</DATE> for a
non-best-selling author. "You had an already monstrous book
(823 pages)," says <PERSON>Peter Schneider</PERSON>, <PERSON>Doubleday</PERSON>'s director of
marketing. "It's a tremendous story, but would people buy it
again?"
   Bookstore managers say they'll be surprised if Doubleday
can move one million copies of "The Stand: The Complete and
Uncut Edition" in hardcover. But they do expect it to sell
many times better than the original version, which is
extremely rare. In the odd instance when an updated version
of a book is issued, it generally sells far fewer copies, as
when <PERSON>Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn</PERSON>'s book "<DATE>August 1914</DATE>" was
re-issued 17 years later with <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> new material. (Exact sales
figures aren't available.)
   "So far, it isn't doing quite as well as a new <PERSON>Stephen
King</PERSON>, but it's awfully close," says <PERSON>Tom Simon</PERSON>, vice president
of merchandising for the Waldenbooks subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>K mart
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> "The big question is the staying power: Is this just a
flurry, or will it stay No. 1 for several months, like most
of his books?"
   One reason for <ORGANIZATION>Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>'s optimistic print run is the
basic change in the hardcover market: While only the hottest
best sellers sold above 75,000 copies in the '70s, best
sellers now routinely sell above 300,000 in hardcover. The
rapid growth in the bookstore chains, along with the more
recent growth in warehouse stores and discount clubs, has
spread books into hundreds of new outlets, most of which
offer substantial discounts to the cover price. The
perception of hardcover books as a splurge has moderated:
Retail price for "The Stand" is <MONEY>$24.95</MONEY>, high even for a major
author, but buyers can find it discounted up to <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>.
   Booksellers say that if this ploy works, <PERSON>Mr. King</PERSON> deserves
the credit. "<PERSON>Danielle Steel</PERSON>, for one, has a huge following,
but I don't think you could re-release one of her back
titles," says <PERSON>Gary DelVecchio</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Doubleday Book
Shops</ORGANIZATION> (no relation to the book's publisher). "<PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON> is
in a class by himself. He's got almost a cult following."
   Not only are his first editions the most prized of
contemporary authors' to collectors, but <PERSON>Mr. King</PERSON> himself is
the subject of more books than he's written, says <PERSON>George
Beahm</PERSON>, author of "The Stephen King Companion." And "The
Stand," with a complicated, fantasy plot about good and evil
and the end of the world, is considered his best book by
fans. "It's ironic," says <PERSON>Mr. Beahm</PERSON>, "that what was once
considered this book's weak point, its length, is now touted
as its strong point."
   ---
   <ORGANIZATION>Corrections &amp; Amplifications
                                                                                                       

   DOUBLEDAY</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Bertelsmann AG</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bantam Doubleday
Dell Publishing Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has so far printed more than half
a million copies of "The Stand: The Complete and Uncut
Edition" by <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>. Yesterday's edition misstated the
number of copies that has been printed.
   (WSJ <DATE>May 9, 1990</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900604-0100
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900604-0100.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Publishing
   ---
   Reporter's Notebook --
   Booksellers Pass the Word at Convention:
   The Trend Is Big Stores, Broad Selection
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
06/04/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   KM CRWN
</CO>
<IN>
SPECIALTY RETAILERS (OTS)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
</IN>
<LP>
   LAS VEGAS, Nev. -- For book lovers -- those who prefer
bookstores that sell more books than video games and party
favors -- there is good news from the American Booksellers
Association's annual convention.
   Bookstore owners attending the convention, which runs
through tomorrow, say the overriding trend in bookstores
today is bigger stores that carry a broad selection of
titles, including previous titles by authors and books by
emerging writers.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "The trend is breadth: The public is interested in
everything," says <PERSON>Edward A. Morrow Jr.</PERSON>, president of the
<ORGANIZATION>American Booksellers</ORGANIZATION> and owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Northshire Bookstore</ORGANIZATION> in
<ORGANIZATION>Manchester Center</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Vt</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Morrow</PERSON> says that the vast
expansion in bookstores in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, coupled with the
demographic growth of book-buying, well-educated yuppies, has
led to an increase in book sales in many areas, from computer
and self-help books to literary fiction.
   <PERSON>Mr. Morrow</PERSON> says that he added non-book items to his own
stock in years past "for defensive reasons, because margins
were better. But now, it's so important to have depth to be
competitive that we're looking to cut back in stationery and
maybe games, so we'll have more room for books."
   Not only are independent bookstore owners re-emphasizing a
broad, thoughtful selection of books, but the big bookstore
chains are also adding titles. The two biggest chains, <PERSON>B.
Dalton</PERSON>, a unit of closely held <ORGANIZATION>BDB Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, and the <LOCATION>Waldenbooks</LOCATION>
unit of <ORGANIZATION>K mart Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, are adding titles in their mall stores
and expanding smaller chains, such as <ORGANIZATION>Brentano</ORGANIZATION>'s, which is
owned by Waldenbooks, that have more books, a classy image
and lots of service.
   The most extreme shift is that of <ORGANIZATION>Crown Books Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a
discount chain based in <LOCATION>Landover</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, which has grown to 260
stores by selling a limited selection of mostly best sellers
for discounts as high as <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT>.
   Crown is just starting to build a series of Super Crown
stores, which have three times as many titles as the old
stores, or about 30,000, says President <PERSON>Robert Haft</PERSON>. Two
Super Crown stores that opened within the past three weeks
near <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> offer discounts even on specially ordered
books. The ambiance of the stores, with piped in classical
music and benches that encourage browsing, isn't what Crown
is known for.
   <PERSON>Mr. Haft</PERSON>, who says people tend to spend about one-third
more money at the new, bigger stores, says: "We just listened
to our customers. They said they loved our prices but there
were more books they wanted to read. I think it's a trend
reflected in all kinds of retailing. People don't just want
low prices, but also service and selection." <PERSON>Mr. Haft</PERSON> says he
has signed leases for four more Super Crown bookstores, and
if they do well, more will follow.
   Among the hundreds of exhibitors' booths here, there are
plenty of non-book products vying for booksellers'
attentions. There are half a dozen booths offering fancy
bookmarks alone, plus others selling videotapes, games,
stuffed animals, rubber stamps, post cards and
answering-machine audiotapes featuring impersonations of
movie stars. There is even a patented invention by housewife
<PERSON>Patty Sremba</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Anaheim Hills</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, called a Sunbuddy, a
little paper device retailing for <MONEY>$1.99</MONEY> that pops up to shade
a paperback book from the sun.
   Even while the staffs of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> publishing houses moan
about the tackiness of <LOCATION>Vegas</LOCATION>, there seems to be a consensus
among the bookish crowd that this <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> convention has been
more respectful about books than some in years past. "It
seems like there was more frivolity at earlier conventions;
lots of fitness celebrities and people dressed as cartoon
characters," says novelist <PERSON>Mark Childress</PERSON>. "This year, it
seems like everybody is running around trying to get galleys
{uncorrected, pre-publication copies of books} before they
run out. The focus is on the books."
   ---
   Proof of the mass popularity of bookstores comes from a
new national poll, released by the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> at the convention.
   <PERSON>Bernard Rath</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Booksellers
Association</ORGANIZATION>, says that 93 million Americans visit a bookstore
at least once a month, according to a national telephone
survey conducted by <ORGANIZATION>Wirthlin Group</ORGANIZATION>. Of those who visit a
bookstore at least once a month, says <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON>, about <PERCENT>54%</PERCENT> are
women; and <PERCENT>62%</PERCENT> of the visitors are between the ages of 18 and
44. <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> region stand out for their
share of bookstore traffic.
   Since the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> hasn't conducted such a survey before, it
isn't clear whether people are visiting bookstores more or
less often than in the past, but bookstore sales have been
climbing rapidly, says <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON>. A recent <ORGANIZATION>ABA/Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> report showed an increase in retail bookstore
sales to <MONEY>$5.1 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, from <MONEY>$3.1 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
Sales are expected to reach <MONEY>$7.2 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>. st
   ---
   Amid the optimism, <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> executive director,
sees several discouraging trends. The survey on bookstore
visits showed that only half the 93 million Americans that
enter a bookstore monthly actually buy a book. <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON>
believes that publishers and booksellers have to band
together to aggressively promote reading.
   One possible tool for promoting books and reading is a new
weekly television series, "First Edition," conceived by a
group of public television producers. At a meeting in the
convention center <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON> presented the idea to a
small group of influential bookstore owners, hoping to get
them to help commit some funding that could then be added to
anticipated corporate and foundation support.
   The new show would be produced by <ORGANIZATION>KQED</ORGANIZATION>, a public
television station in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. The producers emphasize
that this wouldn't be another talking-heads show with
professorial writers blathering on. <PERSON>Marjorie Poore</PERSON>, vice
president for national production at <ORGANIZATION>KQED</ORGANIZATION>, says the show is
modeled more on the syndicated "Entertainment Tonight" than
news shows on public television. It would feature visits to
authors at their homes; reports on industry trends, gossip
and best sellers and reviews, says <PERSON>Ms. Poore</PERSON>.
   Booksellers and publishing executives in the room wondered
if publishers would have enough money in their promotional
budgets for such a venture. Even if funding is found, <PERSON>Ms.
Poore</PERSON> says, "First Edition" probably won't get on the air
before <DATE>fall of 1991</DATE>.
   ---
   There is little doubt among convention-goers about what
will be THE big book this fall: "The Plains of Passage" by
<PERSON>Jean Auel</PERSON>.
   It certainly isn't because <PERSON>Ms. Auel</PERSON>'s publisher, the <ORGANIZATION>Crown
Publishing</ORGANIZATION> unit of <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>, threw a party for 1,000
people on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, complete with wild-animal sounds
and a ballroom-sized copy of the book's cover. (Actually, it
wasn't the cover but a movie backdrop from the film "The Old
Gringo.") This is <PERSON>Ms. Auel</PERSON>'s fourth book in a series about a
couple living in the Ice Age that started with "Clan of the
Cave Bear" in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Her last offering, "The Mammoth Hunters"
came out five years ago, and her fans have been eagerly
awaiting the next book.
   <PERSON>Tom Simon</PERSON>, a Waldenbooks vice president, says "People have
been asking for this book for years. Thousands of people have
called Waldenbooks to reserve a copy of this, and it won't be
out for months."
   In general, booksellers take for granted that new novels
by all the big guns, such as <PERSON>John Updike</PERSON> ("Rabbit at Rest" is
out this <DATE>fall</DATE> from Knopf) and <PERSON>Jackie Collins</PERSON> will
automatically be published in huge quantities, heavily
advertised and sought out by fans. Thus, they are pretty sure
to be best sellers. Betting gets much trickier when it comes
to books, however promising, by little-known authors.
   But one author who may make the leap to bestsellerdom this
year is <PERSON>Mr. Childress</PERSON>, whose third novel, "Tender," is
getting special treatment from Harmony, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Random
House</ORGANIZATION>'s Crown Publishing. <PERSON>Bruce Harris</PERSON>, an executive vice
president of <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>, says the novel, about an Elvis
Presley-like rock star, "just got everybody excited at <LOCATION>Crown</LOCATION>
when they read it." When a copy was sent to <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>, the
bestselling author contributed a blurb calling the book "the
best rock 'n' roll novel I ever read."
   <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> decided to promote the book heavily, including
a 15-city author tour this <DATE>fall</DATE>, plus a party at the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION>
convention. Trying to create a buzz about the book among
booksellers, "Tender" is the only book he's handing out in
galleys this year. <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> recalls that a decade ago, he
handed out galleys at the <ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION> convention of "Clan of the Cave
Bear;" he hopes "Tender" will be a "surprise" best seller,
too.
   ---
                   The Buzz in Publishing:
                     Expected Hot Books
                                                                                                       

 The Plains of Passage by <PERSON>Jean Auel</PERSON>; from <LOCATION>Crown</LOCATION>, a unit of
<ORGANIZATION>Random House
                                                                                                       

 Burden of Proof</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Scott Turow</PERSON>; from <PERSON>Farrar</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Straus &amp; Giroux
                                                                                                       

 Bo Knows Bo</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Bo Jackson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dick Schaap</PERSON>; from <ORGANIZATION>Bantam
Doubleday Dell
                                                                                                       

 Harlot</ORGANIZATION>'s Ghost by <PERSON>Norman Mailer</PERSON>; from <ORGANIZATION>Random House
                                                                                                       

 Lady</ORGANIZATION>'s Boss by <PERSON>Jackie Collins</PERSON>; from <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION>
                                                                                                       

 The General in His Labyrinth by <PERSON>Gabriel Garcia Marquez</PERSON>; from
<LOCATION>Knopf</LOCATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Random House
                                                                                                       

 Tender</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Mark Childress</PERSON>; from Harmony, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Random
House
                                                                                                       

 Trump</ORGANIZATION>: Surviving at the Top by <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>; from <ORGANIZATION>Random
House
                                                                                                       

 Message From Nam</ORGANIZATION> by <ORGANIZATION>Danielle Steel</ORGANIZATION>; from <ORGANIZATION>Bantam Doubleday
Dell</ORGANIZATION>
                                                                                                       

 The First Man in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Colleen McCollough</PERSON>; from <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON>, a
unit of <ORGANIZATION>Hearst Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910531-0004
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910531-0004.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Publishing:
   Booksellers Fret Over How Fall Stacks Up
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
05/31/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
OTHER SPECIALTY RETAILERS OF LIMITED PRODUCT LINES (OTS)
ALL SPECIALTY RETAILERS (RTS)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- The mood of many booksellers on the eve of
their annual convention is apprehensive, but the news for
consumers is mostly good.
   Despite disappointing Christmas sales and a slow spring,
booksellers are hopeful about the fall, when an unusually
dense crop of books by best-selling authors will be
published. Tom Clancy and Stephen King will both have new
books out, and booksellers have high hopes for Katharine
Hepburn's autobiography and the long-awaited sequel to "Gone
With the Wind." These and hundreds of other new fall titles
will be trumpeted by publishers as the annual convention of
the American Booksellers Association starts tomorrow.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Many booksellers complain about erratic sales, but the
<ORGANIZATION>ABA</ORGANIZATION>'s executive director, <PERSON>Bernard Rath</PERSON>, says that bookstores
are doing better than most other retailers. Book sales in the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> rose to <MONEY>$7.3 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>, an increase of <PERCENT>12.3%</PERCENT> from
the year before. <PERSON>Mr. Rath</PERSON> says book sales should rise about
<PERCENT>8.2%</PERCENT> in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   But booksellers argue that the sales rise can be
attributed partly to price increases. Furthermore, with the
rapid growth in bookstores in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, those sales are
spread more thinly. To keep their profits from diving, both
large chains and onestore owners are working harder to
attract and please consumers with everything from extra
discounts and service to a wider selection. Similarly,
hard-pressed publishers have begun cutting their lists and
paying more attention to marketing.
   "We keep looking for the light at the end of the tunnel,
but it just doesn't get any brighter," says <PERSON>William Rickman</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Kroch's &amp; Brentano</ORGANIZATION>'s chain in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. "Our
store on glamorous <LOCATION>Michigan Avenue</LOCATION> still does fine, but the
mall stores are really struggling."
   To pursue buyers more aggressively, <PERSON>Mr. Rickman</PERSON> is
offering more in-store author readings. He is also actively
pursuing organizations around town that have scheduled
speeches by authors, promising to deliver tablefuls of books
beforehand.
   At <LOCATION>Bookland</LOCATION>, a chain of 15 bookstores in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, store
managers are attending "salesmanship school" with a
consultant. "We want every customer to be greeted as they
enter the store," says <PERSON>Nan Knecht</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Bookland</ORGANIZATION>'s district
manager, "and they're training us to do more add-on sales:
You might say to a customer, `You like <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>? Have you
ever tried Dean <PERSON>Koontz</PERSON>?' They taught us that the first book
you sell to a person goes to overhead, and the second will
boost profits."
   The famous book lover's paradise in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, the Tattered
Cover bookstore, is holding seminars for local elementary
school teachers to introduce them to new children's books.
"Bookstores have always been a community resource, but I
think we are all looking to do that to an even greater
degree," says <PERSON>Joyce Meskis</PERSON>, the store's owner and the
president of the booksellers' group.
   Some stores are thriving -- especially those that offer
service and ambiance along with discount prices. Book
<ORGANIZATION>Inventory Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which runs about 13 elegant, lavishly
stocked Borders Book Shops around the country plus another 10
big stores for clients, says it has had "double-digit
increases" this year in existing stores. <PERSON>Robert Di Romualdo</PERSON>,
president of the company, says some of the gains may result
from a highly sophisticated computer-ordering system, but
espresso bars and <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> discounts on best sellers help.
   Even big chains like Waldenbooks are working harder to
please. The chain's Preferred Reader program attracted four
million members in the first year. People pay <MONEY>$10</MONEY> to join,
then receive an extra <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> discount at Waldenbooks stores,
plus a <MONEY>$5</MONEY> gift certificate for every <MONEY>$100</MONEY> they spend.
Waldenbooks is also reducing non-book merchandise throughout
the chain and broadening the titles it carries.
   Many publishers are in a grim mood, too, under pressure by
their owners to keep profits up despite the recession. Books
are coming out now for which hefty advances were paid a year
or two ago, and modest sales wouldn't cover costs. Revered
literary publisher <ORGANIZATION>North Point Press</ORGANIZATION> closed its doors this
year, and others may follow, the doom sayers predict.
   But some of the consequences are positive for consumers.
Meeting resistance to prices above <MONEY>$20</MONEY> for hardcover books,
some publishers are pricing selected titles aggressively low.
Bantam's best-selling hardcover at the moment is "Heir to the
Empire," a novel based on the "Star Wars" movies. The <MONEY>$15</MONEY>
cover price has definitely helped fuel sales, says a
spokesman. A Bantam medical thriller, "Extreme Measures," at
<MONEY>$14.95</MONEY>, sports a banner across the jacket declaring "Special
Low Price]" <ORGANIZATION>HarperCollins Publishers</ORGANIZATION> is selling its novel
"Vengeance" for <MONEY>$14.95</MONEY> until <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Signet</ORGANIZATION> division of <ORGANIZATION>Penguin USA</ORGANIZATION> is offering a
money-back guarantee on a paperback thriller called "Sea
Lion." The guarantee is touted on the back cover and inside
the book -- a spokesman says nobody has asked for money back
yet -- along with a sweepstakes.
   One positive development is the movement among publishers
to publish more creatively. "Things are as bad as everybody
says, but the good news is fewer books are being published
and publishers think harder about how they publish them,"
says literary agent <PERSON>Andrew Wylie</PERSON>.
   Two examples of novels by unknown authors that became
best-sellers because of clever jackets, advance reading
copies for store buyers and follow-up advertising: "The
Firm," a thriller from <PERSON>Doubleday</PERSON>, and "How to Make an
American Quilt," a first novel published by <ORGANIZATION>Villard</ORGANIZATION>. "Other
publishers keep saying to me that this is the kind of book
that gives them hope," says <PERSON>Stephen Rubin</PERSON>, president of
<ORGANIZATION>Doubleday</ORGANIZATION>, about "The Firm." "We didn't overpay to start, and
then we nurtured it."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880329-0058 </DOCNO>
<HL> Waldenbooks to Cut Some Book Prices In Stages in Test of New Selling Tactic </HL>
<AUTHOR> Cynthia Crossen (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> KM </CO>
<IN> RET PUB </IN>
<TEXT>
   In a departure from traditional book retailing practices, <LOCATION>Waldenbooks</LOCATION>, the country's largest bookseller, said it will gradually cut the prices on some books until the books are sold. 

   Unlike most retailers, booksellers enjoy the luxury of being able to return unsold merchandise for full credit. 
If a book isn't selling, there is no incentive for retailers to cut the price and accept a lower profit margin. 

   But some book sellers now believe the key to increasing retail sales is to encourage impulse buying. 
While best-sellers will bring customers into the bookstores, discounts may increase the number of books each customer buys. 

   In a six-month to 12-month test of that, <LOCATION>Waldenbooks</LOCATION>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>K mart Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, is initiating a program in which its retail stores will be able to order titles from a Waldenbooks catalog of some 100 to 125 "bargain books." 
The books, which may not be returned to the publishers, include some former bestsellers, like "Mammoth Hunters" by <PERSON>Jean Auel</PERSON>, "Eat to Succeed" by <PERSON>Robert Haas</PERSON> and "McMahon!" by <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bears</ORGANIZATION> quarterback <PERSON>Jim McMahon</PERSON>; some children's books, like "The Wind in the Willows" and "Peter Rabbit"; and some art books. 
Walden has agreed with its vendors to pay less for the books since they aren't returnable. 

   The books will be discounted in three steps. 
When a book has been in the store for 60 days, the price will be reduced. 
After another 30 days, the price will be reduced again. 
Depending on the original price of the book, there will be a third reduction 120 days after the book entered the store. 
As prices are reduced, the books will be moved from one area of the store to another. 

   "The chains have done many different kinds of discounting, but this is the most pronounced and formalized," said <PERSON>Stuart Applebaum</PERSON>, a senior vice president at <ORGANIZATION>Bantam Books Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 
"I'm sure it will be very controversial in the publishing industry." 

   <PERSON>Dara Tyson</PERSON>, senior manager for public relations and promotions at <LOCATION>Stamford</LOCATION>, Conn.-based Waldenbooks, said the chain considers the program "very revolutionary. 
It represents value and spontaneous buying," she added. 

   Although the discounting will lower profit margins, it could greatly increase volume. 
Furthermore, since the books may turn over faster, the stores' inventory could change more rapidly. 
"What <PERSON>Walden</PERSON> is doing is acting like real retailers," said <PERSON>Allan Lang</PERSON>, head of <ORGANIZATION>International Book Marketing Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> "Instead of returning books, it will mark them down, giving customers the idea that they're getting greater value." 

   But some book sellers aren't convinced that consumers buy books the way they buy other merchandise. 
"It's an interesting gimmick, but it's just that," said <PERSON>Lawrence Abramoff</PERSON>, owner of <ORGANIZATION>Tatnuck Bookseller &amp; Sons</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Worcester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. 
"I don't think the public can be fooled, and if they don't want to buy a book, they won't, regardless of the price. 
If you don't want <PERSON>Sidney Sheldon</PERSON> at <MONEY>$17.95</MONEY>, you probably don't want it at <MONEY>$7.95</MONEY> either. 
You'd have to make it <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> before the price would make any difference. 
And if you're going into <PERSON>Walden</PERSON> for the new Iacocca book, you don't want the old Iacocca book." 

   <PERSON>William Rickman</PERSON>, vice president of book merchandising at <ORGANIZATION>Kroch's &amp; Brentano's</ORGANIZATION>, a regional chain based in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, said the best impulse books are specialty books that are too expensive for many readers but could be very attractive at slightly lower prices. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Rickman</PERSON> said even big discounts won't necessarily move "leftover or would-be" best-sellers. 
"On some books, once they've had a period of selling, they aren't sellable at any price," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890202-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-02-89 0716EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BestSellers     02-02 0293</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Best Sellers,0299</SECOND>
<HEAD>Books On Physics And Spies Lead Times' Top-Sellers List For 1988</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The best-selling hardcover book in the nation
last year was ``Cardinal of the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION>,'' a spy novel by <PERSON>Tom
Clancy</PERSON>, a newspaper survey shows.
   The book, about the race by a member of the <ORGANIZATION>CIA</ORGANIZATION> to rescue an
American mole in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, was published in <DATE>July</DATE> and has
1,277,611 copies in print, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> said in today's
editions.
   Leading the nonfiction hardcover list was ``A Brief History of
Time,'' by <PERSON>Stephen W. Hawking</PERSON>, in which the author reviews efforts
to create a unified theory of quantum mechanics and general
relativity. Published in <DATE>April</DATE>, it has 825,000 copies in print.
   <PERSON>Scott Turow</PERSON>'s big-city murder tale, ``Presumed Innocent,'' was
<DATE>1988</DATE>'s best-selling paperback novel, the <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The top-selling nonfiction paperback was ``Love, Medicine &amp;
Miracles'' by <PERSON>Bernie S. Siegel</PERSON>, about the importance of the
patient's mind and emotions in the treatment of serious illness.
   The leader in the hardcover advice and miscellaneous category was
``The 8-Week Cholesterol Cure'' by <PERSON>Robert E. Kowalski</PERSON> _ which has
been on the Times' best-seller list for 82 weeks.
   <PERSON>Bill Watterson</PERSON>, creator of the <PERSON>Calvin</PERSON> and Hobbes cartoon
characters, dominated the paperback advice and miscellaneous
category, with three of his books occupying the top five slots. The
leader was his ``Something Under the Bed Is Drooling.''
   The survey was based on computer-processed sales figures from
3,000 bookstores and from representative wholesalers with more than
28,000 other retail outlets, including variety stores and
supermarkets. The figures are statistically adjusted to represent
sales in all such outlets across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. Although several
of the books were published before last year, the sales figures used
were for <DATE>1988</DATE> only.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890217-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-17-89 1346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-US-Rushdie 2ndLd-Writethru a0558 02-17 0942</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Rushdie, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0558,0964</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bookstores Report Brisk Sales Of Controversial Book</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf with statement read by company official today;
SUBS 22nd graf, `He said ...' to CORRECT to four lists, sted five.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL STIEG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's largest bookseller, <LOCATION>Waldenbooks</LOCATION>, ordered ``The
Satanic Verses'' off store shelves for fear that threats of violence
against the book's author and publisher might extend to its
employees.
   But the book was missing from many bookstore shelves today for
another reason: Sales were booming.
   ``This is not a freedom of speech issue _ the sole reason is the
protection of our employees,'' <PERSON>Bonnie Predd</PERSON>, executive vice
president of Waldenbooks, said after the chain ordered its copies
removed from display <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``Waldenbooks has fought long and hard against censorship, but
when it comes to the safety of Waldenbooks employees and our
customers, we must act responsibly in their interests,'' said a
statement read today by <ORGANIZATION>Grace Castricone of Waldenbooks</ORGANIZATION>' marketing
department.
   Telephone calls by <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> to Waldenbooks stores
nationwide <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> found that the <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON> novel _
which provoked the Iranian leader, <PERSON>Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, to
call for the author's death _ was available for sale on request in a
few stores, but was not on display.
   Employees answering the telephone at most stores said they had
been instructed by corporate headquarters to say ``No comment'' to
any questions about the book.
   A woman in the president's office at <LOCATION>Stamford</LOCATION>, Conn.-based
<PERSON>Waldenbooks</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> that the decision to pull the book from
public display was made <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> ``when our store managers
received some threats.''
   The woman said she wouldn't give her name, adding, ``Everybody
here is concerned about their safety.''
   In <LOCATION>Forestville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, a Waldenbooks store reported receiving a
telephone bomb threat from an unidentified man who wanted it to stop
selling the book, authorities said.
   The threat was made against the Waldenbooks at <ORGANIZATION>Landover Mall</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, said <PERSON>Prince George</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>County</LOCATION> police spokesman <PERSON>Chuck Cook</PERSON>.
The store received the call from a man with a foreign accent who
said a bomb would be detonated later that day if the store didn't
pull the book from its shelves. But store officials said they never
had the novel in stock.
   Other bookstores said they couldn't keep up with demand for ``The
Satanic Verses,'' which was selling poorly before the death threat.
   ``We had a display of it for three weeks and it just sat there,''
said <PERSON>Carolyn Fenton</PERSON>, manager of Bookstop in <LOCATION>Alamo Heights</LOCATION>, a suburb
of <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. ``I can't remember selling one off it. Then,
like that, they were gone.''
   <PERSON>Brian Weese</PERSON>, general manager of Encore Books, a <LOCATION>Harrisburg</LOCATION>,
Pa.-based chain of 47 stores in the <LOCATION>Middle Atlantic States</LOCATION>, said
several of his outlets have sold out their allotment.
   ``The fist-shaking is happening elsewhere, thank God,'' <PERSON>Weese</PERSON>
said. ``The ironic thing is that it's working against what <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>
and others want to accomplish. It's piqued everyone's interest and
sparked the sales, rather than forcing people to remove it and not
sell it.''
   Seven people died this week in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and northern <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> during
riotous protests against the book, which some Moslems say blasphemes
the prophet Mohammed. The book has been banned in several countries
with mostly Moslem populations.
   Today was to be the start of an 11-city promotional tour of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, but the book's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> publisher, <ORGANIZATION>Viking
Penguin Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, canceled the tour because of the threats. Rushdie, 41,
of <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION>, was reported to be in hiding.
   Viking Penguin executives were wearing bulletproof vests at the
office, the <ORGANIZATION>Daily News</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> reported today, citing
unidentified sources. And <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the company received its ninth
bomb threat since <DATE>December</DATE>. Workers were sent home and told to stay
there today, too.
   The novel, published in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>, has been available
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for several weeks.
   About 10,000 copies of the book were distributed to Waldenbooks
stores in 660 cities nationwide, <PERSON>Predd</PERSON> said. A memorandum authorized
by <PERSON>Harry Hoffman</PERSON>, president of the company, was sent to all the
stores ordering the book off the shelves, she said.
   Viking Penguin began a second printing of the book <DATE>last week</DATE>,
according to a company spokesman. The first run was 50,000 copies.
   ``We're printing to meet demand,'' the spokesman said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
He asked that his name not be used, citing the bomb threats at the
company's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> headquarters.
   He said the <MONEY>$19.95</MONEY> hardcover has hit four regional best-seller
lists _ in this week's <LOCATION>Chicago Tribune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>The Boston Globe</ORGANIZATION> and next
week's <LOCATION>San Francisco Chronicle</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>The Washington Post</ORGANIZATION>.
   A fast-selling book usually gets special treatment from retailers
_ window displays, a separate table or a prominent place on shelves.
Some booksellers said the uproar wouldn't deter them.
   ``No book should be banned from sale for the ideas it contains,''
said <PERSON>Michael Bills</PERSON>, manager of <ORGANIZATION>The Harvard Book Store</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. He said an unidentified group called him <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to urge that
an ``offensive'' <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON> display be removed from the shop window,
but he refused.
   Of five large midtown <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> bookstores, only a <ORGANIZATION>Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION>
outlet on <LOCATION>Fifth Avenue</LOCATION> had copies left <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``I don't have it in the window, but I have it prominently
displayed on both floors,'' said <PERSON>Alex Ostrowsky</PERSON>, the store's
assistant manager. ``There's some concern, but it's not stopping any
kind of merchandising.''
   <PERSON>Norma Carmona</PERSON>, manager of the Classic Book Shop a block away,
said she scrounged up 15 copies of the book <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> but
they were sold in hours.
   ``Everybody's talking about it, everyone wants to read it,'' she
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901126-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-26-90 1649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WhiteHouseBooks 1stLd-Writethru   11-26 0386</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-White House Books, 1st Ld-Wrttethru,a0647,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Millie's Sales Top Ron's</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: SUBS 4th graf: ``Millie's Book,'' to note Millie's publisher,
Morrow</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s autobiography is a
best-seller, but sales of the former president's memoir are lagging
those of ``Millie's Book,'' the dog's-eye-view of life inside the
<ORGANIZATION>Bush White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Millie's Book,'' ghostwritten by <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON>, was No. 3 on
this week's <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> non-fiction best-seller list, five
notches ahead of the weightier <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> book.
   The light-hearted canine narrative held down the No. 5 spot on
the <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Post's best-seller list, while the former
president's 748-page memoir came in at No. 7.
   ``Millie's Book'' was brought out in <DATE>September</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>William Morrow
&amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> and has been perched on the best-seller charts for nine
weeks. ``An American Life'' by <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was published just three
weeks ago.
   ``It's a bit of an unfair comparison,'' <PERSON>Jack McKeown</PERSON>, publisher
of <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION>'s trade division, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``We certainly
don't begrudge any success to `Millie's Book,' but they are
appealing to quite difference audiences.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION> is the publisher of the <MONEY>$24.95</MONEY> Reagan
autobiography.
   ``Millie's Book'' lionizes the president's English springer
spaniel, wrapping a droll narrative of <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> life and lore
around scores of full-color pictures of <PERSON>Millie</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Millie</PERSON> in the <LOCATION>Lincoln Bedroom</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Millie</PERSON> mingling with celebrities,
<PERSON>George</PERSON>, <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> and assorted grandchildren.
   All the royalties from the <MONEY>$17.95</MONEY> book are going to <PERSON>Barbara
Bush</PERSON>'s literacy foundation. <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> penned a similar book about
an earlier pet dog, <PERSON>C. Fred Bush</PERSON>, to raise money for charity when
her husband was vice president.
   Sales of the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> book are accelerating at the major book
chains and ``all the vital signs'' point to big sales of ``An
American Life'' as a Christmas gift book, said <PERSON>McKeown</PERSON>.
   But ``Millie's Book'' is winning the race at the bookstore
nearest the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, a Crown Books outlet on G Street, one
block away.
   ``Millie's the hottest item in the store,'' said assistant
manager <PERSON>Larry Hoffer</PERSON>. ``It's out the door. People come in and buy
10, 15 each - and then come back and buy more. It's a really cute
gift idea.''
   Some of the mega-purchases are by people with <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
connections who can get the books ``signed'' by the first lady and
<PERSON>Millie</PERSON>, via a paw-print stamp.
   The <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> book, which has received lackluster reviews, is
selling well at Crown, ``but not as fast as <PERSON>Nancy Reagan</PERSON> did,''
said <PERSON>Hoffer</PERSON>.
   The former first lady hit the best-seller lists last year by
lashing back at critics and ungrateful children in her life story,
``My Turn.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900430-0128
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900430-0128.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Marketing &amp; Media:
   B. Dalton Bookstore Chain Launches
   Program to Spur Sales of Serious Books
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
04/30/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B6C
</SO>
<IN>
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
SPECIALTY RETAILERS (OTS)
</IN>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- The giant bookstore chains get a lot of grief
about selling books like junk food, filling up the windows
with Stephen King and Danielle Steel.
   But the B. Dalton chain has a new program designed to get
shoppers to buy more of such books as "Skywater" by Melinda
Worth Popham, a serious novel written from the point of view
of a pack of coyotes. A book like this -- without sex, drugs
or detectives, written by an unknown author and published by
a tiny, independent press -- doesn't normally have a chance
to attract wide readership. Obscure novelists who sell 5,000
copies consider themselves lucky.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Starting tomorrow, browsers at more than 250 of the 800 <PERSON>B.
Dalton</PERSON> stores across the country will find "Skywater"
displayed in a special section and recommended in a brochure
along with 28 other novels by unknown or little-known
authors. "Discover Great New Writers" is the name of the
program, and new selections will be made and promoted every
two months. Half a dozen of the titles will be chosen by the
local store manager, with the rest of the books picked by the
chain's buyers in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, after reviewing publishers'
recommendations.
   "We're certainly conscious of our image in the
marketplace," says <PERSON>Leonard Riggio</PERSON>, chief executive officer
and principal owner of <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON>. "We do a great job with the
cookbooks and the how-tos and the big-name authors, but we
know there is frustration on the part of authors that don't
sell. We're going to give them a shot, to express gratitude
and maybe to help discover the future's best sellers. These
shopping-center stores sell to a middle-American client and
we're trying to broaden their reading."
   As the chains, particularly <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON> and Waldenbooks,
expanded rapidly through the '80s until they came to
represent some <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sales, publishers observed the
stores' power to make a book a best seller. Dire predictions
were uttered in publishing circles about the imminent
disappearance of serious books. Then, several years ago, a
series of very demanding fiction and non-fiction books became
surprise best sellers without the chains paying much
attention.
   It turned out that the recommendation of passionate,
book-loving, independent-bookstore owners across the country
had been the spark, and then the chains chimed in. One
example: "The Joy Luck Club," a first novel by unknown <PERSON>Amy
Tan</PERSON>, has sold more than 270,000 copies in hardcover since
<DATE>March 1989</DATE>.
   "The chains like <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON> are trying to pick up on what
has made some independents so successful," says <PERSON>Scott Walker</PERSON>,
founder and editorial director of <ORGANIZATION>Graywolf Press</ORGANIZATION>, which
published "Skywater," the coyote novel. "The chains are
starting to have a broader selection of titles and doing
things like more author signings and readings."
   For a small press like <PERSON>Graywolf</PERSON>, the Discover program is a
special blessing. "We don't have a big promotion budget --
almost nobody does for a first novel," says <PERSON>Mr. Walker</PERSON>. "For
some reason the word `literary' scares people, and we have to
start aggressively marketing to new audiences. I think this
program is one way to reach more readers with this type of
book."
   St. <PERSON>Paul</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Minn.-based Graywolf</ORGANIZATION> publishes only about 14
titles a year, and though its promotion budget for "Skywater"
is one of its biggest, it totals just <MONEY>$7,000</MONEY>. Nationwide.
   The other titles on <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON>'s first "Discover" list
aren't all by small presses, though several others are
represented. But even when the book is the product of a
powerhouse publisher or is a murder mystery that might
automatically grab genre readers, its author is a virtual
unknown or first novelist. Some movie fans may know <PERSON>Hanif
Kureishi</PERSON> as the writer of such cult British movies as "My
Beautiful Laundrette," but <PERSON>Mr. Kureishi</PERSON> is hardly a household
name. "The Buddha of <LOCATION>Suburbia</LOCATION>" is his first novel.
   ---
                 Selections From <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON>'s
                `Discover Great New Writers'
                                                                                                       

   Bedrock
   by <PERSON>Lisa Alther</PERSON>; Knopf
                                                                                                       

   The Book of Evidence
   by <PERSON>John Banville</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Scribner</ORGANIZATION>'s
                                                                                                       

   Buster's Midnight Cafe
   by <LOCATION>Sandra Dallas</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>
                                                                                                       

   Horse Latitudes
   by <PERSON>Robert Ferrigno</PERSON>; <PERSON>Morrow
                                                                                                       

   Walter Winchell</PERSON>
   by <PERSON>Michael Herr</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Knopf
                                                                                                       

   Buddha</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Suburbia</LOCATION>
   by <PERSON>Hanif Kureishi</PERSON>; Viking
                                                                                                       

   The Last World

                                                                                                       

   Clover
   by <PERSON>Dori Sanders</PERSON>; Algonquin Books
                                                                                                       

   Skywater
   by <PERSON>Melinda Worth Popham</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Graywolf Press</ORGANIZATION>
                                                                                                       

   Rush
   by <PERSON>Kim Wozencraft</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0297 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 1655EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Crown-RandomHouse     08-15 0290</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crown-Random House,0303</SECOND>
<HEAD>Random House To Buy Crown Publishing</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Random House Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> it has signed a
contract to acquire <ORGANIZATION>Crown Publishing Group</ORGANIZATION>, a book marketer and
publisher whose best-selling authors include <PERSON>Judith Krantz</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jean
Auel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dominick Dunne</PERSON>. The purchase price was not disclosed.
   Crown's biggest business is <ORGANIZATION>Publishers Central Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, a major
mail-order distributor of books and audio and visual materials; its
second biggest is <ORGANIZATION>Outlet Book Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a leading marketer of
promotional, remaindered and bargain books.
   <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>, which is owned by the <PERSON>Newhouse</PERSON> family's <ORGANIZATION>Advance
Publications</ORGANIZATION>, said the acquisition would open ``new opportunities
in the mail order and promotional book fields.''
   <PERSON>Nat Wartels</PERSON>, who co-founded Crown with <PERSON>Bob Simon</PERSON> in <DATE>1933</DATE>, will
remain as chairman of Crown. Simon died in <DATE>1966</DATE>. <PERSON>Alan Mirken</PERSON> will
remain as president of Crown while becoming vice chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Random
House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Wartels, who is 86, said in a news release: ``We thought long
and hard about selling Crown. But when the time came <DATE>three weeks
ago</DATE>, we spoke only to <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>.''
   He said he was impressed by the amount of support and
independence <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> has given to such previous acquisitions
as <PERSON>Alfred A. Knopf</PERSON>, Pantheon, Times Books, <ORGANIZATION>Villard</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ballantine</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Fawcett</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mirken</PERSON> said ``it was a very harmonious negotiation'' that was
done over three weeks without investment bankers.
   <PERSON>Judith Krantz</PERSON>'s new novel, ``Till We Meet Again,'' will be No. 3
on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> best-seller list <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, four weeks before
official publication, the news release said. <PERSON>Dominick Dunne</PERSON>'s
``People Like Us'' has been on the Times best-seller list 14 weeks.
<PERSON>Jean Auel</PERSON> wrote ``Clan of the Cave Bear'' and ``The Mammoth
Hunters.''
   The sale is expected to be completed by <DATE>Sept. 30</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022489-0093 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 22821 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 24, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 1; Column 2; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1708 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CHAIN POWER; 
</P>
<P>
THE FUROR OVER 'SATANIC VERSES' HAS REVIVED DEBATE ON BOOK PUBLISHING AND 
DISTRIBUTION. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAUL RICHTER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The decision last week by the nation's two biggest bookstore chains to pull 
<PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>'s "The Satanic Verses" from their shelves has brought a new 
outpouring of complaints about the chains' tremendous influence on how widely 
books are distributed and even which ones get published. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>B. Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> chain reversed its position not 
to sell the novel, and Waldenbooks has promised to resume selling the book from 
its stockroom when new copies arrive from the publisher. But all the same, many 
in the book world say the incident again demonstrates how much power the chains 
have acquired since their explosive growth began in the mid-1970s. When the 
chief executives of the two top chains yanked the book, they blocked sales in 
about 2,200 of the country's roughly 7,000 general-interest bookstores, critics 
say. 
</P>
<P>
The critics, who include writers, publishers and independent bookstore owners, 
say the chains' power is exerted quietly every day as they decide which books 
to carry. With the huge orders that they place with publishers, and with their 
enormous promotional budgets, the chains' decisions help assure that some works 
will be best sellers while others are consigned to obscurity. 
</P>
<P>
And as the chains offer their mass-market inventory at discount prices, they 
can also force out of business the independent stores that try to make their 
way selling a broader selection of less popular works, as well as blockbusters, 
the critics say. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
First Amendment Defenders 
</P>
<P>
The chains, of course, have staunch defenders in the book industry, who see 
merit in their concern about their employees' safety and praise the big firms 
for bringing low-price works to neighborhoods that have never had book outlets. 
</P>
<P>
Since the furor over "The Satanic Verses" began last week, booksellers have 
confronted questions of whether they have an obligation to bring books -- even 
controversial ones -- before the public. Some say that they do and that the 
chains have not lived up to that obligation, as the independents have. 
</P>
<P>
"The chains are brilliant at marketing, and they've changed the face of the 
bookselling industry," said <PERSON>Mona Mangan</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Writers 
Guild of America East</ORGANIZATION>. "But they don't have that commitment to getting books 
before the public. It's the little neighborhood bookstore that's out there 
today defending the First Amendment." 
</P>
<P>
The president of the booksellers' trade group that includes the Waldenbooks and 
<ORGANIZATION>B. Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> chains also said he found "some merit" in 
criticism of the chains' withdrawal of the book. 
</P>
<P>
"Unfortunately, this illustrates the Achilles' heel of centralizing the 
industry," said <PERSON>Edward Morrow</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>American Booksellers Assn.</ORGANIZATION> and 
owner of an independent store in <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt</LOCATION>. The chains' decisions meant 
that the book wouldn't be available at all in some communities, he noted. 
</P>
<P>
As the chains pulled the book, <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> said, independent bookstores continued to 
take orders for it, including several that had received bomb threats. "I've 
talked to a lot of independent stores in the last couple of days, and I haven't 
talked to one that said it didn't want to sell the book," <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Will Remain in Stockroom 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> and others in the book trade also saw the rationale behind the 
chains' decision. "They're extremely visible and extremely vulnerable because 
of their size and locations in so many shopping malls," <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> said. "It's not 
as easy to ensure everybody's safety at these little outlets as it is if you 
just own one store." 
</P>
<P>
"This is not an example of the venal corporate mentality taking over the book 
business," added <PERSON>William Kramer</PERSON>, president of the two-store <PERSON>Sidney Kramer</PERSON> Books 
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. "There are legitimate concerns at stake." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>B. Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> chain announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> that it 
would begin selling the book again in about 10 days, when it receives its next 
supply. The chain said it reversed the decision after a poll of employees found 
"overwhelming" support for selling the book. 
</P>
<P>
The Waldenbooks chain, which last week decided to take <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s novel off its 
shelves and sell it only on request, said it would resume selling the book when 
it comes back in stock. The chain also said it would continue "to use 
discretion in displaying the book." 
</P>
<P>
In an interview, a spokesman for Waldenbooks denied that the chains have 
excessive influence on the bookselling business. "We account for only <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of 
the books sold in this country," the spokesman said. "There are thousands of 
other places books can be sold." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> Market Share 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>B. Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> chain did not respond to repeated requests for 
comment, nor did Crown Books. 
</P>
<P>
Despite the comment of the Waldenbooks spokesman, the influence of the chains 
is enormous and growing, although at a slower rate than in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
If Waldenbooks accounts for only <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of all book sales, <LOCATION>Waldenbooks</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>B. 
Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> and Crown Books together account for nearly <PERCENT>45%</PERCENT> of 
the general-interest fiction and nonfiction works known as trade books, 
according to <PERSON>Jim Baker</PERSON>, editor of Publisher's Weekly. While exact figures are 
not available, the three leading chains' market share is believed to have risen 
from about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, he said. 
</P>
<P>
B. <ORGANIZATION>Dalton-Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION> has about 1,250 stores, while Waldenbooks, a unit 
of K mart, has about 1,200. Crown operates about 200 stores. 
</P>
<P>
The chains' influence has been felt in many ways by authors, publishers and 
competitors. 
</P>
<P>
They have brought a new management expertise to the business, with slick 
promotion and marketing techniques, computerized inventory control and other 
features that make traditional booksellers look stodgy and outdated. With the 
chains' backing, a book's sales can quickly climb into the hundreds of 
thousands. 
</P>
<P>
But without the chains, publishers and authors lose their access to huge chunks 
of the American audience. And this often makes them desperate to get their 
books onto the chains' shelves. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Blockbuster Syndrome 
</P>
<P>
Without a large chain order, "you have to consider whether you can raise the 
price for each copy of the book" to cover costs, says <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> publisher 
<PERSON>Jeremy P. Tarcher</PERSON>, who heads a firm that bears his name. Or "you may decide 
that, with such a small press run, the book just isn't economically viable" and 
decide not to publish. 
</P>
<P>
Writers complain that the rise of the chains has increased publishers' interest 
in the mass-market blockbuster at the expense of worthy books that might 
interest a smaller group. 
</P>
<P>
"The publishers were always interested in promoting the potential blockbuster 
at the expense of other books, but the chains have made it worse," said <PERSON>Alec 
Dubro</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>National Writers Union</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The chains' emphasis on the potential blockbuster often comes at the expense of 
so-called mid-list books, which are neither the best sellers ("front list") nor 
classics ("back list.") These can be the work of first-time or less well known 
authors. 
</P>
<P>
For the most efficient use of display space, the chains also typically keep 
books in inventory for shorter periods, to the dismay of writers and 
publishers. 
</P>
<P>
And the chains' presence can put pressure on small publishers, though most 
small publishers aim at narrow rather than mass markets. 
</P>
<P>
Small publishers are confronted with a dilemma when the chains offer them a 
large order. If they decline to accept the full order, they may risk losing 
future business from the chain; if they accept the full order, they may later 
face the crushing expense of a large number of returned copies. 
</P>
<P>
"A giant leaves large footprints," said publisher <PERSON>Tarcher</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Unfair Treatment Charged 
</P>
<P>
Independent bookstores have long complained about the difficulties of competing 
in a world where the chains have narrowed profit margins to razor-thin size. 
"You've got to love books to be an independent, because there's just not that 
much money in it," said <PERSON>Glenn Goldman</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Book Soup</ORGANIZATION>, a bookstore in 
<LOCATION>West Hollywood</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Last <DATE>December</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trade Commission</ORGANIZATION> sided with independent booksellers 
when it filed complaints against six of the largest trade publishers for 
allegedly selling hardback books at lower prices to chain stores than to 
independents. The agency also charged that the publishers treated the chains 
better in joint advertising programs and in providing promotional displays. The 
publishers have denied the charges. 
</P>
<P>
Book lovers have sometimes found that their sympathies lie with the independent 
bookstores in their competition with the chains. When the elegant, 75-year-old 
<ORGANIZATION>Scribner</ORGANIZATION>'s bookstore on <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s Fifth Avenue closed last <DATE>December</DATE>, some book 
lovers took it as another sign of the decline of the old-fashioned bookstore -- 
though the store had recently carried only a limited inventory. 
</P>
<P>
But the chains' admirers argue that the growth of the chains has brought stores 
to many neighborhoods that had no book outlets and reduced book prices to 
within the reach of many who could not afford them in the past. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, in the past several years, there has been a resurgence of the 
independent bookstores, though there are no firm statistics to describe the 
trend precisely. This is partially attributed to a greater interest in books 
among the aging baby boom generation. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, some industry officials, pointing to the slowing growth of the chains, 
believe that their importance may decline in the years ahead. 
</P>
<P>
"Big companies like <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>RCA</ORGANIZATION> got into the book business and got right out of 
it when they discovered it was no gold mine," said <PERSON>Jack Shoemaker</PERSON>, 
editor-in-chief of <ORGANIZATION>North Point Press</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. In the years ahead, 
"corporate <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> may get out and leave it entirely to the little guy." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
THE BIG GET BIGGER 
</P>
<P>
The three largest bookstore chains have steadily increased their market share 
in the period between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>. Percentages are based on total retail 
revenue (including trade, mass market and religious book sales) of <MONEY>$2.3 billion</MONEY> 
in <DATE>1980</DATE> and <MONEY>$3.8 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
1980 
</P>
<P>
Smaller chains and independents <PERCENT>73%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
B. Dalton/Barnes &amp; Noble <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
Waldenbooks <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
Crown Books <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>1987</DATE> 
</P>
<P>
Smaller chains and independents <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
B. Dalton/Barnes &amp; Noble <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
Waldenbooks <PERCENT>21%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
Crown Books <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> 
</P>
<P>
Source: <ORGANIZATION>BP</ORGANIZATION> Report 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Chains such as B. Dalton, above, offer their mass market inventory at a 
discount, putting pressure on smaller chains.; Photo, ; Chart, THE BIG GET 
BIGGER, Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SATANIC VERSES (BOOK); RUSHDIE, SALMAN; BOOKSTORES; PUBLISHING INDUSTRY; 
FRANCHISES; MARKETING; FREEDOM OF SPEECH; B DALTON CO; BARNES &amp; NOBLE 
BOOKSTORES INC; WALDENBOOKS INC; CROWN BOOKS CORP; CENSORSHIP 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910619-0095
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910619-0095.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Publishing:
   To Make Their Big Books Even Bigger,
   Firms Are Spending the Biggest Bucks
   ----
   By Meg Cox
</HL>
<DATE>
06/19/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   PCI TWX U.PSO
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
</MS>
<IN>
ADVERTISING, MARKETING, PUBLIC RELATIONS (ADV)
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDIA, PUBLISHING, BROADCASTING, ELECTRONIC PUBLISHING (MED)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Bigger Than Ever]
   More Than You Would Have Dreamed]
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Lavish Beyond Belief]
   For the nation's book publishers, that sums up the price
of hype these days. Complain though they might about
dwindling profit margins, companies are spending more than
ever on advertising and promotion budgets for major books.
   <ORGANIZATION>Warner Books</ORGANIZATION> has never spent as much to market a book as
the <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> earmarked to launch this <DATE>fall</DATE>'s sequel to "Gone
With The Wind." Viking Penguin will spend in excess of
<MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> promoting <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>'s next novel, even though he
is already one of the top-selling authors in publishing
history. <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> is pitching a thriller called
"Patriots" with ads on radio and cable television, plus a
money-back guarantee -- very rare for a hardcover book.
   And <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION> spent plenty attempting to have <PERSON>Mary
Higgins Clark</PERSON>'s latest thriller, "Loves Music, Loves to
Dance," make its first appearance on the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>'
best-seller list in the No. 1 spot. To that end, <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp;
Schuster</ORGANIZATION> mounted a major campaign that included store
displays, bus ads and network television commercials -- still
fairly rare for books -- on top of a 16-city author tour. And
it worked: "Loves Music" started on top and has been the
top-selling novel on the Times list for six weeks.
   Compared with budgets for movies and consumer products,
these amounts may seem insignificant. But by publishing
standards they are huge: Publishers say the usual marketing
budget for an anticipated best seller is more like <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY>,
while the average "midlist" book by a little-known author is
lucky to get a budget of <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>. Publishers aren't about to
routinely spend big money on expensive media like television;
and for most nonfiction, publishers say publicity is far more
effective than advertising.
   But there are several changes in the book business that
compel publishers to spend so lavishly in tight times for
some titles. For starters, competition is fiercer than ever:
The '80s created a number of merged megapublishers who paid
staggering advances for brand-name authors. As these books
come out, publishers can only make money if sales are
staggering, too. With the recession, sales have been sluggish
lately even for best sellers.
   Also adding pressure is the increasing computerization of
bookstores. Stores now have a much better grasp of what is
selling; what isn't gets shipped back more quickly. If
publishers wait for word-of-mouth to build sales gradually, a
book may be gone from stores by the time it's popular.
   "As publishers, we are all very conscious of the shortened
shelf life of hardcover books," says <PERSON>Jack McKeown</PERSON>, publisher
of trade, or general-interest, books for <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION>, a
unit of <ORGANIZATION>Paramount Communications Inc.</ORGANIZATION> "Computers have brought
many blessings to the bookselling industry, but booksellers
are tempted to drop quickly what doesn't move. It has become
extremely important to maximize sales in the first three,
four weeks."
   Publishers attempt to "leverage" their big authors,
ratcheting up the awareness and sales level with each new
book, which also often requires stepped-up ad spending. In
the case of "Loves Music," <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>'s eighth novel, <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp;
Schuster</ORGANIZATION> wanted to outsell the previous one, which took
several weeks to reach No. 1 and only stayed for two weeks,
says <PERSON>Mr. McKeown</PERSON>.
   "Our objective this time was to start her at No. 1, which
is very hard to do," says <PERSON>Mr. McKeown</PERSON>. "We feel there will be
a payoff for our advertising commitment down the road in
increased sales," he says. When a writer hits a certain level
of mass popularity, all of his or her earlier titles are
often re-released in paperback, and sales of the writer's
whole body of work rise across the board.
   <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION> had experimented with television ads on
<PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>'s previous novel and tracked the sales rise in the
four markets where the TV ads ran. This time, ads ran in
eight cities during morning talk shows for two weeks,
starting the day books landed in stores. The 15-second spot
dramatized the plot, about a serial killer who stalks his
victims through the personal ads: The commercial showed a
newspaper ad, a couple dancing and the woman's dead body.
"Meeting <PERSON>Mr. Right</PERSON> can be murder," says an announcer, a line
also featured in ads inside 500 buses traversing greater <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>.
   "Everything clicked," says <PERSON>Mr. McKeown</PERSON>. "On a week-to-week
comparison at the national chains, her sales are running <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT>
ahead of the previous book." He won't divulge the total cost
of the marketing and promotion campaign but says the
television time alone cost more than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>.
   Given his legions of passionate fans, <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>'s new
novel, "Needful Things" probably doesn't need any promotion
to start out as a No. 1 best seller, but his publisher plans
a massive campaign. "We've always spent a lot promoting
<PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>," says <PERSON>Michael Jacobs</PERSON>, president of <PERSON>Viking
Penguin</PERSON>, a unit of <ORGANIZATION>Pearson PLC.</ORGANIZATION> "Every time we do an
innovative ad campaign, we add new readers. We want to
increase the sales of hardcover copies with each title."
   Weeks before the <DATE>Sept. 30</DATE> publication date, bookstores
will be sent counter-top displays with cards that allow King
fans to reserve their copy of the book, a growing practice
with hot titles. Readers who pre-order will be sent a post
card when the books arrive, plus an as-yet-undetermined
souvenir.
   Later, large cardboard bins called "dumps" will be
distributed to 5,000 stores to display the book in bulk. For
the entire month of <DATE>October</DATE>, transit ads will run on buses
and subways in three cities. There will also be a billboard
-- another medium publishers are using more -- along <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>' <LOCATION>Sunset Boulevard</LOCATION>. Print advertising will include
teasers in newspapers in eight major cities, running three
days in a row just before the book goes on sale.
   With "Scarlett: the Sequel to <PERSON>Margaret Mitchell</PERSON>'s Gone
With the Wind," <ORGANIZATION>Warner Books</ORGANIZATION> says it must spend heavily to
announce the book because its contents are being tightly
guarded. "Since no one has read it and there's no
word-of-mouth, we have to take extra measures so that people
know it's available," says <PERSON>Nanscy Neiman</PERSON>, publisher of the
<ORGANIZATION>Time Warner Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit.
   The <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> budget is Warner Books' biggest ever for
advertising and promotion, but <ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION> reportedly paid <MONEY>$5
million</MONEY> just for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Canadian rights and plans an
ambitious initial run of 500,000 copies. The book was delayed
a year amid rumors of problems, but the publisher insists
"Scarlett" is a great read with a built-in audience. Still,
author <PERSON>Alexandra Ripley</PERSON>, despite three previous best-selling
paperback romances, is hardly a household name.
   To get the word out, <ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION> plans a 30-second television
commercial to run in major markets during talk shows, soap
operas and some prime-time shows as the book arrives in
stores in late <DATE>September</DATE>. <PERSON>Ms. Neiman</PERSON> will only say that the
spot will be "romantic and wonderful."
   In addition, <ORGANIZATION>Warner</ORGANIZATION> plans an extensive print-ad campaign
in popular magazines like People, with lots of newspaper ads,
especially in the South. As with the King book, readers will
be encouraged to pre-order the book in stores. And bookstores
will be sent red buttons for clerks to wear. The button's
slogan, playing off the last line of "Gone With the Wind,"
tells customers: "Tomorrow is here at last . . . ."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890224-0077 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-24-89 0655EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Verses-Waldenbooks     02-24 0521</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Verses-Waldenbooks,0537</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bookstore Chain Proclaims Position on `The Satanic Verses'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A bookstore chain that initially withdrew ``The Satanic Verses''
from its shelves for fear of terrorist attack went on the offensive
today, saying it will continue to sell the book despite ``many
threats of violence.''
   Waldenbooks, one of the nation's largest chains, ran
advertisements in nine newspapers defending its decision to stop
displaying the book, which has been condemned by Moslems worldwide.
   ``We will continue to sell the book when it comes back in stock
at the publisher,'' declared the ads, signed by <PERSON>Harry Hoffman</PERSON>,
continue to use discretion in displaying the book.''
   The advertisement is headlined ``A Statement of Fact in Troubled
Times.''
   Two other large book chains, <PERSON>B. Dalton</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnes &amp; Noble</ORGANIZATION>,
briefly stopped selling `The Satanic Verses'' after <PERSON>Ayatollah
Ruhollah Khomeini</PERSON>, the Iranian leader, called for the execution of
its author, British novelist <PERSON>Salman Rushdie</PERSON>, and those responsible
for its publication. Those stores resumed sales of the book
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after nationwide protests.
   Waldenbooks ordered the book removed from store shelves <DATE>last
Friday</DATE>, but said its managers could sell it from behind the counter.
   Today's advertisement cited ``the many threats of violence made
against our stores and our people.'' A Waldenbooks spokeswoman,
<PERSON>Tracy Urdan</PERSON>, said the chain received an estimated 60 bomb threats in
the first days after the death threat was issued.
   All three of the large chains were criticized by writers' groups
for engaging in a form of censorship, but <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> insisted that his
employees' safety was the real issue.
   In any case, <PERSON>Ms. Urdan</PERSON> said, ``The question is moot for the time
being because there are no more books in stock and there won't be
until <DATE>March 10</DATE>.''
   Viking Penguin, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> publisher of ``The Satanic Verses,'' is
reportedly printing 15,000 copies and has plans for another 50,000
within two weeks, The <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said an unidentified book wholesaler predicted the book
would sell 500,000 copies in hardcover, making it a huge best-seller.
   In <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, speakers at a rally <DATE>Thursday</DATE> urged people to buy the
book to register support for <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>.
   ``Let's not be stampeded by this kind of intellectual terrorism.
Let's vote with our wallets. Buy (<PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s) book,'' said <PERSON>Larry
Heinemann</PERSON>, winner of the <DATE>1987</DATE> National Book Award for his novel
``Paco's Story.''
   Speaking to more than 300 fellow writers and supporters at the
<ORGANIZATION>Chicago Public Library's Cultural Center</ORGANIZATION>, celebrated <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>
Sun-Times gossip columnist <PERSON>Irv Kupcinet</PERSON> said, ``If good people don't
stand up and act ... evil takes over.''
   A small group of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Moslems attended the rally, handing out
brochures condemning <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>'s book for insulting Islam in a manner
that ``scandalizes and maligns'' Muslims' beliefs.
   ``We don't agree with the death threat or the bounty,'' said
<PERSON>Mohammad Kaiseruddin</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Muslim Community
Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``But we are still very offended by passages in `The Satanic
Verses' that use profanity to describe the prophets <PERSON>Abraham</PERSON> and
Mohammed.''
   The Indian-born <PERSON>Rushdie</PERSON>, 4l, went into hiding in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> <DATE>last
week</DATE> after learning of <PERSON>Khomeini</PERSON>'s death threat.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900523-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-90 1559EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APArts:PublishingWoes Adv27   05-23 1188</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-AP Arts: Publishing Woes, Adv 27,1214</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv27</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, May 27, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>SEASON OF ANXIETY</HEAD>
<HEAD>Publishers Face a Time of Trauma</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-AP Arts: Polish Publisher, b0770</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICK HAMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ann Getty</PERSON>, wife of one of the world's richest
men, had a problem: She loved to read all day, but she also
believed in the Protestant work ethic.
   ``I come from nice Puritan stock, and I grew up believing that
you have to work all day,'' she explained.
   <PERSON>Lord Weidenfeld</PERSON>, one of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s most distinguished publishers,
also had a problem: He had been wanting to break into American
publishing for 20 years. But where would he get the money?
   It seemed <PERSON>Getty</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Weidenfeld</ORGANIZATION> had solved their problems in <DATE>1985</DATE>
when they teamed up to buy <ORGANIZATION>Grove Press</ORGANIZATION> and start <ORGANIZATION>Weidenfeld &amp;
Nicholson New York</ORGANIZATION>, a medium-size, independent publisher of quality
books.
   But <DATE>five years later Grove-Weidenfeld</DATE> was put up for auction,
like some paperback rights routinely are. As losses approached <MONEY>$15
million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Getty</ORGANIZATION>'s financial advisers reportedly told the voracious
reader her job was prohibitively expensive.
   The story of Grove-Weidenfeld is merely one trauma in what
<ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> executive <PERSON>Peter Osnos</PERSON> has described as ``a season of
anxiety in publishing.''
   The source of the anxiety is money _ big, corporate,
international money, and its transformation of what had been a
small industry run and staffed by people who cared as much about
literary quality as profit.
   Almost every famous name in publishing now has a famous business
name behind it: <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION> (owed by <ORGANIZATION>Paramount
Communications</ORGANIZATION>), <PERSON>Harper</PERSON> &amp; Row (<ORGANIZATION>Rupert Murdoch's News Corp.</ORGANIZATION>),
<ORGANIZATION>MacMillan Co.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Robert Maxwell Publications</ORGANIZATION>), Little <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>
(<ORGANIZATION>Time-Warner Inc.</ORGANIZATION>), <ORGANIZATION>William Morrow &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Hearst Corp.</ORGANIZATION>).
   Indeed, ``Corporate Takeover of the Word'' was the title of a
recent writers conference at <ORGANIZATION>New York University</ORGANIZATION>. ``I'm struck by
the level of concern, that 120 people would spend a sunny <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
indoors talking about the publishing industry,'' says <PERSON>Alec Dubro</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>National Writers Union</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``If an author is very concerned about the handling of a book,
about its content, he or she is being driven away from the major
publishers,'' he adds. ``The majors are perceived as being far more
homogenized and commercialized than they once were.''
   The complaint, which is difficult to document, runs like this:
Corporations want books that earn quick profits, create little
controversy and accord deferential treatment to any person, product
or cause that it or its subsidiaries hold dear.
   However limited their grasp of literature, corporate managers
can usually read a balance sheet, and it is to this _ not ideology
or censorship _ that much of the season's anxiety can be traced.
   <ORGANIZATION>Simon &amp; Schuster</ORGANIZATION> posted pre-tax losses of <MONEY>$140 million</MONEY>, and the
chairman of <DATE>Doubleday</DATE> was forced out because of financial problems
there. Harcourt <PERSON>Brace Jovanovich</PERSON> borrowed <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> to fend off a
takeover bid, raising questions if the company can meet its
interest payments, let alone invest in its future.
   The predictable corporate response to such conditions: Smaller
advances for authors; layoffs for employees; and, since only two
books in 10 make money, fewer new titles for the public. According
to preliminary figures compiled by Publishers Weekly, new title
output declined by about <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> last year.
   So far, the most notable casualty of the money crunch has been
Pantheon Books, a <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary long known for its
intellectually challenging books on a variety of subjects.
   In <DATE>February</DATE>, <PERSON>Andre Schiffrin</PERSON> resigned as Pantheon's managing
director rather than accept orders from <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> (itself a
subsidiary of the <PERSON>Newhouse</PERSON> family's <ORGANIZATION>Advance Publications</ORGANIZATION>) to
publish fewer books. At this, several authors defected, six senior
editors resigned and several hundred members of the literary
community demonstrated on the street outside <ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION>'s offices.
   Whatever the merits of its books, Pantheon had lost <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>
last year on sales of <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. The demonstrators said <ORGANIZATION>Random
House</ORGANIZATION> should absorb Pantheon's losses, but industry sources say
<ORGANIZATION>Random House</ORGANIZATION> made little or no profit in <DATE>1989</DATE>. Advance's <ORGANIZATION>S.I.
Newhouse</ORGANIZATION> insisted Pantheon pay its own way, saying, ``I do not like
charity cases.''
   Publishing's crisis has its roots in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, when the heart
of the retail book market moved from a relatively few, large city
bookstores to many more smaller ones in suburban shopping centers.
   By the late '70s, bookstore chains, such as Waldenbooks and <PERSON>B.
