<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072690-0114 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 252653 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 26, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
638 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
$550,000 STRAD VIOLIN STOLEN AT L.A. AIRPORT 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PENELOPE McMILLAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
What was to be a vacation quickly turned into "a nightmare" for <PERSON>Erich 
Gruenberg</PERSON>, when his rare Stradivarius violin, valued at <MONEY>$550,000</MONEY>, was stolen 
shortly after he arrived at <LOCATION>Los Angeles International Airport</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It is irreplaceable," the 65-year-old English concert violinist said 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. "It is my life." 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> police said the Stradivarius, along with a second <PERSON>Hirsch</PERSON> violin 
valued at <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY>, were stolen <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, shortly after <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> and 
his wife, Korshed, arrived from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> on a <ORGANIZATION>British Airways</ORGANIZATION> flight. 
</P>
<P>
"They were taken off a cart after he cleared customs," said Detective <PERSON>William 
Martin</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>LAPD</ORGANIZATION>'s specialist in art theft. 
</P>
<P>
The detective said he believes that the thieves probably did not know the 
simple, tan-colored oblong case contained violins. 
</P>
<P>
"Unless they had X-ray vision, they couldn't know what was inside," <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Police statistics show there have been an average 181 thefts a month at the 
airport so far this year, or about six a day. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON>, apparently yet another victim, kept reliving and 
retelling those few seconds when the theft occurred, as though he could not 
believe it happened. 
</P>
<P>
The tall, pale Londoner, who has been concertmaster of the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Symphony 
Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Philharmonic</ORGANIZATION> and is now an international concert 
soloist, is staying at the <LOCATION>Pacific Palisades</LOCATION> home of <PERSON>Harold Hirsch</PERSON>, an old 
friend and the maker of the second stolen violin. 
</P>
<P>
Seated on a sofa, <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> told a reporter that he was loading his luggage 
into <PERSON>Hirsch</PERSON>'s Cadillac. 
</P>
<P>
"I put two suitcases in the trunk." <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> said, and, as was his custom, 
went to take the violins inside the car with him. 
</P>
<P>
"The violin never goes in the trunk," <PERSON>Korshed Gruenberg</PERSON> said as she sat nearby, 
visibly upset and near tears. 
</P>
<P>
Gruenberg continued: "I turned around, I said to my wife, 'Darling, where's the 
violin?' I looked right and left, back and forth. 
</P>
<P>
"Then I thought, this is a bad dream." 
</P>
<P>
Instruments created by <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON>, the 17th- and 18th-Century violin 
maker, are considered unsurpassed in sound quality. Only about 650 still exist 
and they are often used by the world's leading players. 
</P>
<P>
"I think the people who took it were not aware of what they took," <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> 
said. "I hope they just left it somewhere and somebody will find it, and return 
it to me." 
</P>
<P>
Anyone with knowledge of the instruments' whereabouts should call the <ORGANIZATION>Los 
Angeles Police Department</ORGANIZATION>. The Austrian-born violinist added that he "would 
consider some kind of reward" for their return. The instruments are insured, he 
said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> said he acquired the Stradivarius from a violin dealer in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1974</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
For a serious musician, he said, throughout life "you try to find an instrument 
you bond with. You become like a team." 
</P>
<P>
"He just played a few strings of that and I said, 'Eric you don't give it 
back,' " <PERSON>Korshed Gruenberg</PERSON> said, recalling the day the couple first saw the 
Stradivarius. "I love it so much. It's like mine, too. I feel like someone has 
kidnaped my daughter." 
</P>
<P>
During their planned three-week vacation, <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> said, he had agreed to do a 
private recording of a concerto composed by a <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> professor later this week. 
Even though he may not have his precious instrument, or his second violin, 
<PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> said he will still meet the engagement. 
</P>
<P>
"Of course, you can play any violin," he said. "I'll borrow another violin from 
<PERSON>Mr. Hirsch</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
But it will make a difference, <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The difference would be difficult to explain. It's like defining quality," the 
violinist said, quietly. "What you pay for in a violin is an indefinable depth 
and color in sound. If you compare it to a mountain lake, the light shines on 
it like iridescence, and there is depth; endless depths. 
</P>
<P>
"With other instruments in five minutes, they can't give me anything new." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Violinist Erich Gruenberg displays case holding instruments similar to 
ones stolen at airport. LARRY DAVIS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MUSICAL INSTRUMENTS; ROBBERIES -- LOS ANGELES; LOS ANGELES INTERNATIONAL 
AIRPORT; MUSICIANS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072590-0146 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 252303 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 25, 1990, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 1; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
217 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LOCAL; 
</P>
<P>
$550,000 STRADIVARIUS VIOLIN STOLEN AT AIRPORT, POLICE SAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Service Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Stradivarius violin valued at <MONEY>$550,000</MONEY> was reported stolen from a baggage 
cart at <LOCATION>Los Angeles International Airport</LOCATION>, but police said the thief probably 
did not know what he was taking. 
</P>
<P>
The rare instrument, along with a second <PERSON>Hirsch</PERSON> violin valued at <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY>, was 
taken from concert violinist <PERSON>Erich Gruenberg</PERSON> after he arrived from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> via 
British Airways <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, police said <DATE>today</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"They were taken off a cart after he cleared customs," said Detective <PERSON>William 
Martin</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>LAPD</ORGANIZATION>'s specialist in art theft, who was assigned the case. 
<PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> apparently left the cart briefly after rolling it outside the 
terminal. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm just devastated," <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON>, a 65-year-old Austrian-born violinist who 
lives in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> of the loss of the Stradivarius. "It is 
irreplaceable." 
</P>
<P>
The case containing the instruments was rectangular, not shaped like a violin. 
<PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said the thief or thieves probably believed that they were stealing 
luggage. "Unless they had X-ray vision they couldn't know what was inside," he 
added. 
</P>
<P>
Police statistics show that there have been an average 181 thefts a month at 
the airport so far this year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON>, who had journeyed to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> with his wife, had served as 
concertmaster of the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Philharmonic</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900725-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-90 0828EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StolenStradivarius     07-25 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Stolen Stradivarius,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stradivarius Stolen from Violinist at Airport</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER BOWLES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A musician's Stradivarius violin, worth about
half a <MONEY>million dollars</MONEY>, was snatched from an airport baggage cart,
police said.
   <PERSON>Erich Gruenberg</PERSON>, 65, was carrying the violin, crafted in <DATE>1731</DATE>,
as he checked through customs after arriving from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> at <LOCATION>Los
Angeles International Airport</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, said city
police Sgt. <PERSON>Dave Nichols</PERSON>.
   The musician reported the violin disappeared from the baggage
cart as he was leaving the airport, <PERSON>Nichols</PERSON> said.
   The instrument was insured for about <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>. Also stolen were
a violin worth <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> and two bows worth <MONEY>$3,500</MONEY>.
   There were no arrests by early today, <PERSON>Nichols</PERSON> said.
   Thefts at the airport are a common occurrence, but the thief may
not have realized what it was he was plucking from the cart,
<PERSON>Nichols</PERSON> said.
   ``If he reads the paper he will, so I guess it won't take him
too long to figure it out,'' he said.
   Scholars estimate that <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON> made nearly 1,120 of
the prized violins bearing his name before his death in <DATE>1737</DATE>. Less
than a few hundred are believed to exist.
   <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON>'s whereabouts were not known. <PERSON>Nichols</PERSON> said he believed
that <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> came to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> on vacation and was staying with
friends.
   The Austrian-born performer and music teacher makes his home in
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and has played with the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION>. He now
appears as a soloist with leading orchestras in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and abroad.
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 4</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880331-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-88 0848EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-ViolinSale     03-31 0279</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Violin Sale,0288</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stradivarius Sold For Record $889,240</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BEN DOBBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Stradivarius violin fetched a world record
auction price for a musical instrument of <MONEY>$889,240</MONEY> at a <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s
sale today, the auctioneers said.
   The violin, made in <DATE>1709</DATE> by Italian craftsman <PERSON>Antonio
Stradivari</PERSON>, is named after the master English violinist <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON>.
Composer <PERSON>Vaughan Williams</PERSON> composed ``The Lark Ascending'' for <PERSON>Hall</PERSON>,
which she first performed in <DATE>1920</DATE>.
   An unidentified private South American buyer beat out two other
dealers bidding by telephone in a tense, two-minute auction.
   ``It was quite drawn out and tense and there was a round of
applause at the end,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s spokeswoman <PERSON>Beth McHattie</PERSON>.
   The <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON> had been expected to sell for around <MONEY>$846,000</MONEY>,
and bidding started at <MONEY>$376,000</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s said.
   The previous highest auction price for a Stradivarius was
<MONEY>$728,000</MONEY> for The Colossus, dated <DATE>1716</DATE>, which was sold at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s
auction house in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>last April</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of Records</ORGANIZATION> says the highest known price for a
Stradivarius was <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY>. But that was in a private sale of
Stradivarius' Alard violin by <PERSON>W. E. Hill</PERSON> and Sons to a Singaporean
on an unknown date.
   About 700 of 1,116 violins by Stradivarius have survived.
   <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON>, considered one of the finest violinists of her era,
died at age 72 in <DATE>1956</DATE>.
   She acquired the violin in <DATE>1905</DATE> and it was passed on to her
daughter when she died. When it was last auctioned by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in
<DATE>November 1968</DATE>, the violin sold for a then world record price of
<MONEY>$52,600</MONEY>.
   The violin was included in a day-long sale of violins, violas
and other stringed instruments.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880331-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-88 1325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Violin     03-31 0314</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Violin,0325</SECOND>
<HEAD>Stradivarius Breaks Auction Record for Musical Instrument</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BEN DOBBIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <DATE>1709</DATE> Stradivarius violin named in honor of
English concert musician <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON> was sold <DATE>Thursday</DATE> for <MONEY>$889,240</MONEY>,
the highest auction price ever paid for a musical instrument.
   The violin, acquired by <PERSON>Miss Hall</PERSON> in <DATE>1905</DATE>, was bought by an
unidentified South American dealer, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s reported. The dealer
beat out two other foreign rivals bidding by telephone in a tense,
two-minute auction.
   The previous highest auction price for a violin by Italian
craftsman <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON> was <MONEY>$728,000</MONEY>. ``The Colossus,'' dated
<DATE>1716</DATE>, was bought last year by Italian violinist <PERSON>Luigi Alberto
Bianchi</PERSON>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of Records</ORGANIZATION> says the highest known price for a
Stradivarius is <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY>, but that was in a private sale of
<PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON>'s ``Alard'' violin by British dealers <PERSON>W.E. Hill</PERSON> and Sons
to a <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION> dealer.
   Bidding started <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at <MONEY>$470,000</MONEY>, said <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s spokeswoman
<PERSON>Beth McHattie</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON>, considered one of the finest violinists of her era,
died at age 72 in <DATE>1956</DATE>. British composer <PERSON>Vaughan Williams</PERSON> dedicated
his ``The Lark Ascending'' to her, and she first performed it on
her Stradivarius in <DATE>1920</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> bequeathed the violin, previously known as the
``Viotti'' after <PERSON>Giovanni Battista Viotti</PERSON>, to her daughter.
   The owner who sold it on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was not identified.
   The instrument was last auctioned in <DATE>1968</DATE>, when it sold for
<MONEY>$52,600</MONEY> _ a record at the time.
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s auction ``was quite drawn out and tense and there was
a round of applause at the end,'' said <PERSON>Ms. McHattie</PERSON>. ``We're
absolutely delighted to be the record holders again.''
   The violin, kept in very good condition, had been expected to
fetch up to <MONEY>$846,000</MONEY>, she said. It has a distinctive tiger-stripe
wood grain pattern and is varnished in a rich orange-brown color.
   About 700 of 1,116 violins by <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON> have survived.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072690-0238 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 252972 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 26, 1990, Thursday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 8; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
136 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHORT TAKES; 
</P>
<P>
$500,000 VIOLIN STILL MISSING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times wire services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> Stradivarius violin owned by violinist <PERSON>Erich Gruenberg</PERSON> remains 
missing today after disappearing from an airport baggage cart at <LOCATION>Los Angeles 
International Airport</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"The violin is still outstanding and we have no suspects at this time," 
detective <PERSON>Jerry Sparks</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON>, 65, was carrying the violin, crafted in <DATE>1731</DATE>, as he checked through 
customs at <LOCATION>Los Angeles International Airport</LOCATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Gruenberg</PERSON> noticed that the violin was missing from the baggage cart 
"somewhere along the way" to ground transportation, the detective said. 
</P>
<P>
Thefts at the airport are common, but in this case the thief may not have 
realized the cart was carrying a Stradivarius. 
</P>
<P>
The instrument was insured for about <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>. Also stolen was a violin worth 
<MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> and two bows worth <MONEY>$3,500</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901121-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-21-90 1535EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-StradivariusRecord     11-21 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Stradivarius Record,0230</SECOND>
<HEAD>$1.76 Million for Violin Sets Auction Record</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 270-year-old Stradivarius violin named after the
descendants of composer <PERSON>Felix Mendelssohn</PERSON> sold <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for <MONEY>$1.76
million</MONEY>, the highest price paid at auction for a musical
instrument, <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s said.
   The violin, known as <ORGANIZATION>The Mendelssohn</ORGANIZATION>, was purchased by a private
buyer in the salesroom who asked not to be identified.
   ``It was owned by an American collector for the past 35 years
and he probably played it a bit,'' said <PERSON>William Hanham</PERSON>, the
auctioneers' spokesman.
   ``The fact that it had been off the market for a long time was a
considerable help to the price,'' he added. ``We believe that more
expensive instruments have been sold privately.''
   The previous owner, who remained anonymous, sold the violin to
aid the <ORGANIZATION>United Jewish Appeal-Federation</ORGANIZATION> of Jewish Philanthropies of
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Antonio <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON> made the violin in <LOCATION>Cremona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1720</DATE>
toward the end of his ``golden period'' when he produced his finest
instruments. The greatest ones are usually given personal names.
   The violin was named after its owners in the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, the
<PERSON>Mendelssohn</PERSON> family of <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION>.
   The previous musical instrument auction record was <MONEY>$1.22 million</MONEY>
for a Stradivarius cello in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   The same year, a <PERSON>Baron Heath</PERSON> violin made in <DATE>1743</DATE> by <PERSON>Giuseppe
Guarnieri</PERSON> fetched <MONEY>$1.12 million</MONEY> at auction.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900709-0067 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-90 1325EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--ViolinRansom     07-09 0186</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Violin Ransom,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crime Gang Seeks Ransom for Stradivarius</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Criminals holding a 273-year-old Stradivarius violin
stolen three years ago are seeking <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> in ransom, an
Italian newspaper reported <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The instrument, once owned by the last czar of <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nicholas
II</PERSON>, is believed held by an organized crime gang in <LOCATION>Turin</LOCATION>, according
to the <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION> newspaper <ORGANIZATION>Corriere della Sera</ORGANIZATION>.
   The instrument was stolen from French musician <PERSON>Pierre Annoyal</PERSON> in
<DATE>April 1987</DATE> when he was in <LOCATION>Turin</LOCATION> to teach a course at the <ORGANIZATION>European
Academy of Music</ORGANIZATION>, the newspaper said.
   It was reportedly in the trunk of his car, which was stolen when
he went into a shop to buy a pack of cigarettes.
   Police in <LOCATION>Turin</LOCATION> declined to discuss the case. The newspaper said
a photo of the violin was recently delivered to the police by an
individual known to have contacts with organized crime groups.
   Corriere della <PERSON>Sera</PERSON> said the ransom demand was made to the
owner. It did not say how it got the information.
   It did not give a value for the violin but decribed it as
``priceless.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06100044 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06100044 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  CRIME; ROBBERY; MUSIC; EQUIPMENT; HISTORY; PAST; USSR  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A Stradivarius violin that once belonged to Czar Nicholas II has been
recovered in the same town where it was stolen from a car in 1987, police said
Monday.;    The 274-year-old violin, which belongs to French musician Pierre
Amoyal, is valued at more than $2.6 million.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  STOLEN STRADIVARIUS RECOVERED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Carabinieri police said they arrested two men and two women, all Italians,
for investigation of receiving stolen property. They made the arrests <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
in <LOCATION>Saluzzo</LOCATION> after finding the violin in a car they had stopped near the train
station.;    Amoyal was expected to arrive in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> today to retrieve the
violin.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Turin, Italy  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910409  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  99  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 9, 1991
00100044,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900430-0073 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-90 1341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     04-30 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0766</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SANTA MONICA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>,
hospitalized three weeks with pneumonia, had a good <DATE>weekend</DATE> and has
started poring over the thousands of cards and letters from
well-wishers, her publicist said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``She's doing fine,'' spokeswoman <PERSON>Chen Sam</PERSON> said.
   Miss <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, 58, who was reported near death the previous
weekend, was moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to a private room after an 10-day stay
in intensive care at <ORGANIZATION>St. Johns Hospital and Health Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors gave no indication when <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON> could leave the
hospital and continue recuperating at her <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> home, <PERSON>Ms.
Sam</PERSON> said.
   The Oscar-winning star has started to read messages from
well-wishers.
   ``She's beginning to look at some of them, but the doctors are
concerned that she get a lot of rest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Sam</PERSON> said. ``There is an
unbelievable amount of interest. They (cards and letters) are
coming in the masses.''
   Last week, the hospital released a statement on <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON>'s
behalf thanking fans and friends for their cards and letters during
her hospitalization.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>,
hospitalized three weeks with pneumonia, had a good <DATE>weekend</DATE> and has
started poring over the thousands of cards and letters from
well-wishers, her publicist said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``She's doing fine,'' spokeswoman <PERSON>Chen Sam</PERSON> said.
   Miss <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, 58, who was reported near death the previous
weekend, was moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to a private room after an 10-day stay
in intensive care at <ORGANIZATION>St. Johns Hospital and Health Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors gave no indication when <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON> could leave the
hospital and continue recuperating at her <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> home, <PERSON>Ms.
Sam</PERSON> said.
   The Oscar-winning star has started to read messages from
well-wishers.
   ``She's beginning to look at some of them, but the doctors are
concerned that she get a lot of rest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Sam</PERSON> said. ``There is an
unbelievable amount of interest. They (cards and letters) are
coming in the masses.''
   Last week, the hospital released a statement on <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON>'s
behalf thanking fans and friends for their cards and letters during
her hospitalization.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>,
hospitalized three weeks with pneumonia, had a good <DATE>weekend</DATE> and has
started poring over the thousands of cards and letters from
well-wishers, her publicist said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``She's doing fine,'' spokeswoman <PERSON>Chen Sam</PERSON> said.
   Miss <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, 58, who was reported near death the previous
weekend, was moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to a private room after an 10-day stay
in intensive care at <ORGANIZATION>St. Johns Hospital and Health Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors gave no indication when <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON> could leave the
hospital and continue recuperating at her <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> home, <PERSON>Ms.
Sam</PERSON> said.
   The Oscar-winning star has started to read messages from
well-wishers.
   ``She's beginning to look at some of them, but the doctors are
concerned that she get a lot of rest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Sam</PERSON> said. ``There is an
unbelievable amount of interest. They (cards and letters) are
coming in the masses.''
   Last week, the hospital released a statement on <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON>'s
behalf thanking fans and friends for their cards and letters during
her hospitalization.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>,
hospitalized three weeks with pneumonia, had a good <DATE>weekend</DATE> and has
started poring over the thousands of cards and letters from
well-wishers, her publicist said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``She's doing fine,'' spokeswoman <PERSON>Chen Sam</PERSON> said.
   Miss <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, 58, who was reported near death the previous
weekend, was moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to a private room after an 10-day stay
in intensive care at <ORGANIZATION>St. Johns Hospital and Health Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors gave no indication when <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON> could leave the
hospital and continue recuperating at her <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> home, <PERSON>Ms.
Sam</PERSON> said.
   The Oscar-winning star has started to read messages from
well-wishers.
   ``She's beginning to look at some of them, but the doctors are
concerned that she get a lot of rest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Sam</PERSON> said. ``There is an
unbelievable amount of interest. They (cards and letters) are
coming in the masses.''
   Last week, the hospital released a statement on <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON>'s
behalf thanking fans and friends for their cards and letters during
her hospitalization.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actress <PERSON>Elizabeth Taylor</PERSON>,
hospitalized three weeks with pneumonia, had a good <DATE>weekend</DATE> and has
started poring over the thousands of cards and letters from
well-wishers, her publicist said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``She's doing fine,'' spokeswoman <PERSON>Chen Sam</PERSON> said.
   Miss <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>, 58, who was reported near death the previous
weekend, was moved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to a private room after an 10-day stay
in intensive care at <ORGANIZATION>St. Johns Hospital and Health Center</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors gave no indication when <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON> could leave the
hospital and continue recuperating at her <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> home, <PERSON>Ms.
Sam</PERSON> said.
   The Oscar-winning star has started to read messages from
well-wishers.
   ``She's beginning to look at some of them, but the doctors are
concerned that she get a lot of rest,'' <PERSON>Ms. Sam</PERSON> said. ``There is an
unbelievable amount of interest. They (cards and letters) are
coming in the masses.''
   Last week, the hospital released a statement on <PERSON>Miss Taylor</PERSON>'s
behalf thanking fans and friends for their cards and letters during
her hospitalization.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881124-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-24-88 0126EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-BRF--Britain-Violin     11-24 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Britain-Violin,0156</SECOND>
<HEAD>Violin Bought for World Record Price</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An 18th-century Italian violin made by <PERSON>Joseph
Guarneri</PERSON> del Gesu was sold in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> for more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>, an
auction record for any violin, the auctioneers <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s said.
   An unidentified buyer purchased the instrument for <MONEY>$1,059,344</MONEY>
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> from the estate of the late president of the <ORGANIZATION>Swallow
Airplane Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Sam Bloomfield</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan</LOCATION>.
   The violin is known as the <PERSON>Baron Heath</PERSON>, after an Italian
consul-general in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Baron John Benjamin Heath</PERSON>, who owned it
just over a century ago.
   It was made in <DATE>1743</DATE> by <PERSON>Guarneri</PERSON>, who worked in <LOCATION>Cremona</LOCATION> and is
considered by some violinists to be at least the equal of his more
famous fellow countryman, <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1737</DATE>.
   The previous violin auction record was 473,000 pounds (then
<MONEY>$889,000</MONEY>) for a <DATE>1709</DATE> Stradivarius known as the <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON>, sold in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 31</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA043090-0123 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 212043 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 30, 1990, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 8; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
168 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHORT TAKES; 
</P>
<P>
$2-MILLION VIOLINS RECOVERED 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Soviet ballerina <PERSON>Natalia Makarova</PERSON> and her husband have their 18th-Century 
violins back, including the Stradivarius that was snatched in a daring burglary 
at their house. 
</P>
<P>
Police on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> arrested <PERSON>Robert Fisher</PERSON>, 27, of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The recovered Stradivarius was worth more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>. The other violin, a 
Guarnerius, was valued at about <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>, police spokesman <PERSON>David Ambrose</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
The violins, jewelry and a pair of Chinese enameled statuettes were among items 
stolen <DATE>Saturday</DATE> from the home of <PERSON>Makarova</PERSON> and her husband, <PERSON>Edward Karkar</PERSON>. 
Makarova, 49, recently retired from the <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet Theatre</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The couple's <DATE>1986</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Mercedes-Benz</ORGANIZATION> was also stolen. Police said <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON> was 
arrested as he walked away from the car after parking it about a mile from the 
house. Most of the stolen items were in the car, <PERSON>Ambrose</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"Obviously, he didn't realize what he had taken. For that we can be thankful," 
said <PERSON>Karkar</PERSON>. The violins are his, and he said he practices on them regularly. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881109-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-88 1110EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RareViolin     11-09 0234</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Rare Violin,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Find Valuable Steiner in Raid</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HOLLY HILL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The violin was made in <DATE>1676</DATE> by Austrian
<PERSON>Jakob Steiner</PERSON>. It may be as valuable as a Stradivarius. And it was
left behind by burglars in a run-down apartment raided by police.
   Police believe the violin was stolen from the home of a family
that has owned it for five generations and values it at <MONEY>$800,000</MONEY>.
   Detective <PERSON>Tom Ryan</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he found the violin as he
searched an apartment in neighboring <LOCATION>Daytona Beach</LOCATION> for jewelry, guns
and other items taken in a string of house burglaries in the last
two weeks here and in adjoining <LOCATION>Ormond Beach</LOCATION>.
   Two men arrested last week tipped off police to the apartment,
which they said also had been used by two other men as a stash house
for stolen property. Ryan said he suspects the other men took the
violin in an <DATE>Oct. 20</DATE> burglary.
   Violins made by <PERSON>Steiner</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1683</DATE>, may be even rarer than
those of the Italian Antonio Stradivari because <PERSON>Steiner</PERSON> made fewer
of them, according to some collectors.
   According to library records, <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON> made about 650 violins.
   The series of about 18 burglaries netted the crooks between
<MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> in jewelry and guns, police said.
   The two arrested, <PERSON>Jason Lee Signore</PERSON>, 18, and <PERSON>Edward Revas</PERSON>, 20,
were picked up in an unrelated burglary, detectives said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880705-0079 </DOCNO>
<HL> Violin Makers Fret As Musicians Fiddle With Their A-Strings --- Demand for Modern Sounds From Ancient Instruments Arouses Fear of Damage </HL>
<AUTHOR> Philip Revzin (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> CREMONA, Italy  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    The 80 master violin makers of this North Italian town share a collective nightmare:
   A famous violinist is midway through a vigorous Beethoven cadenza on a priceless Stradivarius. 
The 300-year-old instrument -- its strings stretched taut to produce a strong, brilliant sound -- begins to groan, then cracks. 
Suddenly, it explodes. 

   "It could happen," warns violin maker <PERSON>Stefano Conia</PERSON> as he fondly strokes the belly of one of his glistening new violins in his crowded workshop. 

   So far, it apparently hasn't, at least like that. 
But that's irrelevant. 
This is where <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nicolo Amati</PERSON> and <PERSON>Giuseppi Guarneri</PERSON> del Gesu made their world-renowned stringed instruments in the 17th and 18th centuries. 
And that imposes a special burden on residents. 
So <PERSON>Mr. Conia</PERSON> worries. 
"What people are doing to these old violins is crazy," he says. 

   Calmly stated, what people are doing is tuning old violins according to new musical fashion. 
A more passionate view might be that musical treasures are being dangerously souped up to keep pace with unreasonable competitive demands. 

   The problem begins at A. 
In fact, that's pretty much the whole problem. 

   When the first Cremonese masters were making their violins, violas and cellos, everybody agreed that the pitch of A above middle C was around 420 cycles per second, or 420 hertz. 
Since A is the tuning note on which other notes -- up and down -- are based, first A is tuned in, then all strings are tightened accordingly. 
With A at 420 hertz, these instruments, which many say are unequaled for tone quality, sounded warm and rich among the few other strings in a small chamber orchestra. 

   But as orchestras and concert halls got bigger, musicians started to tune their instruments sharper, raising the pitch of A and thus all other notes. 
The more brilliant, more piercing sound could be heard above other players and delight listeners even at the top of the third balcony. 

   The more that violinists tightened their strings, the more pressure they put on their violin bodies. 
Singers had to reach for higher notes, putting more pressure on their bodies, too. 
By the time <PERSON>Giuseppi Verdi</PERSON> was writing his operas in the <DATE>mid-19th century</DATE>, A had sharpened to 435 hertz. 
That, <PERSON>Verdi</PERSON> thought, was enough for both man and machine. 
He got an international meeting in <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION> in <DATE>1885</DATE> to fix A at that level. 

   It didn't last. 
In <DATE>1939</DATE> another international meeting set A at 440 hertz, which is what comes from <PERSON>Mr. Conia</PERSON>'s tuning fork. 
He takes it off a peg on the wall and bings it on his chair. 
"Even 440 is too much, but okay, let's stop there," he says. 

   Few have. 
Many orchestras tune today to 443, 445, or even 450 hertz, stretching strings ever tighter. 
<PERSON>Sergio Renzi</PERSON>, director of <LOCATION>Cremona</LOCATION>'s violin-making school, says he has heard of tunings of 460 hertz. 

   That's just "murderous" for any violin, he says, and especially so for the 500 to 600 old Cremonese violins still being played (out of a couple of thousand produced by the masters). 
These instruments are usually on loan to stellar soloists from investors who buy them at auction or privately. 
Values range from six figures into the millions. 
A Stradivarius cello used by <ORGANIZATION>Yo Yo Ma</ORGANIZATION> went for <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY> last month. 

   The idea is that the instruments are kept healthy by use; stashed away unplayed, their vitality withers. 
But what kind of use? 
"The strings are now pulled so tight that they put enormous strain, driving the bridge {the small wood piece that holds up the strings} right down into the belly," <PERSON>Mr. Conia</PERSON> says, pressing on the midsection of his violin. 
He argues that even reinforcements and alterations made to most old Cremonese instruments over the years won't stand much more. 

   "New violins are built for this, but 300-year-old wood can't take it," he says. 

   So concerned are the Cremonese that at a recent conference to mark the school's <DATE>50th birthday</DATE> and the 250th anniversary of <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON>'s death, experts called for a return to 432 hertz as the standard A. 

   So far, reaction has been akin to the sound made by a violin with no strings at all. 
"There's no crisis, just a problem that has been around for 100 years," says <PERSON>Laurence Libin</PERSON>, curator of musical instruments at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"The Italians are always issuing grand statements but nobody pays much attention to them." 

   Says conductor <PERSON>Georg Solti</PERSON>: "I've never seen or heard of a violin breaking because of the pitch, but it is pretty high today and it's very bad for the singers -- they can't reach the high notes." 
He prefers 440, no higher. 
Some say that while there may not yet be cases of catastrophic breakage, they have seen gradual damage. 
Higher tuning is championed by orchestral players who want to stand out in the middle of the second violin section, but disapproved by some soloists who want to safeguard their investments. 

   <PERSON>Yehudi Menuhin</PERSON>, the violinist, conductor and teacher, plays a 1742 Guarneri known as "the Lord Wilson" and valued at <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY>. 
He favors a lower tuning but thinks the proposed pre-Verdi-era 432 hertz is unrealistic. 
"Our modern ears would consider that rather flat. 
The consumer wants his music brilliant and glossy." 

   That's too bad, too, Sir Yehudi feels. 
"Our ever more competitive age has not only pushed up inflation, it's pushed up the pitch. 
The Viennese are the guiltiest, the British the gentlest. 
A British oboist will often give you a nice, low A, so you can tune right down." 

   These days, as soon as he comes offstage, Sir Yehudi loosens his violin's A and E strings completely. 
But he has given up arguing with conductors about tuning. 
"It's hopeless. 
The most you can hope for is that the orchestra plays in tune at all." 

   Conductor Antonio de Almeida, though himself a proponent of lower tuning, maintains conductors can't do much anyway, given commercial considerations. 
"Music has become such a business, everybody says to hell with what comes naturally. 
If it sells, let's do it," he says. 
"Any move to a lower A would run into tremendous resistance. 
If a record company gets better compact-disk recordings with a higher A, that's what they'll go for." 

   That's fine with some people, too. 
"Life is hard enough. 
Brilliance is what it's all about," says <PERSON>Elmar Olivira</PERSON>, a prize-winning soloist who plays a <DATE>1692</DATE> Strad worth about <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY>. 
"Nobody can stand up in front of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia Orchestra</LOCATION> and hope to project and stand out at 435 hertz." 

   He says his violin is in "wonderful shape" despite centuries of playing, and he's comfortable at tunings between 442 and 447 hertz. 
"Violins don't exist in isolation, they exist to be played," he says. 

   In <LOCATION>Cremona</LOCATION>, however, the goal is brilliance without side effects. 
Most makers produce a couple of dozen violins a year, priced from <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>. 
<PERSON>Mr. Conia</PERSON>'s workshop, typically, is littered with bits of violin bodies, reeks of resinous varnish and hums to the sound of violin concertos played continuously over the stereo system. 
He painstakingly shapes thin strips of pine and maple, and applies 30 coats of varnish, as did <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON>. 

   And he continues to battle. 
He often plays in local churches and town halls. 
The churches he prefers are ones with old, slightly flat organs. 
"I can tune way, way down, and be nice to my violin," he says, giving it a pat. 
"And nobody can tell the difference." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900430-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-90 1007EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a PM-BRF--StuntPlaneCrash     04-30 0160</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Stunt Plane Crash,0164</SECOND>
<HEAD>2 Dead as Stunt Plane Crashes</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW HAVEN, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A stunt plane failed to come out of a
spin and crashed, killing its owner-pilot and a member of the
<ORGANIZATION>Polish Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, authorities said.
   <PERSON>Gordon Moore</PERSON>, 45, and <PERSON>Andrzey T. Rakoczyk</PERSON>, 50, died instantly
when <PERSON>Moore</PERSON>'s single-engine plane crashed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> near the <LOCATION>New
Haven-Macomb County Airport</LOCATION>, the county <ORGANIZATION>Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> and Rakoczyk hat about a mile from the burglary scene.
   Most of the stolen items were in the car, <PERSON>Ambrose</PERSON> said. The
violins, both in a single, felt-lined case, were among the
recovered loot displayed by police for reporters.
   ``Obviously, he didn't realize what he had taken. For that we
can be thankful,'' said <PERSON>Karkar</PERSON>, who is in the electronics business.
The violins are his, and he said he practices on them regularly.
   Stradivarius violins, made in the 17th and 18th centuries by the
Italian craftsman <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON> and his sons, are generally
considered the finest in the world. Guarnerius violins, made during
the same period by the <PERSON>Guarneri</PERSON> family, are also highly prized.
   Police said they also recovered an antique clock worth about
<MONEY>$2,500</MONEY>, a candelabra, some gold coins and a Persian carpet.
   <PERSON>Ambrose</PERSON> said the burglary took place when the occupants were at
home.
   ``We didn't set the burglar alarm before we went to bed,''
<PERSON>Karkar</PERSON> said. ``But we will from now on.''
   <PERSON>Makarova</PERSON>, 49, rose to fame at the <ORGANIZATION>Kirov Theater</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Leningrad</LOCATION> in
the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and <DATE>1960s</DATE> and fled the ballet company during a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
tour in <DATE>1970</DATE>. She said she wanted to broaden her career by
performing modern dances not staged in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   She returned to the Kirov in <DATE>February 1989</DATE>, performing a special
pas de deux with her partner, <PERSON>Alexander Sombart</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880826-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-88 2007EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HomelessAuthor     08-26 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Homeless Author,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Homeless Author Is Offered Shelter by Widow of Violin Thief</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROLYN LUMSDEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SPRINGFIELD, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A best-selling author whose hard luck
has forced him to live out of his van was offered shelter by the
widow of a man who harbored a famous stolen violin for almost 50
years.
   <PERSON>Marcelle Hall</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Bethel</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> she tracked down
<PERSON>Charles Webb</PERSON>, author of ``The Graduate,'' and his ex-wife wife at a
western <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> motel <DATE>earlier this week</DATE> and offered to take
them in after reading of their plight.
   ``I jumped right to the phone as if some power was leading me,''
<PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> said in a telephone interview. ``I saw their picture and
I thought, `They probably do the same things I do, give it all
away, and sometimes you get shafted.'''
   She said she hoped <PERSON>Webb</PERSON> would write a book about the stolen
violin and how she came to be married to the man who held it for a
half-century.
   But <PERSON>Webb</PERSON>'s ex-wife, who uses only the name Fred and who
continues to live with him, said <PERSON>Webb</PERSON> might not be able to write
such a book.
   ``The only problem is that <PERSON>Charles</PERSON> doesn't know if he can write
the story about the violin. He hasn't written anything factual,''
she said.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> gained national attention last year when she said her
second husband, <PERSON>Julian Altman</PERSON>, confessed before he died in <DATE>Aug. 15,
1985</DATE>, that his violin was a stolen Stradivarius he had bought for
<MONEY>$100</MONEY> from the man who had stolen it. The violin was stolen at <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Carnegie Hall</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1936</DATE> from <PERSON>Bronislaw Huberman</PERSON>, an
internationally known violinist who died in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
   The violin was authenticated for its insurer, <PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON>'s of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>,
which had paid <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to <PERSON>Huberman</PERSON>. Last year, <LOCATION>Lloyd</LOCATION>'s insured it
for <MONEY>$800,000</MONEY> and reportedly intended to sell it, and <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> said
<PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON>'s was going to pay her a reward.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> said she met <PERSON>Altman</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> in <DATE>1968</DATE> and they
married in <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> in <DATE>March 1985</DATE>, two days before he was
sentenced to two years in jail for sexually molesting one of her
granddaughters.
   She said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that she had married him to regain control of
her financial holdings. After serving four months of his sentence,
he was diagnosed with stomach cancer and moved to a hospital where
he died, <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Webb</PERSON>'s <DATE>1962</DATE> novel was made into the hit movie of the same name
starring <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON>. The movie evoked the discontent of a
generation fed up with materialism. He and Fred came to
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> in search of a publisher after living for a decade in
their van in southern <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In more prosperous days, the Webbs had given away two houses out
of a need, <PERSON>Webb</PERSON> said, to ``get free of things.''
   Fred said the couple would drive to <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to
meet <PERSON>Mrs. Hall</PERSON> and consider the offer. ``It sounds a little bit
gothic, but we might be able to handle something like that,'' she
said.
   Webb wrote four novels until <DATE>1978</DATE>, when he stopped writing.
   The Webbs divorced <DATE>eight years ago after 20 years</DATE> of marriage
because they believed the institution of marriage violated their
constitutional rights to freedom, <PERSON>Fred</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050190-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 212373 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 1, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 2; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
82 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MORNING REPORT: DANCE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GREG BRAXTON, Arts and entertainment reports from The Times, national and 
international news services and the nation's press. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Stolen Violins Recovered: <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> police recovered a Stradivarius and 
another violin, with a total value of more than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>, that were snatched 
in a daring burglary at the home of former Soviet ballerina <PERSON>Natalia Makarova</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Her husband, <PERSON>Edward Karkar</PERSON>, said the thief "obviously" was not aware of the 
violins' value. Police arrested <PERSON>Robert Fisher</PERSON>, 27, of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, in 
connection with the robbery. Makarova recently retired from the <ORGANIZATION>American Ballet 
Theatre</ORGANIZATION>. GREG <PERSON>BRAXTON</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870206-0075 </DOCNO>
<HL> Your Money Matters:
Old Instruments
Hit Sweet Notes
For Wise Buyers
---
By Julie Amparano
<DD> 02/06/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Charles Rudig</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s musical instrument department in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, scours flea markets, auctions and antique shops for harpsichords, oboes and the like -- for himself and for the company. 
Some of his finds cram his <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> apartment and a rented storage room. 

   Among them is a <PERSON>Cramer</PERSON> celesta, an unusual antique English keyboard instrument that produces bell-like tones. 
<PERSON>Mr. Rudig</PERSON> came across the celesta on an outing in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
"I just had to have it," he says. 
He paid <MONEY>$500</MONEY> for it. 
The instrument was recently appraised at <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY>. 

   For the right kind of investor, musical instruments offer the possibility of good returns -- and, perhaps, more tangible enjoyment than securities in a safe-deposit box. 
But investment advisers caution that the field isn't for those without expertise or substantial resources. 

   <PERSON>James D. Koster</PERSON>, an investment adviser in <LOCATION>Tucson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz</LOCATION>, says that while musical instruments can appreciate rapidly, they can be difficult investments. 
As with other collectibles, liquidity is a problem: If a need for cash arises, it may be difficult to find a buyer quickly for an antique instrument. 
And unlike a block of stock, "you can't sell a little piece of a violin. 
You have to sell the whole thing." 
Also, some instruments require special maintenance. 

   Investors shouldn't tie up more than <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT> of their assets in instruments, <PERSON>Mr. Koster</PERSON> says. 
But despite the limitations, he says, instruments offer a "very exciting investment with high appreciation." 

   Many appraisers, however, expect appreciation in the coming decade to fall short of the gains of the past 20 years. 
While the future of any collectible market is hard to predict, appraisers say they expect antique instruments generally to double in value over the next decade. 
At the start of the boom 20 years ago, prices of some instruments rose ten-fold in about three years. 
Since then, prices generally have doubled about every five years. 

   The spurt has been fueled by investors who earlier concentrated on paintings and sculpture, says <PERSON>Mr. Rudig</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>. 
These investors came to view antique instruments as works of art with musical value, he says. 
As with many other collectibles, the rapid inflation of the <DATE>1970s</DATE> boosted values. 
Changing musical tastes also have played a part: More and more orchestral musicians are seeking an antique sound they can only get from older instruments, he says. 

   Potential investors who aren't expert in the field should have instruments appraised before buying them, says <PERSON>Fred W. Oster</PERSON>, an official in <LOCATION>Christie</LOCATION>'s musical instrument department. 
A hairline crack in the wrong place, he says, can be enough to make an instrument virtually worthless. 

   One basic rule: An instrument that can't be played isn't worth much. 
A <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION> investor paid <MONEY>$500</MONEY> for a vintage flute, then discovered that it made only a honking sound. 
To date, he hasn't been offered more than <MONEY>$100</MONEY> for it. 

   In general, specialists say, the most lucrative instruments are antique strings -- violins, violas and cellos. 
Buying this kind of fine antique involves little risk, they say. 
Violins are considered the most valuable member of this group; their rate of appreciation is highest. 
A Stradivarius that sold 20 years ago for about <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> now commands more than <MONEY>$400,000</MONEY>. 

   More modest investments are available in antique woodwinds, like flutes, oboes and recorders. 
<PERSON>Sydney G. Rosenblatt</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> sold a Haynes flute last <DATE>December</DATE> for about <MONEY>$3,500</MONEY>. 
While he won't disclose his profit, he says the item would have brought about <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> a decade ago. 
But woodwinds involve more risk than string instruments, because their prices haven't been as long established. 

   <PERSON>Michael Sweeney</PERSON>, who owns a piano store in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, says American pianos built between the turn of the century and the Depression have become collectibles. 
<PERSON>Marilyn Gushner</PERSON>, a housewife in <LOCATION>Gladwyne</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, bought a <DATE>1924</DATE> Cunningham player piano four years ago for <MONEY>$3,600</MONEY> while it was "still in a million pieces." 
She recently had it appraised at <MONEY>$6,000</MONEY>. 

   The instruments of famous musicians, even if not antiques, can draw hefty prices. 
<PERSON>Efrem Kurtz</PERSON>, a conductor, reaped a windfall when he auctioned off a platinum flute that had belonged to one of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s greatest flutists, <PERSON>William Kincaid</PERSON>. 
Last <DATE>October</DATE>, at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, the flute brought <MONEY>$187,000</MONEY>, the highest price ever recorded for a woodwind instrument. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870430-0012 </DOCNO>
<HL> What's News --
World-Wide</HL>
<DD> 04/30/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<TEXT>
   A FUND-RAISER PLEADED guilty to an Iran-Contra charge and implicated North. 

   Conservative activist <PERSON>Carl</PERSON> "Spitz" <PERSON>Channell</PERSON> admitted to conspiring to defraud the government by funneling <MONEY>$2.1 million</MONEY> in tax-exempt donations to the Nicaraguan insurgents. 
He named fired <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> aide North as a participant in the conspiracy to arm the rebels. 
<PERSON>Channell</PERSON>, the first figure in the Iran-Contra affair to have criminal charges brought against him, also agreed to cooperate in independent counsel <PERSON>Walsh</PERSON>'s inquiry. 
The move comes less than a week before congressional panels are to open hearings on the affair. 

   Leaders of the congressional Iran-Contra panels said retired <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Maj. Gen. <PERSON>Secord</PERSON> would be the first public witness at hearings <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   ---
   The <ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> is investigating reports that a Japanese company and a Norwegian intermediary were involved in selling to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> sophisticated metal-working machines that could be used to make submarines harder to detect. 
Senate aides identified the firms as <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and arms-maker <ORGANIZATION>Kongsberg</ORGANIZATION>. 

   ---
   Authorities in <PERSON>Buenos Aires</PERSON> said a former army officer who had been a fugitive since leading a rebellion in <LOCATION>Cordoba</LOCATION> two weeks ago surrendered to federal officials. 
Former Maj. <PERSON>Ernesto Barreiro</PERSON>'s refusal to testify in a human-rights case led to the revolt at the <LOCATION>Cordoba</LOCATION> military camp, and sparked a similar uprising outside the capital. 

   ---
   A Nicaraguan rebel leader acknowledged that the insurgents killed an American, <PERSON>Benjamin Linder</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, but said the death was an accident of war. 
In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, while expressing regret over <PERSON>Linder</PERSON>'s death <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> said Americans working in <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> in support of the Sandinistas are "in harm's way." 

   ---
   The <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION> government warned the kidnappers of two West Germans in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION> that it would extradite a Lebanese man to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> unless the captives are released, the Hamburg-based Bild newspaper reported. 
The Lebanese, <PERSON>Mohammed Ali Hamadi</PERSON>, is wanted in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in connection with the <DATE>1985</DATE> hijacking of a <ORGANIZATION>TWA</ORGANIZATION> jetliner. 

   ---
In making his formal declaration in <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> emphasized his plans to create "vibrant and sustained economic growth that provides genuine opportunity for all Americans." 

   ---
   A <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> panel recommended that the new <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> be razed and another structure erected. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Intelligence Committee</ORGANIZATION> also suggested that <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> security offices be reorganized into a single unit and that foreign national employees be replaced by Americans. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> faulted a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee for subpoenaing allegedly withheld documents relating to the spy scandal involving former Marine guards at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. 
A spokesman said "nothing has been denied to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>." 

   ---
   <ORGANIZATION>PTL</ORGANIZATION> officials have begun examining the holdings of evangelist <PERSON>Jim Bakker</PERSON> to determine which of his assets may have been acquired with ministry funds, a spokesman for the Rev. <PERSON>Jerry Falwell</PERSON> said. 
The assets include two homes and luxury cars. 

   ---
   South African riot police surrounded a black union headquarters in <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION> while officers searched the building following the murders of four state railway workers. 
At least 11 people were detained after police entered the building, where members of the railway union were discussing their seven-week-old strike. 

   ---
   <ORGANIZATION>The Senate Rules</ORGANIZATION> panel approved a bill that would establish spending limits on primary and general election campaigns for <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> candidates. 
The limits would be tied to partial public financing for general elections funded by an income-tax check-off system, similar to that already used for presidential campaigns. 

   ---
   An Italian concert violinist bought a 271-year-old Stradivarius violin for the equivalent of about <MONEY>$726,000</MONEY>, the highest auction price ever paid for a musical instrument, <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house said. 
The violin, known as "the Colossus," is one of between 600 and 700 surviving violins made by <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Cremona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>. 

   ---
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Mulroney</PERSON> said <PERSON>Waldheim</PERSON> wouldn't be welcome in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, but a spokesman noted that <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> hasn't any plans to issue a formal ban against the Austrian president because of alleged Nazi war crimes. 
In <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, a dispute arose over whether Chancellor <PERSON>Vranitzky</PERSON> should cancel his visit to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> next month. 

   ---
   Israeli Foreign Minister <PERSON>Peres</PERSON> said several high-ranking Palestinians have "tired" of the <ORGANIZATION>PLO</ORGANIZATION> and would be willing to negotiate peace in the <LOCATION>Mideast</LOCATION>. 
In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, Israeli Premier <PERSON>Shamir</PERSON> said the question of an international forum on Mideast peace could prompt early elections, which he said might damage efforts to improve the economy. 

   ---
   Communist and Moslem rebels said they were joining forces on <LOCATION>Mindinao Island</LOCATION> to fight the Philippine government. 
The announcement came as authorities in <LOCATION>Manila</LOCATION> reported that four people were killed in two separate attacks. 
Police also said that the bodies of three Aquino campaign workers, missing since <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, had been found. 

   ---
   Pope <PERSON>John Paul II</PERSON> is scheduled to begin today a five-day trip to <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> that includes the beatification of a Jewish-born nun who was killed by the Nazis at <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION>. 
The nun's beatification is opposed by some Jews, who contend that the <ORGANIZATION>Vatican</ORGANIZATION> would be honoring someone who deserted Judaism for Catholicism. 

   ---
   Researchers in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> said that a common, non-surgical procedure for opening clogged or narrowed arteries leading to the heart has produced encouraging results. 
They found that a majority of 169 patients who underwent the balloon angioplasty procedure were symptom-free five-to-eight years after receiving the treatment. 

   ---
   A <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> air force jet was downed while chasing Afghan aircraft near the northwest border, <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>'s official news agency reported. 
It said the plane was hit by a missile as it followed a formation of intruding Afghan aircraft. 
The plane reportedly was the first lost by <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> in numerous cross-border raids by both sides. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06288192 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06288192 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PENINSULA; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE CONCERN now is not the eagle's survival, but whether it will be able to
soar like an eagle again. The golden eagle found suffering from shotgun wounds
in Woodside last month is expected to live.;   The original prognosis for the
bird discovered on Whiskey Hill Road in mid-September was not good. The male
bird, estimated to be 4 to 8 years old, has a broken, infected left wing. In
addition to blindness in one eye, the bird also suffered head injuries.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GOLDEN EAGLE'S FLIGHT IN DOUBT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Today on the Peninsula; Shorter version ran on page 2B of the Morning Final
edition  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Rescue workers at first were pessimistic about its chance of survival. But
the eagle pulled through, and the infection is under control. "He's much
perkier," said <PERSON>Valerie Baldwin</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Rescue Inc.</ORGANIZATION> worker who is taking
care of the raptor. The bird now weighs 9.4 pounds, two more than when it was
first brought in.;   Last week, veterinarian <PERSON>Ron May-Pumphrey</PERSON> operated on the
bird to reset a pin in its injured wing. Whether it ever will fly like an
eagle again remains in doubt. "It may be weeks, it may be months," <PERSON>Baldwin</PERSON>
said, "before we'll know for sure.";   Of course, should the eagle lose its
ability to fly, it will be kept in captivity for the rest of its life.;  
Meanwhile, there is no progress in the search for whoever shot the bird, said
Special Agent <PERSON>Ken McCloud</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>. The
up-to-<MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> reward has given investigators a few leads, <PERSON>McCloud</PERSON> said. But,
"nothing has been solid so far," he said.; SAY WHAT?: <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> President
<PERSON>Donald Kennedy</PERSON> spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Club</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>last Friday</DATE>. Afterward, he was
asked what he thought of the controversial and wacky <PERSON>Leland Stanford Jr</PERSON>.
Memorial Marching Band. "Do we have a band?" Kennedy asked, then he went on to
quote '60s folk singer <PERSON>Tom Lehrer</PERSON>, who wrote such songs as "Vatican Rag": "My
muse is not feathered by such inhibitions as taste."; FIDDLES WANTED: Mountain
View schools are looking for a few violins for their string-instrument
students. Higher enrollment and shrinking budgets have forced school officials
to look for alternative ways to come up with 25 violins to meet the demands of
youngsters who can't afford the instrument.;   The string-music program at
<ORGANIZATION>Graham Middle School</ORGANIZATION> and the four elementary schools now has more than 175
students, said <PERSON>Linda Snyder</PERSON>, a string-music teacher. "We have so much more
interest than we have had in the past," she said.;   Last year, the district
was able to purchase eight new violins. This year, none. It's not as though
the district is looking for a Stradivarius. Still, a "bottom of the line"
violin costs <MONEY>$255-250</MONEY> if bought in a bunch of five, <PERSON>Snyder</PERSON> said.;   If you
have an old violin that is no longer being used, the students can sure use it.
Donations are tax deductible. Call <ORGANIZATION>Graham Principal Gay Krause</ORGANIZATION> at (415)
965-9292.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  De Tran column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/Am  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911014  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  496  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 14, 1991
00288192,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880713-0127 </DOCNO>
<HL> Tax Report: A Special Summary and Forecast Of Federal and State Tax Developments </HL>
<AUTHOR> Scott R. Schmedel </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> TAXES GOVMT LABOR </CO>
<IN> FIN STK SCR BON REL CON BNK </IN>
<G> IRS JUS CNG </G>
<TEXT>
   FIDDLE RIDDLE: Is there life after 250 for a Stradivarius? 

   Musician <PERSON>Louis A. Browning</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, paid <MONEY>$130,000</MONEY> for a Stradivarius made in <DATE>1736</DATE>, <MONEY>$27,000</MONEY> for a 1779 Gabbrielli, and <MONEY>$24,000</MONEY> for a <DATE>1675</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Ruggeri</ORGANIZATION>. 
He sought to depreciate them over 12 years, to the tune of more than <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> a year in deductions. 
But the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> denied the deductions, challenging the 12-year-useful-life forecast as too short and arguing that the rare violins' "salvage" value would rise, not fall to zero. 
So <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> appealed to the <ORGANIZATION>Tax Court</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON>, backed by a dealer, said the Strad ("not a prime specimen") and its value would deteriorate with use. 
Yet the dealer had appraised it for insurance at <MONEY>$225,000</MONEY> five years after selling it to <PERSON>Browning</PERSON> and wouldn't speculate on the value after 12 years. 
<PERSON>Judge Hamblen</PERSON> found no evidence that the Strad would be worthless after 12 years or that its useful life would end at that point. 
Browning offered no direct evidence relating to the other two violins. 

   <PERSON>Browning</PERSON>'s claims were "arbitrary and unreasonable," the judge said in upholding the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>. 

   THIS <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> CHECK missed the trick: It bounced instead of rolling over. 

   You may withdraw cash temporarily from an individual retirement account and escape a tax or penalty, if you roll it all over into another <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> in 60 days. 
That's a rigid "if," as a chap we'll call Chip found. 
He took cash from an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> at one bank last <DATE>Aug. 14</DATE> and wrote a check on <DATE>Oct. 7</DATE> for a rollover <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> at another. 
He drew the check on yet a third bank, where a clerical error had restricted his account's credit. 

   Chip's check bounced. 
After clearing up the snafu, he wrote a new check on <DATE>Oct. 28</DATE> -- two weeks after the 60-day deadline -- that set up a new <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE>. 
The delay wasn't my fault, he told the <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>, so I should be allowed a rollover. 
Not so, says <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> private ruling 8824047: Tax law and regulations don't permit any waivers or extensions of the 60-day period. 
Chip's transaction fails to qualify as an <ORGANIZATION>IRA</ORGANIZATION> rollover. 

   EQUITY BEATS OUT consistency in handling disgorged profits, it appears. 

   Last week, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Judge Owen</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> denied requests by insider-trader <PERSON>Dennis Levine</PERSON> and conspirator <PERSON>Robert Wilkis</PERSON> to pay back taxes out of disgorged profits, not other resources. 
The profits are to be held in trust "for the benefit of defrauded investors," the judge ruled. 
Yet in <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Owen</PERSON> had granted the similar requests of ring members <ORGANIZATION>Ira B. Sokolow</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>David S. Brown</PERSON>. 
So lawyers for <PERSON>Levine</PERSON> and Wilkis denounced the unfavorable inconsistency. 

   What's going on? 
Owen's rulings don't address consistency directly, but suggest it's irrelevant. 
Tax claims may be paid at the court's "equitable discretion," he wrote in <DATE>October</DATE>; he considered the defendants' roles in the conspiracy, the amounts of their profits, and other factors. 
As to ringleader <PERSON>Levine</PERSON> and Wilkis, he wrote last week, the courts "have general equity powers to remedy violations of the securities laws and to fashion appropriate remedies." 

   The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION>, eager for its share, hasn't indicated whether it will appeal the latest ruling. 

   I WON'T PAY the <MONEY>$60</MONEY> filing fee or show I can't pay, <PERSON>Bruce Charles Frazier</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, told the <ORGANIZATION>Tax Court</ORGANIZATION> in appealing an <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> bill; he wanted a waiver for raising a constitutional issue. 
But for not paying, the court has dismissed his claims; it also upheld a civil fraud penalty. 

   EMPLOYERS now are liable for Social Security tax on unreported tip income uncovered in audits of employees. 
An employer can set up a reserve for that contingency; but doing it may look like an admission of incorrect tip reporting, warns <PERSON>David J. Silverman</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> tax adviser. 

   WAYS AND MEANS adds <ORGANIZATION>Clay Shaw</ORGANIZATION> (R., <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>) to fill a vacancy caused by the death of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee's ranking minority member, <PERSON>John Duncan</PERSON> (R., <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>). 
<PERSON>Bill Archer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> succeeded <PERSON>Duncan</PERSON> as the committee's ranking Republican member. 

   MORTGAGE SUBSIDIES would be targeted to more of the needy. 

   State and local authority to sell exempt bonds to finance low-interest mortgages for first-home buyers expires <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. 
Tax-bill writers propose to extend it through <DATE>1990</DATE> and to tighten eligibility in response to critics and suggestions from the <ORGANIZATION>General Accounting Office</ORGANIZATION>, which has questioned the efficacy of the subsidies. 
The aim is to get aid to the needy and exclude many families that can afford market-rate mortgages. 

   The bill doesn't go as far as the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> would. 
But it would lower the income ceiling for childless families, giving an advantage to parents. 
It would adjust income limits in areas where housing costs are very high or very low in relation to income. 
And as people tend to sell homes when their incomes rise, it would reward long-term possession: Generally, the government would recapture all or part of the subsidy from a homeowner who sold within 10 years. 

   Among other things, the <ORGANIZATION>GAO</ORGANIZATION> suggested limiting aid to parents over the age of 30. 

   BRIEFS: Just out are reporting requirements for the Social Security tax on employer-paid premiums for group term life insurance; see <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> Notice 88-82. . . . 
The <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> could reduce futile investigations of nonfiling businesses by eliminating duplicate identification numbers, publicizing the need to file quarterly employment-tax returns, and updating its records more accurately with the results of its investigations, the <ORGANIZATION>General Accounting Office</ORGANIZATION> says. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890520-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-89 0218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HolsterArtisan Bjt   05-20 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Holster Artisan, Bjt,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Idaho Craftsman Makes Holsters That Hold</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphoto BD1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL ERTELT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>IDAHO CITY, Idaho (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   While her husband was flying <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
planes during World War II, <PERSON>Bonnie Sparks</PERSON> bought a handicraft kit
for a leather purse to help pass lonely hours in their <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION> apartment.
   When <PERSON>Milt Sparks</PERSON> came home, he was intrigued by his wife's
hobby, which he developed a quarter-century later into the business
of making high-quality holsters sought by gun enthusiasts and
police around the world.
   <PERSON>Wiley Clapp</PERSON>, feature editor of Guns and Ammo magazine and owner
of several <PERSON>Milt Sparks Holsters</PERSON>, calls them ``the very, very
best,'' the first choice of many knowledgeable pistol owners.
   ``I'm sure in the days of Stradivarius there were other violin
makers,'' <PERSON>Clapp</PERSON> said. ``But the virtuoso used a Stradivarius.''
   The dirt-road outskirts of this former gold boom town provide a
natural location for <ORGANIZATION>Sparks</ORGANIZATION>' shop. The town's wooden sidewalks
would make an Old West gunslinger feel at home.
   But <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Wyatt Earps</ORGANIZATION> of yesteryear wouldn't stand a
chance in a modern-day showdown.
   ``I think that any modern pistolero could clean out the OK
Corral before they could get their guns out of their holsters,'' he
said.
   All holsters are not created equal, it seems.
   ``A holster can quite simply be a matter of living or dying,''
said <PERSON>Mike Waidelich</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Bakersfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, detective. ``When you
use it 40 hours a week, it needs to be very serviceable. It needs
to be right.''
   Three years ago, Waidelich convinced <LOCATION>Bakersfield</LOCATION>'s 235-member
police force to make the <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> standard equipment although it cost
about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> more than the holsters they were using.
   Before strapping on a <LOCATION>Sparks</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Waidelich</PERSON> once had his pistol fall
out of his holster while chasing a suspect. Another time he spent
15 minutes coaxing his weapon out of a poorly designed holster, he
said.
   A Sparks holster is crafted to hold the weapon snugly as an
officer runs or climbs over a fence, but relinquish it when it's
needed, <PERSON>Waidelich</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Tony Kanaley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON>' shop manager, estimates that <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of
the company's business is from police officers. Clients also
include such celebrities as <PERSON>Hank Williams Jr.</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kareem
Abdul-Jabbar</PERSON>.
   Sparks starts with a stiff piece of vegetable-tanned cowhide.
Kanaley grades and cuts all the leather, and an individual worker
is responsible for finishing the job.
   <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> said his motto is: ``Do it right.''
   ``Don't sacrifice your integrity to make money,'' he said. ``If
it's not right, if it doesn't save a man's life in a pinch, then
don't do it.''
   In the beginning, satisfaction in a job well done was <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON>'
sole reward. ``Now, I want to make a little money,'' the
72-year-old <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> said.
   Recently he has been able to leave many day-to-day duties to
<PERSON>Kanaley</PERSON> and his three-person crew, freeing him to travel,
participate in shooting competitions and promote his products.
   Sparks, a former charter pilot and flight instructor, worked
briefly during the late <DATE>1940s</DATE> for a <LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION> belt and holster maker,
but did not become serious about his craft until <DATE>1971</DATE> when a fellow
pilot asked him to make a holster.
   Impressed with the results, the friend convinced him there was a
market for well-made holsters.
   The following year <PERSON>Sparks</PERSON> quit his job as a pilot for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Bureau of Reclamation</ORGANIZATION> and in <DATE>1973</DATE> moved to <LOCATION>Idaho City</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06167017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06167017 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Conductor Roger Norrington, left, hit the mark conducting
violin soloist PHOTO: Thomas Zehetmair in an authentic interpretation.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MUSIC; SHOW; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  SAN FRANCISCO THE trial is over, and Antonio Salieri has been exonerated on
the charge of poisoning rival composer Wolfgang Mozart in 1791. A belated
decision, yes, but, as you know, the court dockets have been clogged.;    Once
that business was settled in a pre-concert "trial" at Davies Symphony Hall on
Thursday, one of the Mozart &amp; His Time festival events, the duly inspired San
Francisco Symphony gave one of its best-ever all-Mozart concerts.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ORDER IN THE VIOLIN SECTION
S.F. SYMPHONY, GUEST SOLOIST DO JUSTICE TO
MOZART  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Classical Music  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Leading the orchestra was guest conductor <PERSON>Roger Norrington</PERSON>; appearing as
guest soloist was an exceptional Austrian violinist, <PERSON>Thomas Zehetmair.</PERSON>;    The
30-ish <PERSON>Zehetmair</PERSON> is a newcomer who finds in <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>'s violin concertos
dimensions and shifting moods others only hint at. His playing is, by turns,
playful, profound, serious, seductive, ominous and ironic. His theatricality
-- so apt for a composer such as Mozart -- was grand in the popular Fifth
Concerto. His flair, together with the tones from his "<LOCATION>Falmouth</LOCATION>" Stradivarius,
make these two weeks of concerts (ending <DATE>June 22</DATE>) a must, even for those who
have overdosed on Mozart.;    His playing is also true to often neglected
18th-century conventions: He writes his own tasteful cadenzas or display solos
(avoiding chords), adds ornaments to <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>'s repeats and even plays along
with the first violins in the orchestral passages.;    As for conductor
<PERSON>Norrington</PERSON>, his "authentic" interpretations of pre-Chopin compositions in past
years have ranged from interesting to infuriating. But this time he hits the
mark squarely and surely.;    To achieve the desired effects, he has radically
altered the seating for the orchestra, flanking the central woodwinds with
brass, splitting the basses right and left, and placing the violins
antiphonally up front. It works; I could hear the basses for the first time in
ages.;    On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, he remarkably dramatized the little-heard Overture and
<ORGANIZATION>Ballet Music</ORGANIZATION> from the early opera "Idomeneo," though the long crescendo and
big slowdown in the finale struck me as <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> as reinterpreted in the age of
Beethoven.;    The spirited F Major Divertimento, K. 138, never before played
by the <ORGANIZATION>SFS</ORGANIZATION>, is a work with some brooding and engrossing dark corners, as
energized by Norrington.;    The "Haffner" Symphony (No. 35) also took on new
dimensions in this reading, at least in the absorbing outer movements.
Norrington led it without score or baton until the finale, when he suddenly
produced a baton from nowhere and led the way unerringly through the presto.; 
  As for the Salieri trial, it was a half-hour piece of amateurish theater
prior to the concert, with the ad-libbing <PERSON>Melvin Belli</PERSON> as bewigged judge. The
opposing attorneys -- <PERSON>Weyman Lundquist</PERSON> and <PERSON>William Newsom</PERSON> -- seemed not too
familiar with the script even though they had written it themselves. (<PERSON>Belli</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Lundquist</PERSON> are real-life attorneys; <ORGANIZATION>Newsom</ORGANIZATION> is an appellate-court judge.);  
 Professional actor <PERSON>Peter Donat</PERSON> made a debonair <ORGANIZATION>Salieri</ORGANIZATION>, denying all the
innuendo about his alleged poisoning of <ORGANIZATION>Mozart</ORGANIZATION>. Dr. <PERSON>Nancy Snyderman</PERSON> played
<PERSON>Mozart</PERSON>'s physician coyly and coolly. The audience acted as jury, freeing
<PERSON>Salieri</PERSON> on a technicality: the lack of any evidence.;    Are we going let
hardened composers like <PERSON>Salieri</PERSON> walk the streets? What about his real crime --
not poison but poison-pen attacks on his rival?;    The jury's still out on
that one.; <LOCATION>San Francisco Symphony</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Roger Norrington</PERSON> conducting, <PERSON>Thomas
Zehetmair</PERSON> violinist; Where: <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, Van Ness Avenue at <ORGANIZATION>Grove
Street</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>; When: <TIME>8:30 tonight</TIME> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at 3; Tickets: <MONEY>$21</MONEY>-<MONEY>$46</MONEY>;
Call: (415) 431-5400  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  PAUL HERTELENDY, Mercury News Music Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910615  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  594  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday June 15, 1991
00167017,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881219-0213 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-19-88 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s e BC-APN--Mutter'sMusic ADV01   12-19 1140</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Mutter's Music, ADV 01,1189</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv01</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Jan. 1</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo. ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When she won a national competition for young
musicians in her native <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> at age 7, the government allowed her
to drop out of regular school and be tutored at home so she could
spend more time practicing the violin. Today, at age 25, <PERSON>Anne-Sophie
Mutter</PERSON> is more than a child prodigy. She's an international star in
classical music.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When she won a national competition for young
musicians in her native <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> at age 7, the government allowed her
to drop out of regular school and be tutored at home so she could
spend more time practicing the violin. Today, at age 25, <PERSON>Anne-Sophie
Mutter</PERSON> is more than a child prodigy. She's an international star in
classical music.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By MARY CAMPBELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Newsfeatures Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   
   EDITOR'S NOTE _ When she won a national competition for young
musicians in her native <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> at age 7, the government allowed her
to drop out of regular school and be tutored at home so she could
spend more time practicing the violin. Today, at age 25, <PERSON>Anne-Sophie
Mutter</PERSON> is more than a child prodigy. She's an international star in
classical music.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112290-0160 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 311873 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 22, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 46; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
225 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
DAVID LLOYD KREEGER; INSURANCE EXECUTIVE, ARTS PATRON 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>David Lloyd Kreeger</PERSON>, 81, former chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Government Employees Insurance 
Co.</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Geico</ORGANIZATION>) and longtime patron of the arts. A <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> native who attended 
<ORGANIZATION>Rutgers University</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Harvard Law School</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> was a private attorney, with 
<ORGANIZATION>Geico</ORGANIZATION> as a client, when he formed a group to buy shares in the insurer in <DATE>1948</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1957</DATE>, <PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> gave up his law practice to become a <ORGANIZATION>Geico</ORGANIZATION> vice president. He 
was chairman and chief executive of the company from <DATE>1970</DATE> until his retirement 
in <DATE>1974</DATE>. <PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> served as president of the <ORGANIZATION>National Symphony Orchestra</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> <DATE>from 1970</DATE> to <DATE>1978</DATE> and gave his name to three buildings there 
financed with the help of his donations at area cultural institutions -- the 
<PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> Theater at Arena Stage, the <PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> Music Building at <ORGANIZATION>American 
University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Kreeger Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Corcoran Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION>. He served 
as president and chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Corcoran</ORGANIZATION> for 20 years. His art collection 
contained works of the most famous artists of the <DATE>19th</DATE> and 20th centuries, 
including <PERSON>Degas</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Van Gogh</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> and Kadinsky, but he cared most 
about music. <PERSON>Kreeger</PERSON> was an amateur violinist and owned a Stradivarius, which 
he sometimes played in concerts at his home in the company of such musical 
luminaries as <PERSON>Leonard Bernstein</PERSON>, violinist <PERSON>Isaac Stern</PERSON> and cellist <PERSON>Pablo 
Casals</PERSON>. In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> of cancer. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880623-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-23-88 0154EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Million-DollarCello     06-23 0307</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Million-Dollar Cello,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>World Record $1.2 Million Paid For Stradivari Cello</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An anonymous bidder paid <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY> for a cello
made by <PERSON>Antonio Stradivari</PERSON> about <DATE>1698</DATE> _ a world record auction
price for a musical instrument, the <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house said.
   The cello, known as the <PERSON>Cholmondeley</PERSON> after a previous owner, was
auctioned <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and the seller also asked to remain anonymous.
   The previous record for a musical instrument was <MONEY>$890,000</MONEY> paid
by an anonymous South American in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 31</DATE> for a violin
known as the <PERSON>Marie Hall</PERSON> that was also made by <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON>, an
Italian.
   The previous record for a cello was <MONEY>$393,000</MONEY> paid in <DATE>1984</DATE> by
<PERSON>Robert Cohen</PERSON>, an eminent <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> cellist, for a Stradivari
instrument known as the Bonjour.
   Sotheby's said several people were bidding for the <ORGANIZATION>Cholmondeley</ORGANIZATION>
``in a relaxed way.'' They said they were not surprised by the
price as they had expected the cello to sell for at least <MONEY>$1
million</MONEY>.
   They said the buyer might decide at some time to disclose his or
her identity.
   British cellist <PERSON>Julian Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, younger brother of composer
<PERSON>Andrew Lloyd Webber</PERSON>, spent <MONEY>$280,000</MONEY> in <DATE>1986</DATE> on a Stradivari cello
and was not immediately identified as the purchaser.
   ``The <PERSON>Cholmondeley</PERSON> (pronounced Chumley) is so well made that it
almost plays itself _ as if it had cruise control,'' said <PERSON>Adam
Watson</PERSON>, the cataloguer of <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s auction.
   The cello has a head by a different maker, Joannnes Florenus
Guidantus. The instrument is just over 29 inches long and rich
golden-brown in color.
   It belonged in the mid-19th century to the <ORGANIZATION>Marquess of
Cholmondeley</ORGANIZATION>. It later went to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and was played at
the <PERSON>Stradivari</PERSON> memorial concert in <DATE>1937</DATE> by <PERSON>Ralph Oxman</PERSON>.
   ``It is a well-known instrument and has been in the hands of
several collectors recently,'' said <PERSON>Watson</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910508-0012
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910508-0012.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Guitar-Pickers Are Making a Market
   ---
   Rock of Ages Spurs
   Old-Model Prices
   ----
   By Robert Tomsho
</HL>
<DATE>
05/08/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
TENNESSEE (TN)
</RE>
<LP>
   DALLAS -- Visitors to the Mandolin Brothers' booth at the
recent Greater Southwest Guitar Show found an eye-popping
price tag hanging from one instrument. "OK, so it's
$100,000," read a sign the Staten Island, N.Y., dealer had
placed nearby. "Go find another one."
   That would be hard to do. The rare 1958 Gibson "Flying V"
was one of only 81 shipped the year it was built. Amid a
recession that has driven down prices for Impressionist
paintings and folk art as well as many collectibles, vintage
guitars are hot -- especially those used by vintage rock 'n'
roll stars.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> auction last year, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>
sold a <DATE>1968</DATE> Fender Stratocaster used at <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>Jimi
Hendrix</LOCATION> for <MONEY>$334,000</MONEY> -- nearly four times the expected price.
And actor <PERSON>Gary Busey</PERSON>, who portrayed <ORGANIZATION>Buddy Holly</ORGANIZATION> in a movie,
recently paid <MONEY>$242,000</MONEY> at a <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction in this country
for a <DATE>1945</DATE> Gibson J-45 acoustic once owned by the late
rocker.
   In <DATE>1989</DATE>, an unidentified buyer even paid <MONEY>$1,300</MONEY> for a
fragment of a guitar smashed by rock guitarist <PERSON>Pete Townshend</PERSON>
of the Who. "The guitar market has gone berserk," says
<LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> guitar dealer <PERSON>George Gruhn</PERSON>, also a columnist for
Guitar Player magazine.
   Some industry publications have begun tracking prices
monthly, and major manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Guitar Corp.</ORGANIZATION>
of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fender Musical Instruments Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Brea</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, are building high-priced "reissues" of their own
classics. <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON>'s <DATE>1959</DATE> Les <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> reissues, named for the
legendary guitarist who originally designed the model, sell
for as much as <MONEY>$4,199</MONEY>, compared with about <MONEY>$1,699</MONEY> for a
similar new model.
   The original pre-1960 <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Les Paul</ORGANIZATION> models regularly
sell for more than <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>. And rare prewar Martin D-45
acoustics are going for as much as <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> -- nearly
quintuple the top price of just five years ago. Still, these
prices don't come near the cost of a Stradivarius; one of the
violins sold for <MONEY>$1.7 million</MONEY> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>last November</DATE>.
   The vintage guitar boom is being spurred on, in part, by
aging baby boomers seeking to recapture a piece of their
past. "We've got money to spend, and guitars, banjos and
fretted instruments are the instruments of our youth," says
<PERSON>Kerry Keane</PERSON>, a musical instrument appraiser for <ORGANIZATION>Skinner Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,
an auction house based in <LOCATION>Bolton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   As with most collecting fads, though, fortune hunters
should beware. Like cars, most used guitars still sell for
far less than they cost new, and dealers -- who pay top
dollar only for mint-condition guitars -- complain that many
would-be sellers expect any battered instruments they drag in
to be worth a small fortune.
   Moreover, with prices skyrocketing, guitar counterfeiters
are altering serial numbers and name plates, modifying
cheaper models, and even making pseudovintage instruments
from scratch. Some dealers now dismantle instruments before
buying to check for original paint, wiring and hardware.
"There is no such thing as a perfect forgery," says <ORGANIZATION>Mandolin
Brothers President Stanley Jay</ORGANIZATION>.
   As in so many other collecting areas, prices of vintage
guitars are being driven up by free-spending foreign
collectors and dealers. Many of them are Japanese, who prize
the American-made instruments for their tone, craftsmanship
and continuing status as the choice of most international
recording artists.
   Many <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> guitar dealers send their inventory lists
directly to foreign collectors and dealers, despite grumbling
from some musicians and dealers about the number of vintage
instruments leaving this country. While industry figures are
hard to come by in a largely cash-and-carry business, some
dealers say foreign buyers account for as much as <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of
their vintage sales.
   Overseas buyers have even hired <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> "brokers" to scour
pawnshops and newspaper want ads. "They're out in the
heartland looking for these guitars," says <PERSON>Mark Pollack</PERSON>, of
<LOCATION>Charley</LOCATION>'s Guitar Shop here.
   High-bidding Japanese buyers have become fixtures at the
growing number of guitar shows, which is why <PERSON>Mr. Pollack</PERSON> made
sure he had a Japanese-speaking employee in his booth at the
recent <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> show, the largest of its kind. Japanese
investors have been known to buy instruments by the truckload
for shipment back to their country, where even mass-produced
workhorses like 1970s-vintage Fender Stratocasters are
selling for as much as <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> -- nearly three times the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
price.
   "Mostly, it's the sound," says collector <PERSON>Mac Yasuda</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Newport Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, an executive with <ORGANIZATION>Tsumura &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
large Tokyo-based manufacturer of pharmaceuticals and bath
additives. With the help of a toll-free <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> telephone
number, <PERSON>Mr. Yasuda</PERSON> buys instruments for both himself and
company President <PERSON>Akira Tsumura</PERSON>, who recently opened a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>
museum to display his huge collection. <PERSON>Mr. Yasuda</PERSON>'s own
collection includes 50 <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> J-200 acoustic guitars, 15
vintage <ORGANIZATION>Gibson Les Pauls</ORGANIZATION>, and seven out of the 91 D-45
acoustics made by <ORGANIZATION>C.F. Martin Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Nazareth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, before
World War II.
   A variety of factors make some guitars worth more than
others. Rarities such as the prewar D-45s -- first made for
cowboy crooner Gene Autry -- and the elegant jazz guitars
handmade by the late <PERSON>John D'Angelico</PERSON> have long been prized
for their tone and craftsmanship.
   Collectors seek out certain early Les Paul models because
of the "flame" patterns in the curly maple wood used to make
them. And the <ORGANIZATION>Fender Stratocasters</ORGANIZATION>' mystique is due largely
to their use by rock stars such as <LOCATION>Jimi Hendrix</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Eric
Clapton</PERSON>.
   Meanwhile, a small but growing nostalgia market has
developed for some instruments that never had much snob
appeal. Dealers say baby boomers, apparently recalling the
first budget-priced instruments that their parents bought
them, are paying as much as <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> for Danelectro electric
guitars once sold in <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Roebuck &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> catalogs for <MONEY>$59</MONEY>
and up.
   <PERSON>Dominick Montuoro</PERSON>, a disabled <LOCATION>New Rochelle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
construction worker, began collecting them after playing one
that belonged to a friend's son. "I just fell in love with
it," says <PERSON>Mr. Montuoro</PERSON>, who now has 90 of the homely
instruments, which feature Masonite tops with pickups, a
piece of electronic hardware, made from modified lipstick
tubes.
   With prices for many vintage guitars rising and falling on
such quirky factors as which model certain rockers used on
their last tour, appraisers caution that vintage guitars are
not for investors seeking huge profits. "For the most part,
it's a slow, steady increase," says <PERSON>Mr. Keane</PERSON>, the instrument
appraiser.
   Moreover, veteran dealers like <PERSON>Mr. Gruhn</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> warn
that prices could plummet if economic troubles beset <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
