<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06352096 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06352096 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Associated Press; Canada; The federal government and the Inuit
people have tentatively settled a massive land claim that will create a new
terriroty in the Eastern Arctic, to be known as Nunavut.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CANADA; GOVERNMENT; SPACE; CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Canadian government and leaders of Eskimos in the central and eastern
Arctic reached agreement Monday on a massive land claim settlement that would
divide the Northwest Territories and create a sprawling new territory called
Nunavut whose size would exceed that of California and Alaska combined.;  
Under the agreement, the 17,000 Eskimos in the region would be granted
self-government rights over part of the new territory and would become the
biggest landowners in North America. The Eskimos also would retain hunting,
fishing and other rights elsewhere in Nunavut, a 772,000-square-mile expanse
partly administered by federal authorities that would represent a fifth of
Canada's total land mass.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CANADA TO CREATE ESKIMO TERRITORY
SETTLEMENT WILL SPLIT NORTHWEST TERRITORIES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The accord is subject to approval by the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and a
plebiscite among all 52,000 people living in the <LOCATION>Northwest Territories.</LOCATION>;  
Under the redrawing of the Canadian map, the Eskimos would take legal title to
136,000 square miles of disputed land stretching from the <LOCATION>Manitoba</LOCATION> border to
the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>. They also would receive nearly <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> over 14 years,
including interest payments.;   In return, the Eskimos would relinquish title
claims to about <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of their ancestral land, including areas believed
to contain lucrative oil and gas fields. But they would retain some governing
rights in that area.;   The region covered by the agreement consists mostly of
frozen tundra and wilderness islands of the Arctic archipelago. Eighty percent
of the population is Eskimo. The land claim settlement, the biggest in
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s history, was announced in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> by Native Affairs Minister <PERSON>Thomas
Siddon</PERSON> and leaders of the <ORGANIZATION>Tengavik Federation of Nunavut</ORGANIZATION>, the political
organization of Arctic Eskimos, also known as Inuit.;   The two sides agreed
to negotiate a formal political accord creating the territory of <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION> and
establishing the terms of its financing. Nunavut -- "Land of the People" in
the Inuit language -- would join the Yukon and the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION> as
the third of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s nominally self-governing territories without provincial
status.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Toronto  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911217  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  14A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  356  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday, December 17, 1991
00352096,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06353077 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06353077 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  CANADA; ETHNIC; GROUP; AMERICAN-INDIAN; PLANNING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The likely creation of a huge new Arctic territory for Eskimos marks a
watershed in Canada's efforts to address the many longstanding grievances of
its native peoples.;   But the prospect of the new realm has pitted Canada's
various aboriginal peoples against each other, as they argue over how best to
achieve their ultimate goal: self-government.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CANADA'S NATIVES DIVIDED ON PLAN FOR NEW TERRITORY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Stephen Hazell</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Arctic Resources
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, called the agreement a "shining star," and said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that it was
"one of the better achievements of the federal government.";   But <PERSON>A.J. Felix</PERSON>,
head of the <ORGANIZATION>Prince Albert Tribal Council</ORGANIZATION>, an Indian group, called it "a very
black day," and worried that "the government of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> could unilaterally deny
the rights of one group of people by claiming to recognize the rights of
another group of people." He said the <ORGANIZATION>Tribal Council</ORGANIZATION> planned to go to court
before <DATE>Christmas</DATE> to block the deal for the Eskimos.;   The prospect of new
lands for the Inuit, as Canadian Eskimos prefer to be called, loomed large
this week, when the Canadian government and an Inuit negotiating team
announced <DATE>Monday</DATE> that they had reached a huge land-claims settlement after 16
years of talks.;   If all goes as planned, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> will split its existing
<ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION> in two, and create an Inuit territory called <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION>,
which means "Our Land" in Inuktitut, the language of the eastern Arctic.;  
<LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION> would be enormous -- 772,000 square miles -- bigger than <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> combined, covering a fifth of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s total landmass. The 17,000
Inuit who live in its frozen, barren wastes would eventually govern
themselves.;   The settlement calls for the Inuit to own 136,000 square miles
of <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION> outright, and to extinguish their claims to the rest of the land,
while retaining fishing and hunting rights throughout the territory. They
would also receive nearly <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> over 14 years, including more than <MONEY>$10
million</MONEY> in training funds, so they will be able to administer their own
territorial government.;   But <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION> is not a done deal. "There's still
quite a lot of uncertainty" surrounding the accord, said <PERSON>Jim Bell</PERSON>, a writer
with the <ORGANIZATION>Nunatsiaq News</ORGANIZATION>, the newspaper in <LOCATION>Iqaluit</LOCATION>, a town of 3,200 at the
southern tip of <LOCATION>Baffin Island</LOCATION> that would probably become the territorial
capital if <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION> becomes a reality.;   A major stumbling point is the
objection of Indians in the Western Arctic to <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION>'s proposed boundaries.
The Indians and Inuit have hunted and trapped across overlapping regions of
<LOCATION>Northern Canada</LOCATION> for millenniums; Indians say some lands designated for <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION>
are theirs.;   The Inuit and the Indians will be able to vote on the
boundaries in a <LOCATION>Northwest Territories</LOCATION> plebiscite scheduled for <DATE>March 16</DATE>.
Observers say the vote could be close.;   "I think it will be a rough ride,
because the Dene and the Metis don't agree with the boundaries that are being
imposed," said <PERSON>Jack Anawak</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s only Eskimo member of <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>. The
Dene nation is made up of half a dozen Indian tribes in the Western Arctic and
sub-Arctic; <ORGANIZATION>Metis</ORGANIZATION> are peoples of mixed Indian and white lineage.;   "If the
plebiscite on the boundary fails," <PERSON>Bell</PERSON> said, "then the whole thing could fall
apart."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Toronto  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911218  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  26D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  527  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, December 18, 1991
00353077,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890724-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-24-89 2105EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Greenland-Eskimos     07-24 0311</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greenland-Eskimos,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Eskimos Take Part in Arctic Gathering for First Time</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COPENHAGEN, Denmark (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Arctic Eskimos from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> in the
west to <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION> in the east met in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> to discuss
common cultural and ecological problems.
   It was the first time a Soviet delegation attended a general
assembly of the <ORGANIZATION>Inuit Circumpolar Conference</ORGANIZATION>, a non-governmental
umbrella organization for Inuit, or Eskimos, from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   About 450 Inuit were expected take part in the west <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>
township of Sisimuit.
   A 10-man delegation, which is attending as an observer, says it
represents native Siberians known as Yuit.
   ``Even though President <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON>'s perestroika has
reached areas of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> where the 1,600 Yuit live, there
are many problems we would like to discuss with the <ORGANIZATION>ICC</ORGANIZATION>,''
delegation leader <PERSON>Nadesjda Utke</PERSON> said during a stopover in
<LOCATION>Copenhagen</LOCATION>.
   ``We want to exchange experiences in maintaining traditional
hunting and implements, educational materials and greater
participation by the local people in decision-making,'' she said.
   The fifth general assembly was being held under the motto ``A
Celebration of Inuit Unity,'' to mark the first Soviet
participation. It was opened by the current Conference President,
<PERSON>Mary Simon</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Topics for discussion during the five-day gathering included
environment and renewable resources, promotion of Inuit rights
internationally and transboundry pollution of the Arctic.
   A series of workshops were set up to study and report back on
such specialized topics as Arctic peace and security, whaling, the
``anti-harvesting'' conservation movement's impact on traditional
hunting, Inuit culture, land use and costal zone management.
   About 40,000 Inuit live in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, 28,000 in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and
11,000 in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. The Soviet Inuits comprise a small part of the
150,000 natives of the Siberian north.
   <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, the world's biggest island and a former colony of
<LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, this <DATE>summer</DATE> celebrates its tenth year with homerule-style
local government.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911217-0051
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911217-0051.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Canada to Give Natives
</HL>
<DATE>
12/17/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
REAL ESTATE INVESTMENTS (REA)
</IN>
<RE>
CANADA (CN)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
</RE>
<LP>
   OTTAWA -- The Canadian government agreed to recognize
native ownership of a vast tract of northern land extending
to the North Pole.
   The new jurisdiction, to be called Nunavut (Land of the
People), is the eastern region of what is now the Northwest
Territories.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The government said legislation will be introduced next
year to give the natives title to about 136,000 square miles
of land. The new region's 17,500 Inuit (Eskimos) account for
about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of its total population.
   The agreement would provide the Inuit with mineral rights
to about 14,000 square miles. The area is thought to have
considerable oil and natural gas and mineral potential.
   Inuit president <PERSON>Louis Pilakapsi</PERSON> called it a "fair
settlement."
   The Canadian government will maintain a regulatory role
over portions of the new territory. An Inuit board will be
established to ensure Inuit participation in regulating the
land. "We welcome industry to come in and do business with
us," an Inuit spokesman said.
   As part of the land claim settlement, the government also
agreed to give the area's inhabitants <MONEY>580 million Canadian
dollars</MONEY> (<MONEY>US$507.5 million</MONEY>) over 14 years. In return, the
Inuit agreed to give up their claims to any other land in the
<LOCATION>Northwest Territories</LOCATION>.
   Negotiations are to begin soon on what powers the new
government will have. A final agreement is expected to be
reached in <DATE>April</DATE>. Elections are to be held later.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890729-0024 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-89 0310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EskimoRights     07-29 0409</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Eskimo Rights,0420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Arctic Groups Plan Defense of Traditional Ways of Life</HEAD>
<DATELINE>COPENHAGEN, Denmark (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eskimos from four nations, guarding a
tradition of hunting and fur trading, criticized animal
conservationists for threatening the culture of Arctic people.
   <PERSON>Rosemarie Kuptana</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Inuit Circumpolar
Conference</ORGANIZATION>, urged delegates to force environmentalists and animal
conservationists ``to answer our arguments,'' the <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>
newspaper Information reported <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``Our opponents are much weeker when it is we who set the
agenda,'' <PERSON>Ms. Kuptana</PERSON>, a Canadian, told the 500 Inuit delegates at
a conference's meeting in <LOCATION>Sisimuit</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Greenland</LOCATION>.
   It was the first time a Soviet delegation attended a general
assembly of the conference, a non-governmental organization for
Inuit from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Anger is growing among Arctic natives toward conservationist
groups such as <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>, whose campaigns the Eskimos say have
damaged hunting and the fur trade.
   ``It never ceases to amaze me how people can react so strongly
against traditional hunting on the part of a little group of
indigenous people _ people who during thousands of years of hunting
never have threatened a single animal species _ while at the same
time industrialized society has polluted the planet to such a
degree that there is no way back,'' <PERSON>Ms. Kuptana</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Kirsten Sander</PERSON>, who attended the conference as an
observer, admitted that the group's campaign against seal skins in
recent years had done unintended harm to Inuit hunters.
   To counter future anti-harvesting campaigns, the conference
unveiled a far-reaching Inuit conservation strategy.
   This policy, largely the initiative of conference members from
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, embraces all aspects of environmental concern
in the Arctic.
   <PERSON>Peter Jull</PERSON>, a former Inuit adviser to the Canadian government,
said the document calls for detailed research on the environment
and wildlife, including all species that Inuits depend on for food
and clothing.
   He said the plan was partly ``an expression that the environment
is our interest and not just for the benefit of companies down
south somewhere.''
   The conference also compiled a guide of policy principles on
issues including nuclear power, education and self-government for
use at the regional and local levels.
   ``What we're basically saying is that we live in the Arctic and
we know what happens when you mess it up,'' <PERSON>Jull</PERSON> said.
   About 40,000 Inuit live in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, 28,000 in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and
11,000 in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. The Soviet Inuit comprise a small part of the
150,000 natives of the Siberian north.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890728-0124 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890728 </DD>
<AN> 890728-0124. </AN>
<HL> Enterprise:
@  Eskimo Artists Thrive With Modern Business Methods
@  ---
@  Experience of Inuit Indians May
@  Be Guide for Other Ethnic Groups
@  ----
@  By Udayan Gupta
<DD> 07/28/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> CANDA </CO>
<TEXT>
   When <PERSON>Simon Tookoome</PERSON> began selling his drawings in the late <DATE>1960s</DATE>, he was lucky to command <MONEY>$5</MONEY> or <MONEY>$10</MONEY> each. 
Today, the 55-year-old Canadian Eskimo routinely sells each drawing through his local cooperative at <ORGANIZATION>Baker Lake</ORGANIZATION>, in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s Arctic, for <MONEY>$300</MONEY> or more. 

   Many Canadian Eskimos (or Inuit, as they call themselves) once earned a living mainly by hunting and trapping. 
Today, they are thriving as artists, some earning in excess of <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> annually. 

   A whalebone drummer by <PERSON>Inuk David Atchealak</PERSON> fetched over <MONEY>$37,000</MONEY> at a recent art auction at <ORGANIZATION>Waddington</ORGANIZATION>'s in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, the highest price reportedly ever paid for an Inuit work. 
Corporations such as <ORGANIZATION>Toronto Dominion Bank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Rothman's Inc.</ORGANIZATION> boast large Inuit art collections. 
And <ORGANIZATION>Amway Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Japanese subsidiary recently put up <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> to sponsor an exhibit by Inuit artists that opened in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>June</DATE>. 

   The Inuit artists are prospering because they are using modern business methods to solve their core problem: the producing and marketing of art in the far-flung Arctic. 
They own and operate small co-op businesses that collect their work and sell it to "southern" dealers and buyers in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> and abroad. 

   As such, the Inuit experience may serve as a guide to other groups trying to profit from ethnic arts and crafts. 
Indeed, American Indian groups seem to have enjoyed their biggest commercial success when they went the co-op route. 
And the success stories have begun attracting investors, most notably big Japanese financial houses, including <ORGANIZATION>Daiwa Securities Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   It is the all-encompassing nature of the 1980s-style cooperatives that has made them effective. 
They don't just peddle art. 
They stockpile raw material for the artists for the cold winter months when the region is impassable. 
They collect key data on prices and market trends and act as auditors and bookkeepers. 
Regularly, they organize workshops to help artists with new design ideas and new media. 
And, in the beginning, by regulating production and the quality of prints, they also helped maintain a high level of prices. 

   But success also has hurt the Inuit co-ops. 
Many of the top artists they helped establish have defected, choosing to deal directly with galleries and potential buyers. 
"Why do I need to sell to the co-op when I can get a better deal from the south?" asks <PERSON>Bart Hanna</PERSON>, a Inuk sculptor from <LOCATION>Igloolik</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Some see so much commercial exploitation that the purity of the art form has been tarnished. 
Still others decry the growing layers of bureaucracy. 
Says <PERSON>Alma Houston</PERSON>, who helped start <LOCATION>Cape Dorset</LOCATION> -- one of the first co-ops -- on <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Baffin Island</LOCATION> in <DATE>1961</DATE>: "Some of them have gotten too pedestrian, they lack imagination." 
If the co-ops are going to successfully fend off competitors, the artists will have to once again be involved in the co-op and new marketing ideas will have to be found. 
If the co-ops want to continue as leaders in promoting and selling Inuit art, she says, "they will have to smarten up." 

   Still, "without the co-ops, Inuit art wouldn't be as well-known as it is today," says <PERSON>Gunther Abrahamson</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>, a retired government official who helped develop the first Arctic co-ops. 

   Nor, possibly, would there be thriving art industries in other native American cultures. 
Today, cooperative businesses owned and operated by artists are playing a pivotal role in marketing the art of tribal artists all across <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>. 

   "Cooperatives not only have facilitated the sale of works of art by native Americans, they also have created a forum where the traditions and styles of native American art can be handed down from generation to generation," says <PERSON>Halsey North</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> art-group consultant. 

   In <LOCATION>Cherokee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, for example, <ORGANIZATION>Qualla Arts &amp; Crafts Mutual Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, sells the work of nearly 300 <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Cherokee</ORGANIZATION> artists and craftsmen through a retail store and a mail-order catalog. 
And in addition to buying <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> of work from many artists, it also mails to each artist two dividend checks each year, amounting to about <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> of their total sales. 

   Qualla, which began operating in <DATE>1946</DATE>, earns most of its revenue from its store in <LOCATION>Cherokee</LOCATION>, selling items like arrowhead ash trays that cost <MONEY>$4</MONEY> and sculpture priced at <MONEY>$900</MONEY>. 
The items are also marketed through a mail-order catalog: 30,000 or so were mailed in the past three years. 
In addition, the co-op sells the art work at state fairs and exhibitions and represents artists in dealing with commercial buyers. 
For the <LOCATION>Cherokee</LOCATION>, most of whom prefer a rural, isolated existence, "the art couldn't have been sold without the co-op," <PERSON>George Holt</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>North Carolina Arts Council</ORGANIZATION> says. 

   In <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, artists' co-ops have successfully bridged the problem of distance and fragmented markets, adds <PERSON>Jean Flanagan Carlo</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Alaska Native Arts</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Fairbanks</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. 
Two or three times a year, the co-ops sweep through the state providing raw materials, such as stone and fabric, and buying work to sell to buyers in the cities. 
Says <PERSON>Ms. Carlo</PERSON>, "None of the artists have the resources to do this on their own." 
Nowhere did artists need co-ops more than in the Arctic. 
The Inuit live in scattered settlements, days of travel away from each other and far from their markets. 
And in the early days, there was no market to speak of. 
Says <PERSON>Mr. Tookoome</PERSON>: "I had to sell to anyone and take any price they would give me." 

   The promotion of Inuit handicrafts began when the Canadian Handicrafts Guild sent <PERSON>Ms. Houston</PERSON>, a teacher, and her husband, <PERSON>Jim Houston</PERSON>, an art collector, to the north to encourage development of local industries among the Eskimos. 
The two established <LOCATION>Cape Dorset</LOCATION>'s co-op with the help of the government and local Inuit artists. 

   Among the first accomplishments of co-ops like <LOCATION>Cape Dorset</LOCATION> was to develop a system for producing and selling art. 
Traditionally, each artist would sail up to the quarries and bring back, at most, two or three stones for carving. 
If the weather was bad or the rivers froze, they wouldn't travel at all. 
To remedy the problem, the co-op rented large 40-foot boats and brought back enough stones for a season. 
As for buying work, the co-ops were open year-round, a sharp contrast to the days when a potential buyer would appear maybe once a year. 
"We created a stable market," says <PERSON>Ms. Houston</PERSON>. 

   By the mid <DATE>1960s</DATE>, the 30-or-so Arctic co-ops asked the Canadian government for help in organizing a central marketing system. 
In response, the government established Canadian Arctic Producers and financed its early operations. 
But it wasn't until the <DATE>1970s</DATE> that the marketing group began to have an impact. 
By that time, notes <PERSON>Bill Lyall</PERSON>, a senior marketing official, "we had established a regular channel of distribution and a group of dealers aggressively promoting Inuit art." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881029-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-88 0139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Canada-Whales Bjt   10-29 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Canada-Whales, Bjt,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>Activist Says Whales Should Have Been Eaten, Not Saved</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SOLL SUSSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TORONTO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two whales that captured the world's attention
off <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> should have been eaten instead of freed from the ice, an
Eskimo activist says.
   ``In my mind, there's something wrong to save these two whales
while you are destroying the life of the human beings of the
North,'' <PERSON>Aqqaluk Lynge</PERSON>, of the <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> office of the <ORGANIZATION>Inuit
Circumpolar Conference</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> at a news conference that
concluded a three-day meeting on arctic cooperation.
   ``To my mind it's a degradation of human values,'' he said.
   The native peoples of the Arctic region generally prefer the term
Inuit to <LOCATION>Eskimo</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales, stranded in arctic ice for nearly
three weeks, apparently swam to freedom <DATE>Friday</DATE>, ending a
million-dollar rescue effort that involved Soviet icebreakers,
American scientists and Eskimo volunteers who cut holes in the ice
with chain saws.
   <PERSON>Lynge</PERSON> noted the enormous resources devoted to freeing the whales
and said, ``It's better to eat them.''
   The activist said environmentalists' campaigns against
fur-trapping and seal hunting in the arctic have devastated
traditional cultures in the region.
   The conference, sponsored by the government-affiliated <ORGANIZATION>Canadian
Institute for International Peace and Security</ORGANIZATION> and the
Toronto-based, private Science for Peace, brought together native
activists as well as scientists and academics on arctic issues.
   Organizers of the <ORGANIZATION>International Conference on Arctic Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>
said the participation among all arctic nations, including the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, was remarkable.
   <PERSON>Arkady Cherkasov</PERSON>, a specialist in arctic economics from the
Soviet Academy of Sciences' Institute of the <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, said
the campaign to save the two whales may have helped because of the
attention focused on the region's problems.
   ``It's a good thing,'' he said. ``But still there are many other
problems to solve in the north.''
   Cherkasov also said the Yuit people of the Soviet Arctic might be
able to join the <ORGANIZATION>Inuit Interpolar Conference</ORGANIZATION>. A representative of
the Yuits, who have traveled only rarely outside the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>,
was in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> for the conference.
   The interpolar conference claims to represent the 120,000 Inuit
people from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   But <PERSON>Cherkasov</PERSON> said Soviet participation in such a group could be
difficult because more than 25 different native groups live in the
Soviet Arctic.
   The 70 participants were from eight arctic countries, including
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>),
<LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>.
   Although they failed to agree on a final resolution, organizer
<PERSON>Franklyn Griffiths</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Toronto</ORGANIZATION> said the conference
produced thinking ``about what you can do up there together. Action
comes later.''
   Among the topics discussed were public health problems in the
arctic region, the results of industrialization, the environment and
the greenhouse effect, militarization and science.
   ``Each polar state now faces broadly similar problems preserving
the cultures and way of life of its indigenous peoples,'' the
conference's preliminary statement said.
   ``While the need for international civil cooperation on Arctic
environmental, scientific, social and other matters of common
concern has grown, it is constrained by military-strategic
conflict.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890725-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-89 2247EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Greenland-Eskimos     07-25 0233</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Greenland-Eskimos,0244</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Military Authorities Restrict Soviet Eskimo Delegation</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SISIMUIT, Greenland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military authorities restricted
the movements of a Soviet delegation taking part in an Eskimo
conference, participants were told <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military told the 18 Soviet delegates to remain in
their hotel during a <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> stop at Soendre Stroemfjord, a
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> base in <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, said the Soviets and the conference
president. Delegates from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> were allowed to move
around the base.
   Canadian <PERSON>Mary Simon</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Inuit Circumpolar
Conference</ORGANIZATION>, said the incident was unfortunate.
   ``The Soviets are equal participants in our congress and should
have been treated that way. ''
   The Soviets are attending the conference for the first time. The
other delegates are from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>. The 500
participants represent the world's more than 100,000 Arctic natives.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was the second day of the weeklong conference, being
held in <LOCATION>Sisimiut</LOCATION>, a town of 5,000 people on <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s east coast.
   <PERSON>Ms. Simon</PERSON>, an Inuit from <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION>, told the conference that
self-government remains a vitally important question for the Inuit
_ or Eskimo _ people.
   <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> has enjoyed home rule since <DATE>1979</DATE>. But in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the
issue is one of acute concern, and negotiations with the Canadian
government are proceeding slowly, <PERSON>Ms. Simon</PERSON> said.
   In <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Native Land Claims Settlement</ORGANIZATION> of <DATE>1971</DATE> did nothing
to address the issue of self-government, she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-3260</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ELNEAADWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941214
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 DEC 94 / Observer: II, sir
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Trio Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>David Hagan</PERSON>'s money-broking outfit, is hardly a household
name so only an alert merchant banker would have spotted the new competition
on the block. A bunch of Canadian Inuits is helping underwrite Trio's Pounds
6.5m rights issue.
Don't laugh - <PERSON>Hagan</PERSON> could be on to something. Inuvialuit Investments (II),
which is co-underwriting the issue, helps invest the loot of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s Inuit
people. The Inuit have come into tons of money in recent years thanks to
payments from the federal government to settle long-standing land claims.
The Inuit in the eastern half of the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>, for example, won
a land-claims settlement last year that will net them almost CDollars 1.2bn
over 14 years. Royalties from mines and oil and gas wells in the <LOCATION>Northwest
Territories</LOCATION> are likely to swell their coffers still further.
Trio's newfound underwriter is based high above the Arctic Circle and is the
international investment arm of Inuvialuit Regional Corporation (IRC). II
almost doubled its money earlier this year when it sold a 10 per cent stake
in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Regent Pacific Group</ORGANIZATION>, which just happens to be Trio's biggest
investor and is the main underwriter of the Trio issue. Don't fancy <PERSON>Hagan</PERSON>'s
chances if he lets those eskimos down.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Trio Holdings.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>CAZ  Canada.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P6029 Commercial Banks, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>COMP  Company News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06351125 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06351125 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  The Canadian government in Ottawa has tentatively awarded the Inuit people of
northern Canada with rights to an area of land five times the size of
California, a minister said today. The settlement divides in two Canada's
Northwest Territories and ends 15 years of talks on the Inuit's claim to vast
portions of the land they have lived in for thousands of years. The government
recognizes their right to the land in principal, but will give up only some of
it.;   Under the weekend agreement, the Inuit will receive $580 million ($522
million U.S.) over 14 years, along with the right to hunt, fish and trap
anywhere in a new territory to be known as Nunavut, an area of 740,000 square
miles, and title to 135,000 square miles of that land. Nunavut -- which will
be cut off from the eastern half of the Northwest Territories -- is about the
size of Newfoundland and Labrador, and about five times the size of California.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  INUITS, CANADA REACH ACCORD ON LAND RIGHTS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Foreign News in Brief  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     With the creation of <LOCATION>Nunavut</LOCATION>, the western half of the <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>
will be renamed.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911216  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  180  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, December 16, 1991
00351125,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870415-0074 </DOCNO>
<HL> These Innkeepers
Worry When Guests
Go Out for a Walk
---
They Realize the Destination
May Be the North Pole;
Sleds and Satellite Beacons
---
By Michael T. Malloy
<DD> 04/15/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> CANDA </IN>
<DATELINE> RESOLUTE, Northwest Territories  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
     this remote outpost,
<PERSON>Bezal</PERSON> and <PERSON>Terry Jesudason</PERSON> sometimes worry when their guests
leave their snug little tourist home to go on excursions.
   Lately they have been making radio contact with a guest who checked out early last month for a 600-mile walk across the Arctic ice to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>. 
By satellite they keep in touch with other customers who are trekking by snowmobile and motorcycle to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>, 1,050 miles away. 

   "The people that finally come this far north are very special, and we can't help but worry about them as individuals," <PERSON>Terry Jesudason</PERSON> says. 
Her "most fearful moment" was in <DATE>1982</DATE> when a chartered plane sank through the ice and left a group of shivering tourists stranded near the pole. 
Luckily the weather was good, and a backup plane rescued the group within a few hours. 

   Bezal Jesudason (pronounced BAY-z'l jay-zoo-DAH-s'n) is a small, dark, enthusiastic immigrant from steamy south <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, but he can build an igloo, skin a seal and speak the language of the Inuit, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s Eskimos. 
While his wife looks after their six-room International Explorer's Home, he leads packaged adventure tours across the ice to such unlikely destinations as the north magnetic pole. 

   "I'd be more afraid to be run over or mugged in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> than to walk around in the Arctic," <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> says, but he disapproves when guests like Japanese hiker <PERSON>Mitsuro Oba</PERSON> insist on traveling alone. 

   "Oba-san, many dangers!" 
<PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> warns, pantomiming an angry bear for his Greenland-bound customer, who doesn't speak much English. 
<PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> says that <PERSON>Mr. Oba</PERSON>'s supply of seal meat will lure polar bears from a dozen miles away, possibly when he is asleep. 
But <PERSON>Mr. Oba</PERSON>, who once floated down the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> on a homemade raft, seems to think bear trouble will help his career as a professional adventurer. 
"Nice pictures," he replies, clicking an imaginary camera at his host's imaginary bear. 

   Resolute is one of the harshest places on earth. 
Winter temperatures reach 60 degrees below zero Fahrenheit. 
Snow falls in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
The only civilian settlement on the continent that is farther north is a little Inuit village on <LOCATION>Ellesmere Island</LOCATION> named <ORGANIZATION>Grise Fiord</ORGANIZATION>. 
That is where Bezal, now 46, met <PERSON>Terry</PERSON>, now 38. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON>, a mechanical engineer, had recently immigrated to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> when he signed up in <DATE>1969</DATE> for a federal job maintaining electric-power plants in the Arctic. 
"I didn't even know that there weren't any trees up here," he recalls. 
He hunted seal and caribou with his Inuit neighbors and grew to love the life. 

   <PERSON>Mrs. Jesudason</PERSON> was adventurous in a different way. 
A Canadian, she was working as a secretary in her native <ORGANIZATION>British Columbia</ORGANIZATION> when neighbors returned from a geologic assignment in the Arctic. 
They told her about the difficulties that Inuit-speaking children faced in English-language schools when they entered the first grade. 
So she paid her own way to <ORGANIZATION>Grise Fiord</ORGANIZATION> and used her savings to set up its first kindergarten. 

   The couple soon met, and they married in <DATE>1971</DATE>. 
Most residents of the high Arctic rent their homes from the government, but the Jesudasons built the first private house in Grise Fiord. 
There was no hotel there then, so the community's few visitors took to staying with the gregarious young couple. 
One frequent guest was Japanese adventurer <PERSON>Naomi Uemura</PERSON>, who in <DATE>1978</DATE> revived world-wide interest in polar travel by making the first one-man expedition to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>. 

   Not long after that, when <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> was showing home movies of outdoor life with the Inuit, several tourists told him Americans would pay to go on such wilderness adventures. 
He soon quit his government job and formed <ORGANIZATION>High Arctic International Explorer Services Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> to run snowmobile and camping expeditions out of Resolute, the northernmost point in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> with regular jet service-four flights a week. 
He and his wife bought two abandoned village houses here and nailed them together into a modest home with several extra bedrooms. 

   "We thought we'd just do our own trips and accommodate our own guests," <PERSON>Mrs. Jesudason</PERSON> says, "but because this is the transport center of the Arctic we started getting scientists and media people and independent expeditions." 
Soon the territorial government insisted the Jesudasons get a tourist-home license. 

   The license was an early sign of what the Jesudasons see as the baleful descent of big-city bureaucracy on one of the world's last frontiers. 
"You couldn't afford to stay here," <PERSON>Mrs. Jesudason</PERSON> says, if she and her husband provided, and heated, the minimum amount of living space that regulations require for each guest. 
She won't put an "exit" sign on her kitchen door, either. 
Not homey enough. 

   The Jesudasons charge about <MONEY>$74</MONEY> a day for room and board. 
"From <DATE>February</DATE> to <DATE>September</DATE> we make a profit and we live off our fat for the rest of the year," <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> says. 
When 24-hour darkness covers Resolute in midwinter, the Jesudasons go on a long vacation someplace warmer. 
They have been several times to <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON>'s sweltering hometown of <LOCATION>Madras</LOCATION>. 
"Such a beautiful climate," says his wife. 

   Before the sun returns to Resolute, in <DATE>February</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> begins building sleds and recruiting Inuit guides for the season's visitors. 
His wife starts making her grocery list; she will have about 12,000 pounds of canned goods, soap and sundries on the annual ship that calls here in late <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
It costs about <MONEY>59 cents</MONEY> a pound to fly in anything she forgets, or fresh lettuce for a salad. 
She pays more than <MONEY>$2</MONEY> a quart for milk, about <MONEY>$2.60</MONEY> for a dozen eggs. 

   Food from <PERSON>Mrs. Jesudason</PERSON>'s cheerful white-and-yellow kitchen runs toward hearty beef and potatoes, occasionally enlivened with her musk-ox stew or <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON>'s Indian curry. 
Guests sometimes have to share their rooms with strangers, and there are no private baths. 
Three expeditions to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> are booked into the guest house this season. 

   The guests can be fascinating. 
<PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON>, the first man on the moon, has stayed here. 
So has Sir <PERSON>Edmund Hillary</PERSON>, conqueror of <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Mrs. Jesudason</PERSON> corresponds with former guests in 40 countries. 
With friends in every time zone, she has to take the telephone off the hook at night to get some sleep. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> doesn't take his own tour groups as far as the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>, but he provides equipment, hot showers and the benefit of his long experience to adventurers who are headed there. 
"Any of the expeditions going up there use him as logistics master," says <PERSON>Richard Hamburg</PERSON>, a tourism official with the territorial government and a 20-year Arctic veteran. 
"If he doesn't know about it, nobody does." 

   Need an Eskimo guide, a hunting rifle or a heated workshop for repairing a dog sled? 
<PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> has all that. 
How about a knapsack-sized satellite navigation beacon that reports your precise location to his personal computer, by way of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> weather satellite and a scientific agency in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>? 
Most polar expeditions rent one from <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON>, then call him every day by radio to find out where they are on the featureless Arctic Ocean. 

   "If you combine 20th-century technology and Inuit culture," <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> says of the boom in <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> expeditions, "you can bring any kind of dream to life." 

   But he sees more bureaucratic snakes in his frozen Eden. 
There is a campaign afoot to change local place names from English to <LOCATION>Inuit</LOCATION>, so that Resolute could become Qausuittuq or maybe Kaujuitoq. 
And the federal and territorial governments plan to establish the world's northernmost national park on <LOCATION>Ellesmere Island</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> runs expensive camping trips. 

   "The government doesn't understand that the kind of people who come here want to feel they are walking where nobody stepped before," <PERSON>Mr. Jesudason</PERSON> complains. 
"They won't come if they see footpaths and a sign saying 'Welcome to Our National Park.'" 

   And Qausuittuq? 
"I'll fight it all the way," he says. 
"Nobody will come to a place they can't spell or pronounce." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891120-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-20-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--GreenlandToday Adv03-1stAdd   11-20 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Greenland Today, Adv 03-1st Add,0657</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>NUUK, Greenland: of Australia.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Most of its 870,240 square miles is covered with ice 2{ miles
thick, but the ice-free area is still half the size of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The southern coasts are snowless and verdant in <DATE>summer</DATE>, and it
was here that the Scandinavian Vikings landed 1,000 years ago and
gave the country its somewhat misleading name.
   Eric the Red, a hero of Icelandic sagas, established tiny
colonies that eked out a living for 500 years before mysteriously
dying out.
   Nuuk sits on a long strip of land between two fiords, with
mountains rising on either side like sentinels. Long rows of
publicly built five-story apartment blocks give the city an air of
drabness.
   Today four out of five inhabitants are native Inuits, who are
related by language and custom to the Eskimos of <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>.
   But <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the country's administration is run by <ORGANIZATION>Danes</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Jonathan Motzfeldt</PERSON>, who has been prime minister since autonomy
was granted, says the goal is for <ORGANIZATION>Greenlanders</ORGANIZATION> to take over
entirely. In its first autonomous decade, he says, ``<LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>
already has undergone a silent revolution,'' and he wants it to
become more self-reliant.
   Motzfeldt has announced deep cuts in social benefits, especially
to the unemployed. From now on, he says, welfare clients who refuse
a job offer in the <DATE>summer</DATE> will not be eligible for cash benefits.
   The <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> government also has taken its first international
loan of about <MONEY>$166 million</MONEY>, in German marks and Japanese yen.
   <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>'s rule over <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> dates to <DATE>1776</DATE>, when it set up a
trade monopoly and established missionary stations along the coast.
   The Americans came during World War II, when <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> was a
midway staging area and refueling stop for troop transports and
equipment on the way to the European theater.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces also supplied the Greenlanders with food and
essentials after the Nazis occupied <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, which old-timers still
remember.
   In the early <DATE>1950s</DATE> the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military built defense installations
across <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION> known as the <ORGANIZATION>Distant
Early Warning System</ORGANIZATION>, or DEW Line.
   The philosophy then was that the shortest distance between two
superpowers, as the bomber or ballistic missile flies, is over the
arctic. But the stations have become outdated and are coming down.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> pullout from <PERSON>Sondre Stromfjord</PERSON> also is exacerbating
tensions with <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> over the <LOCATION>Thule</LOCATION> radar base, an important
link for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> defenses in its ballistic missile warning system.
   Thule was once a tiny Inuit hunting and trapping village. Under
the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-Danish Defense Agreement</ORGANIZATION> of <DATE>1951</DATE>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military
relocated the native people and built a big phased-array radar.
   It has been a bone of contention between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, which claims the modernization of <LOCATION>Thule</LOCATION> in recent
years was a breach of the <DATE>1972</DATE> anti-ballistic missile treaty.
   Though it is a source of income for <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, it is a political
embarrassment for <PERSON>Motzfeldt</PERSON>, who is under pressure from leftists
who want to get rid of the base. Motzfeldt grumbles about <LOCATION>Thule</LOCATION> as
``that stupid radar.''
   <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, mindful of its commitments to <ORGANIZATION>NATO</ORGANIZATION>, supports the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
position that <LOCATION>Thule</LOCATION> is ``non-offensive,'' and the <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>
administration has little choice but to fall in line.
   Motzfeldt has intimated that the Americans won't be welcome in
<LOCATION>Thule</LOCATION> unless they agree to continue paying for <ORGANIZATION>Sondre Stromfjord</ORGANIZATION>'s
civilian airport.
   ``We are not going to pay money to have the American bases
here,'' <PERSON>Motzfeldt</PERSON> says. ``On the contrary, we insist that civilian
people have the advantage of the Americans' presence.''
   Despite all of its problems, the latest news of the gold find
should help make the future brighter. For the <DATE>first Christmas</DATE> in a
long time, the world can truly say, ``Yes, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, there is a
<LOCATION>Santa Claus</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900627-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-90 1144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-NativeFurs Adv03   06-27 1076</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Native Furs, Adv03,1117</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv03</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Tuesday PMs, July 3, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Natives to Take on Anti-Fur Movement</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HAL SPENCER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Native people of the north are
preparing to take on the anti-fur movement _ not on the tundra, but
in the marketplace.
   Two native groups in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> plan to seek out small
markets to sell native-trapped and-sewn fur clothing. But animal
rights activists contend the embryonic plans are doomed, and
promise to oppose the products as much as they do furs from
non-native trappers and marketers.
   ``We have no problems with native subsistence wildlife killing
as long as its done as humanely as possible,'' said <PERSON>Michael
O'Sullivan</PERSON>, spokesman for the World Society for the Protection of
Animals in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>.
   ``But we cannot accept commercial fur sales. It's not who
carries out the activity, but the activity itself,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s Athabascan Indians and the Inuit Eskimos of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>
retort that the animal protectionists appear to care little about
the human suffering caused by native unemployment, or about the
survival of native cultures.
   And anti-fur activists, they say, would open the door to other
forms of development that would be far more threatening to the
environment and animals.
   Their anger at the anti-fur forces has simmered for years, but
it was just three years ago that they formed <ORGANIZATION>Indigenous Survival
International</ORGANIZATION>, a militant native group that spans <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   The marketing strategy was the group's idea.
   If all goes according to plan, <LOCATION>Alaska Athabascans</LOCATION>, through their
Yukon Flats Fur Cooperative, soon will seek markets in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> for furs labeled ``Authentic Native Design.''
   They hope to sell through small stores, preferably owned by
natives. They envision consumers who will buy their coats, hats,
boots and other articles more for their native artistry than for
reasons of fashion.
   The plan was forged after the cooperative sold just <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>
worth of furs in the past two years. That small return has
endangered the cooperative because banks refuse to loan it money,
said <PERSON>Clarence Alexander</PERSON>, the Athabascan chief for the village of
<LOCATION>Fort Yukon</LOCATION>.
   Alexander, an <ORGANIZATION>Indigenous Survival International</ORGANIZATION> member, said his
people hoped to generate the modest amounts of cash they need to
supplement a subsistence economy based mostly on hunting, trapping,
fishing and gathering.
   ``Subsistence societies like the Athabascans and the Inuit need
a little cash to buy gas for boats, to heat with oil, to buy
ammunition,'' said <PERSON>Robert Higgins</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian
Inuit</ORGANIZATION>'s umbrella organization, Inuit Tapirisat in <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION>.
   Fur sales are their only ready source of cash, he said.
   The organization wants to revive the harvest of adult ringed
seals as a way of returning <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s 28,000 Inuit to a subsistence
economy, <PERSON>Higgins</PERSON> said.
   Their sealing-based culture was devastated by a powerful
anti-sealing movement that caught on in <DATE>1983</DATE>. The impetus was
photographs _ grisly pictures of non-native sealers clubbing Harp
seal pups to death off <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Higgins</PERSON> said his group primarily wants to replace the Inuits'
store-bought food and clothing with seal meat and fur. But the
Inuit also will sell native-made fur clothing to raise cash, he
said.
   Anti-fur advocates accept native people's need to trap and shoot
animals for their own needs, said <PERSON>Pat Ragan</PERSON>, the program director
of wildlife for the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   But ``to kill animals to market skins is another thing
altogether,'' she said. ``The only hope for these people is to get
away from marketing furs. We acknowledge that there are problems
with that, but I don't think selling furs is the way to solve
them.''
   Her group offers no alternatives to the native fur trade. ``Of
course we don't have an official position on that,'' she said.
``Our job is protecting animals.''
   <PERSON>Tom Morse</PERSON>, an <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> anti-fur activist, said natives wouldn't
need cash if they would return completely to the old ways. ``They
were heating their homes before the white man brought oil,'' and
snaring animals before white trappers introduced the steel leghold
trap, he said.
   ``They have the freedom to follow their own lifestyle. But when
they start combining cultures, the results have been disastrous,''
said <PERSON>Morse</PERSON>, a physics instructor at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Alaska</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   Alexander reacted angrily to that logic.
   ``Some of us would like to return completely to the old ways,''
but the presence of non-natives and their competition for resources
makes that impossible, the Athabascan leader said.
   ``We have always been and still are a non-cash society, but we
are forced now to need some cash,'' <PERSON>Alexander</PERSON> said. Northern
natives, he said, could reject Western tools such as outboard
engines, guns and heating oil only if <PERSON>Morse</PERSON> and the non-native
populations left.
   In destroying the native fur trade, native leaders say, the
anti-fur movement is laying the groundwork for destruction of
animal habitat.
   They point to the <LOCATION>Pribilof Islands</LOCATION>, where the Aleuts hunted
seals for centuries. Then <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> ended the harvest in <DATE>1985</DATE>,
limiting the killings to those used for food, and the federal
government withdrew subsidies for the Aleuts.
   ``Literally overnight, we had human suffering, suicides, more
than 100 documented attempted suicides, massive anxiety, and a
200-percent increase in the cost of groceries from the loss of the
subsidies,'' said <PERSON>Larry Merculieff</PERSON>, a leader of the Aleut islanders
and commissioner of the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Commerce and Economic
Development</ORGANIZATION>.
   The state stepped in and poured <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> into
development of a major port at <LOCATION>Saint Paul Island</LOCATION>, one of two in the
<LOCATION>Pribilofs</LOCATION>, for the thriving <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> fishery, Merculieff noted.
   But that could have other consequences.
   ``Saint <PERSON>Paul</PERSON> soon will be opening its fishing port,'' he said.
``We will then have 2,000 transients on an island that is five
miles wide, 12 miles long, with a million seals, three million
birds and 700 Aleuts. The people being brought in are not sensitive
to village life or wildlife. The disruption won't be confined to
the environment, but to our social and cultural structure as well.''
   The state commerce chief is not optimistic about the native
marketing plan:
   ``It might work for five years or so, but in the long run, the
fur markets of the world are going to be completely destroyed by
the animal rights movement.''
   The effect on native cultures ``to me,'' <PERSON>Merculieff</PERSON> said, ``is
tantamount to genocide. But nobody seems to be listening.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tues PMs, July 03</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA033189-0157 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 38171 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 31, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 27; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
821 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ESKIMO ESCAPADES; 
</P>
<P>
INTRODUCING YOUNGSTERS TO 'PEOPLE OF THE SNOW' RIGHT IN AN IRVINE PARK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CORINNE FLOCKEN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
If the kids have been clamoring for a little kilaujatut, load 'em up in the 
family komatik and head for "Igloos of Fun," the <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> Fine Arts Center ninth 
annual Youth Art Day. But you had better leave the aiverk at home. 
</P>
<P>
If by chance you don't speak Inutitut, the language of the Inuit Eskimo, those 
exotic-sounding words mean, respectively, drum dancing, sled and walrus -- not 
exactly part of the average county schoolchild's vocabulary. 
</P>
<P>
But on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the Inuit come to <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>. Well, sort of. From <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>3 
p.m.</TIME>, children ages 3 to 10 can sample the lighter side of life among these 
hardy "people of the snow" in a day of art workshops, entertainment and games 
on the center's grounds in <LOCATION>Heritage Park</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The children's festival coincides with four Eskimo-themed exhibits on display 
at the center through <DATE>April 28</DATE>. They are "Inuit Games: Traditional Sport and 
Play of the Eskimo," a collection of stone-cut prints and soapstone sculpture 
by Eskimo artists that depict games of skill and endurance; artifacts of the 
<LOCATION>Bering Sea Eskimos</LOCATION> from <ORGANIZATION>Bowers Museum</ORGANIZATION>'s permanent collection, and "The 
Grandparents of My Gloves," a retrospective by <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> dancer <PERSON>Patricia Bulitt</PERSON>, 
which features costumes, recordings and mixed-media remembrances of <ORGANIZATION>Bulitt</ORGANIZATION>'s 
10-year cultural exchange with Eskimos. 
</P>
<P>
Bulitt recently shared her experiences with teachers from the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Unified 
School District</ORGANIZATION>. District teachers passed on the lesson to their students, who 
interpreted their studies in a series of drawings, poetry and clay sculptures 
displayed at the center's gallery. (A drawing by <ORGANIZATION>Culverdale School</ORGANIZATION> student <PERSON>Mike 
Jazayeri</PERSON> sums up the children's cross-cultural experience with a decidedly 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> flair: The Alaskan god of <DATE>summer</DATE>, a six-armed figure, wears 
sunglasses and clutches a hot dog, an ice cream cone and a Beach Boys album.) 
</P>
<P>
Docent tours of the exhibits will be offered through the day. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s festivities center on seven, hourlong art workshops and several 
Eskimo games that will introduce children to the culture, said <PERSON>Jill Stute</PERSON>, the 
center's special events coordinator. 
</P>
<P>
"The Inuit used games as a means of developing strength and manual dexterity," 
<PERSON>Stute</PERSON> said. "Theirs was a harsh way of life, and some of their games were very 
physically taxing. The kids can see those tougher games in the exhibit, and on 
the day of the festival they'll get hands-on experience with games like Eskimo 
yo-yos and bean-bag juggling." 
</P>
<P>
In addition, <PERSON>Stute</PERSON> said, <PERSON>Dori Kirk Fitzgerald</PERSON>, the center's curator of 
exhibitions, will lead children in an authentic Eskimo hunting dance taught to 
her by <ORGANIZATION>Bullitt</ORGANIZATION>, and storytellers will share traditional tales of the Eskimo. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>'s balmy weather is a far cry from the Eskimo's chilly climate, so a snow 
machine will provide a frosting of real snow on the center's lawn. The snow 
will fall at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> Depending on the weather, it should last about an hour, 
<PERSON>Stute</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Art workshops will begin at <TIME>10 a.m</TIME>. In "Magical Masks," children 6 and older 
will create masks based on Arctic animals. "Snow Prints" introduces youngsters 
to a variation on Eskimo-style block printing. In "Charms and Spells," children 
will learn how good-luck charms and magic spells helped the Eskimo succeed in 
the hunt, then create their own charms in clay. 
</P>
<P>
"Arctic Antics" is a collaborative project in which small groups will create 
clay scenes of Eskimo life, which will be fired and later displayed in the 
center's gallery. 
</P>
<P>
"Go Fish" will be geared for children ages 3 to 5. In it, children will learn 
about fish as a staple in the Eskimo diet, then design and decorate their own 
fish from a grab bag of art materials. In the "Drawing and Painting 
Expedition," children will hear tales of the Eskimo hunt, then depict their 
impressions in mixed media. "It's Snowing" will let young artists create snow 
by drawing Arctic scenes, then applying a solution of epsom salts that form 
snowlike crystals on the paper. 
</P>
<P>
Two drop-in workshops -- "Arctic Mural," in which youngsters will contrast 
their life style with the <ORGANIZATION>Eskimo</ORGANIZATION>'s on two large murals, and "Build Your Own 
Igloo," a construction project of fair-weather igloos of cardboard and paint -- 
will be offered throughout the day. Face-painting will also be available for a 
small fee. 
</P>
<P>
In the center's courtyard, such local entertainers as the <PERSON>Lori Hansen Dancers</PERSON>, 
the <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow Singers</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Sky Badger</PERSON>, an American Indian who tells folk stories, 
will be presented. Food will be sold from <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
 Youth Art day will be <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> Fine Arts Center, 14321 <ORGANIZATION>Yale Ave.</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Heritage Park</LOCATION>. Attendance is open to the entire family. Children 
under 6 must be accompanied by an adult. Walk-in registration will begin at <TIME>9 
a.m.</TIME> Registration fee is <MONEY>$9</MONEY> per child and includes two 1-hour workshops, both 
drop-in workshops and all entertainment and games. Adults are free. 
Information: (714) 552-1019. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Displays for the "Igloos of Fun" planned in Irvine on Saturday include 
Eskimo yo-yo, left, and a sculptured skill game. Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ARTS -- ORANGE COUNTY; IRVINE FINE ARTS CENTER; FESTIVALS; ART EXHIBITS; 
CHILDREN; ESKIMOS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891120-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-20-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--GreenlandToday-Village Adv03   11-20 0721</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Greenland Today-Village, Adv 03,0747</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Dec. 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-APN--Greenland Today</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANK POWLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ILULISSAT, Greenland (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A constant parade of Titanic-sized
icebergs slowly drifts with the currents of <LOCATION>Disko Bay</LOCATION> in sight of
this west coast fishing port.
   Spawned by the <ORGANIZATION>Northern Hemisphere</ORGANIZATION>'s most productive glacier 25
miles to the south, these mountains of ice break off with a
thunderous roar and begin their silent arctic voyage.
   The barking of sled dogs, which outnumber the 4,000 people of
the town, mixes with the chugging of cutters and shrimp boats and
the hum of the fish factories in the tiny harbor.
   Against the darkened sky, the Northern Lights unfurl in wavy
sheets of red and green across the horizon.
   <LOCATION>Ilulissat</LOCATION>, which means icebergs in the native language, is
inhabited by Inuits who are culturally and linguistically related
to the Eskimos of <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and others in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>.
   Nearly everyone in the town, 180 miles north of the <ORGANIZATION>Arctic
Circle</ORGANIZATION>, make their living from the sea.
   Its economy is totally dependent on shrimp and halibut catches,
which the local fishermen deliver directly to the two big state-run
fish factories, employing 350 people in the peak season.
   <LOCATION>Ilulissat</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s third-largest town, also is known by its
Danish name, Jacobshavn. <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, which ruled <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION> for 200
years, made it an autonomous territory under the Danish crown 10
years ago.
   About 50 fishing boats, ranging from factory trawlers to one-man
cutters, operate during the <DATE>summer</DATE> from <LOCATION>Ilulissat</LOCATION>'s natural harbor.
   In the winters of 24-hour darkness, many fishermen such as
<PERSON>Soeren Madsen</PERSON> go ``longlining'' on the Icefjord, a frozen fiord at
the foot of the glacier.
   ``We drive 35 miles overland across rough terrain in dogsleds to
the fishing grounds, and the temperature can fall to minus 22
degrees Fahrenheit out on the ice,'' <PERSON>Madsen</PERSON> says.
   Long lines strung with up to 100 hooks are sunk through holes
cut in the ice and then hauled up by hand from the depths.
   ``You have to return with a catch of at least <MONEY>400 pounds</MONEY> to make
it pay,'' <PERSON>Madsen</PERSON> says.
   A typical fishing tour on the ice lasts 48 hours, during which
time the men live in low, conical tents with a Primus stove to keep
warm.
   The dog teams of 10 to 12 huskies sleep huddled together out in
the open. They are capable of running 12 hours non-stop.
   Some of the fishermen make a little extra money on the side
driving sleds for winter tourists who come to see the natural
wonders of the <LOCATION>Disko Bay</LOCATION> area.
   In <LOCATION>Ilulissat</LOCATION>, it's an unwritten law that dog sleds have the
right of way.
   Ilulissat municipality includes four small outlying settlements
of 80 to 100 inhabitants each. Beyond those tiny villages lie
nothing but the glacial ice pack, 2{ miles thick, of <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>'s
interior.
   No roads link the town with its satellite settlements. Travel is
by boat, sled or helicopter.
   The Greenlandic dog, a special breed protected by a ban on
imports of other races, is not tame, and visitors are advised not
to pet them.
   Practically every dwelling in the town has a dog team in the
yard where fish for their fodder is hung up in racks to dry.
   The dogs must be kept chained, their fangs cut. Stray dogs are
shot on orders from the authorities.
   Many hunters are embittered over an anti-sealing campaign waged
by conservationists that ruined the once-lucrative skin trade.
   In the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, environmental groups such as <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>,
spurred on by French actress and self-styled animal friend <PERSON>Brigitte
Bardot</PERSON>, launched highly publicized protests against the Canadian
practice of bludgeoning seal pups to death for their prized white
pelts.
   Gruesome pictures of the Canadian seal hunt became associated in
the public mind with the <ORGANIZATION>Greenlanders</ORGANIZATION>' traditional hunt, which does
not include pups.
   Seal pups are born on the ice floes off northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and are
rarely seen in <LOCATION>Greenlandic</LOCATION> waters.
   Prices for <ORGANIZATION>Greenlandic</ORGANIZATION> skins plunged in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, a major market, banned the import of seal skins.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> eventually apologized to <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>, but they should
have admitted their mistake to the consumers as well,'' said <PERSON>Adolf
Jensen</PERSON>, a hunter who comes from a tiny settlement 62 miles north of
<LOCATION>Ilulissat</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111890-0119 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 309834 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 18, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Book Review; Page 14; Book Review Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
169 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PAPERBACKS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Charles Solomon 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
LIVING ARCTIC: Hunters of the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian North</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>Hugh Brody</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>University of 
Washington Press</ORGANIZATION>: <MONEY>$14.95</MONEY>, illustrated). <PERSON>Brody</PERSON>'s thoughtful essays on the 
history, culture and languages of the Arctic and sub-Arctic peoples of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> 
contrast the let's-rub-noses stereotypes with the true nature of these caring, 
anti-authoritarian cultures. 
</P>
<P>
The respectful relationship that the Inuit maintained with their seemingly 
hostile environment ensured the survival of the people and the animals that 
supplied their food. (Recent studies have shown that their exclusive diet of 
meat and fat supplied all the nutrients necessary for human health: Diabetes 
and other metabolic diseases were unknown among the Inuit until "Southerners" 
introduced them to flour, sugar and alcohol.) The concluding discussion of 
politics documents the growing movement among the Native Peoples to preserve 
their traditional values, despite the increasing commercial exploitation of the 
Arctic and its mineral resources. <PERSON>Charles Solomon</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Book Review; Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900716-0105
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900716-0105.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Gulf Canada Ends
   Plan for Test Well
   In Arctic Ocean
   ----
   By Rose Tamburri
</HL>
<DATE>
07/16/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   CANDA GOU AN CHV
</CO>
<IN>
PETROLEUM (PET)
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
OIL, INTEGRATED MAJORS (OIL)
</IN>
<LP>
   OTTAWA -- Gulf Canada Resources Ltd. said it canceled
plans to drill a 60 million Canadian dollar (US$51.9 million)
exploratory oil well in the western Arctic Ocean because of a
lack of industry support for the project.
   The decision means that no new wells will be drilled this
year in Canada's Beaufort Sea region, which leads into the
Arctic Ocean. Gulf Canada, an energy concern, is a unit of
Toronto-based Olympia &amp; York Developments Ltd., which is
controlled by the Reichmann family. It had proposed to drill
as many as four wells in the region over the next three
years.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Frank Mitton</PERSON>, manager of <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>'s northern
operations, said the company will decide in the next few
months whether to carry out its plans to drill the remaining
wells. <PERSON>Mr. Mitton</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Gulf</ORGANIZATION>'s decision to cancel the well was
unrelated to an earlier ruling by a Canadian environmental
panel. The panel had recommended that the Canadian government
reject <ORGANIZATION>Gulf</ORGANIZATION>'s plans because the company was unprepared to
deal with a major oil spill. "We cannot drill the well
because we don't have sufficient industry support for it,"
<PERSON>Mr. Mitton</PERSON> said.
   The well was to have been located about 18 miles east of
<LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>'s big Amauligak oil field. Several oil and gas
finds have been made in the <LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION> but none of the
discoveries has been brought into production.
   Gulf is the second company that has canceled an Arctic
exploration program this year. <ORGANIZATION>Amoco Canada Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
unit of Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Amoco Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, recently canceled plans to
drill two wells in the <LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION>, because of insufficient
interest from its partners. Amoco plans to carry out some
seismic work this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ed Zederayko</PERSON>, an oil industry analyst, said low energy
prices and reduced federal government exploration incentives
are causing more companies to defer their offshore drilling
plans.
   But a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Chevron Canada Resources Ltd.</ORGANIZATION>, which
was to have held about <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT> interest in <LOCATION>Gulf</LOCATION>'s proposed well,
said <ORGANIZATION>Chevron</ORGANIZATION> was committed to going ahead with the plan.
"has an ongoing interest in the North," he said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Environmental Impact Review Board</ORGANIZATION> had
recommended earlier this month that government regulators
reject <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>'s Arctic drilling plan because of the
potentially devastating effects of an oil spill on the area's
environmentally sensitive coastline. The board, which is made
up of representatives from the federal government, the
governments of the Yukon and <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION> and the
Western Arctic Inuit natives, criticized <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION> and the
government for their "startling lack of preparedness" for
dealing with a major oil well blowout.
   <ORGANIZATION>Canada Oil and Gas Lands Administration</ORGANIZATION>, the government
regulators, had yet to issue its decision on whether it would
accept the environmental board's ruling.
   Gulf <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> officials estimated that a hypothetical
worst-case well blowout could release 40,000 barrels of oil a
day for 66 days, or 10 times more oil than was released when
<ORGANIZATION>Exxon Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Valdez tanker ran aground in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> last year.
They said the cleanup of such a spill could be beyond <LOCATION>Gulf
Canada</LOCATION>'s financial capabilities.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890127-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-27-89 0927EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-ArcticIcewalk Adv03   01-27 0762</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Arctic Icewalk, Adv 03,0779</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Fri PMs Feb. 3 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Team Plans Icewalk to Dramatize Arctic's Environmental Hazards</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SOLL SUSSMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OTTAWA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An international expedition plans to walk 483 miles
across the ice to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> in an effort to dramatize the
hazards they believe are threatening the arctic.
   The team, which includes members from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, hopes
to set out on the 65-day trip around <DATE>March 10-15</DATE> from <LOCATION>Cape Columbia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s northernmost point of land on the <ORGANIZATION>Arctic Ocean</ORGANIZATION>.
   The American in the group is <PERSON>Darryl Roberts</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   ``Everyone has to understand that this is no walk in the park,''
said <PERSON>Peter Baird</PERSON>, the Canadian liaison for the Icewalk expedition.
``This is a life-threatening project.''
   The expedition is led by <PERSON>Robert Swan</PERSON>, the British explorer who
walked to the <LOCATION>South Pole</LOCATION> with two other men in <DATE>1986</DATE>. A successful
completion of the northern trip would make him the first on record
to walk to both poles.
   Baird is an administrator and will not be among the eight-member
team that walks to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>. His <LOCATION>Ottawa</LOCATION> company, the <ORGANIZATION>Conexus
Research Group</ORGANIZATION>, served as the managers for the Canadian-Soviet ski
expedition that crossed the arctic ice cap last year to widespread
acclaim.
   Baird had no easy explanation for why adventurers seem to keep
trying to come up with new projects and goals in the arctic.
   ``Who knows what motivates them?'' he said. ``It's an athletic
thing, clearly, in some ways. It's the right to say you're first. .
.. And some sort of declaration that the human spirit is still alive
and kicking.''
   At around the time the Icewalk begins, another expedition will
have already started, if all goes on schedule, on a dog-sled trek
across the frozen <LOCATION>Bering Strait</LOCATION> separating <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet
Siberia</LOCATION>. The purpose of the trek by a U.S.-Soviet team of 10 men and
two women is to call attention to the common cultural heritage of
the indigenous people living on both sides of the strait. The
two-month expedition is scheduled to depart from <LOCATION>Anadyr</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>, on
<DATE>March 1</DATE>.
   The <MONEY>$4 million Icewalk</MONEY> to the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> has lined up <ORGANIZATION>Amway</ORGANIZATION>, the
Michigan-based marketing company, as its major corporate sponsor.
   The Icewalk is different from other similar ventures in that it
will use only human power. Supplies will be brought along in sledges
that require tremendous energy to haul their 250-300 pound cargoes.
The group will use skis, but there will be no dogsleds or
skimobiles. The team will be flown back after reaching its goal.
   It also hopes to attract attention by bringing an international
group of about 30 teen-age students to a base camp at <LOCATION>Eureka</LOCATION> on
<LOCATION>Ellesmere Island</LOCATION> to help with radio monitoring and to promote the
anti-pollution message.
   Team members will gather snow and atmospheric samples to record
pollution levels in the region. They will be testing for mercury _
said to be the first such tests in the region _ as well as tracking
sulphates, nitrates, chlorides and graphite particles. They also
will collect pollen samples to help find the origin of pollutants.
   Canadian research over the past four years has turned up dozens
of toxic substances in the region's fragile ecosystem, many of them
entering the food chain. Attention also has focused on the thinning
of the world's ozone layer, most notably at the world's poles, and
on acid rain.
   <PERSON>Baird</PERSON> said the team will spend about a month training at a base
camp before venturing out on the ice from <LOCATION>Cape Columbia</LOCATION> on the
65-day trip.
   ``There's only a certain window when you can do this,'' he added.
   Waiting warmer weather means too much open sea and drifting ice;
taking off too soon means too much harsh weather and temperatures
that are too cold.
   ``They can count on rough, rough ice _ sea ice _ for the first
100 kilometers (62 miles),'' <PERSON>Baird</PERSON> said. ``It's a maze; it's like a
giant jigsaw puzzle.''
   The temperatures could be as low as 70 degrees below zero
(Fahrenheit) at the outset, while winds could be as strong as about
55 miles an hour. The plans call for daily consumption of more than
6,000 calories by each member of the team to keep up energy.
   The Canadian on the team is <PERSON>Angus Clarence</PERSON> ``Kaanerk'' <PERSON>Cockney</PERSON>,
who is an Inuit, as Eskimos are called in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. He was born and
reared in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Fri PMs Feb. 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900705-0105
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900705-0105.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Panel Seeks Killing
   Gulf Canada Plan
   For Ocean Drilling
   ----
   By Rose Tamburri
</HL>
<DATE>
07/05/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A5
</SO>
<CO>
   CANDA GOU
</CO>
<IN>
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
PETROLEUM (PET)
</IN>
<LP>
   OTTAWA -- A Canadian environmental panel recommended that
the federal government reject plans by Gulf Canada Resources
Ltd. to drill in the western Arctic Ocean, citing the
potentially devastating effects of a spill.
   The recommendation, if accepted by the federal government,
would result in a suspension of operations in Canada's
Beaufort Sea region, which leads into the Arctic Ocean. Gulf
Canada, a unit of Toronto-based Olympia &amp; York Developments
Ltd., which is controlled by the Reichmann family, is the
only company that planned to drill there this year.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Impact Review Board</ORGANIZATION> said <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>, an
energy concern, and federal regulators had demonstrated
"complacency" toward environmental protection and wildlife
preservation. The regulators, the <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> Oil and <ORGANIZATION>Gas Lands
Administration</ORGANIZATION>, will rule on <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Canada</ORGANIZATION>'s drilling plans.
   Gulf <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> had proposed to drill four wells in the
<LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION> in the next three years.
   The environmental board, made up of representatives from
the federal government, the governments of the Yukon and
<ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>, and Western Arctic Inuit natives, said
<LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION> hadn't been able to estimate the effects of an
oil spill on the area's coastline or to give details of how
the company would carry out cleanup operations in the event
of a spill. It said <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION> didn't provide adequate
evidence at a public hearing last month to enable the board
to estimate the cost of cleaning up a hypothetical worst-case
oil spill.
   Gulf <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> officials estimated that a worst-case well
blowout could release 40,000 barrels of oil a day for 66
days, or 10 times more oil than that released when <ORGANIZATION>Exxon
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Valdez tanker ran aground in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> last year. The
board said such a spill could have "devastating impacts on
sensitive shorelines and on wildlife that could last for
decades."
   <PERSON>Frank Mitton</PERSON>, manager of <LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION>'s northern
operations, said the board's comments were even "harsher than
anticipated." Gulf <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> has "all the plans and precautions
to make sure we don't have an environmental disaster," he
said.
   The review board said it blamed the lack of preparedness
for dealing with oil spills on "a complacency" on the part of
<LOCATION>Gulf Canada</LOCATION> and the government, which is "driven by an
ultimate belief that a blowout is so unlikely to occur that
preparing to meet it is largely an academic exercise."
   It added: "This is the kind of complacency that has been
blamed for the confused response to the Exxon Valdez oil
spill."
   <PERSON>Maurice Taschereau</PERSON>, administrator of the <ORGANIZATION>Canada Oil</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Gas Lands Administration</ORGANIZATION>, said he was "shaken and puzzled" by
the board's criticism. He said the agency has "lots of
contingency plans" in place to deal with environmental
disasters. <PERSON>Mr. Taschereau</PERSON> declined to indicate how his agency
will respond to the board's recommendations. It has 30 days
to reach a decision.
   <PERSON>Stephen Hazell</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Arctic
Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>, an environmental group, said the federal
regulator can't reject the board's advice without calling
into question the government's own environmental review
process.
   No wells are being drilled in the <LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION> now. <ORGANIZATION>Amoco
Canada Petroleum Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of Chicago-based <ORGANIZATION>Amoco Corp.</ORGANIZATION>,
recently canceled its plans to drill two wells in the
<LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION>, because of insufficient interest from its
partners to proceed with the project. An <ORGANIZATION>Amoco</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said
the company now intends to carry out some seismic work this
<DATE>summer</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA120790-0111 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 319024 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 7, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 1; Foreign Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2401 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COLUMN ONE; 
</P>
<P>
AT EARTH'S END, PRIESTS TRY HARDER; 
</P>
<P>
IN THE FAR NORTH, CANADA'S NATIVE PEOPLES HAVE GROWN DISILLUSIONED WITH THE 
'BLACKROBES.' BUT THE CATHOLIC CHURCH IS MAKING NEW EFFORTS WITH CLERGY FROM 
POLAND. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MARY WILLIAMS WALSH, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
FT. SIMPSON, Canada 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More than 100 years ago, the "<PERSON>Francis Xavier</PERSON> of the frigid zone," Father <PERSON>Henri 
Grollier</PERSON>, paddled down the <LOCATION>Mackenzie River</LOCATION> and beached here, kitted out with a 
long black cassock, a bronze crucifix and the Oblate order's motto of grueling 
devotion, "Usque ad extremum terrae" -- "Even unto the ends of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
He evidently made a compelling sight: Within days, he had blessed five 
marriages, baptized 34 children and heard 11 adults ask to be received into the 
<ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"My trip to Ft. Simpson was a triumphal march," he reported to his faraway 
bishop. 
</P>
<P>
All of that belonged to the glory days of Roman Catholicism in the <LOCATION>Canadian 
North</LOCATION>, a time when the "Blackrobes," along with the rough-hewn fur traders of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Hudson's Bay Co.</ORGANIZATION> and a few scattered <LOCATION>Mounties</LOCATION>, made up what there was of a 
Canadian "government" presence in these parts. 
</P>
<P>
Single-minded young priests traveled by dog sled in winter and canoe in the 
<DATE>summer</DATE>, with bundled vestments and skins filled with holy water and wine. They 
slept on spruce boughs in hide tents, hunted, trapped and fished for their food 
and everywhere sought the nomadic native peoples they hoped to convert, who in 
turn sought the migrating caribou. 
</P>
<P>
These days, the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> in the hard, cold <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION> presents a far less 
invigorating picture. The native peoples of northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> -- the <ORGANIZATION>Dene Nation</ORGANIZATION>, 
the Cree and the Inuit, or Eskimos -- have grown deeply disillusioned about 
white outsiders trying to uplift and "improve" them. Many have turned to their 
traditional legends and beliefs, and in doing so, have rejected the church. 
</P>
<P>
And now, too, there is the sheer scarcity of priests. The earliest Blackrobes 
streamed to the Canadian northwest from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION>, bringing 
with them a heartening supposition that as the church took root and flourished 
in the Arctic, a native clergy would rise to carry on. 
</P>
<P>
But not only have Dene and Inuit men proved uninterested in the priesthood; 
these days, even the white Europeans who used to serve in the North are 
unwilling to accept the rigors of celibacy, loneliness, Arctic weather and an 
evermore unreceptive flock. 
</P>
<P>
"I have quite a problem on my hands with recruiting," admits Bishop <PERSON>Denis 
Croteau</PERSON>, sitting in his simply furnished office in <LOCATION>Yellowknife</LOCATION>, capital of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Northwest Territories</ORGANIZATION>. Indeed, when Bishop <PERSON>Croteau</PERSON> came here from <LOCATION>Quebec</LOCATION> as a 
young priest in <DATE>1960</DATE>, there were 62 priests to shrive men's souls in the vast 
775,000-square-mile Mackenzie-Ft. Smith diocese. Now there are only 19. 
</P>
<P>
Most of these are in their 60s and even older. Until recently, a glum reality 
hung over them: When they died, they knew the church in the <LOCATION>North</LOCATION> was likely to 
die with them. 
</P>
<P>
"But there is a light at the end of the tunnel," the bishop adds. That light is 
being shed by <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, a country where, in sharp contrast to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, Catholic seminaries are full, the church enjoys widespread 
credibility and young men come to holy orders with a zeal to share what they 
have with the rest of the world. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1986</DATE>, a delegation of anxious Oblates from northwestern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> visited 
<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, to beg their brethren to send a few good men north of the 60th 
parallel. The appeal worked. By <DATE>1995</DATE>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> is expected to have dispatched a 
dozen young priests to take up the work of the aging Blackrobes in the <LOCATION>North</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"<LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> seems willing to supply us," says <PERSON>Bishop Croteau</PERSON>, whose manpower 
worries were such that he dropped courageous, if futile, hints in the wake of a 
papal visit here that perhaps priests ought to be free to marry. 
</P>
<P>
But in attracting young Polish Oblates to northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the church is also 
attracting controversy. For northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> is marginalized and poor -- a 
little bit of the <ORGANIZATION>Third World</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, people say -- and the 
Blackrobes of yesteryear who grew to understand the region blazed a trail here 
toward the social gospel. 
</P>
<P>
Much in the mold of the liberation theologists of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>, priests 
ministering in the Arctic and sub-Arctic have witnessed native misery and 
concluded that if the church were to have meaning in northern lives, it would 
have to get involved in northern, secular struggles. 
</P>
<P>
Thus, it was missionary priests who set up the first cooperatives in northern 
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and who organized the first native-language radio broadcasts in the 
Arctic. It was priests who devised new alphabets for the indigenous northern 
languages, and priests who were the first to train scholarly eyes on 
traditional spiritual beliefs and practices. 
</P>
<P>
One aging northern Oblate, Father <PERSON>Camille Piche</PERSON>, achieved local fame for saying 
Mass in <LOCATION>Slavey</LOCATION>, an Indian language, even though some of his congregants were 
unilingual whites. Lately, he has been fighting a proposed pulp mill that 
threatens to pollute traditional fishing waters of the <LOCATION>Mackenzie River</LOCATION> basin. 
</P>
<P>
Another noted activist priest, the French-born Father <PERSON>Rene Fumoleau</PERSON>, wrote a 
path-breaking study of northern Indian treaties, and thereby sparked 20 years 
of tough land-tenure negotiations with the federal government. Militant Dene in 
the region regard Father <PERSON>Rene</PERSON>, who lives in a two-room cabin in <LOCATION>Yellowknife</LOCATION> 
with no running water, as one of but a handful of whites they can trust. 
</P>
<P>
"We western missionaries felt we had more to teach than to learn," Father <PERSON>Rene</PERSON> 
says of his early years in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, when he was given five dogs, a sled and 
instructions to ride a 2,000-mile priestly circuit every winter. "It was the 
colonial system. The situation changed, so I changed, too -- no choice." 
</P>
<P>
Can the young priests of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> build on such a legacy? The Polish clergy, 
after all, has encountered problems of a greatly different nature: not neglect 
by Indian-affairs bureaucrats or mindless resource exploitation by huge outside 
concerns, but half a century of totalitarian opposition. 
</P>
<P>
Their thinking, as an unsurprising consequence, tends to the traditional and 
the conservative -- not to say the reactionary. Liberation theology goes down 
poorly with the Poles; leftist biblical exegesis smacks all too much of the 
Marxist dogma that they and their village pastors struggled so long to 
overthrow. 
</P>
<P>
Thus, when the Canadian delegation set out for <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION>, skeptics worried. Would 
transplanted Polish priests ever fit in? 
</P>
<P>
One answer may eventually be found in the fortunes of 29-year-old Father 
<PERSON>Andrezej Stendzina</PERSON>, now of Ft. Simpson. Father <PERSON>Andrezej</PERSON> is the first of the new 
Polish priests to arrive in the Mackenzie-Ft. Smith diocese, and today is by 
far the youngest priest serving the faithful for thousands of square miles. 
</P>
<P>
"When I came to Ft. Simpson, I told the people, I have come to learn, not to 
teach," he says in accented English. As yet, no one in Ft. Simpson, aside from 
a few local Canadians of Polish ancestry, has mastered the pronunciation of his 
Polish name. To everyone, he is simply Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Like most of his priest-compatriots, Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> is an unstinting 
traditionalist. He has little truck with a married priesthood and believes that 
politics and religion mix at the peril of the latter. 
</P>
<P>
Liberation theology? He shakes his head. 
</P>
<P>
"When I hear that in some countries (church) people want to bring communism, I 
can't believe it," he says. 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> is the very picture of open-mindedness when it 
comes to the folkways of Ft. Simpson, a traditional Dene meeting place that 
grew apace with the <ORGANIZATION>Hudson</ORGANIZATION>'s Bay trading post here. Already, he shuffles 
rhythmically in traditional Dene drum dances, down by the sacred confluence of 
the Liard and <PERSON>Mackenzie</PERSON> rivers. He has been teaching the young to play soccer. 
He hopes that in a few more months, he'll be fluent enough to say Mass in 
<LOCATION>Slavey</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> may have his quarrel with a politically engaged priesthood, but 
the faith he has brought to northern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> was shaped in no small part by a 
worldly wise, and militant, Polish church. 
</P>
<P>
"The government was telling us stupid things, but people could learn the real 
facts at church," he says, negotiating his pickup truck along the long, empty 
gravel roads that link the villages of his vast parish, stopping here and there 
to smoke a cigarette or read his daily office from an Oblate breviary. "The 
church was the moral support for everybody who wanted to change things." 
</P>
<P>
Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> was still a seminarian, preparing for the work of the church in 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, when the Canadian recruiters reached his hometown of Lubliniec, in 
southern <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, looking for missionaries for the far north of another 
continent. He thought things through and concluded that the need in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> was 
the more pressing. 
</P>
<P>
"In <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, they can get young priests any time," he says. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1988</DATE>, he arrived in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>, all his earthly possessions in two suitcases. 
He learned English, was ordained in Ft. Simpson, and said his first Mass in 
<LOCATION>Edmonton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>, at a nursing home for elderly missionaries. 
</P>
<P>
"You could almost feel their excitement when they saw that finally someone 
young had come to continue their work," he says. "They had sacrificed their 
health, their life, their energy, and they knew that when they had to leave, 
well. . . . " 
</P>
<P>
There are eight villages in Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON>'s parish, some, but not all, 
connected by gravel roads. The biggest is Ft. Simpson, population 1,000 or so. 
It harbors a rectory roomy enough for the half a dozen priests who used to live 
here; there is also a nuns' residence and a wooden church, painted green and 
white. 
</P>
<P>
Now, though, the nuns are gone, and the priestly population is down to just 
two: Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> and a 49-year-old colleague, Father <PERSON>George LaGrange</PERSON>, who 
until the <LOCATION>Pole</LOCATION>'s arrival was the youngest priest in the diocese. Gone, too, are 
the dog sleds of years gone by. Father <PERSON>George</PERSON>, a pilot, flies a light plane to 
the roadless villages, while Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> serves the rest in his pickup. 
</P>
<P>
Some of Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON>'s parishioners haven't seen a resident priest in years. 
When he arrives on 40-below winter evenings, he must chip away the ice from the 
doorways, find fuel, scare up a place to sleep, hear confessions and say <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. 
Some villages have eager beavers who want to help with the liturgy. But others 
have problems that come as quite a shock to him, after <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Father <PERSON>Andrew</PERSON> had never even heard of child molestation before he left his 
homeland; here, he finds it a spreading concern. 
</P>
<P>
He cannot help but notice the drunkards who dodge him in the streets of Ft. 
Simpson. He has received tearful alcoholics who say they want to dry out -- and 
who leave the rectory and head straight for a bar. He has learned, on pastoral 
visits, to step nonchalantly over heaps of garbage on people's living-room 
floors. 
</P>
<P>
"It's terrible sometimes," he says. "It's really hard." 
</P>
<P>
Still, in every household he visits, the people sooner or later ask him to pray 
with them. 
</P>
<P>
There are those who pin a large measure of responsibility for the <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>'s 
rampant social problems on the <ORGANIZATION>Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION> itself. Angry native Canadians, 
baptized as children, say that in its efforts to "tame" them, the church 
undermined their culture and left them without a sense of who they are. 
</P>
<P>
