<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880810-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-88 0505EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OceanDumping     08-10 0343</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ocean Dumping,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Votes Ban on Dumping of Sludge in Atlantic Ocean</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Medical Waste Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> vote to ban dumping sludge in the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> brings the nation ``closer to the day when we'll
stop using the ocean as a sewer,'' a key sponsor of the measure
says.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, spurred by fears about sludge and medical waste that
has washed up recently on <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> beaches, voted 97-0 on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
to bar the practice.
   A similar bill is awaiting action in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> measure bans the dumping of municipal sludge off the
coasts of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> after <DATE>1991</DATE> and orders the closing
of a sludge dump site 106 miles off the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> coast, the only
site where sludge can currently be legally dumped.
   The site is used by six sewage authorities in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
three in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, including the city of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   ``We need a firm deadline, in the law, to ban the ocean dumping
of sewage sludge,'' said <PERSON>Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, one of the
co-sponsors. ``Only then will alternatives be put in place. Only
then will the dumping stop.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> added an amendment by <PERSON>Sen. Christopher Dodd</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Conn.</LOCATION>,
which bans the disposal of all medical waste in oceans or streams.
It also approved another amendment, by <PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON>, providing a
five-year prison sentence for anyone caught violating that ban.
   ``Last week, virtually every <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> beach was shut down
because of medical waste during one of the hottest spells in the
state's history,'' <PERSON>Dodd</PERSON> told his colleagues.
   ``We're moving closer to the day when we'll stop using the ocean
as a sewer,'' said <PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON>. ``Sludge dumping is a throwaway
approach to our waste problem and contributes to the overall ocean
pollution problem.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> first ordered an end to the ocean dumping of sludge in
<DATE>1972</DATE>. Five years later, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> directed that the dumping be ended
by <DATE>1981</DATE>. But the nine municipalities in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
successfully sued in federal court to ignore that deadline.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880809-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-88 1735EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-OceanDumping     08-09 0377</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Dumping,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Votes Ban on Dumping of Sludge in Atlantic Ocean</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Medical Waste Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM AHERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, spurred by fears about sludge and
medical waste washing onto East Coat beaches, voted 97-0 on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
passage of a bill which bans the dumping of sludge in the <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION>.
   The action sends the measure to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, where a similar bill
is on the floor awaiting final action.
   The bill bans the dumping of municipal sludge off the coasts of
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> after <DATE>1991</DATE> and orders the closing of a
sludge dump site 106 miles off the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> coast. That location
is the only site where sludge currently can be legally dumped.
   The site is used by six sewage authorities in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
three in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, including the city of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Before approving the bill, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> added an amendment by <PERSON>Sen.
Christopher Dodd</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Conn.</LOCATION>, which bans the disposal of all medical
waste in oceans or streams. It also approved another amendment, by
<PERSON>Sen. Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, providing a five-year prison
sentence for anyone caught violating that ban.
   Both amendments were approved by voice vote without any audible
dissent.
   Dodd told his colleagues that because of medical waste washing
up on his state's beaches, ``last week, virtually every <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>
beach was shut down because of medical waste during one of the
hottest spells in the state's history.''
   ``We're moving closer to the day when we'll stop using the ocean
as a sewer,'' said <PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON>, one of the co-sponsors. ``Sludge
dumping is a throwaway approach to our waste problem and
contributes to the overall ocean pollution problem.''
   Sen. <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, agreed. ``We're treating the oceans
as a cesspool,'' he told the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> first ordered an end to the ocean dumping of sewage
sludge in <DATE>1972</DATE>. Five years laters, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> directed that the
dumping be ended by <DATE>1981</DATE>. But the nine municipalities in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> successfully sued in federal court to ignore that
deadline.
   ``We need a firm deadline, in the law, to ban the ocean dumping
of sewage sludge,'' said <PERSON>Lautenberg</PERSON>. ``Only then will alternatives
be put in place. Only then will the dumping stop.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881018-0197 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-18-88 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-OceanSludge     10-18 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Sludge,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Passes Sludge-Dumping Ban</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB McHUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> voted to ban disposal of
sewage sludge in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> after <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The measure, passed by voice vote, would set a <DATE>Dec. 31, 1991</DATE>,
deadline for dumping in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> by nine authorities in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   The bill would impose stiff fines aimed at making the dumping
prohibitively expensive, and use penalty fees to pay for
alternatives.
   ``Today's action means that ocean dumpers have to find
alternatives to using the sea as the world's biggest garbage pail,
or face fines and penalties,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>,
a principal sponsor of the legislation.
   The measure reconciles differing sludge-dumping bills passed by
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE> and by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> earlier this month.
   A <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> vote on the compromise could come as soon as <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>,
with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> then expected to sign the bill.
   Some 8 million tons of sludge a year are dumped by the nine
agencies at a site about 106 miles east of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
closed a site just 12 miles offshore in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The new bill would require dumpers to pay fees of <MONEY>$100 dollars</MONEY>
per ton of sludge beginning next <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>.
   Dumpers, meanwhile, would be required to negotiate with federal
authorities on individual timetables for ending their dumping.
   Those agencies that cannot strike a deal would pay fees that
rise from <MONEY>$100</MONEY> a ton to <MONEY>$200</MONEY> a ton by the end of <DATE>1991</DATE>. Any
authority still dumping sludge in the ocean by the start of <DATE>1992</DATE>
would have to pay penalties in addition to the fees.
   Those fines would begin at <MONEY>$600</MONEY> per ton and rise by <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> a
year for continuing violators, rising to total <MONEY>tens of millions of
dollars</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> originally banned ocean sludge dumping as of <DATE>1981</DATE>, but
that deadline was suspended in a successful lawsuit by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
The original deadline was set in a <DATE>1978</DATE> law, after which some 300
industries and 100 municipalities stopped dumping.
   The proposed ban initially was opposed by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> officials,
who complained that the deadline would be impossible to meet.
   But the opposition weakened as a bipartisan coalition of <LOCATION>East
Coast</LOCATION> lawmakers rallied in favor of a ban.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890109-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-09-89 1536EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SewageDump     01-09 0365</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sewage Dump,0378</SECOND>
<HEAD>Palm Beach County Pours Chlorinated Waste Into The Ocean</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LAKE WORTH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Palm Beach County</LOCATION> dumped a million
gallons of chlorinated raw sewage from an affluent suburb into the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> rather than let it spill onto property and into
canals.
   ``The two alternatives were not very attractive,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Health
Department</ORGANIZATION> engineering director <PERSON>Frank Gargiulo</PERSON>. ``One was
discharging sewage on the ground. The other was discharging it into
the ocean.''
   Health department officials banned swimming, surfing and wading
on 13 miles of beach from <LOCATION>Singer Island</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Lantana</LOCATION> for about 24
hours.
   The problem started with the shutdown of a regional treatment
plant early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to bring a new section on line.
   ``This was a planned event,'' <PERSON>Gargiulo</PERSON> said. ``At night, they
don't generate as much sewage.''
   But <LOCATION>Lake Worth</LOCATION> produced more waste than expected. By <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>,
officials were worried about it spilling and seeping onto the ground.
   For about three hours, waste flowed from a pumping station
through a pipe that extends about a mile into the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>,
officials said.
   Dumping raw waste there is illegal, but <PERSON>Gargiulo</PERSON> described the
step as ``the lesser of two evils.''
   <PERSON>Don White</PERSON>, a state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental Regulation</ORGANIZATION>
official, was present when the waste was discharged. ``They had
emergency approval from us,'' he said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``Up until 25 to 30 years ago, all of the domestic waste from the
<LOCATION>Lake Worth</LOCATION> area was discharged through that outflow,'' he said,
``but it has not been used for 25 years routinely.''
   White said he didn't know what effect the chlorinated sewage
would have on marine life at the discharge point.
   <PERSON>Gargiulo</PERSON> said the action is not expected to cause health problems.
   ``The ocean is usually a hostile environment for bacteria,'' he
said. ``There is a high salt content and strong currents. We're very
confident that tidal activity during the 24-hour (ban) will cleanse
the area.''
   Some beachgoers seemed equally unconcerned.
   Despite red ``no swimming'' flags, <PERSON>Julio Armas</PERSON>, 26, of <LOCATION>West Palm
Beach</LOCATION>, took a blue raft into the ocean.
   He said the water probably has been polluted on other days. ``We
just happened to know about it this time,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881019-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-19-88 2351EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-OceanSludge     10-19 0320</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Sludge,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Approves Ban on Disposal of Sewage Sludge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> voted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to bar authorities
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> from disposing sewage sludge in the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> after <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The measure, passed by a voice vote, would impose stiff fines
for any dumping after <DATE>Dec. 31, 1991</DATE>. The fines are aimed at making
the dumping prohibitively expensive, and the penalty fees would be
used to pay for alternatives.
   Sen. <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, said the bill was ``a major
breakthrough in reclaiming our oceans and shores. This legislation
gives local sewage authorities the clear message that they must
find alternatives to ocean dumping _ not sometime in the distant
future, but right now.''
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> is expected to sign the bill, which is a
compromise between differing sludge-dumping bills passed by the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE> and the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> earlier this month.
   Nine agencies in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> dump about 8 million
tons of sludge a year at a site about 106 miles east of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
Another site 12 miles offshore was closed in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The new bill would set a fee of <MONEY>$100</MONEY> per ton of sludge dumped
beginning <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>, and the dumpers would be expected to negotiate
with federal authorities toward a timetable to end their dumping.
   Those that cannot work out a deal would see their fees rise to
<MONEY>$200</MONEY> a ton by the end of <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   Starting in <DATE>1992</DATE>, penalties starting at <MONEY>$600</MONEY> per ton would be
added to the fees. The penalties would rise by <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> a year
for continuing violators, and eventually would total tens of
<MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> set a <DATE>1981</DATE> deadline to stop ocean sludge
dumping, but <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> sued and got the ban suspended, saying the
deadline would be impossible to meet. However, a bipartisan
coalition of <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> lawmakers worked in favor of a ban.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890616-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-89 2145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SludgeDumping     06-16 0289</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sludge Dumping,280</SECOND>
<HEAD>EPA Staff Recommends Ocean Dumping Permits, With Restrictions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The staff of the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection
Agency</ORGANIZATION> recommended <DATE>Friday</DATE> that permits be issued to nine <LOCATION>New York
City-area</LOCATION> municipalities which dump treated sewage sludge in the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>.
   An <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> hearing officer said authorities should be allowed to
increase dumping sewage to five times their normal rates under bad
weather, up to 15,500 gallons per minute.
   The report also recommends creating two barge tracks inside the
dumping area, rather than the current single track, enabling more
barges to use the dump site simultaneously. The permits would also
reduce the time and distance that must remain between barges.
   ``I believe that these modifications ... while continuing to
provide for maximum protection of the marine environment, result in
a permit which is fully implementable,'' <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> hearing officer <PERSON>Richard
L. Caspe</PERSON> said in his report. ``I do not foresee any environmental
condition which would result in its impracticability or its lack of
environmental protection.''
   The permits, which would be valid until <DATE>March 17, 1991</DATE>, must be
approved by the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> regional administrator, said <PERSON>Herman Phillips</PERSON>, an
agency spokesman in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Currently, <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, Westchester and <ORGANIZATION>Nassau Counties</ORGANIZATION>, and
six sewerage authorities in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> dump more than 8 million wet
tons of sewage sludge annually at a site 106 miles off the <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION> coast.
   They are the only municipalities in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> that dump
sewage sludge in the ocean. The municipalities have been dumping
under a court order issued in <DATE>1981</DATE>, but the Ocean Dumping Ban Act of
<DATE>1988</DATE> makes such dumping illegal after <DATE>Aug. 14, 1989</DATE> unless the
municipality has entered into an agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> to phase out
the practice.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082690-0123 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 267283 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 26, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 30; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
752 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAND BAR WAS ONCE A GLORIOUS ISLAND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAVID ENSCOE, UNITED PRESS INTERNATIONAL 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MOTTS CREEK, N. J. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At low tide, a sand bar peeks out from under the ocean at the mouth of <LOCATION>New 
Jersey</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Great Bay</LOCATION>, the last remnant of an American Atlantis. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Evelyn Suter</PERSON> recalls when that sand bar was a magnificent island, a dreamy sort 
of a place with families and beautiful cedar trees and tales of haunted hotels. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Suter</PERSON>, who turns 83 this month, was one of the children who told those ghost 
stories on <ORGANIZATION>Tucker</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And she may be the last person alive who can tell from personal experience the 
story of the island, which was swallowed by the sea more than half a century 
ago. 
</P>
<P>
It's a story with a lesson, a reminder that man may live on the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and even 
manipulate it, but, in the end, does not control it. 
</P>
<P>
"It was a wonderful place," <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> said of her childhood home. "But now it's 
gone to the bottom of the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
In its glory years, as far back as the late 1700s, <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> was 5 miles 
long and a mile wide. It boasted a lighthouse, two hotels and a school and was 
a popular spot for sportsmen and vacationers from <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The island, north of <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION> along the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> coast, was named for 
<PERSON>Rueben Tucker</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Quaker</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> who bought it in <DATE>1765</DATE>. According to <PERSON>John 
Bailey Lloyd</PERSON>, a historian who has written about the lost island in two books, 
wealthy Quakers gathered there for religious retreats in the years following 
the <ORGANIZATION>American Revolution</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The island was renamed <ORGANIZATION>Sea Haven</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1870s</DATE>, when there were plans to develop 
it into a major resort. Those plans were shelved when the nearby town of <LOCATION>Beach 
Haven</LOCATION>, on another island a few miles to the north, proved to be too much 
competition. 
</P>
<P>
Sea Haven's fate as a commercial enterprise was sealed in <DATE>1886</DATE>, when the 
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Railroad ran a line across <LOCATION>Barnegat Bay</LOCATION> onto <LOCATION>Long Beach Island</LOCATION>, 
<PERSON>Lloyd</PERSON> said. The tracks ended at <LOCATION>Beach Haven</LOCATION> and were never extended. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1913</DATE>, when <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> arrived at age 7, the only residents of the once-bustling 
island were a lighthouse keeper, the staff of a lifesaving station and their 
families. The <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>St. Alban</ORGANIZATION>'s hotels had long since closed. 
</P>
<P>
"I remember these two big hotels in disrepair," <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> said. "We kids would say 
they were haunted." 
</P>
<P>
During her first winter there, she lived in a bungalow with her mother and 
father, who worked at the lifesaving station, rescuing shipwrecked sailors. 
</P>
<P>
The family spent a second winter on the island in a houseboat that <PERSON>Suter</PERSON>'s 
father towed across the bay from Parkertown. 
</P>
<P>
"We stayed there from <DATE>September</DATE> to <DATE>June</DATE>," <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> said. "We didn't stay in the 
<DATE>summer</DATE>, because there weren't that many shipwrecks. 
</P>
<P>
Suter recalls attending a one-room schoolhouse on the island in <DATE>1913</DATE> and <DATE>1914</DATE>, 
with about six other children. She has fond memories of walking the desolate 
beaches with her mother, and going fishing in her father's garvey, a small 
scow. 
</P>
<P>
On blustery winter nights, everyone would gather at the lifesaving station, the 
center of the island's social life. 
</P>
<P>
"They had a gramophone and people would sing and dance," she said. "Nowadays, 
people get bored if they don't have a television set. But we had wonderful 
times." 
</P>
<P>
Those times ended in <DATE>1915</DATE>, when the lifesaving station was disbanded and the 
<ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> took over <ORGANIZATION>Tucker</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>. The family moved back to its house 
across the bay in <LOCATION>Parkertown</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> had been born and still lives today. 
</P>
<P>
Although no one knew it at the time, the island's days were numbered. On <DATE>Feb</DATE>. 
4, <DATE>1920</DATE>, a storm ripped an inlet through <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s Beach, a narrow strip of sand 
that formed the tip of <LOCATION>Long Beach Island</LOCATION> and protected <ORGANIZATION>Tucker</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> from the 
fury of the ocean. 
</P>
<P>
Over the next five years, the inlet widened to the south, consuming <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s 
Beach and exposing <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> to the open sea. The relentless ocean began 
chewing up the island and, one by one, its buildings. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1927</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Little Egg Harbor Light House</ORGANIZATION>, which had stood for nearly a 
century, tumbled into the sea. The ever-encroaching ocean forced the <ORGANIZATION>Coast 
Guard</ORGANIZATION> to evacuate the island in <DATE>1930</DATE>, according to <LOCATION>Lloyd</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Tucker's <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> officially ceased to exist in <DATE>1932</DATE>, when <LOCATION>Long Beach Township</LOCATION> 
removed it from the tax rolls. But a small piece of land where the little 
schoolhouse stood survived until <DATE>1938</DATE>, when it was swept away during a winter 
storm. 
</P>
<P>
Now, only the sand bar is left, and many people <PERSON>Suter</PERSON> meets find it hard to 
believe that so picturesque an island ever stood there. 
</P>
<P>
"People will argue with me about <PERSON>Tucker</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>," she said. "But I always tell 
them, 'I know what it was really like. I lived there.' " 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880707-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-07-88 1443EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-BeachClosings 2ndLd-Writethru a0578 07-07 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Beach Closings, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0578,0622</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Hospital Waste Washes Ashore on Long Island</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to UPDATE with one beach closed again
after more debris comes ashore, picking up 6th graf pvs,
`Inspectors from ....'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAT MILTON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MINEOLA, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More hospital waste, including intravenous
tubing and vials of blood, washed ashore today on a <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>
beach, and officials declared it off-limits for swimmers just a few
hours after it was reopened.
   Swimming bans were lifted today on other beaches along a 25-mile
stretch of the island's south shore, facing the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>, but
officials warned that winds and tides could bring more debris and
force more closings.
   There was no word on where the material came from.
   Meanwhile in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, officials said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that five of
the 104 blood-filled vials that washed up on its shores <DATE>last
weekend</DATE> contained AIDS-contaminated blood. Another two dozen vials
were found <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The waves of debris that washed up today at <ORGANIZATION>Robert Moses State
Park</ORGANIZATION>, the easternmost of the affected beaches, were brought in by a
combination of high tide and southwesterly winds, said <PERSON>Michael
Asheroff</PERSON>, deputy regional director of the <ORGANIZATION>Long Island State Park
Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   The waste was taken to the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental
Conservation</ORGANIZATION> for testing to determine its source.
   Asheroff said the popular <LOCATION>Jones Beach</LOCATION> and the other beaches
closed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and then reopened may see waste washing ashore
later this afternoon or by high tide <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>.
   Health inspectors, after finding no new debris on beaches <TIME>this
morning</TIME>, had decided to reopen them. They also tested the water
quality and found it to be safe, <PERSON>Asheroff</PERSON> said.
   Inspectors from the <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> county health departments
and the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental Conservation</ORGANIZATION> were in
patrol boats looking for clues to the origin of the debris.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Nassau County Health Department</ORGANIZATION> recommended
that the state, county and town beaches remain closed to swimming
until the water was determined safe, said <PERSON>Shelly Domash</PERSON>, a
department spokeswoman.
   ``It's the unknown _ you don't know what it is or what it's
carrying,'' said <PERSON>Ronald F. Foley</PERSON>, regional director of the <ORGANIZATION>New York
State Parks</ORGANIZATION>. ``We wanted to be on the safe side.''
   On a typical weekday, 50,000 to 60,000 people visit <LOCATION>Jones Beach</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Robert Moses</PERSON> state parks, with up to <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> swimming, he
said. On weekends, as many as 200,000 go to <LOCATION>Jones Beach</LOCATION> and about
40,000 to <PERSON>Robert Moses</PERSON>, which is 10 miles east.
   A heat wave has just begun, with forecasters predicting
temperatures in the 90s through the <DATE>weekend</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Domash</PERSON> said officials were trying to figure out where the debris
came from and whether it was related to the debris that washed up
in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   The last time the parks' beaches were closed in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> was
<DATE>1976</DATE> when sewage washed up, <PERSON>Foley</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Health Department</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that five
vials discovered <DATE>last weekend</DATE> in <LOCATION>Bayonne</LOCATION> showed evidence of the
AIDS antibody. It was the second time in a month that vials had
washed ashore in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   The presence of the antibody ``does not necessarily indicate
that there is live virus in the blood,'' said Deputy Health
Commissioner <PERSON>Thomas A. Burke</PERSON>.
   Early last month, two of five vials found in <LOCATION>Ocean County</LOCATION> were
contaminated with AIDS. A third tested positive for hepatitis,
which is substantially more infectious than AIDS.
   Police also said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> they have discovered another two
dozen vials on the <LOCATION>Bayonne</LOCATION> beach which have been turned over to the
<ORGANIZATION>Health Department</ORGANIZATION> for analysis. <LOCATION>Bayonne</LOCATION> is on a bay that feeds into
the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06011130 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06011130 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  OCEAN; WASTE; POLLUTION; TEST; US; SCIENCE; RESEARCH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A group of leading oceanographers gathered here Thursday called for a massive
experiment to test the ocean's potential as a dumping ground for millions of
tons of sewage sludge and toxic waste.;    In a proposal that flies in the
face of public opinion, and challenges traditional ideas about the sanctity of
the seas, the scientists proposed interring garbage in the deep ocean as part
of an "industrial-scale" test of the health and environmental effects of
marine waste disposal.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DEEP-SEA TEST OF WASTE DUMPING PROPOSED
SCIENTISTS SAY OCEANS COULD SPARE LAND, AIR  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Although most scientists would prefer not to dump garbage in the oceans,
researchers meeting here at one of the world's leading marine institutes say
using the deep seas may be one of the only ways to spare the land and air from
additional pollution from landfills and incineration.;    "I don't think
anyone wants to advocate ocean dumping," said <PERSON>Derek Spencer</PERSON>, a senior
scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute</ORGANIZATION>, who is leading the
campaign to study ocean dumping. "But the waste problem is there and it's not
going away. Indeed, it is going to get far worse. Perhaps the bottom of the
sea is the best place for some wastes. Yet nobody wants to hear that.";   
Ocean dumping has been one of the most reviled ways for disposing of waste.
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> has banned all ocean dumping starting next year.;    But the
scientists say the dumping ban was propelled by "environmental hysteria." The
deep ocean far from shore, they say, might be a more appropriate place for
certain waste. They argue that the oceans may in fact be a far better place
than landfills on the coast, which pollute inshore waters with runoff,
degrading beaches and fishing grounds.;    The proposal to experiment with
deep-ocean dumping is sure to run into vigorous opposition from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and
environmentalists who have fought to protect the oceans.;    "I don't think
this is such a good idea," said <PERSON>Elliott A. Norse</PERSON>, a marine ecologist and chief
scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Marine Conservation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. "There are some
folks who never take no for an answer.";    To research the appropriateness of
using the deep oceans as marine landfill, the scientists and engineers meeting
this week at <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole</ORGANIZATION> envision a major collaboration between academia and
foreign financiers.;    In one scenario, a million ton of waste a year or more
would be dumped into the deep oceans for 10 years. Candidates for dumping
include sewage sludge, industrial wastes and the toxic ash left over after
incineration of garbage. A large ship would steam far out into the <LOCATION>North
Atlantic</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> where it would lower, by capsule, load upon load of
garbage.;    Upon reaching the sea floor, some four or five miles below the
surface, the door of the garbage capsule would open and spill out its
contents. With the help of navigation satellites, the garbage ship would be
able to return to the same site over and over again.;    <PERSON>Spencer</PERSON> and his
colleagues concede that ocean dumping could disturb the ecosystem. But at
least one component of their experiment would be to monitor those effects and
to learn whether the ocean floor recovers after dumping is stopped.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Woods Hole, Mass.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910111  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  521  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, January 11, 1991
00011130,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881008-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-08-88 0102EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OceanSludge     10-08 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ocean Sludge,250</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Expected To Act On Sludge-Dumping Ban</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is expected to vote next week on
compromise legislation to ban disposal of sewage sludge in the
ocean by the nation's only remaining ocean dumpers.
   The new agreement, struck <DATE>Friday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> conferees,
sets a <DATE>Dec. 31, 1991</DATE>, deadline for dumping in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> by nine
authorities in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   The legislation imposes stiff fines aimed at making the dumping
exorbitantly expensive, and pools the fines to pay for alternatives.
   ``The agreement is tough but fair. Clearly the end of ocean
dumping is in sight,'' said Rep. <PERSON>William Hughes</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, the prime
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> sponsor.
   ``This bill is a major step in cleaning up our oceans,'' added
Rep. <PERSON>Robert Roe</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>
   The compromise reconciles differing sludge-dumping bills passed
by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE> and by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> earlier this week.
   Senate and <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> votes on the compromise are expected <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> is expected to sign the bill.
   Some 8 million tons of sludge a year are dumped by the nine
agencies at a site about 106 miles east of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
closed a site just 12 miles offshore in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Experts differ on the environmental threat posed by the dumping
of sludge.
   The new bill requires dumpers to pay fees of <MONEY>$100</MONEY> per ton of
sludge beginning on <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> of next year.
   Any authority still dumping sludge in the ocean by <DATE>1993</DATE> would
have to pay penalties in addition to the fees.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880728-0118 </DOCNO>
<HL> Viewpoint: Pollution in New Jersey: The Way the World Really Is </HL>
<AUTHOR> Alexander Cockburn </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<IN> ENV PHA </IN>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> stood last <DATE>Friday</DATE> with Gov. <PERSON>Thomas Kean</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> on a beach in <LOCATION>Point Pleasant</LOCATION> and proclaimed ocean dumping a "national tragedy." 
He thus joined the platoons of public officials who have made haste to echo the public's disgust at the waves of syringes, needles, blood vials and other medical wastes that have been washing up on the beaches of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> this <DATE>summer</DATE>. 

   Those admiring <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON>'s moral fortitude in making a stand for clean water should temper their emotion with knowledge of what -- as the vice president is fond of saying -- the world is, rather than what it should be. 
<PERSON>Lawrence Bathgate</PERSON>, a lawyer who is finance chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Committee</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> state finance chairman for the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for <ORGANIZATION>President Committee</ORGANIZATION> and, according to a <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> campaign spokesman, "one of the campaign's single largest fund-raisers" has also helped the interests of <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION>, one of the most resolute polluters in the state of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, with a well-documented international record of outrageous conduct. 

   Every day, through a private pipeline running 10 miles from its dye and resin plant on <LOCATION>Toms River</LOCATION>, the huge Swiss-owned pharmaceutical company <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> dumps more than four million gallons, or 17,000 tons, of waste into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> off <LOCATION>Ortley Beach</LOCATION>. 
From its own discharge permits to <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Department of Environmental Protection</ORGANIZATION> is aware, that at any given time the effluent may contain lead, chromium, chloronated hydrocarbon and extreme carcinogens such as PCBs and nitrogen-bearing compounds. 
<PERSON>Frank Livelli</PERSON>, a retired chemical-company executive who lives near the pipeline, points out that four million gallons a day in only one year is equivalent to the volume of all the water between the sand beach and 150 feet into the surf for almost the entire coastline of the state of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. 
And <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> has been dumping for more than 20 years. 

   For most of this period people living in the area were in ignorance of the pipeline's existence, let alone what was passing through it and into the waters in which they and their children swam. 
Then, four years ago, the pipeline broke, ripping up the pavement at <LOCATION>Ortley Beach</LOCATION> and spewing all over the street. 
Alarmed local residents, like <PERSON>Mr. Livelli</PERSON>, who later helped found Save Our Ocean, soon came upon a <DATE>1983</DATE> report by the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Environmental Protection</ORGANIZATION> which noted that after testing the <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> effluent the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> had stated that never before had it seen waste water with so great a potential for causing cancer, heart disease and birth defects. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> officials deny its operations in any way endanger health and, of course, direct linkages between cause and effect are notoriously difficult to prove conclusively. 

   Particularly disillusioning to <LOCATION>Ocean County</LOCATION> residents is the extent to which elected officials and those charged with the task of environmental protection have given <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> an easy ride. 
At a meeting with concerned citizens in <DATE>1984</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>DEP</ORGANIZATION> commissioner at the time said that if he found the company was contaminating the ocean he would close the beaches and not the pipeline. 
In <DATE>May</DATE>, in legislative hearings on a bill to outlaw the pipeline by <DATE>Jan. 1, 1990</DATE>, officials from the <ORGANIZATION>DEP</ORGANIZATION> actually testified on <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION>'s behalf, a posture that is truly startling when one reviews <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION>'s record in the state. 

   In <DATE>1972</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> was slapped with a 206-count indictment for polluting the <LOCATION>Toms River</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. 
The company agreed to build a waste-water treatment plant, and so the indictment was dropped. 
This plant may, as <ORGANIZATION>Ciba</ORGANIZATION> claims, be a state-of-the-art facility for treating biodegradable wastes, but the <LOCATION>Toms River</LOCATION> operation barely deals in such wastes. 

   In <DATE>1978</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>DEP</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> recognized that there had been serious violations in some monitoring of the company's discharges. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ciba</ORGANIZATION> assured them it would do better, and the agencies looked the other way. 
At the same time, according to a 35-count indictment issued by the state attorney general, the plant began accepting hazardous wastes from 57 corporate warehouses as well as from some non-Ciba operations throughout the country. 
It then began to dump these through the pipeline, the attorney general has charged in this indictment, in violation of the law. 

   In <DATE>1984</DATE>, acting on an inside tip, state police raided the plant and found 14,000 barrels of liquid hazardous waste for which the company had no permit. 
This resulted, a year later, in a 35-count indictment for conspiracy to defraud and deceive the <ORGANIZATION>DEP</ORGANIZATION>, falsification of documents in order to obtain and keep operating permits, and illegally dumping known and unknown hazardous chemicals through the pipeline, on its site and in its landfill. 
Four company executives were named as co-conspirators. 
This indictment is now the subject of a continuing legal wrangle, so the attorney general has since brought another indictment, which has not reached trial. 

   Yet in <DATE>1985</DATE>, while under indictment and despite the fact that it did not meet the minimum standards set by the Clean Water Act and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> state law, <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> got a new five-year permit for ocean discharge from the <ORGANIZATION>DEP</ORGANIZATION>. No doubt heartened by this compliance, the company this year applied for six new permits to bring to <LOCATION>Toms River</LOCATION> a pharmaceutical operation that has destroyed the <LOCATION>Pawtuxet River</LOCATION> and fouled the air in <LOCATION>Cranston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION> 
By <DATE>1981</DATE> the lower end of the <LOCATION>Pawtuxet</LOCATION>, into which <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> had been pouring 1.2 million gallons of waste each day, could support only those organisms that flourish in sewage and toxic waste. 
<ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> is an itinerant of opportunity. 
Having fouled up the <LOCATION>Pawtuxet</LOCATION> and Toms rivers, the company says it's now planning to move its dye operations to <LOCATION>St. Gabriel</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>, by <DATE>1990</DATE>, making some offensive propaganda in the process about the burden of environmental regulation. 

   In <DATE>June</DATE> the company got a tremendous boost from the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> when <PERSON>Chris Dagget</PERSON>, the agency's regional director, argued to members of the <ORGANIZATION>State Assembly</ORGANIZATION> that the pipeline needed to remain open as an option for cleaning up the <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION> Superfund site, which has contaminated over 1,000 wells, forcing homeowners to depend on bottled water. 

   This <DATE>summer</DATE> the air has been thick with cries from politicians of their dedication to the public weal. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> made his vows on the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>'s edge and not so long ago <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> stood in the same place saying the same thing. 
Such abstract talk is easy. 
Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Ciba-Geigy</ORGANIZATION>'s effluent spills steadily, year after year, into the sea, a squalid reminder of the fact that it's one thing to talk about a better <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and quite another to do serious battle with the forces that make it worse. 
In <DATE>May</DATE> the state <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passed the pipeline bill, but earlier this month 34 members of the Assembly abstained from a crucial vote, leaving the bill in limbo until <DATE>September</DATE>, when sessions reconvene. 
On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, Save Our Ocean is holding a memorial service for the ocean at <LOCATION>Ortley Beach</LOCATION>, south of Point Pleasant, on the barrier island. 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> will hold hearings at <ORGANIZATION>Toms River High School</ORGANIZATION> on proposals for cleaning up the Superfund site. 

   ---

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900713-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-13-90 2148EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OceanDumpingFine     07-13 0204</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Dumping Fine,0207</SECOND>
<HEAD>County Fined for Missing Federal Court Deadlines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Nassau County</LOCATION> must pay a <MONEY>$180,000</MONEY> fine for
failing to meet deadlines for ending ocean dumping of sludge, the
   The county, under a court agreement, had been required to award
two sets of contracts by <DATE>May 15</DATE> _ one to acquire sludge dewatering
equipment and a second to build sludge dewatering facilities.
   Failure to award the contracts triggered penalties that
accumulated at a rate of <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> a day from <DATE>May 15 through June 13</DATE>,
then <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> a day from <DATE>June 14 through June 25</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> said.
Nassau has paid the <MONEY>$180,000</MONEY> into an escrow account.
   Had the county begun building its sludge dewatering plant by
<DATE>June 30</DATE>, the penalties would have been forgiven.
   EPA Regional Administrator <PERSON>Constantine Sidamon-Eristoff</PERSON> said the
penalties will continue building and will reach <MONEY>$420,000</MONEY> on <DATE>July 25</DATE>.
   Nassau is one of nine areas in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> that dump
more than 8 million tons of sewage yearly into an <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>
site 115 miles off <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. The eight other authorities are on
or close to schedule for ending their ocean dumping, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091590-0003 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 276404 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 15, 1990, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 6; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
276 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SEWAGE SPILL CLOSES 2 MILES OF BEACHES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DEANNA BELLANDI, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A 2-mile stretch of beach from <ORGANIZATION>Ocean Beach to Mission Beach</ORGANIZATION> was closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> 
and could be shut down for most of the <DATE>weekend</DATE> because a corroded pipe burst, 
sending 50,000 gallons of sewage sludge into the ocean. 
</P>
<P>
The beaches affected are between <ORGANIZATION>Del Monte Avenue</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Ocean Beach</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Ventura 
Place</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mission Beach</LOCATION>, right near the Giant Dipper roller coaster, said Lt. 
<PERSON>Charles Wright</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> city lifeguard. 
</P>
<P>
The beach area in <LOCATION>Ocean Beach</LOCATION> is scheduled to be closed until <DATE>Monday</DATE>, but 
<ORGANIZATION>Mission Beach</ORGANIZATION> could reopen as early as <TIME>this afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
A hole, 3 inches wide and 8 inches long, sent the treated sewage into the <LOCATION>San 
Diego River</LOCATION> flood channel, where it flowed into the ocean, said <PERSON>Dan Child</PERSON>, a 
waste-water treatment superintendent with the city's <ORGANIZATION>Water Utilities 
Department</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The section of pipe that broke was on <ORGANIZATION>Sea World Drive</ORGANIZATION> on the north side of the 
flood channel. 
</P>
<P>
It is part of an 8-mile-long pipe that carries 800,000 gallons of sewage daily 
from the city's sewage-treatment plant on <LOCATION>Point Loma</LOCATION> to sludge-drying basins on 
<LOCATION>Fiesta Island</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Child</ORGANIZATION> said. 
</P>
<P>
The first report of the break came in about <TIME>8:45 a.m.</TIME> Pumps were shut down, 
stopping the rush of sewage in about an hour, Child said. 
</P>
<P>
The beaches were closed because the bacteria in the sewage contaminated the 
water, <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"There's no real way to clean it up," <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said. "It becomes diluted over 
time in the ocean and the bacteria counts are reduced to the point of not being 
dangerous anymore." 
</P>
<P>
Signs are posted on the beaches warning people to stay out of the water. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to becoming sick, people who ignore the signs could be arrested, 
<PERSON>Wright</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, SEWAGE SPILL: Two miles of San Diego beaches could remain closed through 
much of the weekend after a burst pipe allowed 50,000 gallons of sewage sludge 
into the ocean. Warning sign at Dog Beach, above. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881004-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-04-88 2033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-OceanSludge     10-04 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Sludge,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Passes Bill To End Sludge Dumping By 1993</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB McHUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> passed a much-debated
bill that bans the dumping of sewage sludge in the ocean after <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   The measure, adopted by a 416-0 vote, sets a <DATE>Dec. 31, 1992</DATE>
deadline on sludge dumping by the nation's only remaining
practitioners: nine sewage authorities located in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>.
   The compromise bill, climaxing a 10-year legislative effort,
must now be reconciled with a differing version passed by the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE>.
   Sponsors of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> bills say they expect to
reconcile differences at conference sessions beginning <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
Among other things, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> bill sets a <DATE>Dec. 31, 1991</DATE> deadline _
a year earlier than the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I think there's room for compromise,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Frank
Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, sponsor of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> version.
   Under the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan, drafted by a bipartisan coalition of <ORGANIZATION>East
Coast</ORGANIZATION> lawmakers, sludge dumpers would be forced to stop by the <DATE>1992</DATE>
deadline or face stiff penalties.
   ``These penalties will add up to <MONEY>tens of millions of dollars</MONEY> in
a very short time. There's no question but that the fines will make
it financially prohibitive for municipalities to continue dumping
in the ocean beyond the deadline,'' said Rep. <PERSON>William Hughes</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, a prime sponsor of the ban.
   Rep. <PERSON>H. James Saxton</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.J.</LOCATION>, called the bill, ``a vitory in the
continuing fight for clean oceans.''
   Some eight million wet tons of sludge a year are dumped by the
nine agencies at a site about 106 miles east of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> closed a site just 12 miles offshore in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Experts differ on the environmental threat posed by the dumping
of sludge.
   The new bill imposes fees to dumpers of <MONEY>$200</MONEY> a ton beginning
<DATE>Jan. 1, 1989</DATE>.
   Dumpers meanwhile would be required to negotiate individual
timetables for ending their dumping with federal authorities.
   Those agencies that cannot strike a deal will pay staggered fees
through <DATE>1992</DATE> of up to <MONEY>$400</MONEY> a ton.
   Any authority still dumping sludge in the ocean by <DATE>1993</DATE> would be
forced to pay penalties over and above the fees. Those fines begin
at <MONEY>$800</MONEY> per ton and more than double that by <DATE>1999</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> alone would be liable for more than <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY> if the
state is still dumping by the year <DATE>2000</DATE>.
   The proposed ban was at first opposed by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> lawmakers and
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Edward I. Koch</PERSON>, who complained that the deadline
would be impossible to meet.
   Proponents countered that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> orginally banned ocean sludge
dumping as of <DATE>1981</DATE>, a deadline suspended in a successful lawsuit by
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. The original deadline was set in a <DATE>1978</DATE> law, after which
some 300 industries and 100 municipalities stopped dumping.
   The compromise was reached after inclusion of a system of trust
funds, under which fees and fines would be used to develop
alternatives to dumping.
   The political climate became right for the bill this year, after
repeated and widely-publicized incidents of beach pollution.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881118-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-18-88 2020EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-OceanDumping     11-18 0313</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ocean Dumping,300</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Signs Bill To End Ocean Dumping</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB McHUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> signed legislation
designed to end the dumping of sewage sludge in the ocean by <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   The bill is aimed at closing the nation's last remaining sludge
dumping site, some 106 miles off the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> coast.
   The only agencies affected by the new legislation are three
regional sewage authorities in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, including <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>,
and six authorities in northern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   No other jurisdiction in the nation still dumps its sludge at sea.
   Under the measure, the agencies must end their dumping by <DATE>Dec.
31, 1991</DATE>, or pay stiff penalties amounting potentially to <MONEY>millions
of dollars</MONEY>.
   Meanwhile, the dumpers will begin next year to pay increased
fees, separate from potential penalties, for use of the ocean as a
dump site.
   Both the fees and fines, if needed, will be pooled to help
develop alternate disposal methods.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s signing of the bill, without comment, climaxes a 10-year
legislative effort to halt the dumping. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> voted a first ban
in <DATE>1978</DATE>, effective in <DATE>1981</DATE>, which was successfully challenged in
federal court by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. The dumping has continued under court
authority since.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> lawmakers and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Edward I. Koch</PERSON> opposed the
new measure, but ultimately agreed to a compromise in the face of
mounting congressional pressure.
   ``Ocean dumping is one of the most insidious forms of pollution
ever inflicted on the environment,'' said Rep. <PERSON>William Hughes</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, the principal author of the bill, after it was signed into
law.
   ``We're taking big strides in our effort to clean up the ocean,''
added <PERSON>Sen. Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, the chief <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> sponsor.
   Sen. <PERSON>John Chafee</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-R.I.</LOCATION>, said, ``The environmental health of the
oceans and the economic health of the fishing industry demand that
we end the dumping.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880912-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-88 2338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-FighterCrash     09-12 0232</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Fighter Crash,0240</SECOND>
<HEAD>F-14 Crashes in Atlantic</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HATTERAS, N.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An F-14 Tomcat jet fighter crashed in the
<LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, and one crewman was killed and the other
missing, the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> said.
   A fishing vessel, Jo-Boy II, managed to pick up one crewman, but
he was pronounced dead when he arrived by helicopter at <ORGANIZATION>Portsmouth
Naval Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, authorities said.
   A search continued late <DATE>Monday</DATE> for the second flier.
   The F-14 based at <ORGANIZATION>Oceana Naval Air Station</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Virginia Beach</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, went down 22 miles east of <LOCATION>Oregon Inlet</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> spokesman
<PERSON>P.E. Wilkinson</PERSON>.
   The plane, part of <LOCATION>Oceana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Fighter Squadron 143</ORGANIZATION>, was practicing
air combat maneuvers with several other planes, said Lt. Cmdr. <PERSON>Mike
John</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Fleet</ORGANIZATION> air force.
   The identities of the dead man and the missing man were withheld
pending notification of relatives.
   Two charter boat captains carrying fishing parties watched from
several miles away as the F-14 hit the water.
   ``I saw a streak of flame and a great big fireball about 500
feet from the surface,'' said <PERSON>Warren Gallop</PERSON>, captain of the <ORGANIZATION>Mighty
Wind</ORGANIZATION>, which is based at the <ORGANIZATION>Oregon Inlet Fishing Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``I heard
an explosion and I could see stuff flying through the air. It
sounded like a big boom. It scattered stuff over a wide area.''
   <PERSON>John</PERSON> said the <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY> aircraft sank soon after impact.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890502-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-89 1115EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e PM-APonTV-AtlanticRealm ADV03   05-02 0791</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-AP on TV-Atlantic Realm, ADV 03,0807</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wed PMs, May 3</HEAD>
<HEAD>Atlantic Ocean is Star of New PBS Series</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHRYN BAKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To most of us, it's an innocuous strip of blue
that separates the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> on the world map, or
that tedious nothingness that takes hours to go by outside the
window of an airplane.
   But the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>, a shifting, churning, life-giving,
living character, is the star of an ambitious new, three-part
series, ``Atlantic Realm,'' beginning tonight on <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first episode, ``Island Arks,'' examines the origins of the
ocean, from its beginnings some 165 million years ago as little
more than a river separating two continents before they began to
drift apart.
   The series offers scientific and historical data on the
evolution of the ocean, but is thankfully taken up more with superb
photography of wildlife the ocean has spawned than by maps and
charts. One of the highlights of the first episode is the birth of
a litter of lemon sharks in the shallows near the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, an event
never before photographed in the wild.
   Life above the sea is featured in the first episode, especially
the myriad sea birds that live on islands off the coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
where the delicate ebb and flow of the ecology is easily observed _
such as the environmental upheaval caused when mariners introduced
domesticated cats to one small island.
   The series is engrossing and lovely to watch, despite
occasionally overwrought narrative, such this sample from a segment
on <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>: ``Solidified lava is one of the raw materials of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Forged in fire, it's stern but ready to accept the life that
pioneers its surface. Below, the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> marine organisms would
exploit this new territory, but here, laid bare to the winds of the
air, lichens, mosses and herbs have taken hold along this broad and
rolling swath of the salt that is part of the mid-Atlantic ridge.''
   Phew. Narrator <PERSON>Marty Robinson</PERSON> manages to read such passages with
aplomb if not a breath.
   The series, a joint production of <ORGANIZATION>WTTW</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>,
was created by <PERSON>Rod Redfern</PERSON>, who wrote the book ``The Making of a
Continent'' on which a previous, six-part <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION> television series was
based.
   ``I was looking for something to follow `The Making of a
Continent,''' said <PERSON>Redfern</PERSON> in a statement about ``Atlantic Realm,''
``and the obvious thing was the making of an ocean.'' Redfern's
book on the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> is due out soon.
   Next week's episode, ``Ocean of Light,'' focuses on the effects
of the winds that brush the top of ocean and the life forms that
live near the surface, including whales. The cameras go the
Antarctic for first-time pictures of the underwater ballet of
Weddell seals. Later, they capture the flow of translucent animals
that drift along the surface of the open ocean.
   ``Into the Abyss'' is the series' big finish, with cameras
diving a half-mile below the ocean's surface to examine the strange
creatures that dwell in the lightless depths. The cameras also take
viewers to the longest submerged mountain range on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and take a
peek inside an underwater volcano.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   To most of us, it's an innocuous strip of blue
that separates the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> on the world map, or
that tedious nothingness that takes hours to go by outside the
window of an airplane.
   But the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>, a shifting, churning, life-giving,
living character, is the star of an ambitious new, three-part
series, ``Atlantic Realm,'' beginning tonight on <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first episode, ``Island Arks,'' examines the origins of the
ocean, from its beginnings some 165 million years ago as little
more than a river separating two continents before they began to
drift apart.
   The series offers scientific and historical data on the
evolution of the ocean, but is thankfully taken up more with superb
photography of wildlife the ocean has spawned than by maps and
charts. One of the highlights of the first episode is the birth of
a litter of lemon sharks in the shallows near the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, an event
never before photographed in the wild.
   Life above the sea is featured in the first episode, especially
the myriad sea birds that live on islands off the coast of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>
where the delicate ebb and flow of the ecology is easily observed _
such as the environmental upheaval caused when mariners introduced
domesticated cats to one small island.
   The series is engrossing and lovely to watch, despite
occasionally overwrought narrative, such this sample from a segment
on <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>: ``Solidified lava is one of the raw materials of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Forged in fire, it's stern but ready to accept the life that
pioneers its surface. Below, the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> marine organisms would
exploit this new territory, but here, laid bare to the winds of the
air, lichens, mosses and herbs have taken hold along this broad and
rolling swath of the salt that is part of the mid-Atlantic ridge.''
   Phew. Narrator <PERSON>Marty Robinson</PERSON> manages to read such passages with
aplomb if not a breath.
   The series, a joint production of <ORGANIZATION>WTTW</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION>,
was created by <PERSON>Rod Redfern</PERSON>, who wrote the book ``The Making of a
Continent'' on which a previous, six-part <ORGANIZATION>PBS</ORGANIZATION> television series was
based.
   ``I was looking for something to follow `The Making of a
Continent,''' said <PERSON>Redfern</PERSON> in a statement about ``Atlantic Realm,''
``and the obvious thing was the making of an ocean.'' Redfern's
book on the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> is due out soon.
   Next week's episode, ``Ocean of Light,'' focuses on the effects
of the winds that brush the top of ocean and the life forms that
live near the surface, including whales. The cameras go the
Antarctic for first-time pictures of the underwater ballet of
Weddell seals. Later, they capture the flow of translucent animals
that drift along the surface of the open ocean.
   ``Into the Abyss'' is the series' big finish, with cameras
diving a half-mile below the ocean's surface to examine the strange
creatures that dwell in the lightless depths. The cameras also take
viewers to the longest submerged mountain range on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and take a
peek inside an underwater volcano.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed PMs, May 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880902-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-02-88 1229EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-Bush 1stLd-Writethru   09-02 0750</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0449,750</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Takes To Beaches On Environmental Campaign</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: TOPS with 5 grafs to UPDATE with Bush speech today; SUBS 8th
graf pvs to edit; picks up 9th graf pvs, bgng: Bush sought...</NOTE>
<HEAD>Precede NORWALK, Conn.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BELMAR BEACH, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fiery <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> stepped up his
attack on opponent <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' environmental record today,
accusing him of trying to pollute the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> waters where
sewage has washed up on the beach this <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The Republican presidential nominee spoke on a sunny beach that
in the past has been closed because of medical waste and sewage
washing ashore.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> referred to the <DATE>1985</DATE> request from <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> as governor of
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> to dump his state's sewage off the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> coast
at a site used by <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told a few hundred supporters in beach attire that the next
time <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> visits the state they should ``be sure to ask him why
did you want to dump <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> sludge off our coast in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. ...
Why did you pledge a clean ocean to the people of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> when
your own state applied to pollute it?''
   Speaking on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Norwalk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, of what he called the
``natural heritage that we all have to do something about,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
called himself a `Teddy Roosevelt Republican'' on the environment.
Roosevelt was an avid conservationist responsible for setting aside
millions of acres of forests and launching irrigation and
reclamation projects.
   Aware that Republicans and the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration in
particular are a target of unrelenting criticism by environmental
groups, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> declared nonetheless, ``We're not going to give this
constituency away to the Democrats.''
   He recalled his acceptance speech at the Republican convention
last month when he said he wanted to make the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> ``a
gentler nation.''
   ``This is part of what I mean, a nation in which all of us treat
the environment with greater reverence and greater respect,'' he
said.
   Today <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was continuing his effort to pull votes from the
environmentally-minded with speeches to residents of <LOCATION>Belmar Beach</LOCATION>
and later in <LOCATION>New Castle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> sought to embarrass <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> on a day when the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Herald</ORGANIZATION>
headlined a new poll that put him neck-and-neck with the governor
in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   ``Fantastic,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said when reporters showed him the newspaper.
   ``I can't believe it,'' he said. ``In <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>?''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> survey found <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> tied in the state at <PERCENT>42
percent</PERCENT> each. The poll of 400 likely voters conducted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> had
a 5-point margin of error.
   A poll for the <ORGANIZATION>Herald</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>July</DATE> found <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> leading by 14
percentage points.
   In his <LOCATION>Boston Harbor</LOCATION> tour, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> laid the fault on <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> for
failing to clean up the harbor, which has become a major
embarrassment to the state, with half a billion gallons of raw
sewage being dumped in daily. Construction of new wastewater
treatment facilities is now beginning under federal court order.
   He said <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> had been intent on delay, to do ``anything but
clean up'' the sewage and sludge and twice sought federal waivers
of the Clean Air Act requirement for secondary treatment of sewage.
   ``I don't call that leadership, and I certainly don't call that
competence,'' he said in reference to <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' statement that
voters should look for competence in this presidential race.
   In his first term as governor <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> prepared a waiver request
to the federal government, but it actually was filed by his
successor Gov. <PERSON>Ed King</PERSON> in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   Dukakis filed the second waiver request in <DATE>1984</DATE>. In <DATE>1985</DATE>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> sued the state to force a cleanup.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> also criticized <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> for promising to end the dumping
that has left medical waste cluttering <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> beaches, when
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> himself as governor asked for federal permission to dump
waste off <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>.
   ``The stealth candidate is at it again, making promises on one
hand but hiding his secret record on the other,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said.
   The <DATE>1985</DATE> Massachusetts request to the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> was for temporary
permission to dump 106 miles offshore where <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
were already dumping. A compromise arrangement allowed
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> to dump further out beyond the continental shelf.
   Standing on a <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> ferry boat off of <LOCATION>Deer Island</LOCATION>, the future
site of a new sewage treatment plant near the harbor mouth, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
called for a ban on ocean dumping of sewage sludge after <DATE>1991</DATE>, and
for greater <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> efforts and <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> participation in catching
violators.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880730-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-30-88 1231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SeaScare Bjt   07-30 0700</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sea Scare, Bjt,0718</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sewage and Medical Waste Make For Fear And Loathing At The Beach</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY13, NY16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARJORIE ANDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>summer</DATE> of '88 is already over in the minds
of countless <ORGANIZATION>Northeastern</ORGANIZATION> beach lovers revolted by a tide of dead
rats, syringes and sewage that has left miles of shoreline deserted
and seaside businesses shuttered even on the hottest days.
   ``They finally did it _ they ruined the beach,'' said <PERSON>Joe
Lovecchi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION>. He will limit his ocean dips to ``ankles only
for the rest of the season.''
   Others are not so brave. Attendance has plummeted at <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>
beaches since the scare began <DATE>July 6</DATE>, when needles and vials of
blood, some of which tested positive for the AIDS virus, began
washing up along <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>'s 120-mile southern shore.
   Since then, on beaches from <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>,
lifeguards and rangers with rakes and rubber gloves have harvested
gruesome garbage after nearly every high tide.
   ``Whoever did this is the <PERSON>Typhoid Mary</PERSON> of garbage carters,''
said <ORGANIZATION>New York City Parks Commissioner Henry Stern</ORGANIZATION>. ``This has
ruined the <DATE>summer</DATE> for millions of people.''
   Although health officials say chances of contracting AIDS from
ocean-borne waste are almost nil, in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> officials are playing
it safe. When needles are found, the beach is closed for at least
two relatively ``clean'' high tides.
   <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> beaches remained open after syringes, catheter and
colostomy bags and intravenous tubing washed up last week;
scientists doing computer studies of ocean currents said the waste
was probably dumped near <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in <DATE>June</DATE>.
   Medical waste is not the only reason beaches have closed.
Beaches around <LOCATION>Asbury Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, were closed because of
contamination from human waste, which is a more potent threat to
public health than hospital waste.
   As in past summers, high levels of fecal coliform bacteria also
have forced beaches to close on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION> and around <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>
harbor.
   <PERSON>John Rafferty</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> lifeguard, said he will enter the
water only when his job requires it.
   ``I'm not afraid of AIDS. It's just dirty water. The water's
been dirty for years. I don't enjoy swimming in it,'' he said.
``You come out and you don't feel refreshed.''
   Lovecchi has taken the same position. ``Why take a chance? It's
not just AIDS, but hepatitis, a host of things,'' he said. ``If
they opened up a stand selling <ORGANIZATION>Clorox</ORGANIZATION>, they could sell out to
people who want to wash their feet.''
   Bleach might sell, but hot dogs and beers are not in demand at
deserted beaches.
   ``It's real bad,'' said <PERSON>Wayne Horner</PERSON>, who operates the food
concession at <LOCATION>Jacob Riis Park</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, where attendance is down
from a million last <DATE>July</DATE> to 457,000 this month. <PERSON>Horner</PERSON> said sales
are down by two-thirds. ``Nobody's coming out and there's nothing
we can do.''
   Fear and confusion did not prevent <PERSON>Loli Reyna</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION> from
taking her two young children to the beach last week.
   ``If they get scared of the ocean now, they're never going to go
in again,'' she said. ``Nobody gets AIDS at the beach. You use
drugs and needles, you get AIDS.''
   Problems with sewage plants also have contributed to the beach
crisis. An old sewage plant in <LOCATION>Asbury Park</LOCATION> overflowed and dumped
waste into the ocean; the nearby town of <LOCATION>Bradley Beach</LOCATION> is now
threatening to sue <LOCATION>Asbury Park</LOCATION> for lost business.
   Heavy rains are being blamed for drowning dozens of sewer rats
that washed ashore in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. While they have determined that the
rats didn't come from a lab, officials haven't pinpointed the
source of the medical garbage.
   ``It's real possible all the material came from the same
source,'' said <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> Sanitation Commissioner <PERSON>Brendan
Sexton</PERSON>. ``There are particular outlets and people we are watching.''
   Among lifeguards, who frequently outnumbered sunbathers last
week, there was an almost fatalistic consensus: Tidal debris is not
new and garbage of all kinds will continue to wash ashore as long
as offshore dumping continues.
   ``Things have been washing up for a long time, but AIDS is
scaring people so much they are blowing it out of proportion,''
said lifeguard <PERSON>George Triffon</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880905-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-05-88 1245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BeachWaste-Congress     09-05 0724</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Beach Waste-Congress,690</SECOND>
<HEAD>Congress Expected To Pass Legislation To Combat Medical Waste</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CALLAHAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With uncharacteristic speed, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is
expected in its final weeks to create a new law to combat what has
become one of the biggest and most emotional problems of the <DATE>summer</DATE>
of '88 _ medical waste that has invaded and shut down some of
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s favorite beaches.
   Intense pressure from outraged citizens has driven <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to
hold a series of public hearings, including one this week on <LOCATION>Long
Island</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Jones Beach</LOCATION>, and at least one measure and maybe more will
be passed before the legislative year ends, lawmakers and
environmental activists predicted.
   Separate measures to create a waste tracking system and to
establish specific criminal penalties for medical waste dumping
passed the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> before the <DATE>August</DATE> recess. Similar measures are
pending in various <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committees.
   ``With all the publicity this has gotten, these will sail right
through,'' said <PERSON>John Catena</PERSON>, a science policy analyst at the
<ORGANIZATION>Oceanic Society</ORGANIZATION>, a national environmental group that focuses on
coastal problems.
   ``The fact that you had one of the hottest summers in 50 years
and tens of millions of people ... were unable to make use of the
public beaches really drew the issue right home,'' said <PERSON>Andy Kass</PERSON>,
   Rep. <PERSON>Bruce A. Morrison</PERSON>, a Democrat who represents part of the
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> coast along the <LOCATION>Long Island Sound</LOCATION>, said another reason
for the unusual speed on Capitol Hill is the clarity of the issue.
   ``There's no reputable other side of the issue,'' said <PERSON>Morrison</PERSON>.
``No one can excuse the presence of medical waste in the ocean and
the only way it can get there is from illegal dumping. ... There's
not a lot of technical debate here. We know what we can do. Let's
do it.''
   Environmentalists concede that the medical waste problem poses
much less of a long-term health threat than other issues plaguing
the nation's coastal waters, such as sludge dumping, that have
languished in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for years.
   ``In terms of long-term survival of the ocean, it's not a
serious problem. In terms of impact on people's lives, it is,''
said <PERSON>Andrew Palmer</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>American Oceans Campaign</ORGANIZATION>, another
activist group.
   <ORGANIZATION>Catena</ORGANIZATION> said medical waste simply is ``a much more visible issue.
When it closes your beach down, that makes a lot more rumblings.''
   Many environmentalists see a silver lining in the dirty
syringes, vials, bandages and other hospital debris that has washed
ashore from <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Palmer</PERSON> said public outrage over medical waste has been
transferred to other less well known but potentially more dangerous
coastal pollution problems.
   ``We're seeing it already, and I think that's being translated
to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>,'' he said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Catena</ORGANIZATION> said a bill banning sludge dumping off the <LOCATION>New York-New
Jersey</LOCATION> shore was passed by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> last month because of the
attention surrounding medical waste.
   ``It's helpful, no question about it,'' said <PERSON>Sen. John H.
Chafee</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-R.I.</LOCATION>, a leader in the medical waste fight in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
``It has probably been the best single item to draw attention to
abuse of the oceans.''
   Since incidents of medical waste pollution began making
headlines around the Fourth of <DATE>July weekend</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has passed
a measure by <PERSON>Sen. Frank Lautenberg</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.J.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Chafee</PERSON> to require
hospitals, transporters and disposal companies to adhere to a
manifest system that would give investigators a paper trail to find
the source of illegal dumping.
   The pilot program would cover <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> _ states where much of the dumping is suspected of
taking place. A similar measure is pending in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> also approved amendments to a sludge dumping bill
that would create criminal penalties of up to <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> in fines and
five years in prison for illegal dumping. A <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee has
approved a similar measure.
   Other bills still pending would set up a series of rules for the
handling, treatment, storage, transportation and disposal of
hospital waste.
   But <ORGANIZATION>Catena</ORGANIZATION> warned that proper funding levels must be made
available to back up any new laws.
   ``It's great to have a law issued to address a problem, but if
we don't have the money to enforce it, it's not worth the paper
it's printed on,'' he said.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880830-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-30-88 1306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-NavyDumping     08-30 0244</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Navy Dumping,0249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Navy Will No Longer Dump Medical Waste At Sea</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NORFOLK, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> has ordered ships in the <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION> to stop dumping medical waste at sea, in response to
complaints involving waste that washed ashore.
   Earlier this <DATE>summer</DATE>, beaches in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> were
closed after a large quantity of waste washed ashore. The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> was
not blamed in the dumping.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> admitted <DATE>Aug. 8</DATE> that medical waste was dumped from two
Norfolk-based ships after personnel from the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and the Marines
were used to clean up a 26-mile stretch of <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> beaches
from <LOCATION>Fort Macon</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Emerald Isle</LOCATION>. Sailors and Marines collected what
the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> said was a trashbag full of medical supplies.
   Adm. <PERSON>Frank B. Kelso</PERSON>, head of the 300-ship <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> fleet, said
<DATE>Monday</DATE> he sent a message to all commands on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to cease
dumping at sea.
   ``While only one of these incidents involved a small quantity of
medical waste attributed to <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Fleet</ORGANIZATION> ships, these incidents
clearly dictate increased emphasis on proper disposal of all types
of waste,'' <PERSON>Kelso</PERSON> said.
   Regulations will be adopted immediately by ship commanders that
would require special handling of all potentially infectious
medical waste, he said.
   Kelso defined potentially infectious waste as disposable medical
supplies designed for use in diagnosis, treatment, laboratory
testing or training. Those items will include all sharp objects,
containers of blood and blood products, pathology specimens and
tissue, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881213-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-88 1203EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OceanPollution     12-13 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ocean Pollution,0398</SECOND>
<HEAD>Attorneys General Say Bush Must Attack Ocean Pollution</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH J. HARPAZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The attorneys general of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
_ where beaches were littered by medical waste and other pollution
last <DATE>summer</DATE> _ have presented an anti-pollution plan they hope will
become a blueprint for a national program.
   <PERSON>Cary Edwards</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> said
<DATE>Monday</DATE> that the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration will have to lead an aggressive
attack if the nation's oceans and beaches are to be cleaned up.
   ``The president-elect said he was going to do things differently
than the present administration,'' said <PERSON>Abrams</PERSON>. ``He said he was
going to do more vigorous enforcement. We are going to push for this
agenda. Our role is to be the people's advocate.''
   The two officials said attorneys general from around the country
would lobby for the plan, ``A Blueprint to End Ocean Pollution,'' to
be adopted as comprehensive national anti-pollution program. The
plan was issued by the <ORGANIZATION>National Association of Attorneys General</ORGANIZATION>,
which <ORGANIZATION>Abrams</ORGANIZATION> heads.
   ``We once felt the oceans were so big we could not destroy them,
but we're now realizing that's not the case,'' said <PERSON>Abrams</PERSON>.
   Added <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>, ``Anybody who thinks they can stop the dumping of
syringes and they're going to clean up the ocean, they're crazy.''
   <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> said his investigation into the source of debris that
turned up on the <LOCATION>Jersey</LOCATION> shore in the <DATE>summers of 1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> found
that ``there was no mad dumper. The mad dumper was the American
lifestyle.
   ``The federal government and the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> must weigh in on the
problem,'' he added. ``It can't be dealt with alone by any
individual states.''
   The blueprint offers proposals to:
   _Upgrade sewage treatment plants.
   _Remove toxins from industrial waste water.
   _Promote recycling.
   _Control runoff from fertilizer, pesticides and other chemicals.
   _Expand research on water quality.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Increase Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> surveillance to prevent ocean dumping.
   _Aggressively enforce existing anti-pollution laws.
   <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> said a top priority was ending sewage overflow, or the
dumping of raw or poorly treated sewage into bodies of water when
sewage treatment plants are overwhelmed by the volume of waste water
during storms.
   Ending the dumping of sewage sludge at sea is another priority,
the two men said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880820-0062 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-88 1926EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather     08-20 0256</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Experts Watching Two Tropical Depressions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forecasters at the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>
hurricane center were watching two tropical depressions that formed
in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   One formed at <TIME>midday</TIME> about 150 miles southeast of the
southernmost <LOCATION>Cape Verde</LOCATION> islands, off the African coast, and was
moving west at 15 to 20 mph. It was expected to continue that
movement and gradually strengthen, the weather service said.
   The depressions's highest sustained winds were estimated at
about 30 mph, with higher gusts in squalls.
   The second depression was just south of <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION> in the
<LOCATION>Windward Islands</LOCATION>, which are in the Lesser Antilles, and was moving
west at near 15 mph. Highest sustained winds were estimated at 30
mph, but the depression was expected to strengthen as it moved into
the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Caribbean</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The weather service urged small boats in the <LOCATION>Windward Islands</LOCATION> to
stay in port.
   Depressions are upgraded to named tropical storms when their
sustained winds reach 39 mph and to hurricanes when winds hit 74
mph. There have been three tropical storms so far in the <DATE>1988</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Ocean</ORGANIZATION> hurricane season, but none reached hurricane
strength.
   Meanwhile, a tropical wave _ a weather system weaker than a
tropical depression _ was moving northwest <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after dumping
almost 6{ inches of rain in <LOCATION>West Palm Beach</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Showers and
thunderstorms from the wave were expected to leave as much as four
inches of rain over parts of <LOCATION>Central and North Florida</LOCATION> by <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06306002 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06306002 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; WEATHER  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Coastal communities from Maine to Florida began assessing damage today as they
rode out the last hours of a fierce Atlantic storm that washed away buildings
and roads, eroded beaches and was blamed for as many as four deaths.;   The
intense extra-tropical storm was winding down today. But a separate storm
continued to dump heavy snow from the Rockies to Texas to the Great Lakes
region.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  STORMS LASH EAST COAST, MIDWEST  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     It was ugly along the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> in the aftermath of the onslaught.;   "It
looks like someone ripped open the ocean floor and dumped it on the roadway,"
said <PERSON>Ilyas Bhatti</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Revere</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>;   The scene up and down the coast was
littered with demolished seawalls, flattened homes, torn-up beaches and ruined
roads.;   A fisherman who was swept from a rocky point at <LOCATION>Narragansett</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>,
on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> was missing and presumed dead today, as was a person tossed
from a sailboat off <LOCATION>Cape Hatteras</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>;   The body of a fisherman swept out
to sea in <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, was found under a drawbridge.;   The search
resumed today for an <ORGANIZATION>Air National Guardsman</ORGANIZATION> whose four fellow crew members
were rescued after their helicopter went down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION> south of
<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> as it returned from a rescue mission.;   Thousands
of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> residents were forced to flee their
oceanfront homes, many of which were severely damaged or destroyed. Several
<LOCATION>Cape Cod</LOCATION> homes collapsed into the sea, as did several on <LOCATION>Long Island.</LOCATION>;  
Damage in <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> was also extensive, and Gov. <PERSON>Jim Florio</PERSON> declared a state
of emergency in four coastal counties.;   "We literally lost our whole beach,"
said Police Chief <PERSON>Kenneth Johnson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Sea Bright</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, where about 1,300
people were evacuated <DATE>Thursday</DATE> after waves came crashing over a seawall.;  
<LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Gateway National Recreation Area</ORGANIZATION> at <PERSON>Sandy Hook</PERSON> lost about 200
feet of beach, and part of the <LOCATION>Atlantic City Boardwalk</LOCATION> was damaged.;   In
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, towering ocean swells destroyed a <LOCATION>Lake Worth</LOCATION> fishing pier, slammed
cars into one another and caused severe beach erosion in the southern end of
the state.;   Eight windows in the <ORGANIZATION>Beach Club</ORGANIZATION> at The Breakers hotel in <LOCATION>Palm
Beach</LOCATION> were shattered by huge waves, and the three bridges to <LOCATION>Palm Beach</LOCATION> were
damaged and closed to all but local traffic.;   Meanwhile, the huge cold front
lingering over the <LOCATION>northern Plains</LOCATION>, parts of the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southwest</ORGANIZATION> brought
a foot or more of snow to parts of the <ORGANIZATION>Rockies</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Plains</LOCATION> and the upper
Midwest.;   Snow closed down some schools and offices. In <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, the
20.4-inch total between <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>morning and this morning</TIME> set a record for a
24-hour snowfall, topping a 20-inch snowfall in <DATE>January 1982</DATE>. And it was still
snowing. <PERSON>John Ostrom</PERSON>, operations coordinator at Minneapolis-St. <ORGANIZATION>Paul
International Airport</ORGANIZATION>, said the airport was down to one runway <TIME>this morning</TIME>.
"We're out there constantly," he said. "You close one runway, you open
another. We can barely keep up."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911101  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  14A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  493  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, November 1, 1991
00306002,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891025-0109 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891025 </DD>
<AN> 891025-0109. </AN>
<HL> International:
@  De Beers Digs for Diamonds in the Dunes
@  ---
@  Gems' Glitter Lures Man,
@  Machine to Remote African Coast
@  ----
@  By Roger Thurow
<DD> 10/25/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> AFRIC DBRSY </CO>
<IN> PRECIOUS METALS, STONES, GOLD, SILVER (PCS)
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD) </IN>
<DATELINE> ORANJEMUND, Namibia  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
"They figure it's not a very good advert." 
