<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5381 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas069_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Holds Talks With Vo Van Kiet </H4>

<F P=102> BK1104143194 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network in Vietnamese 
1100 GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1104143194 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network </F>
<F P=105>  Vietnamese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Immediately after the official ceremony held at the 
Presidential Palace in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> to welcome visiting Australian 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
expressed his delight in welcoming his Australian counterpart in 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, considering this a new development in the relations of 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> wished Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> success 
in his visit, thereby significantly contributing to 
strengthening the Vietnam-Australia relations. 
  In his reply, Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> said: <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has 
scored new, significant progress in various aspects, and I wish 
to see this during my visit. On this basis, the <ORGANIZATION>Australian 
Government</ORGANIZATION> will find ways and means to help <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to develop 
its economy and participate in other activities in the region. 
We understand the significance of this historical visit, and we 
will do our best to strengthen the relations of friendship and 
cooperation between our two nations. 
  Dear friends, <TIME>this morning</TIME> the <ORGANIZATION>SRV Government</ORGANIZATION> delegation, 
led 
by Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, held talks with the <ORGANIZATION>Australian 
Government</ORGANIZATION> delegation led by Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. 
  At the talks, both sides informed each other of the 
situation 
in their respective countries and about issues of mutual 
concern, reviewed cooperation during the past period, and 
frankly exchanged views on various issues aimed at improving 
Vietnam-Australia cooperation. 
  This afternoon, Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his 
entourage 
visited the <ORGANIZATION>Central Institute of Ophthalmology</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>ANZ Bank</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. The same afternoon, SRV President Le Duc Anh 
cordially received Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and the 
Australian distinguished guests. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5758 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas071_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-071 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  12 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Do Muoi Meets Keating </H4>

<F P=102> BK1204152294 Hanoi VNA in English 1434 GMT 12 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1204152294 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>April 12</DATE> -- Party General Secretary Do 
Muoi received this afternoon in <LOCATION>Ho Chi Minh City</LOCATION> Australian 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his party on a current visit to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. During the meeting, General Secretary Do Muoi and Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> exchanged views on the issues of common 
concern. They expressed their satisfaction at the fine 
development of the friendship and cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
and their precious assistance and support given to the 
Vietnamese people in national development. 
  He reaffirmed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s persistent policy of renovation. He 
said he hoped that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> would make active contributions to 
the common efforts of the people in the region and in the world 
for the peace, stability, cooperation and development. 
  General Secretary Do Muoi highly valued the Australian 
Government's good will, and [words indistinct] multi-faceted 
cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and Australian further development 
following <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  For his part Prime Minister <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> spoke highly of the fine 
results of the talks and contacts between his delegation and the 
Vietnamese side. He said that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> had a 
number of similar points and that the economies of the two 
countries could supplement to each other [words indistinct] the 
trade and cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> would 
develop further. He reconfirmed the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s 
continuation to support the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s economic reform and 
development as well as in the fields of education and public 
health. 
  The Australian prime minister [words indistinct] improvement 
of relations between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> and other countries 
in the region as well as the big countries and considered it a 
positive factor to peace and development in the region and the 
world as a whole. 
  On this occasion, Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> invited 
General 
Secretary Do Muoi to visit <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The Vietnamese leader 
accepted the invitation with pleasure. Also present at the 
reception were Deputy Foreign Minister <PERSON>Le Mai</PERSON>, Vietnamese 
Ambassador to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> <PERSON>Nguyen Thanh Chau</PERSON> [name and title as 
received] and Australian Ambassador to <PERSON>Vietnam Michael John 
Potts</PERSON>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his entourage left <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> 
<TIME>this 
morning</TIME> for <LOCATION>Ho Chi Minh City</LOCATION>. 
  The second leg of their <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> visit they were seen off by 
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON> on behalf of Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo 
Van Kiet</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4869 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas066_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-066 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Australian Prime Minister Arrives </H4>

<F P=102> BK0504140294 Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network in 
Lao 1200 GMT 5 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0504140294 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Lao </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpts] In response to an invitation from His 
Excellency [<LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, prime minister of our Lao 
People's Democratic Republic [LPDR], at <DATE>1700 today</DATE> <PERSON>H.E. Paul 
Keating</PERSON>, prime minister of the Commonwealth of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, his 
wife, and a high- level delegation of the Australian Government 
arrived in <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> via special plane for a two-day official, 
friendly visit to our country. <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, his wife, and 
delegation were welcomed upon their arrival at <LOCATION>Wattai Airport</LOCATION> by 
<PERSON>H.E. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, prime minister of the LPDR, and his 
wife; <PERSON>H.E. Khamphoui Keoboualapha</PERSON>, deputy prime minister and 
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Planning and Cooperation Committee</ORGANIZATION>; <PERSON>Somsavat 
Lengsavat</PERSON>, minister of foreign affairs; Osakan Thammatheva, 
minister of information and culture; <PERSON>Seun Phetsanghan</PERSON>, deputy 
minister of communications, transport, posts, and construction; 
<PERSON>Bouason Boupphavan</PERSON>, deputy minister attached to the Prime 
Minister's Office; <PERSON>Thongsavat Bouppha</PERSON>, deputy minister of 
foreign affairs; and <PERSON>Vang Lattanavong</PERSON>, ambassador extraordinary 
and plenipotentiary of the LPDR to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>; along with cadres 
concerned and a large crowd of <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> residents. [passage 
omitted on details of welcoming ceremony] 
  After the official welcoming ceremony, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and his wife led <PERSON>H.E. Australian</PERSON> Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, his wife, and delegation from <LOCATION>Wattai 
Airport</LOCATION> in a motorcade to the government guest houses in 
<LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> capital. 
  At <DATE>1900</DATE>, <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, together with his wife and 
party, 
paid a courtesy call on <PERSON>H.E. Nouhak Phoumsavan</PERSON>, president of the 
LPDR, at <ORGANIZATION>Hokham Hall</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>Presidential Office</ORGANIZATION>. Later, at 
<DATE>1930</DATE>, <PERSON>Keating</PERSON>, his wife, and party are scheduled to attend a 
banquet organized in their honor at the <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister's Office</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> by <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and his wife. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5194 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_k_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Sidney Transfers Border Facility to Government </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Sidney Transfers Border Facility to Government </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0704113394 Vientiane KPL in English 0828 GMT 7 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0704113394 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 7</DATE> (KPL) -- Australian Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, yesterday morning handed over to Lao 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> the border control building on 
the Lao side of the friendship bridge. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Vang Lattanavong</PERSON>, Lao ambassador to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Mr. 
Michael Mann</PERSON>, Australian ambassador to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> were among high 
ranking officials from both sides at the solemn hand-over 
ceremony. 
  In his speech, Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> said that 
speaking 
pleased to hand over the border control building to the Lao 
Government and people. He referred to the bridge as a door 
opening up to the development in the country and the adjacent 
facilities were regarded as the key of the development door. 
The building houses immigration, customs, police, banks and 
postal offices. He said that the border control building and 
the Mekong bridge itself could best serve to testify, in the 
concrete term, the fruitful Australian-Lao cooperation and 
friendship. <PERSON>Mr. Paul Keating</PERSON> congratulated both Australian and 
Lao technicians and workers whose high sense of responsibility 
fullfilled the construction targets in terms of time and budget. 
Australian prime minister touched upon the significance of the 
Australian-Lao agreement for the promotion and protection of 
investment which would help establish confidence for potential 
Australian investors. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> in his return 
address, speaking on behalf of the Lao people, said that the 
facilities were built with Australian grant. Apart from the 
Mekong bridge, the border control building, the gifts of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> and people to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, would facilitate the 
work of the Lao personnel. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> expressed thanks once again to the 
Australian side for its generosity and good intention. He said 
that the Australian aid projects for <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> were highly 
appreciated. They were the symbol for the ever increasing 
traditional relations of friendship the two countries had 
enjoyed. The Lao prime minister attached great importance to 
the Australian aid which had instrumentally helped building the 
country's economic infrastructure and helped free <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> from a 
state of economic difficulties. 
  After delivering their speeches, both prime ministers 
officially lifted the veil off the building foundation plate. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Paul Keating</PERSON> and his delegation left <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> on board of a 
special plane for an official visit to the <LOCATION>Kingdom</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. 
The Australian prime minister paid a two-day official visit to 
the Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> [Lao People's Democratic Republic] on <DATE>April 5</DATE> and 6. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5468 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas070_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-070 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Vo Van Kiet, Keating Hold Talks </H4>

<F P=102> BK1204003494 Hanoi VNA in English 1511 GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1204003494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>April 11</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
held talks here this morning with Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul 
Keating</PERSON>, now on an official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
Speaking at the talks, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> welcomed 
Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his wife's first 
official friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as an important event, 
opening a new chapter in the relations of friendship and 
cooperation between the two countries. The Vietnamese leader 
informed the Australian prime minister of the achievements 
recorded by the Vietnamese people in the current renovation 
process and in the implementation of the foreign policy of 
independence, sovereignty and openess in the direction of 
diversification and multilateralization of international 
relations. He reaffirmed <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s desire to strengthen the 
relations of friendship and all-sided cooperation with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
on the basis of mutual respect, non-interference in each other's 
<PERSON>Mr.Paul Keating</PERSON> thanked Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and his wife 
and the Vietnamese people for their hospitality. He spoke 
highly of the achievements recorded by the Vietnamese people in 
various fields, particularly economy in the renovation process. 
The two sides expressed their satisfaction at the rapid 
development of the friendship and effective cooperation in many 
fields since Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>'s visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
in <DATE>May 1993</DATE>. They also expressed their wishes to promote the 
multi-sided cooperation between the two countries, and held that 
the two countries could supplement each other in their economic 
development process for the prosperity of each country, as well 
as of the Asian-Pacific region. They exchanged views on 
measures to further strengthen the cooperative relations between 
the two countries. 
  The Vietnamese side highly appreciated <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s policy 
of attaching importance to the development of cooperation with 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in trade, investment and other fields and its aid 
programme to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, especially <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s experience sharing, 
technical assistance and personnel training to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as well 
as its cooperation in building the north-south 500 kv power line. 
  The Australian side pledged to continue its aid to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and said that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was ready to broaden its 
cooperation and assistance to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in the oil and gas 
industry, telecommunications, energy, water resources, 
infrastructure construction, healthcare, education, personnel 
training and preservation of <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s ancient sector. The two 
sides also compared notes on international and regional issues 
of common concern. Early <TIME>this morning</TIME> a state ceremony was held 
at the presidential palace to welcome Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul 
Keating</PERSON>, his wife and their entourage who arrived here 
yesterday. Present at the ceremony were Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON>, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON>, Mayor of <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> Le At Hoi 
and other Vietnamese officials. This evening, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo 
Van Kiet</PERSON> and his wife gave a banquet in honour of Prime Minister 
<PERSON>P.Keating</PERSON>, his wife and other distinguished Australian guests. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5856 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas072_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-072 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Australia's Prime Minister Keating Ends Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Australia's Prime Minister Keating Ends Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1304143894 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network in Vietnamese 
1100 GMT 13 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1304143894 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network </F>
<F P=105>  Vietnamese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his wife 
visited <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh City</PERSON> on 12 <DATE>April</DATE>. Truong Tan Sang, the 
people's committee chairman, held a meeting with the Australian 
prime minister and his entourage that same day. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> expressed his pleasure in 
visiting <PERSON>Ho Chi</PERSON> <LOCATION>Minh City</LOCATION>, a beautiful and lively city of 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He said that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> shared similar 
features in various aspects and that the Australian Government 
wishes to expand cooperation with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in various domains. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> visited the Australian invested 
<ORGANIZATION>BHT Bien Hoa Steel Company</ORGANIZATION> and the Vietnam-Australia joint 
venture <ORGANIZATION>VIDEMIX Prefabricated Cement Block Factory in Thu Duc 
District</ORGANIZATION>. He also met with the Australian community in <LOCATION>Ho Chi 
Minh City</LOCATION>. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his wife left <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh 
City</PERSON> <TIME>this morning</TIME>, 13 <DATE>April</DATE>, concluding his official visit to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with splendid success. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5249 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_n_94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Upcoming Visit of Australia's Keating Hailed </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Upcoming Visit of Australia's Keating Hailed </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0704161594 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 6 
Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0704161594 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Text] Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will pay an 
official visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> shortly. This event is taking place 
nine months after the visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by Vietnamese Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. Here is our comment on the event: 
  The visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by Vietnamese Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON> in last year is considered a historic event in bilateral 
relations and so it will be the coming visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> by 
Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. [sentence as heard] 
  These significant events taken place in less than a year 
prove that relations between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have reached 
a turning point in cooperation for mutual benefit. 
  During the <DATE>last two years</DATE>, the relations between the two 
countries have seen wonderful developments. In <DATE>1992</DATE>, the trade 
turnover between the two countries was less than <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> and 
the figure is 120 times now, reaching <MONEY>$252 million</MONEY>. At present, 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is the sixth biggest investor in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with 23 
projects worth <MONEY>$2.65 billion</MONEY>. However, leaders of the two 
countries will wish to further develop bilateral cooperation, 
especially in trade. These wishes are likely to be achieved. 
  On his visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON> reaffirmed that the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnamese Government</ORGANIZATION> welcomes and will 
create favorable conditions for Australian companies wishing to 
do business with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  For his part, the Australian prime minister also affirmed 
that his country is ready to help <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in transport, 
telecommunications, infrastructure, energy, and (?oil and gas) 
exploration. 
  It is expected that there will be new and positive decisions 
made during the coming visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> by the Australian prime 
minister to make the bilateral cooperation and relationship more 
fruitful. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4870 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas066_k_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-066 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    President Receives Keating </H4>

<F P=102> BK0604104394 Vientiane KPL in English 0802 GMT 6 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0604104394 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 6</DATE> (KPL) -- Lao PDR [Lao People's 
Democratic Republic] President <PERSON>Nouhak Phoumsavan</PERSON> yesterday 
evening received the visiting prime minister of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 
honourable <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, and his party. 
  The Australian prime minister and his party were accompanied 
by Lao Foreign Minister <PERSON>Somsavat Lengsavat</PERSON>. 
  During the meeting lasting about 30 minutes, President 
<PERSON>Nouhak 
Phoumsavan</PERSON> expressed pleasure to see the Australian prime 
minister and his party visiting the country. He said the visit 
was of historic significance in the Lao-Australian relations and 
cooperation, laying a basis for the immediate and long-term 
bilateral relationship and cooperation, and contributing to 
peace, stability, and cooperation in <LOCATION>South-east Asia</LOCATION> and in the 
world. 
  The Lao president highly valued the growing Lao-Australian 
relations and cooperation and believed that these relations 
would be further broadened and more fruitful for the interest of 
the two countries. He thanked the Australian government and 
people for their economic assistance to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> in building 
communication infrastructure, training Lao technicians in 
various fields, and in community development and other projects, 
especially the friendship Mekong river bridge project. All 
these symbolized the fruitful relations and cooperation between 
<LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  On his part, the Australian prime minister expressed 
pleasure 
over a warm hospitality the Lao Government and people had given 
to him and his party. He was pleased to have visited the Lao 
<ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION>, which affirmed the relationship and cooperation between the 
two countries following the visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> in <DATE>December last year</DATE>. He said <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> have had their good diplomatic relations for more than 
forty years and affirmed that he would do his best to expand and 
make the bilateral relations more fruitful. 
  The Australian prime minister added that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> would 
continue its support and assistance to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> that beginning from 
this year the Australian government will establish a four-year 
specific aid project for <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> at a cost of as one million to be 
time [as received] will mobilize Australian businessmen in 
various sectors to invest in the country, such as in 
agriculture, communication, mining and others. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5451 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas070_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-070 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   PASASON Hails `Success' of Keating Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    PASASON Hails `Success' of Keating Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1204090294 Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network in 
Lao 0000 GMT 7 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1204090294 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Lao </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [7 <DATE>April</DATE> PASASON editorial: "New Step for Lao-Australian </F>
Relations and Cooperation"] 
  [Text] By an invitation from His Excellency [<LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Khamtai 
Siphandon</PERSON>, prime minister of the Lao People's Democratic 
Republic [LPDR], <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime minister of the 
Commonwealth of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, led a government delegation to pay an 
official, friendly visit to the LPDR from 5 to 6 <DATE>April</DATE>. During 
the visit, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his 
delegation were accorded a warm welcome by <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and the multiethnic Lao people. <PERSON>H.E. Paul 
Keating</PERSON> and the delegation paid a courtesy call on <PERSON>H.E. Nouhak 
Phoumsavan</PERSON>, president of the LPDR, in an atmosphere of warm 
friendship. It was considered a very significant event in the 
history of good relations between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  An official consultative meeting to exchange views between 
<PERSON>H.E. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON> was held at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister's Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> in an atmosphere of 
profound friendship and mutual understanding. During the 
meeting, the two prime ministers informed each other about the 
domestic situation as well as lines and policies in their 
respective countries, the lines and policies which serve as a 
firm basis for effectively strengthening cooperation for the 
benefit of the peoples of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, thus contributing 
to the common trend of establishing and promoting peace, 
stability, friendship, and cooperation among various countries 
in the region and the rest of the world. 
  Noteworthy is that following the consultative meeting, the 
two sides reached an agreement on investment promotion and 
protection between the two countries. This agreement is 
considered an important basis for improving cooperation between 
the Lao and Australian peoples to a new level -- a level which 
will bring about ever greater benefits for the two countries. 
Following the meeting, the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> pledged to 
continue its support and assistance to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. Regarding this, 
beginning in <DATE>1994</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> will establish a 
47.5 million Australian dollar four-year aid project for <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. 
In addition, the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> has decided to give, 
through the WHO, gratis aid in the form of food worth <MONEY>one 
million Australian dollars</MONEY> to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. It will also continue to 
support and encourage more and more Australian businessmen to 
invest in the LPDR. 
  During the visit, <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON> also attended the hand 
over ceremony of the <ORGANIZATION>Border Control Station</ORGANIZATION> at the Lao-Thai 
Friendship Bridge, which was built with gratis financial aid 
from the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> and people as a gift to the LPDR. 
The assistance given to the LPDR by the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> 
and people in building the <ORGANIZATION>Border Control Station</ORGANIZATION> as well as the 
Friendship Bridge and other projects in the recent past has 
substantially reflected the long-standing relations of 
friendship between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, which have fruitfully 
developed with each passing day. 
  The multiethnic Lao people highly assess the effective 
assistance in various fields given by <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, and consider it 
infrastructure for the LPDR. The multiethnic Lao people also 
would like to wholeheartedly hail the glorious success of <PERSON>H.E. 
Paul Keating</PERSON> and delegation on their visit to the LPDR, a visit 
which will contribute to further strengthening the already 
effective friendly relations and cooperation between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> for the benefit of the Lao and Australian people as 
well as in the interests of peace, stability, friendship, and 
cooperation for the development in Asia-Pacific and the rest of 
the world. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5099 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas067_k_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-067 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Australian Prime Minister Ends Visit, Departs </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Australian Prime Minister Ends Visit, Departs </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0604132394 Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network in 
Lao 1200 GMT 6 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0604132394 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Lao </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] After attending the ceremony to mark the handover of 
the border immigration station at the Lao-Thai friendship 
bridge, His Excellency [<LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION>] Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> 
bade farewell to <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and 
his delegation at the border station. <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> 
expressed thanks to <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON> for the aid in the border 
station construction. He also hailed the success of the 
high-level delegation of the Government of the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of 
Australia</ORGANIZATION> in its visit to the Lao People's Democratic Republic. 
He wished <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, his wife, and delegation a good 
trip. 
  H.E. Prime Minister and his delegation left <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> for 
<LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> by a special plane <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> for a visit to the 
Kingdom of <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5382 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas069_n_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Editorial Welcomes Keating's Visit </H4>

<F P=102> BK1104160294 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network in Vietnamese 
2300 GMT 10 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1104160294 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam Network </F>
<F P=105>  Vietnamese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Dear friends: Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul 
Keating</PERSON> will pay his first official friendship to our country at 
the invitation of Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. In today's issue, 
NHAN DAN carries an editorial pegged to this event entitled: In 
the Interests of the Vietnamese and Australian Peoples and for 
the <ORGANIZATION>Sake of Peace</ORGANIZATION>, Cooperation, and Development. The editorial 
reads in part as follows: 
  Following the first official visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by our prime 
minister in <DATE>May 1993</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> visit by Australian Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> has drawn the attention of broad sections 
of public opinion in the region and other parts of the world. 
This important event marks a new developmental step in the 
friendly and cooperative ties between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> established diplomatic relations in 
<DATE>1973</DATE>. The friendly and cooperative ties between the two 
countries have continued to develop with each passing day since 
understanding, equality, and mutual benefit. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> highly 
valued <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s renovation achievements in all fields as well 
as <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s foreign policy of diversification and 
multilateralization and its efforts to improve relations with 
many countries in the world, especially in the Asia-Pacific 
region. 
  <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> lifted its trade embargo at an early date and 
resumed its development aid for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. It has also shared its 
experiences and stepped up cooperation with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The 
cooperative ties between the two countries have been improved 
step by step. Both sides have worked together toward the goals 
of implementing agreements on economic and trade cooperation, 
thereby creating favorable conditions for increasing the value 
of bilateral trade activities to <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE> from <MONEY>$2 
million</MONEY> in <DATE>1982</DATE> and to <MONEY>$252 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1992</DATE> and then to <MONEY>$366 
million</MONEY> in <DATE>1993</DATE>. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has become <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s seventh trade 
partner and ranks fifth on the list of foreign investors in 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with 26 projects valued at <MONEY>$776 million</MONEY>. 
  <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has also helped our country with the training of 
hundreds of specialists; the formulation of laws on mining, 
telecommunications, and state management over 
telecommunications; and the enhancement of farmland irrigation, 
hydrometeorological, public health, and tourist sectors in which 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has a need and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has great potential and high 
technologies. 
  Regarding many regional and international issues, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have reached more and more consensus on the need for 
peace, stability, and development in the Asia-Pacific region 
that the two countries have regarded as the top priority 
objectives of their foreign policies. 
  We hope that Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>'s official 
friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> will end in success, help strengthen 
mutual understanding, and lead the multifaceted cooperation 
between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to a higher level, a larger scale, 
and a broader scope for the sake of each country's prosperity 
and in conformity with the common trends of peace, cooperation, 
and development in the Asia-Pacific region. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5445 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas069_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Prime Minister Keating Arrives </H4>

<F P=102> BK1004130694 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 1100 GMT 
10 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1004130694 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s prime minister, <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, has 
arrived in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> for last stop on an Asian tour which has also 
included <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> is the first Australian 
leader to visit <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. Tomorrow, he will hold talks with top 
Vietnamese leaders including President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Communist 
Party General Secretary Doi Muoi</ORGANIZATION>, and the Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van 
Kiet</PERSON>. 
  Australian officials say <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> will take a low-key 
approach to human rights issues despite calls for a strong 
statement from Vietnamese Buddhist group and some Australian 
parliamentarians. The officials say they hope Vietnamese 
officials will finalize arrangement for an Australian 
parliamentary human rights delegation to visit <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> later 
this year, but diplomats say the visit will concentrate on 
expanding economic links with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is currently 
the third largest investor in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> taking <MONEY>$620 million</MONEY> 
[currency not further specified], mostly for oil and 
telecommunications projects. Two-way trade last year was worth 
<MONEY>$366 million</MONEY> with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> running up a <MONEY>$136 million</MONEY> surplus 
through crude oil sales to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> has spent his first 
afternoon in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> sightseeing in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. The formal part of 
the visit will begin in the morning with an official welcome 
before beginning talks with Vietnamese leaders. Graeme Well 
reports <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON>'s main purpose in going to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is to 
assess the potential for economic development and what further 
role <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> can play. 
  [Begin recording] [Well] <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> says <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> has a 
great opportunity to develop and he believes <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> can help 
make a difference in areas like aid programs, education, social 
policies, and commerce. Responding to a call for him to change 
his itinerary to acknowledge Australians who died in the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
War, <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> said he does not discriminate in commemorating 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s war dead. He repeated comments he made last year at 
the opening of the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> Memorial in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Keating</ORGANIZATION> in progress] ...[Words indistinct] same faith in 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and the same belief in our values as every other 
service person did in other (?theaters) of the war. But 
again.... This in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> and, really, in places I am visiting 
there is no natural opportunity as there was in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. [end 
recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5195 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_k_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Media Reports on Khamtai, Keating Statements </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Media Reports on Khamtai, Keating Statements </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0704113994 Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network in 
Lao 1200 GMT 6 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0704113994 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Lao </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] His Excellency [<LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime minister 
of the Commonwealth of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, met with <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister's Office</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> at 
<DATE>0900 today</DATE>. On this occasion, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai 
Siphandon</PERSON> expressed pleasure over and highly appraised the 
official, friendly visit to the Lao People's Democratic Republic 
[LPDR] of <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. He said the visit 
is an event of historic significance in the friendly relations 
and good cooperation between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai</PERSON> expressed the hope that his consultative 
meeting 
and exchange of views with his excellency the Australian prime 
minister will enable both sides to understand ever more 
profoundly the internal situation and policies of each country. 
He said the understanding will serve as a firm basis for 
effective enhancement of cooperation for the benefit of the 
peoples of the two countries, and that it will also contribute 
to common trends for the establishment and promotion of peace, 
stability, friendship, and cooperation among various countries 
in the region and the rest of the world. <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai</PERSON> also 
informed his excellency the Australian prime minister about 
certain problems in the socioeconomic development of the LPDR 
which is entering the eighth year of the implementation of 
comprehensive restructuring. He said: Through the 
implementation of the restructuring policy, the national economy 
has been progressively developed; the average rate of economic 
growth per year is as high as <PERCENT>6.58 percent</PERCENT>; the prices of 
commodities and the kip currency are stable; the living 
conditions and cultural life of the people have explicitly 
improved; and the assistance and cooperation given to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> by 
increased. There are now as many as 410 direct investment 
projects valued at <MONEY>$580 million</MONEY> by foreign countries in <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, 
excluding investment in large-scale hydroelectric projects. 
  Regarding Lao-Australian relations, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> noted that efforts have been made by the two 
countries to promote relations in various fields. He pointed 
out that as of now, bilateral relations between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have expanded ever more extensively and rapidly. <PERSON>H.E. 
Khamtai</PERSON> expressed gratitude to the Australian Government and 
people for their precious assistance given to the Lao Government 
and people in carrying out the socioeconomic development cause 
in the LPDR, in particular in building the communications 
infrastructure as well as training technicians of various 
branches and in community development. <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai</PERSON> reiterated 
that the LPDR is ready to increase cooperation with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> in 
the economic, cultural, scientific, and technical fields. He 
also expressed the hope that the Australian Government will 
continue to support and encourage more and more Australian 
businessmen to invest in the LPDR. 
  Replying, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> expressed thanks to 
the 
<ORGANIZATION>Government</ORGANIZATION> and people of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> for the warm welcome accorded him 
and his delegation during the visit. <PERSON>H.E. Keating</PERSON> noted: 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> have maintained diplomatic relations for 
more than 40 years. It can be assured today about the great 
potential of the friendship. We are two different countries 
which have endured similar problems, for example problems in the 
areas of trade and investment, with a view to making our people 
enjoy security and prosperity. The Australian Government 
pledges to support <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> in carrying out its reform to achieve 
development in the same way other countries do. Regarding 
implementation of reform, the LPDR has put into force the law on 
investment, a law which guarantees security for foreign 
investors. Various Australian companies are now ready to invest 
in <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. 
  In conclusion, the Australian prime minister said: We can 
contribute to the construction and development of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, and on 
the basis of this spirit the <ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> has decided 
to render aid to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> for the construction of this bridge across 
the <LOCATION>Mekong River</LOCATION>. In addition, beginning in <DATE>1994</DATE>, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Australian Government</ORGANIZATION> has decided to set up a four-year 
assistance and cooperation project for <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. This project costs 
more than <MONEY>40 million Australian dollars</MONEY>. Besides, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has 
given <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> gratis aid in the form of food worth <MONEY>one million 
Australian dollars</MONEY>, and another <MONEY>one million dollars</MONEY> of gratis 
aid to preserve the environment in the LPDR. 
  The meeting lasted one hour. Later, <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> attended 
the signing ceremony of a Lao-Australian agreement on investment 
promotion and protection, and a memorandum of understanding on 
the development project of the <PERSON>Se Kaman</PERSON> hyrdoelectric power in 
<LOCATION>Attopeu Province</LOCATION> and the Namcha 1 and 2 hydroelectric works in 
<LOCATION>Vientiane Province</LOCATION>. Signing the agreement and the memorandum for 
the Lao side was <PERSON>Leun Sombounkhan</PERSON>, vice chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Planning 
and Cooperation Committee</ORGANIZATION>; and signing for the Australian side 
was <PERSON>Michael Mann</PERSON>, ambassador extraordinary and plenipotentiary 
of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. Also signing the memorandum on the 
Australian side was <PERSON>Peter Ray</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Hag Enterprise 
Corporation Company</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. The agreement on investment 
promotion and protection between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will serve a 
significant basis in the legal aspect for the two countries to 
march forward to a new level which can bring about ever greater 
benefits to the peoples of the two countries. It will also 
serve as a basis which creates confidence for Australian 
investors to invest in the LPDR. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5727 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas071_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-071 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  12 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Keating Leaves for Ho Chi Minh City </H4>

<F P=102> BK1204122194 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 12 
Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1204122194 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The visiting Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> 
has left <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> for <PERSON>Ho Chi Minh City</PERSON>, continuing his official 
visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. He was seen off by Vietnamese Foreign 
Minister <PERSON>Nguyen Manh Cam</PERSON>, who conveyed him greetings from Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. 
  Speaking to <PERSON>Mr. Cam</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> expressed pleasure at his 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> visit. His meetings with Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> and 
President Le <PERSON>Duc Anh</PERSON> have contributed to better mutual 
understanding and promotion of bilateral ties. He showed 
concern for the development of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in general and <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>, in 
particular. 
  Besides doubling its development assistance to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in 
the 
coming four years, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> will provide <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> with a separate 
aid package for preservation of <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>'s historical areas. 
  <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> highly valued <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s role in the region and 
wished that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> will increase its cooperation with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
to promote development and peace in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4871 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas066_k_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-066 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting Held With Australia in Vientiane </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    PASASON Welcomes Visit </H4>

<F P=102> BK0604082294 Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network in 
Lao 0000 GMT 5 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0604082294 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane Vitthayou Hengsat Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Lao </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Editorial from 5 <DATE>April PASASON</DATE>: "Wholeheartedly Salute and </F>
Welcome the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of Australia Government Delegation</ORGANIZATION>"] 
  [Text] In response to an invitation from His Excellency 
[<LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, prime minister of the Lao People's 
Democratic Republic [LPDR], <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime minister of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of Australia</ORGANIZATION>, will lead a <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of 
Australia Government</ORGANIZATION> delegation on an official, friendly visit 
to the LPDR on 5 <DATE>April</DATE>. The multiethnic Lao people throughout 
the country -- elated at this event, which is significant in 
Lao-Australian relations -- feel greatly honored to have the 
opportunity to welcome the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of Australia Government</ORGANIZATION> 
delegation. 
  This official, friendly visit to the LPDR by the prime 
minister of the Commonwealth of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and his delegation 
follows the official, friendly visit to the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth of 
Australia</ORGANIZATION> by <PERSON>H.E. Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> in <DATE>mid-December 1993</DATE>. The 
visit is considered a new and significant event since the 
over four decades ago. This visit to the LPDR by the prime 
minister of the Commonwealth of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and his delegation 
reflects the Australian people's good friendship with the 
multiethnic Lao people. It is also considered a very 
significant event in the history of relations between the two 
countries. It will, therefore, serve as a firm basis for 
strengthening friendly relations and cooperation effectively in 
the immediate and long terms in the interest of the peoples of 
<LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, thus contributing to the common trend for 
the establishment and promotion of peace, stability, friendship, 
and cooperation among various countries in this region and the 
rest of the world. 
  Laos and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have maintained good relations for a long 
time. Over the past 10 years or so, the two sides have made 
efforts to promote relations in various fields. It is 
noteworthy that following the visit to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>H.E.</LOCATION> Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, Lao-Australian relations have 
developed ever more extensively and rapidly. On this occasion, 
the multiethnic Lao people would like to express their profound 
gratitude to the Australian Government and people for the 
significant support and assistance they have rendered to the Lao 
Government and people in building and developing the LPDR's 
economy and society, especially in building the communications 
infrastructure, training technicians in various branches, and 
developing communities. The assistance in the construction of 
the Friendship Bridge, which serves as a good token of the 
friendly relations and fruitful cooperation between <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, is noteworthy. 
  We wish <PERSON>H.E. Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime minister of the 
Commonwealth 
of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, and his party glorious success in this official, 
friendly visit to the LPDR. Its success which will contribute 
to further promoting and expanding relations and cooperation 
between the two countries ever more fruitfully for the benefit 
of the peoples of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5469 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas070_n_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-070 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    President Meets Keating </H4>

<F P=102> BK1204005794 Hanoi VNA in English 1608 GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1204005794 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>April 11</DATE> -- President Le Duc Anh received 
here today Australian Prime Minister [<LOCATION>P.M.</LOCATION>] <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> who 
pays a courtesy visit to the Vietnamese leader on an official 
friendship visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
  Speaking at the reception, Prime Minister <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> sincerely 
thanked President <PERSON>Le Duc Anh</PERSON> for his reception and highlighted 
the results of the talks he had held earlier with Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>. <PERSON>Mr Keating</PERSON> said that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> was ready to 
increase investment capital and aid for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s development in 
the fields of education, healthcare, mining, telecommunications, 
infrastructure construction, commerce and so on. He expressed 
his pleasure at the achievements gained by the Vietnamese people 
in their renovation process, and he said he believed that 
following his visit the friendship and cooperation between 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> would be further consolidated and 
developed. 
  For his part, President Le Duc Anh welcomed Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Keating</PERSON>'s current <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> visit, and he said he considered it a 
new step of development in the relations between the two 
countries. He sincrely thanked the Australian Government and 
people and <PERSON>P.M. Keating</PERSON> himself for their friendly feelings and 
precious assistance to the Vietnamese people in national 
construction as well as to the Vietnamese immigrants to quickly 
integrate themselves into the community life in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  President Le Duc Anh informed Prime Minister <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> of 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s foreign policy to make friends with all countries in 
the world. He expressed his belief that the relations of 
friendship and cooperation between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> would 
be increasingly developed, thus actively contributing to peace, 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4669 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas064_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-064 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Australian Prime Minister To Visit 5-6 Apr </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Australian Prime Minister To Visit 5-6 Apr </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0204115594 Vientiane KPL in English 0856 GMT 2 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0204115594 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 2</DATE> (KPL) -- <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, prime 
minister of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, will visit Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> [People's Democratic 
Republic] very soon, at the invitation of his Lao counterpart 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, according to a press release issued today by 
the <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister's Office</ORGANIZATION>. The press release indicates that 
the official visit to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> by the Australian prime minister will 
be from <DATE>April 5-6</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5728 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas071_n_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-071 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    More Reports on Summit Meeting With Australia </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Keating Invitation for Do Muoi Chided </H4>

<F P=102> BK1304094994 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0630 GMT 
13 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1304094994 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "International report" program] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s prime minister, <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, is on his 
way home after a three-nation tour of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON>'s trip 
took him to <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, and finally <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, where he 
invited the communist party leader, Do Muoi, to visit <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
It's an invitation the Vietnamese leader accepted and this is 
sure to cause unhappiness among some of the Vietnamese who fled 
their country after the communist's victory in <DATE>1975</DATE> and now live 
in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Christopher Kremmer</PERSON> reports from <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> that <PERSON>Mr. Do 
Muoi</PERSON> will be seen as a more provocative figure than the 
reformist prime minister, <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, whose presence in 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> last year led to demonstrations by Australian 
Vietnamese. 
  [Begin Kremmer recording] It's the oldest rule of war -- 
both 
sides on two-fronts -- and <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> has broken it. His 
invitation to communist party chief Do Muoi proved alienating an 
important lobby group, which so far has remained relatively 
quiet about his visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The invitation was issued 
during what one official described as unusually long and 
interesting talks between <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> and the 76-year-old party 
leader in <LOCATION>Ho Chi Minh City</LOCATION> yesterday. The <ORGANIZATION>VIETNAM NEWS AGENCY</ORGANIZATION> 
later reported that it has been accepted by Do Muoi with 
pleasure. As the party chief has in recent months been visiting 
neighboring <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> countries, an invitation to come to <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
was unexpected. Even a reformist leader like Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo 
Van Kiet</PERSON> attracted the wrath of a small section of the 
Vietnamese community when he visited <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> last year. But 
Do Muoi, head of the party which maintains armed [word 
indistinct] party-rule over <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is an entirely different 
matter. He represents to some Australian Vietnamese a painful 
reminder of a war which did so much damage and deprecation to 
their lives. And as <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> [word indistinct], that it was not 
just the allies who were responsible for atrocities in the war. 
Terror was a weapon used by both sides to polarize communities 
and keep villagers on side. A communist party government is 
still accused by <ORGANIZATION>Asia Watch</ORGANIZATION> and other human right and religious 
groups of serious infringements of civil liberties and political 
rights. Above all the right of the people to choose their 
government at free election. As one commentator remarked 
recently a great deal of history stands between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The same could be said of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
The commentator went on to observe that while communism may be 
dead in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, authoritarianism is thriving. That affects the 
relatives of Australian Vietnamese still living here. Do Muoi's 
communist party is seen by some as bearing most responsibility. 
<PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> has observed that the wounds of war are still deep 
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, but the wounds are also deeply felt by Vietnamese 
who fled their homeland for <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and many of them are 
unlikely to be impressed by the invitation. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5203 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_m_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Thailand </F>
<H3> <TI>   More Reportage on Australia's Keating's Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    More Reportage on Australia's Keating's Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Prime Minister Hosts Banquet </H4>

<F P=102> BK0804083394 Bangkok Radio Thailand Network in Thai 0000 GMT 
8 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0804083394 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok Radio Thailand Network </F>
<F P=105>  Thai </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Prime Minister <PERSON>Chuan Likphai</PERSON> hosted a banquet in 
honor of visiting Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, his 
wife, and his delegation at <ORGANIZATION>Government House</ORGANIZATION> yesterday evening. 
The Australian prime minister and his entourage are currently 
on an official visit to <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> as guests of the <ORGANIZATION>Thai 
Government</ORGANIZATION>. 
  In a welcome speech delivered at the banquet, Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Chuan</PERSON> said that the meeting between the Thai and Australian 
delegations during the visit will provide a good opportunity for 
both sides to develop their existing friendship, create better 
understanding, and expand cooperation between the two countries 
in the exploitation of their energy and potentials. The meeting 
will also enable both sides to find ways to enhance their roles 
in increasing the regional dynamic and collaboration. In 
addition, the prime minister expressed his admiration for 
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s constructive role in the Southeast Asian and 
Asia-Pacific regions. Australian participation in the opening 
of the Thai-Lao Friendship Bridge is an historic event that 
reflects a great achievement resulting from international 
cooperation. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is thereby considered to have a role in 
the process of establishing peace and progress in <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-6142 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas074_n_94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-074 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Visits by Swedish, Australian Leaders Reviewed </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Visits by Swedish, Australian Leaders Reviewed </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1604150994 Hanoi Voice of Vietnam in English 1000 GMT 15 
Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1604150994 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi Voice of Vietnam </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Station commentary] </F>
  [Text] Prime Minister of Sweden <PERSON>Carl Bildt</PERSON> and Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> visited <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in the <DATE>first 
fortnight of April</DATE>. Here is our review of these visits: 
  The two prime ministers came to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> with a view to 
broaden cooperation with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The Swedish prime minister 
inaugurated an <ORGANIZATION>Ericsson</ORGANIZATION> mobile communication system in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Ericsson Group of Sweden</ORGANIZATION> is a well known manufacturer of 
electronic and telecom equipments. The visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> by 
Australian prime minister came after the two countries reached 
an agreement on the construction of My Thuan Bridge crossing the 
<LOCATION>Tien River</LOCATION> in southern <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. This makes <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> rank the 
first among investors in construction in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as well as of 
all <LOCATION>Indochina</LOCATION>. 
  From either side of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> have one 
thing in common, that is to contribute to the construction of 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> infrastructure, one of the most essential needs of 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> at the present moment. 
  The Australian prime minister also announced <MONEY>$140 million</MONEY> of 
aid to <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> to help the latter continue its renovation process. 
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> has also so far [word indistinct] granted aid to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. With the visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> by Prime Minister <PERSON>Carl 
Bildt</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> plans to boost the economic ties with <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. It 
is a new decision taken by <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>. 
  Both Australian and Swedish leaders acknowledged the 
positive 
results of the ongoing renovation process in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. The truth 
created by <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> itself has urged more countries to invest in 
the country. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5380 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas069_n_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Held in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Keating Formally Welcomed </H4>

<F P=102> BK1104055294 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0500 GMT 
11 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1104055294 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s prime minister, <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, has been 
formally welcomed to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in a ceremony at the Presidential 
Palace in <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>. Graeme Well reports <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> has a busy 
round of talks and engagements. 
  [Begin Well recording] <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> is in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> at the 
invitation of Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, who was in <LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION> 
last year. Their talks will cover <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s economic 
development, Australian aid, human rights, and regional issues, 
including security. <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> also hopes to see <ORGANIZATION>Communist 
Party General</ORGANIZATION> Secretary Do Muoi today. He will be meeting 
members of the Australian business community. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is the 
fifth largest investor in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> will also 
visit the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Ophthalmology</ORGANIZATION>, where the <ORGANIZATION>Fred Hollows 
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and Australian Government aid is helping the training 
of surgeons. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-30630 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas124_j_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-124 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Indonesia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Australia's Prime Minister Keating Arrives </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Australia's Prime Minister Keating Arrives </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=105>  Indonesian </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> flew into 
<LOCATION>Jakarta</LOCATION> yesterday afternoon for a three-day working visit to 
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>. Foreign Minister ad interim <PERSON>Susilo Sudarman</PERSON> was on 
hand at the <LOCATION>Halim Perdanakusumah International Airport</LOCATION> to 
welcome Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> and his 26-member 
delegation. 
  According to the schedule, <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> will make a courtesy 
call on President <PERSON>Suharto</PERSON> at <LOCATION>Merdeka Palace</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE> and among 
other things, will discuss the preparations for the upcoming 
<ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION> summit to be held in <DATE>November 1994</DATE>. The Australian prime 
minister will also officially open the Australian trade 
exhibition, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> <DATE>Today 1994</DATE>, tomorrow in <LOCATION>Jakarta</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5432 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas069_m_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-069 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Thailand </F>
<H3> <TI>   Keating Ends Bangkok Visit, Leaves for Vietnam </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Keating Ends Bangkok Visit, Leaves for Vietnam </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK1004121094 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0500 GMT 
10 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK1004121094 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s prime minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> has 
rejected a call to highlight the role of Australian war veterans 
during his visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> yesterday, <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> 
visited the graves of Australians who died working on the 
Thai-Burma railway during the second world war. <ORGANIZATION>National Party</ORGANIZATION> 
leader <PERSON>Tim Fisher</PERSON> has now urged <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> to make a similar 
gesture in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. However, as political correspondent <PERSON>Graeme 
Well</PERSON> reports, <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> said he'll be keeping the focus of his 
visit to economic development. 
  [Begin recording] [Well] Human rights is a sensitive issue 
for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> is expected to raise it. He said an 
Australian delegation will be visiting <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to assess human 
rights. But before leaving <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> for <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> 
played the issue down. 
  [<PERSON>Keating</PERSON>] There is no one particular matter that comes to my 
mind at the moment. So are we engaging the... [pause] I mean... 
I think the important thing about the visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> is that 
I'll be the first Australian prime minister to have gone 
there.... 
  [Well] <PERSON>Mr. Keating</PERSON> says he wants to make certain <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
is involved in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s development. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-4710 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas065_k_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-065 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Agreement on Bridge Signed With Thailand </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Agreement on Bridge Signed With Thailand </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0404125494 Vientiane KPL in English 1022 GMT 4 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0404125494 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 4</DATE> (KPL) -- Lao Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Somsavat Lengsavat</PERSON> and Thai Foreign Minister <PERSON>Prasong Sunsiri</PERSON> on 
<DATE>April 2</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> signed at Lan Xang Hotel in <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> an 
agreement concerning the friendship bridge across the <LOCATION>Mekong 
River</LOCATION>, scheduled to be officially opened on <DATE>April 8</DATE>. 
  The agreement deals with preparation for the official 
opening 
of the bridge in the presence of Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> [Lao People's 
Democratic Republic] <PERSON>Pesident Nouhak Phoumsavan</PERSON> and his majesty 
the king of <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>. On the occasion, Australian Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> will present the bridge, gift from the 
Australian government and people to the people of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, to Lao Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> and Thai Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Chuan Likphai</PERSON>. 
  The agreement represents a legal framework for Lao-Thai 
cooperation in all aspects concerning the management and 
maintenance of the bridge, including the ownership and 
cooperation in dealing with matters that may arise over the 
bridge. 
  This document also stipulates the following terms on the 
operation and maintenance of the bridge. 
  1. The two sides are jointly responsible for the management 
and maintenance of the bridge by equally sharing the cost of its 
management and maintenance. 
  2. A joint commission will be set up to determine and review 
procedures on the management and maintenance of the bridge to be 
carried out by a brigade with its routines according to the 
agreed procedures. 
  3. The sides have agreed that fees for cars passing the 
bridge will be charged only at one time at an equivalent rate as 
vehicles enter the bridge on either Lao or Thai sides, except 
for cargo trucks with drivers which will be charged for the 
passage on both sides. 
  4. The sides have agreed that each will try to simplify its 
transit formalities, making it convenient and fast to ensure the 
effective operation of the bridge. 
  Concerning the ownership over the bridge, the sides have 
agreed to divide it equally. This agreement will have no effect 
on the common border of the two countries as provided in the 
international law. On their cooperation on the bridge operation, 
the sides have agreed that each side sets up a permanent 
committee to monitor, coordinate, consult and discuss with each 
other concerning the operation of the bridge and matters that 
may arise over the area between the transition pier on both 
sides, including arrests of wrongdoers on the said area on a 
case-by-case basis. Solutions to the matters will be considered 
according to the law of each side, and measures against the 
wrongdoers will be taken as mandatory. 
  After signing the agreement, the foreign ministers of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> also gave a news conference. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-30647 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas125_j_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-125 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Indonesia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Discuss Trade Deficit, Press Ban </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Discuss Trade Deficit, Press Ban </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK2806133294 Jakarta ANTARA in English 1310 GMT 28 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK2806133294 </F>
<F P=104>  Jakarta ANTARA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpts] <LOCATION>Jakarta</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jun 28</DATE> (OANA-ANTARA) -- President 
<PERSON>Suharto</PERSON> and visiting Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> 
agreed here <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to work together to reduce <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>'s trade 
deficit with <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  Both leaders shared the view that bilateral trade ties 
between the two countries need to be intensified to cut the 
deficit, <ORGANIZATION>Minister/State</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Murdiono</PERSON> said when announcing 
the results of a two-hour talk between President <PERSON>Suharto</PERSON> and 
Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. 
  Two-way trade between <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> is worth US 
<MONEY>$2.15 billion</MONEY> a year. 
  In the meeting, which lasted 30 minutes longer than 
scheduled, the two heads of state also discussed the upcoming 
informal summit of <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Asia-Pacific Economic Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>) to 
be held in <LOCATION>Bogor</LOCATION>, about 50 km south of <LOCATION>Jakarta</LOCATION>, on 15 <DATE>November 
this year</DATE>. 
  The second <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION> meeting will be attended by representatives 
from 18 countries, namely the <ORGANIZATION>ASEAN</ORGANIZATION> member states (<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Brunei Darussalam</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>), the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Papua New 
Guinea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Prime Minister <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> expressed his readiness 
to help <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> make the <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION> meeting a success, Minister 
<PERSON>Murdiono</PERSON> said. [passage omitted -- covered in referent item] 
  Minister <PERSON>Murdiono</PERSON> also confirmed that President <PERSON>Suharto</PERSON> 
explained about the recent revocation of the licences of TEMPO 
weekly magazine, EDITOR magazine and <LOCATION>DETIK</LOCATION> tabloid to his guest. 
  Keating arrived here on <DATE>Monday</DATE> for a three-day visit to hold 
talks with President <PERSON>Suharto</PERSON> and other Indonesian officials. He 
is also scheduled to open a major Australian trade exhibition on 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
  The trade exhibition is a part of "<LOCATION>Australia Today Indonesia</LOCATION> 
'94", the largest trade and cultural promotion program <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 
has ever undertaken in the region. It is scheduled to last 
until 3 <DATE>July 1994</DATE>. This is the third visit <PERSON>Keating</PERSON> has made to 
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> since he became prime minister. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5467 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas070_n_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-070 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Vietnam </F>
<H3> <TI>   Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Summit Meeting With Australia Begins in Hanoi </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Vo Van Kiet Give Banquet Speeches </H4>

<F P=102> BK1204011494 Hanoi VNA in English 1653 GMT 11 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1204011494 </F>
<F P=104>  Hanoi VNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [All quote marks as received] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Hanoi</LOCATION> VNA <DATE>April 11</DATE> -- Prime Minister <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON> 
gave a banquet here this evening in honour of his Australian 
distinguished guests. At this event, he delivered a speech 
which read in part : 
  `It has been only a year since our first meeting in 
<LOCATION>Canberra</LOCATION>, 
but we have every reason to be satisfied with the rapid 
development of the multi-sided Vietnam-Australia cooperation, 
especially in the economic, trading, educational and training 
fields. We greatly appreciate <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s active help to us in 
building a North-South 500 KV grid, a nearly-completed important 
project in our national construction. We also highly value the 
effective implementation of the Australian aid to train 
Vietnamese officials, as well as <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s active contribution 
to a break-through in the relations between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and the 
international financial institutions. 
  `I am optimistic about the prospect for the development of 
friendly and cooperative relationship between our two countries. 
Despite thousands of miles separating us and the difference in 
historical circumstances and cultural traditions between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, both of us have been looking towards the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 
and identifying ourselves with the common desire for an expanded 
regional cooperation. 
  `We are satisfied with the results of the open and frank 
exchanges of talks between us today. We are convinced that the 
agreement between us in many fields will contribute to further 
consolidation and development of the on-going fine cooperation 
between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, for his part, said: 
  `The effect of the changes you have introduced, combined 
with 
the skill and enterprise of the Vietnamese people, have brought 
this country high levels of economic growth and have opened up 
new opportunities for our bilateral relationship. <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 
too, has been through a process of 'economic renovation'. We 
have opened our industry to competition and our economy to the 
world. 
  `I know, <PERSON>Mr</PERSON> Prime Minister, how difficult the task can be. 
But, like you, I also know how large are the rewards for our 
countries at the end of the process. 
  `And, like <LOCATION>Vietnam Australia</LOCATION> is also seeking closer links 
with our region not only economically but culturally, 
politically and strategically as well. 
  These parallel interests are creating unprecedented new 
opportunities for us. 
  Trade between <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE> was <MONEY>2 million 
dollars</MONEY>. In <DATE>1993</DATE> it was <MONEY>366 million dollars</MONEY>. 
  <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> is now <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>'s third largest foreign investor, 
with nearly <MONEY>800 million dollars</MONEY> invested here. 
  We are also developing new avenues for cooperation on 
regional issues. 
  And <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> can count on warm support from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> as you 
move towards greater involvement in regional organisations. 
  Bilaterally, we are finding new opportunities to work 
together. 
  `I was also pleased to be able to tell you <DATE>today</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr Prime 
Minister</PERSON>, that <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has committed more than <MONEY>200 million 
dollars</MONEY> in a new four-year aid program, which we hope will cover 
areas such as education, health, infrastructure and legal 
training. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5031 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas067_m_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-067 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Thailand </F>
<H3> <TI>   Australia's Keating Arrives on Official Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Australia's Keating Arrives on Official Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0604144494 Bangkok Thai Color Television Channel 9 in Thai 
1200 GMT 6 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0604144494 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok Thai Color Television Channel 9 </F>
<F P=105>  Thai </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>, his wife, 
and delegation arrived on board a special <ORGANIZATION>Royal Thai Air Force</ORGANIZATION> 
plane at <LOCATION>Don Muang Airport</LOCATION> at <DATE>1530 today</DATE> to begin an official 
visit to <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> until 10 <DATE>April</DATE> as guests of the <ORGANIZATION>Thai 
Government</ORGANIZATION>. The Australian prime minister is scheduled to meet 
with Prime Minister <PERSON>Chuan Likphai</PERSON> tomorrow and be received by 
his majesty the king in the <TIME>evening</TIME>. On 8 <DATE>April</DATE>, he will 
proceed to <ORGANIZATION>Nong Khai Province</ORGANIZATION> to participate in the official 
opening of the Thai-Lao Friendship Bridge. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5196 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_k_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Siphandon Receives SRV Deputy Prime Minister </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Siphandon Receives SRV Deputy Prime Minister </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0704120594 Vientiane KPL in English 0836 GMT 7 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0704120594 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 7</DATE> (KPL) -- Prime Minister of the 
Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> [Lao People's Democratic Republic] <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, on 
<DATE>April 5</DATE>, received at <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister</ORGANIZATION>'s Office <PERSON>Mr. Phan Van Khai</PERSON>, 
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnamese-Lao Cooperation Committee</ORGANIZATION> on 
official visit here. 
  On this occasion <PERSON>Mr. Phan Van Khai</PERSON> informed Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> about the result of the 16th session of the 
Lao and Vietnamese cooperation committees and expressed thanks 
for the warm reception given by Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>. 
  Vietnamese vice prime minister highly valued the many sided 
successes of the Lao people in the implementation of the 
renovation policy under the able leadership of the Lao People's 
<ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Party</ORGANIZATION> currently headed by President <PERSON>Khamtai 
Siphandon</PERSON>. He also wished the fraternal Lao people still greater 
success. 
  Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>, for his part, highly 
valued 
the visit of the high level delegation of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, considering 
it as a contribution to the development and strengthening of the 
friendly relations, special solidarity and all-round cooperation 
between the two nations. The Lao prime minister reaffirmed that 
the Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> and the SR [Socialist Republic] of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> enjoyed a 
long standing friendly relation and that the Vietnamese party, 
government and people would still provide assistance and 
cooperation to the Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5148 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas067_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-067 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Keating Urges Help To Defuse Korean `Tension' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Keating Urges Help To Defuse Korean `Tension' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0704050294 Bangkok THE NATION in English 7 Apr 94 p A8 </F>
<F P=103> BK0704050294 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok THE NATION </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Excerpt] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> -- Visiting Australian Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON> yesterday urged <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, a close communist ally of 
<LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>, to help defuse nuclear tension in the Korean 
peninsular, said Foreign Minister Samsavat Lengsavat. 
  The request was raised during <PERSON>Keating</PERSON>'s talks with his 
Laotian counterpart <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>. Laos' response, however, 
was cautious. 
  Somsavat said despite the government's policy fostering 
world 
peace and stability, <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> respected countries' individual 
rights to find solutions to their own problems. 
  "We (<LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>) in fact have good relations. Our 
two countries were the victims of aggression in the past," said 
Somsavat. [passage omitted] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-52354 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas090_q_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-090 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  6 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> AUSTRALASIA </F>
<F P=101> Australia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Human Rights Delegation To Visit Vietnam </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Human Rights Delegation To Visit Vietnam </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   BK0605025194 Melbourne Radio Australia in English 0100 GMT 6 
May 94 </F>

<F P=103> BK0605025194 </F>
<F P=104>  Melbourne Radio Australia </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> has announced the composition of the 
parliamentary delegation which will consult <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> on human 
rights. The one-week visit to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> will start on 7 <DATE>July</DATE> and 
will be led by the chairman of the parliamentary standing 
committee on foreign affairs, defense, and trade, <PERSON>Stephen 
Loosley</PERSON>. The other two parliamentary members will be the 
opposition spokesman on foreign affairs <PERSON>Andrew Peacock</PERSON> and the 
Australian Democrats foreign affairs spokesman <PERSON>Vicky Vaughan</PERSON>. 
  The consultative delegation to look at human rights and 
other 
issues in the relationship was confirmed during the visit to 
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE> by <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>'s prime minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. 
  Announcing the delegation's makeup, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Gareth 
Evans</PERSON> said it would be accompanied by two academics noted for 
their expertise in Asian affairs and human rights and two 
prominent Vietnamese now living in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
  The academics are Professor <PERSON>Nancy Viviani</PERSON>, dean of faculty 
of 
the Asian studies at <LOCATION>Queensland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Griffith University</ORGANIZATION>; and 
Professor <PERSON>Philip Olsten</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for 
International Law</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Australian National University</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Senator <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> had taken up the suggestion 
from 
the Vietnamese prime minister, <PERSON>Vo Van Kiet</PERSON>, made during his 
visit in <DATE>May last year</DATE> that Vietnamese Australians should go 
back to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to see the situation. 
  The foreign minister said the delegation will include <PERSON>Quang 
Luu</PERSON>, head of radio for the <ORGANIZATION>Special Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Ho 
Mai</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Footscray</ORGANIZATION> city councillor in <LOCATION>Melbourne</LOCATION>. 
  Senator <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said the delegation was a strong, 
well-balanced 
one that had 
both status and expertise. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-27717 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas020_m_94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-020 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Thailand </F>
<H3> <TI>   Bridge Talks With Laos To Reopen 8-9 Feb </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK3001100094 Bangkok THE NATION in English 30 Jan 94 p A2 </F>
<F P=103> BK3001100094 </F>
<F P=104>  Bangkok THE NATION </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By Kulachada Chaiphiphat] </F>
  [Excerpts] Laotian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Somsavat Lengsavat</PERSON> 
will lead a delegation to <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> soon for talks on the 
maintenance and administration of the Thai-Lao Mittraphap bridge 
across the <LOCATION>Mekong River</LOCATION>, informed sources said. 
  Talks, set tentatively for 8-9 <DATE>February</DATE>, will also focus on 
official preparations far His Majesty the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s visit to 
<LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION> on the eve of the historic <DATE>April 8</DATE> opening. 
  The bridge, financed and built by <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, completes the 
first land link between <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. 
  The opening will be presided over by the <PERSON>King</PERSON> and the 
President of <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nouhak Phomsavan</PERSON>, in the presence of Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Chuan Likphai</PERSON>, Laotian Prime Minister General <PERSON>Khamtai 
Siphandon</PERSON>, and Australian Prime Minister <PERSON>Paul Keating</PERSON>. 
  However, the build-up to the handover is being plagued by a 
lack of agreement on the question of boundaries. Visa issues 
have also yet to be settled. [passage omitted] 
  <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> maintains that the boundary on the bridge should be 
drawn at the deepest point of the river, the same line which 
marks the frontier along the <LOCATION>Mekong River</LOCATION> between <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Laos</LOCATION> has argued that the two nations should each have 
jurisdiction over and responsibility for half the bridge, in 
accordance with international practice. This boundary would not 
replace the official frontier. 
  The differences have embarrassed both sides, as such basic 
issues were supposed to have been smoothed over earlier in 
anticipation of the historic inauguration of the "friendship" 
bridge that symbolizes cordial ties between the two neighbors. 
  The sources however said the talks are unlikely to focus on 
measures to facilitate the two-way entry into both sides through 
the bridge. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-6202 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas075_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-075 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Prime Minister Mahathir Continues Official Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Prime Minister Mahathir Continues Official Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Meets President, Prime Minister </H4>

<F P=102> BK1804115294 Vientiane KPL in English 0902 GMT 18 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1804115294 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Vientiane</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 18</DATE> (KPL) -- Malaysian Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Datuk Sri Dr. Mahathir</PERSON> bin Mohamed on <DATE>April 16</DATE> arrived 
here on a three-day official visit to the Lao <ORGANIZATION>PDR</ORGANIZATION> [Lao People's 
Democratic Republic] at the invitation of Lao Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON>. 
  The visit was in response to the <DATE>December 1992</DATE> visit of the 
Lao prime minister to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, where three agreements were 
signed between the two governments concerning investment 
promotion and protection, economic, scientific and technical 
cooperation and air transportation. 
  During the visit, the Malaysian prime minister called on Lao 
President <PERSON>Nouhak Phoumsavan</PERSON> and met with Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai 
Siphandon</PERSON>. 
  Talking with the Malaysian prime minister, President <PERSON>Nouhak 
Phoumsavan</PERSON> said this visit was very significant in the history 
of the Lao-Malaysian relations. He expressed hope that the 
bilateral relations would further develop fruitfully in many 
areas. In response, the Malaysian prime minister expressed 
pleasure over a warm hospitality the Lao Government and people 
gave to him and his party. He voiced support to the open-door 
policy of the Lao Government on economic relations and 
cooperation with foreign countries, and confirmed that he would 
do all he could to develop the friendly relations and 
cooperation between the two countries. 
  Lao Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> in his discussion with 
his Malaysian counterpart also said that the visit was historic. 
He considered it as implementing the three agreements signed 
between the two governments in <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
  On the same day afternoon, talks were held between the 
government delegations of the two countries headed by their 
respective prime ministers. At the talks, both sides discussed 
a wide range of issues concerning their bilateral cooperation, 
both public and private, in various fields. 
  The two prime ministers then witnessed the signing of an 
agreement on banking settlement between the governors of the 
central banks of the two countries. 
  In the <TIME>evening</TIME>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> hosted a 
banquet in honour of his Malaysian counterpart. 
  The Malaysian prime minister was officially welcomed at the 
airport by Lao Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamtai Siphandon</PERSON> together with 
Deputy Prime Minister <PERSON>Khamphoui Keoboualapha</PERSON>, Foreign Minister 
<PERSON>Somsavat Lengsavat</PERSON> and other members of the Lao Government 
officials. This three-day visit was the first ever made to the 
country by the Malaysian prime minister following the Lao prime 
minister's visit to <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION> in <DATE>December 1992</DATE>. 
  The Malaysian delegation was accompanied by several 
important 
figures in the business circle of <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5258 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_k_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Laos </F>
<H3> <TI>   Thai King, Queen Make Official Visit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Thai King, Queen Make Official Visit </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Arrive in Vientiane </H4>

<F P=102> BK0804105494 Vientiane KPL in English 0909 GMT 8 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK0804105494 </F>
<F P=104>  Vientiane KPL </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 
