<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880801-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-01-88 0836EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BarbaraJordan 1stLd-Writethru a0487 08-01 0596</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Barbara Jordan, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0487,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Doctors Say Barbara Jordan Recovering</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 5th graf, `Ms. Jordan...' to restore missing word `was.'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOLMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> was listed
in serious condition <TIME>this morning</TIME>, recovering from a near drowning
in her backyard pool, and a doctor says she could be out of the
hospital within a week.
   ``Right now, I think things look very good that she'll get
totally back to normal,'' said <PERSON>Dr. James Little</PERSON>, a neurologist.
``She's very close to normal right now. I think she will continue
to improve. As best as I can tell right now, she probably will
regain full mental functions.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>'s condition was upgraded <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> from
critical to serious but stable, and she continued to improve <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``She started her liquid diet tonight. She is breathing on her
own. She is receiving supplemental oxygen, though,'' hospital
spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, gave the thumbs-up sign <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to her intensive
care unit nurse and was able to talk.
   ``She's in good spirits now because she knows she's going to get
well,'' said <PERSON>Dr. William J. Deaton</PERSON>, a pulmonary specialist.
   ``She's emotional about that and a little bit teary-eyed some of
the time, knowing what she's been through and how close she came to
a real catastrophic event. But she still also has her jovial
personality. She was joking a little bit <TIME>this morning</TIME>,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON>
said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``She is vastly improved.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was flown by emergency helicopter
to <ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after being found floating
face-down in her pool.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>'s live-in companion, <PERSON>Nancy Earl</PERSON>, called paramedics,
who restored her pulse and breathing.
   <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said she came ``within four to five minutes, 10 minutes
at most'' of suffering severe brain damage and possibly death.
   ``She does not know what happened and was clearly concerned
about it and had indicated that she didn't think she would go
swimming alone again,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> was breathing <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> only with the help of a
ventilator, but <DATE>Sunday</DATE> the device was gone and she was responding
to questions and talking, doctors said.
telephoned a message for <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Carolyn
Hinckley Boyle</PERSON> said. <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> made a seconding speech for
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s nomination at the recent <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>.
   Doctors said it isn't known what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in the pool, but the lack of oxygen caused cardiac
arrest.
   <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said he expected <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to remain in intensive care
for 48 hours and to be hospitalized for about a week.
   The doctors said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who has been confined to a
wheelchair for several years, suffers from multiple sclerosis. She
swims as therapy.
   ``She has muscle weakness, and it would be difficult for her to
rescue herself from the swimming pool if she had any warning of any
event. ... I doubt, though, based on the suddenness of the event,
that she had any warning,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said.
   Doctors were uncertain how long she was in the pool before being
discovered. <PERSON>Ms. Earl</PERSON> said she returned from a short errand to find
<PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> unconscious in the pool.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> in <DATE>1966</DATE> became the first black state senator in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
history. In <DATE>1972</DATE>, she was the first Southern black elected to
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> since Reconstruction, serving until <DATE>1978</DATE>, when she left
politics after three terms in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to teach at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Texas</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880731-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-88 2358EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-JordanHospitalized 3rdLd-Writethru a0768nge 07-31 0705</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan Hospitalized, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0768,0719</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Lawmaker Remains Hospitalized But `Vastly Improved'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 3rd graf to UPDATE with condition
Sunday night; picks up 4th graf pvs `Ms. Jordan ...' CORRECTS by
deleting ``Last week'' from 13th graf pvs about Democratic
convention.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOLMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> was
``vastly improved'' and giving the thumbs-up sign to her hospital
nurse <DATE>Sunday</DATE> following a near-drowning in her swimming pool.
   ``She's in good spirits now because she knows she's going to get
well,'' said <PERSON>Dr. William J. Deaton</PERSON>, a lung specialist treating <PERSON>Ms.
Jordan</PERSON>.
   ``She's emotional about that and a little bit teary-eyed some of
the time, knowing what she's been through and how close she came to
a real catastrophic event. But she still also has her jovial
personality. She was joking a little bit <TIME>this morning</TIME>,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON>
said. ``She is vastly improved.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>'s condition was upgraded from critical to serious but
stable, and she continued to improve <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``She started her liquid diet tonight. She is breathing on her
own. She is receiving supplemental oxygen, though,'' hospital
spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, who gained national attention during the <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>
impeachment hearings, was flown by emergency helicopter to
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after she was found floating
face-down in her pool.
   <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said she came within ``four to five minutes, 10 minutes
at most'' of suffering severe brain damage and possibly death.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> apparently lost consciousness while in the pool.
Deaton and <PERSON>Dr. James Little</PERSON>, a neurologist, said it isn't known
what caused her to lose consciousness, but that the lack of oxygen
then caused cardiac arrest.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> had been in critical condition in the hospital's
intensive care unit, but <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> that ``she's
upgraded now. She's certainly stable, in a much less serious
condition.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> was breathing without the aid of a mechanical
ventilator, responding to questions and trying to make sure a
<DATE>Monday</DATE> dental appointment was canceled. ``She obviously has pretty
good mental recall if that's her biggest concern,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said.
   ``Right now, I think things look very good that she'll get
totally back to normal,'' <PERSON>Little</PERSON> said. ``She's very close to normal
right now. I think she will continue to improve. As best as I can
tell right now, she probably will regain full mental functions.''
   The doctors said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who has used a wheelchair for
several years, suffers from multiple sclerosis but her condition
shouldn't have had an effect on the incident.
   ``She has muscle weakness and it would be difficult for her to
rescue herself from the swimming pool if she had any warning of any
event. ... I doubt, though, based on the suddenness of the event,
that she had any warning,'' <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said.
   Little said possible causes for her losing consciousness were a
sudden heartbeat irregularity or a seizure. But hospital tests
showed ``her cardiac status has been very stable. She's had no
evidence of seizure activity,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> delivered a nominating speech for vice presidential
candidate <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> telephoned a message to <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>
on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Carolyn Hinckley Boyle</PERSON>.
   Visitors to the hospital have included <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Treasurer <PERSON>Ann
Rostow</PERSON>, a former aide to President <PERSON>Lyndon Johnson</PERSON>; University of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> women's basketball Coach <PERSON>Jody Conradt</PERSON>; plus <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>'s two
sisters and live-in companion, <PERSON>Nancy Earl</PERSON>, who found <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> in
the pool.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is a fan of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>' Lady Longhorns,
and nurse <PERSON>Barbara Tucker</PERSON> said the basketball team's former star,
<PERSON>Fran Harris</PERSON>, visited before leaving for the Olympic trials.
   ``When I remember seeing <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> on TV, I frequently remember
the thumbs-up sign that things are OK. She's probably given me that
about 20 times today,'' <PERSON>Ms. Tucker</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> in <DATE>1966</DATE> became the first black state senator in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
history. In <DATE>1972</DATE>, she was the first Southern black elected to
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> since Reconstruction, serving until <DATE>1978</DATE>, when she left
politics after three terms in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to teach at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Texas</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880805-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-88 0118EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BarbaraJordan     08-05 0412</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barbara Jordan,0423</SECOND>
<HEAD>Improved Barbara Jordan Talks Politics</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AT3</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, recovering from a near
drowning, talked politics with reporters and her nurses <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
and said she's feeling much better.
   ``I really feel great. All I know is right now, I could not die
because this is the Democrats' year and I have got to be around to
celebrate it,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, who remained in fair condition
at <ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> gave the seconding speech for <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> as the Democrats' vice presidential candidate at the party's
   Sitting in a chair in her hospital room, <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> remarked on
the good wishes she has received from across the nation.
   ``I have received cards, telegrams, letters, flowers from all
over this country,'' she said. ``If I did have the desire to return
to active politics, I think I could make a good run at national
office. I am very grateful and I feel very fortunate to have so
many people feel do deeply and care so much for me.''
   The former three-term congresswoman and first black state
senator in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> history said she has no plans to leave her current
teaching job at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas' Lyndon B. Johnson School
of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``My plans were and are to continue to teach ... and to continue
to educate young minds to take over this country,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> said she didn't remember much about the accident that
happened around noon <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. She lost consciousness while in her
backyard swimming pool and was found face-down in the pool by her
roommate.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who uses a wheelchair because she suffers from what
doctors say is a disease similar to multiple sclerosis, swims for
exercise. She said she hopes the accident won't make her afraid to
continue.
   ``I hope that I'm not traumatized by this event so I refrain
from doing that ... I enjoyed it,'' she said.
   She also said she was grateful for the efforts of the emergency
medical service technicians and hospital helicopter crew who
rescued her.
   ``It's a compilation of people who did superb work to see to it
that I can sit here today and talk to you. And I thank them and am
grateful for it,'' she said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is being treated in the hospital's critical care
unit. Doctors said she may remain hospitalized for about four more
days.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880731-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-88 0529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-JordanHospitalized     07-31 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Jordan Hospitalized,0434</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former Congresswoman Remains In Critical Condition</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> remained in
critical condition early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after she was found floating
unconscious in her swimming pool, authorities said.
   ``She's been awake off and on through the <TIME>night</TIME>, but she goes
right to sleep,'' said <PERSON>Sheryln Gembol</PERSON>, a nursing supervisor at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>. ``We're trying to let her rest.
   ``They're going to be running some more tests throughout the day
<DATE>today</DATE>. They know it was not a heart attack or a stroke, but as far
as what made her unconscious in the pool, they're not sure,'' she
added.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who rose to fame during the Watergate impeachment
hearings, was found in the pool about noon <DATE>Saturday</DATE> by a woman who
lives with her.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, was taken to the hospital by helicopter.
Paramedics ``said she had a pulse, was trying to breathe and they
were able to help her breathe en route to hospital,'' said hospital
spokeswoman <PERSON>Carolyn Boyle</PERSON>.
   At a briefing <DATE>late Saturday</DATE>, a doctor said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> was being
treated for fluid in her lungs but showed no signs of heart or
brain dysfunction.
   ``She has full recovery of her intellectual functions. Her vital
signs are much better,'' <PERSON>Dr. William Deaton</PERSON> said. Though she
remained in critical condition, ``the capital `c' is not so big as
when she got here.''
   ``She has to heal her own lungs, which she will hopefully do,''
added <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON>, a lung specialist. He said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> apparently lost
consciousness while swimming alone in the pool, for unknown
reasons. A lack of oxygen then caused the cardiac arrest, he said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> has had medical problems for several years and has
used a wheelchair to get to her job on the faculty of the <ORGANIZATION>Lyndon B.
Johnson School of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> has refused to discuss the illness, calling it ``a
mobility problem'' and denying it was <PERSON>Lou Gehrig</PERSON>'s disease or bone
cancer. Deaton described it as a progressive loss of ``nerve
function in her lower extremities'' similar to multiple sclerosis.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> became the first black state senator in
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1972</DATE>, she was the first Southern black elected to
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> since Reconstruction.
   She gained a national reputation during the <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary
Committee</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1974</DATE> hearings that ended with a vote to press
impeachment charges against President <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>. She stirred
television audiences when she declared, ``My faith in the
Constitution is whole, it is complete, it is total.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880803-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-03-88 1501EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People-Jordan     08-03 0183</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People-Jordan,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barbara Jordan, Talks Politics, Undergoes Tests</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>,
hospitalized after nearly drowning, talked politics over breakfast
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, a hospital spokeswoman said.
   <PERSON>Carolyn Hinckley Boyle</PERSON> said doctors described <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, as
doing ``better _ much stronger, more cheerful.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION> listed <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> in serious but stable
condition, which was unchanged.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> underwent tests <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, including brain and chest
X-rays, as well a heart examination known as an echo cardiogram,
<PERSON>Ms. Boyle</PERSON> said.
   Nurse <PERSON>Greg Pfahles</PERSON> quoted <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> as saying about the
Democratic presidential ticket, ``This is our year.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Boyle</PERSON> said Pfahles found <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> ``fiesty and spunky but
a very pleasant and cooperative patient.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> was hospitalized <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after being found floating
face-down in her backyard pool.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, she became the first black state senator in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
history. In <DATE>1972</DATE>, she was the first Southern black elected to
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> since Reconstruction, serving until <DATE>1978</DATE>, when she left
politics after three terms in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to teach at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of Texas Lyndon B. School of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890822-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-22-89 1431EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Jordan     08-22 0108</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jordan,0111</SECOND>
<HEAD>Former U.S. Rep. Jordan Hospitalized</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> was in fair
condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>St. David's Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, where she was undergoing
treatment for a urinary infection, a spokeswoman said.
   ``She is improving,'' said <PERSON>Jan McCrory</PERSON>, assistant vice president
for public relations at the hospital. <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> probably would
remain hospitalized for several days to a week, she said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 53, was admitted <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> with a urinary
tract infection, <PERSON>Ms. McCrory</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> has a form of multiple sclerosis and uses a
wheelchair. Last year, she was hospitalized after she nearly drowned
in her backyard swimming pool.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA082289-0158 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 98012 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 22, 1989, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 2; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
83 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NATION; 
</P>
<P>
EX-REP. BARBARA JORDAN IN HOSPITAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
AUSTIN, Tex. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> was in fair condition today at <ORGANIZATION>St. David's 
Hospital</ORGANIZATION>, where she was undergoing treatment for a urinary infection, a 
spokeswoman said. 
</P>
<P>
"She is improving," said <PERSON>Jan McCrory</PERSON>, assistant vice president for public 
relations at the hospital. Jordan probably will remain in the hospital for 
several days to a week, she said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 53, has a form of multiple sclerosis and uses a wheelchair. Last year, 
she was hospitalized after she nearly drowned in her swimming pool. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880803-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-03-88 0106EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     08-03 0684</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0713</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, hospitalized
since she nearly drowned <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, is ``well rested, alert and in
good spirits,'' a spokeswoman says.
   <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 52, remained in serious but stable condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first thing the former Democratic congresswoman asked for
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was a newspaper, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON>.
Nurses said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is very independent and ``likes to do
everything herself,'' according to <PERSON>Ms. Larsen</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was hospitalized after being found
floating face-down in her backyard pool <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Thomas Deaton</PERSON>, who has treated <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, has said she is
suffering from a condition similar to multiple sclerosis and is
unable to walk.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, hospitalized
since she nearly drowned <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, is ``well rested, alert and in
good spirits,'' a spokeswoman says.
   <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 52, remained in serious but stable condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first thing the former Democratic congresswoman asked for
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was a newspaper, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON>.
Nurses said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is very independent and ``likes to do
everything herself,'' according to <PERSON>Ms. Larsen</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was hospitalized after being found
floating face-down in her backyard pool <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Thomas Deaton</PERSON>, who has treated <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, has said she is
suffering from a condition similar to multiple sclerosis and is
unable to walk.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, hospitalized
since she nearly drowned <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, is ``well rested, alert and in
good spirits,'' a spokeswoman says.
   <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 52, remained in serious but stable condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first thing the former Democratic congresswoman asked for
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was a newspaper, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON>.
Nurses said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is very independent and ``likes to do
everything herself,'' according to <PERSON>Ms. Larsen</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was hospitalized after being found
floating face-down in her backyard pool <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Thomas Deaton</PERSON>, who has treated <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, has said she is
suffering from a condition similar to multiple sclerosis and is
unable to walk.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>Eds: A version of the following is moving on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>DETROIT (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, hospitalized
since she nearly drowned <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, is ``well rested, alert and in
good spirits,'' a spokeswoman says.
   <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 52, remained in serious but stable condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first thing the former Democratic congresswoman asked for
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was a newspaper, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON>.
Nurses said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is very independent and ``likes to do
everything herself,'' according to <PERSON>Ms. Larsen</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was hospitalized after being found
floating face-down in her backyard pool <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Thomas Deaton</PERSON>, who has treated <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, has said she is
suffering from a condition similar to multiple sclerosis and is
unable to walk.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>, hospitalized
since she nearly drowned <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, is ``well rested, alert and in
good spirits,'' a spokeswoman says.
   <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, 52, remained in serious but stable condition <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   The first thing the former Democratic congresswoman asked for
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was a newspaper, said hospital spokeswoman <PERSON>Kari Larsen</PERSON>.
Nurses said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is very independent and ``likes to do
everything herself,'' according to <PERSON>Ms. Larsen</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, who gained national attention during the <DATE>1974</DATE>
Watergate impeachment hearings, was hospitalized after being found
floating face-down in her backyard pool <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Dr. Thomas Deaton</PERSON>, who has treated <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, has said she is
suffering from a condition similar to multiple sclerosis and is
unable to walk.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880808-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-08-88 1533EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     08-08 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sporting a ``Where was George?'' button and
flashing a broad smile, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> left a
hospital <DATE>Monday</DATE>, more than a week after she nearly drowned in her
swimming pool.
   ``Thank you for my life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, told emergency
medical personnel and nurses who cared for her during her stay at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dr. <PERSON>William Deaton</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is ``in excellent condition,
and she should return to her normal lifestyle within a couple of
weeks.''
   There is no explanation of what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in her pool on <DATE>July 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said. He said it was
most likely a heart rhythm disturbance.
   The ``Where was George'' button refers to a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> speech by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that criticized
Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s role in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sporting a ``Where was George?'' button and
flashing a broad smile, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> left a
hospital <DATE>Monday</DATE>, more than a week after she nearly drowned in her
swimming pool.
   ``Thank you for my life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, told emergency
medical personnel and nurses who cared for her during her stay at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dr. <PERSON>William Deaton</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is ``in excellent condition,
and she should return to her normal lifestyle within a couple of
weeks.''
   There is no explanation of what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in her pool on <DATE>July 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said. He said it was
most likely a heart rhythm disturbance.
   The ``Where was George'' button refers to a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> speech by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that criticized
Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s role in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>MALIBU, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sporting a ``Where was George?'' button and
flashing a broad smile, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> left a
hospital <DATE>Monday</DATE>, more than a week after she nearly drowned in her
swimming pool.
   ``Thank you for my life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, told emergency
medical personnel and nurses who cared for her during her stay at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dr. <PERSON>William Deaton</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is ``in excellent condition,
and she should return to her normal lifestyle within a couple of
weeks.''
   There is no explanation of what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in her pool on <DATE>July 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said. He said it was
most likely a heart rhythm disturbance.
   The ``Where was George'' button refers to a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> speech by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that criticized
Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s role in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BRUSSELS, Belgium (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sporting a ``Where was George?'' button and
flashing a broad smile, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> left a
hospital <DATE>Monday</DATE>, more than a week after she nearly drowned in her
swimming pool.
   ``Thank you for my life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, told emergency
medical personnel and nurses who cared for her during her stay at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dr. <PERSON>William Deaton</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is ``in excellent condition,
and she should return to her normal lifestyle within a couple of
weeks.''
   There is no explanation of what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in her pool on <DATE>July 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said. He said it was
most likely a heart rhythm disturbance.
   The ``Where was George'' button refers to a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> speech by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that criticized
Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s role in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>RADNOR, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sporting a ``Where was George?'' button and
flashing a broad smile, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> left a
hospital <DATE>Monday</DATE>, more than a week after she nearly drowned in her
swimming pool.
   ``Thank you for my life,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON>, 52, told emergency
medical personnel and nurses who cared for her during her stay at
<ORGANIZATION>Brackenridge Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.
   Dr. <PERSON>William Deaton</PERSON> said <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> is ``in excellent condition,
and she should return to her normal lifestyle within a couple of
weeks.''
   There is no explanation of what caused <PERSON>Ms. Jordan</PERSON> to lose
consciousness in her pool on <DATE>July 30</DATE>, <PERSON>Deaton</PERSON> said. He said it was
most likely a heart rhythm disturbance.
   The ``Where was George'' button refers to a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National
Convention</ORGANIZATION> speech by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that criticized
Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>'s role in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880722-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-88 0549EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-CVN--ConventionBriefs     07-22 0513</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CVN--Convention Briefs,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Conventioneering On $25 A Day</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics who accuse the Democrats of being big
spenders might talk to 22-year-old <PERSON>Marc Homer</PERSON>, an alternate <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
   Homer managed to attend the four-day convention on less than <MONEY>$25
dollars</MONEY> a day.
   ``I rode the bus out here and am staying in a dorm room at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$15</MONEY> a night,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The 44-hour bus
ride cost <MONEY>$69</MONEY> and he will spend the same amount on a circuitous
route home.
   ``I haven't had to spend anything hardly on food,'' he added.
``There are so many parties with free food.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Jordan Says Bentsen Is No ``Tory Democrat''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics who accuse the Democrats of being big
spenders might talk to 22-year-old <PERSON>Marc Homer</PERSON>, an alternate <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
   Homer managed to attend the four-day convention on less than <MONEY>$25
dollars</MONEY> a day.
   ``I rode the bus out here and am staying in a dorm room at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$15</MONEY> a night,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The 44-hour bus
ride cost <MONEY>$69</MONEY> and he will spend the same amount on a circuitous
route home.
   ``I haven't had to spend anything hardly on food,'' he added.
``There are so many parties with free food.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Rostenkowski Says Bentsen Can Win Back Reagan Democrats</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics who accuse the Democrats of being big
spenders might talk to 22-year-old <PERSON>Marc Homer</PERSON>, an alternate <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
   Homer managed to attend the four-day convention on less than <MONEY>$25
dollars</MONEY> a day.
   ``I rode the bus out here and am staying in a dorm room at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$15</MONEY> a night,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The 44-hour bus
ride cost <MONEY>$69</MONEY> and he will spend the same amount on a circuitous
route home.
   ``I haven't had to spend anything hardly on food,'' he added.
``There are so many parties with free food.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Republicans Boast Lots Of Space For Convention</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics who accuse the Democrats of being big
spenders might talk to 22-year-old <PERSON>Marc Homer</PERSON>, an alternate <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
   Homer managed to attend the four-day convention on less than <MONEY>$25
dollars</MONEY> a day.
   ``I rode the bus out here and am staying in a dorm room at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$15</MONEY> a night,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The 44-hour bus
ride cost <MONEY>$69</MONEY> and he will spend the same amount on a circuitous
route home.
   ``I haven't had to spend anything hardly on food,'' he added.
``There are so many parties with free food.''
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<HEAD>Democrats Pay Tribute to Longtime Secretary</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Critics who accuse the Democrats of being big
spenders might talk to 22-year-old <PERSON>Marc Homer</PERSON>, an alternate <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>
   Homer managed to attend the four-day convention on less than <MONEY>$25
dollars</MONEY> a day.
   ``I rode the bus out here and am staying in a dorm room at
<ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$15</MONEY> a night,'' he said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. The 44-hour bus
ride cost <MONEY>$69</MONEY> and he will spend the same amount on a circuitous
route home.
   ``I haven't had to spend anything hardly on food,'' he added.
``There are so many parties with free food.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901206-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-06-90 1439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-06 0734</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0902</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pop diva <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> was ordered by a judge
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> to trim a hedge and pine tree at her <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood Hills</ORGANIZATION> home.
   Superior Court <PERSON>Judge Sally Disco</PERSON> ruled <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> violated an
agreement with neighbor <PERSON>Donald Robinson</PERSON> requiring her to keep her
shrubbery trimmed so it wouldn't interfere with his view.
   The judge rejected <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s claim of <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> damages for
the loss of his view, but she ordered <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> to pay <ORGANIZATION>Robinson</ORGANIZATION>'s
attorney fees.
   <PERSON>Liz Rosenberg</PERSON>, publicist for the singer, was out of the office
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> and couldn't be reached, a receptionist said. Madonna's
lawyer, <PERSON>Meghan Serwin</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s attorney, <PERSON>Robert Rigdon</PERSON>, were
not in their offices <DATE>Thursday</DATE> for comment.
   <ORGANIZATION>Madonna</ORGANIZATION> said in a deposition she bought the house above the
Sunset Strip because of its spectacular view and privacy. But after
she moved in, she said she noticed gardeners peering through her
hedges.
cross-claim against <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> that said he had harmed her by
infringing on her privacy.
   ---
   <LOCATION>SEVIERVILLE</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION> (AP) - <PERSON>Dolly Parton</PERSON>'s younger sister has
filed a worker's compensation lawsuit against the theme park the
entertainer owns.
   <PERSON>Freida Parton</PERSON>, 33, said she injured her back closing a dressing
room door at <LOCATION>Dollywood</LOCATION>, in the foothills of the <LOCATION>Smoky Mountains</LOCATION>.
   In the lawsuit filed this week in <ORGANIZATION>Sevier County Chancery Court</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Freida Parton</PERSON> says she sustained the injury on <DATE>June 10, 1989</DATE>, and
underwent back surgery.
   She seeks unspecified benefits under the state's worker's
compensation act.
   <PERSON>Barbara Headla</PERSON>, marketing manager at <LOCATION>Dollywood</LOCATION>, did not return a
telephone message left at the park.
   <PERSON>Freida Parton</PERSON> and her twin brother, <PERSON>Floyd</PERSON>, are the
next-to-youngest of the 12 <PERSON>Parton</PERSON> siblings.
   <PERSON>Dolly Parton</PERSON> opened <LOCATION>Dollywood</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. She co-starred in ``Steel
Magnolias'' <DATE>last year</DATE> and was host of <DATE>1987</DATE>'s short-lived variety
television series ``Dolly.''
   ---
   <LOCATION>AUSTIN</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> (AP) - Former congresswoman <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> has
agreed to serve as special counsel on ethics for Gov.-elect <PERSON>Ann
Richards</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> is recognized throughout the country as one of
the most important voices in ethics and government that one could
possibly have,'' <PERSON>Richards</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1966</DATE>, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> became the state's first black state senator. In
<DATE>1972</DATE>, she was the first black elected to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> from the South
since Reconstruction.
   Once considered a possible Democratic vice presidential
candidate, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> ended her political career after three terms in
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. She became a professor at the <ORGANIZATION>Lyndon B. Johnson School
of Public Affairs</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texss</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Richards</PERSON> said <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> would counsel members of her administration
on ethical conduct and help draft legislation on ethics.
   <PERSON>Bill Cryer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Richards</PERSON>' press secretary, said <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> was taking
the post on ``an unpaid, voluntary basis'' and would continue
teaching.
   ---
   <LOCATION>LONDON</LOCATION> (AP) - <PERSON>Dame Joan Sutherland</PERSON> is coming out of retirement
after just two months, but for only one performance: a New Year's
Eve farewell to <ORGANIZATION>Covent Garden</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Opera House</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Sutherland, the coloratura soprano with amazing voice range,
will be joined by Italian tenor <PERSON>Luciano Pavarotti</PERSON> and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
mezzo-soprano <PERSON>Marilyn Horne</PERSON>.
   ``Although <PERSON>Dame Joan</PERSON> has retired, she wants to make this one -
and only one - exception, to come to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to say goodbye to
Covent Garden where she began her opera career in <DATE>1952</DATE>,'' said
<PERSON>Kathleen Wilkinson</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Opera</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman.
   Sutherland, 64, will play the ``star guest'' at Prince
<PERSON>Orlofsky</PERSON>'s party in Act II of ``Die Fledermaus'' by <PERSON>Johann Strauss</PERSON>.
The opera will be conducted by her husband, <PERSON>Richard Bonynge</PERSON> and
will be televised live by the <ORGANIZATION>British Broadcasting Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Pavarotti and <PERSON>Horne</PERSON> will appear as fellow party guests.
   Sutherland, known as ``La Stupenda'' (the magnificent one),
retired <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE> with a performance in her hometown of <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Sutherland</PERSON> withdrew from performances at <ORGANIZATION>Covent
Garden</ORGANIZATION>, saying she wanted people to remember her voice in its
prime.
   ---
   SAN FRANCISCO (AP) - Beach Boys' reclusive founder <PERSON>Brian Wilson</PERSON>
made a private concert appearance before a group that included
political cartoonist <PERSON>Garry Trudeau</PERSON> as the two joined in an AIDS
fund-raising effort.
   Looking uncomfortable in a dark suit and tie, a nervous <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>
played piano and sang <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at the private reception. A few
dozen patrons paid at least <MONEY>$125</MONEY> each for the 15-minute
performance.
   ``I enjoyed it,'' <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> said after the performance. ``I had to
close my eyes. That's the only way I can really feel my music,
closing my eyes.''
   Wilson had said before the show that he was ``scared to death.''
   Trudeau, creator of the comic strip ``Doonesbury,'' sat
cross-legged on the floor during the concert.
   Among other tunes, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> played selections from the Beach Boys<DATE>'
1966</DATE> ``Pet Sounds'' album, which recently came out on compact disc.
<PERSON>Andy Lippincott</PERSON>, a character in ``Doonesbury'' who died from AIDS,
had looked forward to the disc's release.
   Before the reception, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Trudeau</PERSON> attended the opening of
an art galley with 59 original drawings of editions of the comic
strip that dealt with <PERSON>Lippincott</PERSON>'s death.
   The drawings are being sold to raise money for the NAMES
Project, which is coordinating the construction of a huge memorial
quilt dedicated to AIDS victims.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880910-0120 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-10-88 1631EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Dukakis-Surrogates     09-10 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dukakis-Surrogates,210</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dukakis Names Dozen Co-Chairmen as Campaign Surrogates</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Political Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democratic nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> named a dozen
prominent Democrats as co-chairmen of his presidential campaign
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> to serve as strategy advisers and surrogates on the
campaign trail.
   Dukakis called them ``12 of the finest leaders or our party, 12
of the finest leaders of our country.''
   The group includes four senators, two <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members, a former
congresswoman, three governors, a mayor and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>'s secretary of
state.
   ``I'm proud to enter the final eight weeks of this campaign with
a distinguished running mate in <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> and our 12
distinguished co-chairs,'' the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor told
reporters. ``These co-chairs represent a cross section of the
<ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> and a cross section of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> and I welcome their advice on policy and
strategy and we will be proud to have them representing us in our
campaign all across this country,'' he said.
   Named were Sens. <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sam Nunn</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>John Glenn</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Barbara Mikulski</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>; Reps.
<PERSON>Norman Y. Mineta</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bill Richardson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>,
and former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   Also Govs. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Madeleine Kunin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>; Mayor <PERSON>Richard Arrington</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> Secretary of State <PERSON>Elaine Baxter</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880721-0228 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-88 2147EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p AM-CVN--ConventionScene     07-21 0623</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CVN--Convention Scene,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Delegates Finally Get a Towering _ A Really Towering _ Democrat</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For once, a really towering Democrat _ not the
towering kind evoked in political rhetoric _ addressed the
<ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>, the senator from <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> who once played on two
world champion <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Knicks basketball teams, got the kind of
reception from convention delegates that marks him as a political
comer.
   The hall blossomed with orange and blue signs, not for <PERSON>Michael
Dukakis</PERSON> or <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, but for ``<PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s
pride.''
   At 6-foot-5, <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> was too tall to use the prompting devices
on either side of the podium, so his speech was scrolled up on a
television screen across the hall.
   ``This is a real first for me tonight,'' he said. ``It's the
first time I've spoken to a national convention and the first time
I've performed in The Omni wearing long pants.''
   The convention hall normally is used for <LOCATION>Atlanta Hawks</LOCATION> games.
   Bradley made everybody's list of vice presidential possibilities
early in the Democratic campaign, but he took himself out of
consideration last month.
   ``Does it make any difference who is president of the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>?'' he asked.
   ``Did Lincoln make a difference? Did <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON> ... Ask
anyone who lived through the depression if <PERSON>Franklin Delano
Roosevelt</PERSON> made a difference. Ask any European who has democracy if
<PERSON>Harry Truman</PERSON> made any difference. Ask anyone who cares about human
rights if <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> made a difference.''
   By the time <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> took the microphone, before <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON>'s name was put in nomination for the vice presidency, the
convention hall was filled to overflowing.
   The delegates let loose with some of the most enthusiastic
cheering of the <TIME>night</TIME> when former Rep. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, a
heroine of Democrats since the Watergate days of <PERSON>Richard Nixon</PERSON>,
seconded <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s nomination.
   ``Why?'' she asked. ``First of all because he's my senator and I
wasn't planning to come to this convention for any purpose'' other
than that.
   ``Our minds are turning away from `Hooray for <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>' and we
are now confronted with the hard reality of a natioln which desires
to become solvent again,''
   ``We want to retake the moral high ground,'' she said.
   ``The rostrum was lowered to desk height to accommodate <PERSON>Ms.
Jordan</PERSON>'s wheelchair. She suffers from a degenerative bone disease.
   True to his word, the fire marshal closed the doors at <TIME>7:30
p.m.</TIME>, shutting out hundreds for the third night. The smart people
got in early.
   Rep. <PERSON>Claude Pepper</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, the oldest <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> member at age
87, sat on the front row of his state's delegation for his 13th
Democratic convention _ every one since <DATE>1940</DATE> when <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON> was
nominated for his third term.
   ``It's a well-run convention, well-handled,'' he said. ``It
shows <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' good management skills. We're going to be
victorious.''
   But you couldn't sell that to many Democrats who had to miss
dinner to make it inside the hall. Long lines formed at The Omni's
food concessions, where the menu consisted of pizza, hot dogs,
popcorn and ice cream bars.
   Inevitably, some concessions ran out of food.
   That did nothing to dampen the spirit of <PERSON>John Economos</PERSON>, a
restaurateur from <LOCATION>Des Moines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. He carried a hand-lettered sign
that read, ``Vote for <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>.'' Nothing unusual about
that, except it was in Greek.
   All was hope and promise in the convention hall on the <TIME>last
night</TIME>.
   ``Do you feel the excitement in the air?'' asked the chairman,
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Speaker <PERSON>Jim Wright</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   ``Yes!'' shouted the delegates.
   ``Are we going carry the South this year?
   ``Yes!''
   ``Will we win in <DATE>November</DATE>?
   ``Yes!''
   ``Do you promise me that?''
   ``Yes!''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880809-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-09-88 0122EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Convention-Texas     08-09 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Convention-Texas,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gramm: Convention Will Have Texas Accent</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AT4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL HOLMES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
have a distinct <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> accent, says the man who will nominate <PERSON>George
Bush</PERSON> for president.
   ``It is clear in this convention that I'm doing the nominating
and another Texan's doing the accepting, and that's pretty much
what conventions are about. So it's a <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> show from that point of
view,'' <PERSON>Sen. Phil Gramm</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Texas</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   However, <PERSON>Gramm</PERSON> said, those watching the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> convention will hear
something quite different from last month's Democratic convention,
where <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> state Treasurer <PERSON>Ann Richards</PERSON> set the tone with several
wisecracks about <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> during her keynote speech including that the
wealthy vice president was ``born with a silver foot in his mouth.''
   ``You're going to see a stark contrast between my speech and the
speeches you heard at the Democratic convention,'' <PERSON>Gramm</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Gramm</PERSON> said he plans to use his speech to highlight the
differences between Vice President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>.
   ``I am not a good name-caller. People don't care what I think
about <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> in terms of some cutesy-poo thing I might
call him,'' he said.
   Still, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> Republicans have a tough act to follow.
   <ORGANIZATION>Texas Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> officials have referred jokingly to last
convention due to the prominent role played by Texans.
   Among them were <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>, the vice presidential
nominee; <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>, the keynoter; <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> House Speaker <PERSON>Jim Wright</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>, convention chairman; former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Rep. <PERSON>Barbara
Jordan</PERSON>, who seconded <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s nomination; Agriculture Commissioner
<PERSON>Jim Hightower</PERSON>, who gave a prime-time speech, and state Rep. <PERSON>Lena
Guerrero</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Austin</LOCATION>, who helped present the party platform to
delegates.
   Democrats also believe the selection of <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> as <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>'
running mate will help their ticket carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, the nation's
third-largest state, and its 29 electoral votes. A total of 270
electoral votes are needed to win the presidency.
   ``The campaign in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is going to be a hotly contested
campaign,'' <PERSON>Gramm</PERSON> said. ``We've got to put before the people of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> those two records. If we don't win in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> given <PERSON>Michael
Dukakis</PERSON>' record, we don't deserve to win.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-13118</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CGOA1AD7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920715
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 JUL 92 / Harmonious voices soar above dissent: At the Democratic
convention, Jurek Martin finds Bush-bashing to the fore
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JUREK MARTIN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE FIRST night of an American political convention is the overture to the
work of the week, and the Democrats certainly sang it in harmony on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
But not everybody belted it out with the same raucous vigour.
Take the lead tenor from <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>. There was a time when <PERSON>Bill Bradley</PERSON>
could hold an audience in <LOCATION>Madison Square Garden</LOCATION> in the palm of his hand on
any given evening.
That stopped 15 years ago. 'Bradley back in the <LOCATION>Garden</LOCATION>' - to quote the
buttons on every <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> delegate in sight - was not wearing basketball
sneakers and a number 24 shirt, but the dark suit and tie of a professional
politician increasingly regarded as the Democratic party's thoughtful
conscience and, albeit less widely, as its best presidential candidate - not
this year but before too long.
Senator <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON>'s keynote address on <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> showed him at his least,
and most, impressive. On the down side, one conclusion is safe. Rumour has
it that he has spent almost as many hours practising his public speaking as
he did his jump shot. If so, it was to much less effect.
The <PERSON>Garden</PERSON> did not hang on his every word, not in comparison to his
fellow-keynote speakers. Governor <PERSON>Zell Miller</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, for example, had
them rocking in the aisles with his full-frontal assault on the Republican
opposition.
Yet even he paled into insignificance when the final act. <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>,
black and now confined to a wheelchair with multiple sclerosis, delivered a
soaring, cadenced civics lecture, in its way as memorable as the address she
gave in the same arena to the <DATE>1976</DATE> convention when a congresswoman from
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
As a formal speaker, <PERSON>Mr Bradley</PERSON> still lacks the necessary attributes of
timing and delivery. He swallows his good lines and talks on when his
audience is applauding.
There are other considerations. First, one speech does not necessarily a
political <DATE>summer</DATE> or winter make. <PERSON>Mr Mario Cuomo</PERSON> gave a great one to the <DATE>1984</DATE>
convention and is still only governor of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>; Governor <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>
delivered a terrible one to the <DATE>1988</DATE> convention and is about to be the
Democratic presidential nominee.
Second, there was, as ever, substance to the <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> speech. The theme -
facing up to collective responsibilities rather than indulging in
'individual thrills' - is not new for him, but he is developing it all the
time. It is one that is not easily reduced to slogans.
'What we face is a crisis of meaning,' he said in one of his pithier
passages. 'Without meaning, there can be no hope; without hope there can be
no struggle, and without struggle there can be no personal betterment.
Individualism degenerates into greed without agreement on its limits. The
microchip may be faster than the human brain but it isn't connected to a
heart. A new drug might defeat a disease but it won't eradicate hatred.'
Or, again on a more hopeful note: 'It is sometimes said Americans lack a
sense of tragic life. It would be more correct to say that Americans are not
content to let tragedy have the last word. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is history's
greatest experiment in the elimination of despair.'
This is the sort of reflective philosophy that political conhear. Add to
them <PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON>'s reflections - the need for equality of sacrifice,
including social entitlement programmes, the impermissibility of racism, be
it black or white, and the imperative of valuing reason over emotion in
assessing character - and it cannot be said that the Democrats were sent
home to bed with nothing to think about.
The vague sense of dislocation is that this was not the intended dual theme
of the first night. One part of this was to be a lot of Bush-bashing, to
which <PERSON>Mr Bradley</PERSON> ponderously contributed. Perot-pulverising, however, was
much less in the score, though there was some of it from Governor <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>.
The Democrats have worked out that the Bush-Perot conflict helps them.
The other element was to demonstrate that this is no longer a party of
pot-smoking, draft-dodging subversives - not in living memory have its
delegates been presented with such an orgy of flag-waving patriotism,
derived from Republican choreography.
Emotions were wound up not, as in days of yore, by the haunting and
socially-conscious songs of <PERSON>Woody Guthrie</PERSON> (This Land is Your Land) and by
gospel choirs, but by a succession of marching and big bands straight out of
high school and <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION> floor shows. This was designed as a celebration of
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, marred only by the fact that a whole line of white tubas was
clearly emblazoned with the name of their Japanese manufacturer.
Dissent was also dismissed with Republican efficiency. When 600-odd
delegates began chanting 'let <PERSON>Jerry</PERSON> speak' on behalf of the former governor
of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the other <PERSON>Brown</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ron</PERSON>, the party chairman, moved briskly to
other business. It will require an act of some magnanimity for the
Californian to be permitted to address the convention. <PERSON>Mr Nelson Mandela</PERSON>,
who is to speak tonight, was much easier to fit in at short notice.
Hardly a word was heard from the podium that might embarrass the party
nominee. <PERSON>Barbara Boxer</PERSON>, running for the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, got in a dig
at the free trade agreement with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, which <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> basically
supports, and <PERSON>Mr David Dinkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> mayor, went further than <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>
in demanding that US cities be rebuilt before those in <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>.
But that was about it. Unless <PERSON>Mr Cuomo</PERSON>, who is to nominate <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON>
tonight, publicly urges him to come clean and raise taxes, as he did on
television on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, departure from the party line is not scripted.
The delegates responded to this new direction. They cheered at every
invocation of their national spirit and at every imprecation against the
Republicans. The <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> delegation leader epitomised the spirit of the night
by declaring that he was from 'the state which knows how to spell potato'
(which Vice-President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> does not).
In this mood, they might have expected something more rollicking from <PERSON>Bill
Bradley</PERSON>. When he talked, so did they, among themselves, which is standard
practice most of the time, but not necessarily in front of keynote speakers
in prime televised time. It took a Jordanesque gift of oratory to make them
listen.
It was indeed a first night which, for all that its target was
middle-America, was not without its subtle contradictions. <PERSON>Mr Clinton</PERSON> will
have to square them when he speaks before the final curtain.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880712-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-12-88 1438EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-Bentsen-Reaction 1stLd-Writethru   07-12 0955</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bentsen-Reaction, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0631,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Retransmits a0688 to restore editor's note</HEAD>
<HEAD>Democrats Liken Apparent Selection of Bentsen to Kennedy-Johnson
Ticket</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 1st graf and INSERTS 3 grafs after 2nd graf to UPDATE
with announcement and to include quotes; picks up 3rd graf pvs,
bgng: Bentsen's ``selection ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PHYLLIS MESSINGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>' choice of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <PERSON>Sen. Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON> to be his running mate drew praise from fellow Democrats
today, with several of them likening it to another
Massachusetts-Texas ticket _ <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lyndon B. Johnson</PERSON>
in <DATE>1960</DATE>.
   ``The Massachusetts-Texas combination got this country moving
again in <DATE>1960</DATE> _ and it will do the same for the nation in <DATE>1988</DATE>,''
said <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, younger brother of the late
president.
   Dukakis and <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> both were quick to draw the comparison
between this campaign and the <DATE>one 28 years ago</DATE>.
   ``The <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> ex'es were good for the
country and good for the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1960</DATE> and it's going to
be a real winner in <DATE>November</DATE> of 88,'' <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   ``Selecting a running mate is probably the first presidential
act _ if I can use that word _ that I will do,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said in
introducing his running mate. ``<PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> brings to this ticket
and will bring to this nation years of experience.''
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s ``selection gives the Democratic Party a strong ticket
for <DATE>November</DATE> _ and even more important, the strong prospect of
eight solid years of effective new leadership for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>,''
<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said.
   Texas State Treasurer <PERSON>Ann Richards</PERSON>, who will be the keynote
speaker at next week's Democratic convention in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, called
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> ``a level guy'' who ``will make a great vice president''
and added:
   ``There's always been a sort of Austin-to-Boston, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>,
connection, and I think that this ticket adds that same sort of
magic.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON> also said that <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> would boost Democrats'
chances in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, one of the states that <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' likely Republican
opponent, <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, calls home.
   Sen. <PERSON>Paul Simon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ill.</LOCATION>, whose own hopes for the presidential
nomination were dashed earlier this year, agreed that <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> could
help the Democratic ticket in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and said he thought the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
senator might help the Democrats carry <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> as
well.
   ``<PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON> is a skilled and seasoned lawmaker,'' <PERSON>Simon</PERSON>
said. ``This is an excellent choice, and this is a winning ticket.
   ``Democratic prospects in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> will be
boosted immediately and, when the American people get to know <PERSON>Lloyd
Bentsen</PERSON>, it will strengthen the ticket everywhere,'' <PERSON>Simon</PERSON> added.
   Arkansas Gov. <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, who will deliver the nominating
speech for <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>, said he also believed that <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> would help
the Democrats carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and would help the party across the
region.
   ``I like and respect him very much,'' <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> said.
   Sen. <PERSON>Barbara Mikulski</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Md.</LOCATION>, said she believes ``<PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>
will be a fine addition to the Democratic ticket. He knows his
issues and he knows his politics. Best of all,'' she said, ``he
knows how to beat <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>. He did just that in <DATE>1970</DATE> to become
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator.''
   In <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, where Democrats had been pushing home state <PERSON>Sen. Bob
Graham</PERSON> for the No. 2 spot on the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> ticket, state Rep. <PERSON>Mike
Abrams</PERSON> also offered praise for <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and said a Dukakis-Bentsen
victory in his state is ``doable.''
   ``We all know it's going to be tough,'' said <PERSON>Abrams</PERSON>, who is
coordinator of the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. But, he added, the
choice of <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> ``shows a sensitivity to the South'' and ``brings
defense and foreign policy and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> experience,'' all
considered crucial to a Democratic victory in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   Even backers of <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>, who came in second to <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> in
the race for the presidential nomination and who had been one of
those the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor had considered for the second
spot, seemed satisfied with <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> state Rep. <PERSON>James Burke</PERSON>, who was the state campaign
coordinator for <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, said, ``We would have preferred to have
had <PERSON>Jesse</PERSON>.'' He added, though, that ``<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> is a better choice
than some of the others he could have picked.''
   <PERSON>John White</PERSON>, a former Democratic national chairman who has been
advising <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, said he was ``excited'' about the choice of
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and said it would ``make <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> a hell of a battlefield.''
   Union activists also praised <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>, saying that the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>
senator had recently shored up his poor record on labor issues with
his deft handling of the trade bill and mandatory plant closing and
layoff notices _ some of labor's top legislative priorities this
year.
   ``<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> was extremely helpful in recognizing that the two _
plant closing notices and the trade bill _ were compatible,'' said
<PERSON>Robert McGlotten</PERSON>, legislative director for the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>. ``And he
let his colleagues know how he felt.''
   <PERSON>Geraldine Ferraro</PERSON>, who four years ago was picked as Democrat
<PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>'s running mate, said she was ``delighted'' at the
choice of <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>.
   ``I think it's an indication that Governor <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> intends to
run a strong national campaign,'' <PERSON>Ms. Ferraro</PERSON> said.
   On the Republican side, <ORGANIZATION>Senate Minority</ORGANIZATION> leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, frequently mentioned as a possible vice president on <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
ticket, said he thought <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> ``couldn't have picked a better
man.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Lynn Martin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Ill.</LOCATION>, who is national co-chairwoman of
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s presidential campaign, called <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> ``a nice man who's
able'' but said she still anticipated that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> would be able to
carry <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   On the similarity to the Kennedy-Johnson ticket of <DATE>1960</DATE>, she
said: ``I'm sure we're going to hear <DATE>1960</DATE> ad nauseum. There's a
slight difference of course. He (<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>) was not selected by his
peers to be in leadership (as <PERSON>Lyndon Johnson</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> majority
leader, had been); nor is <PERSON>Dukakis John Kennedy</PERSON>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880628-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-88 1012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Democrats-Richards 1stLd-Writethru a0437 06-28 0850</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Democrats-Richards, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0437,840</SECOND>
<HEAD>Keynote Speaker For Democrats Noted For Feisty, Humorous Stump
Style</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Updates with Richards comments in top 5 grafs, picking up in
2nd graf pvs, At a; subs 7th graf pvs, ``She will</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KEN HERMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>AUSTIN, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Ann Richards</PERSON>, tapped as the keynote speaker
for the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>today</DATE> she will consult
with advisers to apparent nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> and rival <PERSON>Jesse
Jackson</PERSON> before preparing her speech.
   She also suggested, on a light note, that she might be a
good-luck charm for the party.
   Noting that fellow <PERSON>Texan Barbara Jordan</PERSON> was the only previous
female keynoter at a Democratic Convention, in <DATE>1976</DATE>, she said,
``That year the Democrats went to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> so maybe they saw
my selection, having another female, as a good omen.''
   Before the convention, she said in an interview on CBS-TV, ``I
wanted to be sure to look at the Democratic platform. I wanted to
consult with both the <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign and the <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> campaign.
And of course I welcome any help and any advice that I get.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON> is known for using blunt rhetoric tempered with
wicked humor to get her point across.
   At a recent <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> fundraiser in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, one man
after another _ none of them minorities _ came to the podium to
speak. Finally it was the turn of <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> state
treasurer and potential <DATE>1990</DATE> gubernatorial candidate.
   ``Now are there any other white men who haven't spoken yet?''
she said sweetly. ``God knows we don't want to leave any of you
out.''
   The audience roared with laughter, as <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>' audiences
usually do. And, as usual, her audience got the message.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, her stump style was praised by <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> chief
<PERSON>Paul G. Kirk</PERSON> as he announced her selection as the speaker whose
address will open the party's convention next month in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   The 54-year-old <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kirk</PERSON> said at a <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> news
conference, ``has the ability to tell it like it is.''
   <PERSON>Kirk</PERSON> said <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> had urged the selection of a woman keynote
speaker, the first since Rep. <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> shared that honor with <PERSON>John
Glenn</PERSON>.
   ``He was very hopeful that we might make a selection of a
woman,'' the party chief said, ``not only because of the importance
of the family concerns, the issues of stress and struggle that
women are going through in the daily work lives and family lives,
but I think it is symbolic of the importance of women to the
American family and the realities of all of that.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>, the first woman in 50 years to hold statewide
office in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, is the divorced mother of four grown children.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, her first attempt at elected office, <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>
defeated an incumbent <LOCATION>Travis County</LOCATION> commissioner. In <DATE>1982</DATE>, the
state's incumbent treasurer, under indictment for official
misconduct, withdrew from a Democratic runoff against her. She won
the general election and was re-elected without opposition in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   After the <DATE>1982</DATE> election, <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON> moved quickly to change
operations in the state treasury. She also made staff changes,
boosting the number of women and minorities on the job in the
170-employee agency. She now claims the agency payroll has an
ethnic and sex balance reflecting the state's general population.
   <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that women's issues are ``the same
issues that affect all other human beings'' _ but with a twist.
   ``The difference is the role, sociologically, that women have
played. That is we are the caretakers, the nurturers,'' she says.
``It usually falls to us when any time hard times and bad times
hit.''
   It's a message often repeated by <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>. If you can make a
household work, she says, you can succeed in government.
   ``Most homemakers don't know what enormous skills they have.
Putting three meals on the table each day is a pretty big job in
itself, much less doing the laundry and car pooling,'' she once
told a reporter.
   Her professional success has come despite personal challenges.
In <DATE>1980</DATE>, after being confronted by family members, she sought
treatment for alcoholism. She says she has not had a drink since
then, and she has been active in helping others battle alcoholism.
   Shortly after her treatment, she and husband <PERSON>David Richards</PERSON>
separated, and in <DATE>1984</DATE> the two obtained what they both said was an
amicable divorce.
   <PERSON>Richards</PERSON>, a lawyer, was on hand <DATE>Monday</DATE> when his ex-wife talked
to reporters about being selected to give the keynote speech. She
acknowledged him as someone who ``played a very large role in my
life, politically and personally.''
   Beyond the convention and helping to put a Democrat in the <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON>' most immediate goal is the <DATE>1990</DATE> Texas
gubernatorial race. She has not formally declared her intentions,
but sent out her first exploratory fund-raising letter <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ms. Richards</PERSON> said she is not certain what effect her half-hour
in the political spotlight in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> will have on her
gubernatorial race.
   ``I suppose if I'm good it will help,'' she said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. ``And
if I'm bad it won't.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910429-0153
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910429-0153.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Who's News:
   Burlington Northern Inc.
</HL>
<DATE>
04/29/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B3
</SO>
<CO>
   BNI WNEWS
</CO>
<MS>
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
</MS>
<IN>
RAILROADS (RAI)
</IN>
<NS>
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
</NS>
<RE>
TEXAS (TX)
</RE>
<LP>
   BURLINGTON NORTHERN Inc. (Fort Worth, Texas) -- Barbara
Jordan was named a director, increasing board membership to
12, at this transportation company. Ms. Jordan, 55 years old,
a former member of Congress, is on the faculty of the Lyndon
B. Johnson School of Public Affairs at the University of
Texas at Austin.
</LP>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900629-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-90 1520EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Fires 4thLd-Writethru a0580 06-29 1005</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Fires, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0580,1032</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fires Engulf 600 Homes and Businesses; Death Toll In State Rises
To Two</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with second death reported.
Picks up 2nd graf pvs, `Wildfires, most...'. SUBS 10th-12th grafs,
bgng `Hospitals reported...', with 6 grafs to add detail on latest
death. Picks up 13th graf, `Late Thursday...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LA1,2,3, XPAY2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LINDA DEUTSCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SANTA BARBARA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Milder winds and temperatures gave
firefighters the upper hand <DATE>today</DATE> in a wildfire that engulfed 524
homes and businesses in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara County</LOCATION> and in other blazes
that burned more than 90 homes.
   Two Californians died in the fires _ a state prisoner serving as
a firefighter and a 37-year-old <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> woman found near the
wreckage of her home in a burned-out neighborhood, authorities said
<DATE>today</DATE>.
   Wildfires, most set by arsonists, charred more than 18,700 acres
by <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a six-county area north, east and south of <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>. Arson was blamed for the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> fire and another
that charred 66 homes in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> suburb of <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION> before
it was contained.
   Losses could surpass <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara County</LOCATION> and
<MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> in <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION>, officials said.
   ``You're just lucky to have your life,'' said <PERSON>Kay O'Brien</PERSON>, who
fled her <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> home with her husband carrying only family
pictures and a retirement watch. The home and all their possessions
were lost.
   A county survey completed late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> found 524 structures
destroyed, including 315 single family homes. Officials previously
said 567 homes and businesses had been destroyed.
   Calm wind and overnight temperatures in the 50s helped 800
firefighters subdue the blaze. Officials hoped to contain the fire
by noon <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, said <PERSON>Juanita Freel</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's pretty calm out there now,'' <PERSON>Robert Ooley</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Santa
Barbara County</LOCATION> fire spokesman, said <DATE>today</DATE>. ``It's still smoldering
somewhat, but it's nothing like before. It's certainly on the
downside now.''
   Elsewhere, firefighters controlled blazes in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> and at
<ORGANIZATION>Yellowstone National Park</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, but large fires raged in
<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>. In <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, where six firefighters
died <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, a lightning fire in the <ORGANIZATION>Tonto National Forest</ORGANIZATION>
destroyed a cabin built in the <DATE>1920s</DATE> by <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> novelist <PERSON>Zane Grey</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, Gov. <PERSON>George Deukmejian</PERSON> declared states of
emergency in the <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION> areas. The governor
also authorized separate <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> rewards for information leading to
the arrest and conviction of the arsonists in both blazes.
   Hospitals reported admitting 13 people for fire-related injuries
and treating 55 others.
   <PERSON>Karen Terrill</PERSON>, spokeswoman for the state forestry department,
said in a statement <TIME>this morning</TIME> that a state prisoner died as a
result of injuries suffered while fighting a <LOCATION>Riverside County</LOCATION> fire.
   The victim was <PERSON>Victor Ferrara</PERSON>, 22, according to spokeswoman
<PERSON>Patty Perez</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>San Bernardino</LOCATION> Medical Center. Ferrara, who died
late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, was burned when his crew was overrun by wind-driven
flames, <PERSON>Ms. Terrill</PERSON> said.
   In all, 1,200 state prisoners are helping in the firefighting
effort.
   In <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, the body <PERSON>Andrea Gurka</PERSON>, 37, was found this
morning in a creek bed behind her home in the area where the fire
began, said county fire spokesman <PERSON>Charlie Johnson</PERSON>.
   ``She apparently had attempted to flee her residence when it was
being overrun by flames <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   Late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, in the suburban community of <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>, 30 miles
east of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, an arson-suspected blaze burned out of control
along brush-laden hillsides and consumed 400 acres, authorities
said. Police blocked several residential streets although no homes
were evacuated.
   Police in <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION> were looking for two young men after
witnesses said they saw one of them toss a butane lighter from a
moving car into the brush off the road where the fire started, said
<PERSON>Chris Gray</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Glendale Fire Department</ORGANIZATION> battalion chief.
   The 4,000-acre arson fire that broke out <DATE>late Wednesday</DATE> in a
valley between <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION> and the nearby town of <LOCATION>Goleta</LOCATION> was one
of the worst on record here. Damage to homes alone was estimated
initially at <MONEY>$190 million</MONEY>, and the figure was expected to top <MONEY>$500
million</MONEY>, said county Supervisor <PERSON>Bill Wallace</PERSON>.
   No more homes appeared threatened today.
   Authorities have said an incendiary device was found at the
fire's origin, but they haven't given details.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Santa Barbara City Council</ORGANIZATION> voted <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to call off the
<DATE>July 4</DATE> fireworks at the city beach. Mayor <PERSON>Sheila Lodge</PERSON> implored
residents not to celebrate with their own fireworks. <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>,
which posted a record 109 degrees <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, has tinder-dry foliage.
   A <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> helicopter dropping water on flames
crashed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> in <LOCATION>San Marcos Pass</LOCATION>. The pilot suffered
only scrapes and bruises.
   Firefighters surrounded <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of a 4,500-acre wildfire in
<LOCATION>Corona</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Riverside County</LOCATION> today, but not before it destroyed eight
homes, said Capt. <PERSON>David Parks</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>California Department of
Forestry</ORGANIZATION>.
   The blaze was set as a controlled burn <DATE>June 19</DATE> in the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland
National Forest</ORGANIZATION> but jumped fire lines three times, officials said.
   A 2,500-acre blaze burning today near <LOCATION>Lake Henshaw</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Diego
County</LOCATION> forced the evacuation of a Boy Scout camp and 20 homes,
authorities said.
   Four earlier brush fires in the county blackened about 1,700
acres before firefighters contained the blazes.
   An arson blaze in the Carbon Canyon area that straddles Orange
and <LOCATION>San Bernardino</LOCATION> counties blackened 6,640 acres and destroyed at
least 14 homes. Officials hoped to control the blaze late today,
state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Forestry</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Jerry Hendershot</PERSON> said.
   ``To make matters worse, fireworks go on sale today,'' said
department spokeswoman <ORGANIZATION>Sharon Sellers</ORGANIZATION>. ``We're not happy about
that.''
   A man described as a transient was arrested for investigation of
arson in the <LOCATION>Carbon Canyon</LOCATION> blaze. Authorities said he sparked the
blaze while trying to make coffee with two camp fires.
   In east-central <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, officials said the 24,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>Tonto
National Forest</ORGANIZATION> fire was about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> contained <TIME>this morning</TIME>.
The fire that began with a lightning strike has destroyed about 50
homes and forced the evacuation of more than 1,200 people.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880721-0148 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-88 1333EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p BC-CVN--ConventionSchedule 1stLd-Writethru a0504 07-21
0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-CVN--Convention Schedule, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0504,500</SECOND>
<NOTE>Eds: Updates thruout; no pickup</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here is a schedule of <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s events in the
closing session of the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>. Times are
<ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here is a schedule of <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s events in the
closing session of the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>. Times are
<ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880722-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-22-88 0347EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-CVN-Bentsen     07-22 0565</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CVN-Bentsen,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cast As Conservative, Bentsen Celebrates Differences</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EILEEN PUTMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Lloyd Bentsen</PERSON>, cast in the role of
conservative on the new Democratic ticket, has decided not to bury
his differences with the more liberal <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>, but to
praise them.
   Before millions of Americans who watched <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s convention
on prime-time television, the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> senator served notice that he
does not believe Democrats must ``march in lockstep'' to win the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   His speech was not as dynamic as that of the presidential
nominee, and it did not rouse the crowd to the heights attained by
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' oratory. But <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> had his own way of telling his party
he balances the ticket nicely:
   Democrats, he said, ``are not gray grains of oatmeal in a bland
porridge of privilege ... We have differences of opinion. But on
the basic issues of justice and opportunity, we stand united.''
   If the party does not expect great things of <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s rhetoric,
it does expect great things of him in <DATE>November</DATE>. The senator, whose
name has been described as ``magic'' in the state of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, was
picked for the ticket to win his home state, and its 29 electoral
votes, for the Democrats.
   The Dukakis-Bentsen camp has also made it clear <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> will
spend a good deal of time in the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>, which has been Reagan-Bush
territory of late.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and his aides have stressed those issues on which he and
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> agree: economic growth, jobs creation, women's rights and
better housing, health care and education for all citizens.
   But <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> is more conservative than <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and many Democrats
on many issues, including his support of school prayer, the <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION>
rebels in <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> and his opposition to gun control.
   Still, the quiet-spoken senator, who has a vaguely patrician
air, had plenty of supporters <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Dukakis, in his own remarks, paid tribute to <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>, saying he
would speak up if the <ORGANIZATION>National Security Council</ORGANIZATION> came up with the
``cockamamie idea that we should trade arms to the ayatollah for
hostages.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Dan Rostenkowski</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ill.</LOCATION>, who nominated <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> and works
with him closely on Capitol Hill, called him ``straightforward ...
smart ... and tough.''
   ``He is a sensible, reasonable, rational, common-sense good
choice for vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>United States</ORGANIZATION>,'' said former Rep.
<PERSON>Barbara Jordan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. ``I believe that he is the best choice you
could come up with to give us a strong and winning ticket this
<DATE>November</DATE>.''
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> also won praise from <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> for his longtime
support of civil rights. On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, just as <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s name was
being entered in nomination, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> issued a written endorsement
of the senator.
   ``While I may disagree with both Governor <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and Senator
<PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> on some important issues, our interests converge in
building a coalition to beat the Republicans this <DATE>fall</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>
said.
   Still, when the voice vote was taken to acclaim <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON> the
nominee, many <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> supporters shouted ``no,'' voicing their
continued displeasure at the absence of their candidate on the
ticket. Fifteen members of <ORGANIZATION>Bentsen</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> delegation refused to
join in the celebration. Signs reading ``No Contra aid'' were
sprinkled through the convention hall.
   <PERSON>Bentsen</PERSON>'s own speech drew loud and sustained applause only when
he mentioned <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>, but the senator was unruffled.
   ``Just wonderful, really excited,'' he beamed as he left the
podium with <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> to attend a round of post-convention parties.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900113-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-13-90 0316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BarbaraBush     01-13 0276</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Barbara Bush,270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barbara Bush Finishes Radiation Treatment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON> is finished with the radiation
treatments for a stubborn eye ailment that has impaired her vision
but will not know for at least two months how effective the
treatments have been.
   The first lady underwent the last of 10 radiation treatments on
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, said <PERSON>Anna Perez</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>'s press secretary.
   After receiving the 10-minute radiation dose at <ORGANIZATION>Walter Reed Army
Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> returned to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> and took her
daily swim in the outdoor, heated swimming pool, said <PERSON>Ms. Perez</PERSON>.
   She also attended a briefing on the Head Start education
program, hosting volunteers from the organization.
   ``She feels great,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Perez</PERSON>.
   Doctors will not know for at least two months, and maybe as long
as four, whether the radiation was effective in treating the
symptoms of Graves' disease, an immune system disorder that earlier
affected <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>'s thyroid as well, said <PERSON>Ms. Perez</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> began the radiation treatments after the steroid drug
prednisone failed to improve her eyes. She suffers eye irritation,
double vision and bulging eyes as a result of the Graves' disease,
which was diagnosed early last year.
   The disease initially caused her thyroid to be overproductive,
but a one-time radioactive treatment rendered the thyroid inactive
and cured that effect of the disease.
   The low-level radiation treatments were intended to decrease
swelling behind the eyes, in the small muscles that control eye
movement.
   Although suffering from eye irritation, <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> has maintained
a schedule of public appearances, both with her husband and by
herself.
   Should the radiation fail, surgery would be an option, experts
say.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891102-0232 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-02-89 1956EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a w AM-BarbaraBush Adv06   11-02 1229</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Barbara Bush, Adv 06,1268</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Monday AMs, Nov. 6, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>From a Wartime Christmas Dance to Living in the White House</HEAD>
<HEAD>With Laserphoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   She was 16 and home for the holidays from
finishing school. He was 17 and an <LOCATION>Andover</LOCATION> senior decked out in a
tux for the Christmas dance at a <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, country club.
   It was <DATE>December 1941</DATE>. Three weeks earlier, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> had gone to
war. George ``Poppy'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> already had decided to enlist as soon as
he turned 18.
   But on <TIME>this evening</TIME>, his attention was drawn to the tall,
slender girl with wavy, reddish-brown hair, twirling around the
dance floor in a green-and-red holiday dress with one of his tennis
buddies.
   The friend was happy to oblige <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> with an introduction to
<PERSON>Barbara Pierce</PERSON> of nearby Rye, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   Before they reached the floor, the band switched from a <PERSON>Glenn
Miller</PERSON> tune to a waltz that was beyond <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s dancing ability. So
the couple sat down and talked.
   And talked.
   A few nights later, on their first date, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> borrowed his
folks' big car _ the one with the radio _ to fill the air in case
conversation faltered.
   But, as writer <PERSON>Donnie Radcliffe</PERSON> recounts in a new biography of
<PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON>, ``he need not have bothered.''
   ``Years later he would tease that she started talking that night
and hadn't stopped since,'' writes <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON> in ``Simply <PERSON>Barbara
   The book follows the Bushes from their wartime marriage to the
oil fields of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> to the political career that led them from
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and now, after 29 moves in 44 years of marriage,
to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Radcliffe</PERSON>, who has covered first ladies and the <LOCATION>East Wing of</LOCATION> the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> for <ORGANIZATION>The Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1969</DATE>, recalls <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> saying
on a campaign flight last fall that if he won, ``there's one
prediction I'll make ... <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> will fall in love with <PERSON>Barbara
Bush</PERSON>.''
   ``<LOCATION>America</LOCATION> did,'' adds <ORGANIZATION>Radcliffe</ORGANIZATION>. ``In no time at all, her white
hair, her wrinkles, her size-14 figure and her fake pearls became
the new standards by which American women could measure themselves
_ and hope to measure up.''
   She clearly cuts a different figure than the petite ex-actress,
<PERSON>Nancy Reagan</PERSON>, who last occupied 1600 <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION>.
   As <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> quipped at a <DATE>1986</DATE> charity dinner: ``As you know, we
have a lot in common. ... She fights drugs; I fight illiteracy. She
wears a size three _ so's my leg.''
   Born in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> on <DATE>June 8, 1925</DATE>, she was the third of <PERSON>Marvin</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Pauline Pierce</PERSON>'s four children.
   He was an engineer who turned to publishing. She was, in
<LOCATION>Barbara</LOCATION>'s memory, an ``absolutely ravishing'' woman with a green
thumb, an inveterate joiner of civic causes and a spendthrift. The
Pierces lived well, but beyond their means, in a five-bedroom brick
home in upscale Rye.
   When <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>'s older sister <PERSON>Martha</PERSON> went off to <ORGANIZATION>Smith College</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Vogue</LOCATION> immortalized her on its cover as ``College Girl of the Year.''
   Back home, <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> was a tomboy, 5-foot-8 and 148 pounds at age
12. She recalls looking ``like Porky Pig.''
   At <PERSON>Ashley Hall</PERSON>, the finishing school in <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, she
set school records at speed-knitting, swimming underwater (2{ times
across the pool) and, according to <LOCATION>Radcliffe</LOCATION>, ``eating the most
hot, buttured biscuits in one meal without being caught.''
   After that holiday dance, the teen-age couple had a whirlwind,
if long distance, romance, with the letters postmarked ``ANDOVER''
turning up almost daily in <LOCATION>Barbara</LOCATION>'s school mailbox. He took her to
his senior prom at the prestigious prep school outside <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>.
   A few weeks later, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> joined the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> and began the training
that would make him its youngest pilot.
   After <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>'s graduation in <DATE>1943</DATE>, she spent 17 days with <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
and his family at their oceanfront home in <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, where she was a
hit with <PERSON>Dorothy Walker Bush</PERSON>, the clan's tennis-playing matriarch.
   Barbara dropped out of <ORGANIZATION>Smith College</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1944</DATE> after her freshman
year, planning to marry <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Sept. 2, 1944</DATE>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s torpedo bomber, with ``Barbara''
painted on its side, was shot down by Japanese gunners during a
raid on Chichi Jima.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> bailed out after dropping his four 500-pound bombs; the two
crewman with him didn't make it. An American submarine rescued the
flier, who returned home on <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Eve</ORGANIZATION>, with a Distinguished
Flying Cross and 58 combat missions.
   The wedding took place a few weeks late, on <DATE>Jan. 6, 1945</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was mustered out of the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>August</DATE> and enrolled at
<ORGANIZATION>Yale</ORGANIZATION>. Barbara worked part-time at the <ORGANIZATION>Yale Co-op</ORGANIZATION> and boasts that
