<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06332294 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06332294 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Angela Pancrazio -- Mercury News; Manuel Viveros, top,
creates Aztec-inspired artwork. (color); PHOTO: Above, his works hangs in the
Rosegarden branch library in San Jose. (color); PHOTO:; At left, his work
"Mexican Calendar."; (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HISPANIC; ARTS; CULTURE; EDUCATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Manuel Viveros' paintings are integrated with a feathered snake named
Quetzalcoatl, who was an Aztec Indian god -- the god of education.;   And like
Quetzalcoatl, Viveros is an educator for Aztec culture.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  RARE PAPER INSPIRES AZTEC-STYLE WORKS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on this page; Also ran in EX2/1, EX3/1  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "I want to promote my culture and history," he said. "I'm proud of my Latin
ancestry.";   <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON>, 34, paints the plumed serpent and other Aztec symbols
-- idols, warriors and sacrificial rituals -- on paper amate. The paper and
technique are more than 3,000 years old, but artists had abandoned the
procedure until <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> discovered paper amate, made from the bark of a
Mexican tree, about two years ago while wandering through a bazaar in Mexico.;
  The paintings of flowers and birds were geared toward tourists, yet the
ancient paper appealed to Viveros.;   "There was something in my mind that
said this art is new and original," he said.;   <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> said he doesn't know
of any other artists in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> who use paper amate.;   "I'm
rescuing the technique so we can be proud of our Pre-Columbian ancestors,"
said <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON>, who was born and raised in <LOCATION>Xalapa</LOCATION> in the state of Veracruz.;  
Paper amate is crushed bark from amatl trees, which thrive in tropical weather
and only grow in <LOCATION>Puebla</LOCATION> in central <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>. Viveros travels to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> about twice a year to buy the paper.
The paper, which costs <MONEY>$5</MONEY> for a 14-inch-by-18-inch sheet, is handmade by
Indians, who strip the bark from trees and then smash the bark between a stone
and wood to create brown, white or cinnamon paper.;   The paintings are done
with a Pre-Columbian technique, but using acrylics. Bright and unblended
colors are used for the paintings. "The colors come alive on the paper," he
said.;   In his <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> home studio, he creates symbolic paintings of the
Aztecs on paper amate. The paintings are displayed on a living room wall.;  
<PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> was a graphic designer in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> for two years before he moved to <LOCATION>San
Jose</LOCATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. He is a graduate of the <ORGANIZATION>National School of Plastic Arts</ORGANIZATION> at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Mexico</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. He takes sculpture, ceramic and metal
design classes at <ORGANIZATION>West Valley College</ORGANIZATION>. But to support himself as an artist, he
works full time at a <ORGANIZATION>Safeway</ORGANIZATION> store in <LOCATION>East San Jose.</LOCATION>;   Although <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> also
creates surrealistic oil and acrylic paintings, pencil drawings and bronze
sculpture figurines, he now concentrates on paper amate because of the
attention from the public. At a recent exhibit of his artwork at the
<ORGANIZATION>Biblioteca Latino Americana</ORGANIZATION>, 690 <LOCATION>Locust St.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, people were most
interested in paper amate, he said. "Looking at these paintings makes people
proud of our Latin heritage," he said.;   <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> teaches paper amate to
students at library-sponsored workshops and instructs a weekly class for the
<LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION> School District.;   During the workshops, <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> tells students
about the Aztecs, a highly civilized group of Indians who lived in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> from
about <DATE>1200</DATE> to <DATE>1521</DATE>, the year that <PERSON>Hernando Cortes</PERSON> led Spanish troops to
conquer the Aztecs.;   Viveros touches upon the ancient group's reputation as
warriors, their religious practices which included human sacrifices and their
gods. "I want the kids to realize that there was life before <PERSON>Christopher
Columbus</PERSON>," <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> said. "I teach the kids about their Latin American culture
and then they show their knowledge through the paintings.";   <PERSON>Viveros</PERSON> said he
hopes the workshops offer a positive outlet for teens to speed their free
time. "A lot of kids have nothing else to do with their spare time, which
leads to gangs and trouble," he said. "I want kids to come to my workshops and
feel positive about themselves.";   He recently taught a workshop to 11
students at the <ORGANIZATION>Biblioteca Latino Americana</ORGANIZATION>. The free workshops are sponsored
by friends of the library groups. Viveros will teach a four-week workshop
beginning <DATE>Dec. 10</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Empire Library</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>East San Jose.</LOCATION>;   The students'
paintings will be exhibited through <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. At the <ORGANIZATION>Biblioteca Latino
Americana</ORGANIZATION> during an artist reception last week, <PERSON>Jose Aquirre</PERSON>, 18, talked about
the meaning behind his painting to approximately 30 admirers. He painted a
skeleton, Indians, an eagle and Aztec gods.;   "When I think about <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, I
think about what's in my painting," said the De Anza College student.;   <PERSON>Mark
Lopez</PERSON>, 15, combined his drawing talent and architect career ambition to paint
a group of pyramids. "I learned about the Aztec culture and their life," said
<PERSON>Lopez</PERSON>, a sophomore at <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer High School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>; IFYOU'RE INTERESTED;
<PERSON>Manuel Viveros</PERSON> will teach a four-week paper amate workshop for teens from 4 to
<TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> on <DATE>Dec. 10, Dec. 17</DATE>, <DATE>Jan. 14</DATE>, and <DATE>Jan. 21</DATE>. There will be a reception
for artists on <DATE>Jan. 28</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Empire Library</ORGANIZATION>, 491 E. Empire St. To register,
call the library at (408) 286-5627.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  KIM BERGHEIM, Special to the Mercury News  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911127  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  857  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, November 27, 1991
00332294,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022290-0129 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 179843 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 22, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
164 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ADDING TO MOSAIC OF L.A. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Forest Lawn, the cemetery outfit that brought you replicas of Leonardo da 
<PERSON>Vinci</PERSON>'s "Last Supper" in stained glass and <PERSON>Michelangelo</PERSON>'s "David" in marble, 
has added an attraction at its memorial park in the <LOCATION>Hollywood Hills</LOCATION>: copies of 
ancient Mexican artifacts in sandstone, concrete and plaster. 
</P>
<P>
The park's Plaza of Mexican Heritage, completed in <DATE>1987</DATE>, includes full-scale 
copies of mosaics, sculptures and glyphs from the Olmec, <LOCATION>Zapotec</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Teotihuacan</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Toltec</LOCATION>, Mayan, Aztec, Huastec and Totonac cultures. 
</P>
<P>
There's a circular calendar stone copied from one found buried in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>, 
a sacrificial chacmool figure from the ruins at <ORGANIZATION>Chichen Itza</ORGANIZATION>, a bas-relief from 
the ball court at <LOCATION>El Tajin</LOCATION>, and a god of pulque, the pungent fermented wine 
said to have led to the downfall of Quetzalcoatl, the priest-leader of <LOCATION>Tula</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The plaza also features subtropical plants native to the lush environment of 
southern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and desert plants from the arid areas of northern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Giant calendar stone anchors Forest Lawn's Plaza of Mexican Heritage in 
the Hollywood Hills. ; Photo, Soaring Toltec warrior is a copy of form used as 
pillars in some ancient temple construction. ; Photo, Feathered stone face of 
serpent symbolizing Quetzalcoatl, a principal god of ancient Aztecs, is set 
into wall at park. KEN LUBAS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
FOREST LAWN MEMORIAL PARK; MEXICO -- CULTURE; ART EXHIBITS; SCULPTURE; 
CEMETERIES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA081190-0056 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 260294 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 11, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 2; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
697 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STAGE REVIEW; 
</P>
<P>
'BUSCANDO AMERICA' FINDS A PARODISTIC BRILLIANCE; 
</P>
<P>
THEATER: AN AZTEC GOD WHO AWAKENS IN LOS ANGELES GENERATES A MULTITUDE OF 
INTERESTING SITUATIONS. ITS LIMITATIONS ASIDE, THE PLAY SUCCEEDS IN SHOWING THE 
SHALLOWNESS OF MODERN VALUES. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By By JAN HERMAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SANTA ANA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
What happens when an Aztec god who has lost his powers wakes up on a <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> street and nobody recognizes him? For one thing, you get an allegorical 
sendup of Latino culture that unfolds at times with brilliant parodistic 
energy. 
</P>
<P>
The central premise of <PERSON>Roy Conboy</PERSON>'s "Buscando America/Seeking <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>," which 
opened <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Rancho Santiago College</ORGANIZATION>, couldn't be more pointed in its 
intention to satirize not only the shallowness of contemporary values but also 
the god's inflated vanity and injured pride. 
</P>
<P>
The play does this by exploiting the screwball misunderstandings engendered in 
the basic situation -- which is not unlike the landing of a dumbfounded Martian 
-- multiplying them from one scene to the next with a lowly taco vendor, a pair 
of star-struck Hollywood tourists, a macho drug dealer and his girlfriends, a 
rich woman unsatisfied by her wealth and an imperious magistrate. 
</P>
<P>
The funniest scene by far depicts the god <ORGANIZATION>Quetzalcoatl</ORGANIZATION>'s confrontation with 
Carlos the drug dealer, a strutting vato who worships money, women and his 
immaculately polished, "chariot de oro" pickup truck -- not necessarily in that 
order. The humor is greatest here because it cuts closest to the bone (with no 
small thanks to <PERSON>Eddie Rivera</PERSON>'s exaggerated performance as Carlos). 
</P>
<P>
But as enlightenment begins to dawn on Quetzalcoatl, whose quest to regain his 
former powers provides the play with its satirical thrust, it becomes all too 
apparent that "Buscando America" is trying for pathos as well as bitng social 
commentary. 
</P>
<P>
Unfortunately, <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON> is much less successful at engaging our pity than our 
laughter -- mainly because the writing loses its tension and the tone becomes 
self-indulgent when it takes aim at the tragic dimensions of the story. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, the mythic legend at the heart of the play -- Quetzalcoatl's conflict 
with his brother god Tezcatlipoca -- is established in absurdist terms as an 
Orwellian thriller replete with <ORGANIZATION>Big Brotherish</ORGANIZATION> video newscasts and 
pistol-toting assassins in trench coats and aviator sunglasses. 
</P>
<P>
All of this is played against the vivid backdrop of a huge billboard depicting 
a black cityscape silhouetted by a bright, yellow sky and big, bouncy letters 
proclaiming: "Hello from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>." On either side of the billboard are two 
painted skeletons. The stage floor bears the death's-head emblem of an enormous 
white skull. The blend -- while inventive and visually rich -- just does not 
lends itself to pathos. 
</P>
<P>
The cast, in the meantime, shows the intense enthusiasm of amateurs imbued with 
belief, if not always with polish. As Quetzalcoatl, <PERSON>Michael San Roman</PERSON> brings 
great comic warmth to his performance. <PERSON>Laurie Woolery</PERSON>, who plays Tezcatlipoca 
in various guises -- including the taco vendor, a bus driver, and a corrupt 
major domo -- has a certain furious presence. 
</P>
<P>
Like <PERSON>Woolery</PERSON>, the other cast members also play multiple roles. Rivera stands 
out, though, with his pricelessly overdone strut as the drug dealer. Also 
notable is <PERSON>Jo Bond</PERSON>'s gavel-pounding magistrate, a cartoonish figure who 
purposely can't pronounce Quetzalcoatl's name. 
</P>
<P>
As the playwright, <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON> could have used more help than he has received to 
date at the various workshops where the script has been developed. The script 
still needs to be trimmed of unnecessary repetitions as well as confusing 
inconsistencies. But he clearly has a work-in-progress worth refining. As the 
director, <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON> cannot be faulted. His staging is sharp and highly theatrical. 
</P>
<P>
Finally, it ought to be said that this production of "Buscando America" 
represents something of a triumph as the maiden outing for the new 
multicultural troupe Cucucuevez, especially given its minimal financial 
resources. 
</P>
<P>
'BUSCANDO AMERICA/SEEKING <LOCATION>AMERICA</LOCATION>' 
</P>
<P>
A production of Cucucuevez at <ORGANIZATION>Rancho Santiago College</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Phillips Hall Little 
Theatre West</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION>, at <ORGANIZATION>17th St.</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Bristol</LOCATION>. Written and directed by <PERSON>Roy 
Conboy</PERSON>. With <PERSON>Michael San Roman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Laurie Woolery</PERSON>, <PERSON>Stefane</PERSON>, <PERSON>Laura S. Salcido</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Eddie Rivera</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michael Louie</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marcus Parrish</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jo Bond</PERSON>, <PERSON>Wendi de Barros</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ken 
Jensen</PERSON>. Scenic design by <PERSON>Scott Shaffer</PERSON>. Costumes by <PERSON>Gina Davidson</PERSON>. Lighting by 
<PERSON>Kris Clark</PERSON>. Music and sound by <PERSON>Marcus Parrish</PERSON>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Play Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061690-0147 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 235174 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 16, 1990, Saturday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 3; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
578 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STAGE NOTES: MULTICULTURAL TROUPE FORMS, AIMING FOR 'ART ON RUN'; 
</P>
<P>
CUCUCUEVEZ IS PRESENTING A COMEDY ABOUT THE ADVENTURES OF THE ANCIENT TOLTEC 
GOD QUETZALCOATL IN MODERN L.A. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JAN HERMAN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A new multicultural theater troupe called Cucucuevez is being formed in <LOCATION>Orange 
County</LOCATION> and will present the world premiere of <ORGANIZATION>Garden Grove</ORGANIZATION> playwright <PERSON>Roy 
Conboy</PERSON>'s comedy, "<LOCATION>Buscando America</LOCATION>," as its first production in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The 39-year-old <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON>, who will be the artistic director, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that the 
troupe "will be established for the long term" by a group of about 15 writers, 
directors and performers representing "Latinos, Anglos and Asians." 
</P>
<P>
The first production -- described as "a comedy about the adventures of the 
ancient Toltec god Quetzalcoatl in modern-day <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>" -- will be staged at 
<ORGANIZATION>Rancho Santiago College</ORGANIZATION>'s Little Theatre West in <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> for two weeks, 
beginning <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We won't have a permanent home for a while," said <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON>, a former general 
manager and casting director of the <ORGANIZATION>Grove Shakespeare Festival</ORGANIZATION>. "Among 
ourselves, we think of what we're doing as 'art on the run.' " 
</P>
<P>
The troupe, an outgrowth of the college's New Plays and Players Workshop, will 
receive logistics support from <LOCATION>Rancho Santiago</LOCATION>'s theater department but will 
have to raise <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> on its own to pay for staging "Buscando America." 
</P>
<P>
"We took the name Cucucuevez (koo-koo-KWE-ves) from the name of a homeless 
child who was found abandoned on the street by a man on his way home from 
work," <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"We want to be identified with the values that gave that child a home and 
allowed her to live and prosper," he added. "Her story also poses the question 
of how we balance the values that our culture handed down to us with the 
necessities of modern existence." 
</P>
<P>
Conboy's play has received staged readings at <ORGANIZATION>South Coast Repertory</ORGANIZATION> in the 
Hispanic Playwrights Project and at other workshops in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jose Cruz Gonzalez</PERSON>, the director of the <ORGANIZATION>Hispanic Playwrights Project</ORGANIZATION>, will also 
be a founding member of the new troupe, <PERSON>Conboy</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Scenes from "As Is," which played the Forum Theatre in <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION> <DATE>last winter</DATE> 
and subsequently transferred to the <ORGANIZATION>Comedy Store Playhouse</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, will 
be featured on "Entertainment This Week" at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on <DATE>KNBC-Channel 4</DATE> as 
part of a segment about one of its actors. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>David Napier</PERSON>, who played a role in <PERSON>William Hoffman</PERSON>'s bittersweet play about 
acquired immune deficiency syndrome, is the focus of the segment. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Karen Wong</PERSON>, who produced the segment, said it talks about how <PERSON>Napier</PERSON> copes with 
the disease in real life and how he feels playing someone with AIDS. 
</P>
<P>
Five actors who have previously appeared at the <ORGANIZATION>Grove Shakespeare Festival</ORGANIZATION> will 
co-star with actress <PERSON>Kelly McGillis</PERSON> in a benefit performance at the <ORGANIZATION>Festival 
Amphitheatre</ORGANIZATION> to help match a <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Foundation</ORGANIZATION> challenge grant, it was 
announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>McGillis</PERSON>, who was recently appointed to the classical theater's board of 
trustees, will be joined in "A <ORGANIZATION>Midsummer Night</ORGANIZATION>'s Eve at the Grove" on <DATE>July 30</DATE> 
by <PERSON>Gregory Itzin</PERSON>, <PERSON>John-Frederick Jones</PERSON>, <PERSON>Daniel Bryan Cartmell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carl Reggiardo</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Kamella Tate</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The cast, assembled by the <ORGANIZATION>Grove</ORGANIZATION>'s producing artistic director, <PERSON>Thomas F. 
Bradac</PERSON>, will give readings and perform scenes from a handful of <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>'s 
plays, including "The Taming of the Shrew," "Romeo and <PERSON>Juliet</PERSON>," "Henry V" and 
"<PERSON>Julius Caesar</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
The 12-year-old theater company also hopes to raise money with a 
pre-performance dinner to be attended by the cast and with a gallery exhibit of 
paintings by artist <PERSON>Jean Pol d. Franqueuil</PERSON> in the <ORGANIZATION>Village Green Courtyard</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For information and reservations: (714) 636-7213. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Kelly McGillis will star in a benefit to help Grove Shakespeare Festival 
match a $50,000 grant. Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880314-0254 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-88 1343EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-APN--Artifacts Adv27   03-14 1071</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Artifacts, Adv 27,1103</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv27</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, March 27</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 4 b&amp;w
photos. ColorFoto subscribers get 3 35mm slides.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A museum in southeastern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> offers clues to
three civilizations that predate the Aztecs. Among other things,
there is evidence that these ancient people probably perceived the
earth as round, designed remarkably accurate calendars and had an
advanced knowledge of mathematics and astronomy.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   A museum in southeastern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> offers clues to
three civilizations that predate the Aztecs. Among other things,
there is evidence that these ancient people probably perceived the
earth as round, designed remarkably accurate calendars and had an
advanced knowledge of mathematics and astronomy.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>XALAPA, Mexico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A museum in southeastern <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> offers clues to
three civilizations that predate the Aztecs. Among other things,
there is evidence that these ancient people probably perceived the
earth as round, designed remarkably accurate calendars and had an
advanced knowledge of mathematics and astronomy.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>END ADV for Sunday, March 27</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-10093</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CEBAEADLFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920502
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 MAY 92 / Arts: All eyes on Mayfest - A preview of the Glasgow
galleries participating in this month's festivities
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM PACKER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN THE few years since its inception, <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Mayfest</ORGANIZATION> has become an
important fixture in the British cultural calendar. Natural civic pride and
rivalry apart, it is hardly yet the equal of <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION> as an international
festival of the arts, but who would now say, with enthusiasm on the one
side, and complacency on the other, that a full reversal of the relative
positions was impossible?
So far as the visual arts are concerned, the issue is already nicely
balanced. Glasgow may not yet boast the major exhibitions which <LOCATION>Edinburgh</LOCATION>'s
museums have always the good sense to offer at festival time, with the city
full of visitors. But that effort is usually qualified by a wish to distance
it from the Festival as such, opening particular shows well beforehand and
running them on long afterwards. As for the <ORGANIZATION>Festival</ORGANIZATION> authorities, their
current advance literature is innocent of any reference to the visual arts
at all.
But <ORGANIZATION>Mayfest</ORGANIZATION> has always integrated the visual element into its programme.
This year there may be no single outstanding offering, but across the
spectrum, from public to private, some 15 galleries are participating, with
all but two of them open by this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, and a further eight listed in
association.
To try the flavour, I visited four shows, one of which, at the <ORGANIZATION>Collins
Gallery</ORGANIZATION> (22 <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> Street: until <DATE>June 6</DATE>), with the opening due on <DATE>Friday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>, was on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> but a flurry of carpentry, paint and
wallpaper and a gleam in the artist's eye. 'Access', by <PERSON>Jim Buckley</PERSON>, is to
be an installation that takes further the images he first developed in his
sculpture. This he based on the old peepshow principle, making boxes with
interiors that proposed their own imaginative scale and reality.
Here, in one darkened gold-papered room, <PERSON>Buckley</PERSON> has set into the wall four
large display transparencies taken from the boxes he showed in <LOCATION>Kunst Europa</LOCATION>
in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> last year, the images imagined, richly decorated, sanctuary-like
interiors. The other room, white and light, holds seven peepholes through
which to view photographic details of actual architectural interiors found
in the city itself.
<PERSON>Cyril Gerber</PERSON> was the first dealer to bring modern and contemporary art to
<LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>, and he stands naturally at the heart of <LOCATION>Mayfest</LOCATION>. At his personal
gallery (148 West Regent Street: until <DATE>May 23</DATE>) he shows <PERSON>Benjamin Creme</PERSON>, a
Glaswegian painter now 70 but long neglected. The work here is of the <DATE>1940s</DATE>,
when <ORGANIZATION>Creme</ORGANIZATION> was taken up by the emigre Polish painters <PERSON>Josef Herman</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Jankel Adler</PERSON> then living in <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION>, and the <DATE>1950s</DATE> when he was in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and
one of the circle of <LOCATION>Minton</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>MacBryde</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Colquhoun</PERSON> and others. The figure
drawings and paintings are especially interesting, sophisticated in their
modernism, after <PERSON>Braque</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>, yet direct and personal in feeling and
character.
Up the road at his <ORGANIZATION>Compass Gallery</ORGANIZATION> (178 West Regent Street: until <DATE>May 21</DATE>),
<PERSON>Gerber</PERSON> is showing the recent work of a most distinctive Scottish
print-maker, <PERSON>Elspeth Lamb</PERSON>. With her 'Cornerstones', she offers us the fruit
of a recent visit to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> where she was particularly taken both by the
popular festivals of the Day of the Dead and the ancient architectural
carvings and hieroglyphs of <ORGANIZATION>Chichen Itza</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Teotihuacan</LOCATION> and Quetzalcoatl.
But what makes her show remarkable is not so much the imagery as the medium
by which she has developed and quite literally expressed it. Making the
paper herself, saturating the pulp with pigment, she at once simplifies and
concentrates the image while impressing it into the very fabric of her
material. The paper is itself the image: and rich and dense and beautiful
too.
The <ORGANIZATION>Transmission Gallery</ORGANIZATION> (28 King Street) is a co-operative run by a
changing committee of five artists to show not their own but the work of
artists they would wish to see. Throughout May it offers a group show - a
collaborative relief-cum-lightwork by <PERSON>Paul Maguire</PERSON> and <PERSON>Simon Starling</PERSON>,
consisting of three isometric cubes, small, medium and large, described by
white neon tubes; four cibachrome prints of a leather holster, by <PERSON>Michael
McDonough</PERSON>; and a set of of ironically dispassionate photographs of taped and
sand-bagged windows, taken in <LOCATION>Zagreb</LOCATION> <DATE>last November</DATE> by <PERSON>Donald Urquhart</PERSON>.
Small, black and white, the format insistent in its simple frontality, the
plastic bags oddly disturbing in the way they are heaped and trussed, they
are rather impressive.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06225113 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06225113 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  CONSUMER; QA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Q  Along I-505, a cutoff between I-80 and I-5 35 miles southwest of
Sacramento, a sign off the Road 31 exit reads "D.Q.U." What does this mean?;  
 -- R.W., Palo Alto  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ON THE ROAD TO HIGHER EDUCATION  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Action Line  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  A  It directs people to <ORGANIZATION>Deganawidah Quetzalcoatl University</ORGANIZATION>, now known as <ORGANIZATION>D-Q
University</ORGANIZATION>. It's a small, accredited two-year college with <PERCENT>65 percent</PERCENT> of its
300 students American Indians. The college opened in <DATE>1971</DATE> using the original
name. <PERSON>David Childress</PERSON>, a D-Q spokesman, says <PERSON>Deganawidah</PERSON> is a hero in Indian
culture. He says the <LOCATION>Mohawk</LOCATION> tribe uses the name in its religious ceremonies
and asked the college not to use it in its name. The school complied in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
<PERSON>Childress</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>Quetzalcoatl</ORGANIZATION> is a South American Indian mythical god of
learning and wisdom. D-Q <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> is between <ORGANIZATION>Winters</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Davis</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Yolo
County.</LOCATION>;    Redeeming value;  Q  Boy, am I miffed. I went to <ORGANIZATION>Blockbuster Video</ORGANIZATION>
where there was a promotion that said, "Rent three videos and get a free
Subway sandwich." I rented three videos and received a coupon that stated,
"Good for a free 6-inch sandwich excluding double meat and double cheese
sandwiches." The coupon had a picture of a huge sandwich printed on it. I took
it into a Subway location to get my free sandwich and was told the coupon is
only redeemable for sandwiches up to <MONEY>$2.49</MONEY>. A <MONEY>$2.49</MONEY> sandwich is about equal to
mustard on a bun. The manager refused to fill my order for a six-inch sandwich
(excluding double meat and double cheese). This sure sounds like the old bait
and switch to me. Though it's only a stupid sandwich, I feel consumers should
band together. A coupon should be redeemable for what it says.;    -- <PERSON>Roger
Vance</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>; A  Agreed, says <PERSON>Scott Abbott</PERSON>, official with <ORGANIZATION>Subway
Development Co</ORGANIZATION>. Abbott apologizes for the rejection. He says you should have
received a free six-inch sandwich at any participating Subway location,
regardless of whether the sandwich is valued at more than <MONEY>$2.49</MONEY>. You didn't
specify which location you went to, so he's not sure if you went to a
participating spot. Abbott is making sure all franchise owners are aware that
people with those Blockbuster coupons are supposed to receive a free sandwich.
He says the <MONEY>$2.49</MONEY> value was supposed to be a guide and Blockbuster had
requested a value be printed on the coupons. Abbott is sending you a coupon
for a free sandwich compliments of <ORGANIZATION>Subway Development Co.</ORGANIZATION>;    Call for help; 
Q  I purchased a Pac Tel phone, model FE 5150. It was missing the wall/desk
mounting bracket. I have been trying to call the toll-free 800 number printed
on the instruction sheet. I get either a recording a busy signal but have
never been able to talk to a customer-service rep. I really need the bracket.;
   -- <PERSON>C. Alvarez</PERSON>, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>; A  The bracket is being shipped to you now, says
<PERSON>Amy Damianakes</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Pac Tel Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Damianakes says <ORGANIZATION>Pac Tel</ORGANIZATION> sold the telephone
line a few years back to a company that wasn't ready to handle the volume of
sales. She says the reason you had trouble getting through to the toll-free
number was that the company didn't have a customer-service department until
recently. <PERSON>Damianakes</PERSON> did secure the mounting bracket and is making sure you
get it.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910812  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  559  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday August 12, 1991
00225113,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06283280 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06283280 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Ron Burda -- Mercury News; "Discourse of Circles," 1990, by
Leslie Kaiser, invites the viewer to touch. Thirteen countries are represented
in the show. The rich mix includes a Russian artist living in Seattle, a Czech
in Australia, a Chinese artist living in the United States who must exhibit
anonymously for safety reasons.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; ART; SHOW; HAYWARD; COLLEGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  "Of making many books there is no end.";   Ecclesiastes xii, 12.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  East Extra  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EXHIBIT SURE TO DELIGHT BIBLIOPHILES, ART LOVERS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Also ran in WL1; Community News  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     And a good thing too.;   Bibliophiles and art lovers have a treat in a show
that speaks volumes at the <ORGANIZATION>Cal State Hayward</ORGANIZATION> art gallery. Under the guest
curatorship of <PERSON>Judith Hoffberg</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, 140 contemporary artists have
contributed works for "Cross Currents: Bookworks from the Edge of the
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.";   There's a whole category of art that takes its inspiration from
the idea of the book. In this show, some creations barely touch base with the
book notion before whirling off into metaphor. Some "books" are pages strung
on lines, the individual sheets revealing as much as personal laundry hung
out.;   Others flip open like a child's toy, fan out in accordion pleats or
are folded to represent the sail shapes of the <LOCATION>Sydney</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>) <ORGANIZATION>Opera House</ORGANIZATION>.
You'll find book as political statement, book as intimate personal journey.
The book as object -- say, decorative books in model homes -- is represented
by bricks stamped like book bindings.;   "There's lots of energy here," said
<PERSON>Lew Carson</PERSON>, gallery director, noting the contrast between high- and low-tech
works. The printing technology ranges from hand lettering and wood blocks to
<ORGANIZATION>Xerox</ORGANIZATION> and laser prints. Covers are stamped leather, carved wood, handmade
papers.;   Some of the volumes are fragile, but the show is color coded with
dots marking which books may be opened by the viewer and which should be taken
to the attendant. The curator has thoughtfully provided 100 sets of white
cotton gloves for handling the books.;   Thirteen countries are represented in
the show. The rich mix includes a Russian artist living in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, a Czech in
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, a Chinese artist living in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> who must exhibit
anonymously for safety reasons. Artists living on the <LOCATION>Pacific Rim</LOCATION> have a
different sensibility from those in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hoffberg</PERSON> believes. In the
introductory statement, she writes: "There is something deeply spiritual about
the <LOCATION>Pacific Rim</LOCATION>; it is as if the spirals uncoiled, joining us all to each
other, with a binding that is not tight, but which loosely affects us all.";  
The book show is to be read at many levels. The Chinese political piece, "A
Page in History, <DATE>1989</DATE>," depicts events surrounding the <LOCATION>Tiananmen Square</LOCATION>
massacre. The images are recorded as black and white photocopied news photos
spread on a scroll of rice paper evoking the sense of a roll of film
unfolding.;   Among the visual treats are <PERSON>Michael Tuffery</PERSON>'s wooden cover with
carved tortoise, lizard and crab and <PERSON>Sonya Rapoport</PERSON>'s "Chinese Connection," a
string of bright illustrations and commentary on how the mind and eye work.
<PERSON>Ismael Vargas</PERSON>' feathery Mexican stand-up piece "Quetzalcoatl in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>"
leads the eye right to the bright pop and religious images of "La Bomba" by
Ecuadoran artist <PERSON>Marco Alvarado</PERSON> Lopez.;   <PERSON>Barbara Pucci</PERSON>'s small book "Janson:
His Story" is a commentary on the author of the best-known college art history
text, infamous for ignoring women. Among pages of her own illustrations and
text on art history, the artist has inserted blank pages inscribed with such
statements as, "About women from classical <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Janson</PERSON> says: Nothing." And
so on through the great ages of art, <PERSON>Janson</PERSON> continues to say: "Nothing.";  
The show is one vast reading room of commentary within commentary. Having
begun in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, it continues through <DATE>Oct. 25</DATE> at <LOCATION>Cal State</LOCATION>, then moves
to <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and Japan.; IF YOU'RE INTERESTED; Gallery hours are
<DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>3 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, 1 to <TIME>7 p.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Saturday,
1</DATE> to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> Closed <DATE>Friday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The gallery is on the first floor of the
Arts and Education Building of the <LOCATION>Cal State Hayward</LOCATION> campus. For information,
call (510) 881-4299.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ROBIN WORTHINGTON, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911009  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  680  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, October 9, 1991
00283280,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-2118</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CITABAAQFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920919
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 SEP 92 / Arts: Cultures before Columbus - An ancient art with a
modern feel
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By TIMOTHY POTTS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE quincentenary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s landfall in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> has been the source of
considerable soul searching in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>. While mainstream Mr and <LOCATION>Ms America</LOCATION>
may be happy to celebrate <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s Transatlantic leap, the original new
worlders (not to mention the watchdogs of political correctness) are
demanding apologies and penance for the devastation which the 'white gods'
from the east wrought on the indigeous peoples they encountered.
There is then a timeliness in The Art of <LOCATION>Ancient Mexico</LOCATION>, a fascinating and
worthy celebration of the arts of the Olmecs, <LOCATION>Mayas</LOCATION>, Aztecs and other
cultures which dominated <LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION> for some 3,000 years before the arrival
of the Spanish. The works have been assembled from the major public
collections of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, judiciously supplemented by the British Museum
(Museum of <LOCATION>Mankind</LOCATION>).
It has been over 20 years since the last major exhibition of ancient Mexican
art in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, and an innocent eye is in this case not a bad way to confront
cultures at once so alien and yet visually accessible. By eliciting
reactions we normally expect only from modern western art, Precolumbian art
stoutly refuses to be approached in a narrowly archaeological or even
historical mindset.
A palma of Brancusi-like simplicity and elegance demands to be admired as
pure form, despite its presumed religious or practical function. A Totonac
sculptor carves a head in which only one half of the face is shown, the
other half left undefined and emerging from its stone casing. It is all one
can do to resist images of <ORGANIZATION>Michelangelo</ORGANIZATION>'s bound figures in the <LOCATION>Louvre</LOCATION>. The
<PERSON>Chac Mool</PERSON> reclining on his elbows, was so thoroughly imbibed by <PERSON>Moore</PERSON> that
it seems here strangely familiar and modern. So too the Huastec sculptures
and a <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> jaguar mask which have a futuristic primitivism that is pure
Star Wars. <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> can surely boast some of the most alien of all human art
and it is no accident that <PERSON>Eric von Daniken</PERSON> found here so much fodder for
his extra terrestrial dreamings.
Mayan art, widely regarded as the high-point of the Precolumbian
achievement, took the decorative and iconographic principles established by
the Olmecs in the centuries before <LOCATION>Christ</LOCATION> to a new level of delicacy and
refinement. Jaina ceramic figurines of a women, priests and warriors are
exquisite genre studies whose faces are to be seen all over the Yucatan to
this day. Jade was exploited to lavish effect in relief carvings and, most
spectacularly, in human masks. The so-called 'eccentric flints', fashioned
by knapping the brittle stone with extraordinary skill into bizarre forms,
remain something of an enigma. Disappointingly, there is not a single piece
of 'narrative style' Mayan pottery, in which the native American's show a
remarkable facility for two-dimensional naturalism - an unexpected foil to
the mainstream spirit of strict iconographical formalism.
One surprise is the virtual silence in which the exhibition passes over the
revolution currently taking place in Mayan studies from the decipherment of
the Mayan hieroglyphic script. Since the script is itself a pictorial code
whose understanding is intimately linked to the symbolism of Mayan art, this
new insight lifts a veil from Mayan iconography too. As in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, much
ancient Mexican art needs to be deciphered in as precise and literal a way
as writing. The more official and ceremonial pieces are interspersed with
pottery and other items of everyday use, including rare wood-carvings. These
are much more spontaneous and imaginative, showing the exuberance of the
household or village craft tradition. In the human- and animal-shaped
vessels of the <LOCATION>Colima</LOCATION> potters lies a virtual menagerie of local wildlife and
domestic scenes - a baby, an emaciated hunchback, an acrobat - keenly
observed with real sympathy and inventively adapted to shapes that can also
function as vessels.
The show has been laid out with a keen eye for design and lighting, with
adequate wall tests including evocative quotations from ancient Mexican
texts. The designers have made the most of an awkward ramp at the entrance
by arranging a series of intimidating Huastec statues in sentry-like rows.
The layout of material is by regions, which only partly correspond to the
major cultural entities (<ORGANIZATION>Olmec</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Maya</ORGANIZATION>, Aztec etc.) and cuts across both media
and periods. No system is perfect but this is a half-way measure which fully
serves neither an archaeological nor an artistic end.
The handsome catalogue is itself no small design achievement whose superb
illustrations provide much food for further thought and admiration. Alas the
text - a direct translation of the Spanish version - is rather idiosyncratic
in its selection of themes and suffers from the user-unfriendly focus of
academics. The short bibliography ignores most of the major English-language
studies.
The gold which fuelled the Conquistadores ravages is conspicuoulsy absent
from The Art of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. This is only partly the result of the mindless orgy
in which the finest handiwork of the American goldsmiths was consigned
wholesale to the melting pot by the Spanish invaders. Unlike their South
American contemporaries, the Classic and earlier cultures of <LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION> did
not much value the yellow metal, importing it from the south only sparingly.
The Hayward show rightly avoids any hint of gold lust, focusing instead on
the myriad other artictic achievements of these most ill-fated of peoples.
The Art of <LOCATION>Ancient Mexico</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Hayward Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>September 17</DATE> - <DATE>December 6, 1992</DATE>
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XVI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06033065 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06033065 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  WE all need something to soothe the ache in our souls these days.;   
Fortunately for you, I was struck down Tuesday by the Hades simplex mutant
intestinal virus, so that I have had plenty of time to lie very still on the
sofa and -- in between fever-driven visions of the feathered serpent
Quetzalcoatl -- turn the keen razor of my mind on the future of America.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COLUMNIST'S CREATIVE ENERGY CURBS A WORLD
CRISIS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  McEnroe is a columnist for the Hartford, Conn., Courant.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     My gaze drifts aloft, to Venus.;    From <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> comes the only bit of good
news we have received all week. (It is not precisely clear to me why we are
able to know when somebody moves a crate of apricots across a gorge on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
but we pretty much throw up our hands over whether <LOCATION>Iraq</LOCATION> has jets backed up
bumper to bumper on the inbound <ORGANIZATION>Hammurabi Expressway</ORGANIZATION>.);    Anyway, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has
come up with the news that there are spider-shaped volcanic bulges on Venus
(which, for a planet named after the goddess of love, turns out to have the
kind of big-time cellulite problems we would be more apt to associate with a
planet named after, say, <PERSON>Marge Schott</PERSON>).;    I have traditionally been a
detractor of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> because (a) it's in my nature, generally, to detract; I
can't help that, and (b) I believe <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has not come up with very much for the
commonweal except for the occasional polymer-coated technological marvel, such
as <PERSON>John Glenn.</PERSON>;    In this instance, however, I believe the <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> people are
onto something. They theorize that these spider-shaped bulges were formed when
huge blobs of molten rock inside <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> rose upward, creating fissures, bulges,
volcanic dikes and lava flows.;    Scientists now think the surface of Venus
is shaped by what they call (no kidding) "blob tectonics," the process by
which enormous giblets of molten rock drift upward toward the surface. On
Earth, this process resulted in the formation of the <LOCATION>Hawaiian Islands</LOCATION> as well
as <PERSON>Morton Downey Jr.</PERSON> (Well, nobody's that grown up.);    The idea that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>
is seething with hot molten rock is a fairly new one because <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> is covered
with thick clouds. In <DATE>1918</DATE>, Swedish scientist <PERSON>Svante Arrhenius</PERSON> theorized that
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> must be covered with seas, swamps and steamy jungles, which might well
be inhabited by primeval monsters. Because of all the clouds, you see.
Arrhenius won a <ORGANIZATION>Nobel Prize</ORGANIZATION>. Boy, they were handing them out like Mylanta
tablets back then.;    When this war is over, let's face it, an oil change is
going to cost about the same as filling your crankcase with morel mushrooms.
So we need a new source of energy, and blob tectonics could be the answer.;   
Why couldn't we heat our homes and power our turbines with all that nice hot
magma sloshing around up on Venus?;    Because, you say, it's on Venus.;   
That is the difference between you, a moiling scullion in the common ruck, and
me, a lofty visionary.;    Here is my scheme: We install the
Inter-Solar-System Venus-to-Earth Molten-Rock Pipeline. (Faithful readers of
this column may wish to leaf back a few years in their carefully maintained
laminated loose-leaf binders and marvel at the resemblance of this plan to my
previous Alaskan Ice Cream Roll Pipeline).;    We run this pipeline (some kind
of heat-proof, flexible tubing -- get the guys who did the McDLT box right on
it) down from <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> to, let's say, <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio.</LOCATION>;    I realize it's going to
obstruct the view a little, but what's there to look at in <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>?
Anyway, President <PERSON>Gephardt</PERSON> (it's inevitable, now) isn't going to stick it in
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, is he? Plus, you'll get tourists.;    We're moving fast here, I
realize, but is everyone still with me? We get the hot rock from <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>. Who's
going to kick about it? They got no <ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club</ORGANIZATION> up there. Once we set up the
pipeline, it's easier than pumping oil because it's all downhill, right?;   
So all I've done is figured out a way for us to get free energy, pay off the
national debt and thumb our noses at the rest of the world. (It's the American
way.);    Now try to keep things running smoothly for a while. It's too much
trouble for me to be getting sick all the time.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Colin McEnroe column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910202  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  719  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday February 2, 1991
00033065,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-9039 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreeu076__a94057" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EEU-94-076-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Romania </F>
<H3> <TI>   Official Previews Crans Montana Talks </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Official Previews Crans Montana Talks </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   AU1804161894 Bucharest ROMPRES in English 1439 GMT 18 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> AU1804161894 </F>
<F P=104>  Bucharest ROMPRES </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Bucharest ROMPRES</LOCATION>, 18/4/1994 -- In the presence of 
<PERSON>Jean Paul-Carteron</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Forum Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Romanian Government</ORGANIZATION>'s secretary-general and secretary-general of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Crans Montana Conference</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> Viorel Hrebenciuc and 
numerous mass media representatives the press centre was 
inaugurated on 18 <DATE>April</DATE> of the <ORGANIZATION>Crans Montana Forum</ORGANIZATION> due in 
<LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> over <DATE>21-24 April</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry Spokeswoman Simona 
Miculescu</ORGANIZATION> will be spokeswoman also of the centre. 
  The press centre will issue every morning a document in 
Romanian, English and French with details of the day's schedule. 
It will also issue daily press releases in Romanian, French and 
English referring to the debates in plenum and in the sections 
on themes. They will comprise syntheses of the participants' 
addresses. Journalists will also receive Romanian and foreign 
press reviews, home and foreign news supplied by the ROMPRES 
national news agency, the texts of the statements and addresses 
of the previous day's speakers, other publications. The 
spokesperson will meet the journalists daily at 1300 hours [1000 
GMT]. Journalists that want to contact various personalities 
will apply directly to the office set up to this end under the 
conference's secretariat general. The press office will 
function daily between 0800 hours [0500 GMT] and <DATE>2000</DATE> [1700 
GMT]. It will accommodate also offices of the national radio, 
television and of ROMPRES. The documents issued by the press 
centre will not be official. 
  So far, the following heads of state have confirmed their 
participation in the <LOCATION>Crans-Montana</LOCATION> Forum: of <LOCATION>Cyprus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Belarus</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Lithuania</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Palestine Liberation 
Organization</ORGANIZATION>. All in all there will be 1,100 participants and 
700 journalists. Mme. <PERSON>Catherine Lalumiere</PERSON> will be present on 
the presidium at the inaugural session. Participating will also 
be nine prime ministers and deputy prime ministers, five 
parliament presidents and speakers, 12 foreign ministers and 
deputy foreign ministers, 20 ministers, 17 ambassadors, 12 
secretaries-general and assistant secretaries-general of 
international organizations, 67 members of the diplomatic corps 
accredited in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION>, 129 other political personalities. 
  The meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>Crans Montana Forum</ORGANIZATION>, a world-scale event, 
is going to take place over <DATE>April 21-24</DATE> in <LOCATION>Bucharest</LOCATION> at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament Palace</ORGANIZATION>, one of the world's largest buildings. 
  With a surface of 508,000 square meters, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament 
Palace</ORGANIZATION> is mentioned by the Guiness book of records as the second 
largest administrative building in the world, next to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Pentagon</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> with a total surface of 604,000 square 
meters. 
  In point of the constructed volume, the palace is world's 
third with 2,550,000 square meters, next to a sky-rockets 
assembling building in <LOCATION>Cape Canevral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, with 3,666,000 
square meters and Quetzalcoatl Pyramid at <LOCATION>Cholula</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, with 
3,300,000 square meters, but ahead of the Keops pyramid ranked 
fourth with 2,500,000 square meters. 
  The construction works started on <DATE>June 25, 1984</DATE>, and 
swallowed about 480,000 cubic meters of high-quality cement, 
65,000 tonnes of steel for reinforced concrete, 42,000 tonnes of 
rolled steel. 
  The palace is furnished with a 286,000 square meter green 
backyard. 
  The building is the outcome of a great national effort, 
starting from its design and erection and ending with the 
materials suppliers, everything is Romanian. About 17,000 
people have worked on the building site. 
  Along with numerous main and secondary offices, reception 
rooms, meeting rooms, a plenary sitting room of the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of 
Deputies</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>'s Palace has also a set of halls, rooms 
and lobbies impressing through astonishing elegance, size, 
furnishings and design, bearing names such as the main hall, the 
honorary gallery, the hall of the provinces, the union hall, the 
lobby of the union hall, the human rights hall. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880529-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-29-88 2348EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Mexico-Civilization     05-29 0945</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mexico-Civilization,0974</SECOND>
<HEAD>Delta Yields Traces Of Another Ancient Mexican Civilization</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ISAAC A. LEVI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>XALAPA, Mexico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deep in a mangrove swamp near the <LOCATION>Gulf of
Mexico</LOCATION>, archaeologists have discovered traces of what could be
another ancient Mexican civilization.
   So far, the only clues to these mysterious people are a four-ton
stele, or stone slab, covered with hieroglyphic writing and a
19-inch-high clay figure of a fertility-rite priest.
   ``But,'' says <PERSON>Fernando Winfield Capitaine</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Xalapa Museum of Anthropology</ORGANIZATION>, ``the finds are so promising that
the museum is planning to mount an expedition to that area of
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> state in cooperation with the <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic
Society</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The stele was found in <DATE>November 1986</DATE>. It is covered with
inscriptions in an unknown language but with some Mayan numerals.
   The priest in the clay figure is wearing the human skin of a
flayed sacrificial victim.
   Both are about 1,800 years old.
   ``That would place them in the <DATE>second century A.D.</DATE>, which is
after the archaeological Olmecs, who flourished in the area from
around <DATE>1050</DATE> to 500 B.C., and before the Mayas who emerged around
the fourth century A.D,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said in an interview.
   Adding to the intrigue, the Mayas lived in the <LOCATION>Yucatan
Peninsula</LOCATION>, more than 700 miles to the east, <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said at the
museum in <LOCATION>Xalapa</LOCATION>, where the stele and figure are kept.
   ``But there are two dates on the stele in Mayan writing, in
their so-called Long Count Calendar made up of dots and bars,
equivalent to <DATE>May 22</DATE>, 143 (A.D.), and <DATE>July 13</DATE>, 156 A.D.,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON>
said.
   If the mysterious people did exist, <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said, they also
appeared to be unrelated to the other two of the four known
civilizations that inhabited the gulf coast: the Totonacas, who
emerged around the seventh century <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> in the area where the
artifacts were found, or the Huaxtecas farther north, about one
century later.
   ``They could be the Xicalancas, of which Clavijero briefly
talked about,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said, referring to the Rev. <PERSON>Francisco
Javier Francisco Javier Clavijero</PERSON> (1731-1787), a Jesuit priest who
was the first to systematically study <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s ancient languages
and peoples.
   In his ``History of Ancient Mexico,'' Clavijero in three lines
briefly mentioned the Xicalanca civilization in relation to the
Olmecs, but did not go into details.
   In ``nahuatl,'' the trading language of the Aztecs, who came
much later, Xicalanca means ``the people who live by the Great Body
of Salt Water,'' as the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION> was called.
   The two artifacts were found within 130 feet of each other in
the village of <LOCATION>La Mojarra</LOCATION>, where the <LOCATION>Piojo River</LOCATION> meets the <LOCATION>Acula
River</LOCATION>. The crocodile-infested region is so swampy that it can be
reached only by boat, <ORGANIZATION>Winfield</ORGANIZATION> said.
   La Mojarra, with a population of fewer than 200, is up the <LOCATION>Acula</LOCATION>
about 20 miles south of the port of Alvarado in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> state. But
neither the village nor the <LOCATION>Piojo River</LOCATION> can be found on any map of
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Carved in relief on the previously polished stele, which is of
basalt, one of the world's hardest rocks, is the full length
profile of a regal figure, a man about 25 years old, holding out in
both hands a vessel in a gesture of offering.
   ``He was probably a ruler, or a chief warrior, or a high priest
_ or maybe all three since that was the custom in the gulf region
in ancient times,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said.
   The figure wears ear-stops, a tall headdress adorned with four
representations of something like a rain god, trimmed with eight
feathers, and a breastplate full of other allegorical figures over
what appears to be a pleated cotton shirt or tunic.
   A total of 577 glyphs, or picture-words, divided into 21 neat
rows running from top to bottom, plus 33 ``elements'' like the
rain-god representations, cover the rest of the slab.
   ``It was all carved during one continuous period,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON>
said. ``It was a single piece of work. It is the oldest and richest
piece of writing found yet about this area of ancient <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.''
   About 7 feet tall, slightly oblong and with a gently rounded
top, the stele once stood on the right bank of the Acula, just
outside La Mojarra.
   Over the years, erosion toppled it, and it lay in the river
until a fisherman discovered it and dragged it out with the help of
villagers.
   Archaeologists retrieved the stele, but <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said he kept
the find quiet for two years so work could proceed ``without the
pressure that such a discovery creates.''
   The second piece, the ceramic figure of a priest made with the
region's thick orange clay, has a square base. It is the only one
of two artifacts from that area with a base. The other, also in the
museum, is so badly damaged it cannot be studied, <ORGANIZATION>Winfield</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In the La Mojarra figure, only the head is missing.
   That type of clay figure was very popular among the four gulf
cultures. The Aztecs called it in Xipe Totec, or the Lord of the
Flayed, and it was variously worshiped as the god of <DATE>spring</DATE>, of
fertility, of abundance and of the metalworkers.
   A peasant at La Mojarra found the shattered figure many years
ago while digging the foundations for his house and kept the pieces
in a cardboard box.
   ``We got wind of it three weeks ago, and we convinced him to let
the museum have it,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said.
   Winfield suspects the La Mojarra area could have been a
ceremonial site.
   ``If so, there surely must be more stele and artifacts to be
found,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880525-0306 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-25-88 0754EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Mexico-Civilization Adv30   05-25 0957</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mexico-Civilization, Adv 30,0985</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv30</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Mon AMs, May 30, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Delta Yields Traces of Another Ancient Mexican Civilization</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ISAAC A. LEVI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>XALAPA, Mexico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Deep in a mangrove swamp near the <LOCATION>Gulf of
Mexico</LOCATION>, archaeologists have discovered traces of what could be
another ancient Mexican civilization.
   So far, the only clues to these mysterious people are a four-ton
stele, or stone slab, covered with hieroglyphic writing and a
19-inch-high clay figure of a fertility-rite priest.
   ``But,'' says <PERSON>Fernando Winfield Capitaine</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>Xalapa Museum of Anthropology</ORGANIZATION>, ``the finds are so promising that
the museum is planning to mount an expedition to that area of
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> state in cooperation with the <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic
Society</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The stele was found in <DATE>November 1986</DATE>. It is covered with
inscriptions in an unknown language but with some Mayan numerals.
   The priest in the clay figure is wearing the human skin of a
flayed sacrificial victim.
   Both are about 1,800 years old.
   ``That would place them in the <DATE>second century A.D.</DATE>, which is
after the archaeological Olmecs, who flourished in the area from
around <DATE>1050</DATE> to 500 B.C., and before the Mayas who emerged around
the fourth century A.D,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said in an interview.
   Adding to the intrigue, the Mayas lived in the <LOCATION>Yucatan
Peninsula</LOCATION>, more than 700 miles to the east, <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said at the
museum in <LOCATION>Xalapa</LOCATION>, where the stele and figure are kept.
   ``But there are two dates on the stele in Mayan writing, in
their so-called Long Count Calendar made up of dots and bars,
equivalent to <DATE>May 22</DATE>, 143 (A.D.), and <DATE>July 13</DATE>, 156 A.D.,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON>
said.
   If the mysterious people did exist, <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said, they also
appeared to be unrelated to the other two of the four known
civilizations that inhabited the gulf coast: the Totonacas, who
emerged around the seventh century <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> in the area where the
artifacts were found, or the Huaxtecas farther north, about one
century later.
   ``They could be the Xicalancas, of which Clavijero briefly
talked about,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said, referring to the Rev. <PERSON>Francisco
Javier Francisco Javier Clavijero</PERSON> (1731-1787), a Jesuit priest who
was the first to systematically study <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s ancient languages
and peoples.
   In his ``History of Ancient Mexico,'' Clavijero in three lines
briefly mentioned the Xicalanca civilization in relation to the
Olmecs, but did not go into details.
   In ``nahuatl,'' the trading language of the Aztecs, who came
much later, Xicalanca means ``the people who live by the Great Body
of Salt Water,'' as the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION> was called.
   The two artifacts were found within 130 feet of each other in
the village of <LOCATION>La Mojarra</LOCATION>, where the <LOCATION>Piojo River</LOCATION> meets the <LOCATION>Acula
River</LOCATION>. The crocodile-infested region is so swampy that it can be
reached only by boat, <ORGANIZATION>Winfield</ORGANIZATION> said.
   La Mojarra, with a population of fewer than 200, is up the <LOCATION>Acula</LOCATION>
about 20 miles south of the port of Alvarado in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> state. But
neither the village nor the <LOCATION>Piojo River</LOCATION> can be found on any map of
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Carved in relief on the previously polished stele, which is of
basalt, one of the world's hardest rocks, is the full length
profile of a regal figure, a man about 25 years old, holding out in
both hands a vessel in a gesture of offering.
   ``He was probably a ruler, or a chief warrior, or a high priest
_ or maybe all three since that was the custom in the gulf region
in ancient times,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said.
   The figure wears ear-stops, a tall headdress adorned with four
representations of something like a rain god, trimmed with eight
feathers, and a breastplate full of other allegorical figures over
what appears to be a pleated cotton shirt or tunic.
   A total of 577 glyphs, or picture-words, divided into 21 neat
rows running from top to bottom, plus 33 ``elements'' like the
rain-god representations, cover the rest of the slab.
   ``It was all carved during one continuous period,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON>
said. ``It was a single piece of work. It is the oldest and richest
piece of writing found yet about this area of ancient <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.''
   About 7 feet tall, slightly oblong and with a gently rounded
top, the stele once stood on the right bank of the Acula, just
outside La Mojarra.
   Over the years, erosion toppled it, and it lay in the river
until a fisherman discovered it and dragged it out with the help of
villagers.
   Archaeologists retrieved the stele, but <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said he kept
the find quiet for two years so work could proceed ``without the
pressure that such a discovery creates.''
   The second piece, the ceramic figure of a priest made with the
region's thick orange clay, has a square base. It is the only one
of two artifacts from that area with a base. The other, also in the
museum, is so badly damaged it cannot be studied, <ORGANIZATION>Winfield</ORGANIZATION> said.
   In the La Mojarra figure, only the head is missing.
   That type of clay figure was very popular among the four gulf
cultures. The Aztecs called it in Xipe Totec, or the Lord of the
Flayed, and it was variously worshiped as the god of <DATE>spring</DATE>, of
fertility, of abundance and of the metalworkers.
   A peasant at La Mojarra found the shattered figure many years
ago while digging the foundations for his house and kept the pieces
in a cardboard box.
   ``We got wind of it three weeks ago, and we convinced him to let
the museum have it,'' <PERSON>Winfield</PERSON> said.
   Winfield suspects the La Mojarra area could have been a
ceremonial site.
   ``If so, there surely must be more stele and artifacts to be
found,'' he said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Mon AMs May 30</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-9698</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHGABAB3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920804
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 AUG 92 / Arts: Wisdom of the Aztecs, writ in blood - Art
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PATRICIA MORISON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE WISDOM of the Aztecs was enshrined in a painted literature. As the
conquistadors observed, the great Aztec ruler <PERSON>Moctezuma</PERSON> had libraries full
of painted books and scrolls, the work of priest-scribes who 'wrote' in
colourful images rather like strip-cartoons. Human blood was dripped on to
the pages to feed the images.
The exhibition Mexican Painted Books: Before and After the <ORGANIZATION>Conquest</ORGANIZATION>, at the
<ORGANIZATION>British Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, offers a rare opportunity to see these most vivid
survivals of a vanished civilisation. But it does not make much of a fist at
explaining the complexity of what 'reading' meant to the ancient Mexicans.
The American peoples were analphabetic. Essentially, the Aztecs and their
neighbours used pictograms and ideograms, although by the <DATE>16th century</DATE> they
were beginning to evolve phonetic symbols. Page layout, the scale of
symbols, the way they are grouped, even colour values: all influenced
meaning. Decoding a book, as the Europeans commented, was a dual process,
the eye scanning the images which prompted the reader to recite oral
history.
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s museums and libraries own a remarkable collection of ancient
Mexican manuscripts, the large part of which can now be seen in the
exhibition. The earliest codexes to appeal to English bibliophiles reached
<ORGANIZATION>Oxford</ORGANIZATION>'s Bodleian Library in the <DATE>early 17th century</DATE>
The magnificent <PERSON>Codex Mendoza</PERSON> was illustrated by native artists on the
orders of the Spanish ambassador, to show <PERSON>Emperor Charles</PERSON> V what his new
subjects were like. However, it never reached him - the galleon taking it to
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> was intercepted by a French man-of-war. Bought by <PERSON>Richard Hakluyt</PERSON>, the
English ambassador to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, it ended up in the Bodleian Library at <ORGANIZATION>Oxford
University</ORGANIZATION>. Libraries at <LOCATION>Liverpool</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Manchester</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Glasgow</LOCATION> have also loaned
books, maps and scrolls.
Perhaps inevitably, one's first impression of this show is one of gloom.
Ancient Mexican books are fragile so light levels have to be kept low: even
scholars normally have to make do with facsimiles.
Mexican books were written on animal-skins coated with gesso, or on native
paper made from the beaten inner bark of trees of the <PERSON>Moraceae</PERSON> family, such
as figs and mulberries. Paper (amatl to the Aztecs) was also used to costume
the statues of the Aztec gods and in burnt offerings.
Quite the most remarkable things in the exhibition are the elaborate
pre-Hispanic screenfold books, long accordions of painted animal-skins which
could be read on both sides. In <ORGANIZATION>Codex Egerton</ORGANIZATION>, a Mixtec genealogy, we see 26
generations of rulers, symbolised by husbands and wives seated on thrones
and passing mysterious presents to each other.
The Fejervary, Zouche and Laud skin-fold books are splendid, but baffling.
Zouche was one of the manuscripts which <PERSON>Cortes</PERSON> sent to <PERSON>Charles V.</PERSON> One side
(it will be turned during the show) relates the bloodthirsty career of the
hero Eight Deer. On the other side, there is a genealogy focused on
generations of goddesses all called Three Flints.
In the brilliantly coloured scenes in the Fejervary codex - red, turquoise,
and pale yellow within heavy black outlines - there are such ominous images
that the human sacrifices of the Aztecs come readily to mind. Gods hold
small figures by ropes around their necks. Severed heads are perched on
stools and a jaguar-headed god holds a human head between its jaws.
Figuratively speaking, these pages are spattered with the blood of
codicologists struggling to interpret them.
Post-Conquest books are, on the whole, easier to follow as native artists
painted for their foreign masters, and became progressively influenced by
the woodcuts in European books. Opportunely, there is a new book on this
topic: <PERSON>Serge Gruzinski</PERSON>'s Painting the Conquest: The Mexican Indians and the
European Renaissance (Unesco/Flammarion, 231 pages).
This would be my candidate for the most desirable of all the new books on
the Conquest. Written by a specialist, it is both a pleasure to read and
beautifully illustrated from post-Columbian codices, especially the
Florentine Codex; none of the pictures, oddly enough, are from the BM's
collection.
In the exhibition itself, the <ORGANIZATION>Kingsborough Codex</ORGANIZATION> provides a vivid picture of
the fabulous wealth of the new country and of the cruel exactions of the
conquerors. Indians are grabbed by the hair to force them to disgorge for
the annual sailing of the tribute-ships for <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, laden not only with gold,
'the divine excrement', but with furs, obsidian, shoes, pottery jars, and
brilliantly-coloured mantles and cloth.
In one scene, <PERSON>Cortes</PERSON> himself appears, ordering four reluctant tribute-payers
to be burnt alive. Remarkably, one such Aztec tribute-list now on view was
unearthed as recently as <DATE>1986</DATE> in the Ulster Museum. A charming little
treatise of the <ORGANIZATION>mid-17th Century</ORGANIZATION> shows the manufacture of cochineal, a red
dye made from crushed beetles, which remained for centuries an important
export.
As for Christianity, arguably <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s greatest export to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, it is
represented by an 18th century illustrated example of the popular <ORGANIZATION>Doctrina
Christiana</ORGANIZATION>. Here we see the radical disjunction between word and image which
initially was so foreign to the Indians. The woodcut shows <PERSON>Adam</PERSON> and Eve
expelled from the <ORGANIZATION>Garden of Eden</ORGANIZATION>. Was this a particularly poignant image to
these recent converts? The text is in <LOCATION>Nahuatl</LOCATION>, written in Roman script.
The <ORGANIZATION>BM</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Aubin Codex</ORGANIZATION>, a history of the Aztec from <DATE>1168</DATE> to <DATE>1608</DATE>, just might
jog visitors' memories. Aubin was a <DATE>19th century</DATE> French ethnographer who
also gave his name to a pre-Hispanic codex of horoscopes which in <DATE>1841</DATE>, was
presented to the <ORGANIZATION>Bibliotheque Nationale</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. And then, ten years ago
this <DATE>summer</DATE>, a Mexican journalist 'liberated' it from its wooden box. By the
time the library authorities had noticed its loss, the book was in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>National Museum of Anthropology</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Jacques Lang</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>French Minister of Culture</ORGANIZATION>,
objected, but nothing doing. The Mexicans are sticking to their precious
specimen of reverse plunder.
The exhibition runs until next <DATE>spring</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 13
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021190-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 174672 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 11, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 1; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1931 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PARTY IN VERACRUZ; 
</P>
<P>
MEXICO'S FUN-LOVING PORT ENJOYS ONE OF THE LIVELIEST CARNIVALS IN THE CARIBBEAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JUDITH BARISH and JENNIFER MNOOKIN, Barish and Mnookin are Palo Alto 
free-lance writers researching a book in Mexico. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
VERACRUZ, Mexico 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"The only madhouse with a sea view." That's how one <PERSON>Jarocho</PERSON>, as locals here are 
known, characterizes this city. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, the boisterous street life of this bustling port on the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION> 
frequently verges on the insane. <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>'s zocalo has a reputation, in fact, 
as <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s liveliest central square. 
</P>
<P>
And at this time of the year things get even livelier. The week before Lent 
brings the annual carnaval, and to understand it, a visitor first must 
understand what passes for normal in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>, especially around the white 
colonnaded zocalo. 
</P>
<P>
In sidewalk bars, white-shirted waiters pile bottles of beer precariously on 
tables already overloaded with empties. Mariachi bands serenade the crowd, 
while strolling trumpeters, harpists and marimba players in silver-trimmed 
uniforms and oversized sombreros offer song lists to prospective customers. A 
white-faced mime, or perhaps a troupe of lavishly costumed dancers, performs 
for an audience gathered around the central fountain. 
</P>
<P>
At the same time, a moving market threads its way between the cafe tables. 
Vendors offer goods of all kinds -- silk hammocks and pistachios, cigarettes 
and embroidered dresses, preposterous model ships several feet long and 
elaborately rigged, even <ORGANIZATION>Polaroid</ORGANIZATION> snapshots to commemorate your evening in 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
This is everyday <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. But the city really comes into its own during the 
weeklong carnival, when it plays host to one of the biggest fiestas between <LOCATION>New 
Orleans</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Rio de Janeiro</ORGANIZATION>. This year it is set for <DATE>Feb. 20-28</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
All work comes to a halt during the carnival, and everyone -- visitor and 
native alike -- gets down to the serious business of having fun. Each day the 
streets are filled with colorful parades that begin in mid-afternoon, when 
revelers have recovered from the festivities of the night before, and last into 
the early morning hours. 
</P>
<P>
Teen-age beauty queens wave from atop outlandish floats (a giant fish on 
wheels, for instance), uniformed bands march endlessly, and neighborhood 
musicians play odd instruments that have no names in English. 
</P>
<P>
Squalls of confetti fill the air. Salsa, rumba, tango, calypso -- all the music 
of the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> dances its way past the crowds watching from street level or 
from balconies. Many people sport elaborate costumes -- some older folks, for 
example, dress in the fashions of their youth, while others parade about 
disguised as the Aztec god Quetzalcoatl or perhaps as Batman. 
</P>
<P>
The carnival has always carried an undertone of social and political satire 
amid the festivity. This has not always set well with the authorities, but 
attempts by government to tone down the exuberance have invariably failed. 
</P>
<P>
This year, as in years past, the first of more than 40 floats will celebrate 
the ritual burning of Bad Humor, a larger-than-life, papier-mache character 
dressed in black and scowling. In previous carnivals, Bad Humor has lampooned 
corrupt politicians or police officials. This year former Panamanian dictator 
<PERSON>Manuel Noriega</PERSON> is one candidate for the role; another is President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. 
Jarochos like to poke fun through their choice and at the same time make a 
statement. 
</P>
<P>
At the close of the carnival there is the symbolic funeral of <PERSON>Juan Carnaval</PERSON>, 
not a papier-mache caricature this time but a real person who wanders about the 
city surrounded by grieving women draped in mourning attire. Juan will, of 
course, be reborn the following year. 
</P>
<P>
In between the burning of Bad Humor and the mock funeral of <PERSON>Juan Carnaval</PERSON>, the 
city throws what is virtually a nonstop party. All-night dances fill the 
plazas. Fireworks erupt almost continuously. The spirit is intoxicating, and 
those who begin as spectators usually end up as participants. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>'s light-hearted approach to life may well be a result of its turbulent 
past. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1519</DATE>, <PERSON>Hernando Cortes</PERSON> and his army of Spanish Conquistadors landed at the 
tiny island of <LOCATION>San Juan de Ulua</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> harbor. They negotiated with envoys 
of the Aztec emperor <ORGANIZATION>Montezuma</ORGANIZATION>, set up a shrine to the <PERSON>Virgin Mary</PERSON> and founded 
the first Spanish town in the <LOCATION>Americas</LOCATION>. They optimistically named it <LOCATION>Villa Rica</LOCATION> 
de la <PERSON>Vera Cruz</PERSON> -- the Rich Town of the <ORGANIZATION>True Cross</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
San <PERSON>Juan de Ulua</PERSON> and the harbor were vital in the country's trade and defense. 
In the <DATE>16th Century</DATE> the port was repeatedly attacked by pirates, and after such 
infamous marauders as <PERSON>John Hawkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Francis Drake</PERSON> successfully plundered 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>, the authorities of <LOCATION>New Spain</LOCATION> fortified the island. Even so, during a 
17th-Century raid the soldiers stationed at the fort deserted their posts 
because they hadn't been paid, and the town succumbed to Dutch buccaneers. 
</P>
<P>
Today the "island" of <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> is connected by a highway to the mainland and is 
home port to naval ships and enormous industrial tankers, signs of <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>'s 
latter-day development as the largest city and busiest port in the oil-rich 
state of <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A 15-minute bus ride from the town center, the old fort, in contrast to the 
concrete jungle of the shipyards, looks like a kindergartner's idea of a 
castle, complete with moat, drawbridge and dungeons. Its wind-swept balustrades 
look out over the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION>. Deep inside are dank, rough-hewn dungeons 
known as <ORGANIZATION>Glory</ORGANIZATION>, Purgatory and Hell. It is hard to believe that any of them were 
anything but hellish. 
</P>
<P>
Centuries after the last pirate attack the harbor continued to play a role in 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s defense. During the War of Independence, <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>'s fort was the final 
stronghold of the Spanish, who were expelled by anti-colonial forces after a 
long and bloody battle in <DATE>1825</DATE>. In the so-called Pastry War of <DATE>1838</DATE>, the French 
invaded <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>, claiming that the Mexican government owed them money for 
damaged property. The supposedly impregnable fort of <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> capitulated 
readily to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s superior firepower. But the French later were persuaded to 
withdraw. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> also invaded <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, twice using <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> as the starting 
point. During the Mexican-American War in <DATE>1847</DATE>, Gen. <PERSON>Winfield Scott</PERSON> attacked 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>, leading troops hurriedly through the town on the way to <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> 
to avoid the perennial yellow fever that plagued the coastal area. 
</P>
<P>
During the Mexican Revolution, <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON> sent the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fleet to subdue 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> and hence protect the gulf. 
</P>
<P>
To honor the town's resistance to those four foreign invasions, <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> 
officially proclaims itself "four times heroic." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Museo Cultural de la Ciudad</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>'s city museum on <ORGANIZATION>Avenida Zaragoza</ORGANIZATION> 
between <ORGANIZATION>Calle Canal</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Calle Morales</PERSON>, celebrates these feats. It also offers 
intriguing details on the town's history, such as the number of times it burned 
down during the 17th Century (four, aided by fierce northerly winds) and major 
goods that once passed through the port (such as hand grenades, silk and olive 
oil from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and chile, cocoa, tobacco and gold from the colony). 
</P>
<P>
Frequent epidemics during the 17th and 18th centuries, due to its humid 
tropical climate and mosquito-infested jungles, earned <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> the nicknames 
"Port of Hell" and "Graveyard of the Living." 
</P>
<P>
Early Spanish settlers hurried inland to more civilized regions. Left behind in 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> were sailors, merchants, <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and African slaves, and random 
wanderers just looking for a good time. 
</P>
<P>
Out of this multicultural blend of starry-eyed adventurers and sturdy vagabonds 
emerged the <PERSON>Jarocho</PERSON>, or <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> native. Jarocho culture is reckless, 
irreverent, insubordinate, and has produced some memorable political escapades. 
</P>
<P>
In the <ORGANIZATION>17th Century</ORGANIZATION>, for example, an Angolan slave named <LOCATION>Yanga</LOCATION> -- who was 
either a bandit or liberator of the oppressed, depending on whom you talk to -- 
led the first slave revolt in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>. In this century vociferous 
<LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> prostitutes ignited a tenants' rebellion that helped precipitate a 
revolution. 
</P>
<P>
Modern Jarochos are more laid-back than revolutionary; they talk slowly, dress 
casually, and excel in music and dance. Music is inescapable. In the zocalo 
alone, you hear four or five varieties at once on almost any evening throughout 
the year. 
</P>
<P>
Those visitors inspired to try swinging to the Latin beat should head for <ORGANIZATION>La 
Bamba</ORGANIZATION>, a waterfront club named after the world-famous dance that supposedly 
originated in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At a little bar called <ORGANIZATION>La Bella Epoca</ORGANIZATION>, two blocks southwest of the zocalo on a 
pedestrian alleyway, a band of funky old men play guitars, drums and percussive 
gourds in the home-grown style of "sol" -- not soul, but sun -- which began in 
the <DATE>1940s</DATE>. The bar's regulars, who look old enough to know, claim that the same 
individuals who play today were among the founders of this syncopated, eclectic 
musical style. 
</P>
<P>
Jarochos are fond of music and equally fond of good food, particularly seafood, 
which is fresh and inexpensive here. The best seafood restaurants are in the 
village of <LOCATION>Boca</LOCATION> del Rio, on the <LOCATION>Rio Jamapa</LOCATION> about five miles south of <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. 
There the restaurant most often recommended is Pardino's, which is a little 
more upscale than the rest, serving such dishes as octopus or sea bass with 
Veracruzana sauce -- a delicious mixture of onion, garlic, tomatoes, olives, 
green pepper and herbs. 
</P>
<P>
A good place in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> to try some traditional Mexican favorites, meanwhile, 
is Restaurant <LOCATION>Tlaquepaque</LOCATION>, three blocks from the zocalo. There, combinations of 
marinated meats and fresh vegetables on tortillas can be enjoyed for less than 
<MONEY>$5</MONEY> per person. 
</P>
<P>
Accommodations are no problem in <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>, either, except during the carnival. 
The city has an enormous range of hotels, all of which are reasonably priced by 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> standards. For a visit during carnival time, reservations must be made 
months ahead. A few rooms are available for this year's event, but only in the 
budget hotels. 
</P>
<P>
The most luxurious hotel on the zocalo is the <LOCATION>Hotel Veracruz</LOCATION>, where lovely 
air-conditioned rooms cost about <MONEY>$75</MONEY> a night. Those who prefer a beach-side 
setting would do well to check out the architecturally splendid Hotel Mocambo, 
a few miles south of town at <ORGANIZATION>Playa Mocambo</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Hotel Mocambo</ORGANIZATION> has an outdoor 
pool set among spacious patios. Rooms are about <MONEY>$60</MONEY> a night. More lavish and 
more expensive resorts share the same stretch of coast, where the dark-sand 
beaches are the best in the area. 
</P>
<P>
For the more budget-minded traveler, several hotels near the zocalo -- such as 
the Hotel Imperial, the Concha Dorado and the Hotel Rex -- make up in charm 
what they lack in luxury, offering reasonable accommodations for less than <MONEY>$15</MONEY> 
a night. 
</P>
<P>
How to get there: <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> is easily reached from <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. Mexicana offers 
40-minute flights from the capital twice a day. First-class ADO buses take 
about six hours, and leave hourly. There are no direct flights to <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION> from 
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Hotels, with prices per room, not per person: 
</P>
<P>
Hotel <LOCATION>Veracruz</LOCATION>. Avenida Independencia at <ORGANIZATION>Calle Lerdo</ORGANIZATION>. <MONEY>$65</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel Mocambo. Carretera Veracruz-Mocambo, in <LOCATION>Mocambo</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$60</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel Emporio. Insurgencies and Xicotencatl. <MONEY>$55</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Hostal de Cortes</ORGANIZATION>. Blvd. Avila Camacho at <LOCATION>Las Casas</LOCATION>. <MONEY>$70</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Inexpensive hotels at <MONEY>$30</MONEY> or less per room: 
</P>
<P>
Hotel Colonial. Calle Lerdo 117. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel Imperial. Calle Lerdo 153. 
</P>
<P>
Concha Dorado, <ORGANIZATION>Calle Lerdo 77</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Hotel <PERSON>Rex</PERSON>, <PERSON>Calle Morales</PERSON> 226. 
</P>
<P>
Restaurants and night life: 
</P>
<P>
La Bamba. Blvd. Avila Camacho at <ORGANIZATION>Calle Zapata</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
La Bella Epoca. Lagunillo 59. 
</P>
<P>
Pardino's. Calle Zamora, <LOCATION>Boca</LOCATION> del Rio. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Tlaquepaque</LOCATION>. Molina 363 at <LOCATION>Madero</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Gran Cafe de la Parroquia</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Avenida Independencia 1187</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For more information on travel to <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Mexico Government Tourist 
Office</ORGANIZATION>, 10100 <LOCATION>Santa Monica Blvd.</LOCATION>, Suite 224, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 90067, or call (213) 
203-9335. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Brightly decorated floats bring color to the streets by day PHOTO 
SELECTS / After Image; Photo, COLOR, while fireworks light up Veracruz's main 
square at night during the annual carnival. AL MOLDVAY / After Image; Photo, 
Harbor at Veracruz has played a dramatic role in the Caribbean's colorful 
history for more than 400 years. ; Map, Veracruz, MEXICO, JOHN SNYDER / Los 
Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA093090-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 285283 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 30, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Page 3; Calendar Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2324 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
3000 YEARS OF MEXICAN ART; 
</P>
<P>
LANDMARK EXHIBIT OF WORKS RANGING FROM PRE-COLUMBIAN TO MID-20TH CENTURY OPENS 
NEXT WEEK AT NEW YORK'S METROPOLITAN MUSEUM AND COMES TO L.A. IN 1991 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN PHILLIP SANTOS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
As <PERSON>Hernan Cortes</PERSON>' small army neared the Aztecan capital of <LOCATION>Tenochtitlan</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1519</DATE>, they arrived at <LOCATION>Iztapalapa</LOCATION>, a hilltop village that gave the Spaniards 
their first panoramic view of the sprawling New World metropolis in the valley 
of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. Cortes and his men numbered only 400. The city was the seat of the 
expansive Aztec empire, and had a population of a half million. 
</P>
<P>
As one chronicler in <PERSON>Cortes</PERSON>' band described it, "We saw so many cities and 
villages built in the water and other great towns on dry land . . . we were 
amazed and said that it was like the enchantments they tell of in the legend of 
Amadis, on account of the great towers and cues and buildings rising from the 
water . . . And some of our soldiers asked whether the things that we saw were 
not a dream . . . all was cemented and very splendid with many kinds of stone 
monuments with pictures on them, which gave much to think about." 
</P>
<P>
It is in such moments of confounded awe -- on the eve of great destruction -- 
that Mexican art, as we know it, had its ambiguous birth. For finally, the 
conquest of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> was as much a triumph of the eye as it was a victory of the 
sword and gun. 
</P>
<P>
For many years to come, the conquistadores' way of seeing the world would be 
the only true one, and they quickly set about remaking much of the fantastic, 
alien world they encountered in their own image, as a "<LOCATION>New Spain</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
The chronicler, writing 30 years after the events, concludes his account of the 
dazzling first sight of Tenochtitlan by noting that, "Of all these wonders that 
I then beheld today all is overthrown and lost, nothing left standing." 
</P>
<P>
Now, 471 years later, at <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s Metropolitan Museum of Art, 
preparations are nearly complete for a new Mexican conquest. Opening <DATE>Oct. 10</DATE> is 
"<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>: Splendors of Thirty Centuries," the most significant exhibition of art 
from <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> to appear in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> in 50 years. 
</P>
<P>
From <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>, the nearly 400 objects in the show will later travel 
exclusively to the two Chicano capitals of <LOCATION>Mexamerica</LOCATION>, appearing first at the 
<LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> Museum of Art (<DATE>April 6-Aug</DATE>. 4, <DATE>1991</DATE>), and then at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
County Museum of Art (<DATE>Sept. 29-Dec</DATE>. 29, <DATE>1991</DATE>). For <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, it will be the 
most important public presentation of Mexican art since the <DATE>1978</DATE> "Treasures of 
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>" show, sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Armand Hammer Foundation</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>County Museum</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>1940</DATE>, the Museum of Modern Art in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> mounted "Twenty Centuries of 
Mexican Art," the first major exhibition of its kind to be shown in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> (see accompanying story). And in <DATE>1970</DATE>, the Metropolitan Museum hosted 
"Before Cortes," an historic show of the pre-Columbian sculpture of 
<LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
But the Met show is perhaps the most comprehensive collection of ancient, 
colonial and modern Mexican artistry ever assembled in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. In 
scale, it is the largest show the museum has presented since "The Vatican 
Collection: The Papacy and Art" in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Currently, designers, lighting engineers, and workmen at the Metropolitan 
Museum are finishing the specially constructed, maze-like exhibition gallery as 
some of the pieces are being installed. 
</P>
<P>
According to the show's four co-curators, all members of the museum staff, 
featured works include Mayan and Aztecan sculptures, early post-conquest 
manuscripts, popular religious and devotional objects, costumes, graphics, and 
paintings, ranging in date of origin from 1000 BC to AD <DATE>1950</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Amassing such an enormous grouping of objects is a logistics triumph that has 
been three years in the making, with pieces drawn from 41 public and 24 private 
collections in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The principal financial supporter of the multi-million dollar event is a newly 
formed, Los Angeles-based foundation, "Friends of the Arts of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>," which in 
turn is the brainchild of <PERSON>Emilio Azcarraga</PERSON>, the chairman of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Televisa</ORGANIZATION> 
network. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Azcarraga</PERSON> approached <PERSON>Philippe de Montebello</PERSON>, director of the 
Metropolitan Museum, with the idea for a comprehensive show of Mexican art. 
</P>
<P>
Although "<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>: Splendors of Thirty Centuries" is its most high-profile 
undertaking to date, the organization -- which has a mandate to promote 
appreciation of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s artistic and cultural heritage in this country -- has 
already sponsored a touring exhibition of work by young Mexican artists, as 
well as efforts to preserve the Rock Art of <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> and the <PERSON>David 
Alfaro Siquieros</PERSON> "America Tropical" mural on Olvera Street. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John McDonald</PERSON>, exhibition coordinator of the Metropolitan show, and curator for 
the 19th-Century section, modestly sums up the collection that has been 
gathered for the <DATE>October</DATE> opening in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> as "more than a roundup of 
the usual suspects." 
</P>
<P>
"We wanted to do a comprehensive exhibition. With 50 years since the last major 
show, it was long enough for people to forget, for generations to come and go 
and not have a chance to see this work. It will be an eye-opener for a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
audience." 
</P>
<P>
As befits an imperial exhibition of this sort, the scope of cultural periods 
and styles to be represented in the show is impressive, offering the North 
American public a rare opportunity to see under one roof a spectrum of Mexican 
artistic expression that would be difficult to match in weeks of museum touring 
in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Included in the pre-Hispanic section, which will comprise one-third of the 
exhibition, will be one of the colossal stone heads of the Olmec people, who 
came before the more familiar Mayan and Aztecan civilizations. The giant heads, 
discovered in <LOCATION>La Venta</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Lorenzo</LOCATION>, Tabasco on the <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION> beginning in 
the <DATE>1920s</DATE>, depict faces that appear distinctly Negroid and have caused many to 
speculate on the possibility of ancient contact between the peoples of 
<LOCATION>Mesoamerica</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
From the ancient Mayan city of <LOCATION>Palenque</LOCATION>, there will be an exquisitely 
naturalistic sculptured stucco head with an unforgettable penetrating, yet 
tranquil gaze. <PERSON>Julie Jones</PERSON>, curator for this section of the exhibition, 
explains that recent breakthroughs in cracking the Mayan hieroglyphic language 
allow us to now identify this figure as the king <PERSON>Pacal II</PERSON>, who ruled <LOCATION>Palenque</LOCATION> 
during during its 7th-Century heyday. 
</P>
<P>
According to <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>, the pre-Columbian portion of the show will not just be "the 
son of 'Before Cortes,' " -- the Metropolitan's <DATE>1970</DATE> show -- but will reflect 
the expansion of knowledge related to the ancient cultures of <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> that has 
taken place over the <DATE>last 50 years</DATE>, with such "meaningful digging" as the <DATE>1978</DATE> 
excavation of the <ORGANIZATION>Templo Mayor</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
