<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891113-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-13-89 0212EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panama     11-13 0393</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama,390</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Foreign Ministers Meeting in Washington</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Lead prospects uncertain</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> prepares
to call for a decisive hemispheric stand against <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s Gen.
<PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> as foreign ministers from the <ORGANIZATION>Organization
of American States</ORGANIZATION> gather here today.
   A highlight of the meeting is expected to be the admission of
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> as the 32nd <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> member, effective <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE>. There also is some
sentiment in support of readmitting <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> expelled the government of president <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON> in
<DATE>1962</DATE> on grounds that the country's Marxist-Leninist philosophy is
incompatible with <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> principles.
   <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers usually convene only once a year, but the
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> crisis has prompted four special <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> sessions since <DATE>May</DATE>. An
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> commission appointed in <DATE>May</DATE> was unable to fulfill its mandate
of arranging a democratic transfer of power in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> was expected to deliver a tough speech
condemning the Panamanian government, but it was not clear whether
he would make specific proposals.
   The inaugural session was scheduled for <TIME>this morning</TIME>, and
<PERSON>Baker</PERSON>'s remarks were to be delivered in <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>.
   The <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> crisis arose six months ago when Panamanian
authorities threw out the returns from national elections amid
widespread allegations of fraud. A <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> crony, <PERSON>Francisco
Rodriguez</PERSON>, was sworn in <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE> as the unelected president.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has been the strongest proponent of decisive
action against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, but other <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> countries maintain that the
group should stay out of what is an essentially internal Panamanian
matter.
   Also on the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> agenda is <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>'s scheduled <DATE>Feb. 25</DATE>
presidential election. The meeting is expected to produce numerous
calls for a free and fair election process.
   <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> has been sharply critical of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> over the years,
looking on the organization as an instrument of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> foreign
policy. But seven leading Latin American democracies called last
month for <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmission to the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> has said it's
ready to accept.
   <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> has far more diplomatic support in the hemisphere than at
any time since it was expelled from the <DATE>OAS 27 years ago</DATE>.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has lobbied hard against <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmission,
citing alleged Cuban support for subversion in Central American and
reported human rights abuses.
   <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmission would require a two-thirds vote of member
nations in attendance.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890519-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-19-89 0935EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0411 05-19 0746</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0411,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>WASHINGTON TODAY: Noriega's Latest Feat: Unifying the Hemisphere</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: Subs 10th graf, Secretary of, to restore dropped matter</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> needed a spirit-nourishing issue.
<PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> may have provided it.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> has been unable to accomplish much of anything this
decade. One of the organization's principal aims is to keep the
peace, but it has been on the periphery of the continuing bloodshed
in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> and was irrelevant at the time of the
British-Argentine war in <DATE>1982</DATE> over the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> and the
U.S.-led invasion of <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> a year later.
   At one point several years ago, an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> official said the
organization was so feckless that it was unable to agree on a
resolution commemorating the upcoming 500th anniversary of the
discovery of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   But for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> has been heaven-sent. The organization,
which seemed paralyzed by factionalism, was able to close ranks
against the Panamanian leader <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   With only <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> dissenting, <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers
agreed to blame <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> for ``the grave events and abuses'' that
have occurred since the <DATE>May 7</DATE> national elections in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   International organizations normally are loathe to single out
leaders of member states for criticism but the scenes of opposition
candidates and ordinary citizens being bludgeoned by government
agents turned stomachs from one end of the hemisphere to the other.
It was time for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to drop its genteel guard.
   The foreign ministers approved a resolution which not only held
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> personally responsible for the bloodshed, but also
appointed a mediating team to take steps aimed at ensuring a
``transfer of power'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   That is quite a departure for an organization which normally has
as its highest principle the right of member states to be spared
outside intervention.
   Noriega, of course, will put his own spin on the resolution. He
is expected to tell the mediators that he is a soldier for
democracy who wanted nothing more than to see a ``transfer of
power'' resulting from the <DATE>May 7</DATE> elections. On that basis,
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s foreign minister was able to go along with the resolution
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> has shown interest in
reviving the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>. He is planning to appoint one of the <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION>'s most accomplished Latin American hands, <PERSON>Luigi Einaudi</PERSON>,
as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador to the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>.
   But <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> didn't take office soon enough to head off the layoffs
earlier this year of 300 <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> employees, about <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the
total. That step was largely brought on by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arrearages
amounting to more than <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>. More layoffs are expected next
month.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> heyday was the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. It was the Cold War era and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
administrations were able to forge an anti-communist consensus with
rightist dictators and hawkish democratic governments which
dominated the hemisphere at the time.
   Cuban President <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON> was everybody's villain. The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
expelled him from its ranks a few years after his revolution and,
25 <DATE>summers ago</DATE>, the organization slapped a mandatory economic and
diplomatic embargo against <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1965</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> invaded the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>, a
seeming violation of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter. But <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> nations, albeit
reluctantly, gave their blessing to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> action rather than
siding with the target of the invasion.
   With the demise of rightist dictatorships in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and
their replacement by elected governments, the anti-communist
consensus in the hemisphere has unraveled.
   Never has <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> been more democratic or less willing to
go along with <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s policies. Support for President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> policies in the hemisphere was virtually invisible.
   The special session on <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> recalled the time 10 years when
the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> decided to move against <ORGANIZATION>Nicaraguan President Anastasio
Somoza</ORGANIZATION>. A month after the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers called for <ORGANIZATION>Somoza</ORGANIZATION>'s
resignation, he fled to <LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION>.
   Now the question is whether the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> stand against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> will
contribute to a similar result.
   One of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mediators who will sit down with <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> next
week is Ecuadoran Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>, the principal
architect of the agreement that led to the withdrawal of Soviet
troops from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> starting a year ago.
   If <PERSON>Cordovez</PERSON> was able to get more than 100,000 Russian troops
out, surely he can do the same with one Panamanian. Or can he?
</TEXT>
<HEAD>___</HEAD>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> needed a spirit-nourishing issue.
<PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> may have provided it.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> has been unable to accomplish much of anything this
decade. One of the organization's principal aims is to keep the
peace, but it has been on the periphery of the continuing bloodshed
in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> and was irrelevant at the time of the
British-Argentine war in <DATE>1982</DATE> over the <LOCATION>Falkland Islands</LOCATION> and the
U.S.-led invasion of <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> a year later.
   At one point several years ago, an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> official said the
organization was so feckless that it was unable to agree on a
resolution commemorating the upcoming 500th anniversary of the
discovery of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   But for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> has been heaven-sent. The organization,
which seemed paralyzed by factionalism, was able to close ranks
against the Panamanian leader <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   With only <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> dissenting, <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers
agreed to blame <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> for ``the grave events and abuses'' that
have occurred since the <DATE>May 7</DATE> national elections in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   International organizations normally are loathe to single out
leaders of member states for criticism but the scenes of opposition
candidates and ordinary citizens being bludgeoned by government
agents turned stomachs from one end of the hemisphere to the other.
It was time for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to drop its genteel guard.
   The foreign ministers approved a resolution which not only held
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> personally responsible for the bloodshed, but also
appointed a mediating team to take steps aimed at ensuring a
``transfer of power'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   That is quite a departure for an organization which normally has
as its highest principle the right of member states to be spared
outside intervention.
   Noriega, of course, will put his own spin on the resolution. He
is expected to tell the mediators that he is a soldier for
democracy who wanted nothing more than to see a ``transfer of
power'' resulting from the <DATE>May 7</DATE> elections. On that basis,
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s foreign minister was able to go along with the resolution
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> has shown interest in
reviving the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>. He is planning to appoint one of the <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION>'s most accomplished Latin American hands, <PERSON>Luigi Einaudi</PERSON>,
as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador to the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>.
   But <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> didn't take office soon enough to head off the layoffs
earlier this year of 300 <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> employees, about <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of the
total. That step was largely brought on by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> arrearages
amounting to more than <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>. More layoffs are expected next
month.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> heyday was the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. It was the Cold War era and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
administrations were able to forge an anti-communist consensus with
rightist dictators and hawkish democratic governments which
dominated the hemisphere at the time.
   Cuban President <PERSON>Fidel Castro</PERSON> was everybody's villain. The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
expelled him from its ranks a few years after his revolution and,
25 <DATE>summers ago</DATE>, the organization slapped a mandatory economic and
diplomatic embargo against <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1965</DATE>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> invaded the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>, a
seeming violation of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter. But <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> nations, albeit
reluctantly, gave their blessing to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> action rather than
siding with the target of the invasion.
   With the demise of rightist dictatorships in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and
their replacement by elected governments, the anti-communist
consensus in the hemisphere has unraveled.
   Never has <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> been more democratic or less willing to
go along with <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s policies. Support for President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> policies in the hemisphere was virtually invisible.
   The special session on <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> recalled the time 10 years when
the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> decided to move against <ORGANIZATION>Nicaraguan President Anastasio
Somoza</ORGANIZATION>. A month after the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers called for <ORGANIZATION>Somoza</ORGANIZATION>'s
resignation, he fled to <LOCATION>Paraguay</LOCATION>.
   Now the question is whether the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> stand against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> will
contribute to a similar result.
   One of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mediators who will sit down with <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> next
week is Ecuadoran Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>, the principal
architect of the agreement that led to the withdrawal of Soviet
troops from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION> starting a year ago.
   If <PERSON>Cordovez</PERSON> was able to get more than 100,000 Russian troops
out, surely he can do the same with one Panamanian. Or can he?
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890517-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-89 1325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-OAS-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0575 05-17 0837</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0575,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>White House Predicts Condemnation Of Panama At OAS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads and edits top 11 grafs with White House comments on meeting,
pics up 8th graf pvs, This year...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Organization of <ORGANIZATION>American States</ORGANIZATION> foreign
ministers assembled here today for a historic debate on the <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
crisis, with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> prepared to ask for a resolution
demanding that Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> step aside.
House</ORGANIZATION> was ``confident there will be general hemispheric
condemnation of <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s actions'' at the session.
   ``We hope and expect the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> will take a strong stand on <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
and against the <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> regime,'' <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said, adding the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> would let other countries ``take the lead'' in proposing
specific motions. He said <ORGANIZATION>Secretary of State James A Baker III</ORGANIZATION>
would ``speak up forcefully regarding our views.''
   In <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, opponents to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> called for a one-day general
strike today to protest the voided elections and the beating by the
general's supporters of political opposition leaders. But many
factories, stores and street stands were open, although commuter
traffic was lighter than normal.
   As the delegates prepared for their opening session, the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> was emerging as perhaps the most militant of the 31 nations
represented here for the first special <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers
meeting in seven years.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration was ready to
ask the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to demand that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> step down following an election
10 days ago that the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> claimed was rigged initially
and then voided when the fraud could not be concealed.
   But the preliminary signs for the administration were not
encouraging because two of the countries thought to be most
sympathetic to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> view, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>, were proposing
resolutions that fell far short of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> objectives.
   Neither mentions Noriega by name nor recommends that he step
down.
   At his daily <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> briefing for reporters, <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said
the administration was not seeking a country where <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> could
find exile.
   ``There have been a number of countries that have said they
would accept Gen. <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>,'' he added. ``At least some of them are
countries that don't have extradition treaties with the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> session evoked memories of one 10 years ago when <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
foreign ministers, including then-U.S. Secretary of State <PERSON>Cyrus
Vance</PERSON>, demanded the resignation of Nicaraguan President <PERSON>Anastasio
Somoza</PERSON>. He fled less than a month later.
   This year, the delegates seem somewhat reluctant to interfere in
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s internal affairs to the degree that they did a decade ago
in <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>.
   The Venezuelan draft calls for the ``immediate recognition'' of
the <DATE>May 7</DATE> electoral returns in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> while asserting that the
solution to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s crisis rests exclusively with the Panamanian
people.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official said the Venezuelan proposal is not plausible
because no accurate count of the election returns is possible since
most of the ballots have been destroyed.
   The Peruvian draft calls on the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> secretary general to
facilitate a dialogue between the Panamanian government and
opposition, leading to the election of new authorities.
   Alternatively, other mechanisms would be agreed to that would
ensure ``the transfer of power'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   While <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration officials consider both drafts to be
tepid, the decision to raise the events surrounding the Panamanian
election to the highest hemispheric tribunal is seen as a plus for
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> policy.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has been attempting to topple <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> for more
than a year, a policy that Panamanian delegates at today's meeting
are expected to seize on.
   Based on official statements in recent days, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> was
preparing to accuse the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at today's meeting of
systematic violation of Panamanian sovereignty in violation of the
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter.
   As examples, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> was intent on highlighting <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economic
sanctions imposed 14 months ago and the reported <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
government donation to opposition forces in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> during the
election campaign.
   <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> requested the meeting after international observers
contended that the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election was marked by massive fraud
committed by the pro-Noriega coalition.
   Subsequently, the results were tossed out after a bloody
confrontation between armed supporters of <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> and opposition
demonstrators, including presidential candidate <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON>
and a vice presidential running mate, <ORGANIZATION>Guillermo Ford</ORGANIZATION>.
   Scenes of the bloodshed were widely disseminated outside <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
and had a major impact on hemispheric public opinion.
   The dilemma facing the delegates stems partly from conflicting
provisions in the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter. One paragraph calls representative
democracy an ``indispensible condition'' for stability in the
hemisphere while another stresses that no state shall be subject to
outside intervention ``for any reason whatsoever.''
   <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> deputy spokesman <PERSON>Richard Boucher</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
the administration looks forward to working with governments
throughout the hemisphere to develop ``action in support of
democracy'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Indicating that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> plans a circumspect role at
the meeting, <PERSON>Boucher</PERSON> said, ``This is a meeting called by Latins,
led by Latins, and we expect the result to reflect Latin interest
in democracy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890518-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-89 1512EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-OAS-Panama 4thLd-Writethru   05-18 0827</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 4th Ld-Writethru,a0548,820</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Mediators Will Try To Solve Panama's Crisis</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 8th graf pvs to say mission leaving Monday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In a diplomatic compromise accepted by both
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION>
called for a transfer of power through democratic means in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
while leaving the details to a team of mediators.
   The plan was unanimously authorized late <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
foreign ministers in a resolution that condemns the ``grave events
and abuses'' by Panamanian leader Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> but
which also stops short of criticizing his government.
   The resolution, approved in an unusually efficient manner by the
29 delegates present, was sufficiently ambiguous to win the
approval of the two biggest antagonists at the session: Secretary
of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> and Panamanian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Jorge
Ritter</PERSON>.
   Baker pronounced himself ``very pleased'' with the outcome.
<PERSON>Ritter</PERSON> said, ``I feel fully satisfied.''
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, responding to a question shouted by a reporter
as he headed from the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> to a helicopter <TIME>this morning</TIME>,
called the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> action a ``good resolution.'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> left for a
four-day trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>.
   The president's spokesman, <PERSON>Marlin Fitzwater</PERSON>, later told
journalists on <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> One that the resolution ``constitutes a
condemnation of Noriega by name for his abuses of the electoral
process.'' He added: ``We're gratified that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> countries
shared the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>' position.''
   The key provision empowers the foreign ministers of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> to try to promote a ``national accord,
within democratic mechanisms and in the shortest period possible,
to ensure the transfer of power with full respect for the sovereign
will of Panamanian people.''
   OAS Secretary General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON> was asked to assist the
delegation that will travel to the Central American nation. The
organization issued a statement this afternoon saying the envoys
will depart <DATE>Monday</DATE>. They were asked to report back by <DATE>June 5</DATE>, and
the resolution said unspecified ``subsequent measures'' may be
needed after <DATE>June 5</DATE>.
<LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> on ``CBS This Morning,'' called the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> meeting ``the
rest of the hemisphere because we have all agreed on a declaration
defending democracy for <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and we have all condemned the
abuses commited in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>....''
   <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> is expected to tell the envoys that he never has opposed
the fundamental purpose of the resolution _ a transfer of power
through democratic means. He is likely to claim the <DATE>May 7</DATE>
presidential elections, which he later ordered voided, were
designed to achieve that very goal.
   The most divisive aspect of the proceeding centered on whether a
direct reference to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> was appropriate.
   The initial draft of the resolution, prepared by a 10-nation
delegation, omitted any reference to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> but the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
and other countries strongly opposed to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> reversed that
omission during a closed session of more than two hours, paving the
way for final approval.
   The new language warned that the ``grave events and abuses'' by
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> ``could unleash an escalation of violence'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   The decision to include the reference to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> was approved by
a 20-2 vote with seven delegates abstaining. The Panamanian and
Nicaraguan delegates opposed the change in wording while the
abstainers were from <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION> and five <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> countries.
   The Nicaraguan delegate failed in two efforts to win approval of
amendments assailing President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s decision last week to send
2,000 more <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s stated purpose was to
protect American lives.
   Ritter expressed satisfaction with the final resolution, saying
it fell far short of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> demand for a condemnation of the
Panamanian government. He promised that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation would be
welcomed by Panamanian authorities.
   Noriega's critics have maintained he first tried to rig the
outcome of the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election in support of his candidate, <PERSON>Carlos
Duque</PERSON>, then ordered the returns voided when he could no longer
conceal the fraud. Government agents severely beat at least two
opposition candidates, a point noted in the resolution.
   <PERSON>Sen. Connie Mack</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> Republican who went to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> as
an observer for the election, attended the meeting at <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
headquarters and termed the final resolution ``very positive'' but
said he would have preferred an explicit demand that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> step
down.
   The resolution marks a return to a key diplomatic assignment for
Ecuadoran Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>, a member of the
mediating team. Cordovez was the principal negotiator for the
agreement that led to the withdrawal of Soviet forces from
<LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>.
   In contrast to other <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers meetings, this one
was short on rhetoric and stressed substantive give-and-take.
   <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON> had predicted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> the session could
drag on until <DATE>Friday</DATE> but the resolution was in its final form and
approved by consensus at <TIME>11:50 p.m.</TIME>, barely six hours after the
formal proceeding had got under way.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890622-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-89 1100EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0455 06-22 0557</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0455,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Officials Say OAS Mediation in Panama a Failure</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: New lead to include Baker comment; inserts grafs 8-9, Testifying
before</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials have virtually given up hope
that <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> mediators will be able to
succeed in arranging a democratic transfer of power in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, but
Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> remained publicly optimistic
today.
   One official dismissed the mediation as a ``corpse'' and said
alternative ideas must be pursued for pressuring Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON> to step down.
   Three <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mediators, aided by Secretary General <PERSON>Joao Baena
Soares</PERSON>, have made two visits to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> over the past month to
attempt to seek a solution to the country's political crisis.
   On their last visit, the mediators left some ideas with the two
most powerful political blocs in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and with the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION>
on how to promote a dialogue.
   <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON> is ``neither optimistic nor pessimistic'' about the
prospects for success but believes the progress achieved to date has
been satisfactory, according to an aide.
   But a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official criticized the effort, saying ``the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> has
fallen on its face on this.''
   The official, asking not to be identified, said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> diplomats
from around the hemisphere have been trying to enlist governments
from <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> to support the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> position.
   Testifying before the <ORGANIZATION>House Foreign Affairs Committee</ORGANIZATION> this
morning, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> he remains ``very hopeful'' that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
mediators will be successful.
   He reaffirmed the longstanding <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> view that there can be no
normalization of relations with <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> so long as <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> remains in
power.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has been attempting to force <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> out of
office since he was indicted by two <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> grand juries on drug
smuggling charges in <DATE>February 1988</DATE>.
   But few, if any, governments in the hemisphere are as
unswervingly opposed to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. Many are
reluctant to intervene in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s internal affairs, while others
see the issue as a U.S.-Panamanian problem that should be dealt with
as such, the officials said.
   The official <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> position is that the mediation
effort should not be judged until <DATE>July 19</DATE>, the deadline for the
mediators to submit a report on their activities to <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign
ministers.
   The administration believes the only acceptable solution is for
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> to agree to step down as <ORGANIZATION>Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> commander before the
deadline. Privately, officials say there is no sign that will occur.
   The crisis arose last month when <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s electoral tribunal,
dominated by <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s allies, tossed out the returns from the <DATE>May 7</DATE>
presidential elections. Independent observers said the opposition
slate had won by a landslide.
   There was indignation throughout the hemisphere when, three days
after the election, opposition candidates were beaten by government
security agents. A week later, the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mediating team was set up.
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers blamed <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> for the ``grave events and
abuses'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   But much of the anti-Noriega sentiment has dissipated over the
past six weeks, generating pessimism here that the mediators will be
able to fulfill their mandate.
   The officials said the administration is weighing a series of
options for bringing additional pressure to bear on <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>,
including the seizure of his overseas assets, believed to number in
the hundreds of <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890523-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-89 0421EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0435 05-23 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0435,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mediators Head for Panama, Seeking Democracy</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: LEADS with 5 grafs to reflect Trinidad minister's arrival; picks
up 5th graf pvs, bgng: ``OAS foreign...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three Latin American foreign ministers,
fulfilling a mandate from the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION>,
headed to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> today to promote a democratic transfer of power.
   Panamanian authorities have promised to cooperate with the
mediators but <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration officials said initial comments
by Panamanian authorities have not been encouraging.
   A pro-government party in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> it wants the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to
focus on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ``aggression'' against <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   The foreign minister of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sahadeo Basdeo</PERSON>,
arrived <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and said the delegation is ``not here to
interfere with the internal affairs of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>. We came as friends
and neighbors.''
   The other two, from <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, were to fly
separately to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and planned to join <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General <PERSON>Joao
Baena Soares</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers last week blamed Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON> for ``the grave events and abuses'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> following the
failed election process in that country earlier this month.
   After a vote count that international observers said was marred
by massive fraud, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s electoral tribunal threw out the
results. The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration has maintained that the opposition
slate, based on an independent count, won the election by a 3-1
margin.
   Opposition candidates subsequently were beaten and bloodied by
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> supporters during a post-election demonstration.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> claims that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> has disrupted
constitutional processes on two occasions in 15 months. The first
was the ouster of then-President <PERSON>Eric Arturo Delvalle</PERSON> in <DATE>February
1988</DATE> and the second was what the administration says was the theft
and subsequent annulment of the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election.
   In addition to <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON>, the delegation is made up of the
foreign minister of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>; of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sahadeo
Basdeo</PERSON>; and of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mario Palencia</PERSON>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> resolution calls for the mediators to ``secure a
national accord, within democratic mechanisms and in the shortest
time possible, to ensure the transfer of power with full respect
for the sovereign will of the Panamanian people.''
   The tentative plan is for the ministers to report back to their
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> colleagues on <DATE>June 6</DATE>. If Panamanian authorities show no
interest in complying with the spirit of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> resolution, the
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration is expected to support an escalation of <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
pressure against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official, insisting on anonymity, said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> has raised the possibility of resolving the crisis by
inviting opposition presidential candidate <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON> to join
a three-member junta. The other members would be Noriega allies.
   ``Noriega is proposing one of you and two of us,'' said the
official, suggesting that any such proposal would not be acceptable
to <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> ministers.
   The opposition's three top candidates, seeking recognition of
their victory claim in the election, shook hands and passed out
leaflets in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> welcoming the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> will not solve all our problems, but it will create
the environment. They have come to investigate,'' said <PERSON>Endara</PERSON>.
   A pro-government party <DATE>Monday</DATE> criticized the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> for condemning
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> and said its delegation could not mediate among Panamanians.
   ``We call on the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to adopt a virile attitude toward
aggression against our people by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' said a
statement issued by the <ORGANIZATION>Revolutionary Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, the largest
pro-government group.
   Noriega and his allies have consistently maintained that
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s problems stem from a systematic <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> effort to subvert the
country's democratic process, citing accounts of a <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>CIA</ORGANIZATION>
contribution to the opposition coalition.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33751 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat113__a94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-113-A </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Cuba </F>
<H3> <TI>   Discussions on Cuban Readmittance to OAS Noted </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Discussions on Cuban Readmittance to OAS Noted </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0806155494 Havana PRENSA LATINA in Spanish 1855 GMT 7 Jun 
94 -- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> PA0806155494 </F>
<F P=104>  Havana PRENSA LATINA </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Rio de Janeiro</LOCATION>, 7 Jun (PL) -- The 24th <ORGANIZATION>OAS General 
Assembly</ORGANIZATION> continued today receiving new requests urging the 
readmittance of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> into the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>, from which it was removed in 
<DATE>1962</DATE> due to its political disagreement with the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
  During the second day of talks in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Para State</ORGANIZATION>, 
Brazilian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Celso Amorim</PERSON> reintroduced the topic 
of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmittance before the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> meeting and reiterated the 
need for "reviewing the Cuban situation within the hemispheric 
community." 
  During the inauguration of the 24th <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Assembly on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, 
outgoing <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON> as well as 
Brazilian President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON> recommended that <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s 
readmittance be considered, although this topic is not part of 
the agenda to be discussed at the meeting which will conclude 
<DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
  In his speech to the foreign ministers and representatives 
of 
the 34 OAS-member countries, Amorim recalled that his country 
"maintains friendly relations and has significant cultural links 
with <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>." 
  "Despite everything, we do not believe that economic and 
political isolation is the best way to contribute to a 
transition that is already in the making in that country," 
Amorim added. 
  <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON>, who will conclude almost a decade as head of 
the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> on 20 <DATE>June</DATE>, made similar statements yesterday. 
  "As everyone knows, I have been inquiring whether this is 
the 
right moment for <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> members to review the measure adopted over 
30 years ago when the Cuban Government was suspended ... the 
90's are not the 60's," he stated. 
  According to diplomatic sources, this was the first time the 
outgoing <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> head has dealt with this topic officially before a 
regular <ORGANIZATION>OAS General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>. 
  "<LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s removal is not in keeping with the political 
revolution the world has faced in the past years," he added. 
  Meanwhile, President <PERSON>Franco</PERSON> supports that <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> be readmitted 
and the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> reassess its position regarding <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. "<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> 
favors a harmonious dialogue among all nations, without 
exceptions," he added. 
  In statements to the media in <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, Bolivian Foreign 
Minister <PERSON>Antonio Aranibar</PERSON> expressed his support for <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s 
readmittance into the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> while his Costa Rican counterpart 
<PERSON>Fernando Naranjo</PERSON> proposed that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> establish channels of 
communication with the <ORGANIZATION>Cuban Government</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33667 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat111bb_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-111 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTER-AMERICAN AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   OAS Assembly Meeting Continues 8 Jun in Brazil </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    OAS Assembly Meeting Continues 8 Jun in Brazil </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Cuban Readmission Not `Formally Proposed' </H4>

<F P=102> PY0906022294 Madrid EFE in Spanish 2117 GMT 8 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> PY0906022294 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, 8 Jun (EFE) -- OAS Assistant Secretary 
General <PERSON>Christopher Thomas</PERSON> stated here today that so far none of 
the 34 <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> member countries have formally proposed <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s 
readmission into the organization. 
  Thomas, who represents <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> 
Secretary General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON> had proposed that <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s 
return to the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> be discussed. He noted, however, that so far 
no country has made a formal request to this effect. 
  In accordance with <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> regulations, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> said, the 
readmission of a member country into the organization must first 
be formally proposed by one member country, and then consulted 
with the other members attending the <ORGANIZATION>General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Thomas is actively participating in the 24th <ORGANIZATION>OAS General 
Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, which opened on 6 <DATE>June</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Amazon</LOCATION> city of <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION>, in 
northern <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. He said: "As <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON> said, circumstances 
today are conducive to reexamining <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmission to the 
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>, but so far I am unaware of any country having made such a 
proposal." 
  As assistant secretary general, <PERSON>Thomas</PERSON> will replace <PERSON>Baena 
Soares</PERSON> -- whose term expires this month, after having served 10 
years in office -- during the two-month period preceding the 
installation of the new secretary general-elect, Colombian 
President <PERSON>Cesar Gaviria</PERSON>. 
  Although some Latin American foreign ministers have timidly 
defended <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON>'s proposal that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> member countries 
discuss the possibility of readmitting <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, only <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> has 
formally stated its position on the issue; that is, its 
opposition to the proposal. 
  During a news conference <ORGANIZATION>Argentine OAS</ORGANIZATION> Ambassador <PERSON>Hernan 
Patino Meyer</PERSON> said flatly: "The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> consists of democratic 
states, and as soon as <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> takes steps toward its 
democratization it will be possible to readmit it into the 
organization." 
  Asked why <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> had, then, continued as <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> 
member states under the military regimes, <PERSON>Patino Meyer</PERSON> said that 
at that time the <DATE>1992</DATE> clause that provides for the separation 
from the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> of nondemocratic states had not yet been approved. 
"Had I been the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> secretary general at that time, I would 
have expelled <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> from the organization," 
<PERSON>Patino Mayer</PERSON> said. 
  In his opening speech at the 24th <ORGANIZATION>OAS General Assembly</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Baena 
Soares</PERSON> said: "I have been asking for some time whether it is 
the right moment for the member countries to reexamine the 
decision they made more than 30 years ago to suspend the <ORGANIZATION>Cuban 
Government</ORGANIZATION> from <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> activities. The nineties are different from 
the sixties." 
  <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON>' proposal was not immediately discussed by the 
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers because they were more interested in 
discussing the Haitian crisis. 
  Although President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON> did not discuss the Cuban 
issue in his speech at the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Assembly, he stated shortly 
before returning to <LOCATION>Brasilia</LOCATION> that "the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> must look at the 
Cuban position." 
  <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> was separated from the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1962</DATE>, three years after 
the victory of the Cuban Revolution led by President <PERSON>Fidel 
Castro</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0049EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0696 06-13 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,0509</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Mission Meets With Opposition, Government Officials</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Solis Palma meeting Noriega
after talks with OAS mission. Pickup 4th pvs, ``Joao Baena ...''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALINA GUERRERO</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Acting President <PERSON>Manuel Solis Palma</PERSON>
met with military strongman Gen. <PERSON>Antonio Manuel Noriega</PERSON> <DATE>Monday</DATE> after
he conferred with an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mission trying to mediate <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s election
deadlock.
   On its second trip to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION>
mission met separately <DATE>Monday</DATE> with <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON> and opposition party
members.
   Immediatedly after his one-hour meeting with <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> officials <PERSON>Solis
Palma</PERSON> met for another hour with <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>. The general was seen
entering the governmental palace in civilian clothing with <PERSON>Carlos
Duque</PERSON>, the government's candidate in the <DATE>May</DATE> election that was
annulled.
that Panamanian officials and the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> representatives were trying to
find ``an acceptable formula'' for a dialogue between the government
and opposition.
   ``This mechanism even though it obviously doesn't exist yet .. .
this is what we are searching for,'' <PERSON>Ritter</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> did not speak with reporters.
   One <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegate, Ecuadorean Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>,
said earlier he is confident the government and opposition have the
political will to settle their differences.
   He said it is up to the Panamanians to resolve the dispute.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> only can ``promote a dialogue and perhaps give ideas
based on our national experience based on similar situation,'' he
said.
   <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> secretary-general, and the foreign
ministers of <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> are the other members
of the mission.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s political crisis began with the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election, which
international observers said the opposition won by at least a 2-1
margin. The government controlled by <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> annulled the election
and opposition candidates were attacked and beaten by his supporters.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> then agreed to send the mission to negotiate a national
dialogue on the transfer of power on <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, as required by the
constitution.
   On their first visit to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> at the end of <DATE>May</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
diplomats could not persuade the opposition and government to hold
direct talks. Opposition leaders said they would talk only with
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, and he refused.
   Cordovez, a former <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> official who negotiated the Soviet
withdrawal from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>, was optimistic <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   ``I think there is a political will in the government and the
opposition that has to be translated into specific steps,'' he said.
``It seems to me that it is most urgent to establish mechanisms that
allow Panamanians to talk and negotiate.''
   Noriega and government officials blame <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s problems on the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, which they say wants to renege on <DATE>1977</DATE> treaties that
turn over the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> at the end of the century.
   Noriega, commander of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION>, was indicted on
drug trafficking charges last year in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. He denies
the charges and has refused <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> demands he resign.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890517-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-89 2321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-OAS-Panama 5thLd-Writethru a0805 05-17 0735</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-OAS-Panama, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0805,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>OAS Ministers Approve Sending Mediators to Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: New lead with approval of resolution, additional details; editing
changes throughout; picks up into next-to-last graf pvs, As the meeting
...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
American States</ORGANIZATION> approved a resolution <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> to send
mediators to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> in an effort to end that country's political
crisis through a ``transfer of power.''
   The resolution also held Panamanian leader <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON> responsible for the ``grave events and abuses'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
in recent days.
   The mediators were ordered to report back by <DATE>June 5</DATE> on their
mission in order to determine whether any subsequent measures are
appropriate to resolve <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s crisis.
   The resolution asked the foreign ministers of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, assisted by <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON>,
to undertake the mission in order to secure a ``national accord''
in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> within ``democratic mechanisms.''
   The accord is to be reached in the ``shortest period possible to
ensure the transfer of power with full respect for the sovereign
will of the Panamanian people,'' the resolution said.
   The most divisive aspect of the proceeding centered on whether a
direct reference to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> was appropriate.
   The initial draft resolution, prepared by a 10-nation
delegation, omitted all references to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, but the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> and other countries strongly opposed to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> reversed
that omission during a closed session of more than two hours,
paving the way for final approval.
   The new language warned that the ``grave events and abuses'' by
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> ``could unleash an escalation of violence'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   The decision to include the reference to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> was approved by
a 20-2 vote with seven delegates abstaining. The Panamanian and
Nicaraguan delegates opposed the change in wording.
opposing the any change in the initial resolution, said he was
pleased with the overall result. Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker
III</PERSON> also said he was pleased.
   The delegates reassembled in public session after their private
meeting late <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to give the resolution final approval, but
that was considered a mere formality.
   The resolution was seen as a compromise between <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> factions
which had been advocating markedly different approaches to the
Panamanian crisis. One faction had advocated a hands-off policy
toward <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, citing <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> principles of non-intervention, and a
hard-line faction which had demanded the removal of <ORGANIZATION>Noriega</ORGANIZATION> from
power. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was in the latter category.
   Critics of the resolution argued that the call for a transfer of
power is largely meaningless because <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> himself backed the
country's recent election process.
   But backers of the draft pointed out that the proposal calls for
an end to the crisis through democratic procedures.
   Noriega's candidate in the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election, <PERSON>Carlos Duque</PERSON>, claimed
victory, but the results subsequently were voided by the <ORGANIZATION>Panamanian
Electoral Tribunal</ORGANIZATION> after widespread allegations of vote-rigging.
There also were brutal attacks by government agents on several of
the candidates in the election, a point noted in the draft
resolution.
   Noriega sees himself as no more than the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> commander
who serves at the pleasure of a president who is the product of a
constitutional process. The first test of the resolution is whether
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> demonstrates a willingness to cooperate with the mediators.
   The proposal was presented by the delegations of <LOCATION>Bolivia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Dominican
Republic</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
   At the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>, 57 members of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> encouraged <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>, in a
letter, to press hard for <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> action.
   ``We urge the members of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to pass a resolution calling
for the immediate replacement of the <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> regime and
installation of a democratic government in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> which reflects
the free will of the people of that country.'' the letter said.
   Ritter argued in closed session that <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s problems are the
product of a systematic campaign of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> interventionism, including
a series of economic sanctions and what he says was a <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY>
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government contribution to the opposition campaign.
   As the meeting started, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was aligned with the
Central American countries and some <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands in calling
for a strong stand against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   At the other end of the spectrum, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> were
believed to be encouraging a more cautious approach, one that takes
into account <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> principles requiring respect for the sovereignty
of member nations.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890524-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama     05-24 0559</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama,0577</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panama Presents Its Case to the OAS</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD HERZFELDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
election said he told of massive fraud by both pro- and
anti-government parties today during a meeting with a delegation
   The Panamanian government presented its case against the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> during a meeting <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation, sent in
the wake of the nullified election.
   ``The Panamanian government took the opportunity to present a
series of documents and actions that contributed to invalidate the
elections of <DATE>1989</DATE>,'' presidential spokesman <PERSON>Jose Hernandez</PERSON> said.
   An <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> source who refused to be named said the meeting was
``difficult,'' but he did not go into detail.
   Sources said the delegation was attempting to arrange a meeting
with Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION> chief and de
facto ruler of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation said they had come to facilitate a
search for solutions to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s political troubles.
   Opposition presidential candidate <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON> and his two
vice presidential candidates were scheduled to meet with the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
delegation. They contend they won the <DATE>May 7</DATE> vote by about 3-to-1
over <LOCATION>Noriega</LOCATION>'s hand-picked candidate.
   The government, however, nullified the vote, and blamed
opposition fraud and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> interference in the election.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> group met <TIME>this morning</TIME> with <LOCATION>Hildebrando Nicosia</LOCATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Authentic Panamanian Party</ORGANIZATION>'s presidential candidate. He received
only a small percentage of the vote.
   <LOCATION>Nicosia</LOCATION> said he described ``massive fraud committed by both
sides.'' He added, ``People are tired of instransigence on both
sides. The solution is for negotiations without prior conditions.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> approved a resolution last week criticizing <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> and
calling for ``a transfer of power in the shortest possible time.''
It sent a delegation consisting of the foreign ministers of
<LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> as well as <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
Secretary-General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON>.
   Acting president <PERSON>Manuel Solis Palma</PERSON>'s government said it hoped
the mission would ``establish the truth of the crisis as a conflict
between <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' and it cited <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> sanctions
as proof of malice.
   The government has proclaimed it will accept no interference in
internal Panamanian affairs and said some aspects of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
resolution violate the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> ``expounded its points of view about the events that
began 24 months ago,'' said <PERSON>Hernandez</PERSON> in a statement after <PERSON>Solis
Palma</PERSON> and members of his cabinet met with the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation.
   The first street demonstrations against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s rule began in
<DATE>June of 1987</DATE>. Since then, <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> has been indicted on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> drug
charges, charges he says are part of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> plot to renege on its
commitment to give up the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION> at the end of <DATE>1999</DATE>.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation made no comment on the meeting
except for Ecuadorean Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>, who said
only, ``We have formed no impression.''
   At the airport after arriving <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Cordovez</PERSON> had said the
idea was to assist Panamanians in finding their own solutions and
to convey Latin American concern about the situation.
   Meanwhile, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops staged an amphibious landing exercise and
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said armed convoys of troops were being dispatched
over Panamanian roads with instructions not to stop.
   Several times in the past Panamanian police have stopped <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
convoys, which they have no right to do, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890523-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-89 2117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0712 05-23 0636</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0712,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Official Says OAS Meeting With Government Was `Amicable'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 15 grafs to UPDATE with quotes after meeting. Pick
up 13th pvs, `Solis Palma's...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELOY O. AGUILAR</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s foreign minister said top
officials held a ``positive, amicable'' meeting <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with a
Latin American mission to reconcile the military-controlled
government and the opposition.
   The delegation from the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> arrived
earlier to mixed reactions and took a conciliatory tone.
   ``We are going to try to facilitate dialogue among Panamanians.
This is a situation that only Panamanians can resolve,'' said
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, one of four <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
delegates.
   They are investigating charges that <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s de facto ruler,
Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON>, nullified national elections to
prevent an opposition victory.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, defense officials said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
sending armed military convoys on trips across <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> to ``flex our
muscles'' and draw a line against Panamanian harassment.
   Two convoys of 10 or so vehicles carrying armed soldiers have
crossed without incident in either directions under escort by
Panamanian soldiers, as provided in the canal treaties, the
   <PERSON>Rafael Vargas Santos</PERSON>, ambassador to <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, said in
<LOCATION>Port-au-Prince</LOCATION> the government would destroy the <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> Canal in the
event of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> invasion.
   ``We will not be taken by surprise because we are already
prepared,'' he said on <ORGANIZATION>Radio Haiti Inter</ORGANIZATION>. ``The first thing we will
do is blow up the canal.''
   Cordovez, <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary-General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON> and foreign
ministers <PERSON>Sahadeo Basdeo</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Mario Palencia</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> met with acting president <PERSON>Manuel Solis Palma</PERSON> and several
Cabinet members for two hours but issued no statement.
what was discussed but said the meeting was ``positive, amicable.
... I think it was a very cordial, wide-ranging and positive
climate.''
   The group will meet with other ``political figures'' over the
next 10 days, <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON> said. No plans for a meeting with
<PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> were mentioned.
   Opposition leaders, who want their <DATE>May 7</DATE> presidential election
victory recognized, had welcomed the delegation and said the
Pan-American organization ``has understood the urgent need to act.''
   But the government proclaimed earlier it would not accept any
interference in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s internal affairs. Government-controlled
media accused the organization of prejudging the case.
   ``They'll come, they won't see _ and they'll leave,'' said a
headline in Matutino newspaper.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> last week denounced <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> and called for a swift
transfer of power.
   <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON>'s government issued a proclamation <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>
saying parts of the organization's resolution violate its charter,
including the ``ill-willed'' mention of <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   The government proclamation, however, welcomed the mission and
said it hoped it would ``establish the truth of the crisis as a
conflict between <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.'' It cited <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
sanctions against <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> as proof of malice.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> newspapers accused the organization of being led by the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Cordovez</PERSON> described its resolution as ``a Latin
American effort based on principles that we all respect _ the
principle of non-intervention.''
   In his arrival statement, <PERSON>Cordovez</PERSON> said Latin Americans are
concerned about <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and the mission is a ``gesture of good will,
a gesture of friendship and solidarity that should not be
misinterpreted.''
   The opposition has called for a demonstration at noon <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
in defiance of a government ban on demonstrations that lasts until
<DATE>June 5</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION> mission is to file
its report.
   Noriega, who commands <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION>, was indicted on
denies the charges and says they are part of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> plot to renege
on its commitment to hand over the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION> at the end of <DATE>1999</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890527-0035 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-27-89 0359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Panama     05-27 0435</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama,0448</SECOND>
<HEAD>Noriega, Opposition Still at Odds After OAS Visit</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD HERZFELDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government and opposition
appeared no closer to resolving the presidential election crisis
after a visit by representatives of the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American
States</ORGANIZATION>.
   The opposition said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s de facto ruler, must be a party to any negotiations.
Noriega, however, insisted the opposition must negotiate with
pro-government parties.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> mission, scheduled to leave today, had hoped to help
resolve an impasse that arose when the government nullified the <DATE>May
opposition won by a 3-1 margin.
   ``At this time what we hoped for has not been achieved, an
agreement among Panamanians to resolve the crisis that bedevils
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>,'' opposition candidate <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> after
meeting with the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation.
   A member of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> delegation, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, said the opposition and government ``understand each
other better, but it will require an enormous effort from the
Panamanian people because they have to develop the formulas to
solve the problem.''
   The other members of the mission were the foreign ministers of
<LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General <PERSON>Joao
Baena Soares</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>. The delegation must file a report the day
before the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> foreign ministers meet on <DATE>June 6</DATE> to consider the
organization's next step.
   Endara said he would not accept the presidency on <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, even
if <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> allowed it but remained commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Panamanian
Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I would just be a puppet,'' <PERSON>Endara</PERSON> said.
   The opposition has said repeatedly that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Defense
Forces</ORGANIZATION> hold real power in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and therefore must be a part of
any talks.
   Noriega, at a news conference after his own meeting with the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
delegation, said: ``The key to the problem lies with the contending
political parties ... If the opposition remains intransigent, the
<ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION> are not going to slip on a banana peel'' and be
drawn into the dispute.
   ``The two sides have to start talking,'' he said. ``They both
claim they won.''
   He said questions about the possibility of his own resignation
were ``stupid.''
   <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, who was indicted in <DATE>February 1988</DATE> on drug charges in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, said he told the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> that <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s problems were
caused by ``interfering hands.''
   He cited the drug charges, which he denies, and economic
sanctions as proof that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was plotting to keep the
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> Canal despite treaties that call for the canal to be turned
over at the end of <DATE>1999</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891113-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-13-89 1943EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-OAS-Panama     11-13 0730</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-OAS-Panama,1st ld-writethru,a0657,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>EDs: Tops with Baker, Panamanian comments, other changes; picks up
11th graf pvs, now 20th graf: ``A number,''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Secretary of State <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON> accused
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> of supporting ``violence, destruction
and war'' in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> and he said these activities are the
biggest obstacle to genuine superpower accommodation.
   In a speech to foreign ministers of the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American
States</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> also said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> will never accommodate
itself to the ``outlaw regime'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and he called for the
international community to isolate that country.
   Panamanian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Leonardo Kam</PERSON> responded immediately,
calling <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> policies toward his country ``fascist.''
   Baker's remarks on the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> reinforced the notion that
<LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> may be the most divisive issue when President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
and Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON> have their <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION>
summit in three weeks.
   ``The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> bears a special responsibility because its
arms and money, moving through <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>, continue to
support violence, destruction and war,'' <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said.
   He said shipments of Soviet weapons to leftist rebels in <LOCATION>El
Salvador</LOCATION> are incompatible with the ``new thinking'' in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> _ the
term <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> uses to describe his break with past policy.
   ``Soviet behavior toward <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> remains the
biggest obstacle to a full across-the-board improvement with the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.''
   <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would be pleased to have normal
relations with a democratic <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>. But, he said, ``there is a
dictator, and his name is (Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio</PERSON>) <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.'' He added
that after the release <DATE>Monday</DATE> of an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> report critical of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>,
no ``self respecting democracy'' should make an accommodation with
that country.
   After <PERSON>Baker</PERSON>'s remarks, <PERSON>Kam</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> diplomat was resorting
``to a very old formula _ a fascist one _ of repeating time and
again false words so that they could ring true.'' He said <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
was a victim of ``relentless <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> aggression.''
   Until <PERSON>Baker</PERSON> spoke, the mood at the meeting was upbeat, with
speaker after speaker hailing the entry of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> as the 32nd
member of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>. About 25 foreign ministers were on hand for the
opening day deliberations.
   Costa Rica introduced a resolution calling on all <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> member
states to withraw their ambassadors from <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> until a process is
said in its report on <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> that the Panamanian government
routinely violates the rights of its citizens to, among other
things, life, humane treatment, personal liberty and judicial
guarantees.
   The commission called on <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> to take ``immediate steps to
control the excessive violence that the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> police and
paramilitary groups employ against the civilian population.''
   These forces, the report said, must end the ``mistreatment,
torture and other cruel and inhuman and degrading treatment that
the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION> inflict upon individuals deprived of their
freedom.''
   An <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> effort to try to arrange a democratic transfer of power
in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> was suspended in late <DATE>August</DATE> after it became apparent
that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> was not interested in surrendering power.
   A separate <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> report on <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> demands the release of all
political prisoners and says that there are no guarantees the <DATE>Feb.
25</DATE> national elections there will be free and fair because of
built-in advantages enjoyed by the incumbent Sandinistas.
   The renewed fighting in <LOCATION>El Salvador</LOCATION> prompted Nicaraguan Foreign
Minister <PERSON>Miguel D'Escoto</PERSON> to introduce a resolution calling on the
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to make an urgent appeal to the government of <ORGANIZATION>El Salvador</ORGANIZATION> ``to
cease immediately the bombing of the civilian population.''
   Shortly before the afternoon session was convened, a delegation
of Sandinista and <ORGANIZATION>Nicaraguan Contra</ORGANIZATION> officials met at an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> annex
several blocks away. The talks are a continuation of discussions
begun <DATE>last Thursday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>.
   The objective is to reach agreement restoring the cease fire and
to lay the groundwork for the demobilization of the Contras.
readmission of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> after a 27-year absence.
   <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> has said it is ready to accept an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> invitation but
diplomats said that issue was not likely to come up at this year's
meeting.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has lobbied hard against <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>'s readmission,
citing alleged Cuban support for subversion in <LOCATION>Central America</LOCATION> and
reported human rights abuses.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890721-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-21-89 1106EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-OAS-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0434 07-21 0482</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0434,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Asks Noriega to Transfer Power in Six Weeks</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDs: Recasts lead and inserts new 4th graf, The declaration, to clarify
terms of declaration</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Organization of <ORGANIZATION>American States</ORGANIZATION> foreign
ministers are asking Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> to arrange a
transfer of power over the next six weeks as part of a plan to
restore democratic rule in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   A declaration approved by the ministers <DATE>Thursday</DATE> was a
masterpiece of diplomatic evenhandedness, earning the support of
both the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> delegate and <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s representative.
   Specifically, the declaration said the proposed transfer of
power on <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE> and subsequent free elections are to be carried
out through ``democratic means and in conformity with existing
internal Panamanian procedures.''
   The declaration lacks an enforcement mechanism and does not
specifically ask for <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> to step down. Advocates of a stronger
statement expressed concern that he might try to rig the process in
a way that enables him to maintain control from his power base as
commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Panamanian Defense Force</ORGANIZATION>.
   Privately, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials expressed dismay with the outcome but
remarks that the declaration has enough teeth to warrant <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
backing.
   Addressing delegates from the 31-member body assembled at the
ornate <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> headquarters, <PERSON>Eagleburger</PERSON> said the transfer of power
envisioned in the declaration ``must reflect the will of the
Panamanian people.''
   In addition, the new democratic elections called for must not be
held in ``one, two or three years but as soon as possible,''
consistent with the wording of the declaration, he said.
   ``General <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> must go,'' <PERSON>Eagleburger</PERSON> added.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has called for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to exert maximum
pressure on <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, who has been accused by two <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> grand
juries of drug smuggling activities.
   The ministers also extendeduntil <DATE>Aug. 23</DATE> the mandate of an <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
mediating team which has been trying to facilitate an end to the
two-month old political crisis in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
government's full cooperation with the mediating team, which is
comprised of the foreign ministers of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guatemala</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and which has received the cooperation of <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary
General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON>.
   According to the Panamanian constitution, a new president is to
be installed <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>. The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration had hoped the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
would push for the installation as president of the opposition
candidate in the <DATE>May 7</DATE> national elections.
   The results of that balloting were thrown out by <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s
electoral tribunal amid widespread claims that <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON>,
the candidate opposed to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, had won in a landslide.
   By calling for another round of elections after <DATE>Sept. 1</DATE>, the
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>, in effect, accepted as permanent the annulment of the <DATE>May 7</DATE>
balloting.
   The reference to the need to abide by ``existing internal
Panamanian procedures'' also was seen as a concession to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890523-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-89 1312EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Panama     05-23 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Panama,0251</SECOND>
<HEAD>OAS Delegation Arrives</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
American States</ORGANIZATION> arrived here today to investigate charges that Gen.
<PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> scrapped the results of national elections
to prevent an opposition victory.
   ``We will organize our work and seek meetings with government
and political figures so we can return to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to present a
report filling the mandate of the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>,'' <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> Secretary-General <PERSON>Joao
Baena Soares</PERSON> said in a statement after arriving at the airport.
   The organization last week condemned <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, the nation's
military chief and de factor ruler, and called for a transfer of
power.
   Foreign Minister <PERSON>Diego Cordovez</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> said the mission
would ``tell all Panamanian sectors that there is concern in <LOCATION>Latin
America</LOCATION> about <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s crisis.''
   The delegation is being welcomed by <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s opposition, which
wants the organization to recognize its victory in <DATE>May 7</DATE>
won the elections by a 3-1 margin. Noriega nullified the vote after
it was apparent his candidates were losing.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s government has warned the mission should not be turned
into ``an international vote tabulation board or an international
court of appeal.''
   Noriega holds real power in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> because he commands the
<ORGANIZATION>Panamanian Defense Forces</ORGANIZATION>. He has been indicted on drug charges in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, charges he says are part of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> plot to
renege on its commitment to give up the <LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION> at the end of
<DATE>1999</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881115-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-15-88 0506EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-OAS     11-15 0585</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-OAS,0607</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shultz Says Group Not Sufficiently Pressuring Nicaragua On Reform</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICHARD HERZFELDER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN SALVADOR, El Salvador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American States</ORGANIZATION>, Secretary of State <PERSON>George P.
Shultz</PERSON> criticized its members for not doing more to pressure
<LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> into democratic reforms.
   ``This organization has not always been out front on issues
concerning democracy,'' he said in the meetings' keynote speech.
   <PERSON>Shultz</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>'s leftist Sandinista government had
promised the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> it would maintain a ``pluralistic'' political
system, but that member states had not held the Nicaraguans to their
commitment.
   <PERSON>Victor Hugo Tinoco</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>'s vice-minister of foreign affairs,
disagreed.
   ``The general movement is towards discussion, towards
negotiation,'' he said during an informal press conference. ``The
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> has started to take a political role in ending the Central
American crisis.''
   Tinoco noted that Secretary-General <PERSON>Joao Baena Soares</PERSON> has agreed
to a direct role in monitoring a now-stalled peace agreement between
the leftist Sandinista government and U.S.-backed Contra rebels.
   The meeting took place under strict security despite a unilateral
truce declared for the duration of the session by leftist Salvadoran
guerrillas opposed to the government of President <PERSON>Jose Napoleon
Duarte</PERSON>.
   Duarte, in welcoming the delegates, condemned the guerrillas and
called for support for the overall Central American peace process,
   Other topics discussed at the <ORGANIZATION>General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> included Latin
American debt, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> concern with drug trafficking and the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>'s
own financial straits.
   The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> is nearly bankrupt because most member nations are behind
on their dues. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, which provides the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>
headquarters in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, owes <MONEY>$41 million</MONEY>.
   ``The member governments must decide what they want to do with
the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> at this critical juncture in the life of the Americas,''
said <PERSON>Baena Soares</PERSON>, lamenting the organization's ``critical economic
condition.''
   The Brazilian was re-elected by acclamation to a second five-year
term as <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> secretary-general.
   An <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> commission has recommended that the group cut its <MONEY>$66
million</MONEY> annual budget by <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> and fire a fourth of about 1,000
staff members.
   Delegates to the <ORGANIZATION>General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> will decide whether to accept
that recommendation this week.
   <PERSON>Shultz</PERSON>, who will be replaced by <PERSON>James A. Baker</PERSON> when
President-elect <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> takes office in <DATE>January</DATE>, said he would
press for full funding by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> failure to pay its full contribution has been
interpreted by some Latin nations as an effort to reassert its
dominance over the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION>'s original sin is that it was founded to further <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
aims in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Tinoco</PERSON> said. ``But other countries are
trying to contribute a little more.''
   <PERSON>Bosco Matamoros</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> spokesman who came to <LOCATION>San Salvador</LOCATION> to
press the rebels' case, questioned <PERSON>Tinoco</PERSON>'s motives.
   ``They want negotiations on a biblical time scale _ to last a
thousand years,'' he told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>. ``They only want to
stretch things out to reinforce their grip.''
   At a news conference after his speech, <PERSON>Shultz</PERSON> pointed to the
exclusion of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> from a meeting of Latin American nations last
month as an example of the kind of diplomatic sanction that could be
taken by <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> nations.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Shultz</PERSON> noted pointedly, was excluded from the ``Group of
Eight'' because it was no longer a democracy while under Gen. <PERSON>Manuel
Antonio Noriega</PERSON>'s thumb.
   In another speech to the assembly, <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>'s foreign minister
<PERSON>Felipe Errazuriz</PERSON> reiterated the intention of Gen. <PERSON>Augusto Pinochet</PERSON>'s
government to hold elections in <DATE>1989</DATE>. However, he said, terrorism
was the major menace to the democratic process in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890516-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-89 2221EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Panama 3rdLd-Writethru a0742 05-16 1019</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Panama, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0742,980</SECOND>
<HEAD>US to Press for Tough OAS Resolution on Panama</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Panama Evacuations, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>EDS: RECASTS lede to show US dissatisfaction with Venezuela, Peru
plans; ADDS ^By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said they were displeased with
the wording of preliminary draft resolutions intended for
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s emergency session of the <ORGANIZATION>Organization of American
States</ORGANIZATION> to discuss the <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> crisis.
of their main objections to the draft resolutions by <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> was that neither mentioned Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> by name.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is expected to push hard for a resolution
demanding that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s military leader and de facto ruler
of the country, step down.
   The Venezuelan draft calls for the ``immediate recognition'' of
the <DATE>May 7</DATE> electoral returns in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> while asserting that the
solution to <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s crisis rests exclusively with the Panamanian
people.
   A <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> official said the Venezuelan proposal is not plausible
because no accurate count of the election returns is possible since
most of the ballots have been destroyed.
   The Peruvian draft calls on the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> secretary general to
facilitate a dialogue between the Panamanian government and
opposition, leading to the election of new authorities.
   Alternatively, other mechanisms would be agreed to that would
ensure ``the transfer of power'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Among the 31 <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> members, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is aligned with a
cluster of democratic countries in Central and <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> while
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> are proponents of a less activist policy, citing
<ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> provisions guaranteeing respect for the principle of
non-intervention.
   The meeting is being convened at the request of Venezuelan
President <PERSON>Carlos Andres Perez</PERSON>, who reportedly favors a resolution
calling on Noriega to step down.
   The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration position favors the recognition of the
opposition candidate in the <DATE>May 7</DATE> election, <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON>, as
the legitimate authority in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>. Four days after the election,
the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> began referring to <PERSON>Endara</PERSON> as <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s
``president-elect.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> voted 413-0 on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to approve a resolution
condemning <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s ``reprehensible actions'' in thwarting the
election, and calling on him and the Panamanian military to
recognize <PERSON>Endara</PERSON> as president.
   ``Despite these deplorable efforts to thwart the will of the
Panamanian people, all credible Panamanian and international
observers have recognized <PERSON>Guillermo Endara</PERSON> as the indisputable
winner of the election,'' stated the non-binding resolution which
was sent to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   It also endorsed the ``careful and prudent policy steps'' taken
by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> ``as an appropriate and measured response to the
crisis in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.''
   ``We have a better indication of positive results than we have
come to expect in the past,'' <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> press secretary <PERSON>Marlin
Fitzwater</PERSON> said of the reaction by Latin countries to the
administration's call for solidarity against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   There is hope that the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> will take a strong position, he said.
``On the other hand, we don't have any specific indication of what
the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> might do,'' he said.
   He said he was unaware of an effort reported from diplomatic
sources in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is engaged in a petition
effort to get other countries to recall their ambassadors from
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> as the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has done.
   As to whether the administration wants <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> to accept an
offer of refuge in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Fitzwater</PERSON> said, the president's
feeling is that, ``he ought to take any offer he could get.''
   <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> deputy spokesman <PERSON>Richard Boucher</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
the administration looks forward to working with governments
throughout the hemisphere to develop ``action in support of
democracy'' in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Indicating that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> plans a circumspect role at
the meeting, <PERSON>Boucher</PERSON> said, ``This is a meeting called by Latins,
led by Latins, and we expect the result to reflect Latin interests
in democracy.''
   Meanwhile, Panamanian diplomats are expected to try to convince
their hemispheric colleagues that <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s problems are the product
of a systematic campaign of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> interventionism, including a
series of economic sanctions and a widely reported <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
government contribution to the opposition campaign.
   The dilemma facing the delegates stems partly from conflicting
provisions in the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> charter. One paragraph calls representative
democracy an ``indispensible condition'' for stability in the
hemisphere while another stresses that no state shall be subject to
outside intervention ``for any reason whatsoever.''
   With a large majority of hemispheric countries headed by elected
governments, some delegates are expected to push hard for an
anti-Noriega resolution because to do otherwise might encourage
restive military officers to displace civilian presidents.
   But others are likely to be reluctant to push <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> too hard,
particularly concerning allegations that he attempted to rig the
elections. These delegates may be wary about setting a precedent in
the event that the election processes in their own countries face
similar criticism.
optimistic on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that a consensus existed for an anti-Noriega
resolution.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> is on the ropes,'' one official said, noting that the
organization is plagued by declining prestige and onrous financial
problems. About 300 <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> employees were laid off earlier this year.
   The official said it would make no sense for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> to ``create
a cloud of dust'' by convening a foreign ministers meeting and then
do nothing.
   A large turnout of foreign ministers will be on hand for the
special session, the first of its kind for the <ORGANIZATION>OAS</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1982</DATE> when
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> went to war over their conflicting claims to
the Falkland-Malvinas Islands.
   Among the handful of foreign ministers not expected to attend
are the ones from <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>. They will be represented by
subordinates.
   <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Roman Popadiuk</PERSON> said that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> called
presidential <PERSON>Endara</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> ``to express sympathy over the
