<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910510-0045
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910510-0045.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   California May Sharply Curtail Business
   Of First Capital Holdings' Unit Today
   ----
   By David B. Hilder and Frederick Rose
</HL>
<DATE>
05/10/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
</RE>
<LP>
   California insurance regulators are expected as early as
today to sharply curtail the operations of one of troubled
First Capital Holdings Corp.'s major life insurance units,
according to people familiar with the company.
   It is believed that the action will likely be followed by
a conservatorship, in which California regulators formally
take control of the company and all its operations.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   First Capital won't resist <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Insurance
Commissioner <PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>'s plan to issue cease and desist
orders barring the unit, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>,
from honoring policyholders' redemption requests and from
selling new policies, those familiar with the situation said.
   The expected orders would halt an apparently increasing
demand for policy redemptions that strip the company of its
cash and can compel the sale of assets at fire-sale prices.
The bar on new business is widely seen as a formality, since
few new policies are being sold these days.
   The regulatory orders would be the second major action
taken by <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators in the past month against a
junk bond-laden insurance company. On <DATE>April 11</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr.
Garamendi</PERSON>'s department seized <ORGANIZATION>First Executive Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Executive Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit, in the largest insurance
failure ever.
   Industry observers noted that cease and desist orders can
be more quickly carried out than a conservatorship. A
conservatorship is expected to follow because it is harder to
restore policyholder rights of redemption without the
complete regulatory control that conservatorship gives
insurance regulators.
   The exact timing of <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s expected move couldn't
be determined. One person familiar with discussions among <PERSON>Mr.
Garamendi</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> and its advisers said his order is
expected today or <DATE>Monday</DATE>. Another such person predicted the
order will come "very soon" but declined to be more specific.
   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> said the company "is
exploring all our options to best protect policyholders'
investments" but wouldn't elaborate. A spokesman for <PERSON>Mr.
Garamendi</PERSON> declined to comment, as did a spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>American Express Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> had invested assets of <MONEY>$4.1 billion</MONEY> at
<DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' other major life insurance
unit, Virginia-based <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, had
invested assets of <MONEY>$4.0 billion</MONEY>. It isn't known whether
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> regulators will take any action, although industry
observers say it is likely to follow <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s actions
closely.
   The immediate peril to the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> units has been
demands by policyholders to redeem their investments. It is
believed that redemption demand -- already strong in the
weeks since Executive Life was taken over by regulators --
soared this week, after it was disclosed that <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
regulators were negotiating with <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> for a
rescue of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s spokesman declined to disclose the amount
of redemption requests. However, he said "the numbers have
been increasing and any increase is a matter of concern." He
added that requests have been "manageable."
   Still, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s woes go deeper than the recent jump
in redemption demand. As with Executive Life, the <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION> units suffered from plunging junk-bond investments.
About <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s invested assets are in such
high-yield securities.
   The market value of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> bonds at year's
end was <MONEY>$692 million</MONEY> less than the <MONEY>$5.73 billion</MONEY> at which the
securities were carried on the company's books. First
Capital's spokesman said the market value of those bonds has
improved by <MONEY>$187 million</MONEY> since the <DATE>end of the year</DATE>.
   Several officials involved in the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> rescue
talks say <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s portfolio isn't as troubled as
First Executive's, largely because <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> tended to
buy bonds with better claims on issuing companies' assets and
avoided bonds that don't pay cash interest.
   <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION>, which is representing <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and evaluated First Executive's portfolio for
regulators, has said it can sell <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s junk bonds for no net loss or gain, according to
people familiar with the talks. A <ORGANIZATION>Salomon</ORGANIZATION> official declined
to comment.
   The main effort to bolster <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s financial
foundation came with <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s request that <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> shore up the company, but those talks haven't
produced any results yet.
   Besides its own <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> shares, <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> is concerned about the insurer's fate largely because
stockbrokers at its <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> securities
unit sold their customers thousands of insurance policies and
annuities issued by <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> has tried to raise cash by selling
a portion of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>'s insurance business that
amounts to about <MONEY>$1.3 billion</MONEY> of assets. Advisers to <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION> have said that some action by regulators might make
it easier to sell part or all of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> by
stopping the recent rush of policyholder withdrawals.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910506-0002
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910506-0002.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   American Express, California in Talks
   To Prop Up Struggling First Capital
   ----
   By David B. Hilder
</HL>
<DATE>
05/06/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
</RE>
<LP>
   American Express Co. is talking with the California
insurance commissioner about ways to prop up First Capital
Holdings Corp., a struggling insurance company in which
American Express owns a 28% stake, according to people
familiar with the talks.
   The talks between officials of American Express and John
Garamendi, the California insurance commissioner, have been
going on for about two weeks, and began with a meeting that
included Mr. Garamendi, American Express Chairman James D.
Robinson III and Howard L. Clark Jr., chairman of Shearson
Lehman Brothers Inc., American Express's securities unit. Mr.
Garamendi and Mr. Clark are scheduled to meet again today in
New York, people familiar with the discussion said.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s interest in having <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>
bolster <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> could indicate that the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
insurance company's problems are more serious than <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION> has indicated. In <DATE>March</DATE>, defaults on junk bonds in
its investment portfolio forced <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> to revise its
<DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> financial results to a loss of <MONEY>$24.7 million</MONEY>,
or <MONEY>53 cents</MONEY> a share. The company had previously reported net
income of <MONEY>$10.2 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>22 cents</MONEY> a share, in the period.
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> said it would try to sell some of its insurance
business and its long-time chairman resigned.
   For <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>, the problems of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> come on
the heels of his seizure last month of the largest insurance
unit of <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles-based First Executive Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which also
was hurt by its big holdings of junk bonds. <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> is
trying to find a rescuer for the <ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION> unit,
<ORGANIZATION>Executive Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, while <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
regulators are seeking a buyer for another unit, <ORGANIZATION>Executive
Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> has invested a substantial part of its <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> of assets into high-risk, high-yield junk bonds. In
the past, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> has reported that about <PERCENT>23.5%</PERCENT> of its
assets are in securities rated below investment grade. But
new reporting rules for insurance companies are likely to
increase that amount.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> is concerned about the fate of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION> largely because <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> stockbrokers sold their
customers thousands of insurance policies and annuities
issued by <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s main unit, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life
Insurance Co</ORGANIZATION>. If <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> becomes insolvent,
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> would most likely face some lawsuits and many angry
customers.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> has proposed buying from <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>
the insurance business that involves <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers, or
taking over the management of that business and guaranteeing
that <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers won't incur losses on their policies,
people familiar with the talks said. It isn't clear whether
those proposals will satisfy <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s concerns.
   Officials at <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>California Insurance
Department and First Capital</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment. <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION> shares closed at <MONEY>$2.25</MONEY> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, up <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY>, in <ORGANIZATION>New
York Stock Exchange</ORGANIZATION> composite trading.
   For <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, the negotiations with <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>
represent an unwelcome reminder that the process of digesting
problems created in its massive expansion of the <DATE>late 1980s</DATE>
aren't yet over. Many of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s annuities and
policies were originally sold by stockbrokers at <ORGANIZATION>E.F. Hutton
&amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> acquired after the <DATE>1987</DATE> stock market
crash. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> also was once a <ORGANIZATION>Hutton</ORGANIZATION> unit.
   Insurance industry executives say <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s woes
stem from its promise of relatively high interest rates on
annuities and insurance policies and its failure to raise
capital to support its growth.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910513-0001
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910513-0001.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   First Capital
   Unit Blocked
   By Regulators
   ----
   By Frederick Rose
</HL>
<DATE>
05/13/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP CCI FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
SECURITIES (SCR)
</IN>
<NS>
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
VIRGINIA (VA)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- California regulators clamped down on
operations at the largest insurance unit of First Capital
Holdings Corp., amid growing questions about the medium-sized
insurer's sudden plunge and the risk of major losses to
policyholders.
   The effects of the regulatory order rippled widely Friday,
in the latest woes to surface about a junk bond-laden
insurance company. Worries that regulators would dump the
company's junk bonds prompted a slump in the bond market,
which in turn triggered a wave of computer-guided stock sales
orders.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s regulatory step, which had been anticipated,
echoed at <ORGANIZATION>American Express Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which said it will take a
<MONEY>$144 million</MONEY> pretax charge in the current quarter,
representing all of a <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> stake in Los Angeles-based <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> held by <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman
Brothers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit. There were also negative implications for
<ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> unit, the leader of a <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY>
syndicated loan to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>.
   Beleagered <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> stock shed nearly a
third of its value in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s tumbling stock markets,
falling <MONEY>43.75 cents</MONEY> to close at <MONEY>93.75 cents</MONEY> in composite
stock slid <MONEY>87.5 cents</MONEY> a share, to close at <MONEY>$23.875</MONEY> on the <ORGANIZATION>Big
Board</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Insurance Commissioner <PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>, in a
cease and desist order, declared <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the unit of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, to be in "hazardous"
financial condition and barred all policy redemptions and
loans. He also barred the company from writing any new
business. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> will continue to pay ordinary
policyholder claims, including death and annuity benefits.
   The order, issued <DATE>Friday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, was agreed to by
the company, which said the halt to redemptions would help
"stablilize" financial conditions at <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> said his action was impelled by an
unexpected explosion in redemption demands from policyholders
after a disclosure of his demands that <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION> bolster <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s financial base. From
an average of about <MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> a day <DATE>two weeks ago</DATE>,
redemption requests surged to <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> last <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <MONEY>$30
million</MONEY> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, and <MONEY>$100
million</MONEY> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Redemption requests that were in process
won't be paid as long as regulatory curtailments are in
effect.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, is one of two
major units of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. It had assets of <MONEY>$4.46
billion</MONEY> at <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>, about 190,000 policyholders and 93,000
annuitants in 49 states. The other major unit, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, had
assets of <MONEY>$4.07 billion</MONEY> at <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>, with about 120,000
policyholders and 105,000 annuitants. In all, the two
companies have more than <MONEY>$31 billion</MONEY> of insurance liabilities
payable over many decades.
   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Virginia's Bureau of Insurance</ORGANIZATION> said the
state agency is keeping a close watch on <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers</ORGANIZATION> and
is in contact with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators. He said the company
currently is "in good standing" with regulators and meets
legal capital requirements.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>, announcing the cease and desist order, said
that <PERSON>Gerry R. Ginsberg</PERSON>, president and chief operating officer
of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, was removed from oversight of the
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> unit and that <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>'s
president, <PERSON>Fred Arthur Buck</PERSON>, will report directly to <PERSON>Richard
K. DeScherer</PERSON>, acting chairman of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>.
   First Capital, with about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of its investments in
high-yield investments, is the second major junk bond-laden
insurer to come under regulatory control in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the
past month. It's roughly half the size of <ORGANIZATION>First Executive
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Executive Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> unit, seized by
regulators on <DATE>April 11</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> said that <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s financial problems aren't as severe as those of
<ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION>'s units.
   Although he asserted that <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> has serious
problems, <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> announced a series of measures that
he said cure the company's woes, among them the sale of a
part of the company's business, a search for added capital,
and a program to sell the company's junk bonds -- which
sparked <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s swoon in the bond market. "We believe
policyholders will receive <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> of contracted benefits," he
told reporters.
   But analysts were far less assured of a happy outcome and
speculated that there may be a "black hole," in the words of
one, of prospective losses. Among other things, the failure
of <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> to recapitalize the troubled
insurer concerned observers. Based on public numbers, such a
recapitalization would by one estimate require between <MONEY>$100
million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> -- a relatively small sum for these
institutions, if it fixed the problem.
   "I have to wonder whether there's something that I just
don't know here and which the public hasn't been told," said
<PERSON>Ray Dirks</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Baird, Patrick &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, who has in the
past recommended the stock of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment on the
failure, to date, of their rescue talks with <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>.
   But a number of signs point to crumbling foundations at
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and its units. Although the company
share, on revenue of <MONEY>$980.7 million</MONEY>, its bond and real estate
investments showed marked weaknesses.
   A particular concern with analysts is the company's bond
portfolio, consisting not only of junk bonds, but in many
cases ones for which there is no active market. The so-called
"market value" of the insurer's bonds was about <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>
less than the value at which they were carried on the
company's books at <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE> -- a gap almost twice the <MONEY>$383.8
million</MONEY> in shareholder equity at that date.
   However, only about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of the company's <MONEY>$7.48 billion</MONEY> in
short-term and long-term securities was valued by market
quotes. Market values for the rest were determined by various
"statistical services" and "internal methods," according to
the company's annual filing with the <ORGANIZATION>Securities and Exchange
Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   While the company's junk bond problems predominate, there
are other serious weaknesses. Some <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of the company's <MONEY>$275
million</MONEY> mortgage loan portfolio has interest more than 90
days overdue or is in foreclosure proceedings -- more than
twice the insurance industry average.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$144 million</MONEY> charge is likely to
produce a <DATE>second-quarter</DATE> loss at its <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers</ORGANIZATION>
securities unit. And <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> may face additional
future costs from its association with <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>. About
three-quarters of the policies and annuities issued by <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance unit (formerly <ORGANIZATION>E.F. Hutton
Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>) are held by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers -- a
potential legal liability if <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> fails.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> has resisted <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s demands that
it inject capital into <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> but says it is
still "in discussions" with the commissioner.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s problems also mean bad news for <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>,
which last year led the syndicate that lent <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> to
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s cease and desist orders
block the flow of cash between <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> and its
parent. Some bankers have said that <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> still holds most
of the <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> loan because few other banks were willing
to buy portions of the debt. <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> declines to say how
much of the loan it still holds or whether it has reserved
against a potential loss on the loan.
   ---
   <PERSON>David B. Hilder</PERSON> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> contributed to this article.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920128-0153
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920128-0153.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Shearson Lehman Said to Be Discussing
   Bailout Proposal for First Capital Life
   ----
   By Susan Pulliam
</HL>
<DATE>
01/28/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
SECURITIES (SCR)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY DECLARATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS (BCY)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
VIRGINIA (VA)
</RE>
<LP>
   Shearson Lehman Brothers Inc., a unit of American Express
Corp., is discussing a bailout plan for ailing First Capital
Life Insurance Co. in order to protect Shearson customers who
bought First Capital policies, sources close to the talks
said.
   In recent weeks, talks with California insurance
commissioner John Garamendi have led to a Shearson proposal
to inject roughly $50 million to boost the capital levels of
First Capital Life, which was seized by regulators last
spring, according to one person close to the situation. First
Capital Life is a unit of First Capital Holdings Corp., both
of Los Angeles.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   A large portion of the policies of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> were
sold through <ORGANIZATION>E.F. Hutton &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> acquired after
the stock-market crash in <DATE>1987</DATE>. As a result, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> is said
to be trying to come to an agreement with <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> to
protect its customers. New York-based <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> may also be
trying to protect itself against potentially large lawsuits
from policyholders and shareholders.
   Shearson is also proposing to provide a guarantee of the
company's policyholder obligations that would give
policyholders <MONEY>100 cents</MONEY> on the dollar and a minimum interest
rate on annuities and interest-bearing policies, one person
close to the talks said. Under the plan, however,
policyholders wouldn't be able to withdraw their money for
five years without paying a stiff penalty, the individual
said. The guarantee from <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> would be backed up by
<ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>, people close to the talks said.
   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> said the company is "engaged in
discussions with the insurance commissioner in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>."
He declined to elaborate. A spokesman for the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
insurance department also said talks were "progressing."
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> tried last <DATE>spring</DATE> to convince <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> to ante up roughly <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> in capital for <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, which was struggling with a large junk bond
portfolio. <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> took control of the insurer, however
when <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> balked at the idea. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, filed for bankruptcy protection.
   Meanwhile, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> regulators are said to be close to
unveiling a rescue plan for <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, unit of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, which
was seized soon after the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> unit. As many as eight
potential buyers are said to be interested in buying in the
unit, including <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, which is still in
bankruptcy proceedings, a person close to the situation said.
   Though talks between <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s insurance regulators and
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> have continued intermittently
since last <DATE>spring</DATE>, the discussions recently began to "move
forward," according to a person close to the negotiations. A
final agreement could be as long as two weeks away, however.
   A plan to rescue <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> involving <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
could run aground if a battle with creditors erupts over
their treatment under the proposal. <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> is owed roughly
<MONEY>$260 million</MONEY> under a loan to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> that is
secured by the stock of both of its life insurance units.
   It is unclear how much, if anything, <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> would
receive under the plan. The banking company holds roughly
two-thirds of the loan. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> also has
roughly <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> in subordinated debt outstanding.
   In an unusual move <DATE>several weeks ago</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>National
Westminster Bank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>NationsBank</ORGANIZATION> resigned from the creditors
committee overseeing the bankruptcy proceedings of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. One person close to the situation said the
group resigned because they are secured creditors, while the
other creditors are not.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06127075 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06127075 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  CALIFORNIA; INSURANCE; COMPANY; DEFECT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Shearson Lehman Brothers is negotiating with California insurance regulators,
trying to head off a potential failure of First Capital Life Insurance Co.,
which has more investments in "junk bonds" than other insurers still
operating, people who have been briefed on the talks said Sunday.;    Shearson
is the largest seller on Wall Street of First Capital's policies and owns 28
percent of the company, whose parent is based in Los Angeles.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SHEARSON OFFERS PLAN TO AVERT FAILURE OF
CALIFORNIA INSURER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     It is expected to offer two different approaches, either taking over
management of the insurer's portfolio, guaranteeing more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> that
backs the policies, or buying back all the universal life policies that
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> sold.;    That offer is expected to be discussed <DATE>today</DATE> when <PERSON>Howard
Clark Jr.</PERSON>, chairman and chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, meets in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> with
<PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s first elected insurance commissioner.;    A
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Calls to the <ORGANIZATION>California
Insurance Department</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> were not answered.;    <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>
has retained <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION> to examine ways to shore up its finances, which
were crippled with the collapse of the junk bond market last year.;   
Executives involved in the situation said <PERSON>Salomon</PERSON> was exploring at least two
options with <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, including the sale of its universal life business
or the sale of a large number of the insurance company's junk bonds in the
open market.;    Both moves, if successful, would help <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s
troubled financial position.;    These executives said at least two potential
buyers for the universal life business had held discussions with <ORGANIZATION>Salomon</ORGANIZATION>,
although their names could not be immediately determined.;    A <ORGANIZATION>Salomon</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman did not return a telephone message Sunday.;    The scramble to deal
with <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> comes amid increasing concerns about the health of some
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> insurance companies.;    Last month, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators seized control
of <ORGANIZATION>Executive Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>First Executive Corp.</ORGANIZATION>;   
Executive Life was then the insurance company with the largest portfolio of
junk bonds. <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON>, who oversaw the seizure, said the company was in a
hazardous financial condition, primarily because of defaults and the declining
values in its junk bond portfolio.;    A recent accounting change also has
hurt <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>. As a result of the change, which affects how insurance
companies define junk bonds, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, which reported <DATE>last year</DATE> that <PERCENT>20.2
percent</PERCENT> of its assets were in junk bonds, has increased that figure to 40.7
percent.;    The negotiations between <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators are a
result largely of the Wall Street firm's ill-fated acquisition in <DATE>1988</DATE> of <ORGANIZATION>E.F.
Hutton &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. Hutton ran an insurance company, called <ORGANIZATION>E.F. Hutton Life</ORGANIZATION>, which
it sold in <DATE>1987</DATE> to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, the parent of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life.</ORGANIZATION>; 
  When <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> bought <PERSON>Hutton</PERSON>, it acquired a <PERCENT>44 percent</PERCENT> interest in <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, whose products the firm began to market.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  KURT EICHENWALD, New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910506  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  464  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday May 6, 1991
00127075,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910507-0049
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910507-0049.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Little Progress
   Is Made in Talks
   On First Capital
   ----
   By David B. Hilder
</HL>
<DATE>
05/07/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A11
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP CCI FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
</RE>
<LP>
   California's insurance commissioner and American Express
Co. made little progress in their talks about a possible
rescue of First Capital Holdings Corp., amid signs that the
commissioner may soon take action against First Capital's
main unit.
   The commissioner, John Garamendi, met in New York
yesterday with Howard L. Clark Jr., chairman of American
Express's Shearson Lehman Brothers Inc. securities unit.
According to people familiar with the talks, Mr. Garamendi
expressed reservations about plans proposed by Shearson that
would aid Shearson clients who bought policies from a unit of
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> is seeking a solution that would help all
policyholders of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, which has been hurt by its
large investments in the high-risk, high-yield securities
called junk bonds. First Capital had <MONEY>$747 million</MONEY> in paper
losses on its <MONEY>$3.15 billion</MONEY> junk bond portfolio at year end
and <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> of paper losses on other investments,
Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> had originally asked New York-based <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> to put cash into <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, but <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>
has rebuffed that suggestion, according to people familiar
with the talks.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> is also talking with officials of <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>,
whose main unit was the lead bank in a <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> loan to
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> last year.
   First Capital, which is <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> owned by <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>, has
about <MONEY>$8 billion</MONEY> in assets and is roughly half the size of
<LOCATION>Los Angeles-based</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>First Executive Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which last month
became the largest <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> insurance holding company to fail,
also because of losses on junk bonds. If regulators have to
take control of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s insurance units, one of
several possible actions, it will add significantly to a
burden of insurance insolvencies that is already the largest
in history.
   Although <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> is continuing to talk to both
<ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> about <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s problems,
he is concerned that publicity about <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s woes
could lead to an increase in requests from policyholders to
withdraw their funds, people familiar with the discussions
said.
   Spokesmen for <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and New York-based <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>
declined to comment. A spokesman for <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> confirmed
that the commissioner met with <PERSON>Mr. Clark</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> but
declined to elaborate. Spokesmen for <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> said they
were aware of the meeting, which comes in the wake of
separate discussions between the commissioner and the company
over the infusion of more capital into the company's main
unit, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance Co</ORGANIZATION>. They declined further
comment.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> bought an insurance unit of the former <ORGANIZATION>E.F.
Hutton &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> shortly before <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> acquired <PERSON>Hutton</PERSON>. As a
result, many <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers hold policies issued by <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life Insurance</ORGANIZATION>.
   ---
   <PERSON>Rhonda L. Rundle</PERSON> contributed to this article.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910515-0147
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910515-0147.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   California Takes
   Control of Unit
   Of First Capital
   ---
   Action Follows Creditors'
   Move to Force the Parent
   Into a Chapter 11 Filing
   ----
   By Frederick Rose and David B. Hilder
</HL>
<DATE>
05/15/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP CCI FCH NW
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
</IN>
<NS>
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
GREAT BRITAIN (UK)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- California regulators yesterday formally
seized control of First Capital Life Insurance Co. after
senior creditors sought to have the parent, First Capital
Holdings Co., put into involuntary bankruptcy.
   The bankruptcy petition by Citibank and other creditors
wasn't expected and appears to have interrupted California
Insurance Commissioner John Garamendi's efforts to revitalize
First Capital Life without a complete takeover.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   In response to the bankruptcy petition, <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>
yesterday entered an order of conservation against <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, giving the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance department full
operating control over the company. <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> said he
took the formal action to protect policyholders from
uncertainties created by the creditors' bankruptcy petition.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> had instituted narrower
cease-and-desist orders against the company, barring policy
redemptions and loans but affirming normal payments of death
benefits and annuities.
   In an interview, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner
said he has been in talks with <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American Express
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, holder of a <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. "We
knew that it was possible that there might be a bankruptcy
filing when we cut {the holding company's} air hose off" with
the cease-and-desist order. "But now it's going to be a lot
more work and responsibilities."
   <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>'s motives for the petition weren't entirely
clear. The bank said only that its action was "an attempt to
protect the bank group's rights." As recently as <DATE>last
Thursday</DATE>, people familiar with <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> sought to minimize
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s troubles and said the company wasn't
delinquent in its obligations under the loan agreement.
   The petition for involuntary bankruptcy under Chapter 11
of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Bankruptcy Code was filed by <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>, a unit of
New York-based <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>, as agent for a <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY>
syndicated credit agreement. The filing in federal court in
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> asserted that <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> is due and outstanding
under a term loan and that about <MONEY>$11.6 million</MONEY> is due as
reimbursements of payouts under a letter of credit.
   It's believed that <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> is owed about <MONEY>$175 million</MONEY> of
the <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> loan total. <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> put its portion of the
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> loan on non-performing status, according to
people familiar with the discussions. The step's actual
impact on <DATE>second-quarter</DATE> earnings will depend on whether and
how much <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> sets aside as a provision for possible
losses on the loan.
   <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>'s filing, supported by two other members of the
banking group, <ORGANIZATION>Mitsui Manufacturers Bank</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>National
Westminster Bank</ORGANIZATION>, says the loan is secured by stock in
various units of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, including <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which
was taken over <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> regulators.
   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> and its
subsidiaries said the Los Angeles-based company was
"considering its options" and that the company believed the
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner's formal takeover of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> "was the best way to protect the policies of our
customers."
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> has 20 days to respond to
<ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>'s court request for involuntary bankruptcy.
   Some observers speculated that the petition may have been
filed to forestall any temptation by <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
regulators to grab holding company assets in satisfaction of
insurance-company debts. Among other things, the holding
company has about <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> in cash. With the petition in
place, any such transactions would be subject to court
scrutiny.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-403</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BELAGAE2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910511
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 MAY 91 / International Company News: Californian regulator moves
against insurer
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
MR <PERSON>JOHN Garamendi</PERSON>, the rec-ently-appointed Californian insurance
commissioner, yesterday issued a 'cease and desist' order against <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life Insurance Company</ORGANIZATION>, a San Diego-based insurer whose parent
company is 28 per cent-owned by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers</ORGANIZATION>.
The order prohibits <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> from making payments to its parent
company, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, or to its affiliates without the
Commissioner's permission, and from writing new business.
It also places a moratorium on surrenders by <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> policyholders and
on life insurance policy loans.
Announcing the order, <PERSON>Mr Garamendi</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> was in a 'hazardous'
financial condition. Concern about the company's position had triggered a
wave of surrenders in recent days, thus compounding its problems, he said.
First Capital is not large - its assets are Dollars 4.5bn and it has 190,000
policyholders - but the authorities' intervention comes at a sensitive time.
Last month, a much bigger Californian insurer, <ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION>, was seized
by the regulators after concerns about its heavy junk bond portfolio
prompted a similar wave of surrenders and a collapse of its marketing
network.
Like First Executive, much of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> problems stem from sizeable junk
bond exposure.
The Commissioner has been putting pressure on <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> to help shore up the
insurer, but no deal has emerged.
Shearson Lehman <TIME>last night</TIME> said it will take a Dollars 144m <DATE>second quarter</DATE>
pre-tax charge related to its investment in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, Dow Jones reports
from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910530-0016
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910530-0016.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   California to Question
   Two First Capital Officers
</HL>
<DATE>
05/30/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C12
</SO>
<CO>
   FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- California regulators are looking into
whether two top officers of a now-failed First Capital
Holdings Corp. insurance unit improperly redeemed personal
insurance or annuity policies shortly before the unit was
seized by the state, a California insurance department
official said.
   The official, a spokesman for California Insurance
Commissioner John Garamendi, said the commissioner met
yesterday with Fred A. Buck, president of First Capital Life
Insurance Co. and with Julia S. Kelly, a senior vice
president, to discuss their actions.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The two may have redeemed policies sometime before
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators seized <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, on <DATE>May 14</DATE>.
The commissioner and his officials are looking into whether
the company's officers improperly put themselves ahead of
other policyholders in making redemptions. It isn't clear
whether such actions would violate <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance law.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s spokesman declined to elaborate on either
the meeting or the investigation. <PERSON>Mr. Buck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Ms. Kelly</PERSON>
couldn't be reached.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, is a unit of Los
Angeles-based <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, which has said it plans
to file for Chapter 11 protection from creditors. <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' other major insurance unit, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, was
seized by regulators in that state on <DATE>May 13</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT921-10537</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CBEBPAF2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920205
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  05 FEB 92 / International Company News: American Express to back insurer
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIKKI TAIT
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   NEW YORK
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>AMERICAN Express</ORGANIZATION> and its <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION> investment banking subsidiary have
agreed to inject Dollars 50m in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance</ORGANIZATION> (FCL), the
ailing life company seized last <DATE>May</DATE> by state insurance regulators. They have
also agreed to underpin the value of policyholders' contracts.
The aim is to rehabilitate the insurer, whose troubles stemmed largely from
its heavy junk bond exposure and a significant policyholder run last year.
As part of the deal with the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators, <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> will take over management of FCL - earning a 'modest' but
undisclosed fee - while selling down a portion of the junk bond portfolio.
During a five-year rehabilitation programme and for a short period after
this, they will also have an option to acquire 100 per cent of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s assets and liabilities at <MONEY>20 per cent</MONEY> of their
actuarial-determined value. At end-1991, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> had around Dollars
4bn in assets, 190,000 policyholders and 60,000 annuitants.
The involvement of <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> with <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> dates
back to the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. In <DATE>November 1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Robert Weingarten</PERSON>, who had built the
fast-growing company partly by acquisitions and partly by selling highly
competitive policies backed by a high-yielding portfolio of junk bonds, sold
his family stake in the insurer's parent company to <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>.
Shearson, meanwhile, sold a large number of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> policies to its
own clients between <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1991</DATE>.
When the junk bond market collapsed and the troubles at neighbouring
Executive Life, another junk bond-ridden <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurer, hit the
headlines, many <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> policyholders sought to cash in their
policies. Around 36,000 contracts were surrendered between <DATE>January 1991</DATE> and
<DATE>May</DATE>, when the regulators stepped in.
Last <DATE>spring</DATE>, <PERSON>Mr John Garamendi</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner, had
sought a capital infusion from <ORGANIZATION>American Express/Shearson</ORGANIZATION> - which holds a 28
per cent stake in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, the bankrupt parent company - but
he met resistance. Asked yesterday why this solution had taken so long to
arrange, he said only that it was 'a very complex business'.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 23
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920205-0160
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920205-0160.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Shearson Agrees
   To Guarantee
   Policy Values
   ---
   Firm, After Being Pressured,
   Will Provide $50 Million
   For First Capital Life
   ----
   By Susan Pulliam
</HL>
<DATE>
02/05/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<NS>
CONSUMER ISSUES (CSU)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
VIRGINIA (VA)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- Shearson Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc., bowing
to pressure from angry customers, agreed to inject $50
million into ailing First Capital Life Insurance Co. and to
guarantee the full value of policyholders' accounts.
   The accord, which was expected, will help protect all
policyholders, including 150,000 Shearson customers, against
losses on annuities they bought from the insurer. The
agreement also will help insulate Shearson, a unit of
American Express Co., from the threat of embarrassing and
costly policyholder litigation.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The agreement represents a turnabout by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, which
balked last <DATE>spring</DATE> when <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Insurance Commissioner
<PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON> asked <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> to inject <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY>
into <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, which was hurt by junk-bond losses.
At the time, <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> was willing to bail out only
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers, roughly <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the total 250,000
policyholders and annuitants of the insurer. <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>
owns <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, the Los
Angeles-based parent of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>.
   The agreement "represents a commitment from <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> to help not only those policyholders who
are <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> customers but all policyholders," said <PERSON>Mr.
Garamendi</PERSON>, who announced the accord in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> yesterday
along with <PERSON>Howard L. Clark Jr.</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman.
   Shearson agreed to manage the San Diego-based insurer and
will also reduce <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$1.2 billion</MONEY> junk-bond
holdings by <MONEY>$450 million</MONEY>.
   In exchange for its guarantee of obligations of the
insurer, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> has the right under the plan to receive <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT>
of the profit of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> in the future. In
negotiations with creditors, including a syndicate of banks
led by <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> that are owed <MONEY>$260 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> and
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> have offered them the right to a <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> share in the
insurer's profits. Creditors haven't yet agreed to a deal,
however.
   Shearson and <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> still could be subject to
large liabilities under the guarantee to policyholders,
however. <PERSON>Mr. Clark</PERSON> said he believes the insurer is currently
financially healthy enough to cover its obligation to
policyholders.
   To receive the full value of their policies, policyholders
will be required to keep their policies with <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Life</ORGANIZATION> for five years. Though they will continue to receive the
guaranteed interest rates on their contracts for now, rates
on policyholders' policies are likely to be cut, in many
cases in a year or less, based on the performance of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s investments. The agreement calls for a minimum rate
of <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> to be paid to policyholders.
   Policyholders who surrender their policies before the plan
is in effect or during the first year of the plan will
receive <PERCENT>75%</PERCENT> of their cash value. The cash value paid
increases in the second year to <PERCENT>77%</PERCENT> and rises to <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> during
the fifth year.
   The agreement is pending settlement of policyholder
litigation filed in both state and federal court in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. As part of the settlement with policyholders,
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> agreed to refund a percentage of the surrender
charges paid by policyholders who withdrew their money
between <DATE>January 1990</DATE>, and <DATE>May 13, 1991</DATE>, the day before the
insurer was seized by <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   In an unusual concession to former policyholders, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
also offered the 36,000 policyholders who withdrew their cash
values a chance to reinstate their policies. They would be
credited the full amount of surrender charges already paid.
   The agreement doesn't include policyholders of <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> unit of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. Insurance regulators in <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> are said
to be in negotiations with several potential buyers for that
company, which is considered the stronger of the two units.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06128015 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06128015 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  STOCK; INVESTMENT; COMPANY; CALIFORNIA; INSURANCE; REGULATION; MEETING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Negotiations between executives of Shearson Lehman and California insurance
regulators broke down Monday, as an effort to avert a potential failure of
First Capital Life Insurance Co. grew more intense, people who have been
briefed on the talks said.;    At the meeting Monday morning in Manhattan,
Shearson offered two proposals to improve the finances of the troubled
insurance company, which has more investments in "junk bonds" than other
insurers still operating.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  INSURER'S PLANS FOR BAILOUT REJECTED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Plans called insufficient;    But both proposals were rejected by <PERSON>John
Garamendi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s insurance commissioner, as being insufficient to deal
with the company's deteriorating finances.;    <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, which is the largest
seller of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s policies and owns <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT> of the company's
parent, offered proposals that would address the risks only to holders of
policies sold through the Wall Street firm.;    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> rejected those
proposals because he wanted a comprehensive solution to the company's
troubles, people who have been briefed on the discussions said.;    Rush to
find solution;    The breakdown in the talks set off a rush to find a solution
to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s situation, as <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> approached other financial
institutions for help. But people familiar with the situation said there was a
growing concern that anxieties in the marketplace might overtake the efforts,
resulting in a seizure of the insurance company.;    "The real problem now is
that there is real doubt about whether there is time remaining to work
anything out," one person familiar with the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> situation said.
"Everybody is under pressure to come up with a solution before time runs
out.";    A spokesman for <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> confirmed talks with <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> executives
had been held <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, but declined to elaborate. A spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> declined to comment.;    <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> approached;    As the <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
talks were hitting snags, <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> was said to have approached executives at
<ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>, which was said to be a significant lender to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>,
the insurance company's parent.;    The hope, according to people who have
been briefed on those talks, is that <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION> would infuse more capital into
the company to help preserve the quality of outstanding loans. A <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>
spokeswoman did not return a telephone call <DATE>Monday</DATE> night.;    At the same
time, <ORGANIZATION>Salomon Brothers</ORGANIZATION>, which has been hired by <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> to deal with its
unraveling finances, was said still to be exploring possible ways that the
insurance company could raise the badly needed cash. Those plans were said to
include selling off one of the company's businesses, or selling a large
portfolio of its junk bond holdings.;    The flurry of activity came in the
shadow of the recent seizure of <ORGANIZATION>Executive Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of
<ORGANIZATION>First Executive Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which had been the insurance company with the largest
portfolio of junk bonds.;    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON>, who oversaw the seizure, said at the
time that the company was in hazardous financial condition, primarily because
of defaults and declining values in that portfolio.;    The seizure of the
<ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION> unit intensified concerns among regulators and the financial
community about the health of a number of other insurance companies, including
First Capital.;    An accounting change recently also hit <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s
capital base very hard. As a result of the change, <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>, which was
reporting last year that <PERCENT>20.2 percent</PERCENT> of its assets were in junk bonds, has
raised that figure to 40.7 percent.;    After the seizure of <ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> arranged two weeks ago to meet with <PERSON>Howard Clark Jr.</PERSON>, chairman and
chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>James D. Robinson III</PERSON>, chairman and chief
executive of <ORGANIZATION>American Express Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>'s parent. The recent negotiations
with the firm followed those meetings.;    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON>'s concerns <DATE>Monday</DATE> were
said to have stemmed largely from what he saw as extensive problems at <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, at both its <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Capital</ORGANIZATION>, and its
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> subsidiary, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which has <PERCENT>37.6
percent</PERCENT> of its assets in junk bonds, according to <ORGANIZATION>Weiss Research</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>West Palm
Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, firm. That is second only to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>California.</LOCATION>;    The
proposals rejected <DATE>Monday</DATE> by <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> involved <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>'s protection of its
customers who bought policies through the firm.;    Under the more radical
proposal, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> would guarantee a portfolio of more than <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> that is
backing the policies and contracts of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> that are held by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
customers.;    Once the guarantee was made, the firm would begin a push to get
holders of the policies to cash them in, executives briefed on the talks said.
The portfolio contains investments in a range of securities, including a large
amount of the junk bonds that were purchased by <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910507  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  759  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday May 7, 1991
00128015,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06129017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06129017 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  STOCK; INVESTMENT; COMPANY; CALIFORNIA; INSURANCE; REGULATION; FINANCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A dispute between Shearson Lehman Brothers and California insurance regulators
intensified Tuesday, with the state's insurance commissioner contending that
the Wall Street firm had a responsibility to infuse First Capital Life
Insurance Co. with more capital.;    The struggling insurance company has more
investments in "junk bonds" than any other insurer still independently
operating.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GARAMENDI URGES SHEARSON TO SHORE UP AILING
FIRST CAPITAL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>, which owns <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT> of the insurer's parent, has been the
largest seller on Wall Street of the company's policies and contracts.;    The
dispute comes after more than two weeks of negotiations between the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
regulators and executives of <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> and its parent, <ORGANIZATION>American Express Co</ORGANIZATION>. On
<DATE>Monday</DATE>, those talks broke down when the regulators rejected proposals by
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> to protect its own customers who had purchased <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>
products. <PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s insurance commissioner, was said to be
seeking a more comprehensive solution to the problem.;    In statements
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> said that the financial problems of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> appeared
to be extensive, and that both <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> needed to take
action to handle the entire problem, rather than protecting only their
customers.;    "Our continuing review" of the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance
Company</ORGANIZATION> "indicates that the company needs a substantial infusion of cash,"
<PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> said. "This is <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION>'s and <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'
responsibility.";    He added that the position in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> had been
purchased "so that they would have annuities and life insurance products to
sell through their financial consultants, and sell they did.";    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON>
said that from <DATE>1986</DATE> through the <DATE>first quarter of this year</DATE>, more than <PERCENT>75
percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s business was produced by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> employees.;    He said that, in that time, the two companies
"generated more than <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> worth of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> business. Meanwhile,
the percentage of non-investment grade assets of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> grew from less
than <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> to more than <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of total assets." A recent accounting
rule change was responsible for much of that change, increasing the junk bond
holdings <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> reported from <PERCENT>20.2 percent</PERCENT> of its assets to 40.7
percent.;    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> said he believed that both <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> should make sure that <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> was viable, and referred to
<ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s well-known advertising campaign.;    "If membership has its
privileges, than ownership has its responsibilities," he said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  New York Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910508  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  380  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 8, 1991
00129017,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920212-0161
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920212-0161.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   First Capital, Units
   File a Joint Plan
   To Reorganize
   ----
   By Earl C. Gottschalk Jr.
</HL>
<DATE>
02/12/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C11
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP CCI FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
MAJOR MONEY CENTER BANKS (BAN)
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY DECLARATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS (BCY)
RESTRUCTURINGS, RECAPITALIZATION (RCN)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
VIRGINIA (VA)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- First Capital Holdings Corp. and its two
life insurance holding company subsidiaries filed a joint
plan of reorganization in U.S. Bankruptcy Court here.
   Under terms of the proposed plan, First Capital Holdings'
senior secured lenders -- a syndicate of banks led by
Citicorp would receive 100% of the outstanding stock of the
two life insurance holding company subsidiaries. The banks
hold $260 million of senior secured debt.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The reorganization plan deals with companies at the
holding company level. They are <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance
Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a holding company for <ORGANIZATION>San Diego-based First
Capital Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Insurance
Group</ORGANIZATION>, a holding company whose principal asset is stock in
Virginia-based <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   Last week, <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, bowing
to pressure from angry customers, agreed to inject <MONEY>$50
million</MONEY> into ailing <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> and to
guarantee the full value of policyholders' accounts. The
accord will help protect all policyholders, including 150,000
Shearson customers, against losses on annuities they bought
from the insurance company. <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>New
York-based American Express Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   According to <PERSON>Charles Perkins</PERSON>, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, this plan of reorganization doesn't affect
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> policyholders' accounts and the <ORGANIZATION>Shearson
Lehman Brothers</ORGANIZATION> guarantee. <PERSON>Mr. Perkins</PERSON> said the plan does,
however, reduce <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>'s share of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>'s
future profit to <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> from <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT>. <PERSON>Mr. Perkins</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> was
involved in the negotiations for the plan of reorganization.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance Group</ORGANIZATION> would continue to hold
a <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> equity interest in the rehabilitated <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Life</ORGANIZATION>, subject to an option held by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION> to acquire
the assets and liabilities of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> at a price
equal to <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> of their fair market value. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Insurance
Commissioner <PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>, who played a key role in getting
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> to make the investment in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, said
he had no comment on the reorganization plan.
   <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> is being operated
under the conservatorship of the <ORGANIZATION>Virginia Insurance
Commissioner</ORGANIZATION>. The commissioner is currently evaluating
various proposals for the rehabilitation of the insurance
company. A spokesman for the <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> insurance commissioner
said he had no comment on the reorganization plan.
   General unsecured creditors of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and the two life insurance holding company subsidiaries
would receive cash equal to <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of their claim, subject to
overall "caps," according to the plan.
   Holders of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' <PERCENT>13%</PERCENT> senior subordinated
debentures would receive no distribution or other
consideration under the proposed plan. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>
would be dissolved, and the holders of common stock of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> would receive no distribution or other
consideration under the proposed plan.
   The proposed reorganization plan is subject to execution
of a comprehensive settlement among <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>, the debtor companies and certain officers,
directors and lenders of the debtor companies; final orders
approving the rehabilitation of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life</ORGANIZATION>; settlement of policyholders' and other
class-action litigation; and bankruptcy court approval.
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> filed for Chapter 11
bankruptcy protection <DATE>last May 30</DATE>. Earlier last <DATE>May</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life
Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> were seized by insurance regulators in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910510-0062
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910510-0062.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   California to Ban Accounting Practice
   It Says Inflates Insurers' Capital Levels
   ----
   By Susan Pulliam
</HL>
<DATE>
05/10/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH FEXC
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY DECLARATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS (BCY)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
</RE>
<LP>
   California is forcing life insurers in the state to end an
accounting practice that regulators contend artificially
inflates an insurer's capital levels.
   As a result, the new rule will sharply reduce the reported
capital levels of many insurers operating in California. The
change, which hasn't been publicly announced, is the latest
attempt by California regulators to tighten control over
insurers following recent problems involving First Executive
Corp. and First Capital Holdings Corp.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The new rule, outlined in an <DATE>April 15</DATE> letter from <PERSON>John
Garamendi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner, to 640
insurance companies licensed to operate in the state, would
ban the use of a controversial reinsurance contract.
Reinsurance companies assume some of the risk on insurer's
policies in return for fees or a share in future revenue.
They also pay commissions for taking the policies, which
insurers list as capital. <PERSON>Norris Clark</PERSON>, chief of financial
analysis, says the department acted after it concluded that
companies had used questionable reinsurance agreements to
boost their capital levels.
   The rule, which takes effect at the end of this year, will
hit California-based companies hardest, but it also could
have an impact on reinsurers and any insurance company
operating in the state. "There are a lot of these
transactions out there," said <PERSON>Mr. Clark</PERSON>. "The early
indications are that it impacts a number of companies. There
are also insurers that have made their business out of
writing these agreements," he said.
   Of the life insurance companies operating in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
58 are based in the state. Companies that are based in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> would have to eliminate the transactions by <DATE>Dec.
31</DATE>, which would reduce their capital levels. Out-of-state
companies would have to choose between doing business in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and reducing their capital levels for reporting
purposes in the state.
   The accounting change helps explain some of the actions
taken recently regarding the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance unit of
<ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>
unit of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. Regulators seized the unit of
<ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION> after huge junk bond losses. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
regulators are expected to sharply restrict the operations of
the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> unit in a matter of days.
   People close to the situation say regulators made the
accounting change after examiners discovered several weeks
ago that <MONEY>$64 million</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life Insurance</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$107
million</MONEY> in capital at year end came from questionable
reinsurance agreements. Roughly <MONEY>$165 million</MONEY> of the <MONEY>$474
million</MONEY> in capital at <ORGANIZATION>First Executive</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> unit came
from these transactions, according to people familiar with
the company.
   Insurance companies routinely use reinsurance agreements
to lower their risk of doing business. Many kinds of
reinsurance also have the benefit of boosting capital,
because insurers are able to shift the expense of doing
business to the reinsurer. <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> objects to
reinsurance agreements that serve only to raise an insurer's
capital, without also lowering the risk.
   The department has sent a survey to all 640 companies to
find out how widespread such practices are, <PERSON>Mr. Clark</PERSON> said.
   In the industry, the move "is creating chaos . . .," says
<PERSON>Bruce Winterhof</PERSON>, consulting actuary with <ORGANIZATION>Milliman &amp;
Robertson</ORGANIZATION>, a nationwide actuarial consulting firm. "There are
many insurance companies whose capital would be reduced under
the rule," he says.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910514-0073
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910514-0073.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Regulators Curb
   Second Big Unit
   Of First Capital
   ----
   By Frederick Rose
</HL>
<DATE>
05/14/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A8
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
STOCK AND BOND RATINGS (RTG)
SECURITIES (SCR)
</IN>
<NS>
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
BOND &amp; STOCK RATINGS (RTG)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
VIRGINIA (VA)
</RE>
<LP>
   Virginia regulators seized Fidelity Bankers Life Insurance
Co., the second major unit of beleaguered First Capital
Holdings Corp. to be curbed by regulators in less than a
week.
   The action by Virginia's Bureau of Insurance blocks all
policy redemptions and loans but permits routine payments of
death and annuity benefits, as well as accident and health
claims.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, had assets of
about <MONEY>$4.07 billion</MONEY> at <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>, and about 213,000 life
insurance policies and 97,000 annuitants.
   The unit is slightly smaller than <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life
Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, whose business was sharply
curbed by <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> regulators on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>
had assets of <MONEY>$4.46 billion</MONEY> at <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>, about 190,000
policyholders and 93,000 annuitants. Both companies have
substantial holdings of junk bonds.
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>'s move puts substantially all of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital
Holdings</ORGANIZATION>' insurance business under regulatory restrictions.
Together, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers and First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION>, have more
than <MONEY>$31 billion</MONEY> in life insurance benefits owed to
policyholders over the coming decades.
   Although industry watchers had expected <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
regulators to swiftly follow <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s action, a <ORGANIZATION>Virginia
Bureau of Insurance</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers</ORGANIZATION> was in "good standing" and that the company met
minimum capital requirements. The spokesman, <PERSON>Kenneth Schrad</PERSON>,
said he didn't know what had occurred between <DATE>Friday</DATE> and
yesterday to change the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s view.
   <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers</ORGANIZATION> said it was cooperating with <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
regulators, adding that it believed the step was in the best
interest of policyholders.
   Much of the business of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers</ORGANIZATION> was written through securities dealers, who were
major sellers of annuities written by both companies, opening
the potential for substantial legal liability at various
brokerage companies.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman Brothers</ORGANIZATION> securities unit of <ORGANIZATION>American
Express Co.</ORGANIZATION>, with a <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>,
based in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, sold business that brought in some
<MONEY>$1.74 billion</MONEY> of premiums in the <DATE>last three years</DATE> at the two
filing. <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber Inc.</ORGANIZATION> accounted for business that brought
in <MONEY>$641.9 million</MONEY> over the same period.
   <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION> have said they are
continuing talks with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance regulators. As
previously reported, <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> said it will take a
<MONEY>$144 million</MONEY> pretax charge in the current quarter,
representing the <PERCENT>28%</PERCENT> stake. Also there are negative
implications for <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> unit, leader of a <MONEY>$275
million</MONEY> syndicated loan to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION>. A
<ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman declined to comment on the company's
sales -- believed to have been written largely with <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers</ORGANIZATION>.
   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Moody's Investors Service Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Standard &amp;
Poor's Corp.</ORGANIZATION> said they downgraded <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s subordinated debt.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06136167 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06136167 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: John Garamendi  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  INSURANCE; COMPANY; CALIFORNIA; REGULATION; LAW; BANKRUPT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  California State Insurance Commissioner John Garamendi Tuesday seized ailing
First Capital Life Insurance Co. of San Diego, after major lenders sought to
force its parent company into Chapter 11 bankruptcy proceedings.;    Garamendi
said that the state placed the company in conservatorship to protect the
interest of more than 250,000 First Capital policy and annuity holders. It is
the second largest failure of a life insurer ever, and comes on the heels of
the seizure last month of the biggest, Executive Life Insurance Co.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  REGULATORS TAKE OVER AILING FIRST CAPITAL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  (box) Bidding opens on failed Executive Life, Page 6F.
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The state took control of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> after a group of lenders headed by
<ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION> petitioned late <DATE>Monday</DATE> to force its parent, <LOCATION>Los Angeles-based</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Holdings Corp.</ORGANIZATION> into bankruptcy for defaulting on a <MONEY>$275 million</MONEY> loan.;
   By placing <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> into conservatorship, regulators actively run the
company. <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> will still pay customers death and annuity benefits in
full, along with accident and health claims. But the state is prohibiting
policy redemptions and loans on policies.;    The effect of <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON>'s action
is to shield the insurance company against claims filed by banks and other
creditors. "We place the insurance company in a protective envelope, if you
will, walling it off from all of its other creditors," <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> told a state
Capitol news conference.;    <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings</ORGANIZATION> was a high-flying
insurance operation headed until <DATE>March</DATE> by <PERSON>Robert Weingarten</PERSON>, one of the
industry's highest-paid executives who last year took home <MONEY>$1.35 million</MONEY>. The
company's problems stem largely from investments in risky, high-yield junk
bonds.;    <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION>, an <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> subsidiary, owns <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT> of
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> and regulators have been pressuring the brokerage firm to
provide more financial support to the insurance units. Negotiations are
continuing on that issue.;    Last week, <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> slapped restrictions on
<ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> after customers flooded the company with requests to cash
in their policies -- a situation analogous to a run on a bank. On <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> insurance authorities seized its sister unit, <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity Bankers Life
Insurance</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, Va.-based insurance firm slightly smaller than <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital Life.;    First Capital</ORGANIZATION> has assets of <MONEY>$4.46 billion</MONEY>, 190,000 life
insurance policyholders and 62,000 annuitants, the state said. <ORGANIZATION>Fidelity
Bankers</ORGANIZATION> has assets of <MONEY>$4.07 billion</MONEY>, 120,000 policyholders and 105,000
annuitants. Both operate in 49 states.;    <PERSON>Garamendi</PERSON> previously said that he
believes <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> policyholders will receive all of their benefits. At
the news conference, he said that he would not have placed the firm into
conservatorship had the creditors not sought to force it into bankruptcy. He
added that a liquidation of the company is not planned.; IF YOU'RE INTERESTED;
Policyholders can call the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of Insurance</ORGANIZATION> consumer hot line for
information -- (800) 927-HELP.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Sacramento  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910515  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  466  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 15, 1991
00136167,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910520-0161
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910520-0161.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Junk-Bond Sale
   To Be Avoided
   By California
   ---
   Garamendi Vows `Fire Sale'
   Of Two Insurance Units'
   Holdings Won't Be Held
   ----
   By Frederick Rose
</HL>
<DATE>
05/20/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<CO>
   F.CLC FCH FEXC
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
BANKRUPTCIES (BCY)
ALL BANKS, BANKING NEWS AND ISSUES (BNK)
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
TENDER OFFERS, MERGERS, ACQUISITIONS (TNM)
BOND MARKET NEWS (BON)
</IN>
<NS>
BANKRUPTCY DECLARATIONS AND PROCEEDINGS (BCY)
ACQUISITIONS &amp; MERGERS, TAKEOVERS, BOARD BATTLES (TNM)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
FRANCE (FR)
</RE>
<LP>
   LOS ANGELES -- California insurance commissioner John
Garamendi, seeking to calm skittish bond markets, promised to
avoid "a fire sale" of billions of dollars of junk bonds from
two failed companies now in his department's control.
   "It isn't in anybody's interest to force this market down
by a disorderly liquidation process" of bonds held by
Executive Life Insurance Co. and First Capital Life Insurance
Co., Mr. Garamendi said at a public meeting Friday attended
by about 500 Executive Life policyholders.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The commissioner, who took office in <DATE>January</DATE> and who has
blamed the failure of the two companies on his predecessor,
was greeted with applause and occasional levity during his
one-hour question-and-answer session.
   Junk bond markets sagged early last week after <PERSON>Mr.
Garamendi</PERSON> seized <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> and announced that his
officials planned to pare the company's big junk-bond
portfolio. Spooked, some holders of junk bonds began dumping
the securities. Executive Life is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>First Executive
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>; <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> is a unit of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Holdings
Corp</ORGANIZATION>. Both parent companies are based in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and,
combined with other insurance units under state control in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, hold more than <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY> face value
of junk bonds.
   Most junk bonds fell 1/2 point <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON>'s problems with jumpy bond markets are but
one of the many complications of a proposed restructuring of
about <MONEY>$10.17 billion</MONEY> in Executive Life assets. The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
insurance department has said it will conduct what amounts to
an auction for groups interested in acquiring the failed
company's business.
   The front runner in that auction is a group lead by <ORGANIZATION>Altus
Finance</ORGANIZATION>, a <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT>-owned subsidiary of the French bank <ORGANIZATION>Credit
Lyonnais</ORGANIZATION>, which has committed to provide financing or a
letter of credit for as much as <MONEY>$3 billion</MONEY> in an as-yet
undetermined restructuring. The <ORGANIZATION>Altus Finance</ORGANIZATION> group has been
talking with <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> officials for some months and has
been analyzing a variety of complicated information that
other prospective bidders are only now going to be able to
review.
   Although little has been said publicly about the
prospective look of a "renewed" Executive Life company,
people familiar with the situation say that any restructuring
would consist of a successor company holding the liabilities
to current policyholders, backed by large portions of
Executive Life's present assets and an infusion of new
capital to shore up the company's depleted equity.
   While the assets of the company will need to be shored up,
its liabilities -- what it must pay to policyholders -- must
be reduced. It's expected that, at minimum, interest rates
paid to policy and annuity holders on cash balances will be
sharply reduced.
   <PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that he won't require bidders
for Executive Life to sell the company's deeply devalued
holdings of junk bonds, but rather to issue guaranties of a
minimum value for the portfolio. Such a guarantee would
likely be backed by an outside bank or by assets held by the
bidders. He added that his officials were looking for ways in
which policyholders might participate in gains in bond values
in future years.
   However, it's likely that any renewed Executive Life would
have to prune its bulging portfolio of high-yield bonds.
Insurance analysts doubt that policyholders would trust a
company with large holdings of high-yield securities. Also,
state restrictions are expected that will limit junk-bond
holdings to no more than <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> of assetsfar below the more than
<PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> held by Executive Life. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> already has a <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> limit.
   Despite the complications of auctioning Executive Life,
<PERSON>Mr. Garamendi</PERSON> told the policyholders <DATE>Friday</DATE> that it's far
better than the alternative. "Liquidation," he said, "would
be an unmitigated disaster for everybody involved; it would
take forever to liquidate this company {because} there is no
ready market for many of the assets."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910510-0022
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910510-0022.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Heard on the Street:
   American Express's Stake in Insurer Is Likely
   To Mean Another Quarter of Weak Earnings
   ----
   By David B. Hilder
</HL>
<DATE>
05/10/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE C2
</SO>
<CO>
   AXP FCH
</CO>
<MS>
FINANCIAL (FIN)
</MS>
<IN>
DIVERSIFIED FINANCIAL SERVICES, CREDIT INSTITUTIONS (FIS)
HEARD ON THE STREET (HRD)
LIFE INSURANCE (INL)
INSURANCE (INS)
STOCK MARKET, OFFERINGS (STK)
SECURITIES (SCR)
</IN>
<NS>
HEARD ON THE STREET (HRD)
STOCK &amp; OTHER MARKET NEWS (STK)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NEW YORK (NY)
</RE>
<LP>
   NEW YORK -- American Express thought it got out of the
risky part of the insurance business two years ago when it
sold its last common shares of Fireman's Fund.
   But American Express has found a new way to lose money in
a California insurance company. This time it's First Capital
Holdings, a struggling life insurer of which American Express
once owned 44%, now reduced to 28%. Many Wall Street analysts
think it's unlikely American Express will emerge unscathed
from its association with First Capital, and they have begun
estimating how bad the pain will be.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> owns the former <PERSON>E.F. Hutton</PERSON> life insurance
company. Customers of <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman
Brothers</ORGANIZATION> unit, including many acquired when the firm bought
<PERSON>Hutton</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE>, hold about <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY> of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>
policies and annuities.
   Insurance regulators are looking hard at <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> and
its two insurance units, which invested heavily in junk
bonds, bank loan participations, and commercial real estate.
The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner is expected to sharply
restrict the operations of <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
insurance unit in a matter of days. This week the
commissioner publicly called on <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> to pump cash
into the unit, but <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> is balking.
   Analysts' estimates of potential charges against <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION>'s earnings begin at around <MONEY>$200 million</MONEY> and run as
high as <MONEY>$430 million</MONEY>. While that's manageable for a company
of <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s size and cash flow, it is likely to
produce a second consecutive quarter of weak earnings and
could force the company to raise more capital, perhaps by
selling common stock.
   The <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> woes come at a bad time. <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION>'s charge-card business is under competitive attack.
First-quarter profit of its charge card and travelers check
unit fell <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT>.
   Analysts are lowering their <DATE>1991</DATE> earnings estimates, and
at least one, <PERSON>Frank DeSantis</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>PaineWebber Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has
downgraded <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> to a rating of "unattractive"
from "neutral."
   The problem, <PERSON>Mr. DeSantis</PERSON> believes, is that write-offs
related to <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> could wipe out much of <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>'s
capital. Because <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> needs good credit ratings to
continue its activities in the capital markets, <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> would probably bow to pressure from ratings agencies
to shore up <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> with more cash.
   The pain could start with the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> stake, still
on <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION>'s books at <MONEY>$144 million</MONEY> though its market
value is below <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. If insurance regulators seize
control of the insurance units, <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> will have to
write off its investment, analysts say; they put the profit
impact at <MONEY>20 cents</MONEY> to <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> a share.
   A tougher question is how much it might also cost <ORGANIZATION>American
Express</ORGANIZATION> to prop up <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance unit,
the seller of nearly all the policies held by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
customers, or to make up potential losses to <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
clients. Early estimates of those costs run from <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>
to nearly <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY>. <PERSON>James P. Hanbury</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Wertheim Schroder</ORGANIZATION>
says "no more than <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> or <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>." <PERSON>Mr.
DeSantis</PERSON>'s estimate is <MONEY>$280 million</MONEY>, or about <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of the
value of the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> policies held by <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION>
customers. (He uses <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> because the market value of <ORGANIZATION>First
Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s year-end assets was some <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> below book value.)
   In response to those estimates, a <ORGANIZATION>Shearson</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said,
"We are confident that <ORGANIZATION>First Capital Life</ORGANIZATION> currently has the
resources to repay clients at least their original
investments. Shearson now views any guarantees as open-ended
commitments, which it is not in a position to make."
   <PERSON>John Garamendi</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> insurance commissioner,
won't say how much cash he thinks <ORGANIZATION>American Express</ORGANIZATION> should put
into <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>. But people familiar with the talks say he
privately asked for <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY>. Several officials involved
in the <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION> rescue talks say <ORGANIZATION>First Capital</ORGANIZATION>'s
