<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102590-0235 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 297893 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 25, 1990, Thursday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 1; Column 2; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
343 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ASTRONOMERS STAR-STRUCK OVER DISCOVERY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From United Press International 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Astronomers have discovered what may be the largest galaxy in the known 
universe, a mammoth cluster of stars that stretches for 6 million light years 
-- more than 60 times the size of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, it was reported today. 
</P>
<P>
The giant object is located in the heart of a cluster of galaxies known as 
<ORGANIZATION>Abell 2029</ORGANIZATION>, a team of astronomers reported in the journal Science. 
</P>
<P>
The object is 1 billion light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> -- that is, the distance light 
travels in <MONEY>1 billion</MONEY> years at a speed of 186,000 miles per second. 
</P>
<P>
Boughn</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Haverford College</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Jeffrey Kuhn</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State University</ORGANIZATION> were 
able to detect a "halo" of diffuse light surrounding a massive galaxy at the 
center of <ORGANIZATION>Abell 2029</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A mosaic of 16 images made with light-sensitive electronic "chips" showed the 
diffuse halo to be remarkably uniform, leading the astronomers to conclude they 
were looking at a single galaxy, the largest ever discovered. 
</P>
<P>
Measurements indicate that the galaxy has a diameter of 6 million light years, 
more than 4 1/2 times the diameter of the previous record holder and 60 times 
wider than <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, which has a diameter of about 100,000 light 
years. 
</P>
<P>
The scientists believe that they are seeing a giant galaxy primarily because 
the halo's light spreads very smoothly outward from the central galaxy and 
because the halo has the same elliptical shape as the central galaxy. 
</P>
<P>
"Quite simply, the central galaxy is indistinguishable from the diffuse light 
that extends . . . from the cluster center," they said. "Thus, this object is 
among the largest and most luminous galaxies observed." 
</P>
<P>
The galaxy shines with 2 trillion times the light produced by <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sun and 
is elliptical in shape. About <PERCENT>26%</PERCENT> of the light given off by the galactic 
cluster is contributed by this one galaxy. 
</P>
<P>
"This is an organized mass of light and energy," <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said in a news release. 
"It's a very large, organized galaxy." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901026-0025 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-26-90 0205EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-LargestGalaxy     10-26 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Largest Galaxy,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>Largest Galaxy is 60 Times Size of Milky Way, Astronomers Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers reported today they have found the
largest galaxy ever discovered in a concentration of stars that
stretches for 6 million light years, or more than 60 times the size
of the Milky Way.
   A central galaxy in a distant cluster of galaxies called <ORGANIZATION>Abell
2029</ORGANIZATION> has more than 100 trillion stars, said a study published in
the journal Science. The Milky Way, which includes the sun and its
solar system, has about 3 billion stars.
   The stellar structure ``is the largest single galaxy that has
been resolved,'' said <PERSON>Jeffrey R. Kuhn</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State University</ORGANIZATION>
astronomer who coauthored the study.
   ``If we talk about the galaxy and the halo (diffused light
around the galaxy) as a single entity, then it is the largest
object that we are aware of,'' he said.
   Until this study, the largest known galaxy was <PERSON>Markarian</PERSON> 348,
which was identified in <DATE>1987</DATE>. It is 1.3 million light years in
diameter.
   <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> and his co-investigators, <PERSON>Juan M. Uson</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Radio Astronomy Observatory</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Stephen P. Boughn</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Haverford
College</ORGANIZATION>, determined the size of the galaxy using a series of
   Sixteen photos taken by the observatory's 36-inch telescope were
processed through a computer that removed from the view all of the
light from other sources. This enabled the scientists to precisely
measure the brightness and size of the galaxy, although individual
stars could not be resolved.
   Later, a second series of photos from <ORGANIZATION>Kitt Peak</ORGANIZATION> confirmed the
findings.
   <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Abell 2029</ORGANIZATION> cluster of galaxies is about a billion
light years away and includes about a thousand galaxies, each with
billions of stars.
   ``If you were to look up into the sky and could see this
cluster, they would occupy an area a little smaller than the
moon,'' he said. ``Of course, they are much fainter than the eye
can see.''
   A light year is 5.89 trillion miles, the distance that light can
travel in one year in a vacuum.
   The very large galaxy, classified by astronomers as a cD (for
central dominant), emits more than a quarter of all the light
radiated by the entire cluster.
   <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said that by analyzing the diffuse light by computer, the
group was able to determine that there was little stellar matter
between the cD galaxy and others in the <LOCATION>Abell</LOCATION> <DATE>2029</DATE> cluster. This
suggests, he said, that the cD galaxy and the cluster itself formed
about the same time.
   ``One of the theories about cD galaxies has been that they form
by collisions of galaxies,'' <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said. ``When galaxies collide,
stars in the smaller galaxies end up being stripped away and fall
into this giant galaxy in the middle.''
   But the cD galaxy in <DATE>Abell 2029</DATE>, he said, ``is much too large to
have been formed by stripping. It seems likely that it formed at
the same time that the cluster formed and it may have formed out of
remnant material that did not fall into the small galaxies.''
   Also, <PERSON>Kuhn</PERSON> said, if stripping was a factor in the formation of
the galaxy, there would still be clumps of debris giving off light
between the galaxies. But the observations detected only a smooth,
empty space.
   <PERSON>Richard Mushotzky</PERSON>, an astronomer at the <ORGANIZATION>Goddard Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>, said the work may help solve one of the underlying
mysteries in astronomy.
   ``We don't understand how clusters are built,'' <PERSON>Mushotzky</PERSON> said.
``If this (<ORGANIZATION>Abell</ORGANIZATION> 2029 study) can be verified, it could
substantially advance our understanding of how galaxies and
clusters are formed.''
   Science is the journal of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association for
Advancement of Science</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880323-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-88 0158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GalaxySurvey Bjt   03-23 0702</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galaxy Survey, Bjt,0720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Most Comprehensive Survey Of Milky Way Galaxy To Start Thursday</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The most detailed survey of the Milky Way
will start <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the world's most sensitive radio telescope,
an array of 27 dish-shaped antennas spread across <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>'s
desert.
   ``Without a doubt this will give us the most comprehensive
picture of our galaxy yet obtained in any kind of wavelength,''
including visible light and radio and infrared radiation, said
<PERSON>Robert H. Becker</PERSON>, associate professor of astronomy at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>.
   The <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>, two-year survey will be conducted by <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> and
astronomer <PERSON>David Helfand</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia University</ORGANIZATION>. They will use the
Very Large Array radio telescope, a set of 27 antenna dishes, each
about 80 feet in diameter, that move on 20 miles of tracks west of
Socorro, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>
   The telescope, which started operations in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, can
detect fainter radio signals than any other radio telescope, <PERSON>Becker</PERSON>
said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> during a telephone interview.
   More complete surveys of the heavens beyond our galaxy have been
conducted using powerful optical and infrared telescopes aimed to
look above or below the Milky Way's flattened disk.
   But such telescopes can't survey our own galaxy very well
because visible light is blocked by tremendous amounts of dust
between the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>'s stars and because the galaxy is so full of
infrared light sources that it's hard to distinguish various
objects, <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said.
   The survey will construct maps of the <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of the Milky
Way visible from the <LOCATION>Northern Hemisphere</LOCATION> by detecting objects that
emit radio waves, which penetrate the dust.
   Such objects include supernovas, or dying, exploding stars; vast
dust-and-gas clouds where new stars are born; and very dense
supernova remnants called neutron stars, pulsars and black holes.
   ``What this kind of survey can do is give you the overall
picture,'' <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said. ``Until you catalog the contents of your
own galaxy, you're never going to have a clear picture of what the
galaxy is.''
   The disk-shaped Milky Way contains an estimated 100 billion
stars clumped in spiraling arms that stretch across 100,000 light
years, or about 588,000 trillion miles, of space. Earth is located
roughly 22,000 light years, or 130,000 trillion miles, from the
galaxy's center.
   Becker said the survey undoubtedly will produce unexpected
discoveries, but also could help astronomers determine the
frequency and location of supernova explosions invisible to optical
telescopes.
   Shock waves from such explosions are thought to compress gas and
dust to create new stars.
   The survey will help determine if that theory is correct by
showing if there is a link between the location of supernovas and
regions of star formation, <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said.
   While some stars leave nothing behind after they explode as
supernovas, other supernovas collapse into dense neutron stars,
rotating neutron stars called pulsars or even more dense objects
called black holes, which have gravity so intense that not even
light escapes.
   Becker said the survey should help astronomers learn what
proportion of supernovas become neutron stars, pulsars or black
holes because such objects generate radio signals.
   While the survey won't detect life that might exist elsewhere in
the galaxy, it could help scientists improve estimates of the odds
that such life exists, <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said.
   ``If one wants to estimate the probability of finding
intelligent life elsewhere in our galaxy, you have to know what the
environment of our galaxy is,'' including the number of objects
that may be orbited by inhabited planets, he said.
   Recent improvements to the <ORGANIZATION>Very Large Array</ORGANIZATION> gave it a much
larger field of view, so ``it will take fewer pointings of the
telescope to map out the Milky Way,'' <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said.
   Becker and <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON> will have 300 hours of viewing time during
the survey. They then will spend another year or two using
computers to contruct maps using the detected radio signals.
   The first 20 to 24 hours of survey-related observations will
start <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and end <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, with more intermittent
observations regularly scheduled during the next two years each
time the antennas are re-aimed, <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said.
   The survey is financed by the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lawrence Livermore National
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0195 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 2223EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-FootballGalaxy 1stLd-Writethru   01-11 0743</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Football Galaxy, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0702,620</SECOND>
<NOTE>For Release at 6 p.m. EST _ Time set by source</NOTE>
<HEAD>Earth's Home Galaxy Has Football-Shaped Core, Experts Say</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS grafs 7-8: ``In other,'' with new ``attractor''
observations</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way Galaxy</ORGANIZATION>, home of the sun and the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, has a core shaped like a football instead of the perfectly
spherical center many astronomers have long believed, according to
a new study.
   Astronomers at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maryland</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Princeton
University</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the discovery of evidence that the
spiral arms of the Milky Way actually rotate around an oval center,
causing the sun to follow an elliptical path in its 200
million-year orbit of the galaxy center.
   <PERSON>Leo Blitz</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maryland</ORGANIZATION> said that the discovery
shows that the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION> is a so-called barred spiral galaxy. This
means that the spiral arms, composed of stars, gas and other
matter, flare out from a so-called bar structure of stars and gas
at the center. In a normal spiral galaxy, the arms curve out like
spokes from the very center.
   ``It has been something of a holy grail for astronomers to
determine if the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION> is a barred spiral or a normal spiral
galaxy,'' said <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON>. ``This study shows it is barred.''
   The Milky Way galaxy is disk-shaped with a large bulge in the
middle. Seen from above, arms flare out like curved spokes,
creating a spiral appearance. The galaxy has a diameter of about
100,000 light years and a thickness, seen from the edge, of about
4,000 light years.
   A light year is the distance light will travel in a year, about
6 trillion miles.
   In other galactic news, two other astronomers said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they
have confirmed that the Milky Way and about 100 other galaxies are
being pulled toward a powerful gravitational source called ``the
great attractor'' over a region of space 100 million light years
wide.
   The new findings, expanding on preliminary <DATE>1987</DATE> observations,
show galaxies on both sides of the ``attractor'' are swerving
toward it in addition to their normal motion away from each other,
said <PERSON>Alan Dressler</PERSON> of the Carnegia Instititon of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and
   The sun and its solar system, which includes the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, are
located in one spoke, about midway out from the galaxy center. That
spoke, along with the four other arms of the Milky Way, rotate
about the galaxy core. Though the rotation rate of the arm at the
sun's location is about 600,000 miles an hour, the galaxy is so
large that it takes about 200 million years to complete one
rotation, or orbit.
   Because the sun is away from the middle of the galaxy _ about
25,000 light years from the center _ the galaxy is seen edge-on
from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. This means that stars, clouds and dust obscures the
view of most of the Milky Way. And this has blocked astronomers
from being able to determine the shape of the galaxy center
directly.
   Blitz and <PERSON>David Spergel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION> overcame this problem by
examining the movement of hydrogen gas clouds in the outer regions
of the Milky Way, an area called the galactic halo that surrounds
the Milky Way like a globe.
   <PERSON>Spergel</PERSON> said the hydrogen movement was first studied about 15
years ago, but the motions were never well understood. He said the
new study, developed with the help of a computer, showed that
movement of the clouds, caused by gravitational influences, could
be explained only if there is an ellipsoidal center to the galaxy.
   ``The center is like a football,'' said <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON>. ``There is
absolutely no question about the data on this.''
   Since, according to the study, the sun and its solar system move
about the galaxy in an ellipse instead of a circle, the sun's
distance from the galactic center will change regularly over time.
Right now, <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON> and <PERSON>Spergel</PERSON> said the sun is about halfway between
its closest approach to the center and the farthest point of its
orbit.
   The sun will reach its outermost point from the galactic center
in 25 million years. That is about 1,500 light years farther away
than the point of closest approach to the center.
   ``It's not something we have to worry about,'' said <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON>.
   A paper on the study was given <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the 175th national
meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890829-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-89 2022EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-GalaxyBirth 1stLd-Writethru a0617 08-29 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galaxy Birth, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0617,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>Cloud Of Hydrogen May Be Forming Galaxy, Astronomers Say</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: SUBS word ``huge'' for ``massive'' in lede and 14th graf,
Most astronomers ...; DELETES word ``massive'' from overline. ^By PAUL
RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A huge disk of hydrogen gas discovered 65
million light years away suggests that galaxies are still being
formed in the universe, a finding that could modify the current
theory that star systems formed within a relatively short time after
the ``big bang.''
   <PERSON>Riccardo Giovanelli</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Radio Astronomy Group</ORGANIZATION> at the
and <PERSON>Martha Haynes</PERSON>, associate professor of astronomy at <ORGANIZATION>Cornell
University</ORGANIZATION>, found the gas cloud earlier this year using the
1,000-foot radiotelescope dish at <LOCATION>Arecibo</LOCATION>.
   Others astronomers said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that the findings were
``exciting'' and ``important'' and could reshape the current view of
the history of the universe.
   The cloud of hydrogen gas is 10 times larger in diameter than the
<ORGANIZATION>Milky Way Galaxy</ORGANIZATION>, which includes the sun, and appears to be in the
shape of a disk that is rotating slowly, the <ORGANIZATION>National Science
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> announced.
California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, said the gas cloud ``is a very important
discovery.''
   ``It shows that there are clouds of gas out there that have not
yet turned into galaxies,'' he said. Further study, said <PERSON>Heiles</PERSON>,
could lead to modifications of the basic ``big bang'' concept of the
universe.
   The ``big bang'' theory postulates that the universe began with a
cataclysmic explosion 10 billion to 20 billion years ago and that
galaxies of stars formed within a few hundred million years after
that. Astronomers have earlier reported findings that suggested star
formation within existing galaxies, and studies that indicated that
some galaxies may have formed billions of years later than others.
   But there have been no earlier reported findings of true
``proto-galaxies,'' or star systems at the very beginning of
formation. The general belief has been that such formation halted
billions of years ago.
   <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON> and <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> said they made the discovery through luck.
They were attempting to calibrate the radiotelescope by aiming it at
a part of the sky they thought was empty.
   ``Before stumbling into this thing, neither I nor <PERSON>Martha</PERSON> were
great believers in the existence of such objects,'' <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON> said
in a statement. ``But this cloud indicates that the disks of
galaxies can form slowly throughout the history of the universe and
not just be something that happened during some magic period of the
distant past.''
   Gas clouds have been discovered in the heavens, but those were
associated with existing galaxies.
   ``This cloud seems to have formed independently, in a pocket of
space isolated from other galaxies,'' said <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON>.
   No stars were found in the gas cloud.
   Most astronomers believe that galaxies form when hydrogen atoms
collect in
   huge clouds that are collapsed by gravity and that form clumps
that further gravitational collapse turn into stars.
   <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON> and <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> estimated the mass of the cloud at about a
tenth of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, which contains billions of stars.
   Heiles said the relatively small mass of the cloud presents no
problems to the theory that it is a proto-galaxy.
   ``There are lots of small galaxies out there, lots that are about
<PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> the size of our Milky Way,'' he said.
   <PERSON>James Rose</PERSON>, an associate professor of astromony at the <ORGANIZATION>University
of North Carolina</ORGANIZATION> who has studied young galaxies, called the new
finding ``very exciting.''
   ``This would be the first time that we could see a mass of gas
changing itself into a galaxy,'' he said. ``It offers the
opportunity to study the process in great detail.''
   Rose said that fact that the cloud is close to Earth by
astronomical standards, just 65 million light years away, will help
astronomers study it. A light year is a measure of distance used by
astronomers. It is the distance that light travels through a vacuum
in one year, about 5.7 trillion miles.
   Heiles said the next step now is to conduct a careful search for
other such clouds in the universe. He said astronomers may find that
there are many other such clouds, or forming galaxies.
   Presently, said <PERSON>Heiles</PERSON>, it is believed that vast areas of the
heavens are devoid of any matter. He said a survey might find that
many of those voids are not empty at all, but filled with hydrogen
clouds, or proto-galaxies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890829-0082 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890829 </DD>
<AN> 890829-0082. </AN>
<HL> Technology:
@  Team Says It Discovered Galaxy in Making
@  ---
@  Finding Contradicts Theory
@  All Galaxies Were Made
@  Many Billion Years Ago
@  ----
@  By Bob Davis
<DD> 08/29/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION> astronomers said they believe they have discovered a galaxy in the making, possibly undermining theories of the universe's evolution. 

   "We found a galaxy without stars," said <PERSON>Martha Haynes</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> astronomer who made the discovery on a giant radio telescope at <LOCATION>Arecibo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. 
"This galaxy is just getting ready" to become a profusion of stars. 
<PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> found the unborn galaxy along with <PERSON>Riccardo Giovanelli</PERSON>, another <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> astronomer. 

   Galaxies are clusters of billions of stars; the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the sun are part of the cluster known as the Milky Way. 
By the prevailing theories of the origin of the universe, galaxies started to form shortly after the <ORGANIZATION>Big Bang</ORGANIZATION>, a cataclysmic explosion of gases about 16 billion years ago that launched the universe, and they continued forming for about 10 billion years. 
So every galaxy should have been born billions of years ago. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> observations contradict this time theory. 
<PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> said she found the unborn galaxy -- a massive cloud of hydrogen gas 10 times larger than the Milky Way -- 65 million light years away. 
In astronomy, distance translates into time, so the cloud observed by <PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> actually corresponds to the cloud as it was 65 million years ago. 
Because these clouds take hundreds of millions, perhaps billions, of years to form stars, the cloud is now evolving into a galaxy. 

   "This is the first time a galaxy-sized thing has been caught in the act of forming," said <PERSON>James Gunn</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> astrophysicist familiar with the work, which was conducted in <DATE>March</DATE> but will be published in the <ORGANIZATION>Astrophysical Journal of Letters</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>November</DATE>. 
"This is the Rosetta stone of galaxy formation." 

   Galaxies form from the collapse of dust and hot gases, mostly hydrogen, under the weight of their own gravitation. 
<PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> theorized that this particular galaxy, which she calls simply "The Cloud," is taking so long to form because it's only slightly more dense than necessary for matter to collapse. 
"It's forming right now, under our noses," said <PERSON>Mr. Gunn</PERSON>. 

   <PERSON>K.Y. Lo</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Illinois</ORGANIZATION> astronomer, who also has searched for unborn galaxies, cautioned that the discovery needs to be confirmed. 
He said astronomers must make sure that the hydrogen cloud isn't leftover material associated with another galaxy, or that the cloud isn't inhabited by faint stars. 
"The evidence is tantalizing," he said. 
"But it might not be a proto-galaxy with pristine {hydrogen} gas." 

   <PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> attributed the discovery largely to luck. 
She said that she and her colleague, <PERSON>Mr. Giovanelli</PERSON>, were studying the galaxy UGC-7394, when they turned the radio telescope to what they thought was empty space to calibrate the instrument. 
To their surprise, they found the empty space emitted radio signals indicating a huge hydrogen cloud. 

   The radio signals "looked like they would if there was a galaxy there," <PERSON>Ms. Haynes</PERSON> said, "but there was nothing there." 
The hydrogen cloud, which isn't detectable by optical telescopes, is just south of the Virgo cluster -- the cluster of galaxies nearest the cluster containing <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gunn</PERSON> said he expected that the <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> finding would lead to the discovery of other unborn galaxies in different parts of the universe. 
After scientists have a number of hydrogen clouds to compare, he said, they should be able to learn more about what happened in the first sliver of a second after the <ORGANIZATION>Big Bang</ORGANIZATION>, when the primordial matter from which galaxies were formed exploded outward. 

   <PERSON>Jonathan Grindlay</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION>'s astronomy department, said the <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION> work might indicate what will happen at the end of time. 
Astronomers currently debate whether the universe will continue expanding forever or slow down and collapse into a cataclysmic Big Crunch. 
The existence of unexpected hydrogen clouds would indicate there's more mass than previously believed in space. 
"That goes in the direction that the universe will collapse," he said. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891213-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-13-89 1447EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-StarDiscovery 1stLd-Writethru a0497 12-13 0608</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Star Discovery, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0497,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Accidental Discovery of Distant Star Distends the Galaxy</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS two grafs of comment from Astronomical Society after
7th graf pvs, `We used ...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATTY REINERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers have spotted the most distant known
star in the <LOCATION>Milky Way</LOCATION>, and say the accidental discovery could help
determine the total mass of the galaxy.
   That includes mysterious invisible matter that astronomers know
exists but are unable to identify, an astronomer with the <ORGANIZATION>Space
Telescope Science Institute</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``Astronomers suspect that there is a lot of additional material
surrounding our galaxy that doesn't give off light,'' said <PERSON>Howard
Bond</PERSON>, who along with two others discovered the distant star last
<DATE>spring</DATE>.
   ``We don't know the mass of the Milky Way, but if we can find
objects that are far out and measure their speed, it will help us
determine the galaxy's total mass _ the visible areas and the dark
areas.''
   Astronomers use the speed of stars to determine gravitational
pull upon them, and from its gravity, the mass of the galaxy.
   Astronomers theorize the galaxy's dark matter could be dim stars
that are too faint to be seen, black hole remnants of massive stars
that exploded early in the galaxy's history or some unknown type of
subatomic particle, <PERSON>Bond</PERSON> said.
   ``We used to think that the majority of the mass of the Milky
Way was stars, but now we suspect stars may only be <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of
all the mass,'' he said. Once the mystery of the dark matter is
solved, he said, ``we may find something completely unexpected that
could revolutionize our thinking about physics.''
   <PERSON>Andrew Fraknoi</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION>
of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, said the discovery is important
because it is another confirmation that the Milky Way is much
larger than once thought.
   ``When you look at in a larger context that's what makes this so
exciting _ if they've really found something so distant that it is
way beyond where we thought the borders of the galaxy lay,'' he
said.
   The scientists stumbled upon the star while studying a distant
galaxy. The star is located 160,000 light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in the
direction of the constellation Virgo.
   The Milky Way was once thought to be only about 100,000 lights
year across. Since the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is about 30,000 light years from the
center of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, the discovery means the galaxy is larger
than even more recent estimates indicated.
   ``It was just dumb luck that this star was in the way of what
they were looking at. It was totally serendipitous,'' said <PERSON>Ray
Villard</PERSON>, a spokesman for the institute. ``It just shows that there
are a lot of wonderful surprises out there that we may stumble upon
when we're looking for something else.''
   The star is an isolated member of an immense but thinly
populated halo of old, faint stars surrounding the Milky Way. It
was spotted while astronomers <PERSON>Robin Ciardullo</PERSON> and <PERSON>George Jacoby</PERSON> of
surveying the giant elliptical galaxy M49, which is 50 million
light-years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Ciardullo, <PERSON>Jacoby</PERSON> and Bond have observed the star using
telescopes in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, and measurements of its
brightness have been made at the <ORGANIZATION>Cerro Tololo Interamerican
Observatory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION>.
   The star is a member of a well-known class of stars called the
RR Lyrae variables, <PERSON>Bond</PERSON> said. Because the brightness of those
stars already has been documented, astronomers can use the
brightness of the new star, known only as the ``Virgo variable,''
to measure its distance, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890829-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-89 1053EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-GalaxyBirth 1stLd-Writethru a0440 08-29 0422</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galaxy Birth, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0440,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Hydrogen Protogalaxy Found</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts new 3rd graf, The discovery, with Big Bang threory challenged</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION> says
astronomers believe they have stumbled across evidence that galaxies
may still be forming in the universe.
   The evidence is a massive cloud of hydrogen, 10 times larger than
the Milky Way galaxy, all by itself and close by astronomical
standards _ 65 million light-years away, the foundation said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The discovery would appear to challenge the current belief that
all galaxies were formed within the first few hundred million years
after the ``Big Bang'' explosion dispersed hydrogen and matter in
the universe.
   The hydrogen cloud was found by <PERSON>Riccardo Giovanelli</PERSON>, adjunct
professor of astronomy at <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University</ORGANIZATION> and head of the radio
astronomy group at the foundation's <ORGANIZATION>National Astronomy</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Ionosphere Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Arecibo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, and co-worker, <PERSON>Martha
Haynes</PERSON>, associate professor of astronomy at <ORGANIZATION>Cornell</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Before stumbling into this thing, neither I nor <PERSON>Martha</PERSON> were
great believers in the existence of such objects,'' <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON> said.
   ``But this cloud indicates that the discs of galaxies can form
slowly throughout the history of the universe and not just be
something that happened during some magic period in the distant
past.''
   <PERSON>Giovanelli</PERSON> and <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> found the cloud while calibrating detectors
attached to the 1,000-foot dish radio telescope at <LOCATION>Arecibo</LOCATION>. For
calibration, they pointed the dish at a region of the sky thought to
be devoid of objects _ and found the characteristic radio signal of
hydrogen.
   Astronomers believe galaxies, massive groupings of millions to
billions of stars, must form from the condensation of hydrogen, the
simplest element _ a proton accompanied by an electron.
   Previous searches for cloud ``protogalaxies'' had failed to find
anything, though there is strong evidence for the existence of
clouds of hydrogen.
   Light from quasars, incredibly bright objects 10 billion or so
light years away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, was missing frequencies characteristic
of what would be absorbed by hydrogen in its path.
   The cloud emits a strong radio signal, but there are no stars
associated with it, and it does not show up in optical surveys.
   Though 10 times larger than the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, it has only <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>
of the mass of that galaxy and it isn't clear whether the cloud will
evolve into a galaxy, the astronomers said.
   The cloud, south of the Virgo cluster, consists of two large
clumps of gas that may be merging, they said.
   A full report will appear in the <ORGANIZATION>Astrophysical Journal</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880808-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-08-88 1953EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GalaxySighted 1stLd-Writethru a0659 08-08 0442</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galaxy Sighted, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,440</SECOND>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs 1st graf to insert dropped word ``light'' and 8th graf,
``The red xxx to CORRECT years to miles.</NOTE>
<HEAD>Scientists Announce Discovery of Most Distant Galaxy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers on <DATE>Monday</DATE> announced the discovery
of the most distant galaxy known, a cluster of stars 15 billion
light years away that formed long before the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and the sun.
   ``This is very unusual and very rare,'' said <PERSON>Ken Chambers</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins University</ORGANIZATION>, one of the co-discovers. ``We're seeing
something from before the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> formed, possibly before our own
galaxy, and when the universe was very different than today.''
   The distant galaxy, known as 4C41.17, is far too faint to be
seen by the eye, but it emits a radio signal a billion times more
powerful than the sun's radio signal.
   ``It is one of the most powerful radio galaxies we know of,''
said <ORGANIZATION>Chambers</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though the galaxy was located by radio signals, its distance
from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> was established by analyzing the optical spectrum, or
type of light, put out by the galaxy.
   Chambers said the galaxy puts out a sharp optical signal of the
type characteristic of hydrogen and carbon. The wavelength of the
emission, however, is stretched by movement away from the observer.
   This stretch causes the light color to shift toward red, the
so-called ``red shift.'' By measuring this shift, the astronomers
could calculate the distance of the galaxy.
   A red shift of 3.8 found for 4C41.17 shows that it is about 15
billion light years away. A light year is the distance light
travels in a year, about 5.8 trillion miles.
   Chambers said at <MONEY>15 billion</MONEY> light years, the galaxy is about <PERCENT>90
percent</PERCENT> of the distance to what is thought to be the edge of the
universe. He said it also gives a view back in time and the galaxy
as seen now is only few billion years after the Big Bang, the
massive explosion that is thought to have started the universe
expanding outward.
   The galaxy is thought to be ``primitive,'' or in an early stage
of formation, <ORGANIZATION>Chambers</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``To be able to study the dynamics as it is forming will tell us
a lot of how galaxies are formed,'' he said.
   The Earth and sun are thought to have formed about 4.6 billion
years ago.
   The study of the distant galaxy was announced at the 20th
assembly of the <ORGANIZATION>International Astronomical Union</ORGANIZATION>. Chambers'
co-discovers were <PERSON>George Miley</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>
representative at the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope Science Institute</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>Wil
van Bruegel</PERSON>, an astronomer at the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900303-0147 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-03-90 0558EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-NewGalaxy     03-03 0418</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Galaxy,0430</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronomers Report Finding New Dwarf Galaxy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   British astronomers, searching for quasars in far
outer space, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> they believe they have stumbled across an
undiscovered galaxy ``in our back yard.''
   They said if their finding is confirmed, it is the first new
galaxy discovered in 35 years.
   <PERSON>Richard McMahon</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge University Institute of
Astronomy</ORGANIZATION> said he and colleague <PERSON>Michael Irwin</PERSON> discovered the very
dim, dwarf galaxy, two weeks ago. He said they are doublechecking
to make sure no one spotted it before.
   ``It's a bit like discovering a new planet; it's an exciting
discovery,'' <PERSON>McMahon</PERSON> said. ``We usually work in a more distant part
of the universe, and we pretty much assume that everything is
already known about the vicinity of the Milky Way'' _ the galaxy
around <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The scientists used a seven-ton, computerized laser machine that
scans detailed photographic plates of space.
   ``After the plates are scanned, the data are computerized to
look for more subtle variations,'' <PERSON>McMahon</PERSON> said. ``All the easy
galaxies have been found by the eye; the machine finds the harder
ones. The nearer ones are not so easy to see because the bright
background of the Milky Way blurs the picture.''
   The galaxy, named Sextans after the constellation where it was
found, is the smallest of the 10 satellite galaxies of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky
Way</ORGANIZATION>, the astronomers said in telephone interviews.
   The dwarf, spherical galaxy is 100,000 times fainter than the
Milky Way and cannot be seen without a powerful telescope, they
said.
   ``The sun is 30,000 light-years from the center of the Milky
Way, and this particular galaxy is a factor of 10 farther out. The
edge of the visible universe is about 15,000 million light-years
away, so this is basically in our back yard,'' <PERSON>Irwin</PERSON> said.
   A light-year is the distance that light travels in a vacuum in
one year.
   The scientists said they will follow up their finding with a
more detailed study of Sextans. They predicted that five or six
more galaxies would be found within the next three years.
   ``The odds are there won't be too many more found. If we find
them, fine; if we don't, it's all right, as long as we keep
churning out the unusual stuff,'' said <PERSON>Irwin</PERSON>, adding that he and
<PERSON>McMahon</PERSON> consider themselves specialists in quasars, not galaxies.
   Quasars are starlike objects that emit huge amounts of light.
They are thought to be the ancient traces of the exploding origins
of new galaxies.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890111-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-89 0316EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BlackHole Bjt   01-11 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Black Hole, Bjt,0598</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronomers Spot More Evidence Of Black Hole In Middle Of Milky Way</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The discovery of a river of gas flowing toward the
middle of the Milky Way supports the belief that an infinitely dense
speck more massive than 1 million suns lies at the heart of the
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s galaxy, astronomers say.
   The speck is known as a black hole, collapsed stars with such
intense gravitational pull that nothing can escape from it, not even
light. While many astronomers believe that a massive black hole
exists at the core of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>, this has still not been proven.
   In research presented <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, astronomers described their
discovery of a 90-trillion-mile-long stream of gas that apparently
is being sucked across the heavens into the black hole.
   Although black holes cannot be seen, astronomers look for other
evidence of their existence, such as the tug of their gravity on
nearby celestial objects.
   <PERSON>Paul Ho</PERSON>, who directed the research at the Harvard-Smithsonian
Center for Astrophysics in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, noted that the galaxy's center
is a gravitational well.
   ``We think that stars drift toward the center,'' he said. ``It's
a natural place for a massive black hole to form.''
   Ho's radio telescope observation was made with astronomers from
the <ORGANIZATION>Max Planck Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Cologne</ORGANIZATION>,
   The report was presented at a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION> here.
   ``This is a complex region,'' <PERSON>Bonnerd J. Teegarden</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s
``Results like these are adding a lot to our understanding.''
   <PERSON>Teegarden</PERSON> said that most astronomers believe that a massive black
hole exists at the center of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>.
   He noted that the nature of this and other black holes is one of
the most exciting areas of research and speculation in astronomy.
   ``It pushes hard on the basic concepts of physics,'' he said.
``Physicists don't really know what happens when you collapse a
million solar masses of matter down to a point. The laws of physics,
as we know them in the laboratory, are inadequate to explain such an
extreme situation.''
   Earlier, astronomers have spotted signs of a massive gaseous
cloud spinning around the Milky Way's center, which is 30,000 light
years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in the constellation Sagittarius. A light year is 6
trillion miles, the distance light travels in a year.
   Scientists believe the cloud is circling a black hole that is 1
million times more massive than the sun. They theorize that parts of
the cloud constantly fall into the black hole.
   Perhaps the equivalent of one-thousandth of the mass of the sun
spirals into the black hole each year. This produces tremendous
amounts of kinetic energy, the energy released by motion.
   ``These black holes could be the most powerful generators that we
know about,'' said Ho.
   Astronomers believe that black holes provide the energy of
quasars, enormously powerful radio emitters that are the most
distant objects in the universe.
   The latest discovery suggests that a stream of gas snakes across
space, providing the fuel that keeps the Milky Way's black hole
going.
   Ho believes that a recent stellar explosion, called a supernova,
knocked loose part of a large nearby island of gas. This, in turn,
was grabbed by the gravity of the black hole and pulled in a stream
into its own orbiting cloud.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06017109 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06017109 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO:  Some astronomers are delighted and awed by discoveries made by
the telescope, despite its fuzzy vision.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Despite a flaw that gives the Hubble Space Telescope a fuzzy view of the
heavens, some astronomers are delighted and awed by discoveries made by the
$1.5 billion craft.;    Researchers said Wednesday that instruments on the
Hubble have found what may be the most massive star ever analyzed, taken the
first step toward a precise measure of the universe and found a large star
that may be about to explode.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FLAWED HUBBLE STILL PRODUCING
TELESCOPE SPOTS MASSIVE STAR, STARTS MEASURE
OF UNIVERSE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     But scientists at the <ORGANIZATION>American Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION> meeting here said the
Hubble must be repaired to get its full scientific value. One researcher said
about <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of his studies had been canceled because of the telescope's
problems.;    <ORGANIZATION>Hubble</ORGANIZATION> was launched in <DATE>April</DATE> and engineers later discovered that
a mirror on the telescope was ground to the wrong prescription, giving a
slightly out-of-focus view.;    The flaw, however, has little effect on a
Hubble instrument called the high resolution spectrograph. And <PERSON>Sally Heap</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> astronomer, said the instrument has studied the most massive star ever
measured precisely.;    <PERSON>Heap</PERSON> said the star, called <PERSON>Melnick</PERSON> 42, is about 100
times larger than the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sun and shines about a million times brighter.; 
  Every 100,000 years, she said, <PERSON>Melnick</PERSON> 42 boils away gas with a mass equal
to the sun, creating a "stellar wind" that moves away at more than 6 million
miles an hour.;    <PERSON>Melnick</PERSON> 42 is in a galaxy about 170,000 light-years from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. A light-year is about 5.8 trillion miles.;    "We couldn't have made
these measurements without the Hubble," Heap said.;    She said the space
telescope's spectrograph will be used to survey stars in a number of galaxies
to learn how stars form in different parts of the heavens.;    "Stars in other
galaxies may form in different ways because the chemistry of the galaxies is
different," she said. "It is like sampling from different cultures.";    <ORGANIZATION>Nino
Panagia of the Space Telescope Science Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> said the
Hubble's faint object camera had been able to make the most accurate
measurements of the distance between the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and a star outside the Milky
Way galaxy.;    <ORGANIZATION>Panagia</ORGANIZATION> said that by measuring light from different parts of a
ring that has formed around an exploded star called supernova 1987A, he has
been able to determine the distance from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> at 169,000 light-years. That's
twice as accurate as measurements taken from ground instruments, he said.;   
The work, he said, is the first step toward determining precisely the scale of
the universe. The study will be used to calibrate other measurements taken on
stars deeper and deeper into the universe, <LOCATION>Panagia</LOCATION> said.;    <PERSON>Jeff Hester</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Hubble</ORGANIZATION>'s wide-field camera had
been used to make unprecedented photos of a star called <LOCATION>Eta Carina</LOCATION> that may be
on the brink of exploding.;    Images collected from the star were processed
through a computer to remove <ORGANIZATION>Hubble</ORGANIZATION>'s focusing flaw, and clearly shows it's
spewing material and is surrounded by a halo-like cloud structure.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Philadelphia  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910117  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  514  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday January 17, 1991
00017109,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891120-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-20-89 1227EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-FarthestObject 1stLd-Writethru a0467 11-20 0720</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farthest Object, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0467,0734</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quasar, Most Distant Object, May Light up Creation's Building Blocks</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 14th-15th grafs, bgng `Advocates of...', to CORRECT 14th
graf quote attribution to Schneider sted Bahcall. Picks up 16th graf pvs,
`Because of...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists say they've spotted the
farthest and oldest object ever seen, a quasar that gives a peek of
the universe near the beginning of time and challenges a popular
theory of how stars developed.
   The star-like body, about 14 billion light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,
possibly has illuminated like a flashlight in the fog the matter
that spawned everything from galaxies to life itself, according to
scientists.
   ``Astronomers have looked for more than 20 years for this
primordial stuff of which galaxies, stars and then us were
formed,'' said astrophysicist <PERSON>John Bahcall</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for
Advanced Study</ORGANIZATION>. ``One possible interpretation is that it's been
found.''
   The object was seen through the 200-inch <PERSON>Hale Telescope</PERSON> at
<ORGANIZATION>Palomar Observatory</ORGANIZATION>, northeast of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. The quasar is in the
constellation Ursa Major just below the <ORGANIZATION>Big Dipper</ORGANIZATION>'s bowl.
   ``We've found the most distant object on record,'' said
astronomer <PERSON>Maarten Schmidt</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of
Technology</ORGANIZATION>. ``We are now seeing an object as it was a little over <MONEY>1
billion</MONEY> years after the beginning of the universe.''
   Schmidt and astronomers <PERSON>James Gunn</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Donald Schneider</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Advanced Study</ORGANIZATION>, an
independent research center in <LOCATION>Princeton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, report the
discovery in <DATE>December</DATE>'s Astronomical Journal. The find was to be
formally announced today.
   Quasars, as large as our solar system, are the brightest objects
in the universe. The brightest emits more light than 1,000 galaxies
of 100 billion stars each.
   Astronomers believe quasars form near black holes in the centers
of galaxies. Black holes are so massive their gravity sucks in even
light. But as matter is pulled in, intense bursts of light also are
emitted.
   Scientists say a gigantic explosion, the ``Big Bang,'' created
the universe 10 billion to 20 billion years ago. They usually cite
15 billion years as the universe's age.
   On that scale, the newly discovered quasar formed at least 14
billion years ago, meaning its distance from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is 14 billion
light years, or 82 trillion billion miles. One light year equals
5.88 trillion miles, the distance light travels in one year.
   If the universe is 20 billion years old, <PERSON>Schmidt</PERSON> said the quasar
would be about 18.5 billion light years away, or 109 trillion
billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The discovery is ``striking, unexpected and very significant''
because it suggests the first galaxies and stars developed much
faster than can be explained by what is known as the ``cold, dark
matter'' theory, said <PERSON>Bahcall</PERSON>.
   The theory says that ``cold, dark matter,'' or hydrogen gas,
clumped together because of gravity to form stars and galaxies over
several billion years, not merely 1 billion years, <PERSON>Bahcall</PERSON> said
during a phone interview.
   <PERSON>Schneider</PERSON> said advocates of the theory may ``have to come up
with (new) theories that make galaxies faster.''
   Alternatively, light from the quasar may be partially blocked by
clouds of gas, but not primordial gas, which was uniformly
distributed in the young universe, <PERSON>Bahcall</PERSON> said.
   Because the age of the universe is uncertain, scientists measure
a quasar's absolute age and distance using a property called ``red
shift.''
   Just as a train whistle seems to shift to a lower pitch as a
train moves away from a listener, light from distant quasars shifts
toward the color red as they move away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> while the
universe expands.
   The newly found quasar has a red shift of 4.73, making it <PERCENT>7
percent</PERCENT> older and more distant than the previous record holder, a
quasar with a red shift of 4.43 whose discovery was announced in
<DATE>December 1987</DATE> by scientists in <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   The quasar is so distant that its light is 400,000 times too
faint to be seen by eye.
   Schmidt devised the idea of using the <ORGANIZATION>Hale Telescope</ORGANIZATION> to search
for distant quasars. Gunn built an extremely sensitive electronic
camera that made the search possible, while <PERSON>Schneider</PERSON> designed a
computer program that recognized the distinguished quasars from
hundreds of thousands of other objects.
   ``It's a fantastic technical achievement, a tour de force,''
<PERSON>Bahcall</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880213-0165 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-88 2027EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-MilkyWay 1stLd-Writethru a0608 02-13 0609</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Milky Way, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0608,0623</SECOND>
<HEAD>Milky Way Has Scalloped Edge</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, `Beyond that...', to CORRECT that invisible
mass is 90 percent of mass of galaxy, sted universe. Picks up 12th
graf pvs, `It could...'.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RAEBURN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Editor</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The disk-shaped Milky Way galaxy is not flat, but
resembles instead a warped phonograph record and is adorned with a
delicate, scalloped edge, new observations show.
   ``The scalloping is something we don't understand,'' <PERSON>Leo Blitz</PERSON>,
an astronomer at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maryland</ORGANIZATION>, said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
the <ORGANIZATION>Advancement of Science</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON> said, ``Our picture of the galaxy
has changed significantly in the last five to 10 years.''
   The Milky Way, once considered merely a typical example of a
spiral galaxy, is now thought to be a much more exciting and
interesting aggregation. Among the recent findings reported
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> were:
   _ <PERCENT>Ninety percent</PERCENT> of the galaxy is invisible, and nobody knows
what this huge ``dark halo'' is made of.
   _ The galaxy is powered by two compact objects at its center
that might be the remnants of starburst formation or that could be
associated with a black hole.
   _ The galaxy's dark halo could be full of remnants of the big
bang called weakly interactive massive particles _ or WIMPs.
   The galaxy consists of a slim star-studded disk about 100,000
light-years across, <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON> said. (A light year is about 6 trillion
miles.)
   Surrounding that visible disk is a cloud of hydrogen gas
extending another 25,000 light-years.
   It is at the edge of that gaseous disk that radio astronomers
have found warping and scalloping, <PERSON>Blitz</PERSON> said.
   Beyond that lies <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the mass of the galaxy. It is
invisible, and astronomers don't know what it is, said <ORGANIZATION>Martin Rees
of Cambridge University</ORGANIZATION>.
   It could be made of a trillion very small, faint stars, each
one-tenth the size of the sun. Another possibility is that it is
composed of black holes, the remnants of massive stars.
   Or it could be made of WIMPs, an explanation that <PERSON>Rees</PERSON> said is
more radical than the others.
   ``What we want to do is narrow down the possibilities,'' <PERSON>Rees</PERSON>
said. ``What we see is a trace of sediment in a universe where
galaxies in a cosmic sea are dominated by this missing matter.''
   The galaxy's oddities are not limited to its outer edges,
however. ``The inner <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of our galaxy seems to be unique,''
said <PERSON>Leonid Ozernoy</PERSON> of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for
Astrophysics in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> ``The star density is huge there.''
   It is also a powerful source of radiation, emitting infrared,
X-rays and gamma rays, <PERSON>Ozernoy</PERSON> said.
   A black hole could lie at the center of the galaxy, driving its
rotation. Such a black hole ``could be the remnant of starburst
formation,'' <PERSON>Ozernoy</PERSON> said.
   Observations yet to be made could resolve some of the puzzles
that remain, <PERSON>Rees</PERSON> said.
   It might be possible, he said, to use gravitational lenses _
areas in space in which gravity bends light in the same way that a
magnifying glass does _ to see small, faint stars in the dark halo,
if they exist.
   Experiments are being planned in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> to
try to identify the WIMPs, if they exist, <PERSON>Rees</PERSON> said.
   The problem of missing mass is one that extends across the
entire universe, not only in the <LOCATION>Milky Way</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rees</PERSON> said, and the
discovery of new particles in this invisible matter would have a
payoff ``so colossal that the modest investment in such experiments
seems more than justified,'' <PERSON>Rees</PERSON> said in his prepared remarks.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061490-0072 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 233331 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 14, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
746 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENCE / ASTRONOMY; 
</P>
<P>
'BLOBS' SUGGEST A BLACK HOLE AT CENTER OF GALAXY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ALBUQUERQUE 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Giant "blobs" of material have been discovered around a mysterious object near 
the center of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way Galaxy</ORGANIZATION>, leading scientists to believe they may be 
getting their best look yet at one of the most baffling objects in the universe 
-- a black hole. 
</P>
<P>
It isn't possible to actually see a black hole, and no one has been able to 
prove that they exist, because a black hole would be so dense that even light 
would not escape its gravity. 
</P>
<P>
But black holes exist in theory -- and probably in fact -- as part of the 
legacy of <PERSON>Albert Einstein</PERSON>. Despite years of searching, they remain the most 
elusive trophies in the astronomical zoo. 
</P>
<P>
But armed with increasingly powerful tools, including giant radio telescopes, 
scientists believe that they are getting closer to proving that black holes do 
exist, even if they cannot be seen. 
</P>
<P>
The search consists mainly of looking for evidence of the kind of violent 
activity that should take place in a black hole's immediate neighborhood. 
Theoretically, as the black hole captures material within its gravitational 
reach, atoms and molecules literally should be ripped apart, sending out 
various types of radiation that can be studied from as far away as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, scientists told the <ORGANIZATION>American Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION> meeting here that 
they believe that they have identified a series of giant "blobs" -- most likely 
clouds of hot, charged gas particles -- around an object known as Sagittarius 
A, which had been discovered previously by an infrared telescope. 
</P>
<P>
The "blobs," they said, were probably created when matter was ripped apart as 
it plunged toward the black hole. Each of the giant blobs measures nearly a 
trillion miles in diameter. 
</P>
<P>
They hope that additional study will unmask Sagittarius A and prove it to be 
the long-sought but never seen black hole that scientists suspect lurks at the 
heart of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way Galaxy</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The research is being carried out by <ORGANIZATION>Farhad Yusef-Zadeh of Northwestern 
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Evanston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mark Morris</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Ron Ekers</PERSON> of the 
Australian Telescope. Their main tool in the search for the black hole is the 
Very Large Array, a series of large radio telescopes in the <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> desert. 
</P>
<P>
"This is the first time we have seen these blobs," Yusef-Zadeh said. 
</P>
<P>
Yusef-Zadeh said he cannot tell yet if the blobs are being pulled toward 
Sagittarius A or blown away by hot gases similar to the solar wind. But he is 
confident that the research he presented <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> goes a long way toward 
proving that a black hole does lie at the center of any galaxy, and in our own 
Milky Way, the most likely candidate is Sagittarius A. 
</P>
<P>
One problem that has been particularly vexing for astronomers is that the 
central area of the galaxy is so clouded with dust and gas that it is not 
possible to see objects near the galactic center. Thus observations are limited 
primarily to radiation that can pass through the dusty shield, such as radio 
waves and X-rays. 
</P>
<P>
So for the last few years, scientists have used giant radio telescopes to study 
the galactic center, and their search for the black hole has been generally 
narrowed to two objects. One is a tight cluster of stars, called <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> 16, and 
the other is Sagittarius A. 
</P>
<P>
Yusef-Zadeh presented evidence <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that he said strongly supports 
Sagittarius as the prime candidate. 
</P>
<P>
The most compelling evidence in addition to the blobs, he said, is a cloud of 
dust and gas that surrounds a nearby star, called <ORGANIZATION>IRS</ORGANIZATION> 7. "'Radiographs," which 
are similar to photographs, produced by the scientists show that the cloud of 
dust is being swept past the star much the same as the tail of a comet is 
pushed back by the solar wind. 
</P>
<P>
The cloud is pointing directly away from Sagittarius A, just as the tail of a 
comet points away from the sun. That indicates that powerful interstellar winds 
-- such as those expected to be produced by a very energetic object such as a 
black hole -- are in fact coming from Sagittarius A. That clearly suggests that 
<PERSON>Sagittarius</PERSON> is the black hole that scientists have been looking for, 
Yusef-Zadeh said. 
</P>
<P>
The scientists, who are at the forefront in the search for a black hole at the 
center of the Milky Way, have been alloted time on an even larger radio 
telescope, called the <ORGANIZATION>Very Large Baseline Array</ORGANIZATION>, which is under construction in 
<LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>. Yusef-Zadeh said he hopes that powerful instrument, which actually 
will consist of many telescopes linked together so that they will act as one, 
will finally resolve the issue. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ASTRONOMY; MYSTERIES; MILKY WAY (GALAXY); SPACE EXPLORATION; BLACK HOLES; 
RESEARCH; TELESCOPES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890110-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-10-89 1831EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BlackHole 1stLd-Writethru a0626 01-10 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Black Hole, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0626,0561</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronomers Spot Gas Stream Feeding Milky Way's Black Hole</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 4th graf to CORRECT from David to Paul.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 90 trillion-mile-long stream of gas is flowing
toward the center of the Milky Way, perhaps fueling a massive black
hole at the very heart of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s galaxy, astronomers reported
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Researchers said their discovery is the first evidence of a thin
river of gas being sucked across the heavens by the awesome gravity
of a black hole.
   The radio telescope observation, made by an international team,
provides new support for the still-controversial idea that a massive
black hole exists at the center of the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``That is the gravitational well of the galaxy. We think that
stars drift toward the center. It's a natural place for a massive
black hole to form,'' said <PERSON>Paul Ho</PERSON>, who directed the research at the
reported the results <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at a meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   A black hole is what remains when stars collapse upon themselves,
leaving only a speck of infinite density. Their gravitational pull
is so strong that nothing escapes, not even light.
   Even though black holes cannot be seen, astronomers look for
other evidence of their existence, such as the gravitational tug on
nearby celestial orbs.
   Ho's discovery, made with astronomers from the <ORGANIZATION>Max Planck
Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>University of Cologne</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, and
evidence in the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s galaxy.
   Astronomers had earlier spotted signs of a massive gaseous cloud
around the Milky Way's center, which is about 30,000 light years
from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in the constellation Sagittarius. A light year is 6
trillion miles, the distance light travels in a year.
   Experts believe that this cloud is swirling around a black hole
that is 1 million times more massive than the sun. They theorize
that parts of the cloud constantly tumble into the black hole.
   Perhaps the equivalent of one-thousandth of the mass of the sun
is drawn into the black hole each year. This produces tremendous
amounts of kinetic energy, the energy released by motion.
   ``These black holes could be the most powerful generators that we
know about,'' said Ho.
   The latest discovery suggests that a stream of gas snakes across
space, providing the fuel that keeps the Milky Way's black hole
going. Ho believes that recent stellar explosion knocked loose part
of a large island of gas. This, in turn, was grabbed by the gravity
of the black hole and pulled in a stream into its own orbiting cloud.
   ``This is a complex region,'' said <PERSON>Bonnerd J. Teegarden</PERSON> of the
are adding a lot to our understanding.''
   <PERSON>Teegarden</PERSON> said that most, but not all, astronomers believe that a
massive black hole exists at the <ORGANIZATION>Milky Way</ORGANIZATION>'s center.
   The nature of black holes ``pushes hard on the basic concepts of
physics,'' he said. ``Physicists don't really know what happens when
you collapse a million solar masses of matter down to a point. The
laws of physics, as we know them in the laboratory, are inadequate
to explain such an extreme situation.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900112-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-12-90 2056EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-X-RaySource     01-12 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-X-Ray Source,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Say X-rays Stream From Galaxy Neighbors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ARLINGTON, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The violence of early star formation in
new galaxies may be a major source of cosmic X-rays, a mysterious
radiation that has puzzled astronomers for decades, two <ORGANIZATION>Columbia
University</ORGANIZATION> scientists said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Astrophysicists <PERSON>David Helfand</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thomas Hamilton</PERSON> said they have
found seven galaxies reasonably near the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s own Milky Way
galaxy that are spewing out X-rays at a hotter rate than the
so-called background X-rays detectable all over the universe.
   Though they only found seven such galaxies, the scientists said
that further searches may reveal many more, showing perhaps that
such galaxies provide a high percentage of the cosmic X-rays in the
universe.
   ``These galaxies are representative of a larger population at a
greater distance that makes up (or emits) the bulk of the X-ray
background,'' said <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON>. ``These that we see are only the
nearest neighbors.''
   The galaxies are called ``neighbors,'' said <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON>, because
``they are relatively nearby, only a couple of billion light
years'' away.
   This is considered close, astronomically.
   A light year is the distance that light travels in space in a
year, about 6 trillion miles.
   The discovery of X-ray emitting galaxies so close and seemingly
undergoing star formation, <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON> said, suggests that in the
history of the universe star formation continued up until
relatively recently. Most astronomers believe that star formation
took place in the early part of the 15 to 20 billion-year-old
universe and then tailed off.
   ``These galaxies may be bright X-ray sources because they are
undergoing an early stage of their evolution and still forming
massive stars,'' said <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON>. ``They may be a key link in being
able to study the evolution of galaxies.''
   X-rays are thought to be generated naturally in the universe
when interstellar gas is heated to millions of degrees. Such
heating can occur during the course of star formation when vast
amounts of matter are attracted to a core by gravitational force.
Black holes, bodies massive enough to create a gravitational field
that keeps even light from escaping, can also generate X-rays by
pulling material from nearby stars, <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON> said.
   X-rays cannot be detected on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, which is shielded by the
atmosphere. But satellites orbiting above the atmosphere can
measure the radiation.
   To find the X-ray emitters, <PERSON>Helfand</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> gathered data
on 100 faint radio sources in a region of the sky about the size of
the full moon. These sources were then checked to see if they
coincided with X-ray hot spots that had been discovered by
satellites. Seven of the radio emitters were found to be bright in
X-rays, and these later were found by optical telescopes to be very
faint galaxies.
   Helfand and <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> presented their study at the 175th national
meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American Astronomical Society</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880809-0072 </DOCNO>
<HL> Astronomers Discover Galaxy Near Visible Limits of Universe </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> BALTIMORE (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers have discovered a galaxy 15 billion light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, one of the most distant galaxies ever seen, it was announced today by the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope Science Institute</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The galaxy, named 4C41.17, was discovered by scientists using a new search strategy. 
It was located because of the enormous power and peculiar spectrum of its radio emissions. 

   The galaxy is more than <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of the distance to the visible limits of the universe, the announcement said. 

   The discovery was made by <PERSON>Ken Chambers</PERSON>, a graduate student at <ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins University</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>George Miley</PERSON>, astronomy professor at <ORGANIZATION>Leiden University</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> who was stationed at the telescope science institute in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>. 
They made their observations with <PERSON>Wil van Breugel</PERSON>, an astronomer at the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>. 

   Extremely distant galaxies are of great interest to astronomers. 
Because light from them takes billions of years to reach the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, remote galaxies can be used to provide data about the early stages of the universe. 
The record distance of the new galaxy means it is being seen only about a few billion years after the big bang, which many scientists believe marked the beginning of the observable universe. 

   The announcement was made in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>General Assembly of the International Astronomical Union</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880808-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-08-88 1334EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-GalaxySighted     08-08 0231</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galaxy Sighted,0234</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Announce Discovery of Distant Galaxy</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers have discovered a galaxy 15 billion
light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, one of the most distant galaxies ever seen,
it was announced today by the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope Science Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   The galaxy, named 4C41.17, was discovered by scientists using a
new search strategy they developed. It was located because of the
enormous power and peculiar spectrum of its radio emissions.
   The galaxy is more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the distance to the
visible limits of the universe, the announcement said.
   The discovery was made by <PERSON>Ken Chambers</PERSON>, a graduate student at
<ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins University</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>George Miley</PERSON>, professor of astronomy
at <ORGANIZATION>Leiden University</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, who was stationed at the
telescope science institute in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>European Space
Agency</ORGANIZATION>. They made their observations with <PERSON>Wil van Breugel</PERSON>, an
astronomer at the <ORGANIZATION>University of California-Berkeley</ORGANIZATION>.
   Extremely distant galaxies are of great interest to astronomers.
Because light from them takes billions of years to reach the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,
remote galaxies can be used to provide data about the early stages
of the universe. The record distance of the new galaxy means it is
being seen only about a few billion years after the Big Bang, which
scientists believe marked the beginning of the observable universe.
   The announcement was made in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>General Assembly
of the International Astronomical Union</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 2117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-CrowdedGalaxy     08-29 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Crowded Galaxy,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hubble Telescope Spots Galaxy That May Have Black Hole</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Tod in 6th graf is cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A photo taken by the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION>
shows a galaxy seen only as fuzzy ball by telescopes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is
actually so tightly packed with stars that it may harbor a black
hole at its center, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The picture, which an official said was taken ``to prove to the
public that the Hubble is not broken,'' shows a galaxy 400 times
more tightly packed with stars than the sun's own Milky Way galaxy.
   Scientists said the Hubble photo captured more detail of the
galaxy than is possible by Earthbound telescopes and was thus able
to determine that the stellar group had many more stars than
expected.
   The picture was taken by the wide field-planetary camera on
Hubble, one of the instruments officials said was seriously
affected by a focusing flaw manufactured into the telescope but not
discovered until after it was launched.
   Officials also released a photo taken with another Hubble camera
that shows a ring of matter encircling a supernova, a star that
exploded in the southern sky in <DATE>1987</DATE>. The ring of material had not
been spotted before by telescopes on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Tod R. Lauer</PERSON>, an astronomer with the <ORGANIZATION>National Optical Astronomy
Observatories</ORGANIZATION>, said the compact galaxy of stars discovered by the
Hubble ``is vastly denser than we expected this galaxy to be.''
   He said ground-based photos of the galaxy showed a smooth blob
of light and gave no suggestion that it contained so many stars.
   ``We've never been able to study any galaxy outside of our local
group (two dozen galaxies near the Milky Way) at this resolution
before,'' <PERSON>Lauer</PERSON> said.
   The galaxy, called NGC7457, is 40 million light years away and
contains about 30,000 stars within an area of only about nine light
years.
   Hubble chief scientist <PERSON>Ed Weiler</PERSON> said that one explanation for
such a dense galaxy would be the presence of a black hole.
   ``We're not claiming that this is a black hole,'' he said at a
news conference. ``It is not inconsistent with a black hole,
however.''
   Astronomy theory holds that a black hole can be formed when
stellar matter collects in such a mass of such density and of such
a high gravitational force that even light cannot escape.
   There have been no confirmed black holes found in the universe,
but <PERSON>Weiler</PERSON> said that if one existed it might take on the appearance
of the galaxy photographed by the Hubble.
   <PERSON>Weiler</PERSON> said the galaxy will be further studied by Hubble
instruments to determine if it does contain a black hole.
   The other photo released showed a glowing ring encircling
supernova 1987A, an exploded star 160,000 light years from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The picture was taken by <ORGANIZATION>Hubble</ORGANIZATION>'s faint object camera, an
instrument made the <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION> for the space telescope.
   Nino <LOCATION>Panagia</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>ESA</ORGANIZATION> scientist, said the photo shows that matter
ejected from the star years before its explosion was compacted and
then set aglow by the burst of light when the star blew up. He said
the ring will be blow apart within a few years when the blast wave
from the exploding collides with the material in the ring.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> took the pictures as part of a campaign to demonstrate that
the Hubble is a valuable telescope even though it has flawed optics.
   <PERSON>Eric Chaisson</PERSON>, educational director of the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope
Science Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, said he wrote memos in recent weeks
calling for a campaign to change the perception of the public and
of the science community about the problems with Hubble.
   In a memo obtained by the <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>) <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Chaisson</PERSON> said action should be taken to change the public image of
the <MONEY>$1.6 billion</MONEY> observatory.
   ``Unless a dramatic campaign is mounted to share with the
American public the technical truth with a positive spin,''
<PERSON>Chaisson</PERSON> wrote, ``then we should prepare ourselves for an endless
stream of newspaper cartoons, late-night TV talk-show jokes and
blistering post-mortems by columnists the world over.''
   He added: ``We shall continue to see an erosion of public
support for <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s ambitious space program.''
   Reached by telephone, <PERSON>Chaisson</PERSON> confirmed that he had written
such a memo, noting that the pictures of the galaxy and supernova
were taken in part because of his efforts.
   ``We needed some science to prove to the public that Hubble is
not broken,'' he said. ``I don't apologize for it. What I was
trying to do (with the memo) was to jerk the system around so it
would do a little science.''
   Since Hubble has been launched, it has been in a shakedown
operation designed to test it capabilities. Since the focusing flaw
was found, engineers have been operating the Hubble to find out the
precise nature of the malfunction.
   <PERSON>Chaisson</PERSON> said his memo helped persuade <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to interrupt the
engineering checkout and take some pictures of scientific value.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111789-0151 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 136283 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 17, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 33; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
622 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STRUCTURE IS LARGEST YET SEEN IN UNIVERSE; 
</P>
<P>
ASTRONOMY: A NEWLY DISCOVERED SHEET OF GALAXIES STRETCHES FOR 500 MILLION 
LIGHT-YEARS. HARVARD SCIENTISTS CALL THEIR DISCOVERY THE GREAT WALL. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, TIMES SCIENCE WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Scientists have discovered the largest structure seen so far in the universe, a 
narrow sheet of galaxies stretching more than half a billion light years across 
space. 
</P>
<P>
The scientists, who have pioneered in the effort to determine the large-scale 
structure of the universe by creating three-dimensional images of space, have 
called their discovery the Great Wall. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Margaret Geller</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Huchra</PERSON> of the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for 
Astrophysics in <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> said the string of galaxies is 500 million 
light-years long, 200 million light-years wide, and about 15 million 
light-years thick. (A light-year is the distance light travels in a year, about 
6 trillion miles.) They reported their discovery in today's issue of the 
journal Science. 
</P>
<P>
The Great Wall is more than 200 million light-years away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, and it 
cannot be seen with the unaided eye. In fact, it does not even show up in 
normal astronomical photographs because it is revealed only through a 
three-dimensional effect. 
</P>
<P>
Geller and <PERSON>Huchra</PERSON> are engaged in an ambitious research project that has 
revolutionized the thinking on the shape of outer space. By measuring the 
distance between <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 10,000 galaxies in a pie-shaped wedge of the 
northern celestial hemisphere, they have been able to plot the galaxies with a 
computer and they have produced some startling results. 
</P>
<P>
Four years ago they announced that their first three-dimensional image revealed 
that the universe is structured around giant voids that look somewhat like soap 
bubbles in a dishpan. Galaxies are strung along the skin of the "bubbles," and 
scientists have debated fiercely over how the bubbles could have been created. 
</P>
<P>
Some of the bubbles are huge, measuring 150 million light-years in diameter. 
That is so big that scientists are at a loss to explain how the matter that 
makes up galaxies could have been swept clear of such a large area in the 10 to 
20 billion years since the universe was born. 
</P>
<P>
Early explanations, including the suggestion that massive explosions sent 
matter flying out from the center of the voids to create the bubble effect, 
have not gained acceptance because scientists cannot explain how matter could 
have traveled far enough to create the giant voids in the lifetime of the 
universe. 
</P>
<P>
Today's announcement only adds to the mystery and was described by the two 
scientists as "one of the most sobering results" of their research. 
</P>
<P>
It may well be that there are even much larger structures waiting to be 
discovered, further complicating the lives of cosmologists who are already 
struggling to explain why the universe should have enormous areas that are 
devoid of galaxies. 
</P>
<P>
"The size of the largest structures we detect is limited only by the extent of 
the survey," <PERSON>Geller</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Although earlier attempts to determine the structure of the universe suggested 
in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> that space had some areas that were devoid of galaxies, <PERSON>Geller</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Huchra</PERSON> were the first to carry the surveys far enough into space to see the 
large-scale structures, including the bubbles and the Great Wall. 
</P>
<P>
They have used the 60-inch telescope at the <ORGANIZATION>Smithsonian</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Whipple Observatory</ORGANIZATION> 
on <LOCATION>Mt. Hopkins</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, to measure the "red shift" of galaxies in a pie-shaped 
"slice of the universe." As a galaxy speeds away from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, the light it 
emits is shifted to the red end of the electromagnetic spectrum. By measuring 
the red shift, the scientists are able to determine the distance to the 
galaxies. 
</P>
<P>
The first results suggested that voids were present. Subsequent surveys, 
looking twice as far into space as previous efforts, revealed that the patterns 
continued farther out. 
</P>
<P>
The Great Wall became a distinct structure as the scientists finished their 
fourth "slice of the universe." 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNIVERSE; GALAXIES; ASTRONOMY; SPACE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900425-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-90 0115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Gee-WhizTelescope Bjt   04-25 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gee-Whiz Telescope, Bjt,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Telescope Opening a Window on the Beginning of Time</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Already they're saying it's the
biggest happening in astronomy since <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> put his eye to a
telescope.
   So, step right up folks, and discover the wonders of the
universe. See how big it is. Learn its age. Look at light created
14 billion years ago and arriving at your eye only this instant.
   Ride along to the beginning of everything, almost, to the Big
Bang of 10 or 20 thousand million years ago. See stars born and see
them die. Watch galaxies form. Follow the flow of gas into the
Milky Way's halo. Peer deep into the universe, past so many stars
in our own galaxy that it would take a person more than a lifetime
to count, to a hundred billion other galaxies each with about 200
billion stars.
   For scientists, and then the rest of us, all that becomes
possible now that the space shuttle Discovery has carried the
Hubble Space Telescope into the sky to see what no one has seen
before. The telescope, a silvery tube as long as a tanker truck,
has an unmatched ability to detect and capture the faintest light.
   Light, speeding along at 186,000 miles a second, is the
messenger of creation. Tracking the trail of light from today to
the first moments contains all the information we will ever have
about the creation of the universe.
   The Hubble promises to give science an open window perhaps to
the first echoes of creation. This is a world-class event, even if
astronomy is not your thing.
   Superlatives?
   ``In the history of optical astronomy there have been two great
leaps in the resolution of the universe: <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s telescope in the
<DATE>autumn of 1609</DATE>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>April 1990</DATE>.'' _
<PERSON>Eric J. Chaisson</PERSON>, a senior scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Space Telescope Science
Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>.
   One more?
   ``No one ever made anything that good,'' <PERSON>James Westphal</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Another?
   <PERSON>Dr. Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, predicts that the
Hubble telescope ``will literally be the dawn of a new era in
astronomy.''
   Eras rarely can be proclaimed in advance. But the <ORGANIZATION>HST</ORGANIZATION>, named
after <PERSON>Edwin Powell Hubble</PERSON>, holds that kind of promise.
   Hubble was an astronomer in the <DATE>first half of the century</DATE> who
concluded not only that distant galaxies are moving away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
but that the farther away they are, the faster they move. The
theory of an expanding universe supported the belief that the
universe originated in a cosmic explosion and that all matter is
still rushing from the site of that so-called Big Bang.
   Astronomers think the <ORGANIZATION>Big Bang</ORGANIZATION> occurred 12 billion to 20 billion
years ago and sent the entire universe flying out at incredible
speed and heat. Eventually matter cooled and condensed into
galaxies, stars and planets.
   There are bigger telescopes than the Hubble, but they are all on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and all subject to a major limitation _ the atmosphere _
which is fine for breathing but lousy for seeing through. The
problem of skywatching through layers of air has been likened to
birdwatching from the bottom of a swimming pool.
   The Voyager spacecraft, which sent back astonishing views of
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s sister planets, had to travel 12 years to get close enough
for pictures as they whizzed past. With the Hubble, says scientist
<PERSON>Edward Weiler</PERSON>, such pictures are possible any time we want.
   The telescope is 42.5 by 14 feet and consists of a 94.5-inch
primary mirror that gathers incoming light.
   ``On a clear, dark night you can see a flashlight from two miles
away,'' says <PERSON>Weiler</PERSON>, chief <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientist on the Hubble project.
``With a 28-power telescope you can see it on the moon 250,000
miles away. With the <ORGANIZATION>HST</ORGANIZATION> you could see a firefly in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> from
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891117-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-17-89 2026EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-BiggestStructure     11-17 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Biggest Structure,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronomers Find Biggest Structure in Universe</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronomers have discovered a gigantic
collection of galaxies that they say is the biggest structure ever
seen in the universe.
   The structure, which they call the Great Wall, is so difficult
to explain that it raises new questions about theories of the
origin and structure of the universe.
   The researchers reported their discovery in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s issue of
the journal Science.
   The galaxies that make up the Great Wall form a sheet that is at
least 500 million light years long, or <MONEY>3,000 billion billion</MONEY> miles,
and it is 200 million light years wide and 15 million light years
thick.
   By comparison, the earth's Milky Way galaxy is 100,000 light
years across. The entire universe is thought to be between 10
billion and 20 billion light years across.
   The Great Wall was discovered by <PERSON>Margaret Geller</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Huchra</PERSON>
a detailed three-dimensional map they have been compiling of a
section of the heavens. The structure is so big that it appears to
run off the edges of the map.
   <PERSON>Geller</PERSON> said no one knows of a force that could have produced a
structure so big in the time since the universe was formed.
   ``My view is it's something really missing, something we really
don't understand,'' said <PERSON>Geller</PERSON>. ``It's not just a more complex
version of something we already know.''
   Astronomers say each new survey of skies turns up still bigger
structures.
   ``This is the latest chapter in a saga that's been going on
since the <DATE>late 1970s</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Edwin Turner</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Princeton University</ORGANIZATION>.
``We keep being surprised that we keep seeing something bigger as
we go out farther.''
   He said theories about how the universe arrived in its current
form already have been stretched by earlier discoveries, and it is
not clear whether the Great Wall ``will be the straw that broke the
camel's back.'' Virtually all current theories hold that the
universe began with a ``big bang'' about 15 billion years ago and
expanded rapidly into a highly uniform mix of matter and energy.
   In their report, the <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION> scientists suggested building a
national observatory to extend the exploration of the universe.
They proposed a telescope with a light-gathering mirror four
meters, or 160 inches, across, giving it six times the
light-gathering power of the telescope used to find the Great Wall.
   ``With a telescope that size, you can not only look nearby, but
you can look at large enough distances where you can begin to see
how these structures really evolve,'' <PERSON>Geller</PERSON> said. ``That's one
thing we really have in our favor, that as we look out to greater
distances, we look back in time.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06207071 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06207071 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Diagram; DIAGRAM: Associated Press (color); NEW WORLD; British astronomers
claim to have discovered the first known planet outside our solar system. The
planet orbits a very dense, compact star called a neutron star.; ...; Relative
sizes of planets and stars:; New Planet: about 10-12 times the mass of Earth
and 16,000 - 24,000 miles in diameter.; Neutron star: about 20 miles in
diameter; Sun: 865,000 miles in diameter.; Earth: 7,9930 miles in diameter.;
...; Their relative positions in our galaxy:; The neutron star and its planet
are about 20,000 - 30,000 light years from Earth, in the direction of the
center of our galaxy.; ...; Source: Mercury News Wire Service, Nature,
Discovering the Universe.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; RESEARCH; REPORT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Scientists have discovered what may be the first known planet outside our
solar system -- a mysterious object, about 10 times the mass of the Earth,
orbiting a dead and distant star.;    The finding by a team of British
astronomers, reported today in the journal Nature, set astronomers buzzing.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GOOD HEAVENS! ANOTHER PLANET MAY BE OUT THERE,
SCIENTISTS SAY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     If confirmed, it will challenge fundamental views of how stars and solar
systems evolve, <PERSON>David C. Black</PERSON>, director of the Lunar and <ORGANIZATION>Planetary Institute</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, wrote in an accompanying commentary.;    Evidence for the
existence of the planet is strong, astronomers say, but they are at a loss to
explain how it got there.;    The problem: Its parent star, known as
PSR1829-10, blew up more than a million years ago in a supernova. If the
planet had been around at the time, it probably would have been destroyed or
released from orbit. And no theory exists to explain how it could have formed
in the years since.;    "I'm usually quite skeptical. But I thought this was
quite a strong case," said <PERSON>Douglas Lin</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Santa
Cruz</PERSON>, who spent <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> debating the new findings with a dozen
colleagues and students. "It is very exciting, very intriguing. We're
discussing various possibilities for how this thing could have formed and how
it could currently exist.";    Detecting planets around other stars is tricky.
If they exist -- and most astronomers now believe they do -- they are
relatively tiny objects lost in the glare of their respective suns, too dim to
see directly with the most powerful telescope.;    Although a number of
scientists claimed to have found indirect evidence of planets over the past
few decades, none of their discoveries has ever been confirmed.;    The latest
report came almost by accident.;    <PERSON>Andrew Lyne</PERSON> and his colleagues at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Manchester</ORGANIZATION> were surveying a type of neutron star known as a
pulsar. It represents one of the last stages in the life cycle of a star like
our sun, which over millions of years would be expected to expand, explode in
a supernova and contract into a small, dark, extremely dense neutron star.;   
