<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0267 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 0153EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-MinimumWage-Glance     11-09 0322</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage-Glance,0334</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Provisions of Minimum Wage Bill</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Minimum Wage, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE RATE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>THE SUBMINIMUM</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>TIP CREDIT</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SMALL BUSINESS EXEMPTION</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>OTHER EXEMPTIONS</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891101-0284 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-01-89 2059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f BC-MinimumWage-Glance 1stLd-Writethru f0319 11-01 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Minimum Wage-Glance, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0319,0357</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Provisions of the Minimum Wage Bill</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: CORRECTS ``The Subminimum'' section to note that subminimum
may never fall below $3.35; CORRECTS $3.21 in table to $3.35. Also moving
on general news wires.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>THE RATE</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>THE SUBMINIMUM</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE> Min SubMin</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>TIP CREDIT</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>SMALL BUSINESS EXEMPTION</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>OTHER EXEMPTIONS</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation to
increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour while creating a new
subminimum wage for certain teen-age workers. The bill becomes
effective next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900331-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-90 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MinimumWage-Glance     03-31 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage-Glance,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Key Provisions of Minimum Wage Increase</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Minimum Wage Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>THE RATE</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>TRAINING WAGE</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>WAGE-POVERTY LEVEL</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>TIP CREDIT</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>SMALL BUSINESS EXEMPTION</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>OTHER EXEMPTIONS</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   Here are key provisions of the legislation
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passed last year to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an
hour and establish a subminimum training wage for certain teen-age
workers. The measure takes effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032489-0042 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 34922 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 24, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 3; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
611 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HOUSE, DEFYING VETO THREATS, OKS WAGE BILL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ART PINE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, defying threats of a presidential veto, voted <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to raise the 
federal minimum wage from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> by late <DATE>1991</DATE>, <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> higher 
than President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has said he would accept. 
</P>
<P>
Congressional leaders said that the vote, 248 to 171, is likely to spur the 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> into approving an even higher minimum wage -- possibly <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an hour, as 
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Democrats have proposed. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Backs 'Training' Pay 
</P>
<P>
Nevertheless, the vote is substantially short of the two-thirds' majority that 
would be needed to override a veto. And the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill would allow a subminimum 
"training" wage -- <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of the prevailing minimum wage -- only for a worker's 
first two months on a job, less than the six months sought by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. "We're hanging tough." 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> (D-Mass.), chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor and Human 
Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION> and the chief sponsor of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> bill, held out the 
possibility that the Democrats might be open to further bargaining. 
</P>
<P>
He urged <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to "refrain from further veto threats until he sees the shape of 
the bill that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> finally sends him. This is an excellent opportunity for 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Administration</ORGANIZATION> to demonstrate that they can work together." 
</P>
<P>
The <MONEY>$4.55-an-hour</MONEY> figure voted by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> was billed as a bipartisan 
compromise. The <ORGANIZATION>House Education and Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> originally had sought <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> 
but agreed to a 10-cent reduction to halt defections by conservative Democrats. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> rejected, 218 to 198, the <ORGANIZATION>Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s <MONEY>$4.25-an-hour</MONEY> proposal. 
Before finally approving the bill, <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members voted, 240 to 179, to approve 
the <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> figure. 
</P>
<P>
On final passage, 226 Democrats and 22 Republicans voted for the measure, while 
147 Republicans and 24 Democrats opposed it. The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> delegation 
essentially split along party lines, with two exceptions: Rep. <PERSON>Charles Pashayan 
Jr.</PERSON> (R-Fresno) voted for the compromise bill, and Rep. <PERSON>Henry A. Waxman</PERSON> (D-Los 
Angeles) did not vote. 
</P>
<P>
The dispute over how much to increase the federal minimum wage is mainly a 
political one. Economists say that the economic impact of a higher minimum wage 
is likely to be modest because labor is already in such short supply that few 
jobs are still paying the federal minimum. 
</P>
<P>
And in some states -- such as <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, where the minimum is <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> -- state 
law already provides for a higher wage than federal law. 
</P>
<P>
Nevertheless, the issue has become a major rallying point for Democrats and 
organized labor. The federal minimum wage has not been increased since <DATE>1981</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, Speaker <PERSON>Jim Wright</PERSON> (D-Tex.), urging <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> approval of the 
compromise proposal, told lawmakers that "it isn't enough, but it certainly is 
better than nothing. I'm asking you for this vote today . . . " 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has insisted on including a so-called "training" wage for new workers on 
grounds that employers might cut back on hiring if they are forced to pay a 
higher minimum wage to inexperienced workers. He wants the training wage to be 
today's <MONEY>$3.35-an-hour</MONEY> minimum. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to providing only a 60-day training period, the House-passed bill 
would apply the training minimum only to new workers with no experience. 
</P>
<P>
The full minimum wage would rise to <MONEY>$3.85</MONEY> an hour on <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE>, <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> a year later 
and <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> in <DATE>October</DATE> of <DATE>1991</DATE> -- a year before <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s proposed <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> would go 
into effect. 
</P>
<P>
The compromise measure would also increase the number of businesses that are 
exempt from having to pay the federal minimum wage. Currently, employers whose 
gross earnings are less than <MONEY>$362,000</MONEY> a year are exempt. The bill would raise 
the figure to <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
MINIMUM WAGE; BUSH, GEORGE; LEGISLATION -- UNITED STATES; VETOES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900331-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-90 1208EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MinimumWage Bjt   03-31 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage, Bjt,650</SECOND>
<HEAD>Minimum Wage Increases Sunday for First Time Since 1981</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KAREN BALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation's minimum wage increases for the
first time in nearly a decade <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, but it won't lift millions of
low-wage workers above the poverty level.
   The minimum wage, paid to about 3 million Americans, increases
from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY> and will go to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour next <DATE>April
1</DATE>. The new law also establishes a subminimum training wage for
certain teen-age workers.
   Critics say the increase should have been greater.
   ``Right now, it's not at a level where people can pull
themselves out of poverty,'' said <PERSON>Jo Ann Mort</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Amalgamated
Clothing and Textile Workers Union</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``When people hear minimum wage, they think children working
after school, and that's not the reality of it. The reality is that
adults are trying to support families on this,'' <PERSON>Mort</PERSON> said.
   Sen. <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, last week called the size of
the increase a ``disgrace'' and said he would push <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> next
year to bring the wage to ``a level that is fair to millions of
workers who are being unfairly exploited now.''
   Kennedy blamed the size of the increase on the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration, which vetoed a proposal last year to raise the wage
to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an hour.
   The increase was ``the best we could do against an anti-worker
administration that refuses to do justice for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s working
poor,'' said <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor and Human
Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   The administration considers the increase an equitable boost
that will result in fewer jobs being lost than under the <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY>
proposal, <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Stephen Hart</PERSON> said.
   Polls have shown a majority of Americans support a minimum wage
of at least <MONEY>$5</MONEY> an hour.
   The minimum wage was established in <DATE>1938</DATE> as part of the first
Fair Labor Standards Act. During its first 40 years, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> acted
six times to keep the rate at about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the average
hourly earnings of all non-supervisory employees.
   The <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> rate, which equaled <PERCENT>48 percent</PERCENT> of the national average
earnings in <DATE>1981</DATE>, fell to an all-time low of <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> of the
nation's average earnings last year, according to the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>.
   After <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s increase, full-time minimum-wage workers will
still be <MONEY>$516</MONEY> a year short of what the government figures it takes
to support a family of two at the poverty level and <MONEY>$4,796</MONEY> below
the basic needs level for a family of four. The government placed
the poverty level for a family of four at <MONEY>$12,700</MONEY> in <DATE>February</DATE>.
   Still, the boost in the minimum wage may help millions of other
low-paid workers. For instance, companies paying <MONEY>$4</MONEY> or <MONEY>$4.50</MONEY> an
hour may decide to raise wages <MONEY>45 cents</MONEY> to keep trained workers.
   There are more than 11 million Americans making less than <MONEY>$4.50</MONEY>
an hour and nearly 15 million making under <MONEY>$5</MONEY> an hour, according to
the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   Under the new law, workers ages 16 to 19 may be paid a
subminimum training wage for their first three months in the work
force and for an additional 90 days if the employer has a formal
training program.
   The training wage will be <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour when the minimum wage
rises to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY> an hour and <MONEY>$3.62</MONEY> an hour when the minimum wage
reaches <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> next <DATE>April</DATE>. Migrant seasonal farmworkers are exempt
from the subminimum and the entire subminimum provision expires in
<DATE>April 1993</DATE>.
   The wage that employers are required to pay workers who receive
tips will increase to <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum wage, providing
that tips bring workers' hourly pay to at least the minimum. The
percentage, which was <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> before <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, goes to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT>
a year from now.
   The level at which small businesses are exempt from the federal
minimum wage increases from <MONEY>$362,500</MONEY> in gross sales to <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY>.
   Hundreds of special exemptions exist, such as for some farm
workers, including tobacco leaf harvesters, casual babysitters,
newspaper delivery workers, amusement park employees, wreath
makers, employees at small radio stations in cities with fewer than
25,000 residents and mollusk and crustacean harvesters.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880510-0079 </DOCNO>
<HL> States Know Best What Labor's Worth </HL>
<AUTHOR> Kathy Ann Ormiston </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> LABOR </CO>
<G> CNG </G>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> soon will consider an increase in the federal minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour. 
Supporters of the increase argue that a major impetus has been recent boosts in many state minimum-wage levels. 
Last year alone, nine states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> raised their minimum wage above the current federal level, and this year <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> are considering doing the same. 
Yet, state and federal minimum-wage comparisons should be made with a great deal of caution. 

   There are many loopholes in federal minimum-wage coverage. 
Certain occupations, including casual babysitters and most farm workers, are excluded as well as employees of small businesses and firms not engaged in interstate commerce. 
State minimum-wage laws are intended to cover these workers. 
At the same time, if a state's minimum is higher than the federal minimum, the state minimum applies. 

   Moreover, the quoted minimum wage for a state is often deceptive. 
Some states offer what is, in reality, a menu of minimum wages rather than a single minimum. 
The District of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, whose minimum of <MONEY>$4.85</MONEY> is the highest in the country, actually has seven other "minimum wages," all of which are lower than <MONEY>$4.85</MONEY>. 
Workers in the retail trade and laundry industry, for example, receive a minimum of only <MONEY>$3.50</MONEY>. 
Furthermore, the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, like many states, has a subminimum, or "training" wage, of <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> for employees in some job categories who are under age 18. (Some states also have subminimums based on age, student status, approved internship programs or for new hires.) 
Moreover, 13 states have minimums below the federal level and nine have no minimum at all. 

   Another frequently overlooked point is that although 16 states have enacted minimum-wage levels above the current federal minimum of <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY>, not one has a minimum at or above <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY>. 
A minimum wage of <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> would require even the high-minimum-wage states of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> to increase their mandated minimums by <PERCENT>19%</PERCENT>. 

   Nonetheless, both Republican and Democrat members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> from high-wage states will likely find it difficult to vote against raising the federal minimum wage, since raising it would equalize wage costs among states and increase the competitiveness of labor in high-minimum-wage states. 
Yet the different minimum-wage levels to a large extent reflect regional variations in levels of unemployment and labor demand, as well as costs of living. 
Typically, states with high minimum wages have low levels of unemployment and/or high costs of living. 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, with unemployment rates of <PERCENT>5.6%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>3.8%</PERCENT> are representative of states with high minimum wages. 
Compare these unemployment rates to those of <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, states that have no minimum wage. 
Their unemployment rates are <PERCENT>7.9%</PERCENT> and <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> respectively. 

   The advantage of allowing state or regional differences in minimum-wage levels is that the appropriate minimum wage for <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> might force massive layoffs in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. 
Wyoming's minimum of <MONEY>$1.60</MONEY> would be meaningless, even laughable, in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, where most employers must pay well above the federal minimum wage to attract applicants for job openings. 
Because states are the best judges of local conditions, they are in a better position to set minimum-wage laws. 

   Proponents of a federal increase argue that recent state increases signal grassroots support of the current minimum-wage bill before <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
Yet 41 states are still at or below the current federal level. 
As <PERSON>Robert Martin</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> has pointed out: "Most states recognize that what you pay someone is determined by supply and demand." 
This is a lesson the folks in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> could bear learning. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Ormiston</PERSON> is an economist for the <ORGANIZATION>House Republican Research Committee</ORGANIZATION>. 

   ---

                       Minumum Wages
    Proposed federal wage (1/1/92)          <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY>
    <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>                              4.85
    Proposed federal wage (1/1/91)          <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY>
    <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> (7/1/88), <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION> (10/1/88)         4.25
    <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION> (1/1/90)                           3.95
    <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> (1/1/90)           3.85
    <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> (7/1/88)                    3.75
    <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION> (1/1/89),
    <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION> (7/1/88)                       3.65
    <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt</LOCATION>.                         3.55
    Current Federal wage                    <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY>
    <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ken.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>,
    <LOCATION>Mont.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nev.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>,
    <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Penn.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>, (7/1/88),
    <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>W.V.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wisc</LOCATION>.                       3.35
    <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, (1/1/89)                           3.30
    <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga</LOCATION>.                                3.25
    <LOCATION>N.D.</LOCATION>                                     3.10
    <LOCATION>Colo</LOCATION>.                                    3.00
    <LOCATION>S.D.</LOCATION>                                     2.80
    <LOCATION>Utah                                     2.75
    Va.</LOCATION>,
    <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> (7/1/88)                            2.65
    <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.                       2.30
    <LOCATION>Ind</LOCATION>.                                     2.00
    <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo</LOCATION>.                               1.60
    <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ariz.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>La.</LOCATION>,
    <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn</LOCATION>.                  None

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880311-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-88 1648EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MinimumWage     03-11 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage,270</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kennedy Supports Increasing Minimum Wage To $5.05 Per Hour</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor and Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>, expressed his support
<DATE>Friday</DATE> for increasing the minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> per hour over four
years but said he still remains committed to raises tied to
inflation.
   ``I continue to support indexing,'' said <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, in a statement
released by his <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> office. ``It's the best way to make the
minimum wage a living wage.''
   <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said his committee has scheduled action on the minimum
wage bill during the <DATE>week of April 11</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House Education and Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> voted <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to raise
the federal minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour in several steps over the
next four years.
   The vote to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY>, instead of the
<MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> voted last week by the <ORGANIZATION>House labor standards subcommittee</ORGANIZATION>,
was seen as an attempt by supporters of an increase to gain a
bargaining chip that will assure the minimum wage will be at least
<MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> when the measure leaves the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Last week, the subcommittee approved a bill to raise the
<MONEY>$3.35-an-hour</MONEY> minimum wage to <MONEY>$3.85</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>, <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE> and
<MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE>. At the same time, the subcommittee voted to strip
the bill of a controversial proposal that would have indexed or
tied future increases to the rate of inflation.
   ``A fourth year increase is less satisfactory, but it could make
a stronger package, given the president's veto threats,'' said
<LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>. ``The last time <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> raised the minimum wage in <DATE>1977</DATE>,
we enacted a four-step increase, too.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030989-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 28494 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 9, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 4; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
723 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SENATE PANEL, DEFYING VETO THREAT, BACKS HIKE IN MINIMUM WAGE TO $4.65 BY 1991 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM J. EATON, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Defying President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s veto threat, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> voted 11 to 5 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for a bill that would raise the <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> hourly minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> in 
three steps by <DATE>1991</DATE> without any subminimum rate. 
</P>
<P>
The committee's swift approval, with similar action expected in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, 
could set the stage this month or early in <DATE>April</DATE> for the first legislative 
showdown between the new President and <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has proposed a three-stage increase in the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour, 
with an eventual top rate of <MONEY>90 cents</MONEY> an hour less for new workers in their 
first six months of employment, and he has said he will veto any more generous 
bill. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'His Last Offer' 
</P>
<P>
the President would not yield. "He's giving them our best and last figure up 
front, and his proposal for an increase to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour is fair and firm and 
his last offer," he said. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> (D-Mass.) said that the minimum wage has been 
unchanged since <DATE>1981</DATE> and he believes there is enough congressional support for 
an increase to override a presidential veto. 
</P>
<P>
"It's on a fast track now," said <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> panel and 
chief advocate of the legislation. "The earlier the better, so far as I am 
concerned." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> may vote as early as next week, he said. The <ORGANIZATION>House Education and 
Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> is expected to approve a similar bill next week and seek 
passage by the entire <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> before the Easter recess starts on <DATE>March 23</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The federal minimum wage, first enacted <DATE>a half century ago</DATE> at the rate of <MONEY>25 
cents</MONEY> an hour, has been a major battleground for liberals and conservatives in 
almost every decade since. Although former President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> successfully 
opposed any increase in his two terms, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> announced during his campaign that 
he would favor an increase in the minimum rate but only if it was accompanied 
by a "training wage" for new workers. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Rejects <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> Plan 
</P>
<P>
Before approving <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>'s bill, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> rejected <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s 
plan in a 10-6 vote, mainly along party lines. Two Republicans, <PERSON>Dave 
Durenberger</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> and <PERSON>James M. Jeffords</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>, then joined nine 
Democrats in sending the <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> legislation to the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> floor. 
</P>
<P>
Opponents, led by <PERSON>Sen. Orrin G. Hatch</PERSON> (R-Utah), argued that a higher minimum 
wage would destroy 650,000 jobs and contribute to inflation. Their arguments 
were echoed by a business coalition formed to fight any increase in the <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> 
hourly rate. 
</P>
<P>
Coalition director <PERSON>Bob Martin</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> said the 
committee-approved bill was "misguided and would have very serious economic 
consequences. We're saying it will set off a <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> round of inflation." 
</P>
<P>
But, after the committee vote, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said the case was "compelling" for an 
increase to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an hour to restore the <DATE>1981</DATE> buying power of workers on the 
economic ladder's bottom rung. 
</P>
<P>
As for the President's proposal to pay new workers a lower rate for six months, 
<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Labor Department</ORGANIZATION> estimated that minimum-wage workers could be 
trained in one month. He said he would listen to proposals for a compromise on 
the amount and duration of a lower wage rate. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Called 'Substandard Wage' 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sen. Howard M. Metzenbaum</PERSON> (D-Ohio) said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s proposal to pay those workers 
<PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the minimum wage rate prevailing for most workers was "just a 
substandard wage for fast-food operators and others like that." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Hatch</PERSON> termed it a "classic compromise" between those in the Administration 
who oppose any increase and those who want to raise the federal minimum rate on 
equity grounds. The lower rate, <PERSON>Hatch</PERSON> said, would reduce the loss of jobs that 
otherwise might accompany a <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> wage. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Dashed by <PERSON>Filibuster 
</P>
<P>
Kennedy</PERSON>'s efforts to get <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> approval of a <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> hourly minimum wage last 
year were dashed by a GOP-led filibuster at the session's close, despite <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s 
general support for an unspecified increase. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> never took up similar 
legislation in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>' last session, partly because Democratic leaders 
decided that they lacked the votes to pass it. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said that proponents were in a stronger position this year, adding: 
"This case is so compelling -- it's a minimum standard of decency. This 
President (<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>) even recommended a <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> increase in pay for members of 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>." 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
UNITED STATES -- LABOR; BUSH, GEORGE; VETOES; UNITED STATES -- WAGES AND 
SALARIES; MINIMUM WAGE; SENATE (U.S.) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880622-0248 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-88 2156EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-MinimumWage 1stLd-Writethru a0715 06-22 0486</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0715,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kennedy Scales Back Proposal To Increase Minimum Wage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS last graf to correct amount of increase proposed by
Quayle</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM SEPPY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sen. <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> unveiled a scaled-down
proposal <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to increase the federal minimum wage <MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an hour over the next three years.
   The labor-supported proposal from the <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> Democrat
came as the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> began deliberations on <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>'s
earlier minimum wage bill. Republican Sens. <PERSON>Strom Thurmond</PERSON> of <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> immediately expressed their
opposition.
   Kennedy's original bill would have boosted the minimum wage, now
at <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> per hour, by <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> next year, <MONEY>40 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE> and <MONEY>40
cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE>, with automatic increases tied to inflation to keep
it at <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the average wage nationally.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> already has completed action on a
measure that would raise the federal minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour
over the next four years. It is understood, however, that the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
panel's chairman, Rep. <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, will offer
the <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> proposal as a substitute when the measure gets to the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> floor sometime after the <DATE>July 4</DATE> recess.
   In its brief meeting <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION>
rejected 12-4 an amendment by <PERSON>Sen. Paul Simon</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ill.</LOCATION>, who wanted
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> to be required to keep the federal minimum wage.
   Kennedy's proposal includes <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, but permits the country
to exempt itself if the island's minimum wage board certifies to
the labor secretary that there is a ``substantial finding of
unemployment.''
   In introducing his substitute bill, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said the current
minimum wage has fallen to its lowest point since its inception 50
years ago, with today's minimum of <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> per hour representing only
<PERCENT>36 percent</PERCENT> of the average hourly earnings.
   Historically, he said, the minimum has been maintained at a
figure of one-half the hourly average.
   ``Congressional action to restore the minimum wage is long
overdue,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Thurmond</PERSON> said, however, said he was opposed to a significant
increase in the minimum wage because ``it is inflationary, it
reduces entry-level and part-time jobs for teen-agers and unskilled
workers, as well as decreases services to consumers.''
   He said only ``big labor'' would benefit from an increased
minimum wage.
   ``Minimum wage legislation has always been promoted by labor
unions and other special interest groups for their purely
self-serving political considerations,'' <PERSON>Thurmond</PERSON> said. ``The labor
unions in our country are looking to this measure as a means of
securing their positions and turning around a decline in membership
that they have experienced in recent years.''
   <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> said he would propose an amendment which would increase
the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4</MONEY> and combine it with a reform of the earned
income tax credit, similar to an approach presented in the <ORGANIZATION>House
Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> by Rep. <PERSON>Tom Petri</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Wis.</LOCATION>, but rejected by the
panel.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880630-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-30-88 0144EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MinimumWage     06-30 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Labor Committee Clears Minimum Wage Increase</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM SEPPY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Congressional Democrats are poised to act on
compromise legislation to increase the federal minimum wage of
<MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> per hour by <MONEY>$1.20</MONEY> over the next three years.
   The task will not be easy, though, if Republicans are able to
anything about it.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> voted 11-5 <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to approve
legislation to raise the federal minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> per hour by
<DATE>1991</DATE>.
   But floor action on the bill is not expected until after the
<ORGANIZATION>Democratic National Convention</ORGANIZATION>, which takes place the week of <DATE>July
17</DATE>. The <ORGANIZATION>House Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> passed a wage increase in <DATE>March</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Senate Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>,
sponsor of the compromise, said the panel's vote ``brings us a
major step closer to our goal of raising the minimum wage for the
first time since <DATE>1981</DATE>.''
   Five million men and women will gain by the increase ``and they
deserve it,'' <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said. ``They're the working poor. They'd
rather work than live on welfare, and they deserve a living wage.
   ``For 50 years, the minimum wage has been a promise by <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>
that if you work for a living, you won't have to live in poverty.
Reaganomics broke that promise and it's time for <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to fix
it.''
   Kennedy did not waste time in getting the committee vote to send
the measure to the floor. As soon as a quorum was formed at a
hastily-called meeting in the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>, the vote was taken.
   Although Republicans indicated a week ago that they would offer
amendments in committee, none was introduced.
   ``There was no reason to take on those issues in committee,''
said <PERSON>Sen. Orrin G. Hatch</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Utah</LOCATION>. ``There will be amendments when
the bill gets to the floor. I am sure we can conjure up some.''
   He predicted that floor action ``will be a donnybrook. There is
a lot of irritation on this bill. They (Democrats) haven't had the
intestinal fortitude to bring up the bill before now.''
   <PERSON>Hatch</PERSON> said the increase in the minimum wage ``could cost up to a
million jobs, especially those that need them - black youths and
(Hispanic) youths. We just can't write them off.''
   Republicans in both the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> are expected to offer
amendments that would cap the increase at <MONEY>$4</MONEY> an hour, provide a
training wage and exempt all small companies from the wage
requirement.
   The 11-5 committee vote was mainly along party lines, with
Republicans <PERSON>Robert T. Stafford</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Lowell P. Weicker Jr.</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> joining the nine-Democrat majority.
   The <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> compromise was worked out between Democratic
congressional leaders and organized labor after it became clear
that the initial proposal approved by the <ORGANIZATION>House Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> was
going nowhere.
   The Kennedy bill would raise the current <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour minimum
wage to <MONEY>$3.75</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>, <MONEY>$4.15</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE> and <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The exemption for small businesses would be raised to cover
companies with annual sales of <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> or less. The exemption
currently applies to companies with sales of <MONEY>$362,000</MONEY> or less.
   In addition, the bill would increase the so-called tip credit
for restaurant workers from <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> by <DATE>Jan. 1,
1990</DATE>.
   Employers are currently allowed to count <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of an
employee's tips toward payment of the minimum wage.
   Kennedy and Rep. <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, chairman of the
<ORGANIZATION>House Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION>, initially sponsored legislation that would
have raised the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an hour over a three-year
period, then ``index'' all future increases by tying them to the
inflation rate.
   Opposition to the indexing provision by a number of Democrats on
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee forced the leadership to abandon it before the
bill could get out of subcommittee. In place of indexing, the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
committee voted to increase the minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> over four
years.
   When the bill reaches the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> floor, after the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> acts,
Reps. <PERSON>Tommy Robinson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ark.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Thomas J. Ridge</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>, will
substitute the <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> version of <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an hour for the one passed
by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110989-0124 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 132294 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 9, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 25; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
568 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CONGRESS ENACTS $4.25 MINIMUM WAGE; BUSH PRAISED FOR BACKING COMPROMISE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By WILLIAM J. EATON, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> completed action <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on a compromise bill to raise the federal 
minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour and sent it to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> for President 
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s promised signature. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, in a swift follow-up to overwhelming approval in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> last 
week, beat back proposed amendments that would have aided small business and 
agricultural interests and passed the measure, 89 to 8. 
</P>
<P>
The bill provides for the federal minimum wage to rise from the current <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> 
an hour to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY> next <DATE>April 1</DATE>, then to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> a year later. 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> vetoed a bill last <DATE>June</DATE> that would have raised the basic pay rate 
to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an hour over three years, he was praised by <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Majority Leader 
<PERSON>George J. Mitchell</PERSON> (D-Me.) and others for his support of the compromise. 
</P>
<P>
"The working poor are about to receive an increase, although it is not as much 
as they deserve," said <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> (D-Mass.), chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate 
Labor and Human Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION> and chief sponsor of the legislation. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said he would do his best to see that another increase, effective in 
the presidential election year of <DATE>1992</DATE>, is passed. 
</P>
<P>
Sponsors said that about 11 million workers would benefit from the increase. In 
a concession to <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, the bill would also establish for the first time a lower 
"training rate" for teen-agers during their first 60 days of working. Employers 
could pay the lower wage for 60 days longer if their training programs are 
approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Labor</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, which already has a <MONEY>$4.25-an-hour</MONEY> minimum wage, would not be 
affected by the federal legislation. 
</P>
<P>
The President at first proposed raising the base wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour over 
three years, with a lower rate for six months for all newly hired workers, 
regardless of age or previous experience. At one point, he said that he would 
veto any bill that differed from his proposal. 
</P>
<P>
President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> successfully opposed any increase in the minimum wage 
during his eight years in the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, on grounds that it would be 
inflationary and would price younger, unskilled workers out of the job market. 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>Orrin G. Hatch</PERSON> (R-Utah) made the same arguments <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, but <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s 
endorsement of the bill ensured its passage through the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Proponents of the raise said that the average hourly pay for all rank-and-file 
workers has climbed to <MONEY>$9.70</MONEY> an hour and that starting pay for even menial jobs 
is now <MONEY>$5</MONEY> or <MONEY>$6</MONEY> an hour in many parts of the country. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>, who has been a frequent critic of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> in recent weeks, paid tribute 
to him during the closing debate. 
</P>
<P>
"We owe a debt of gratitude to the President, who was willing to stand up and 
come out for a minimum wage increase, contrary to the previous Administration," 
<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Kennedy took a more critical view, saying that the Bush-backed compromise "owes 
more to the ideological embarrassment of those seeking tax relief for capital 
gains than it does to any real commitment to the minimum wage." 
</P>
<P>
Secretary of Labor <PERSON>Elizabeth Hanford Dole</PERSON> praised the outcome in a statement, 
saying: "With the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passage of the minimum wage bill, the President's 
commitment to a reasonable wage hike coupled with a meaningful training wage is 
finally fulfilled." 
</P>
<P>
At the <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> hourly rate, a person working full time would earn <MONEY>$170</MONEY> a week, or 
<MONEY>$8,840</MONEY> a year. That is below the federal poverty-level income of <MONEY>$12,100</MONEY> a year 
for a family of four. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BUSH, GEORGE; LEGISLATION -- UNITED STATES; UNITED STATES -- LABOR; UNITED 
STATES -- WAGES AND SALARIES; MINIMUM WAGE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051889-0149 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 58711 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 18, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 20; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
756 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CONGRESS PASSES $4.55 WAGE FLOOR BILL IN FACE OF VETO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ART PINE, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> gave final approval <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to a bill raising the federal minimum 
wage to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an hour -- setting the stage for a certain veto by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> 
and a major confrontation with the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> over how far Democrats can push 
on social issues. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> reiterated <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that he will veto the legislation, arguing in a 
speech before a retailers' conference that it would force employers to cut back 
on the number of new entry-level jobs they create and that it would ultimately 
exacerbate inflation. 
</P>
<P>
"If the majority in the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> rejects my offer of a reasonable compromise," 
he said, "a veto is going to be inevitable." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has proposed an increase to no more than <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour, to take effect in 
<DATE>1992</DATE> rather than in <DATE>1991</DATE>, as the bill passed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> provides. 
</P>
<P>
The President reasserted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that he would not accept any increase that 
exceeds his own proposal -- a point underscored by <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> Chief of Staff 
<PERSON>John H. Sununu</PERSON>. He had told the same group earlier that "<MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> is fine" but 
"<MONEY>$4.26</MONEY> is vetoland -- now and forever." 
</P>
<P>
Democratic strategists conceded that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> appeared to have the upper hand in 
the standoff. The 63-37 vote in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> fell short of the two-thirds 
majority that Democrats would need to override a veto. The measure was passed 
<DATE>May 11</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> on a 247-172 vote, also short of a two-thirds majority. 
</P>
<P>
It was not clear whether Democrats would seek to scale back the size of the 
increase after <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> vetoes the new legislation or simply allow the measure to 
languish and use the veto as a political issue to paint the Administration as 
uncaring about the poor. 
</P>
<P>
The Democrats already have compromised somewhat by agreeing to create a new 
subminimum wage that would enable employers to pay new workers with fewer than 
60 days' experience <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> of the minimum in an effort to stave off any job cuts 
from the increase in labor costs. 
</P>
<P>
Sen. <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> (D-Mass.), who led the Democratic effort on the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> 
floor, challenged as "a sham" <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s assertions that he had attempted to 
compromise with <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. " 'Let them eat cake' is the message (to the poor) 
from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>," <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s hard-line stance is only partly on economic grounds. <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> 
strategists said the President must draw the line now on the minimum wage issue 
or Democrats will be emboldened to challenge him with more-expensive proposals 
on other social issues, such as child care. 
</P>
<P>
Most analysts contend that, with unemployment now so low -- and labor scarce -- 
the measure would have little real economic impact. Only a few million workers 
of the 99 million now in the work force actually earn the federal minimum wage, 
which is <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, in the eight years since the last increase in the federal minimum 
wage, many states -- including <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> -- have enacted state minimums that 
are higher than the federal minimum. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s minimum wage, for example, is 
<MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour. 
</P>
<P>
Nevertheless, a veto by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> later this month would put the Democrats in 
something of a quandary. Mainstream Democrats, led by <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> and Rep. <PERSON>Augustus 
F. Hawkins</PERSON> (D-Los Angeles), have made the minimum wage issue a major agenda 
item this year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s hard-line position on the issue stands in sharp contrast to the more 
conciliatory approach he has taken in other areas, such as foreign affairs and 
reduction of the budget deficit, where he has sought to hammer out bipartisan 
accords. 
</P>
<P>
It also marks a major break with the <ORGANIZATION>Ronald Reagan Administration</ORGANIZATION>, which had 
consistently opposed any increase in the minimum wage. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> announced the shift 
during the <DATE>1988</DATE> presidential campaign but tempered it with a demand that 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> enact a subminimum training wage. 
</P>
<P>
In his speech to the retailers' group <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the President sought to 
portray the Democratic-sponsored legislation as likely to hurt low-income 
workers by depriving them of jobs. He disagreed with Democratic assertions that 
the difference between his stance and theirs is "three thin dimes." 
</P>
<P>
"My difference with the majority in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is not about <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> an hour on 
the minimum wage legislation; it's about hundreds of thousands of people . . . 
who won't have a job to go to if the minimum wage legislation before the 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> now becomes law," <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told the group. 
</P>
<P>
"I can sign the legislation pending in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and go back to the tired agenda 
of government intervention that so often hurts the very people it attempts to 
help, or we can step forward to keep <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> on the path to a competitive 
future," he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LEGISLATION -- UNITED STATES; UNITED STATES -- LABOR; UNITED STATES -- WAGES 
AND SALARIES; MINIMUM WAGE; BUSH, GEORGE; VETOES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880311-0282 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-11-88 0849EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f PM-MinimumWage 1stLd-Writethru f0027 03-11 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0027,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>Labor Secretary Criticizes Plan To Increase Minimum Wage</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 1-4 grafts to UPDATE with McLaughlin comments.
Picks up 3rd graf pvs, The subcommittee ... A version moving on
general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM SEPPY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Labor Secretary <PERSON>Ann McLaughlin</PERSON> <DATE>today</DATE> said a
proposal to raise the federal minimum wage to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour over
the next four years may sound ``like the right thing to do'' but it
actually would cause a loss of jobs.
   <PERSON>Mrs. McLaughlin</PERSON> said the proposed increase, likely to be
approved next week by the <ORGANIZATION>House Education and Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION>,
would be particularly hard on young people with no skills who are
seeking their first jobs.
   ``This is a tough one. <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour, I'm afraid would make
almost any economist have some jitters,'' <PERSON>Mrs. McLaughlin</PERSON> said in
an interview on <ORGANIZATION>NBC-TV</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Today'' show. ``The body of economic
thinking is that the increase in the minimum wage, while
well-intentioned and it sounds like the right thing to do, actually
will cause a loss of jobs, particularly impacting on young people
who need to get into the workforce.''
   Education and <ORGANIZATION>Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, scheduled a session next <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for final action on
the minimum wage bill. The panel had been unable on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> to
address all the amendments to a proposal that was approved by the
<ORGANIZATION>House labor standards subcommittee</ORGANIZATION> a week ago.
   The subcommittee approved an increase from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an
hour over a three-year period, with a 50-cent raise in <DATE>1989</DATE> and a
40-cent jump in both <DATE>1990</DATE> and <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   During the full committee's hearing, Rep. <PERSON>Carl C. Perkins</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Ky.</LOCATION>, proposed an amendment for an increase of another <MONEY>40 cents</MONEY> in
<DATE>1992</DATE> in an effort to keep the federal minimum at approximately one
half of the nation's average wage.
   The committee approved the <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> amendment on a vote of 18-14
with only two Democrats, Reps. <PERSON>Austin J. Murphy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Timothy J. Penny</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, joining Republicans in opposing the
proposal.
   <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON>, chairman of the labor standards subcommittee, said his
panel had fashioned a measure which would be acceptable to the full
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> and possibly the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We don't know what impact the fourth year will have on the
loss of jobs,'' <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON> said.
   Rep. <PERSON>Stephen J. Solarz</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, however, read from a letter
written to <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON> by <ORGANIZATION>Labor</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Ann McLaughlin</PERSON> who said
senior <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> advisers would recommend to President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
that he veto any legislation increasing the minimum wage.
   ``It doesn't matter what we do; the executive will be against
it,'' he said.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dick Armey</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Tex.</LOCATION>, who opposes any increase, proposed an
amendment to the <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> measure to raise the base to <MONEY>$20</MONEY> an hour,
but withdrew it after <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON> called it absurd.
   The committee approved 20-13 an amendment by Rep. <PERSON>Tommy F.
Robinson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ark.</LOCATION>, to increase the ``tip credit'' for restaurant
employers.
   Current law allows employers of workers who regularly receive
tips _ such as waiters and waitresses _ to count the tips as earned
wages equivalent to <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum wage.
   Thus, a restaurant owner could pay a worker <MONEY>$2.01</MONEY> an hour, with
the remaining <MONEY>$1.34</MONEY> _ <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of today's <MONEY>$3.35-an-hour</MONEY> minimum
wage _ supposed to come from tips.
   The <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> proposal would increase the credit to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has a companion bill, sponsored by <PERSON>Sen. Edward M.
Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Labor and Human Resources
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, which raises the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an hour over a
three-year period.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891102-0094 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891102 </DD>
<AN> 891102-0094. </AN>
<HL> House Approves
@  Minimum Wage
@  Rise of 90 Cents
@  ---
@  Compromise Calls for $4.25
@  Hourly Rate in '91, Less
@  As Teen `Training' Level
@  ----
@  By Albert R. Karr
<DD> 11/02/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> LABOR </CO>
<GV> CONGRESS (CNG)
EXECUTIVE (EXE) </GV>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890411-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-89 1824EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-MinimumWage 1stLd-Writethru f0235 04-11 0622</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage, 1st Ld-Writethru, f0235,0639</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats' Minimum Wage Plan Moves Ahead After Rejection of Bush
Offer</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: TOPS with 5 grafs to raise reference to $4.55 level, insert
reax from Mrs. Dole; PICKS UP graf 4 pvs, `More amendments...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> rejected President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s minimum
wage plan <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and moved closer to confronting him with
legislation raising the hourly figure to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY>, which he repeatedly
has promised to veto.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, on a 61-39 vote largely along party lines, backed an
amendment to legislation sponsored by <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, that brought the measure essentially in line with a
House-passed bill that would boost the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> by
<DATE>October 1991</DATE>.
   Rejected, by 58-41, was <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s proposal to increase the minimum
wage by <MONEY>30 cents</MONEY> a year from the current <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> in
<DATE>January 1992</DATE>. It was the second time <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s proposal was defeated
in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>; the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> rejected it three weeks ago.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s action brought a quick response from the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration.
   ``Today <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> had a golden opportunity,'' Labor Secretary
<PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON> said after the vote. ``But Senate Democrats
squandered the chance, the first chance in eight years, to raise
the minimum wage.''
   More amendments were being considered before the legislation
faced a final <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> vote, likely to come <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, but no further
significant changes were expected before then.
   ``We compromised,'' said <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, referring to his past
proposals to raise the minimum wage even higher. He also noted a
number of other changes in the legislation, including expanded
exemptions for small businesses, to meet Republican concerns.
   ``The president's approach is a far superior approach,'' <PERSON>Sen.
Orrin Hatch</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Utah</LOCATION>, said in his unsuccessful effort to win support
for substituting <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s proposal for the <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> bill.
   The action seemed to guarantee the first domestic-policy
showdown between <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, barring a compromise while the
bill is before a conference committee that will work out minor
   Such a deal, however, appears unlikely.
   ``There isn't going to be a compromise,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Republican
leader <PERSON>Robert Dole</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>. ``It's going to be <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour and
a six-month training wage, period.''
   Democrats nonetheless called on <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to accept their proposal.
   ``If there is any one thing that the 101st <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> must do it
is to increase the minimum wage,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Majority Leader
<PERSON>George Mitchell</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Maine</LOCATION>, chastising <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for opposing a <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> an
hour minimum wage while supporting expanded capital gains tax
breaks for the wealthy. ``This legislation will be a test of
whether we indeed are seeking a kindler, gentler nation,'' said
<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>.
   Both the defeated <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> proposal and the amended <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> bill
contain provisions allowing some workers to be paid a wage below
the federal minimum wage.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has insisted that provision extend for six months to all
newly hired workers, regardless of prior work experience.
   Kennedy, like the sponsors of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill, balked at that
proposal but to win the support of moderate and conservative
Democrats agreed on a two-month period during which some employees
could be paid <PERCENT>85 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum wage.
   That provision was contained in the amendment, offered by
Democratic Sens. <PERSON>Bob Graham</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <PERSON>David Pryor</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.
   ``Our training wage proposal is a proper balance of the need to
train new workers and the need to set a fair minimum wage,'' said
<PERSON>Graham</PERSON>.
   The Graham-Pryor amendment requires an employee to hold one job
for at least 30 days before the two-month training period would
expire. The House-passed bill also allows for a two-month training
period at a subminimum wage but only if the affected employee had
no prior job experience.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090789-0023 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 104033 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 7, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 6; Column 1; Editorial Writers Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
395 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
IT'S PAST TIME FOR A RAISE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Congressional Democrats will try again to give the nation's lowest-paid workers 
a raise, their first in nearly nine years. Increasing the federal minimum wage 
beyond the current <MONEY>$3.35-an-hour</MONEY> has proven a difficult task because of strong 
opposition from business interests and a majority of Republicans. Democrats 
have accepted the fact that the only chance of getting an increase in the rate 
is a compromise that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> can live with. They are putting one 
together. 
</P>
<P>
The President in <DATE>June</DATE> vetoed legislation sponsored by <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON> 
(D-Mass.) and Rep. <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON> (D-L.A.) that would have raised the 
hourly rate to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> over three years. He argued that the increase was 
excessive and inflationary and would cost thousands ofjobs. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, who during 
the <DATE>1988</DATE> campaign promised to raise the minimum wage, indicated he was willing 
to approve a more modest boost, to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour, but only if the legislation 
includeda lower sub-minimum training wage for new workers. 
</P>
<P>
Compromise legislation, introduced by Rep. <PERSON>Austin J. Murphy</PERSON> (D-Pa.), would 
raise the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> as <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has insisted upon. The increase -- only 
<MONEY>90 cents</MONEY> an hour -- would bespread over two rather than three years. The 
sub-minimum would last for 60 days. At thispoint, it offers the best chance for 
the working poor. 
</P>
<P>
The modest raise would boost a weekly salary based on the federal minimum wage 
from <MONEY>$134</MONEY> to <MONEY>$170</MONEY>. That's not much, and it won't make up for the losses in 
buying power due to inflation over the years. But a small raise is better than 
none. 
</P>
<P>
An estimated 5.4 million Americans earn the minimum wage. Their ranks include 
many teen-agers and new workers, but at least half are older than 25, and many 
are working parents who could bring more money into the house with a welfare 
check. For a parent with two children, welfare and related benefits are worth 
more than a pay check based on the federal minimum wage in 23 states, according 
to <PERSON>Isabel V. Sawhill</PERSON>, an economist at the <ORGANIZATION>Urban Institute</ORGANIZATION>. Yet thousands of 
poor Americans choose to work for less. They deserve more. 
</P>
<P>
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> can encourage Americans who are willing to work. He can help 
working mothers who are trying to help themselves. He can help working fathers 
who are taking responsibility for their families. A compromise on the minimum 
wage is the best hope of achieving those goals. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Editorial 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880310-0189 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-88 1711EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MinimumWage     03-10 0601</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage,610</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Committee Approves Increase In Minimum Wage To $5.05 Over 4
Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM SEPPY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An increase in the federal minimum wage from
<MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour was tentatively approved <DATE>Thursday</DATE> by the
<ORGANIZATION>House Education and Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
   The original bill before the committee called for an increase of
<MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1989</DATE>, <MONEY>40 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE> and <MONEY>40 cents</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE> to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY>.
   The committee adopted, on a vote of 18-14, an amendment by Rep.
<PERSON>Carl C. Perkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ky.</LOCATION>, which added a 40-cent increase in the
fourth year, on <DATE>Dec. 31, 1991</DATE>.
   The full committee was unable to take action on all the pending
amendments and will continue debate on the bill next week.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has a companion bill, sponsored by <PERSON>Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Labor and Human Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>, which
would raise the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> over a three-year period.
   The <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> amendment was approved essentially along party lines
except that two Democrats, Reps. <PERSON>Austin J. Murphy</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Timothy J. Penny</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, joined the Republicans in
opposing the proposal.
   Murphy is chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House labor standards subcommittee</ORGANIZATION>,
which had approved an increase to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY>. He said that legislation
was ``crafted so that it will be accepted by the full <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and the
executive branch. If we accept this (<PERSON>Perkins</PERSON>) proposal, it will not
be accepted.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Stephen J. Solarz</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, read from a letter written by
<ORGANIZATION>Labor</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Ann McLaughlin</PERSON>, who said senior <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>
advisers would recommend to President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> that he veto any
legislation increasing the minimum wage.
   ``So it doesn't matter what we do, the executive will be against
it,'' <PERSON>Solarz</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee also voted 20-13 on an amendment by Rep.
<PERSON>Tommy F. Robinson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ark.</LOCATION>, to increase the ``tip credit'' for
restaurant workers.
   Current law allows employers of workers who regularly receive
tips _ such as waiters and waitresses _ to count the tips as earned
wages equivalent to <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum wage. Thus, a
restaurant owner could pay a worker <MONEY>$2.01</MONEY> an hour, with the
remaining <MONEY>$1.34</MONEY> - <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of today's <MONEY>$3.35-an-hour</MONEY> minimum wage
_ coming from tips.
   Under the <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> amendment, the tip minimum would be raised to
<PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum. Thus, if the minimum wage were increased
to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> an hour, an employer could pay a <MONEY>$2.52</MONEY> hourly wage, with
the other <MONEY>$2.52</MONEY> coming from tips.
   The biggest argument of the session came over the amendment by
<PERSON>Perkins</PERSON> who said his proposal ``does not go far enough, but it is a
start.''
   ``It gives the American worker some level of decency,'' <PERSON>Perkins</PERSON>
said.
   He said his amendment would still not bring workers up to what
is described by the federal government as the ``poverty level,'' a
family of three earning approximately <MONEY>$9,500</MONEY>.
   Rep. <PERSON>Dick Armey</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Tex.</LOCATION>, who opposes any increase in the minimum
wage because he said he would destroy jobs, proposed an amendment
to raise the base to <MONEY>$20</MONEY> an hour.
   ``I don't think we ought to be pikers,'' he said. ``It would put
minimum wage workers on the par with members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.''
   Rep. <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, the committee chairman,
called the proposal ``absurd.'' <PERSON>Armey</PERSON> said he thought the entire
discussion was absurd because the committee refused to discuss the
number of jobs that would be lost because of the minimum wage
increase.
   Armey, an economist, said different studies show anywhere from
300,000 to 800,000 job opportunities would be lost because of the
increase. <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON> said there was not support for such projections.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880317-0033 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-17-88 0414EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-MinimumWage     03-17 0611</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Committee Approves Minimum Wage Hike</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM SEPPY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moves by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to raise the federal minimum
wage this year will put presidential candidates on the spot and
force them to take a position on the issue, the chairman of the
<ORGANIZATION>House labor committee</ORGANIZATION> says.
   ``They like to say they are for a good education or a living
wage for everyone,'' said Rep. <PERSON>Augustus F. Hawkins</PERSON>. ``They will
have to discuss in detail the numbers that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> sets. They
won't be able to just say they are for a living wage.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>House Labor and Education Committee</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> ignored the
threat of a presidential veto and approved legislation to raise the
minimum wage from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> per hour to <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY> over the next four years.
   The measure, which passed after numerous Republican attempts to
weaken or gut it, now goes to the full <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This will be one of the great election issues,'' <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, said in an interview. ``Each candidate will be pinned
down.''
   The Democratic-controlled committee approved the measure by
voice vote after rejecting a Republican proposal to permit a
special ``new hire'' wage of <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour.
   <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON> said he expected the full <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> to take up the
legislation within 10 days after members return <DATE>April 11</DATE> from their
Easter recess.
similar bill during the <DATE>week of April 11</DATE>, according to its
chairman, <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass</LOCATION>.
   Labor Secretary <PERSON>Ann McLaughlin</PERSON> says senior <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> advisers
will urge President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> to veto any minimum wage increase that
would lead to a decrease in the number of job opportunities.
   The initial <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill would have raised the minimum to <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> an
hour over three years; that figure is still contained in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
bill. The administration claims the proposal would result in
elimination of 880,000 jobs because employers won't be willing to
pay their workers that much.
   Under the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> committee-passed bill, the minimum wage would go
to <MONEY>$3.85</MONEY> an hour next year, <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> in <DATE>1990</DATE>, <MONEY>$4.65</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE> and <MONEY>$5.05</MONEY>
in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   Last week, the committee added the fourth-year increase of <MONEY>40
cents</MONEY> as a substitute for ``indexing'' _ or tying _ future raises
to inflation.
   Indexing was supported by <PERSON>Hawkins</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> and organized labor,
but Democrats dropped the plan because they feared it would result
in little or no increase this year.
   The final version of the bill was sent to the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> floor after
the committee defeated, <DATE>20-13</DATE>, a proposal by Rep. <PERSON>Steve Bartlett</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>R-Texas</LOCATION>, to create a ``new hire'' or training wage by which
employers could pay new workers <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour for 90 days.
   <PERSON>Bartlett</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> told him the president would veto
any legislation not containing a lower starting wage.
   Rep. <PERSON>Matthew G. Martinez</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>, called the training wage
proposal ``a sham, a joke and a fraud.'' He said it was ``nothing
more than a way to get around the minimum wage.''
   The committee also rejected another <PERSON>Bartlett</PERSON> amendment which
would have given private employers the right to grant compensatory
time off in lieu of wages for overtime.
   Also defeated by a voice vote was an amendment by Rep. <PERSON>Thomas E.
Petri</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Wis.</LOCATION>, to permit employers to include the cost of fringe
benefits, such as health insurance, in the calculation of the
minimum wage and an amendment by Rep. <PERSON>William F. Goodling</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>,
to exempt motorcycle dealers from paying overtime.
   <PERSON>Robert McGlotten</PERSON>, legislative director of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION>, said the
committee ``recognized the need to bring this nation's working poor
to at least the poverty level by gradually raising the minimum
wage.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891117-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-17-89 2244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MinimumWage 1stLd-Writethru   11-17 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0643,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Signs Minimum Wage Increase _ to $4.25 by Spring 1991</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 11th graf, bgng: Under terms xxx to remove extraneous figure.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> signed a bill that
will raise the minimum wage from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour by the
<DATE>spring of 1991</DATE>, formally accepting the compromise that ended a year
of disagreement with congressional Democrats and organized labor.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> praised the measure, which he said would ``protect jobs and
put more money into the pockets of our workers.'' But <PERSON>Sen. Edward
M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, said it merely marked progress ``to the
50-yard line'' on the issue.
   The increase, the first since <DATE>1981</DATE>, would bring the wage to
<MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour by <DATE>April 1991</DATE>, after going to an intermediate <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY>
on <DATE>April 1, 1990</DATE>.
   The new law also includes a lower ``training wage'' for new
workers who are teen-agers, a provision sought by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> but
initially opposed by congressional Democrats.
wage to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> over three years.
   At an <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> signing ceremony attended by congressional
leaders and sponsors, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> called the new act ``a good example of
what we can do in the future on other matters.''
   ``I have called for an increase in the minimum wage that would
protect jobs and put more money into the pockets of our workers. In
my view, this bill does exactly that. I'm pleased to sign it,''
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said.
   However, <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, who supported a higher minimum, said
after the ceremony, ``I think we've arrived on the 50-yard line on
this.''
   ``It's not as much as the working poor deserve, but it was a
real compromise and it brought the president's position to one of
not saying take it or leave it,'' <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate
Labor and Human Resources Committee</ORGANIZATION>, told reporters.
   <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said a Democratic-led effort to boost the wage further
in <DATE>1992</DATE>, a presidential election year, was ``a live option.''
   Under terms of the new law, young people 16-to-19 years old who
have never worked could be paid <PERCENT>85 percent</PERCENT> of the minimum wage for
90 days. Employers with a training plan in place could pay the
young workers a training rate for 90 days more.
   The training wage can be paid to workers 16-19 years old for
their first three months of work experience and for three
additional months provided they are in certified training programs.
   The training wage would be <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour after next <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
When the minimum wage increases to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> a year later, the
subminimum would increase to <MONEY>$3.61</MONEY> an hour. The provision allowing
for the subminimum expires in <DATE>April 1993</DATE> unless extended by
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> called for a <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> minimum wage during his campaign.
   Also at the signing ceremony were <ORGANIZATION>Labor</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth
Speaker <PERSON>Thomas S. Foley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wash.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Minority Leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>R-Kan.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Minority Leader <PERSON>Robert Michel</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Ill.</LOCATION>; <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> Majority
Leader <PERSON>Richard Gephardt</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mo.</LOCATION>; Rep. <PERSON>Austin Murphy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Pa.</LOCATION>, and Rep.
<PERSON>William Goodling</PERSON>, R-Pa.
   Murphy is chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee on labor standards,
and <PERSON>Goodling</PERSON> is the senior Republican member on the <ORGANIZATION>House Education
and Labor Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891108-0279 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-08-89 1540EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-MinimumWage 2ndLd-Writethru f0131 11-08 0455</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage, 2nd Ld-Writethru, f0131,0464</SECOND>
<HEAD>Final Vote Expected to Bring First Minimum Wage Hike in Nine Years</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Restores last 4 grafs which cut off previously. This also moved
on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN KING</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Labor Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> headed today toward a final vote on
a compromise plan to raise the minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour, which
some Republicans claimed would hurt the economy and cost young
workers their jobs.
   ``There is unanimous agreement, except among politicians, that
this is not the thing to do,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Jesse Helms</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N</LOCATION>.C, citing
studies that a higher minimum wage likely would fuel inflation and
make marginal businesses less likely to hire new workers. ``So what
do politicians do? They go ahead and do it.''
   The opposition of <PERSON>Helms</PERSON> and other Republicans notwithstanding,
the compromise plan agreed to by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and congressional
Democrats was expcted to win final passage by day's end.
   The vote originally was planned for <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> but negotiations on a
plan to raise the federal debt limit stalled the minimum-wage
debate. That logjam was broken late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and the minimum-wage
bill was the first order of <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> business today.
   Several <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> senators were mulling amendments, despite an attempt
by the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration to persuade them not to offer any. If
offered, none was expected to pass but debate on them would delay a
final vote, still expected later today.
   The compromise, passed by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> last week, would raise the
wage floor for the first time since it reached <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour in <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   Labor Secretary <PERSON>Elizabeth Dole</PERSON>, in a letter <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, reminded
senators the administration supported the compromise approved by the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and ``accordingly I ask for your support of this same bill now
before the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> with no amendments attached.''
   Aides to <PERSON>Sen. Orrin Hatch</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Utah</LOCATION>, said he planned to offer an
amendment to exempt small businesses from the increase in the
minimum wage. Sen. <PERSON>Gordon Humphrey</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.H.</LOCATION>, said today he also might
offer an amendment but did not offer details.
   The minimum wage, paid to an estimated 4 million Americans, would
rise to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY> next <DATE>April 1</DATE> and to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> a year later under the
legislation.
   It also would create a subminimum for workers 16 to 19 years old
new to the job market. All workers in that age group could be paid
the subminimum for their first three months of work experience and
up to six months provided they were in certified training programs
for the final three months.
   The subminimum would be <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> when the minimum wage rose to
<MONEY>$3.80</MONEY>. It would rise to <MONEY>$3.61</MONEY> when the minimum wage rose to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY>.
The provision allowing the subminimum expires in <DATE>1993</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06092013 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06092013 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SALARY; INCREASE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Millions of Americans begin earning larger paychecks today as the federal
minimum wage jumps by 45 cents an hour to $4.25, but organized labor says the
boost falls well short of lifting many workers out of poverty.;    "They can't
support a family on this and in many cases can't support themselves," said
Rudy Oswald, chief economist of the AFL-CIO, which wants the base wage
increased to $5.75 an hour by April 1994.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  FEDERAL WAGE BASE NOW $4.25  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The increase in the minimum wage from <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY> an hour is the second step of a
two-part increase <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> enacted in <DATE>1989</DATE> after a long and fierce battle with
the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> had vetoed an earlier version he considered
too hard on businesses.;    The first step of the increase took effect a year
ago, when the minimum wage went from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY>. It was the first
increase in nearly a decade.;    <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> already has a minimum wage of
<MONEY>$4.25</MONEY>, as do <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and Oregon.;    About 3
million Americans earn the minimum wage. But millions of higher-paid workers
also may benefit because the boost could put pressure on employers to boost
their wages by comparable amounts.;    <PERSON>Sen. Edward M. Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>,
raise an "April Fool's increase, well below what low-wage workers deserve.";  
 "Just to restore the ground lost in the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> years, the minimum should be
<MONEY>$5.15</MONEY> an hour <DATE>today</DATE>," <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said. <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> should close the gap and end
"this continuing exploitation of the working poor," he said, promising that
his committee will take up minimum wage legislation this year or next.;   
Business executives dismissed the need for another boost in the minimum wage,
and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> indicated it probably would oppose another increase.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910401  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  8A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  302  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 1, 1991
00092013,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890407-0176 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-07-89 1614EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-MinimumWage     04-07 0543</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Minimum Wage,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Democrats Budge a Bit on Minimum Wage; Bush Says He Won't</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senate Democrats on <DATE>Friday</DATE> reduced the size of
the increase they are asking in the minimum wage but not enough for
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> who vowed again to veto any raise of more than <MONEY>90
cents</MONEY> over three years.
   In the second day of debate on the measure, Democrats cut by a
dime to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> the minimum wage they want in effect by <DATE>October 1991</DATE>
_ compared with the current <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> _ and agreed for the first time
to a 60-day subminimum for workers who are new on the job.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, however, declared he had ``no intention of budging one
inch'' on allowing a minimum wage that high or on accepting that
short a period during which employers could pay a ``training wage''
<PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> below the federal floor.
   ``I will veto any bill which exceeds a <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> wage level and
which does not contain a six-month training wage for new hires,''
he said in a letter <DATE>Friday</DATE> to <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> Republican Leader <PERSON>Bob Dole</PERSON>.
   Two showdown votes were scheduled for next <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> _ the first
on the latest compromise between Northern and Southern Democrats
and the second on what <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said again is his only offer.
   ``We fired our best shot and last shot and only shot first,''
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told reporters at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. ``I have no inention of
budging one inch on this. I have too much at stake.''
   The leading proponent of the wage increase, <PERSON>Sen. Edward M.
Kennedy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, appeared confident he had the 51 votes to pass
what essentially is the same bill approved by the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> last month.
But he acknowledged he lacked the two-thirds majority required to
override a veto.
   ``They've come a long way,'' he said of the administration.
``We've come a long way. I would hope they don't again lay down
this line in the sand.''
   However, <PERSON>Dole</PERSON> said many Republicans believe <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> already ``has
gone too far'' on allowing an increase.
   The latest Democratic plan was put together by <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> and Sens.
<PERSON>Bob Graham</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <PERSON>David Pryor</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>.
   Like the House-passed bill, it would provide annual 40 cent
hourly increases, to <MONEY>$3.85</MONEY> an hour on <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE>, to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> on <DATE>Oct. 1,
1990</DATE>, and to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> a year later. The orginal version called for a
<MONEY>50 cent</MONEY> increase this year.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s version calls for annual 30 cent increases, beginning
next <DATE>January</DATE> to <MONEY>$3.65</MONEY> and then up to <MONEY>$3.95</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE> and <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> in
<DATE>1992</DATE>. The minimum wage has been frozen at <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> since <DATE>1981</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and new Senate Democratic measures differ only in the
way they treat the 60-day training wage. Only if it is a worker's
first job could an employer pay the lower wage in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
version. Under the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> measure, a new worker would have to have
at least 60 days of experience in one or more jobs before his
employer would have to pay the higher scale.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s subminimum would allow employers to continue paying <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY>
to any new hire, regardless of their previousexperience, for six
months. That subminimum would rise to <MONEY>$3.40</MONEY> an hour in <DATE>1992</DATE> under
the president's proposal.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890622-0282 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-89 0218EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-MinimumWage     06-22 0326</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Minimum Wage,0339</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Democrat Offers Alternative Minimum Wage Bill</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>House Democrat</ORGANIZATION> has proposed raising the
minimum wage to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> by next year, but his attempt at breaking an
impasse between <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> contains provisions the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> has insisted it won't accept.
   Rep. <PERSON>Austin J. Murphy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Pa.</LOCATION>, introduced a revised minimum-wage
bill <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, a week after <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> vetoed legislation that would have
raised the wage from <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour to <MONEY>$4.55</MONEY> by <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> last week was unable to override the veto, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s first.
   <PERSON>Murphy</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee with jurisdiction over
the minimum wage, proposed raising the hourly minimum wage to <MONEY>$3.80</MONEY>
on <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE> and to <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> a year later.
   His final target matches that of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, although the minimum wage
would not reach <MONEY>$4.25</MONEY> an hour until <DATE>January 1992</DATE> under the
president's proposal.
   Murphy's proposal gave no ground on the issue on which the
majority Democrats in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> have their greatest
difference _ whether employers should be allowed to pay newly hired
workers a subminimum wage for an initial training period.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has said he will not support any increase in the minimum
wage unless <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> also establishes a new subminimum wage
employers could pay all new workers for up to six months.
   Democrats intially resisted any attempts to establish a
subminimum wage, but eventually included in the measure <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> vetoed
