<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890825-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-25-89 1730EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Voyager-Neptune Bjt   08-25 0892</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt,0916</SECOND>
<HEAD>Probe Unveils Triton's Ice Volcanoes, Glacier-Like Terrain, Faults</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserColor XJPL4C</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2 brushed by <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole
and photographed volcanoes that once gushed ice lava on frosty,
fault-cracked <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, revealing ``a world unlike any we've ever
seen,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``All we can say now is, wow! _ what a way to leave the solar
system,'' said <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON>,
deputy leader of Voyager's photographic imaging team.
   The one-ton space probe capped its historic 4.43-billion mile,
12-year tour of four planets when it skimmed 3,048 miles over
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, then dove past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, the
planet's largest moon. It made its closest approach about 23,900
miles above the moon's surface at <TIME>2:10 a.m PDT</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``We are witness today to truly an amazing feat of American space
technology,'' Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> told hundreds of scientists
and dignitaries <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory. ``I am exceedingly
delighted to be here on this very historic day for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s space program.''
   During its approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager discovered six moons in
addition to <LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION> and frost-covered <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, which were first
observed from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The spaceship also discovered one complete ring of debris around
the planet and a partial ring, or ring arc, scientists believe will
also prove to be a complete ring.
   Voyager's closest photos of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> were recorded on tape for
playback to earth this <DATE>weekend</DATE>, but those returned <DATE>Friday</DATE> astounded
scientists. <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> said they showed at least three volcanoes, now
inactive, that once produced flows of viscous ice _ perhaps frozen
natural gas or nitrogen ice.
   ``The images returned this morning revealed a world unlike any
we've ever seen,'' said Voyager project scientist <ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION>.
   While icy volcanic flows without associated craters have been
seen on Uranus' moon <PERSON>Ariel</PERSON> and some other moons, ``it's the first
time we've seen an icy volcano,'' Stone said, referring to one of
the huge craters on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. ``This is a real volcano.''
   But Stone noted that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s volcanoes are ``filled with ice
instead of rock. The lava flow is a flow of ice, not of rock.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> geologist <PERSON>Joseph Boyce</PERSON> said one of the ice volcanoes _ which
look like dry lakebeds filled with smooth material _ measures
several hundred miles across.
   Other <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> photos showed long fault lines, ridges, low-lying
cliffs and ``ice structures of various sorts, like glacier
terrain,'' <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> scientist <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON> said. ``They're like
things you see in polar caps on Mars.''
   ``It looks like there's all kinds of fault systems all over the
place,'' <PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> said, adding that the faults suggest
``Tritonquakes'' may have occurred at one time on the moon.
   Also visible were some meteorite impact craters, and long sets of
parallel ridges bounding apparent valleys filled with icy ``erupted
plastic masses,'' he said. The icy flows either poured down valleys
or erupted from valley floors, similar to what happens if someone is
``using a razor and slicing open the side of a toothpaste tube,''
<PERSON>Soderblom</PERSON> said.
   He said scientists don't yet know the makeup of the volcanic ices
and other ice flows, or when the volcanoes last erupted.
   Earth and <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io are the only objects in the solar
system known to have volcanoes that are currently active.
   Voyager also revealed <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has an atmosphere, as predicted.
It's content wasn't immediately determined, but <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the haze
might be like photochemical smog.
   Stone said the discovery that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s surface once was
geologically active supports the theory that the backward-orbiting
moon _ about four-fifths the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon _ once was a
comet-like, sun-orbiting object captured into orbit around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Under that theory, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> initially would have orbited <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> in
a long ellipse, but <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s gravity slowly pulled it into a
circular orbit, making <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> a semi-molten, geologically active
ball for the first billion years after its capture, he said.
   By <TIME>9 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, Voyager will be 2.753 billion miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 1.385 million miles from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding away from the
giant planet at 37,847 mph.
   The spacecraft revealed 400-mph winds in <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s bluish
atmosphere, as well as cloud ``streamers'' stretching thousands of
miles, and an assortment of storms, including an Earth-sized cyclone
called the Great Dark Spot.
   Voyager 2 was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE> and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Its trip to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> followed a
4.43-billion mile curving path, although the planet is now 2.75
billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 1 also was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE>, exploring <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>
and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE> before speeding out of the plane of the planets.
   Until its official ``near encounter'' period ends <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>, Voyager
2 will look back over its shoulder at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. Then it, like Voyager
1, will head toward interstellar space.
   ``Voyager 2 is now past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and is continuing to press
outward into the darkest and farthest region of the solar system,''
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator <PERSON>Richard Truly</PERSON> said. ``The Voyagers are destined
to wander through the Milky Way. ... What wonders they will
encounter.''
   <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, an associate administrator of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, called the
climax of the Voyager mission historic because ``it's the last time
we're seeing a planet for the first time. We've completed the
reconnaissance of the planets, except <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900210-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-10-90 1701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Voyager-Planets     02-10 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Planets,0489</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager 1 to Make Family Portrait of the Planets</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Galileo-Venus, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 1, which joined its twin
exploring the outer solar system, will snap pictures this week to
make an unprecedented family portrait of most of the planets and
the vast empty space between them.
   ``It will speak more to the mind than to the eye because of the
tremendous distances. What will be impressive will be the
distances,'' said <PERSON>Jurrie van der Woude</PERSON>, a spokesman at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet
Propulsion Laboratory.
   The complete portrait will be too large to be published, but
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> may assemble the 64 eight-by-10-inch photos into a mosaic
stretching 100 to 150 feet along a wall at the laboratory.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Uranus, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, Mars, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> will
appear as tiny dots against a background of dark space and the
constellation Eridanus.
   Mercury will be hidden by the sun's glare. <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> is too distant
to appear in any images.
   While the solar system portrait won't have scientific value, its
purpose is ``really historical,'' said <PERSON>Bob MacMillin</PERSON>, a spokesman
   ``This is not just the first time, but perhaps the only time for
decades that we'll be able to take a picture of the planets from
outside the solar system,'' said Voyager project scientist <ORGANIZATION>Edward
Stone</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager 1, which is about 3.7 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, will use
its two cameras to photograph the planets and the sun between <TIME>5:15
p.m.</TIME> and <TIME>9:20 p.m. PST Tuesday night</TIME>.
   Because of other demands on <ORGANIZATION>NASA Deep Space Network</ORGANIZATION> tracking
antennas, the photos won't be sent back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> until late <DATE>March</DATE>,
and it will be late <DATE>April</DATE> until they are processed and can be
assembled into a mosaic, <PERSON>MacMillin</PERSON> said.
   The twin Voyager spacecraft were launched from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1977</DATE> and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Voyager 2 explored
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>, Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> <DATE>last August</DATE>. Voyager 1
explored <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, then flew above the plane in which the
planets orbit the sun, known as the ecliptic plane.
   Photographing the sun for the solar system portrait may warp the
shutter blades on Voyager 1's wide-angle camera, but there are no
plans to use the camera again anyway, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Voyager 1 will take the photos for the solar system portrait by
looking down from a position 32 degrees above the ecliptic plane.
Stone said no future missions are planned that would send a
spacecraft so high above the ecliptic plane.
   Voyager 1 was chosen to make the photograph because it is in
better position that Voyager 2.
   Both spacecraft are now studying electrically charged particles
and magnetic fields as they fly toward interstellar space. They are
expected to return at least limited measurements for another 25 to
30 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900215-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-90 1122EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Galileo-Venus     02-15 0534</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo-Venus,0546</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Experiment Gets Galileo to Send Venus Photos Early</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers were unwilling to wait
until <DATE>October</DATE> to see the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft's photographs of Venus,
so they used an experimental method to get three of the pictures
sent to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> early.
   One of the photos released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> shows clouds as small as 25
miles wide as well as clouds rising from lower in the atmosphere.
It was taken <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> when the Jupiter-bound <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was about
1 million miles past <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, the second planet from the sun.
   ``You can see clouds, and you can see some very interesting
detail in the cloud patterns,'' said <PERSON>Neal Ausman</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> mission
Propulsion Laboratory. ``The engineers and scientists are
exceptionally pleased.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is scheduled to go into orbit around <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>December
1995</DATE> in a <MONEY>$1.35 billion</MONEY> mission to study the solar system's largest
planet. Just before <TIME>10 p.m. PST</TIME> <DATE>last Friday</DATE>, the spacecraft swooped
about 10,025 miles over <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> so that planet could act as a gravity
slingshot to help hurl the spacecraft on its way to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Most of the photographs and other data collected during and
after the flyby won't be sent back until <DATE>October</DATE>, when the
spacecraft is closer to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s main antenna now is furled
to protect it from the heat of the sun. A smaller antenna, which
can transmit and receive information only at a very slow rate, is
being used almost exclusively to operate the spacecraft.
   But <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers were able to get <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to send the three
photos back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by transferring separate
batches of the computer data that make up each image for radio
transmission, <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Jim Wilson</PERSON> called the technique ``experimental
and difficult.''
   <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said engineers also were able to get the spacecraft to
send back some infrared light measurements designed to study <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
lower atmosphere, as well as ultraviolet light measurements and
data from sensors designed to detect dust and magnetic fields in
space around <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>.
   By the time <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s fly-by of Venus formally ends <DATE>Friday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>, the spacecraft's television camera will have taken about 80
pictures of cloud-shrouded <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   Many other spacecraft have photographed <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, some from much
closer than <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>. But the new photos still should have
scientific value, <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was deployed from the space shuttle Atlantis last <DATE>Oct.
18</DATE> on a looping 2.4 billion, six-year route that requires <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and
Earth to be used as gravity slingshots to hurl the spacecraft to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. It will fly past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>, then again on <DATE>Dec. 8,
1992</DATE>.
   Meanwhile, in the outer reaches of the solar system, the Voyager
1 spacecraft sent radio signals indicating it had successfully
snapped photographs to make up the first group portrait of the
solar system, according to <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Mary Hardin</PERSON>.
   Voyager 1, which photographed <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1981</DATE>, was ordered to shoot the pictures <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>. But it
took five hours and 36 minutes for confirmation of the photographs
to travel the 3.7 billion miles to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hardin</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890821-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-21-89 1513EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Voyager-Neptune 3rdLd-Writethru a0523 08-21 0930</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0523,0950</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Nears Neptune For Last Planetary Flyby</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with comment from news conference,
today's planned activities. Picks up 9th graf pvs, `On its...'.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a 12-year, 4.4 billion-mile space
odyssey, Voyager 2 fired its thrusters today to take final aim
toward <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the most distant and last unexplored planet due for
a visit by a spacecraft from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the final movement in the Voyager symphony of the outer
planets,'' said Voyager project scientist <PERSON>Edward Stone</PERSON>, referring to
<ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s previous exploration of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus.
   ``We're in for a good ride, and it's great everybody can share in
the discoveries that are going to unfold in the <DATE>next week</DATE>,'' Stone
said during a <TIME>late morning</TIME> news conference.
   The small adjustment in direction today was the last needed to
target Voyager for <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s close encounter with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and
<DATE>Friday</DATE>'s flight past its largest moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The maneuver, meant
to nudge Voyager to the right and increased its speed a tiny 1.1
mph, means <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will fly closest to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> about <TIME>8:55 p.m. PDT</TIME>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory received a signal
from the spacecraft at <TIME>8:15 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> indicating the thrusters
started firing at <TIME>4:09 a.m</TIME>. It takes four hours and six minutes for
the signals to reach Earth, even at the 186,000-mile-per-second
speed of light.
   The approaching encounter with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has drawn scientists here
from all over the world.
   ``It's almost like being on a ship of discovery like <PERSON>Marco Polo</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>,'' says <PERSON>Jurrie</PERSON> van der Woude, a laboratory
spokesman.
   ``For most of us, this is the last picture show, the last foreign
shores we visit in the solar system.''
   Today's schedule of activities for Voyager included searching for
northern lights around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole, studying the planet's
turbulent weather and snapping pictures of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and another moon,
<LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION>. The probe also was programmed to make 39 images of the
region in which partial rings of debris may be orbiting the planet.
   As Voyager gets nearer to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, cable television stations will
carry live <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> broadcasts of photographs from the planet.
   On its approach to the solar system's fourth-largest planet, the
picture-snapping space probe already has discovered four moons in
addition to <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and Nereid, which had been discovered from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>,
as well as two partial rings of debris orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Voyager also discovered <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a magnetic field;
hurricane-like storms dubbed ``scooters'' with 400 mph winds;
2,700-mile-wide bands vaguely like <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s jet streams; and a
8,100-by-4,100-mile Great Dark Spot, probably a huge storm like
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> listed <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s position as of <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> as 2.743
billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 3.211 million miles from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>,
approaching the planet at 42,310 mph. Since it was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE>,
Voyager 2 has traveled a curving path totaling 4.4 billion miles.
   With no one planning a mission to <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is the last
unexplored planet that will be visited by a spacecraft from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in
the foreseeable future.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, usually the eighth planet from the sun, currently is the
ninth and most distant. Pluto follows an elongated elliptical orbit
and is closer now.
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> makes its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> by
skirting 3,000 miles above the planet's cloud tops _ much closer
than its encounters with <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus
in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   <DATE>Sunday</DATE> was the 12th anniversary of the spacecraft's launch from
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 20, 1977</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter is the climax of the
<MONEY>$865 million</MONEY>, twin-spacecraft Voyager mission, which also saw
Voyager 1 explore <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Sending Voyager to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> was like ``sinking a 2,260-mile golf
putt, assuming the golfer can make a few illegal fine adjustments
while the ball is rolling across this incredibly long green,''
according to ``The Voyager Neptune Travel Guide,'' written by
mission planning manager <PERSON>Charles Kohlhase</PERSON> and his staff.
   About 170 researchers from around the world are at the laboratory
for the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter. They will share ultimate exhilaration as
front-row observers for humanity's first close-up look at the
planet, a blue-green ball nearly four times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s diameter.
   But their excitement is tinged with nostalgia because Voyager's
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter will be the last planetary flyby for a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
spacecraft. Future probes will orbit their target planets: <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
at <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and the Mars Observer.
   Up to 8,000 photographs from Voyager's two television cameras and
discoveries by 10 other science experiments are expected to pour in
will conduct daily news conferences through <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>.
   Some scientists have said the planet may have 50 or more ring
arcs, different than the complete rings encircling <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus.
   They also say <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s magnetic field may create auroras like
<ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s northern lights, and also may trap orbiting radiation belts
similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts.
   Today's course correction was designed to assure Voyager can aim
a radio signal at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> when the probe starts to pass behind <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   By measuring changes in the signal, scientists hope to determine
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s atmospheric pressures, temperatures and chemical makeup;
whether ring arcs are made of dust, sand, pebbles or boulders; and
how material is distributed inside <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   After the encounter, Voyager II like its sister craft will
continue on its way out of the solar system. It will continue to
send data back to earth until its fuel runs out in 28 years.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900607-0017 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-07-90 0059EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SolarSystemPortrait Bjt   06-07 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Solar System Portrait, Bjt,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager Photos Show Earth as Tiny Blue Dot _ and No Life Elsewhere</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From 3.8 billion miles, the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is a blue dot
in an ocean of black.
   ``On that blue dot, that's where everyone you know, everyone you
ever heard of, every human being who ever lived, lived out their
life,'' astronomer <PERSON>Carl Sagan</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> as <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> released an
extraordinary photo taken from a vantage point in deep space.
   Voyager 1, speeding toward the edge of the solar system, looked
back in <DATE>February</DATE> and snapped photos of six of the nine planets that
whirl around the sun.
   The photograph, actually a mosaic of 64 images taken in a
four-hour period, was the last from the spacecraft. The pictures
were recorded <DATE>Feb. 13-14</DATE> but were not played back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> until
late <DATE>March</DATE> because deep-space radio receivers were occupied with
higher priority tasks.
   The camera looked down from 32 degrees above the ecliptic plane _
the track in which most of the planets orbit the sun. It captured
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Uranus, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   Mars was washed out by the sun, <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> was too close to the sun
to be photographed and <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> was too far away and too small to
appear. By happenstance, <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> was within a band of sunlight but
<PERSON>Sagan</PERSON> said it had no special significance.
   The twin spacecraft, Voyager 1 and Voyager 2, were launched in
<DATE>August</DATE> and <DATE>September 1977</DATE> from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. Between them,
they explored all the giant outer planets of the solar system, 48 of
their moons and the systems of rings and magnetic fields of those
planets.
   <ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone of the California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>, chief
scientist on the Voyager project, said he expected the Voyagers to
leave the solar system and cruise into interstellar space sometime
between the years <DATE>2000</DATE> and <DATE>2010</DATE>. Voyager 1 is heading outward at a
rate of nearly a million miles a day.
   Sagan was asked what had been learned from the Voyagers that
would change descriptions of the solar system published in
encyclopedias in <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   ``I would say you would simply tear them up,'' he replied. The
knowledge gained from the space probes ``have wholly changed our
knowledge of the solar system.''
   Stone said the greatest discovery was that Io, a moon circling
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, had active volcanoes _ the first such discovery on another
body in the solar system. The Voyagers together observed nine
volcanic eruptions on Io.
   He showed reporters time-lapse pictures that showed graphically
that other storms meld into <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot, and that
storms circle the planet moving in opposite directions.
   Voyager showed that Uranus, a planet tipped on its side, also has
a previously undiscovered magnetic field that is tilted 60 degrees
from the planet's axis of rotation.
   Sagan recalled that the first successful planetary mission
occurred when Mariner 2 flew past Venus in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   ``In 27 years the human species has flown close by or landed on
every planet in the solar system except <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>,'' he said. Still,
``we have no evidence, not a smidgen of evidence, suggesting life
anywhere else.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890706-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-06-89 0237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Voyager-Neptune Bjt   07-06 0699</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt,0716</SECOND>
<HEAD>Spacecraft Reveals Broad Bands of Clouds Encircling Neptune's Poles</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA7 of July 5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Neptune's poles may be encircled by broad
bands of dark clouds blown by jet streams like those on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, say scientists studying a new photograph from the Voyager 2
space probe.
   Two dark bands, each about 2,700 miles wide, are clearly visible
forming a collar around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s south pole. The photograph also
shows hints of similar banding around the north pole, said <PERSON>Edward
Stone</PERSON>, Voyager project scientist for <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   ``They are probably regions of clouds associated with high-speed
jet streams,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION>, a physicist and vice president at the
<ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   The planet's southern hemisphere bands stretch from 50 degrees
south latitude to 70 degrees south latitude, said <PERSON>Candice Hansen</PERSON>, a
planetary scientist at <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.
   The new photograph was taken by Voyager 2 on <DATE>June 22</DATE> when it was
57.2 million miles from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. Because of the time needed to
process an enhanced color image, it was released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by the
best color photo of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> taken so far by the Voyager 2
spacecraft.''
   Today, the spacecraft was 44.6 million miles from the remote
planet, cruising at 42,202 mph as it headed for its <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE> close
encounter with the solar system's fourth-largest planet.
   Voyager was 2.67 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, but has traveled 4.38
billion miles along its curving path since it was launched 12 years
ago.
   The photograph shows in greater detail a large dark spot _ a
cloud system bigger than the entire planet Mars _ seen in earlier
images of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. Scientists have said the 6,200-mile-wide spot
probably is a storm similar to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot or <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
hurricanes.
   Earth's jet streams are 65- to 200-mph high-altitude air currents
that zigzag across various latitudes as they blow around the globe.
The cloud bands on <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and apparently on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> are
straight belts encircling those planets. Uranus also shows faint
hints of narrower cloud bands.
   Scientists believe <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s jet streams meander across latitudinal
lines because of interference from continents and temperature
differences in the oceans.
   It may be that the bands are straight on the giant planets
because those worlds have extremely thick atmospheres with
relatively simple wind patterns, said <PERSON>Hansen</PERSON> and Caltech planetary
scientist <PERSON>Andrew Ingersoll</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s 250-mph jet streams are found along the edges of its
cloud bands, and scientists suspect the same is true on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. There is no obvious association between jet streams and
cloud bands on <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, he added.
   Stone said that on <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, and possibly <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the cloud bands
help create the jet streams and then are blown by them. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s
clouds are pushed to high altitudes by winds stirred up by heat
within the planet. They try to fall back to lower elevations by
moving north or south. But the planet's rotation deflects the
falling clouds to form jet streams, he said.
   Voyager is still too far from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> to determine if the bands
contain dark high-altitude clouds or if they are broad ribbons of
clear sky that allow Voyager to peer at dark clouds lower in
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s atmosphere, said <PERSON>Rich Terrile</PERSON>, a Jet Propulsion Laboratory
astronomer.
   Studying <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s atmosphere will give scientists ``an
understanding of the circulation pattern on a planet at one of the
most remote fringes of our solar system,'' <PERSON>Terrile</PERSON> said, adding that
knowledge of alien atmospheres ``improves our ability to understand
our own atmosphere.''
   Voyager 2 and its twin, Voyager 1, were launched from <LOCATION>Cape
Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   They explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>. Voyager 1 flew past <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>
and is headed toward interstellar space. Voyager 2 encountered
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE>, Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE> and will fly about 3,000 miles above
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole cloudtops at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>.
   Five hours later it will encounter <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s backward-orbiting
moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, at a distance of about 25,000 miles.
   Neptune usually is the eighth planet from the sun, but because of
<LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s elongated orbit <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> will be the ninth and outermost
until <DATE>2007</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890825-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-25-89 1444EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Voyager-Neptune 7thLd-Writethru a0602 08-25 1259</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, 7th Ld - Writethru, a0602,1290</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robot Explorer Encounters Neptune, Finds Ice Volcanoes On Moon Triton</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, and 11th graf pvs, `Five hours...', to CORRECT
that Voyager is a spaceship, sted satellite, since it does not orbit another
body; Picks up 6th graf, `We are...'; Lennard is cq in 8th graf.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos LA1,2,4,5,6,7,8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2 plunged over <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north
pole and <DATE>today</DATE> took its closest look at the moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, discovering
dormant ice-spewing volcanoes and snapping photos of cliffs, faults
and glacier-like lunar terrain as the spacecraft capped its epic
exploration of four planets.
   ``This is it _ we are exploring new worlds!'' laboratory
astronomer <PERSON>Rich Terrile</PERSON> said after the 12-year-old spaceship made
its historic rendezvous with the outermost planet. Neptune ``is not
a gee-whiz, science-fiction, special effects movie. It's a real
place.''
   The one-ton Voyager probe skimmed 3,048 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s icy
north pole cloud tops at <TIME>8:56 p.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE> _ the closest of its
planetary encounters _ after being accelerated by <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s gravity
to a speed of 61,148 mph.
   Its photos of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> revealed that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s major moon has
large, inactive volcanic craters, called calderas, ``filled with ice
instead of rock. The lava flow is a flow of ice, not of rock,'' said
Voyager project scientist Ed Stone.
   ``It's the first time we've seen an icy volcano,'' although
volcanic ice flows without associated craters were detected on a
moon of Uranus, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. ``This is a real volcano.''
   ``We are witness today to truly an amazing feat of American space
technology,'' Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> in a speech to
hundreds of scientists and dignitaries at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   Reiterating President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s <DATE>July</DATE> statement in support of an
eventual permanent base on the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon and a manned trip to
<ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> declared: ``We Americans have been opening new
frontiers throughout our history and we will continue to do so.
Today, space is <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s frontier.''
   <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, an associate administrator of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>, called the climax of the
Voyager mission historic because ``it's the last time we're seeing a
planet for the first time. We've completed the reconnaissance of the
planets, except <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>.''
   Five hours after the rendezvous with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, the spaceship made
its closest pass by the moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>2:10 a.m.</TIME>, a flyby that was
confirmed when signals reached <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> at <TIME>6:16 a.m. PDT</TIME>.
   The four hour and six minute delay is the time it takes Voyager's
radio signal to travel the 2.75 billion miles to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The array of information on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s largest moon had
scientists, if anything, more excited than they were about <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
itself.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> will upstage <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>. It's filled with hummocky,
rippling terrain,'' <PERSON>Terrile</PERSON> said.
   ``It looks like there's all kinds of fault systems all over the
place,'' said <PERSON>Laurence Soderblom</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Geological Survey</ORGANIZATION>. The
faults suggest that ``Triton quakes'' may have occurred at one time
on the moon.
   Later, <PERSON>Joseph Boyce</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> geologist, said there was ``abundant
evidence of ice volcanism'' in the latest pictures. He referred to
volcanoes that once spewed frozen natural gas or other ice-like
substance rather than molten rock.
   Voyager's newest photos of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> received <TIME>this morning</TIME> showed a
smooth feature, looking somewhat like a dry lakebed, that <PERSON>Boyce</PERSON> said
measured several hundred miles across.
   ``It looked like it could be a ... crater of a volcano itself,''
<PERSON>Boyce</PERSON> said. ``It looks like some sort of feature flooded by
material, and the material is probably volcanic material.''
   The Voyager mission found similar evidence of icy volcanic flows
on Uranus' moon <PERSON>Ariel</PERSON> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, and earlier found active
sulfur-spewing volcanoes on Io, a moon of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Boyce</PERSON> emphasized there is no evidence yet that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s icy
volcanism is currently active, but said the smooth floor of the
crater, unmarked by meteorite impact craters, indicates that the ice
volcano may have been active within the last million years or so.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Bradford Smith</PERSON>, head of Voyager's photographic imaging
team at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory, had described <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s
surface in photos taken <DATE>Thursday</DATE> as ``extremely strange and
puzzling.''
   The photos showed long fault lines, ridges, low-lying cliffs and
``ice structures of various sorts, like glacier terrain,'' scientist
<PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON> said.
   While difficult to interpret, the early photos of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> gave
``the same impression as if you stepped out onto some strange and
alien surface,'' with what appears to be a blue, pink and white
topography that is ``closer to flat than big mountains,'' said
<PERSON>Smith</PERSON>, who called the pictures ``Just short of spectacular.''
   At <TIME>11:59 p.m. PDT</TIME>, signals were received showing that Voyager had
been bombarded by dust particles up to 100 times a second as it
passed through the plane containing <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s rings, said <PERSON>Donald
Gurnett</PERSON>. The particles, each about a millionth of a yard across _
the size of the particles in cigarette smoke _ did not damage the
spacecraft, <PERSON>Gurnett</PERSON> said.
   Voyager's safe progress through the ring plane prompted
scientists to toast each other with champagne even before the
spaceship's near encounter with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said.
   ``There's certainly euphoria,'' he said. ``We are all very
excited.''
   Scientists announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that Voyager discovered two more
tiny moons orbiting the solar system's fourth-largest planet: a
60-mile-wide moon designated <DATE>1989</DATE> N5, and the even smaller <DATE>1989</DATE> N6,
which is a mere 30 miles wide.
   That brought the number of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s moons discovered before the
close encounter to eight, including the two moons detected from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> _ <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and Nereid _ and four found earlier by Voyager.
   Voyager also found a complete ring of debris encircling <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>,
although it was at first thought to be a partial ring or ring arc.
Voyager photos also indicated a ring arc orbiting farther from
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> almost certainly also is a complete ring.
   During its flight past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, Voyager was programmed
to shoot radio waves through the atmospheres of both worlds to study
their atmospheres; measure changes in distant starlight to study the
rings and search for others; and take its best but still
2.9-million-mile-distant pictures of Nereid.
   Voyager's hectic schedule also included numerous measurements of
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s atmosphere in an effort to understand its 400-mph winds,
high-altitude clouds, and its Earth-sized Great Dark Spot and other
cyclones.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> calculated <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION>'s position during the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> flyby as
nearly 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. But the ship had traveled a
curving path totaling 4.43 billion miles since it was launched in
<DATE>1977</DATE>, and explored <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in
<DATE>1986</DATE>.
   Champagne flowed at the laboratory <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when Voyager crossed
the supersonic shock wave where the solar wind meets <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
magnetic field.
   Earlier pictures of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> suggested the backward-orbiting moon
had meteorite impact craters and possibly glaciers of frozen natural
gas on its pink-and-blue surface.
   Using occasional trajectory corrections and engineering wizardry
to aim a space probe built with <DATE>1960s</DATE> technology, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> they got Voyager to within 20 miles of where it was
supposed to be after the long journey.
   ``Not bad shooting,'' said one engineer.
   Voyager 1 visited <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE>, and now is
speeding toward interstellar space _ just as Voyager 2 will do after
it stops studying <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
   Neptune usually is the eighth planet from the sun, but <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s
elliptical orbit means it now is closer, making <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> temporarily
the solar system's outmost planet.
   ``Someday there ought to be a <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> flyby,'' <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. ``But
there are no active plans to do that.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900210-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-10-90 0107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo-Venus 2ndLd-Writethru a0787 02-10 0998</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Venus, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0787,1020</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Jupiter-Bound Galileo Spacecraft Swings Past Venus</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with spacecraft making closest
approach to Venus; picks up 4th graf, `That started ...' Stands for
AMs.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY86</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spaceship swooped past Venus
early <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, and the cloud-shrouded planet acted as a gravity
slingshot to help hurl the craft toward its <DATE>1995</DATE> rendezvous with
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Engineers at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory received a radio
signal confirming that the 2.8-ton spacecraft made its closest
approach to Venus at <TIME>12:59 a.m. EST</TIME>, cruising 10,028 miles above
the planet's hellishly hot surface.
   ``We have just flown through our closest approach point to
Venus,'' said <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>, science and mission design manager.
``The greatest challenge of getting <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> has been
met.''
   Four hours before the close encounter, radio signals received on
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> confirmed the spacecraft computer ordered <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared
light sensor to start observing <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. The instrument was looking
for the glow of the hot lower atmosphere backlighting cooler clouds
overhead, <PERSON>O'Neil</PERSON> said.
   That started an eight-hour period of intensive photography and
measurements, including a photographic search for lightning.
Earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> studied dust particles and magnetic fields
in space, and measured Venusian atmospheric temperatures.
   ``The Venus encounter is our first major milestone in the
mission,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> project scientist <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>. ``After
the encounter, we have gained enough energy out of this celestial
billiard shot to get the energy we need to make it all the way to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.''
   The power the spacecraft gains in the flyby is triple the energy
of its propellant supply, said mission director <PERSON>Neal Ausman</PERSON>.
   The <MONEY>$1.35 billion</MONEY> mission will let <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> examine <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, its
moon and one or two asteroids before the spacecraft separates into
an orbiter and a small probe in <DATE>July 1995</DATE>. In <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, they
arrive at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's largest planet, after a
2.4-billion-mile trip, including 182 million miles to reach <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was deployed from the space shuttle Atlantis last <DATE>Oct.
18</DATE>.
   Venus circles the sun between the orbits of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION>,
the closest planet to the sun. Acid-laden clouds extend 40 miles
above the surface, trapping heat in a runaway ``greenhouse effect''
that raised surface temperatures to 900 degrees Fahrenheit.
Atmospheric pressure is 90 times that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Venus is about <PERCENT>95
percent</PERCENT> as wide as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Scientists suspect it may have active
volcanoes and shifting plates on its crust.
   The Venus flyby was designed purely to give <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> a boost for
its trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> by increasing its speed from 83,750 mph to
88,740 mph. In two other ``gravity assist'' maneuvers, the
spacecraft will use the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as a slingshot next <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and again
on <DATE>Dec. 8, 1992</DATE>, so it will be properly aimed toward <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said.
   Scientists decided to take advantage of the Venus encounter by
having <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s camera and instruments make photographs and
measurements of Venus starting <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and continuing for a
week.
   But almost all the pictures and data _ stored on three tracks of
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s four-track tape recorder _ won't be sent back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
until <DATE>October</DATE>, when the spacecraft is close enough to transmit the
material with its low-gain antenna. That antenna now can be used
only for communications to keep <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> operating.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s main umbrella-shaped antenna must remain furled to
protect it from sunlight until after the craft makes its first
flight past <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was programmed to photograph <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and study the planet
with its ultraviolet, infrared and visible light sensors to look
for lightning, study the makeup of the carbon dioxide atmosphere,
examine cloud and wind patterns, map cloudtop temperatures and peer
at the lower atmosphere.
   Sensors that detect particles and magnetic fields were
programmed to study how solar wind interacts with <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
atmosphere. At the same time, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> arranged for the <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer Venus
Orbiter</ORGANIZATION>, circling <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> since <DATE>1978</DATE>, to make similar measurements
closer to the planet, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   While nearly 20 other <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet spacecraft have visited
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, ``we think we're going to get some real good stuff,'' he
said.
   But scientists won't know for months unless engineers meet
success next week when they try to have <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> send back a small
amount of data, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> added.
   Studies from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and previous spacecraft indicate <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> has
continent-sized highlands with peaks dwarfing <LOCATION>Mount Everest</LOCATION> and
hundreds of thousands of volcanoes stretching across lowland plains.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, launched from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> <DATE>last May 4</DATE>,
will go into orbit around Venus in <DATE>August</DATE>. It will use radar to
peer through the clouds and map at least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>'
surface during a <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> mission.
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe and orbiter reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the probe will
parachute into the atmosphere and make measurements until intense
heat and pressure vaporize it. The orbiter will photograph and
study <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and its major moons until late <DATE>1997</DATE>, circling the
planet instead of flying past it like the Pioneer and Voyager
planned to send <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> on a two-year trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> by launching
it with a <ORGANIZATION>Centaur</ORGANIZATION> rocket after it was released from a shuttle.
   But the <DATE>1986</DATE> explosion that destroyed Challenger and killed
seven crew members raised safety concerns. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> decided against
using the volatile, liquid-fueled Centaur.
   So <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched with a much weaker <ORGANIZATION>Inertial Upper Stage</ORGANIZATION>
booster after it was deployed by Atlantis' crew. The weaker rocket
required <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to redesign <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s route so the craft could
utilize gravity from <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and Earth for a much longer, looping
trip to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>.
   Environmentalists failed in court to stop <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> from having a
shuttle carry <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> into space. They feared a Challenger-like
explosion could contaminate <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with plutonium in <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s
nuclear batteries, which are not reactors but generate electricity
using heat from the radioactive decay of plutonium. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the
risk was minimal.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> is named for the Italian Renaissance astronomer who
discovered <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s major moons.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890419-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-89 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-ReturntothePlanets Adv23-2Takes   04-19 0902</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Return to the Planets, Adv 23 - 2 Takes,0917</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, April 23, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Back to the Planets _ Shuttle Carrying Venus-Bound Craft</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Story is complete in one take; optional 1st Add is for editors
desiring more detail and background</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The shuttle Atlantis is set to soar
into space <DATE>Friday</DATE> to rekindle an American planetary exploration
program that has languished for a decade because of budget cuts and
the Challenger accident.
   The cargo is the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft which has a radar system
powerful enough to pierce the dense sulfuric acid clouds of Venus
and map its surface. The mission costs <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> and the radar
images could reveal much about the history of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and the
evolution of our own <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Liftoff is scheduled for <TIME>2:24 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and six hours later,
<PERSON>Atlantis</PERSON>' five astronauts are to release <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> on the start of a
466-day outward journey to the mysterious planet.
   No American planetary spacecraft has been launched since the
Pioneer-Venus probe in <DATE>1978</DATE>, and <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will be the first
planet-bound vehicle to be dispatched from the space shuttle.
   When the 7,000-pound payload reaches <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>, it is
to fire into orbit and start its 243-day mapping assignment.
   ``The goal is to obtain radar images of at least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of
the planet,'' said <PERSON>Stephen Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project scientist at
   He said the images could help scientists understand how Venus
was formed and might provide an answer to the puzzling question of
how Earth and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, evolved so differently even though at the
beginning of the solar system they were almost identical. At the
Venusian surface, the temperature is 900 degrees Fahrenheit and the
atmospheric pressure is 90 times greater than that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> pictures might answer questions about
the extent of volcanic activity and settle disputes over whether
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> once had oceans of water and whether it has shifting crustal
plates similar to those on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The radar is designed to produce images showing features as
small as 150 yards across. In comparison, the <DATE>1978</DATE> Pioneer-Venus
probe could not distinguish features smaller than 60 miles across.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is the first of two planetary craft scheduled for
launching from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> this year. The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> is
to set forth in <DATE>October</DATE>.
   The two spacecraft have been in development for more than a
decade. They initially were delayed by budget cuts resulting from a
slowdown in the space program after the completion of the Apollo
man-to-the-moon program.
   They finally were assigned to shuttle missions set for liftoff
in <DATE>1986</DATE>. But those flights were derailed after Challenger exploded
in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>, grounding the shuttle fleet for nearly three years.
   ``It's been a long time coming,'' <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   The first manmade spacecraft to probe another planet was
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>'s Venera 1, which scouted Venus in <DATE>1961</DATE>. In the years that
followed, a parade of these vehicles, each more sophisticated than
the last, pushed deep into the solar system to take the pulse of
our planetary neighbors.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has successfully sent five probes to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
six to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, four to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, three to <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, and one each to
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. And in <DATE>August</DATE>, the long-traveling Voyager 2 is
to take the first closeup look at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has sent 19 successful spacecraft to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and
nine to Mars. Its most recent and most ambitious probes both failed
_ Phobos 1 <DATE>last September</DATE> while en route to Mars and Phobos 2 as it
was starting its exploration from Martian orbit last month.
   Soviet engineers have not perfected the long-term
nuclear-powered batteries needed to travel to the outer planets.
The Soviet craft employ solar panels which draw electrical power
from the sun. But at distant <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and Uranus,
these panels would be too far from the sun to be effective.
   At their destinations, some of these robot marvels skim close,
snapping pictures and gathering a few days of data before soaring
on to another planet or into interstellar space; some orbit their
targets to examine them at length, and some descend to the surface.
   What they collect is flashed as binary bits to Earth-bound
computers, which translate the unknown into recognizable places
filled with surprises and secrets. Vague speculations of the past
have been replaced by solid scientific findings.
   Humans have caught their first views and hints of the great
storm systems and rings of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>; the active volcanoes on its
salt-covered moon, Io; the parched and cratered wasteland of
Mercury; ancient river bottoms, raging winds and an inactive
volcanoe almost 80,000 feet high on Mars; sulfuric acid clouds,
lightning and the hellish temperatures on Venus; the thousand rings
and tantalizing moons of <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>; a scalding 6,000-mile deep ocean
beneath the cloudtops of Uranus.
   From these flights, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is assembling a vast mosaic about the
solar system and its intricate workings. A basic goal is to learn
more about planet <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, fitting it into the cosmic puzzle that is
the origin, the evolution and the structure of the universe.
   Some astronomers believe, for example, that Mars may today
represent an earlier evolutionary state of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> when its
atmosphere was being formed, and that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> may represent what
might happen to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> if its surface temperature were to rise
significantly.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890702-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-02-89 2351EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-EXP--Voyager-Neptune     07-02 1152</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-EXP--Voyager-Neptune,1181</SECOND>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Approaches Neptune for Grand Finale of Solar System Trek</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twelve years, three planets and 4.4
billion miles after leaving <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 is converging on
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, a swirling, blue-green planet with a backward moon, for the
last stop on an extraordinary tour.
   ``The solar system is our neighborhood, and we're getting to the
end of the neighborhood,'' said <PERSON>Norm Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Admnistration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   Voyager 2 already has detected a dark spot on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> that may be
a giant storm like <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. As it nears the planet,
the probe will search for undiscovered moons and partial rings. And
at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will swoop within 3,000 miles of
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole cloudtops _ the closest of its close encounters
and the first spacecraft to visit the planet.
   It will be 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after traveling 4.43
billion miles along its curving path. The information it sends back
at the speed of light will take four hours and six minutes to arrive.
   Five hours after the closest encounter, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will fly within
25,000 miles of the backwards-orbiting moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The other known
moon is Nereid.
   Voyager 1 and 2, laden with TV cameras and an array of sensors,
were launched from <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. They visited <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1979</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1981</DATE>, respectively. Voyager 2 reached
Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Voyager 1 now is heading toward interstellar space.
   Voyager 1 and 2 returned 65,000 photographs of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>
and their moons and rings. Voyager 2 sent back 8,000 pictures of
Uranus and its moons, and will take another 8,000 of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   At a cost <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> pegged at <MONEY>$865 million</MONEY> through the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
encounter, the Voyagers ``returned more new knowledge about the
outer planets ... than existed in all of the preceding history of
astronomy,'' according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, discovered in <DATE>1846</DATE>, is 30,700 miles in diameter _ six
times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s size and the fourth largest planet after <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. A Neptunian year lasts 165 Earth years, and a day
lasts 17 to 18 Earth hours _ a detail Voyager may pinpoint. Neptune
usually is the eighth planet, but because of <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s elongated orbit
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> will be the ninth and outermost until <DATE>2007</DATE>.
   Scientists expect Voyager to discover at least 10 small moons,
said deputy project scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON>.
   Some moons may confine or shepherd the 5- to 12-mile-wide
incomplete rings, called ``ring arcs,'' orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, said
physicist Ed Stone, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Voyager project scientist and a vice
president at <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager also may discover dust bands and 50 to 100 partial rings
in addition to the three to six arcs scientists believe they
detected from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Stone added. The partial rings, possibly made
of dust and pebbles, most likely are debris from the collision of a
comet and an ancient moon, he said.
   Voyager should be some 33,400 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s clouds when
it crosses the ring region, so it is unlikely to be destroyed by an
unseen arc, he said.
   The probe also will study <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s weather. Scientists believe
the 6,200-mile-wide dark spot it found probably is similar to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes or <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. The source of the
internal heat driving <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s storms is a mystery; Earth's comes
decaying radioactive material in rocks.
   Neptune is pale blue-green because methane, or natural gas, in
its mostly hydrogen-helium atmosphere absorbs red light. Scientists
suspect that a third of the way toward the planet's center the
atmosphere becomes a superhot slurry of hot water and rock, so
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ like neighboring Uranus _ probably lacks a distinct
sky-sea boundary, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Despite any internal heat, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> receives 900 times less
sunlight than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, so the temperature at the top of its atmosphere
is 350 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, about the same as on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> _ 1,400 to 2,240 miles wide, roughly
the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon _ will be the most fascinating part of
Voyager's flyby.
   When a planet and its moons form from a spinning disk of gas and
solid material, the moons should orbit in the direction the planet
rotates. <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s reverse orbit suggests it once orbited the sun
like a comet or a planet but collided with a moon to form a new
backwards-moving satellite, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> probably is cold and geologically inactive, with an icy
mantle over a rocky core. But it once may have had a molten interior
that created ridges, valleys, cliffs, canyons and volcanoes that
Voyager might photograph.
   Observations from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> indicate <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere contains
methane and nitrogen. Sunlight likely converts methane into complex
hydrocarbons, creating a transparent reddish-orange photochemical
haze, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. The hydrocarbons may form heavier particles,
coating the surface with frozen sludge.
   Could the organic chemicals have allowed life to develop on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>?
   ``The temperature is very, very cold, so I think it's unlikely,''
he said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has extreme seasons because its orbit
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is highly inclined: One pole faces the sun for 82
years and the other remains in darkness. This may mean <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s
atmosphere gets thinner and thicker as methane-nitrogen icecaps
cover one pole, then the other.
   Researchers discarded the theory that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has liquid nitrogen
oceans, but puddles or lakes are possible, along with fields of
nitrogen ice crystals, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Nereid, about 190 to 620 miles wide, has a very elongated
elliptical orbit. Caltech astrophysicist <PERSON>Peter Goldreich</PERSON> speculates
Nereid once had a circular orbit that was disturbed by gravity from
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> or a large passing object.
   If Voyager confirms that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a magnetic field, the planet
also may have an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s, and a mysterious ultraviolet
``electroglow.'' A magnetic field should trap a radiation belt
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s
radiation belts damaged some of Voyager's equipment; <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> doubts
similar problems at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 2 has worked 12 years with only relatively minor
failures, although it contains electronics equal to 10,000
television sets, he said.
   Commands sent to <LOCATION>Voyager</LOCATION>, and photos and information it sends to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, travel at the speed of light. But the one-way trip still take
four hours, six minutes. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is using 38 dish-shaped radio antennas
in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to capture the
radio signal, which is like trying to see a 20-watt light bulb
burning 2.75 billion miles away.
   ``Both Voyagers are expected to return valuable data well into
the 21st century'' before their power supplies run out in about
<DATE>2020</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   After <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 will join Voyager 1 and Pioneers 10 and
11 in seeking the true edge of the solar system, where solar wind
gives way to interstellar wind billions of miles beyond the planets.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891206-0037 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-06-89 0640EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Voyager-Neptune     12-06 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune,0728</SECOND>
<HEAD>More Active Volcanoes Found on Triton; Neptune Has 1,500 mph Winds</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Up to four more active ice volcanoes on
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> were discovered in snapshots taken by Voyager
2, which found the planet itself is swept by 1,500 mph winds _ the
fastest yet seen in the solar system.
   Because the spacecraft photographed at least two and possibly
five of the geyser-like volcanoes erupting on only a portion of
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, ``chances are that there are a dozen of these things going
off globally'' at any time, said <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, a planetary
   Confirmation of the first active volcano was announced <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>
after scientists analyzed photos Voyager 2 snapped during its <DATE>Aug.
24-25</DATE> flight past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   Detection of more such volcanoes _ which spew nitrogen ice and
gas 5 miles high and 90 miles downwind _ was announced <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
during a news conference at the <ORGANIZATION>American Geophysical Union</ORGANIZATION>'s fall
meeting.
   <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> is only the third world in the solar system known to have
active volcanism. The others are Earth and <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io, which
has sulfur-spewing volcanoes. Scientists suspect there are
volcanoes on cloud-shrouded Venus.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s jet-stream winds push frozen clouds of natural gas
past the north edge of the planet's Earth-size, hurricane-like
Great Dark Spot at nearly 1,500 mph, Voyager project scientist
<ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION> told reporters. That's about the speed of sound in
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s atmosphere.
   ``These are the fastest we've observed,'' easily exceeding the
previous record winds of 1,100 mph in <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s jet stream, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION>
said. ``These almost may be supersonic winds ... a wind which is
Mach 1.''
   The speed of sound on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is about 700 mph, depending on
temperature and altitude. It's much faster on planets with colder
atmospheres containing gases lighter than those in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s air.
   The clouds racing in <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s winds could be seen in a movie
made by computer from still photographs taken by Voyager. Also
shown at <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s news conference was another computer movie
clearly showing two of the dark volcanic plumes on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s largest moon and the coldest known object in the solar
system.
   The plumes rise like columns, each forming a cloud that drifts
back and forth as it is blown downwind. A shadow cast by one cloud
also is visible.
   The movie also shows what scientists suspect are two or three
more plumes, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   When Voyager swept past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> early <DATE>Aug. 25</DATE>, scientists saw
streaks on dark material deposited on the moon's surface by what
they believed were active nitrogen-ice volcanoes.
was sure there was one active volcano after conducting stereoscopic
analysis of the photos.
   But the images were so fuzzy ``you had to take our word for
it,'' <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   So <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> used a computer to overlap still photos taken from
different angles and replay them in sequence repeatedly. The
resulting movie revealed additional volcanic plumes.
   The causes of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s nitrogen ice volcanoes and <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s high
winds are mysterious.
   Stone described one theory on the volcanoes: Darker material
settles on the moon's surface, then is covered by transparent
nitrogen ice. Sunlight penetrates the ice, and warms the darker
material beneath. But the heat cannot escape through the ice, so
some of the buried ice melts into gas, causing pressure to build
until the gas erupts upward through cracks, carrying ice and dark
material with it.
   Neptune gets 900 times less sunlight than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Scientists are
perplexed about how the internal heat left over from <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
formation is enough to drive 700-mph winds in the Great Dark Spot,
not to mention the 1,500-mph jet stream winds blowing between 15
and 20 degrees south latitude, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Part of the explanation may be that the flow of fluid gases in
the planet's atmosphere may be so smooth that little energy is
needed to power high winds, he said.
   Voyager 2's Neptune-Triton exploration capped a 12-year mission
in which it flew past <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. The spacecraft
discovered six moons at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, bringing the total to eight, and
found several rings of debris orbiting the planet, which is 30
times farther from the sun than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890629-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-29-89 1246EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--Voyager-Neptune Adv03   06-29 1164</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Voyager-Neptune, Adv 03,1195</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv03</HEAD>
<HEAD>For release Monday, July 3, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Voyager 2 Approaches Neptune for Grand Finale of Solar System Trek</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Twelve years, three planets and 4.4
billion miles after leaving <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 is converging on
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, a swirling, blue-green planet with a backward moon, for the
last stop on an extraordinary tour.
   ``The solar system is our neighborhood, and we're getting to the
end of the neighborhood,'' said <PERSON>Norm Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager
at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Admnistration</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory.
   Voyager 2 already has detected a dark spot on <ORGANIZATION>Nep</ORGANIZATION>
a giant storm like <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. As it nears the planet,
the probe will search for undiscovered moons and partial rings. And
at <TIME>9 p.m. PDT</TIME> on <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will swoop within 3,000 miles oftune
that may be
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s north pole cloudtops _ the closest of its close encounters
and the first spacecraft to visit the planet.
   It will be 2.75 billion miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after traveling 4.43
billion miles along its curving path. The information it sends back
at the speed of light will take four hours and six minutes to arrive.
   Five hours after the closest encounter, <ORGANIZATION>Voyager</ORGANIZATION> will fly within
25,000 miles of the backwards-orbiting moon, <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. The other known
moon is Nereid.
lion through the <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
encounter, the Voyagers ``returned more new knowledge about the
outer planets ... than existed in all of the preceding history of
astronomy,'' according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, discovered in <DATE>1846</DATE>, is 30,700 miles in diameter _ six
times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s size and the fourth largest planet after <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. A Neptunian year lasts 165 Earth years, and a day
lasts 17 to 18 Earth hours _ a detail Voyager may pinpoint. Neptune
usually is the eighth planet, but because of <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>'s elongated orbit
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> will be the ninth and outermost until <DATE>2007</DATE>.
   Scientists expect Voyager to discover at least 10 small moons,
said deputy project scientist <PERSON>Ellis Miner</PERSON>.
   Some moons may confine or shepherd the 5- to 12-mile-wide
incomplete rings, called ``ring arcs,'' orbiting <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, said
physicist Ed Stone, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Voyager project scientist and a vice
president at <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Voyager also may discover dust bands and 50 to 100 partial rings
in addition to the three to six arcs scientists believe they
detected from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, Stone added. The partial rings, possibly made
of dust and pebbles, most likely are debris from the collision of a
comet and an ancient moon, he said.
   Voyager should be some 33,400 miles above <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s clouds when
it crosses the ring region, so it is unlikely to be destroyed by an
unseen arc, he said.
   The probe also will study <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s weather. Scientists believe
the 6,200-mile-wide dark spot it found probably is similar to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s hurricanes or <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s Great Red Spot. The source of the
internal heat driving <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s storms is a mystery; Earth's comes
decaying radioactive material in rocks.
   Neptune is pale blue-green because methane, or natural gas, in
its mostly hydrogen-helium atmosphere absorbs red light. Scientists
suspect that a third of the way toward the planet's center the
atmosphere becomes a superhot slurry of hot water and rock, so
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> _ like neighboring Uranus _ probably lacks a distinct
sky-sea boundary, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Despite any internal heat, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> receives 900 times less
sunlight than <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, so the temperature at the top of its atmosphere
is 350 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, about the same as on <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> _ 1,400 to 2,240 miles wide, roughly
the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon _ will be the most fascinating part of
Voyager's flyby.
   When a planet and its moons form from a spinning disk of gas and
solid material, the moons should orbit in the direction the planet
rotates. <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s reverse orbit suggests it once orbited the sun
like a comet or a planet but collided with a moon to form a new
backwards-moving satellite, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> probably is cold and geologically inactive, with an icy
mantle over a rocky core. But it once may have had a molten interior
that created ridges, valleys, cliffs, canyons and volcanoes that
Voyager might photograph.
   Observations from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> indicate <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere contains
methane and nitrogen. Sunlight likely converts methane into complex
hydrocarbons, creating a transparent reddish-orange photochemical
haze, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said. The hydrocarbons may form heavier particles,
coating the surface with frozen sludge.
   Could the organic chemicals have allowed life to develop on
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>?
   ``The temperature is very, very cold, so I think it's unlikely,''
he said.
   Scientists believe <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has extreme seasons because its orbit
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is highly inclined: One pole faces the sun for 82
years and the other remains in darkness. This may mean <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s
atmosphere gets thinner and thicker as methane-nitrogen icecaps
cover one pole, then the other.
   Researchers discarded the theory that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> has liquid nitrogen
oceans, but puddles or lakes are possible, along with fields of
nitrogen ice crystals, <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Nereid, about 190 to 620 miles wide, has a very elongated
elliptical orbit. Caltech astrophysicist <PERSON>Peter Goldreich</PERSON> speculates
Nereid once had a circular orbit that was disturbed by gravity from
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> or a large passing object.
   If Voyager confirms that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> has a magnetic field, the planet
also may have an aurora like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s, and a mysterious ultraviolet
``electroglow.'' A magnetic field should trap a radiation belt
around <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> similar to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s Van <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> belts. <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s
radiation belts damaged some of Voyager's equipment; <PERSON>Haynes</PERSON> doubts
similar problems at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Voyager 2 has worked 12 years with only relatively minor
failures, although it contains electronics equal to 10,000
television sets, he said.
   Commands sent to <LOCATION>Voyager</LOCATION>, and photos and information it sends to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, travel at the speed of light. But the one-way trip still take
four hours, six minutes. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is using 38 dish-shaped radio antennas
in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to capture the
radio signal, which is like trying to see a 20-watt light bulb
burning 2.75 billion miles away.
   ``Both Voyagers are expected to return valuable data well into
the 21st century'' before their power supplies run out in about
<DATE>2020</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   After <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, Voyager 2 will join Voyager 1 and Pioneers 10 and
11 in seeking the true edge of the solar system, where solar wind
gives way to interstellar wind billions of miles beyond the planets.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for July 3</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890829-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-89 0049EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Voyager-Neptune Bjt   08-29 0713</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt,0735</SECOND>
<HEAD>Last-Minute Adjustments Saved Voyager's Photos of Icy Triton</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: News briefing 12:30 p.m. EDT; top prospects uncertain.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager's pictures of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s moon
<ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> _ which revealed a unique world of icy volcanoes _ might have
been washed out if not for last-minute adjustments to the
spacecraft's cameras, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> says.
   ``It wouldn't have wiped out the mission, but would have made a
lot of photographs embarrassingly overexposed,'' said <PERSON>Rich Terrile</PERSON>,
Jet Propulsion Laboratory. ``It would have been an incredible
disappointment.''
   ``They would have been white images,'' Voyager project scientist
<ORGANIZATION>Edward Stone</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Meanwhile, scientists said the spacecraft found that <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> is
the coldest body ever measured in the solar system, and that <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
has something in common with <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>: smog.
   Only days before Voyager made its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>
<DATE>last Thursday</DATE> and zipped past <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, scientists
recognized that the frosty surface of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s largest moon
reflected much more light than originally expected, said <PERSON>Mary Beth
Murrill</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman.
   Engineers compensated by sending Voyager new computer commands
reducing the exposure time on its television cameras from 6.68
seconds to 3.84 seconds for the best close-ups of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Murrill</PERSON>
said.
   Those photographs revealed that giant craters, called calderas,
once oozed an icy form of lava that flooded thousands of square
miles of lunar terrain. They also found what scientists believe are
active ice volcanoes that explosively propel frozen nitrogen
particles 20 miles skyward.
   During its <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter, Voyager's cameras discovered six
moons in addition to <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Nereid</LOCATION>, which were discovered from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. They also found three thin rings of debris and five broad
rings encircling the solar system's fourth-largest planet.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers are investigating the feasibility of reprogramming
Voyager to take a snapshot of the entire solar system sometime in
the coming months, said <PERSON>Lanny Miller</PERSON>, manager of the flight
engineering office.
   By <TIME>9 p.m. PDT tonight</TIME>, Voyager will be 2.76 billion miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and 4.55 million miles behind <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, speeding toward the
edge of the solar system at 37,568 mph.
   Voyager 2's ultraviolet detector determined <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>'s surface
temperature is 400 degrees below zero Fahrenheit, making the moon
``the coldest body we have seen in the solar system,'' said <PERSON>Roger
Yelle</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION>.
   Scientists believe <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION> and its moon <PERSON>Charon</PERSON> are the
second-coldest bodies in the solar system.
   Voyager also found smog on <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   Sunlight hitting natural gas, or methane, high in the planet's
atmosphere converts it into a 90-mile-thick icy layer of
photochemical smog at the bottom of <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s stratosphere, said <PERSON>Jim
Pollock</PERSON>, an imaging team member from <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ames Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   ``Photochemical smog exists any place we've been that has an
atmosphere,'' imaging team leader <PERSON>Bradford Smith</PERSON> said of other
planets and moons.
   ``In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, the problem is it's happening way down low
where we have to breathe it in amounts exceeding anything we've seen
except on Titan,'' he said, referring to <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s smoggy moon.
   In another finding, the best close-up shot of the Neptunian moon
<DATE>1989</DATE> N1 showed it has a huge crater half the width of its
lumpy-looking, 240-mile-wide surface.
   That indicates that a big meteorite once smacked into <DATE>1989</DATE> N1,
one of the six moons discovered by Voyager since <DATE>June</DATE>, <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said.
   Voyager found earlier that <DATE>1989</DATE> N1 really is <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s
second-largest moon after <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>. Scientists previously thought
Nereid was No. 2.
   Instruments aboard Voyager discovered <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is encircled by
electrically charged particles that form a giant doughnut shape,
called a torus.
   The torus is created by gases coming off of <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Ralph
orbited by a similar torus of sulfur particles spewed by sulfur
volcanoes on the Jovian moon Io.
   The space probe also found <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION> have auroras
vaguely like <ORGANIZATION>Earth</ORGANIZATION>'s northern and southern lights. They glow in
ultraviolet light wavelengths invisible to the human eye, however,
unlike <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s visible auroras.
   Voyager's close encounter with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> capped its epic
tour of the four outer planets, including <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and
Uranus. The probe was launched in <DATE>1977</DATE> along with its twin, Voyager
1, which explored only <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901129-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-29-90 1818EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Galileo-Earth     11-29 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Galileo-Earth,0543</SECOND>
<HEAD>Galileo Spacecraft Speeds Toward Earth for Gravity Slingshot to
Jupiter</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft, racing toward a
close encounter with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> next week so it can reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1995</DATE>, will explore its home planet like an alien world, scientists
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The camera-bearing planetary spacecraft will be the first to
approach Earth from space, so the <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> flyby will be ``our first
chance to look at <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as we have at other planets in the solar
system,'' <PERSON>Torrence Johnson</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s chief scientist, said during
a news conference.
   ``It gives humankind a vantage point to look at their world as
they've never seen it before,'' <PERSON>Bill O'Neil</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> project
   Galileo is the most sophisticated planetary spacecraft ever
built. It was launched from space shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Oct. 18,
1989</DATE>, starting its <MONEY>$1.4 billion</MONEY>, 2.4 billion-mile journey to
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, the solar system's largest planet.
   Starting in <DATE>December 1995</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> orbiter will spend two
years exploring <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and 10 of its moons after deploying a probe
that will make measurements in <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s atmosphere until it is
crushed by intense pressure there.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s route was designed so the unmanned spacecraft could
use Venus and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> as ``gravity slingshots'' to expand its orbit
around the sun and reach <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. It will use Earth for that
purpose <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE> and again in <DATE>December 1992</DATE>. It used <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> as a
gravity slingshot last <DATE>February</DATE>.
   Scientists decided to take advantage of the close encounters to
make pictures and measurements of Venus and <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Data collected
at <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION> was stored on <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s tape recorder and sent to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>
<DATE>last week</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s optical camera made detailed pictures of the uppermost
layer of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' sulfuric acid clouds, as did spacecraft that
visited Venus previously. But <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION>'s infrared camera made the
first still pictures and a movie showing clouds moving in 150 mph
winds in <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' middle and lower cloud decks.
   Severe turbulence that may be caused by thunderstorms was
detected in the middle cloud layer, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scientist <PERSON>Robert Carlson</PERSON>
said.
   Studying <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' acid clouds and its carbon dioxide atmosphere
may help scientists understand how increasing carbon dioxide levels
in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere will warm the planet like glass traps heat in
a greenhouse, said <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> astronomer <PERSON>Michael Belton</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also discovered remarkably fast high-energy particles
flowing away from <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, a surprise because space around the planet
was thought to be placid, said <ORGANIZATION>University of Iowa</ORGANIZATION> physicist <ORGANIZATION>Louis
Frank</ORGANIZATION>.
   The spacecraft also recorded scratchy and screechy sounds
created by waves in electrically charged solar wind particles that
sweep around <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. Scientists played the tape <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will swoop about 593 miles above the southwest <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION> at <TIME>3:35 p.m. EST</TIME> <DATE>Dec. 8</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was 4.46 million miles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The spacecraft will measure gases that cause ``greenhouse
effect'' warming of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s atmosphere, and study high-altitude
water vapor that helps create and destroy <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s protective ozone
layer, <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> also will be the first spacecraft with modern
instruments to study the far side of the moon, which is always
pointed away from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900208-0028 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-08-90 0244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Galileo-Jupiter     02-08 0265</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Galileo-Jupiter,260</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Probe Flies By Venus on Jupiter Trip</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> space probe, heading for <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>
on a six-year roundabout journey, will fly past the planet <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>
late <DATE>Friday</DATE> and early <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and gain momentum for the second leg
of the trip _ back toward <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will be 10,028 miles above <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>' cloud tops when it makes
its closest approach at <TIME>9:59 p.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> time, <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Although the space probe's instruments will be recording
information about Venus _ Earth's closest planetary neighbor _ the
data won't be played back for scientists until <DATE>October</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> was launched last <DATE>October 18</DATE> from the cargo bay of the
space shuttle Atlantis. After passing <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and gaining slingshot
momentum from that flyby, the <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> probe loops back and
will come within 620 miles of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   With that added second push, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> once more will head out
into deep space and return in <DATE>1992</DATE>, coming as close as 200 miles of
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> before it starts out for <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> where it will arrive in
<DATE>December 1995</DATE>.
   There, a robot will separate from the main spacecraft and plunge
through the gaseous atmosphere of the solar system's largest
planet. Galileo itself will orbit the planet for two years taking
scientific measurements.
   Galileo carries a 49-pound nuclear generator to provide
electricity to power the craft's instruments. Similar generators
have been used on other deep space probes, including Voyager, which
last year sent back photographs as it passed <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>, at that point
the planet farthest from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890820-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-89 1430EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Voyager-Neptune Bjt   08-20 0799</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt,0821</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Last Flyby: Voyager 2 Closes In On Distant Neptune</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A robot explorer named Voyager 2 flies
past <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> <DATE>this week</DATE> for its dazzling last picture show _ the
final photo opportunity during the spacecraft's four-planet, 4.4
billion-mile odyssey.
   ``We're getting close, everything is working extremely well and
we're all excited,'' said <PERSON>Norm Haynes</PERSON>, Voyager project manager at
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   ``The surf is definitely up here at <LOCATION>JPL</LOCATION>,'' joked <PERSON>Franklin
O'Donnell</PERSON>, a spokesman for the lab where about 170 scientists from
around the world are asembling for the critical period.
   Coincidentally, <DATE>Sunday</DATE> was the 12th anniversary of Voyager 2's
launch from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 20, 1977</DATE>.
   The researchers will share ultimate exhilaration as front-row
observers for humanity's first close-up look at the solar system's
fourth-largest planet, a blue-green ball nearly four times <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
diameter.
   But their excitement is tinged with nostalgia because Voyager's
<LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter will be the last planetary flyby for a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
spacecraft. Future probes will orbit their target planets: <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
at <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and the Mars Observer.
   And with no one planning a mission to <LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> is the last
unexplored planet that will be visited by a spacecraft from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in
the foreseeable future.
   ``It's almost like being on a ship of discovery like <PERSON>Marco Polo</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Jurrie</PERSON> van der Woude, a <ORGANIZATION>JPL</ORGANIZATION> spokesman.
``For most of us, this is the last picture show, the last foreign
shores we visit in the solar system.''
   Only a few days and a few million miles remain until <TIME>8:59 p.m.
PDT</TIME> <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, when Voyager makes its closest approach to <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> by
skirting 3,000 miles above the planet's cloudtops _ much closer than
its encounters with <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in
<DATE>1986</DATE>.
   As of <TIME>9 a.m. PDT</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, Voyager 2 will be 2.743 billion miles
