<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031289-0072 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 29753 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 3; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
632 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HENPECKED COWPOKES; 
</P>
<P>
RAISING OSTRICHES RUFFLES FEATHERS OF OLD-TIME CATTLEMEN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
STONYFORD, Calif. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Life hasn't been the same the last couple of years on the 1,800-acre Flying S 
Ranch in <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>'s sparsely populated <LOCATION>Colusa County</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Ray 
Williams</PERSON> runs a herd of Brahman cattle. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>, 47, has been a cowboy all his life, all over the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, working many 
different breeds of cattle and even buffalo and sheep. 
</P>
<P>
"When I first came to this country nobody had Brahmans, but everybody's 
accustomed to them now. It's these damn birds that's changin' things around. 
Biggest birds on earth," allowed <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Clowns of Bird World 
</P>
<P>
He was surrounded by the clowns of the bird world, enormous, eight-foot, 300- 
to 325-pound, flightless ostriches with skinny limber necks nearly half their 
length and funny, fuzzy small heads with duck-like bills, soft brown eyes and 
thick black eyelashes. 
</P>
<P>
"Whoever thought ranching would come to this," sighed the cowpoke as one of the 
ostriches began pecking at his jacket buttons. Williams raised his finger in 
the air, admonishing the bird to cut it out. 
</P>
<P>
Another big bird uncorked its neck and in a flash with its bill grabbed the cap 
off the cowboy's head. "Give that back," shouted <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> sternly, and the 
ostrich dropped his lid. "Playful critters aren't they?" mused the cowboy. 
</P>
<P>
The Flying S is one of a dozen ostrich farms and ranches in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, one of 
about 200 growers in the nation with a total of about 5,000 birds, mostly in 
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>. Ostrich farms are an answer to trade sanctions against 
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> imposed in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Until then, this country had been importing upward of 90,000 ostrich hides a 
year from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. The soft grained leather is used to make purses, belts, 
shoes and boots. 
</P>
<P>
Now the big push among ostrich growers is to build up numbers. The birds 
command a lot of money: <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> for a chick, <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> for breeding 
adults. 
</P>
<P>
"Ostriches are going to be big business in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> within a few years, just you 
watch and see," said <PERSON>Svend Steffen</PERSON>, 54, owner of the Flying S who also owns and 
operates a steel company in <LOCATION>Redwood City</LOCATION>. "Not only for the hides, but for the 
meat and feathers as well," he added. 
</P>
<P>
An ostrich yields 90 pounds of cholesterol-free, beef-like meat. "Ostrich meat 
is a popular dinner item in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. I never tire of eating ostrich. It 
tastes great," insisted <PERSON>Steffen</PERSON>. He has 22 ostriches and plans to have as many 
as 200 within a few months. 
</P>
<P>
"These birds are similar to chickens in many ways," chimed in <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION>. "Males 
are called roosters, females, hens, babies, chicks. Like chickens they roost at 
night and males, like barnyard roosters, make a lot of noise at sunup. Male 
ostriches make a booming noise. It makes your hair stand on end. It's like 
something you've never heard before." 
</P>
<P>
The cowboy laughed and said, "Imagine eating an ostrich drumstick. One 
drumstick is enough to feed nearly a dozen people. One ostrich egg weighs three 
pounds and equals 26 chicken eggs." An ostrich hen lays an egg every other day 
with a total of 40 to 60 eggs in a laying season. Eggs hatch out in 42 days. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Ostrich Runways 
</P>
<P>
The big birds on the Flying S Ranch are kept in two acres embraced by a 
six-foot high fence. Eight 200-foot-long runways are in the ostrich yard. The 
birds exercise by racing back and forth at speeds at times in excess of 40 
m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
"You don't cowboy ostriches. No way is anybody going to lasso one of those 
characters," observed <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>, who begins his day at sunup feeding his birds 
corn, barley and alfalfa pellets. 
</P>
<P>
"They're waiting at the gate to greet me. I kind of take a shine to some of the 
friendlier birds like <ORGANIZATION>Big John</ORGANIZATION> over there and <PERSON>Sam</PERSON> and this hen I call Lucy," 
said <PERSON>Williams</PERSON>, scratching <PERSON>Lucy</PERSON> on her long neck. 
</P>
<P>
The rest of the day, <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION> is out on the ranch cowboying like most cowboys 
do -- with cows, not birds. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Ray Williams runs a herd of cattle on the Flying S Ranch, but ostriches 
on the ranch run him ragged by stealing his hat, above. ; Photo, An ostrich 
henpecks lifelong cowpoke Ray Williams. CHARLES HILLINGER / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 0652EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Ostriches     05-16 0420</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ostriches,0435</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ostriches: Bad Company, Good Eating</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANGUS SHAW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HARARE, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bad-tempered, high-kicking African
ostrich can run at 60 mph, but that's not fast enough to escape a
group of breeders who see the world's largest bird as a nonstop
profit machine.
   The breeders say there is increasing demand for their feathers,
skin and high-protein, low-cholesterol meat.
   Along with ostrich meat's newfound popularity among stressed
executives and health nuts in <LOCATION>Western</LOCATION> industrialized nations, the
Japanese have taken to preparing it sushi-style and eating it raw,
says breeder <PERSON>Kevin Grant</PERSON>.
   Unlike its domestic relative, the chicken, the ostrich yields
red meat with a distinctive flavor. About 55 pounds of top quality
meat worth about <MONEY>$500</MONEY> can be stripped from the average-size bird.
   But the 6-footer offers other values, says <PERSON>Grant</PERSON>, head of a
recently established organization representing about 40 <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
breeders.
   Finely tooled ostrich skin cowboy boots fetch as much as <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>
a pair in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. The leather industry in that state alone demands
94,000 15-foot-square skins a year.
   Not much else of the ostrich goes to waste, either. The
feathers, a symbol of justice in ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> and of wealth to
European royalty in the early <DATE>1900s</DATE>, made a comeback in the French
haute couture of top fashion designer <PERSON>Christian Lacroix</PERSON> earlier
this year.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> wants the feathers to dust its cars, and already Japanese
dealers have been sent to inspect <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s fledgling ostrich
industry.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>Grant</ORGANIZATION>, an adult ostrich provides about three pounds
of feathers and, in all, meat, skin and other by-products account
for about <PERCENT>98 percent</PERCENT> of its body weight.
   Scientists are even studying whether ostrich corneas are
compatible with the human eye.
   The flightless bird is not susceptible to tick-borne diseases or
traditional livestock ailments covered by international quarantine
and transportation laws on animal products.
   ``It makes good practical sense,'' Grant says.
   Neighboring <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> is the world's biggest supplier of
ostrich products. Some ranchers in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and other parts of the
American southwest also are dabbling with the birds.
   Grant says the fertile ostrich's giant egg is far too valuable
to scramble for breakfast and, contrary to popular belief, the
ostrich does not bury its head in the sand.
   As well as that formidable kick, the bird's rapier-like toe can
cut a person from chest to groin in a single swipe.
   ``The risk of being kicked is part of the business,'' says
<ORGANIZATION>Grant</ORGANIZATION>. ``I have a gambler's heart and this could be a big money
spinner.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-11388</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DG2CSAFXFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930729
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  29 JUL 93 / Commodities and Agriculture: Feathered herds give
heavyweight profits - The rapid growth of US ostrich ranching
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MATTHEW KAMINSKI
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
EVOLUTION DEALT the ostrich a mixed hand. The world's largest, presumably
oldest and certainly moodiest bird boasts a protective hide covered with
motley coloured feathers, carries around 300lb of red meat and lays
delicious eggs. Such impressive physical endowment has, unfortunately for
the earth-bound avian, great commercial value.
African farmers have long realised the birds' potential. But in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> only
recently have ostriches become a hot commodity. In fact, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> supply for
this alternative cash crop remains solely in the hands of breeders, who sell
the birds at inflated prices to satisfy demand.
Since ostriches were first introduced from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> in the mid-1980s the
number of ranchers raising them has grown to about 3,000.
The ranches are usually small, but surprisingly profitable. An adult pair,
which can produce between 30 and 120 eggs per year, now carries a Dollars
60,000 price tag, which is still rising quickly. Two yearlings can be bought
for about Dollars 12,000 to Dollars 15,000 and chicks, which require much
care, are a bargain at Dollars 3,000 each. No wonder many Americans with a
backyard and a high fence have at least mulled over this investment.
<PERSON>Mr Howard W. 'Bud' Kerr Jr.</PERSON>, who runs the one-man (no window) small-scale
farming office at the sprawling <ORGANIZATION>US Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, says he gets
as many as 30 inquiries about ostriches each week.
At the <ORGANIZATION>Circle M Ranch</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>south-west Missouri</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr Bob McKean</PERSON> has been raising
ostriches since <DATE>1986</DATE>, when he bought his first pair for only Dollars 8,000.
He now owns 35 birds, quite a lot by present standards, which are raised on
a 75ft by 120ft plot.
Many such breeding ranches are run across the country's farm belt,
especially in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>.
It is not clear when the demand will be satisfied, though estimates range
from five to ten years. Other large-scale agricultural commodities like
<PERSON>Angus</PERSON> cattle and the <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> longhorn also were launched by a breeder's
market.
The ostriches' potential under normal market conditions has not been
questioned. The bird has many uses.
Ostrich flesh, already used to make jerky in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, caters to the demand
for low fat and low cholesterol meat. Large-scale slaughter has not begun,
but the meat, now taken from sterile birds, sells for Dollars 6 to Dollars
10 a pound. Health-conscious <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has been cited as a possibly fertile
future market.
The black, blue and white feathers, which on the European market bring
Dollars 50 to Dollars 1,000 a pound, are used in feather dusters, fashion
accessories, theatre costumes and pens. This is a renewable resource; an
ostrich can be deplumed twice a year.
But perhaps most coveted is the hide, used to make boots and brief cases.
Tanned hides bring Dollars 30 to Dollars 50 a sq ft while custom 'full
quill' boots can cost as much as Dollars 2,000.
Starting an ostrich farm is easy, farmers say. An estimated 2,000 birds are
needed to turn a profit under normal market conditions. For now, however, an
operation even smaller than <PERSON>Mr McKean</PERSON>'s can do the trick.
The birds, unlike cattle, need little space and eat little. They usually
live for around 70 years and most of them are fertile. 'They're just large
chickens,' says <PERSON>Mr Ronald Mascher</PERSON>, who publishes the Small Farm Today
magazine.
But they are probably not as smart. Owners warn that the birds must be
trained and handled carefully because, with a brain barely bigger than a
peanut, the ostrich has an impulsive character.
The birds do not stick their heads in the sand to avoid danger - a terribly
damning myth, ostrich owners lament - but they are prone to unrelenting
pecking, running around at speeds in excess of 45 mph and generating enough
force with their two-toed feet to, in the words of one expert, 'disembowel a
lion'.
There are other problems. Chicks often have a high mortality rate, usually a
consequence of indigestion or inclement weather; the market for many ostrich
products, particularly meat, remains untested; and prices are highly
volatile.
Volatility may not be such a drawback, however, as <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> farmers are well known
for having a strong speculative streak.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P0279 Animal Specialties, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891012-0283 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-89 1240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a f BC-OstrichFarming Adv16   10-12 0854</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ostrich Farming, Adv 16,0882</SECOND>
<HEAD>Texas Ostrich Farmer Says He Doesn't Have His Head in the Sand</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOLDEN LEWIS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ODESSA, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A nine-foot-tall, male ostrich is a strange
sight in the <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> oil fields, especially when it's trying to
scare interlopers and attract females, but to <PERSON>Cooper Campbell</PERSON>,
there's gold in them there quills.
   ``Careful,'' he said, handing a visitor an off-white, pebbly
surfaced, 3{-pound ostrich egg the size of a human baby's head.
``That's worth <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY>.''
   If the egg is fertile, and the embryo survives its 42-day
incubation, and the chick survives the critical first three months
_ the odds of everything going right are about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> at best _
the 2-foot-tall baby bird can command more than <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>.
   A pair of fertile, productive adults can bring <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> is manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Yellow Rose Ostrich Ranch</ORGANIZATION> south of
<LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION>, part of a business taking its first steps in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   Potential profits attract ranchers all over the country,
especially in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, although
the hardy birds can be raised in almost every state and even above
the Arctic Circle in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Just a few years ago, ostriches in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> could be
found only in zoos and in the pastures of exotic-animal collectors.
Now the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commercial ostrich population is 4,000 to 8,000, said
<PERSON>Tom Mantzel</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Fort Worth-based American
Ostrich Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's growing, growing, growing at a phenomenal clip,'' said
<PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON>, who promotes the ostrich industry with preacher zeal.
About 500 ranchers belong to the organization, three-quarters of
them in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Most of the rest are in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   Mantzel estimated the country's adult ostrich population will
have to reach at least 75,000 before it makes economic sense to
slaughter them for their hide, feathers and meat. Until then, which
he estimates will be in the mid-1990s, the birds are more valuable
as breeders.
   The hide is used to make western boots, belts, other items of
clothing and luggage. The feathers are used in dusters. <LOCATION>South
Africans</LOCATION> and Europeans eat the meat, which looks, feels and tastes
like beef and is low in cholesterol and fat.
   Ostriches are slaughtered at 12 to 14 months, when they weigh
about 300 pounds and carry about 80 pounds of meat. The hide,
feathers and meat are worth <MONEY>$400</MONEY> to <MONEY>$500</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said.
   Ostrich ranchers are getting a boost from global politics since
virtually all ostrich products come from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Because of American economic sanctions aimed at protesting <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s apartheid racial segregation system, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> consumers can't
buy ostrich hides directly from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and must buy treated
skins from third countries.
   <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> believes American ostriches will mean big business, and
that Americans will develop an appetite for the meat just as they
have developed a taste for catfish and sushi.
   Americans already have developed a liking for ostrich leather.
Highest-grade, treated hide costs about <MONEY>$28</MONEY> a square foot, said <PERSON>Joe
Lama</PERSON>, buyer for the <ORGANIZATION>Tony Lama Boot Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>.
   The average ostrich will yield about five boots made from the
best-looking skin, called full quill, <ORGANIZATION>Lama</ORGANIZATION> said. About two pairs
can be made from the bird's lesser-quality hide, whose
characteristic bumps are smaller and less prominent than in
full-quill leather.
   Before a cowboy sticks his feet into a pair of ostrich-skin
boots, though, the bird has to hatch and grow up. That's <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION>'s
business.
   The laying season lasts from about <DATE>March to October</DATE>, with hens
laying an egg about every other day. After 42 days in an incubator
and hatchery, the hatchling is ready, sometimes getting a little
human help to peck itself out of the eggshell, which is about as
thick as a nickel.
   A hatchling weighs about 1{ pounds and can stand up and walk
almost immediately. Its gray feathers look and feel like coarse
hair.
   Days after hatching, chicks already can run. They grow eight to
10 inches a month during their first few months. They can reproduce
at about 2 to 3 years of age. Ostriches in the wild can live to be
75.
   Because of their speed, they have few predators.
   ``They can sustain 35 to 40 miles an hour for five or six
miles,'' <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> said, adding that lions and even cheetahs have
trouble catching the birds in the wild and almost always go for
something more attainable.
   Contrary to popular belief, they don't stick their heads in the
sand. If they're cornered or don't feel like running, they can
kick. <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said the birds have been known to kick coyotes to
death on the American range.
   A 20-acre tract of range can sustain 50 or 60 ostriches, which
forage and eat pellet feed.
   ``I tell ranchers, `Just set aside <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of your land, two
or three acres, and raise ostriches,''' <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said. ``I say,
`Instead of spending a dollar and a dime to make a dollar, try
something you can make a profit on.' Someday, it will be a barnyard
industry like sheep, cattle and goats.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday Oct. 16</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   A nine-foot-tall, male ostrich is a strange
sight in the <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> oil fields, especially when it's trying to
scare interlopers and attract females, but to <PERSON>Cooper Campbell</PERSON>,
there's gold in them there quills.
   ``Careful,'' he said, handing a visitor an off-white, pebbly
surfaced, 3{-pound ostrich egg the size of a human baby's head.
``That's worth <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY>.''
   If the egg is fertile, and the embryo survives its 42-day
incubation, and the chick survives the critical first three months
_ the odds of everything going right are about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> at best _
the 2-foot-tall baby bird can command more than <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>.
   A pair of fertile, productive adults can bring <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> is manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Yellow Rose Ostrich Ranch</ORGANIZATION> south of
<LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION>, part of a business taking its first steps in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.
   Potential profits attract ranchers all over the country,
especially in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, although
the hardy birds can be raised in almost every state and even above
the Arctic Circle in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Just a few years ago, ostriches in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> could be
found only in zoos and in the pastures of exotic-animal collectors.
Now the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commercial ostrich population is 4,000 to 8,000, said
<PERSON>Tom Mantzel</PERSON>, executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>Fort Worth-based American
Ostrich Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It's growing, growing, growing at a phenomenal clip,'' said
<PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON>, who promotes the ostrich industry with preacher zeal.
About 500 ranchers belong to the organization, three-quarters of
them in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Most of the rest are in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
   Mantzel estimated the country's adult ostrich population will
have to reach at least 75,000 before it makes economic sense to
slaughter them for their hide, feathers and meat. Until then, which
he estimates will be in the mid-1990s, the birds are more valuable
as breeders.
   The hide is used to make western boots, belts, other items of
clothing and luggage. The feathers are used in dusters. <LOCATION>South
Africans</LOCATION> and Europeans eat the meat, which looks, feels and tastes
like beef and is low in cholesterol and fat.
   Ostriches are slaughtered at 12 to 14 months, when they weigh
about 300 pounds and carry about 80 pounds of meat. The hide,
feathers and meat are worth <MONEY>$400</MONEY> to <MONEY>$500</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said.
   Ostrich ranchers are getting a boost from global politics since
virtually all ostrich products come from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>.
   Because of American economic sanctions aimed at protesting <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s apartheid racial segregation system, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> consumers can't
buy ostrich hides directly from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> and must buy treated
skins from third countries.
   <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> believes American ostriches will mean big business, and
that Americans will develop an appetite for the meat just as they
have developed a taste for catfish and sushi.
   Americans already have developed a liking for ostrich leather.
Highest-grade, treated hide costs about <MONEY>$28</MONEY> a square foot, said <PERSON>Joe
Lama</PERSON>, buyer for the <ORGANIZATION>Tony Lama Boot Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>El Paso</LOCATION>.
   The average ostrich will yield about five boots made from the
best-looking skin, called full quill, <ORGANIZATION>Lama</ORGANIZATION> said. About two pairs
can be made from the bird's lesser-quality hide, whose
characteristic bumps are smaller and less prominent than in
full-quill leather.
   Before a cowboy sticks his feet into a pair of ostrich-skin
boots, though, the bird has to hatch and grow up. That's <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION>'s
business.
   The laying season lasts from about <DATE>March to October</DATE>, with hens
laying an egg about every other day. After 42 days in an incubator
and hatchery, the hatchling is ready, sometimes getting a little
human help to peck itself out of the eggshell, which is about as
thick as a nickel.
   A hatchling weighs about 1{ pounds and can stand up and walk
almost immediately. Its gray feathers look and feel like coarse
hair.
   Days after hatching, chicks already can run. They grow eight to
10 inches a month during their first few months. They can reproduce
at about 2 to 3 years of age. Ostriches in the wild can live to be
75.
   Because of their speed, they have few predators.
   ``They can sustain 35 to 40 miles an hour for five or six
miles,'' <PERSON>Cooper</PERSON> said, adding that lions and even cheetahs have
trouble catching the birds in the wild and almost always go for
something more attainable.
   Contrary to popular belief, they don't stick their heads in the
sand. If they're cornered or don't feel like running, they can
kick. <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said the birds have been known to kick coyotes to
death on the American range.
   A 20-acre tract of range can sustain 50 or 60 ostriches, which
forage and eat pellet feed.
   ``I tell ranchers, `Just set aside <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> of your land, two
or three acres, and raise ostriches,''' <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said. ``I say,
`Instead of spending a dollar and a dime to make a dollar, try
something you can make a profit on.' Someday, it will be a barnyard
industry like sheep, cattle and goats.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102489-0098 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 125074 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 24, 1989, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 8; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
373 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
OSTRICHES FIND HOME ON THE RANGE, HELP RANCHERS FEATHER THEIR NESTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ODESSA, Tex. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A 9-foot-tall male ostrich is a strange sight in the <LOCATION>West Texas</LOCATION> oil fields, 
especially when it's trying to scare interlopers and attract females, but to 
<PERSON>Cooper Campbell</PERSON>, there's gold in them there quills. 
</P>
<P>
"Careful," he said, handing a visitor an off-white, pebbly surfaced, 3 
1/2-pound ostrich egg the size of a human baby's head. "That's worth <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY>." 
</P>
<P>
If the egg is fertile and the embryo survives its 42-day incubation and the 
chick survives the critical first three months -- the odds of everything going 
right are about <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> at best -- the 2-foot-tall baby bird can command more than 
<MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
A pair of fertile, productive adults can bring <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> is manager of the <ORGANIZATION>Yellow Rose Ostrich Ranch</ORGANIZATION> south of <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION>, part of a 
business taking its first steps in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Potential profits attract ranchers all over the country, especially in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, although the hardy birds can be raised in 
almost every state and even above the Arctic Circle in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Just a few years ago, ostriches in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> could be found only in 
zoos and in the pastures of exotic-animal collectors. Now the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commercial 
ostrich population is 4,000 to 8,000, said <PERSON>Tom Mantzel</PERSON>, executive director of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Fort Worth-based American Ostrich Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's growing, growing, growing at a phenomenal clip," said <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON>, who 
promotes the ostrich industry with a preacher's zeal. About 500 ranchers belong 
to the organization, three-quarters of them in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. Most of the rest are in 
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Mantzel estimated the country's adult ostrich population will have to reach at 
least 75,000 before it makes economic sense to slaughter them for their hide, 
feathers and meat. Until then, which he estimates will be in the mid-1990s, the 
birds are more valuable as breeders. 
</P>
<P>
The hide is used to make western boots, belts, other items of clothing and 
luggage. The feathers are used in dusters. <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> and Europeans eat the 
meat, which looks, feels and tastes like beef and is low in cholesterol and 
fat. 
</P>
<P>
Ostriches are slaughtered at 12 to 14 months, when they weigh about 300 pounds 
and carry about 80 pounds of meat. The hide, feathers and meat are worth <MONEY>$400</MONEY> 
to <MONEY>$500</MONEY>, <PERSON>Mantzel</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
OSTRICHES; ANIMAL BREEDING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091089-0034 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 105322 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 10, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 4; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1197 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BUT CRITICS WARN OF A GLUT ON THE MARKET; 
</P>
<P>
IOWANS SAY OSTRICH-FARMING WON'T LAY AN EGG AS THEIR PROFITS SOAR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PAULA YOST, The Washington Post 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WESTSIDE, Iowa 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Big Jim the ostrich hunkered down and, in what has become a daily ritual, 
curved his long neck into an S-shape and waved it from side to side. Sally, the 
focus of his attentions, batted her long eyelashes and looked away. 
</P>
<P>
The courtship of these ostriches isn't very private. When <ORGANIZATION>Big Jim</ORGANIZATION> performs his 
dramatic mating dance, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> farmer <PERSON>Dick Hugg</PERSON> watches and smiles. At <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> a 
chick, ostrich breeding is serious business. 
</P>
<P>
The birds deliver offspring promptly and punctually. Every other day between 
<TIME>4:30 p.m.</TIME> and <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>, <PERSON>Sally</PERSON> lays an egg, and the Huggs -- between growing corn 
and soybeans and feeding hogs -- head out to the ostrich pen to pluck an egg 
and place it in an incubator. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Taller Than Cornstalks 
</P>
<P>
Ostriches in <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>? At 8 and 9 feet tall, these 300-pound African birds stretch 
higher than cornstalks and cause double-takes among Hugg's neighbors in this 
conservative German farming community. 
</P>
<P>
But Hugg, along with an estimated 100 farmers in the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> and 200 in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, see ostriches as the salvation of a distressed agricultural 
economy unable to support the more traditional soybean, grain, beef and pork 
producers. 
</P>
<P>
"It is the brightest picture on the agricultural scene <DATE>today</DATE>, and it's going to 
stay that way," said <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> rancher <PERSON>Dale Coody</PERSON>, who owns 60 ostriches and 
wrote "Ostriches, Your Great Opportunity." 
</P>
<P>
"Let's face it, agriculture is in trouble, and this is the surest way out of 
trouble that I know of," he said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Enough Profit for a Pizza 
</P>
<P>
It was <DATE>1975</DATE> when <PERSON>Dick</PERSON> and <PERSON>Doris Hugg</PERSON> realized that they could not earn a living 
from cattle. After raising 180 head, marketing them and rushing the cash to the 
bank to pay off their note, "we had just enough left over to buy a pizza," <PERSON>Hugg</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
So the Huggs, and others who survived a farm crisis that left many bankrupt, 
sought ways to diversify. Some got hooked on ostriches, and, according to many 
who invested, are making huge profits. <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> farmer <PERSON>LeRoy Kaufman</PERSON> said he earned 
more than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE> by raising and selling the birds. 
</P>
<P>
Ostrich breeders are confident that they can carve a niche in American 
agriculture for the marketing of ostrich feathers, hide and meat. "We foresee 
it eventually being a commercial business, much like turkeys or chickens or 
hogs, where they'll be routinely raised for slaughter," <PERSON>Hugg</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Low-Cholesterol Meat 
</P>
<P>
Ostrich meat, popular in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, is a red meat one-third lower in fat and 
cholesterol than beef. Ostrich promoters have dubbed it the health meat of the 
'90s. "We'll have ostrich burgers someday," <PERSON>Hugg</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
But ostrich filets and ostrich-skin bucket seats are at least seven years away, 
according to <PERSON>Tom Mantzel</PERSON>, executive director of the Texas-based <ORGANIZATION>American 
Ostrich Assn</ORGANIZATION>. This country's ostrich population, estimated at 6,000 adults, is 
not big enough to support a slaughterhouse, so the current market is for 
breeders only. 
</P>
<P>
The birds are hard to come by and command a high price. An adult mating pair 
costs <MONEY>$35,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>, and an unusually prolific pair can carry a <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY> 
price tag. 
</P>
<P>
Ostriches, particularly attractive to breeders because of their reproductive 
habits, lay 35 to 100 eggs annually for 40 of their 70 years of life. 
</P>
<P>
Even at high prices and with the birds' high reproductive rate, breeders say 
they cannot meet the demand. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Made Profit in 85 Days 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kaufman</PERSON> said that 85 days after he bought a few birds in <DATE>1987</DATE>, he recouped his 
<MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> investment and pocketed a <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> profit. "I've made more dollars here 
than I ever did in farming," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Not everyone is so optimistic. <PERSON>Fred Thornberry</PERSON>, a poultry specialist at <ORGANIZATION>Texas 
A&amp;M University</ORGANIZATION>, called the enterprise speculative and warned prospective 
breeders not to jump in hastily. 
</P>
<P>
He said that, like so many once-promising ventures in agriculture, such as the 
failed rabbit-harvesting craze in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> several years ago, this one could fall 
dead in its tracks. "This is not an industry as yet, and I would be very 
cautious (about) investing money I could not afford to lose," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Thornberry, who has received more than 600 ostrich-related queries from farmers 
across the country, said that profits probably peaked in <DATE>1987</DATE>. The farmers who 
bought birds at low prices in <DATE>1986</DATE> and earlier will pocket the highest profits. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Population Explosion Seen 
</P>
<P>
What makes the venture especially risky for incoming breeders is the likelihood 
of an ostrich population explosion this year, which could cause prices to 
plummet, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The hundreds of chicks hatched in <DATE>1986</DATE>, the year the ostrich movement picked up 
speed, will begin reproducing this year. "I think we're approaching the point 
where it's getting riskier and riskier," he said. 
</P>
<P>
However, the Huggs do not expect an imminent population explosion, because 
raising an egg to a full-grown ostrich is a difficult task that most breeders 
have yet to master. 
</P>
<P>
Baby ostriches are frail and die easily. And, because ostriches are a new 
agricultural frontier, farmers do not quite know how to raise birds that can 
run 40 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
Feeding them is not such a problem. Ostriches, said to eat anything, are 
usually raised on prepared alfalfa pellets with some grain and other 
ingredients mixed in. The Huggs feed them lettuce and cabbage also. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Male Turns Dangerous 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sally</PERSON> and <PERSON>Big Jim</PERSON>, which are kept inside a 5-foot wire fence, exhibit distinct 
personalities, the <PERSON>Huggs</PERSON> said. She is always docile. He is, too, unless it's 
mating season, when he turns cantankerous and downright dangerous. 
</P>
<P>
In mating season, males are reputed to be able to kill with a kick, and the 
Huggs stay out of the pen, using a cane to retrieve eggs from the nest. "He 
doesn't like people messing with his eggs or his girl," <PERSON>Hugg</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Most breeders are able to hatch <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of their eggs, and the <PERSON>Huggs</PERSON>' hatch rate 
runs about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT>. They attribute their success to a labor-intensive operation and 
a willingness to do whatever it takes to hatch a chick and help it grow. 
</P>
<P>
For example, if a chick has trouble cracking out of its egg, the Huggs help it 
along with pliers. 
</P>
<P>
Breeders expect <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ostrich prices to be buoyed should the <ORGANIZATION>Department of 
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> permanently ban importation of the birds from <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. The 
department temporarily embargoed ostriches in <DATE>June</DATE>, when ticks not indigenous 
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> were found on incoming birds. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Breeders Back Import Ban 
</P>
<P>
Some breeders prefer an import ban, so they can build the ostrich population 
from birds already here. Once the pool is high enough to support a processing 
plant, breeders see a virtual fail-safe enterprise, because every part of the 
bird is usable: feathers for computer dusters, ceremonial plumes and fashion 
wear; leather for boots, purses, car seats, egg shells for jewelry and meat for 
health-conscious consumers. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Richard Whitaker</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> banker and owner of 40 ostriches, said he has 
received letters from a Swiss company expressing interest in ostrich meat 
produced here, because <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> controls the industry and does not export 
enough to meet Swiss demand. "They can't get enough of it in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Dominique's restaurant in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> used to offer ostrich meat but 
discontinued it, because "it was not appreciated." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Matthew Hugg, 10, keeps a respectful distance from a pecking ostrich 
chick on his family's farm. ; Photo, As Big Jim struts away, farmer Dick Hugg 
shows his wife, Doris, a sample of the egg-laying prowess of Big Jim's mate, 
Sally. BILL SNEAD / Washington Post 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910103-0126
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910103-0126.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Poultry in Motion
   Breeders Sell Shares
   In Ostrich Market
   ---
   Investors Hope to Get Rich,
   But So Did the People
   Who Raised Chinchillas
   ----
   By Karen J. Benfield
</HL>
<DATE>
01/03/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<IN>
COMMODITY NEWS, FARM PRODUCTS (CMD)
TEXTILES AND APPAREL (TEX)
</IN>
<LP>
   WEATHERFORD, Texas -- George and Andrew Williams are
looking for a nest egg.
   The father and son sell insurance in nearby Fort Worth,
but George is sure that there is no end to the money that can
be made from Red Necks, a variety of ostriches. Also from
Blue Necks.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The Williamses are thinking of putting up <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY> to join
all the Americans supposedly flocking to ostrich ranching.
   A three-month-old ostrich chick sells for as much as
<MONEY>$3,000</MONEY>. A mature breeding pair of three-year-old birds can
command <MONEY>$70,000</MONEY>. A fertile egg goes for <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>. A
particularly fecund ostrich can lay up to 120 eggs a year,
<PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of them fertile, and go on laying for as long as 40
years.
   All of that explains the "rich" in ostrich to the
<LOCATION>Williamses</LOCATION> and others who are buying a piece of the action,
sometimes just part of an ostrich. Skeptics hear of this and
recall the folks in the <DATE>1950s</DATE> who thought they were going to
get rich raising chinchillas for fur coats but lost their
shirts instead.
   "You can regain your capital within the first year," says
<PERSON>Ronda Barton</PERSON>, who sells people on the idea for <ORGANIZATION>Bordelon
Breeders International</ORGANIZATION>, a big, high-tech ostrich ranch
outside <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>. The company sells birds outright and
syndicates one-half and one-third interests in ostriches that
<PERSON>Bordelon</PERSON> raises for clients. Bordelon pays dividends in
chicks. It holds "marketing seminars." You can buy or lease.
   One recent <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, 50-odd would-be ostrich owners joined
the Williamses in hearing the <PERSON>Bordelon</PERSON> pitch. "With cattle,
you've just got the hides and the meat," says <PERSON>Craig
Longhurst</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bordelon</PERSON>'s marketing director. "But with ostriches
you've got hide and feathers, then you've got meat, and then
you've got eggs. So you've got two more profit centers."
   Profit centers? It is true that ostrich leather -- a
pimply skin -- is highly prized, certainly highly priced.
Mark Cross in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has an ostrich handbag that sells for
<MONEY>$3,475</MONEY>, though it may not move as fast as an ostrich on the
hoof (40 mph). And at the <ORGANIZATION>Nocona Boot Company</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>,
ostrich-leather boots walk out the door at <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> a pair.
   Ostrich feathers -- the birds can be shorn like sheep --
sell to designers for as much as <MONEY>$150</MONEY> a pound. Feather
importer <PERSON>Anthony Trento Jr.</PERSON> says his AmCan <ORGANIZATION>Feather Co.</ORGANIZATION> sells
more than <MONEY>a million dollars</MONEY> in feathers annually to
designers. And he is really excited about the possibilities
the lesser feathers have in feather dusters. "Turkey-feather
dusters just move dust from one place to the next. An ostrich
duster will actually pick up dirt." Imagine if everybody had
one.
   "I'm so pleased to see proud plumage on the runways in
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>," says couturier <PERSON>Victor Costa</PERSON>, who claims to have spent
<MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> on feathers in <DATE>1990</DATE>. Designer <PERSON>Bob Mackie</PERSON>, who
specializes in sequins, agrees that "there's something
magical about ostrich feathers -- they're lighter than air
and very soft." <PERSON>Mr. Mackie</PERSON> says if thick white feathers from
the wing of a male could be obtained from domestic breeders,
the cost would certainly go down. "And that would be a help
since they're quite expensive."
   The ostrich (Struthio camelus) stands head and shoulders
above other birds, not just in profitability. It is the
world's biggest, heaviest bird, standing about eight feet
tall in stalking feet, and weighing in at about 325 to 375
pounds. Obviously, it can't get off the ground. The ostrich
also has only two toes on each foot, with which, says rancher
<PERSON>Patti Stickler</PERSON>, it "could split you totally in half." As
vegetarians go, ostriches are pretty powerful.
   Also, they are odd vegetarians. While they prefer plants
and eat six pounds of feed a day, they have been known to
swallow <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> bottles or anything else that piques their
interest, their eyes being bigger than their brains. Says
<PERSON>Mrs. Stickler</PERSON>: "Mine have eaten coins, rocks, sticks and
nails." Brilliant they aren't.
   Not only will they eat anything, they can survive in
virtually any climate and will flourish on the worst
rangeland. <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> was the first to ranch the birds and
is still the major producer. But the <DATE>1986</DATE> Anti-Apartheid Act
banned the importation of South African ostrich hides. So
many customers in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> get the leather from countries
that get it from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. (Most ostrich leather is
processed and tanned in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.)
   Because of a tick that infests the big birds, the
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1989</DATE> imposed further import
restrictions. "At present, we have a ban on the importation
of the {live} ostrich and its eggs," says <PERSON>Dr. Robert Whiting</PERSON>
at the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Animal Plant Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>.
   Does that spell opportunity for domestic breeders? Yes and
no. There are only 10,000 to 15,000 ostriches in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>,
and maybe only 1,500 breeding pairs. Chicks are back-ordered.
So it is a breeder's market. That is true in every sense.
Buyers are mainly breeders buying from other breeders.
   Nobody in this country is slaughtering ostriches yet in
any numbers; the birds are far more valuable as breeding
stock. The current slaughter value of an ostrich is only
about <MONEY>$1,250</MONEY>, rather less than the price of a live chick.
   Breeders say that when the ostrich population has
stabilized at more than 250,000 breeding pairs, about five to
eight years from now, ranchers can begin killing the birds
for leather and for meat, which tastes more like beef than
chicken, at least in meatballs. A <ORGANIZATION>Texas Department of
Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> report predicts that within 10 years ostriches
could be a <MONEY>$170 million</MONEY> business in the state. Others,
hearing that, chuckle and think of bars of gold held for
investors by third parties -- a boom of the past that went
bust.
   "It just can't be anything more than a pyramid scheme,"
says <PERSON>William Cawley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> A&amp;M extension poultry specialist
emeritus, speaking of no abuse in particular. "The people who
get in early make all the money. A lot of poor people on the
bottom are going to get hurt." <PERSON>Mr. Cawley</PERSON> recalls something
similar happening once with <LOCATION>Shetland</LOCATION> ponies. He thinks the
ostrich business is birdbrained.
   Tell that to the folks who are investing in ostriches at
the <LOCATION>Bordelon</LOCATION> ranch. For <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Bordelon</ORGANIZATION> will sell you a
third interest in a breeding pair. Bordelon will care for
your birds, for a fee, and you get chicks as they are
hatched. Says <PERSON>Bordelon</PERSON>'s <PERSON>Mr. Longhurst</PERSON>: "We do all the work.
Anybody can get involved this way." In the <DATE>last six months of
1989</DATE>, <PERSON>Bordelon</PERSON> says it sold <MONEY>$332,000</MONEY> in ostriches and ostrich
shares.
   In theory at least, when the ostrich population grows
large enough, prices will fall and Americans will start
eating ostrich meat. <PERSON>Susan Adkins</PERSON>, who presides over the
<ORGANIZATION>American Ostrich Association</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fort Worth</LOCATION>, says she
regularly gets calls from <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> requesting ostrich meat,
"and of course it's not available here yet." She says the
meat, considered a delicacy on the Continent, is "lower in
calories, cholesterol and fat than turkey and chicken." <PERSON>Ms.
Adkins</PERSON> admits that it could be difficult to persuade <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
omnivores to switch to these big drumsticks despite the
nutritional percentage in it.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Stickler</PERSON> is among those who believe that ostriches
have truly great potential. She and her husband, <PERSON>Harry</PERSON>, have
raised ostriches in <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> since <DATE>1986</DATE>. The Sticklers
originally raised cattle but have replaced their herd with
funny-looking birds. "My husband likes new exciting things,
and we make much more money with the ostriches," she says,
selling prospective broilers to breeders from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>.
   If by some chance the market for flightless birds fails to
get off the ground, there always is show business. The
Sticklers have a bird that was on "Late Night With <PERSON>David
Letterman</PERSON>."
   "His name is Chuck," says <PERSON>Mrs. Stickler</PERSON>. "He does tricks.
He dribbles a basketball, and he takes people's hats off."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900917-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-17-90 0009EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-OstrichMeat     09-17 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Ostrich Meat,0347</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rancher Touts Ostrich Meat as Health Food of the '90s</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LOUINN LOTA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Doug Stickler</PERSON> is sticking his neck out for
ostrich meat.
   Stickler, who with his older brother <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> have an ostrich spread
in the middle of <LOCATION>Oklahoma Panhandle</LOCATION> cattle country, predict meat
from the bareheaded bird will be the health food of the '90s.
   The Sticklers have brought four of their flightless flock to the
<LOCATION>Los Angeles County Fair</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Pomona</LOCATION>.
   ``It won't be long until you see people eating <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> fried
ostrich,'' <PERSON>Stickler</PERSON> said in a telephone interview <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. ``It's
definitely the future.''
   The <PERSON>Turpin</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, rancher said the meat is low in cholesterol,
high in protein and tastes like steak with the texture of veal.
Stickler said doctors and nutrition experts who have seen the
future are investing in ostriches.
   Cost per pound - <MONEY>$10</MONEY>, since there are so few of the birds in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. But <PERSON>Doug</PERSON> figures in 20 years, he'll be giving the
beef a run for its money.
   ``At first, we got a lot of teasing from the area ranchers. They
thought we were crazy,'' he said. ``Well, those same ones that
teased us have been coming down to see what we're doing.''
   Stickler got into the ostrich breeding business in <DATE>1986</DATE>. He
bought his first birds from ostrich-farming monks in <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION>.
   Two years later, the Sticklers moved their 10,000 head of cattle
out and moved the birds in - about 175 of them now. The brothers
have sold more than 300 chicks nationwide. Prices range from <MONEY>$500</MONEY>
to <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> per chick.
   ``You just feed 'em, water 'em and leave 'em alone,'' he said.
``With cattle you worked from dark to dark. Back home it takes 30
minutes to do the ostrich chores.''
   Stickler said that according to the <ORGANIZATION>American Ostrich
Association</ORGANIZATION>, there are more than 5,000 ostriches being bred across
the country. The association predicts an ostrich population boom of
75,000 to 100,000 by mid-1990.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890705-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-05-89 1647EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AfricanTicks     07-05 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-African Ticks,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ostrich Imports Banned Because of Tick Danger</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> it
has stopped issuing import permits for live ostriches because
African ticks that can carry livestock disease were recently found
on some of the birds.
<ORGANIZATION>Plant Health Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>, said 18 ticks _ identified as
African Bont ticks and Bont-legged ticks _ were found on two
imported ostriches in <LOCATION>Andrews</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Quinlan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, in late <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Some of the ``exotic'' ticks also were found later on adult
ostriches in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, he said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> agency announced <DATE>June 19</DATE> that African ticks had been
detected on shipments of ostriches and told livestock producers to
be on the alert.
   Bont ticks are known to transmit heartwater, a disease of cattle,
sheep, goats and other ruminants. However, <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks
removed from the ostriches are not known to transmit any human
diseases.
   ``So far, there is no evidence that the ticks have spread to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
livestock,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said his agency ``is reviewing inspection methods and
quarantine facility standards to determine if other action is needed
to prevent additional pests from entering the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   He said the ostriches were in a shipment of 44 adult birds
imported from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 2</DATE>. Twenty-five survived and were
released <DATE>30 days later</DATE> from a privately owned, USDA-approved
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Mundelein</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. Those were sent to cities in
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said 50 ostrich chicks from <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> also were imported
<DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> and that 45 survivors were released from a private
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Schaumburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. They went to dealers in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   No ticks were found on the ostrich chicks.
   ``Animal health officials placed the infested premises under
state quarantine, identified all the ostriches and are treating the
birds and soil every 14 days with a pesticide used to control
livestock ticks,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said.
   ``Other birds or animals that may have had contact with the
ostriches or those immediately adjacent to the birds are being
examined for ticks and treated,'' he said. ``If no ticks are found,
the state or federal veterinarian will lift the quarantine and
continue a tick surveillance for six months.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said rabbits, birds, steers and other ``sentinel''
animals are being placed on all farm premises with the adult
ostriches to see if the ticks are still a threat to domestic
animals. Agency health officials also are trapping wildlife on the
farms to check for ticks.
   Heartwater affects the heart, lymph nodes and brain of livestock,
causing muscle twitching, diarrhea, convulsions and death.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks are reddish-orange or dark brown and
commonly attach themselves to the neck, udder, hoof or tail area of
livestock.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100489-0102 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 116023 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 4, 1989, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part 4; Page 2; Column 1; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
546 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
RANCHERS SWITCH TO RAISING OSTRICHES, DEER AND BUFFALO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Reuters 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CHICAGO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The entrepreneurial spirit thrives in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> livestock industry, with farmers 
and ranchers raising new and exotic livestock. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, domesticated deer are raised in a feedlot where cattle were once 
fed, and ostriches roam on a <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> ranch next to quarter horses and 
Thoroughbreds. 
</P>
<P>
"The ostrich industry is over 100 years old, but not in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>," 
said <PERSON>Cooper Campbell</PERSON>, who started raising the birds on his <LOCATION>Odessa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, horse 
ranch three years ago. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> expects in four to six years that there will be enough commercially 
raised ostriches to sustain markets for the meat, feathers and hide. Until 
then, the best market will be for breeding stock. 
</P>
<P>
Newborn and young ostriches are expensive, costing <MONEY>$6,000</MONEY> for a pair of 
3-month-old chicks and escalating to <MONEY>$45,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY> for a pair of 
3-year-olds, <ORGANIZATION>Campbell</ORGANIZATION> said. However, prices should drop sharply once the 
industry matures and populations increase, he said. 
</P>
<P>
A lot of economic hurdles face these fledgling livestock industries. Markets 
have to be developed for the meat, hides and breeding stock, and government 
standards for the meat must be established. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> has a large commercial ostrich industry, and meat from the giant 
birds is marketed throughout <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Campbell</PERSON>, who is a 
director of the <ORGANIZATION>American Ostrich Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It is a lean, red meat that more closely resembles beef than anything else," 
he said. It is low in cholesterol and fat and can be processed into steaks and 
roasts. 
</P>
<P>
Better-established in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is the market for ostrich hides, which 
are used for jackets, boots, belts and shoes. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dennis Gibson</PERSON>'s feedlots were empty for six years after he quit 
the cattle-feeding business in <DATE>1981</DATE>. Then in <DATE>1987</DATE> he began commercially raising 
fallow deer, a domesticated Asian deer that is more disease resistant than the 
white tail and mule deer indigenous to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
His herd of 250 deer is primarily for breeding purposes, and he regularly sells 
stags to other breeders. 
</P>
<P>
"The deer are flighty but have no trouble adapting to the northern climate," he 
said. 
</P>
<P>
In five years, <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> hopes that supplies will be sufficient to develop and 
sustain marketing channels for venison. Local cattle slaughter plants presently 
process the small amount of commercial venison on the market, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> extension service has supported deer farming with a 
symposium and educational material. Deer farming is successful in <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, 
where there is a commercial herd of 700,000 head, and the industry is growing 
by <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> a year, the university said. 
</P>
<P>
"In the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, there isn't enough product (venison) available to establish a 
market, but we take <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> of the venison <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> exports," said <PERSON>R.M. Jordan</PERSON>, 
a <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> extension animal scientist. 
</P>
<P>
Venison contains <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>4%</PERCENT> fat, compared to <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> for high-quality beef, <PERSON>Gibson</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Still in its infancy is the commercial raising of native American bison, 
commonly known as the American buffalo. The <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> extension 
service reports about 90,000 head in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, of which <PERCENT>85%</PERCENT> is under 
private ownership. 
</P>
<P>
Demand for bison meat has increased in some areas because of its leanness and 
perceived lower cholesterol content. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ENTREPRENEURS; LIVESTOCK; UNITED STATES -- AGRICULTURE; DEER; VENISON; 
OSTRICHES; BUFFALO; FARMERS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06218120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06218120 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  TEXAS; ROBBERY; BIRD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Ranchers are diversifying by raising emus and ostriches -- and rustlers, who
traditionally have made off with cattle and horses, are changing with the
times.;    Authorities are investigating two recent Austin-area thefts in
which $132,000 worth of emu and ostrich chicks were stolen.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NEWFANGLED TEXAS BANDITS RUSTLE OSTRICHES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "There's been numerous thefts of ostriches and emus all over <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, and they're extremely hard to trace," said <PERSON>Malcom Wilkes</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Milam
County Sheriff's Department</ORGANIZATION> investigator.;    <ORGANIZATION>Emu</ORGANIZATION> and ostrich farmers envision
their livestock's low-cholesterol, high-protein meat as a natural alternative
to beef for health-conscious Americans.;    About 20,000 ostriches and 18,000
emus are being raised across the country, and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is the leading state for
growing both types of large, flightless birds, according to representatives of
bird organizations.;    One breeding pair of adult emus can sell for <MONEY>$15,000</MONEY>,
and two ostriches can sell for <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>.;    More than 40 ostrich
chicks were stolen <DATE>July 20</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Austin, Texas  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910805  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  153  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday August 5, 1991
00218120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890818-0090 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-89 1310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-OstrichBan     08-18 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Ostrich Ban,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>USDA Bans Other Ratites: Emus, Rheas and Cassowaries</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> it is
expanding its recent ban on ostrich imports to include related
flightless birds such as emus, rheas and cassowaries because they
may carry disease-bearing parasites.
and <ORGANIZATION>Plant Health Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>, said the expanded import ban
was effective immediately and would remain indefinitely.
   ``We must curtail the entry of flightless birds into the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> until further notice to ensure that these birds do not
introduce disease-carrying parasites to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> livestock,'' he said.
   The flightless birds affected by the ban are known as ratites and
include ostriches, emus, rheas and cassowaries. These birds have
only small or rudimentary wings.
   An agency spokeswoman, <PERSON>Marlene Stinson</PERSON>, said the import ban does
not apply to penguins because those are of a different family.
Neither will the ban affect kiwis, because the bird's homeland, <LOCATION>New
Zealand</LOCATION>, does not permit exports, she said.
   Interest in ostrich farming has grown rapidly, and so have
imports. <PERSON>Stinson</PERSON> said no ostriches were imported in <DATE>1986</DATE> but that
348 entered the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, 537 in <DATE>1988</DATE>, and 825 through
<DATE>July 31</DATE> of this year.
   At present, sales of chicks and adult ostriches are confined
primarily to other breeders, who envision a potential market for
ostrich hide and meat.
   <PERSON>Slagle</PERSON> said the crackdown on imports was prompted by the
discovery earlier this year of 18 exotic ticks on adult ostriches in
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   The ticks were identified as African Bont and Bont-legged ticks,
which are known to transmit heartwater, an often fatal disease of
cattle, sheep, goats and other ruminants. No further tick findings
have been reported.
   <PERSON>Slagle</PERSON> said the disease does not affect humans and does not exist
in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>July 5</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> agency announced it had stopped issuing
import permits for ostriches as a result of the tick threat and was
reviewing import inspection methods and quarantine standards.
   <PERSON>Slagle</PERSON> said the official rule-making publication of the new
import curbs will be <DATE>Aug. 21</DATE>. Public comments can be sent by <DATE>Oct. 20</DATE>
to: Chief, Regulatory Analysis and Development, <ORGANIZATION>PPD</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>APHIS</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION>,
Room 866, Federal Building, 6505 Belcrest Road, <LOCATION>Hyattsville</LOCATION>, MD
20782.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890706-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-06-89 0046EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-FarmScene     07-06 0845</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Farm Scene,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ostriches Barred Entry After Ticks Found</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DON KENDALL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Farm Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Live ostriches have been denied entry into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> because African ticks
that can carry livestock disease recently were found on some of the
imported birds.
<ORGANIZATION>Plant Health Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>, said 18 ticks _ identified as
African Bont ticks and Bont-legged ticks _ were found on two
imported ostriches in <LOCATION>Andrews</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Quinlan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, in late <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Some of the exotic ticks also were found later on adult ostriches
in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, he said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>June 19</DATE> that African ticks had been detected
on shipments of ostriches and told livestock producers to be on the
alert.
   Bont ticks are known to transmit heartwater, a disease of cattle,
sheep, goats and other ruminants. However, <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks
removed from the ostriches are not known to transmit any human
diseases.
   ``So far, there is no evidence that the ticks have spread to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
livestock,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said his agency ``is reviewing inspection methods and
quarantine facility standards to determine if other action is needed
to prevent additional pests from entering the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   He said the ostriches were in a shipment of 44 adult birds
imported from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 2</DATE>. Twenty-five survived and were
released <DATE>30 days later</DATE> from a privately owned, USDA-approved
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Mundelein</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. Those were sent to cities in
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said 50 ostrich chicks from <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> also were imported
<DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> and that 45 survivors were released from a private
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Schaumburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. They went to dealers in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   No ticks were found on the ostrich chicks.
   ``Animal health officials placed the infested premises under
state quarantine, identified all the ostriches and are treating the
birds and soil every 14 days with a pesticide used to control
livestock ticks,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said.
   ``Other birds or animals that may have had contact with the
ostriches or those immediately adjacent to the birds are being
examined for ticks and treated,'' he said. ``If no ticks are found,
the state or federal veterinarian will lift the quarantine and
continue a tick surveillance for six months.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said rabbits, birds, steers and other ``sentinel''
animals are being placed on all farm premises with the adult
ostriches to see if the ticks are still a threat to domestic
animals. Agency health officials also are trapping wildlife on the
farms to check for ticks.
   Heartwater affects the heart, lymph nodes and brain of livestock,
causing muscle twitching, diarrhea, convulsions and death.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks are reddish-orange or dark brown and
commonly attach themselves to the neck, udder, hoof or tail area of
livestock.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Live ostriches have been denied entry into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> because African ticks
that can carry livestock disease recently were found on some of the
imported birds.
<ORGANIZATION>Plant Health Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>, said 18 ticks _ identified as
African Bont ticks and Bont-legged ticks _ were found on two
imported ostriches in <LOCATION>Andrews</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Quinlan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, in late <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Some of the exotic ticks also were found later on adult ostriches
in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, he said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>June 19</DATE> that African ticks had been detected
on shipments of ostriches and told livestock producers to be on the
alert.
   Bont ticks are known to transmit heartwater, a disease of cattle,
sheep, goats and other ruminants. However, <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks
removed from the ostriches are not known to transmit any human
diseases.
   ``So far, there is no evidence that the ticks have spread to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
livestock,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said his agency ``is reviewing inspection methods and
quarantine facility standards to determine if other action is needed
to prevent additional pests from entering the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   He said the ostriches were in a shipment of 44 adult birds
imported from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 2</DATE>. Twenty-five survived and were
released <DATE>30 days later</DATE> from a privately owned, USDA-approved
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Mundelein</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. Those were sent to cities in
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said 50 ostrich chicks from <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> also were imported
<DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> and that 45 survivors were released from a private
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Schaumburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. They went to dealers in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   No ticks were found on the ostrich chicks.
   ``Animal health officials placed the infested premises under
state quarantine, identified all the ostriches and are treating the
birds and soil every 14 days with a pesticide used to control
livestock ticks,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said.
   ``Other birds or animals that may have had contact with the
ostriches or those immediately adjacent to the birds are being
examined for ticks and treated,'' he said. ``If no ticks are found,
the state or federal veterinarian will lift the quarantine and
continue a tick surveillance for six months.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said rabbits, birds, steers and other ``sentinel''
animals are being placed on all farm premises with the adult
ostriches to see if the ticks are still a threat to domestic
animals. Agency health officials also are trapping wildlife on the
farms to check for ticks.
   Heartwater affects the heart, lymph nodes and brain of livestock,
causing muscle twitching, diarrhea, convulsions and death.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks are reddish-orange or dark brown and
commonly attach themselves to the neck, udder, hoof or tail area of
livestock.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Live ostriches have been denied entry into the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>Agriculture Department</ORGANIZATION> because African ticks
that can carry livestock disease recently were found on some of the
imported birds.
<ORGANIZATION>Plant Health Inspection Service</ORGANIZATION>, said 18 ticks _ identified as
African Bont ticks and Bont-legged ticks _ were found on two
imported ostriches in <LOCATION>Andrews</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Quinlan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, in late <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Some of the exotic ticks also were found later on adult ostriches
in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, he said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>USDA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>June 19</DATE> that African ticks had been detected
on shipments of ostriches and told livestock producers to be on the
alert.
   Bont ticks are known to transmit heartwater, a disease of cattle,
sheep, goats and other ruminants. However, <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks
removed from the ostriches are not known to transmit any human
diseases.
   ``So far, there is no evidence that the ticks have spread to <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
livestock,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said his agency ``is reviewing inspection methods and
quarantine facility standards to determine if other action is needed
to prevent additional pests from entering the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   He said the ostriches were in a shipment of 44 adult birds
imported from <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 2</DATE>. Twenty-five survived and were
released <DATE>30 days later</DATE> from a privately owned, USDA-approved
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Mundelein</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. Those were sent to cities in
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said 50 ostrich chicks from <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> also were imported
<DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> and that 45 survivors were released from a private
quarantine facility in <LOCATION>Schaumburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill</LOCATION>. They went to dealers in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>.
   No ticks were found on the ostrich chicks.
   ``Animal health officials placed the infested premises under
state quarantine, identified all the ostriches and are treating the
birds and soil every 14 days with a pesticide used to control
livestock ticks,'' <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said.
   ``Other birds or animals that may have had contact with the
ostriches or those immediately adjacent to the birds are being
examined for ticks and treated,'' he said. ``If no ticks are found,
the state or federal veterinarian will lift the quarantine and
continue a tick surveillance for six months.''
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said rabbits, birds, steers and other ``sentinel''
animals are being placed on all farm premises with the adult
ostriches to see if the ticks are still a threat to domestic
animals. Agency health officials also are trapping wildlife on the
farms to check for ticks.
   Heartwater affects the heart, lymph nodes and brain of livestock,
causing muscle twitching, diarrhea, convulsions and death.
   <PERSON>Glosser</PERSON> said the ticks are reddish-orange or dark brown and
commonly attach themselves to the neck, udder, hoof or tail area of
livestock.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891227-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-89 1251EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EmuFarm     12-27 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Emu Farm,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emu Ranchers _ Their Heads Aren't Buried in the Sand</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Retransmitting a0547, which had incorrect cycle designator.
Originally transmitted for Wednesday PMs; also moved on financial wire.
Now available for Thursday AMs.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto HT2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL GRACZYK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOVELADY, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   There's oil in them thar birds, and two
entrepreneurs are cashing in on the animal that's so despised in
its native land that the government once paid people to kill the
varmints.
   On a 65-acre tract in the <LOCATION>East Texas Piney Woods</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mark Solomon</PERSON>
and Dusty <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> are entering their second year as a new breed of
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> oilmen _ raising emus.
   ``It's just been unbelievable for us, beyond our wildest
dreams,'' said <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON>, 27, whose full-time job with the <ORGANIZATION>Texas
Department of Criminal Justice</ORGANIZATION> is designing furniture manufactured
for the state by inmates.
   ``We have to pinch ourselves to see if we're awake. It's still
hard to believe and we have to tell ourselves it's really
happening,'' added <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON>, 29, a tax consultant.
   Last <DATE>October</DATE>, the lifelong friends purchased a pair of emus for
<MONEY>$1,800</MONEY>. The Australian birds, which resemble ostriches, now fetch
more than <MONEY>$12,000</MONEY> per pair.
   They now have 31 birds, including 12 breeding pair. And profits
from sales of birds to people who buy them as an investment have
enabled <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> to purchase the 65-acre spread in
<LOCATION>Houston County</LOCATION>.
   ``People don't know what they are, but they've been good for
us,'' <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> said.
   Emus can grow to about 5{ feet tall and can weigh up to 120
pounds. The only bigger bird is the ostrich. Emus have
brownish-black feathers, long neck and long legs that can propel
them about 30 mph.
   The bird's meat, leather and feathers are marketable, but what
makes emus valuable is the oil they secrete.
   The oil _ about 5 quarts per processed bird _ is used as a
pharmaceutical for people suffering from arthritis. In cosmetics,
the oil is used in production of wrinkle-retarding emollient.
   <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> say the meat, although not readily
available, tastes like beef and has less cholesterol and fewer
calories. The leather is used like ostrich leather and the feathers
are used for fishing lures and feather dusters. Even the large
toenails _ three per foot _ are used for jewelry.
   ``Right now it's strictly a breeders' market,'' <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> said
recently. ``That's why prices are so high because there are not so
many around. But it's getting more common.''
   Emu prices are on the rise because of speculation about placing
a processing plant in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>American
Emu Association</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Harper</LOCATION>. One plant already operates in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and another in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, where thousands were killed and
bounties were placed on the emu because the bird trampled sheep
fences and ate crops.
   The association estimates about 1,500 breeding pair were in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as of last year, with the largest concentration in
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> have driven as far as <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state
and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> to purchase birds.
   ``Whenever the processing stage comes into play we're going to
get less per bird,'' <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> said. ``But I'll be tickled to death
when it happens because you'll be looking at a definite place to
sell the bird and a definite income coming in.''
   Their first breeding pair, named <PERSON>Bonnie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clyde</PERSON>, laid 36 eggs
the first year. The eggs, which are dark green and resemble
avocados, hatch in 48 to 52 days. And once the birds get into a
cycle, they'll lay eggs every three days.
   <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Solomon</PERSON> are expanding their farm and hope to
eventually have 90 pens in operation.
   Some people will purchase chicks at <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> apiece,
keep them for three or four months and then sell for as much as
<MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> each. Feed costs are minimal, ranging from <MONEY>$150</MONEY> to <MONEY>$180</MONEY> per
year for each bird.
   Neighbors who raise cattle like to joke that <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> is a land for
moo-moo, not emu.
   ``They are an ugly bird,'' <PERSON>Driskell</PERSON> acknowledged. ``But when
they sell for <MONEY>$12,000</MONEY>, they look pretty good.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880324-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-88 0939EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a PM-BRF--OstrichFlap     03-24 0180</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-BRF--Ostrich Flap,0190</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ostrich Farmer Sqwaks At Ruling</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LEBANON, Ohio (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A ostrich farmer thinks county
commissioners may have their heads in the sand for failing to agree
that an ostrich has as much value as a turkey.
   The dispute is over an <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> law that allows farmers to be
reimbursed by the county if dogs kill their farm animals.
   <PERSON>Michael Erwin</PERSON> of <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> filed a <MONEY>$600</MONEY> claim for two ostriches
killed by dogs.
   But <ORGANIZATION>Warren County Commissioners</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> damages can be
collected only on animals that provide meat, eggs, or feathers, and
ostriches didn't.
   ``No one could think of any (agricultural value of the
ostrich),'' said commission President <PERSON>George Terwilleger</PERSON>.
   He invited <PERSON>Erwin</PERSON> to appeal, and <PERSON>Erwin</PERSON> said he would.
   ``I think that ostrich farming has as much credibility as cattle
farming or sheep farming,'' said <PERSON>Erwin</PERSON>, 32.
   He said ostrich hides and feathers are sold in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, and he
plans to breed ostriches for meat. He said the meat is more of a
bargain than turkey.
   ``You get a lot more bird for your money.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06089136 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06089136 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Karen T. Borchers -- Mercury News; One of five ostriches
rounded up at a home in Almaden Valley on Thursday peers through a fence on
the property, at left. PHOTO: A Customs agent who asked not to be identified,
right, looks into garage where more than $300,000 worth of ostrich eggs were
being incubated.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; AGRICULTURE; OFFICIAL; SAN-JOSE; UNUSUAL; ARREST; AFRICA; BIRD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  U.S. Customs Agent Matt Van Dyke is used to storming houses to arrest
suspected drug dealers and other bad guys.;    But this was the first time his
prey wanted to bury its head in the sand.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CUSTOMS AGENTS SCRAMBLE TO ROUND UP OSTRICHES,
EGGS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     This week, <PERSON>Van Dyke</PERSON> went on his first ostrich raid.;    He and other agents
from Customs and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> were called in <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
to seize more than 300 ostrich eggs and four ostrich chicks from a home in <LOCATION>San
Jose</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Almaden Valley</LOCATION>. And, oh yes, there was the matter of chasing down five
6-foot-tall ostriches in the back yard when agents returned Thursday.;   
Customs officials believe the 300 eggs -- valued at more than <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> -- were
imported from <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> <DATE>less than 10 days ago</DATE>. Customs officials say the
importation of the eggs is prohibited by federal law because they may carry
Newcastle disease, a contagious, highly lethal virus that affects birds'
respiratory and nervous systems and can spread through a flock quickly.;   
The eggs -- and birds -- will be quarantined for 45 days.;    The owner of the
<PERSON>McKean</PERSON> Road house, <PERSON>Stacey Siegert-McGowen</PERSON>, has not been charged but remains
under investigation, <PERSON>Van Dyke</PERSON> said.;    He would not say whether these
ostriches are part of a larger, illegal wildlife importation ring.;   
According to <PERSON>Van Dyke</PERSON>, ostrich importing is a very lucrative business.
Unhatched fertilized eggs can go for more than <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> each, newborn chicks can
bring in more than <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY>, and a full-grown mating pair can be sold for more
than <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>.;    According to <PERSON>Patti Stickler</PERSON>, owner of Stickler Premium
Ostriches of <LOCATION>Turpin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Okla.</LOCATION>, their value is so high because there is a lot of
money to be made in ostrich meat.;    "It's because the meat tastes like beef
but has less calories and fat than chicken," said <PERSON>Stickler</PERSON>. "All the ostriches
being sold now are going to grow up to be breeders.";    Right now, she said,
large-scale processing of ostriches is about eight years away so that ostrich
"farmers" can build a breeding base of more than 180,000 birds.;    A single
ostrich can lay up to 80 eggs per year and, when slaughtered, provide 125
pounds of red meat.;    <PERSON>Stickler</PERSON> said she has been offered <MONEY>$225,000</MONEY> for a
mating pair.;    The investigation into the <LOCATION>Almaden Valley</LOCATION> home was initiated
with the <DATE>October 1990</DATE> arrest of <PERSON>Roger Jacobson</PERSON>, who allegedly attempted to
smuggle 327 eggs into the <LOCATION>United States.</LOCATION>;    Also confiscated from the home's
garage were one huge incubator and several smaller ones and various related
documents discovered upon execution of the search warrants.;    The
confiscated items -- including the full-grown birds -- will be taken to the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> station in <LOCATION>San Ysidro</LOCATION> for quarantine, <ORGANIZATION>Van Dyke</ORGANIZATION>
said. If they are found to be healthy, they will be sold at auction.;    If
Customs officials determine that the eggs and the birds were imported
illegally, Siegert-McGowen and others involved in the case could face felony
charges of smuggling of merchandise contrary to the law, and smuggling of
wildlife contrary to the law, which both carry -- at the minimum -- stiff
fines, <PERSON>Van Dyke</PERSON> said.;    But it wasn't the desire to "get their man" that
drove Van Dyke and other Customs and <ORGANIZATION>Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION> agents
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. It was the desire to get those birds, which were left in a two-acre
grazing pen behind the home.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MICHELLE GUIDO, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910329  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  614  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday March 29, 1991
00089136,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890821-0101 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890821 </DD>
<AN> 890821-0101. </AN>
<HL> One-Horse Town
@  Has Five Ostriches
@  That Lay $35 Eggs
@  ---
@  People of Plentywood, Mont.,
@  Also Try to Make a Buck
@  Selling Korea Elk Velvet
@  ----
@  By Scott McMurray
<DD> 08/21/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<DATELINE> PLENTYWOOD, Mont.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This rural outpost, 400 miles northeast of <ORGANIZATION>Helena</ORGANIZATION>, has one stoplight and five ostriches. 

   Other inhabitants include mountain lions, Nubian ibexes, African sheep, Asian goats, and llamas. 

   There are 2,500 people here, too, a number of whom -- 10 maybe -- have turned to exotic-animal husbandry as a way around drought and persistent rural recession. 
To make money, in other words. 
Nobody knows why people are taking up this sideline -- here particularly -- but they are. 
At least, says <PERSON>Steven Howard</PERSON>, county attorney and ostrich rancher: "It's more interesting than cattle or sheep." 

   So when breakfast conversation down at <ORGANIZATION>Randy's Cafe</ORGANIZATION> turns to the subject of eggs, it might just be a local banker and <PERSON>Mr. Howard</PERSON> discussing ostrich fertility rates -- and counting their <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> chicks before they are hatched. 

   Sometimes, the talk concerns elk velvet -- another Plentywood export. 
The fuzz-covered immature antlers that sprout each year from elk heads are, in powdered form, a popular aphrodisiac in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and elsewhere in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. 
People here figure the rising price of antlers has to do with the <DATE>1986</DATE> nuclear-reactor disaster in <LOCATION>Chernobyl</LOCATION>. 
Radioactive fallout from the plant contaminated the reindeer feeding grounds in northern <LOCATION>Scandinavia</LOCATION>. 
Hence, <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION>, who also have a lot of discretionary income these days, are shopping for elk antlers in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. 

   Local grain-store operator <PERSON>Harry</PERSON> "Tubby" Hilyard, meanwhile, has only to display his huge red welts to prove he is telling the truth about the time one of his 150-pound mountain lions bit through his arm. 

   "If you act afraid, they won't let go," he says, speaking from experience, adding that he had to talk reassuringly to the big cat for several seconds before it let him loose and went back to its customary dinner of beef tartare. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hilyard</PERSON> bought his first mountain lion, <ORGANIZATION>Hobo</ORGANIZATION>, from a zoo in southern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and tried keeping it as a pet. 
But "he didn't take to my wife, and cost me a couple of drapes," he says. 
Now Hobo guards the feed store. 

   Not everyone here is an exotic-animal enthusiast, far from it. 
<PERSON>Robert Kane</PERSON>, a local veterinarian for 24 years, says there is little established demand, except from other breeders, for many of the animals people here are raising. 
He expects the prices some exotic animals and their byproducts fetch will go down as more producers jump in. 
"This looks a lot to me like what we had with chinchillas 20 years ago," he says. 
"We had at least three breeders here who lost all their investment." 

   But exotic-animal entrepreneurs don't look back just to be dissuaded by history. 
<PERSON>Mr. Hilyard</PERSON>'s scheme is to build a hunters' paradise. 
He plans to fence in about 100 acres of his ranch five miles north of town and hold lion hunts in the hills and gullies. 
Customers will pay (he hopes) up to <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> to stalk and shoot a male lion. 
An additional few thousand acres of land he owns eventually could be used for bighorn sheep shoots, at a fee something more like <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> a head. 

   But for the moment, the food bill is mounting for his pride of lions. 
"They go through a cow a week," says the portly 50-year-old, who has helped clean out many a local deep freezer. 
People give him pastits -- prime meat they are throwing out, also their sick cattle. 

   Meanwhile, back at the <ORGANIZATION>Big Sky Ostrich Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Howard</PERSON>, the county attorney, and <PERSON>Jerry Wiedebush</PERSON>, the president of <ORGANIZATION>Security State Bank</ORGANIZATION>, are eagerly awaiting the birth of their first ostrich chick. 
Eggs the size of grapefruit, weighing four pounds each and gleaming like porcelain, rotate once an hour in their small wooden incubator. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Wiedebush</PERSON> got the idea to raise ostriches after reading a magazine article last year about the money to be made in breeding the big birds. 
He brought <PERSON>Mr. Howard</PERSON> in on the plan. 

   Their two ostrich hens, <PERSON>Sally</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lonnie</PERSON>, have laid more than 50 infertile eggs, much to the consternation of Plentywood's after-hours ostrich ranchers. 
Of course, even unhatched eggs aren't a total loss: Some people are willing to pay <MONEY>$35</MONEY> for one they can paint and resell as art. 

   The real potential payoff is in chicks, which can fetch <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> at the age of 10 weeks. 
The ranchers hope eventually to build a troop of 20 to 24 birds, some of which they might sell as leather and feathers. 
<PERSON>Mr. Howard</PERSON>, dodging an attempt by <PERSON>Lonnie</PERSON> to peck the glasses off his face, is among those who have noticed that the current market for chicks is almost exclusively other breeders. 

   Ostriches normally go for the warmer climates of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Near East</LOCATION>. 
Plentywood is just 18 miles south of the Canadian border. 
Nevertheless, the eight-foot-tall birds didn't appear to suffer during their first <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> winter last year, when outdoor temperatures dropped to 30 below zero. 
"We didn't even turn the heat on in the barn," he says. 
The ostrich ranchers lost one bird, however, after it swallowed a piece of ice and bled to death from the throat. 

   Plentywood got its start in animal exotica partly because of <ORGANIZATION>Walt Arion</ORGANIZATION>. 
The lean, weather-beaten rancher took up exotic game ranching eight years ago, raising small numbers of Nubian ibexes, fallow deer, yaks, bezoar goats, mouflons, buffaloes and elk. 
His ranch is named Elk Haven, but he recently sold 15 of his 26 elk to Canadian buyers as breeding stock. 
He made the sale to pay off some of what he had borrowed from banker <PERSON>Wiedebush</PERSON>, the latter-day ostrich breeder. 

   His success at finding buyers for his most exotic breeds has been mixed. 
"Everybody thinks I'm making a mint," <PERSON>Mr. Arion</PERSON> says. 
"But you don't move this stuff in a minute." 

   One of the area's largest offbeat animal outfits is south of town, where <PERSON>Robert Spokley</PERSON> and his son-in-law, <PERSON>Bill Nyby</PERSON>, tend a herd of about 100 elk. 
In the past several weeks, they have been tranquilizing their two-year-old bulls. 
The elk then are blindfolded and their velvet-covered antlers, which will sprout again next year, are sawed off. (Ranchers must take care to cut above the pedicel, the growth bud at the base of each antler; otherwise, next year's output could be seriously deformed.) 

   Buyers from <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> swing through this time of year to buy the 10- to 14-pound antlers, which ranchers keep fresh in their freezers. 
Buyers pay <MONEY>$70</MONEY> to <MONEY>$75</MONEY> a pound. 
Although in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> the antlers are ground up and used as aphrodisiacs, <PERSON>Mr. Spokley</PERSON> says, "Let's not forget they use them for medicinal purposes, too." 
He doesn't know of any in particular, but he is sure there are some. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Spokley</PERSON> said that certain elk raisers also have hunts on their property. 
He isn't interested, but not for humane reasons. 
"There's no point," he says, "in shooting an animal that will produce <MONEY>$700</MONEY> to <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> a year for 20 years." 
