<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06153001 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06153001 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-FRANCISCO; BRIDGE; AUTO; VEHICLE; COST; INCREASE; CHART  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Directors of the Golden Gate Bridge District on Friday boosted the toll for
cars from $2 to $3, making the new fee three times as expensive as any other
bridge toll in California.;    Directors said without the increase, they would
have to cut transit service by 50 percent and would be unable to retrofit the
54-year-old span to withstand a major earthquake.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  California News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MARIN MOANS AT $3 GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE TOLL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to end of article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The new toll takes effect <DATE>July 1.</DATE>;    The action brought hoots from several
residents attending the board meeting. Wearing a broach in the shape of the
Golden Gate Bridge with a tea bag hanging from it, <LOCATION>Tiburon</LOCATION> resident <PERSON>Susan
Deluxe</PERSON> told the board, "This is bad government at its worst.;    " 'I got
ripped off on my way to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>' will become a new saying.";    Carrying
a placard that read, "Fight the <MONEY>$3</MONEY> Toll," <PERSON>Gene Pratt</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Rafael</LOCATION> told the
board: "We will take this fight to <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>. There will be 100,000 of us
before this is over!";    Under the plan adopted by a 13-5 vote, tolls will be
<MONEY>$3</MONEY> for cars, but commuters who use discounted monthly toll books will pay
<MONEY>$2.22</MONEY>, up from <MONEY>$1.67</MONEY>. About <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of the bridge's motorists use the
advance-purchase discount tickets.;    Fares for Golden Gate Transit buses and
ferries also will increase by <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> each year.;    The increased tolls
and fares are expected to raise <MONEY>$102 million</MONEY>, partly for seismic upgrading on
the bridge. Toll booths will be renovated, and an electronic toll collection
system will be installed.;    The toll increase did not come as a surprise.
The district held four public meetings in <DATE>April</DATE> and <DATE>May</DATE>, and on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the
board's finance committee approved the boost before submitting it to the full
panel.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Air Quality Management District</ORGANIZATION> had urged a <MONEY>$3</MONEY> toll to
reduce the number of vehicles on the bridge. One speaker, <ORGANIZATION>Red Dodge</ORGANIZATION>, urged the
toll be raised even higher, to <MONEY>$5</MONEY>, to persuade people to take mass transit.;  
 The board's action <DATE>Friday</DATE> did not alter the current carpool policy. Cars with
three or more occupants do not pay a toll from 5 to <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> and from 4 to <TIME>6
p.m.</TIME>;    Unlike the state's nine other toll bridges, the Golden Gate Bridge
does not come under the purview of the <ORGANIZATION>State Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION>. Its
board is independent.;    The current one-way car toll of <MONEY>$2</MONEY> every day has
been in effect since <DATE>1988</DATE>. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, the district voted to make the toll <MONEY>$1</MONEY>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> through <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and <MONEY>$2</MONEY> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> and Saturday.;    When the bridge
was opened on <DATE>May 28, 1937</DATE>, the toll was <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> each way. As the district
paid off its debt, the toll gradually dropped to <MONEY>25 cents</MONEY> each way by <DATE>1955</DATE>. In
<DATE>1968</DATE>, the district began charging tolls only on the way into <LOCATION>San Francisco.</LOCATION>;  
 <LOCATION>Golden Gate</LOCATION>'s; new toll rates;  Cars, regular rate                   <MONEY>$3</MONEY>;
Cars, 12-ticket rate (x)          <MONEY>$2.22</MONEY>; Rush-hour car pools               
Free; Trucks, three-axle                <MONEY>$4.50</MONEY>; Trucks, nine-axle              
 <MONEY>$13.50</MONEY>; (x) Price rises to <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> for the second, third, and fourth years and
to <MONEY>$2.67</MONEY> in <DATE>1995</DATE>-'96.; Source: <ORGANIZATION>McClatchy News Service</ORGANIZATION>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  McClatchy News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910601  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  CHART  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  531  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday June 1, 1991
00153001,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901103-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-03-90 1635EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--Quake-Bridge     11-03 0153</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Quake-Bridge,0151</SECOND>
<HEAD>Quake-Proofing Design Study Set for Golden Gate Bridge</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Golden Gate Bridge made it through the
big <DATE>1989</DATE> earthquake without any apparent damage, but bridge
directors think a <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY> quake-proofing project would be a
wise investment.
   ``Quite frankly, that's a good bargain,'' said director <PERSON>Jim
Harberson</PERSON>.
   He said replacing the 53-year-old Golden Gate would cost about
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>.
   A committee of bridge directors voted <DATE>Friday</DATE> to spend <MONEY>$550,000</MONEY>
for a design study on a project that would srengthen the bridge so
it can withstand an earthquake with a Richter scale magnitude of 8
or greater.
   The retrofitting project would cost <MONEY>$75 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>,
and financing remains ``the big question,'' <PERSON>Harberson</PERSON> said.
   The <DATE>October 1989</DATE> earthquake registered 7.1 on the Richter scale
Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900601-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-01-90 0629EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Gorbachev-Chaos     06-01 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Gorbachev-Chaos,0438</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rush Hour Drive Scratched in Latest Gorbachev Tour Change</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The threat of rush hour traffic over the
Golden Gate Bridge apparently proved too much for organizers of
<PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> tour.
   Tentative plans were scrapped <DATE>Thursday</DATE> for a <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> motorcade
over the landmark span to <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>.
   The Soviet leader and his wife, <PERSON>Raisa</PERSON>, will instead view the
bridge from a parking lot on the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> side. <PERSON>Robert
Stockwell</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate Bridge District</ORGANIZATION>, is to give
the Gorbachevs a tour <DATE>Monday</DATE> of gardens near the bridge's toll plaza.
   ``We want to show them the most beautiful part of the bridge and
show them the view that millions of visitors have admired,'' he said.
   Stockwell also is to present the Gorbachevs with several bridge
mementos, including a section of the original suspension cable, a
copy of Chief Engineer <PERSON>Joseph Strauss</PERSON>'s original report on how and
why the bridge was built and a pair of sweat shirts.
   Civic leaders hope the trip will boost <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s economic
spirits, devastated by the <DATE>Oct. 17</DATE> earthquake.
   ``<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> has been feeling some of the downturn in business
ever since the earthquake,'' Chamber of <ORGANIZATION>Commerce</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Carol
Piasente</PERSON> said. ``Having <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> visit is a great boost to the
local economy.''
   At <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, the post office plans to issue a special envelope
<DATE>Monday</DATE> commemorating the <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> visit with a special cancellation
design featuring <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>'s face above the word ``Stanford,''
written in Cyrillic alphabet.
   At <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the Soviet flag will be flying.
Mayor Art Agnos, joined by Soviet Consul General <PERSON>Valentin Kamenev</PERSON>
and the city's chief of protocol, <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> Mailliard Swig, planned
to raise the flag today off the balcony of the mayor's office.
   ``There's a great deal of excitement about the visit,'' said <PERSON>Ms.
Piasente</PERSON> said. ``We're fielding hundreds of phone calls.''
   While <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> meets with <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> business leaders, <PERSON>Mrs.
Gorbachev</PERSON> will take a separate tour of the city <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>,
traveling by motorcade to <LOCATION>Golden Gate Park</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>War Memorial Opera
House</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Davies Symphony Hall</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of America</ORGANIZATION> building and
Fisherman's Wharf.
   Earlier plans to include the Civic Center, where dozens of
homeless people have been living for months, were dropped.
   The Gorbachevs' whirlwind tour _ arriving in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME> and leaving <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> _ will include a bit of
socializing.
   Four members of a group called ``Friends of <PERSON>Raisa Gorbachev</PERSON>''
were scheduled to meet with <PERSON>Mrs. Gorbachev</PERSON> at the Soviet consul
general's residence for a ``nonpolitical, people-to-people''
conversation.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102089-0169 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 123443 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 20, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Special Section; Part Q; Page 4; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
202 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE BAY AREA QUAKE; 
</P>
<P>
5:04 P.M.; 
</P>
<P>
A TIME WHEN LIVES CHANGED; 
</P>
<P>
TALES OF THE QUAKE: DEATH, HEROES AND LUCK ; 
</P>
<P>
ON GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE -- A SCARE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CATHLEEN DECKER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Lissa Collins-Gudim</PERSON>, 28, was halfway across the Golden Gate Bridge, heading 
toward <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> from a house-hunting trip to <LOCATION>Sonoma</LOCATION> with her husband, <PERSON>Tim</PERSON>, 
when it began. 
</P>
<P>
"The first thing I thought was maybe we'd lost all four tires," said the 
<LOCATION>Pacific Palisades</LOCATION> resident. "All of a sudden, the guy driving us, the real 
estate broker, said: 'Oh, my God! We're having an earthquake!' And then it got 
worse. 
</P>
<P>
"The bridge was swaying . . . . The next thing that happened is that it began 
waving. It fanned, sort of. The cables -- the little ones that go up and down 
-- were like spaghetti. The big ones, those big fat ones, they were moving from 
side to side, six feet in either direction." 
</P>
<P>
Brake lights flared. Cars screeched to a halt, each driver trying to avoid the 
next. Across the bay in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, a huge column of dust arose from the 
collapsed buildings in the <LOCATION>Marina District</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
On the Golden Gate, the swaying lasted 40 to 50 seconds, Collins-Gudim 
estimated, nearly three times the elapsed time of the actual quake. 
</P>
<P>
"I just thought I was never going to see my kids again," she said. "I had my 
hand on the car door. If we were going to fall in the water, I didn't want to 
drown." CATHLEEN DECKER 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EARTHQUAKES -- SAN FRANCISCO; EARTHQUAKES -- NORTHERN CALIFORNIA; GOLDEN GATE 
BRIDGE; DISASTER VICTIMS; COMMUTING; FEAR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102089-0173 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 123453 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 20, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Special Section; Part Q; Page 7; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
981 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE BAY AREA QUAKE; 
</P>
<P>
PRESSURE POINTS; 
</P>
<P>
WHAT WORKED, WHAT DIDN'T, AND WHY; 
</P>
<P>
BRIDGES; 
</P>
<P>
QUESTIONS GROW ON FLAW THAT BROKE BAY SPAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By STEVEN R. CHURM, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The way <PERSON>Jim Sawyer</PERSON> figures it, the collapse of a 50-foot length of the Bay 
Bridge may have begun with a two-cent rivet. <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> has made a career of 
designing and examining bridges, and he is sure that the seismic blast from the 
earthquake snapped a row of rivets and caused a patch of concrete five lanes 
wide to give way on the top deck of the Bay Bridge. 
</P>
<P>
The falling slab pierced the traffic lanes on the lower deck, exposing daylight 
and the chilly bay waters 250 feet below. Two cars wedged by the falling debris 
teetered on the edge of the damaged roadway. Initial reports said some 
motorists jumped into the water, but the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> said there is no evidence 
of that. 
</P>
<P>
It was a staggering scene, one that framed the disaster for a nation that had 
tuned in to watch Game 3 of the World Series only to see live pictures of a 
stricken bridge. 
</P>
<P>
And <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Tampa Bay</LOCATION> civil engineer watching on television in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, could 
not help but think about the rivets that join the huge concrete panels on the 
bridge. 
</P>
<P>
"It was probably a connection failure, right about where the rivets sit," 
<PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> said. "Chances are it wouldn't happen in a hundred years. Those rivets 
are routinely inspected." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> and other structural experts who watched the quake's flattening 
power say it is impossible to examine each joint, each beam and each rivet. 
</P>
<P>
"Truth is you can't go over it with a microscope," <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In time, <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> officials will eyeball, photograph, measure and note what 
happened to the failed link of the Bay Bridge and draw conclusions as to the 
cause. And they will undoubtedly ponder why the Golden Gate Bridge, the more 
glamorous of the twin spans that link <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> with its bayside neighbors, 
weathered the shake with little more than a superficial crack or two. 
</P>
<P>
One theory advanced by experts focuses on the inability of the Bay Bridge to 
bend or give when struck sideways by the powerful ground waves generated by the 
temblor. As evidence, the roadway collapse occurred along one of the bridge's 
most rigid sections. 
</P>
<P>
"The bridge didn't give. It broke," said one structural engineer, who requested 
anonymity because he has a contract with the state. "It was more like a stick 
that snapped than a rubber band that stretched. That jolt may have displaced 
the bridge as much as a foot before that section went." 
</P>
<P>
State highway officials have declined to speculate, saying it is too soon to 
know what caused the bridge failure. <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> has spent <MONEY>$58 million</MONEY> since the 
<DATE>1971</DATE> Sylmar earthquake to strengthen and upgrade 1,500 bridges in quake-prone 
areas, including the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>. Among the retrofitted structures was the <LOCATION>Bay 
Bridge</LOCATION>, where crews retied the bridge decks to column supports, <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> 
spokeswoman <PERSON>Lisa Covington</PERSON> said. A second <MONEY>$64-million</MONEY> phase to reinforce more 
than 700 bridge columns and supports statewide should be completed by <DATE>1992</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"Some retrofitting of the Bay Bridge has been done, but what sections had been 
worked on is unclear," <PERSON>Covington</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jim McCarty</PERSON> believes the busted bridge may have had more to do with geography 
than concrete patch jobs. The Bay Bridge, built during the Depression, runs 
east and west, tying <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> with <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. When the quake hit, it sent a 
powerful ground swell north from its epicenter near <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> toward the Bay 
Bridge, said <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>'s public works director for two decades. 
</P>
<P>
The Bay Bridge incorporates three engineering styles, with the <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> side of 
the bridge supported by metal trusses. Unlike the Golden Gate Bridge or even 
the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> side of the Bay Bridge, both of which are supported by cables 
that give when rocked by a quake, metal trusses tend to be more resistant to 
movement, <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Thus, when the quake's powerful groundswell broadsided the bridge, a chunk of 
the upper deck collapsed, <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The Golden Gate Bridge, which opened a year after the Bay Bridge, was spared 
because it was perpendicular to ground motion. The Golden Gate's roadbed, 
resting in a massive sling of cables and span, swayed with the 15-second shake 
but survived intact. 
</P>
<P>
"A truss bridge is much more rigid, much less forgiving," <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON> said. "The TV 
pictures showed us that." 
</P>
<P>
The section of bridge that failed is over a pier support, and <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON> said he 
believes that the columns supporting the roadway "separated ever so slightly, 
and boom, the concrete gave way." 
</P>
<P>
Moments after it happened, <PERSON>Thomas Kelly</PERSON> was driving his camper on the bridge's 
upper deck, trying to return to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. Then, as he videotaped the 
confusion among rattled motorists around him, he witnessed a car falling 
through the crevice in the roadway. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a moment frozen in my mind," said <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON>, an Oklahoman who was vacationing 
in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> with his wife, <PERSON>Debbie</PERSON>. "One minute the car was there. The next 
it was gone. I really thought we were next. I thought the entire bridge was 
going." 
</P>
<P>
The Golden Gate remained opened, and after several closures to inspect joints 
and seams, the <LOCATION>San Mateo Bridge</LOCATION> was declared safe and passable for motorists 
fewer than 24 hours after the quake. 
</P>
<P>
Reopening the Bay Bridge, traveled daily by half a million motorists, is less 
certain. 
</P>
<P>
A large marine crane moved into place <DATE>Thursday</DATE> below the wounded structure to 
lift the downed section bridge in an attempt to assess the damage. Officials 
also considered spanning the gap with steel girders called <ORGANIZATION>Bailey Bridges</ORGANIZATION>, a 
World War II innovation to move tanks and heavy equipment across waterways. 
</P>
<P>
It is a temporary fix, at best, and one <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> official said rather than 
putting a "Band-Aid on the hurt, we'd like to fix it right." But that could 
mean it will be several weeks before the toll bridge is open again for 
business. 
</P>
<P>
"That bridge has done a damn good job for 50 years," said <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> 
resident for most of his life. "Until it's reopened, life just won't be the 
same." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Linda Reed looks over the edge of a collapsed section of the Bay Bridge 
in an unsuccessful search for her husband among the victims trapped in the 
rubble. United Press International 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EARTHQUAKES -- SAN FRANCISCO; EARTHQUAKES -- NORTHERN CALIFORNIA; OAKLAND (CA); 
BRIDGE COLLAPSES; SAN FRANCISCO OAKLAND BAY BRIDGE; ENGINEERING; BUILDING 
MATERIALS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06149178 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06149178 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BRIDGE; COST; INCREASE; PLANNING; SF-BAY-AREA; ANALYSIS  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A proposal to raise tolls on the Golden Gate Bridge to $3 has roiled this
normally serene enclave and brought a wave of rhetoric more recently heard on
the lips of Soviet dissidents.;    Bridge directors "defy the will of the
people . . . and we have no recourse," complained Gene Prat, one leader of a
group called Marin United Taxpayers Association. "It's undemocratic and
contrary to everything in this country. It's an atrocity."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  $3 'ATROCITY': A TOLL TOO FAR?
GOLDEN GATE PLAN WOULD BE 2ND $1 PRICE HIKE
IN 2 YEARS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on P. 2B of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <MONEY>$1</MONEY> price hike would be the second in <DATE>two years.</DATE>;    The Golden Gate
bridge district says tolls have to be raised to cover a projected <MONEY>$14 million</MONEY>
deficit. The additional money is needed to make the bridge earthquake-safe and
to stanch financial losses from the bus and ferry lines that provide the only
alternative to air-polluting cars, says <PERSON>Carney Campion</PERSON>, the district's general
manager.;    With such seemingly solid reasons for a price hike, one has to
ask: Is a dollar more per day really going to prove a hardship for residents
of the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>'s wealthiest county?;    <ORGANIZATION>Marin</ORGANIZATION> protesters brush aside such
queries and say that the issue is really one of democratic rights.;    "This
is taxation without representation," Prat said.;    In fact, the <LOCATION>Golden Gate</LOCATION>
bridge district is something of a political anomaly in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. It runs the
only toll bridge in the state not operated by <ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION>. And its 19-member
board is appointed by six member counties according to a complex formula that
has preserved, even through several changes, its "north-south" balance.;   
That balance means <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> gets nine seats on the board, although
everyone acknowledges that the majority of bridge users are <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>
residents.;    <ORGANIZATION>Board</ORGANIZATION> members serve at the pleasure of the appointing body --
usually county supervisors or other elected officials -- and many have served
lengthy terms. One, <PERSON>L.E. Castner</PERSON>, a retired insurance executive from <LOCATION>Boyes Hot
Springs</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Sonoma County</LOCATION>, has been on the board since <DATE>1952.</DATE>;    The district's
six counties -- <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sonoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Napa</LOCATION>, Mendocino and <ORGANIZATION>Del Norte</ORGANIZATION> --
are the ones that pledged their residents' personal property to guarantee a
bond issue of <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY> to build the bridge, which was completed -- without
a nickel of federal or state money -- in <DATE>1937</DATE>. The bridge was completely paid
off by <DATE>1971</DATE>, which is just around the time the district asked the Legislature
to allow it to begin running bus and ferry lines for commuters.;    One
commuter on board;  Mill Valley Mayor <PERSON>Richard Spotswood</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
attorney who is the only board member to regularly commute over the bridge,
understands the frustration of fellow <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION> residents.;    "<LOCATION>Marin
County</LOCATION> is not asking anyone to feel sorry for it," said <LOCATION>Spotswood</LOCATION>, who admits
he drives a Mercedes most days rather than taking the bus across the bridge.
"It would just like to control its own destiny.";    But he also notes that a
directly elected board -- a prime goal of the taxpayers group -- would, if
based on population, leave <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION> with even fewer representatives than
the four it now has.;    "It's a quandary," <LOCATION>Spotswood</LOCATION> said.;    About 124,000
cars cross the graceful, 1.7-mile span every day, while a fleet of 270 buses
carries 28,000 commuters and four ferries ply an additional 4,000 across the
bay. Carpools -- about 1,000 a day -- cross free of charge.;    Revenues
shrink;  To a certain extent, the district's success in persuading drivers to
give up their cars for mass transit has hurt its finances, manager <PERSON>Campion</PERSON>
said. A <MONEY>$125 million</MONEY> price tag for earthquake improvements -- even with <PERCENT>80
percent</PERCENT> expected from federal sources -- has only deepened the district's
financial woes.;    It's widely expected that the board will approve the <MONEY>$3</MONEY>
toll later this week, with rate hikes effective <DATE>July 1</DATE>. But the real political
tussle will come over discount rates for commuters -- which now stand at <MONEY>$1.67</MONEY>
but may rise significantly.;    "The average person in <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION> says <MONEY>$3</MONEY> is a lot
for a toll," <LOCATION>Spotswood</LOCATION> said. "You can give them good reasons but it still just
seems like a lot."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  MIRANDA EWELL, Mercury News San Francisco Bureau  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Rafael  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910528  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  678  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday May 28, 1991
00149178,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102389-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 124863 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 23, 1989, Monday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 1; Column 6; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
520 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BAY AREA CREEPS TO WORK AT A BUMPER-TO-BUMPER PACE; 
</P>
<P>
GALES, WILD WAVES, RAIN -- MISERY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CATHLEEN DECKER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Their misery compounded by soaking rain and bone-chilling winds, hundreds of 
thousands of <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> commuters struggled to work aboard the remaining links of 
the earthquake-ravaged transportation system today. Conditions across the area 
were crowded and chaotic, but mass gridlock was avoided. 
</P>
<P>
"We've got gale winds, heavy rains and heavy traffic -- your basic nightmare 
conditions," said <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Highway Patrol Officer <PERSON>John Lash</PERSON>. "Somebody up 
there doesn't like us." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bruce Selby</PERSON>, a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate Bridge District</ORGANIZATION>, said officials 
there were "absolutely amazed that things are going so smoothly." 
</P>
<P>
"People are turning to mass transit, he said. "Our buses and ferries are 
running at double and triple the normal level." 
</P>
<P>
But "smoothly" was still only relative. Neophyte riders of the <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Rapid 
Transit District</ORGANIZATION> subway were drenched while waiting for cars that carried them, 
sardine-like, from the <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. An armada of ferryboats 
braved squalls and rough seas to deliver their seasick passengers to <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> piers. To the south near the epicenter of <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s quake, <LOCATION>Santa Cruz 
County</LOCATION> travelers made their way to work on Highway 17 thanks to a fleet of <ORGANIZATION>CHP</ORGANIZATION> 
escorts. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, meanwhile, the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> announced that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> will 
seek <MONEY>$2.5 billion</MONEY> in new federal aid for earthquake victims -- a figure well 
below that sought by congressional Democrats who were working on a relief 
package. Estimates of the actual cost of damages continued to mount, exceeding 
<MONEY>$6.6 billion</MONEY> at last count. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> coroner added two more victims to the list of confirmed dead, 
bringing that tally to 61. Another 52 people were officially missing and 
believed trapped in the yet-uncleared wreckage of the <ORGANIZATION>Nimitz Freeway</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. Officials in <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> also launched a search for a man believed to 
have been trapped in a landslide on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Bay Area workers, returning en masse to work for the first time since <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s 
6.9 temblor, were forced onto BART trains, ferries and roundabout freeways 
because of the collapse of the <ORGANIZATION>Nimitz Freeway</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay 
Bridge</LOCATION>. Authorities were also forced to close I-280 and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s 
Embarcadero Freeway because of threatening cracks. 
</P>
<P>
By <TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME>, BART had carried 99,732 passengers, compared to an average of 
69,638 on a normal weekday. Two passengers fainted after getting off trains at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Embarcadero Station</ORGANIZATION> after crossing the bay. 
</P>
<P>
"They were hyperventilating, I guess from being nervous in the tube," said 
<PERSON>Debby Tudor</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Westinghouse Elevator</ORGANIZATION> technician dispatched to tend to the 
station's escalators. 
</P>
<P>
But traffic from the northern suburbs over the Golden Gate Bridge was fast and 
smooth. And the morning commute on Highway 101 from the southern suburbs began 
light -- but then the freeway flooded. 
</P>
<P>
"Mother Nature is having a field day with us," commuter <PERSON>Joyce Bustinduy</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
At sea, it was even rougher. Hundreds of commuters -- many afraid of traveling 
in the under-bay BART tube -- sought to make their way to work aboard ferries, 
but found the boats crowded and the seas wild. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Stormy commute -- Heavy Marin County and East Bay traffic jams Golden 
Gate Bridge early today as many are forced to go long way around in rain to get 
into San Francisco with the Bay Bridge closed. J. ALBERT DIAZ / Los Angeles 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06149070 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06149070 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: (Golden Gate Bridge)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  EARTHQUAKE; REPAIR; CHANGE; BRIDGE; SF-BAY-AREA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  An engineering firm has recommended a series of improvements to enable the
Golden Gate Bridge to survive a major earthquake. T.Y. Lin International of
San Francisco recommended strengthening the structure and "tuning" it to make
it less prone to shaking. The project is expected to take five years.
Preliminary cost estimate is $125 million. These are among the key quake
recommendations:; (box)Bridge towers: Strengthen the 746-foot twin steel
spires that form each tower, the struts that connect them, the saddles on top
that hold the main cables and the reinforced concrete piers supporting the
towers. Rebuild connections to roadway supports.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MAKING BRIDGE QUAKE-SAFE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related story on P. 1B of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  (box)Pylons: Strengthen the concrete pylons at each end of the bridge,
anchoring them securely to bedrock, and anchor the steel tie-downs that hold
the bridge's main cables to bedrock.; (box)Viaducts leading to bridge: At both
ends, strengthen the towers and piers that support the roadway trusses, and
the trusses themselves, and install bearings designed to isolate the trusses
from earthquake motion. At the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> end, install shock-absorbing
units in the <LOCATION>Fort Point</LOCATION> arch at far left to dissipate the earthquake's energy.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910528  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  200  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday May 28, 1991
00149070,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA053190-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 226702 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 31, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
912 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BAY AREA LIFTS BROW AT GORBACHEVS' TOUR; 
</P>
<P>
DIPLOMACY: RAISA'S PLANNED STOP AT FISHERMAN'S WHARF IS SEEN AS DECLASSE. 
WORSE, THE COUPLE WILL CLOG TRAFFIC BY VISITING THE GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE AT RUSH 
HOUR. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAN MORAIN, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The excitement surrounding Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>'s upcoming 
visit here was tempered <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with the release of his wife's itinerary and 
news that the Gorbachevs hope to visit the Golden Gate Bridge -- at rush hour. 
</P>
<P>
To ensure security, Golden Gate Bridge officials and the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Highway 
Patrol plan to slow traffic on the heavily traveled bridge while the Gorbachevs 
and their 30-car motorcade make their way across, sometime between <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> and <TIME>7 
p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Earlier that afternoon, <PERSON>Raisa Gorbachev</PERSON> is tentatively scheduled to go on an 
hour-long tour of the city, viewing some of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s finest sights and 
some of its most blighted and tacky. 
</P>
<P>
"Talk about abominations," one <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> native involved in the planning 
sniffed upon hearing that <PERSON>Raisa Gorbachev</PERSON> will visit touristy Fisherman's 
Wharf. 
</P>
<P>
The itinerary released by <ORGANIZATION>PBN Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> public relations firm that 
is coordinating aspects of the visit, shows that her entourage apparently will 
bypass such monuments to Western consumerism as <ORGANIZATION>Union Square</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>I. Magnin</PERSON> said at one point they would close the entire store if she wanted to 
shop there. But she's not going to (<ORGANIZATION>Nordstrom</ORGANIZATION>). She's not going to go to <PERSON>I. 
Magnin</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Staci Walters</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>PBN</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
After spending the morning with her husband at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford University</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mrs. 
Gorbachev</PERSON> will take her tour. She probably will be escorted by <PERSON>Tatyana Kamenev</PERSON>, 
wife of the Soviet consul general, and perhaps <PERSON>Sherry Agnos</PERSON>, wife of Mayor Art 
Agnos, said <ORGANIZATION>Charlotte Mailliard Swig</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s chief of protocol. 
</P>
<P>
"They won't have much time, but I think she'll like it and come back," Swig 
said. "I just hope they don't stop in Civic Plaza." 
</P>
<P>
Her itinerary will include a trip to <LOCATION>Golden Gate Park</LOCATION>, perhaps a stop at a 
museum, and a visit to Civic Center, locale of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s ornate City <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> 
and home to hundreds of homeless people who camp in the plaza there. <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> has been sprucing up the plaza in recent months, but does not plan to 
relocate the residents. 
</P>
<P>
"It is part of life," Art <PERSON>Silverman</PERSON>, spokesman for Mayor Agnos, said of the 
tent dwellers in the plaza outside <LOCATION>City Hall</LOCATION>. "It is our own glasnost policy, 
you might say. We're not going to try to hide anything." 
</P>
<P>
"I think it's great," said <PERSON>Warden Coleman</PERSON>, 33, who has been living in the plaza 
for three months with his dog, Lady. The out-of-work bartender put down his 
book -- a spy novel -- and pointed out that if <PERSON>Mrs. Gorbachev</PERSON> drives by or 
stops at the plaza, "she'll get to see that her country isn't the only one 
having trouble." 
</P>
<P>
The tentative schedule also has <PERSON>Mrs. Gorbachev</PERSON> heading to the heart of the 
city's financial district, stopping at the 52-story <ORGANIZATION>Bank of America</ORGANIZATION> building, 
then going on to Fisherman's Wharf. 
</P>
<P>
While she tours <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, her husband is scheduled to speak to business 
and political leaders at the <ORGANIZATION>Fairmont Hotel</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> police spokesman 
<PERSON>David Ambrose</PERSON> said he expects that the largest demonstration of the Soviets' 
<LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> stop will take place outside the hotel. 
</P>
<P>
Southern <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> representatives of ethnic Armenian, Latvian, Estonian and 
Lithuanian groups said several busloads of demonstrators will arrive <DATE>Monday</DATE> 
from such locales as <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Santa Ana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"There won't be a shortage of Baltic flags flying around," said <PERSON>Jaak Treiman</PERSON>, a 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> attorney of Estonian extraction. 
</P>
<P>
At the Fairmont, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> reportedly is planning to acknowledge Gov. <PERSON>George 
Deukmejian</PERSON>'s relief efforts on behalf of victims of the Armenian earthquake in 
<DATE>1988</DATE>. <PERSON>Deukmejian</PERSON>, who is of Armenian descent, has said he does not know if he 
will have a chance to speak privately with the Soviet leader. 
</P>
<P>
If given the opportunity, the governor added, he will tell <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> that 
Armenians in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> "hope <PERSON>Mr. Gorbachev</PERSON> and his government would 
take steps to ensure greater protection for Armenian people living there, and 
greater assistance to help them to rebuild from the devastating earthquake." 
</P>
<P>
After the Fairmont speech, <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> will return to the Soviet consul general's 
home, meet with his wife, and head to the Golden Gate Bridge. 
</P>
<P>
Officer <PERSON>Bill Wylie</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>CHP</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>, said the Gorbachevs 
tentatively plan to cross the bridge and get out of their cars at the vista 
point on the <ORGANIZATION>Marin</ORGANIZATION> side. After gazing upon the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> skyline for about 
15 minutes, they will return to their cars for the drive to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and 
the airport. 
</P>
<P>
"We're very happy that he's coming to view our area and our bridge," <PERSON>Wylie</PERSON> 
said. 
</P>
<P>
But feelings of peace and goodwill aside, the sightseeing excursion is likely 
to take its toll on the <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> commute across the Golden Gate. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wylie</PERSON> said at the minimum, the <ORGANIZATION>CHP</ORGANIZATION> will slow traffic, and "they could shut down 
the bridge for a minute," while <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> and his entourage cross the span. At 
rush hour, 6,000 cars an hour head north from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Marin</LOCATION> across the 
bridge. 
</P>
<P>
"We don't think the motorcade itself will impact traffic as much as people 
wanting to get a view of the President of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Wylie</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Golden Gate Bridge officials say the 25-minute operation -- 15 minutes at the 
vista point and 10 minutes for the round-trip drive -- will not result in 
gridlock. 
</P>
<P>
"People in this area stay clear when they know there's going to be a major 
event. They go home early or they stay late," said <PERSON>Carney Campion</PERSON>, manager of 
the bridge. 
</P>
<P>
Times staff writer <PERSON>Doug Smith</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Glendale</LOCATION> contributed to this story. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
GORBACHEV, MIKHAIL S; GORBACHEV, RAISA; OFFICIAL VISITS; SCHEDULES; SAN 
FRANCISCO (CA) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891120-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-20-89 1925EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SF-Quake-Traffic     11-20 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF-Quake-Traffic,0667</SECOND>
<HEAD>Light Traffic To Welcome Back The Bay Bridge</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto FX5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JAMES O. CLIFFORD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Traffic flowed smoothly on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the
first workday since the quake-battered Bay Bridge reopened, but
officials said Thanksgiving week could be the cause and suggested
the real crunch could come next week.
   The doctor who cared for Buck Helm, the longshoreman who
survived 3{ days in his car in a collapsed section of Interstate
880, said his death <DATE>Saturday</DATE> was partly due to a heart condition
they had been unaware of.
   However, <PERSON>Dr. Tom McDonald</PERSON>, chief of surgery at <ORGANIZATION>Kaiser Permanente
Medical Center</ORGANIZATION>, told a news conference in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> that Helm
suffered ``overwhelming'' injuries in the freeway collapse that
claimed 41 other lives.
   In all, the <DATE>Oct. 17</DATE> quake killed 67 people, injured more than
2,800, left more than 14,000 homeless and inflicted an estimated <MONEY>$7
billion</MONEY> damage.
   The quake sent a 50-foot section of the <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland
Bay Bridge</LOCATION>'s upper deck crashing onto the lower deck, cutting the
main link between <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. The 8.5-mile-long span
formally reopened <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Traffic <DATE>Monday</DATE> on the bridge was running <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> less than
<DATE>Oct. 17</DATE>, said Lt. <PERSON>Jim Simmons</PERSON> of the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Transportation</ORGANIZATION>, who is toll supervisor at the bridge. Before the
quake, an average of 260,000 cars used the bridge each day.
   ``Obviously, people are still taking mass transit and coming in
earlier,'' said <PERSON>Greg Bayol</PERSON>, a spokesman for the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Transportation</ORGANIZATION>. ``The test will come later, this being a holiday
week.''
   Traffic also was down on the Golden Gate Bridge, which handles
traffic southbound into the city. It is used along with the
<ORGANIZATION>Richmond-San Rafael Bridge</ORGANIZATION> by commuters from bedroom communities to
the east.
   From <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME> to <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME>, 14,086 cars used the span, down from
17,634 for the same period a week ago, said Capt. <PERSON>Jackson Fong</PERSON> of
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate Bridge District</ORGANIZATION>. The Golden Gate handles about
146,000 cars daily.
   The Bay Area Rapid Transit system, which set records almost
every day while the Bay Bridge was closed, carried about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
fewer passengers during the morning commute than a week ago. By
<TIME>8:30 a.m.</TIME>, the system had transported 65,239 passengers, compared
to 78,003 the previous <DATE>Monday</DATE>, said <ORGANIZATION>BART</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Sy Mouber</PERSON>.
   However, <PERSON>Mouber</PERSON> pointed out that BART carried just 47,415
passengers on <DATE>Oct. 5</DATE>, making <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s load <PERCENT>118 percent</PERCENT> of that
before the quake.
   Asked if these figures meant people have permanently changed the
way they commute, <PERSON>Mouber</PERSON> said, ``I don't think we are seeing the
results yet. I think people are taking an early Thanksgiving
holiday.''
   ``Next week may look a little different,'' said <PERSON>Mike Mills</PERSON>, a
spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Alameda Contra Costa Counties Transit System</ORGANIZATION>,
which runs public buses.
   The number of passengers taking <ORGANIZATION>AC Transit</ORGANIZATION> buses across the
bridge on routes beginning in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and Alameda appeared to be
down, <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> said.
   The number of people riding a ferry from <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> was also down, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Red &amp; White Fleet</ORGANIZATION>.
Between <TIME>6 a.m. and 9 a.m.</TIME>, there were 1,165 passengers, a drop of
472 from last <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>Alameda County Coroner's Office</ORGANIZATION>, Helm died of
blunt trauma to his head and body, respiratory failure due to
extensive chest injuries, kidney failure and abdominal infection.
   Before the quake, Helm, 58, had high blood pressure and diabetes.
   Doctors learned after Helm's death that he had an enlarged
ventricle, the chamber of the heart that pumps blood into the
arteries, <ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION> told reporters. McDonald said it had not been
possible for doctors to know about the heart problem.
   The surgeon said he had been looking forward to taking Helm off
the respirator that kept the longshoreman breathing, and was as
shocked by anyone by his death. ``We had all been so encouraged,''
<ORGANIZATION>McDonald</ORGANIZATION> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870429-0121 </DOCNO>
<HL> Golden Gate Bridge
Has Troubled Waters
For Its Birthday Bash
---
Squabbling of Rival Groups
Frightens Away Sponsors;
A Job for a Protocol Chief
---
By Carrie Dolan
<DD> 04/29/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> SAN FRANCISCO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Citizen watchdog groups have been formed. 
One man calls it the biggest scandal here in 20 years. 
His opponent deems him "nasty and defaming." 
The mayor has stepped in. 
Sabotage and conspiracy charges are fired. 

   This is serious. 
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> is trying to throw a party. 

   The Golden Gate Bridge, one of the world's loveliest ways to cross water, turns 50 next month, and tourist-conscious <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> plans a birthday bash <DATE>May 24</DATE>. 
But as the big day approaches, sponsors are scarce, organizers are about <MONEY>$800,000</MONEY> in debt, and plans have shown all the smooth coordination of Donnybrook Fair. 

   Even for a city that loves a good time, the initial plans for a <MONEY>$22 million</MONEY> extravaganza struck some as a bit overblown. (The 100th-anniversary celebration for the <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> Bridge in <DATE>May 1983</DATE> cost about <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>). 
Some party-poopers even suggested the money might be better spent on the needy. 
San <ORGANIZATION>Francisco Examiner</ORGANIZATION> columnist <PERSON>Bill Mandel</PERSON> wrote, "In money matters, the {bridge} district exhibits the self-control of a 22-year-old rock star with a bad coke habit." 

   Two rival groups vied to be the main merrymakers and planned competing concerts, fireworks and parades. 
Each camp charges the other has torpedoed its fund raising and events. 
The chaos has caused corporate sponsors to back off. 

   Such disarray is surprising in a haven of seasoned socializers. 
In <DATE>May</DATE> alone, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> will have a citywide ball for 12,000 people and the annual Bay to Breakers footrace, the world's largest and wildest, with 100,000 joggers dressed as bowling pins or bananas or pulling kegs of beer. 

   Most <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> bridges are state-run, but the Golden Gate is run by the Golden Gate Bridge, Highway and <ORGANIZATION>Transportation District</ORGANIZATION>, a group of political appointees, and financed by tolls. 
Several members of the group are members of the party committee, known as the Friends of the Golden Gate Bridge. 

   Early on, the bridge bash hit troubled waters. 
The chief fund-raising firm was let go because its task became impossible, an organizer says. 
The events director stepped down. 
A man hired to provide entertainment died shortly afterward. 
At an unveiling of party plans, a map of the Bay area was upside down and an out-of-state organizer told the <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> audience, "You <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> people are going to love this!" 

   <PERSON>James Bronkema</PERSON>, the chairman of the Friends, admits, "I could write a book on the mistakes." 
But he blames the local press, too, for making fun of the party. 
He notes that over half the original <MONEY>$22 million</MONEY> budget was for the long-term goal of a museum. 
And he says of rebel reveler <PERSON>Scott Redmond</PERSON>, whose <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> firm produces special events, "Our competitor has been undermining our sponsorship very badly." 

   <PERSON>Mr. Bronkema</PERSON> says <PERSON>Mr. Redmond</PERSON> had a "religious fervor" to have the party. 
"He can have anything he wants, except the bridge. 
After all, that's ours." 

   The bridge directors declined the help of <PERSON>Mr. Redmond</PERSON>, who has staged an outdoor party for 250,000 people, tied the world's largest bow around a hotel, and landed a flying saucer in a corporate board room. 
<PERSON>Mr. Redmond</PERSON> accuses the Friends of sabotage conducted in "the most nasty, heinous way possible" and of seeking political gain. 

   A group called <ORGANIZATION>Citizens for Bridge District Reform</ORGANIZATION> has sent out letters charging that some of the festive doings are part of "<PERSON>David Rockefeller</PERSON>'s overall plan to, figuratively, buy the bridge" and win political favors in order to build a <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 

   The reference is to <PERSON>James Bronkema</PERSON>'s role as president of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s big Embarcadero Center office and shopping complex. 
Embarcadero Center, owned by <PERSON>David Rockefeller</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Prudential Insurance</ORGANIZATION>, donated <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> to the celebration. 
<PERSON>Mr. Bronkema</PERSON> calls the charges ludicrous and says the donation was "part of our civic duty." 

   Rock promotor <PERSON>Bill Graham</PERSON> volunteered to stage a free show featuring <PERSON>Huey Lewis</PERSON> and the News and the Grateful Dead, two bands with local roots. 
He wanted the bridge closed during the Sunday-afternoon concert to "let her breathe." 
The folks in wealthy <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>, on the other end of the bridge, protested, so <PERSON>Mr. Graham</PERSON> has canceled. 
But he is frustrated. 
"I feel like I'm tied up with rope, having to watch <PERSON>Ava Gardner</PERSON> parade back and forth in front of me." 

   <PERSON>Joyce Pavlovsky</PERSON>, a member of a citizens' group called Bridgewatch, says <PERSON>Marinites</PERSON> fear medical emergencies if the bridge is closed, not to mention the inconvenience. 
"It's going to be such a mess," she says. 
"This is not an occasion for fun." 

   <PERSON>Herb Caen</PERSON>, the columnist for the <LOCATION>San Francisco Chronicle</LOCATION>, riled some by asking why "the spoiled brats in Marin" couldn't stand being out of their BMWs for a few hours. 
<PERSON>Mr. Caen</PERSON>, one of 200,000 who walked across the bridge the day it opened, also wrote that rock music has little to do with the bridge. 
<PERSON>Mr. Graham</PERSON> responded to <PERSON>Mr. Caen</PERSON>'s opinion by calling him "an amoeba filled with pus." 

   With plans going badly awry, organizers belatedly brought in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION> "Tex" <ORGANIZATION>Mailliard</ORGANIZATION>, a wealthy widow renowned as a party thrower and the city's acting chief of protocol. 
<PERSON>Mrs. Mailliard</PERSON>, who served Cheerios to 10,000 people at a farewell breakfast for the queen of <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, threw a citywide celebration for the cable cars, shot off fireworks inside city hall and enlisted the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>'s aid in baking the world's largest birthday cake to mark <ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>'s birthday, is known to stay and sweep up after her affairs. 

   "I never would have forgiven myself if there wasn't a celebration for the bridge," <PERSON>Mrs. Mailliard</PERSON> says. 
The bridge can be viewed from many places in her home, including the shower. 

   <PERSON>Mrs. Mailliard</PERSON> enlisted the aid of Mayor <PERSON>Dianne Feinstein</PERSON>. 
The city donated <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>, and the mayor has been successfully urging corporations to make "modest" contributions. 
Although the party has been "one controversy after another," Mayor <PERSON>Feinstein</PERSON> concedes, "controversy is an everyday part of life here." 

   Plans of the <ORGANIZATION>Friends</ORGANIZATION> committee now include a dawn walk across the bridge, <PERSON>Tony Bennett</PERSON> singing again about his misplaced heart, fireworks, new lighting for the bridge and a performance by a marching band from <LOCATION>Pottstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, the city that made the steel for the bridge. 
The current budget is about <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>, including in-kind contributions. 
The group <PERSON>Mr. Redmond</PERSON> works with plans art shows, whaleboat races and a stamp-cancellation festival. 

   The celebration will clearly out-glitz last <DATE>November</DATE>'s festivities for the 50th anniversary of the Bay Bridge, connecting <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>. 
The Bay Bridge, always in the shadow of its sister span, celebrated with a string of lights, a 250-foot candle and a donated fireworks show, all costing about <MONEY>$225,000</MONEY>. 
"We wanted a low-cost, dignified celebration," a spokesman says. 
Bay Bridge officials had asked Golden Gate directors if they could celebrate together, the spokesman says, but the Golden Gaters replied, "We're professionals -- have your own party." 

   The Bay Bridge is overshadowed in other ways by the <LOCATION>Golden Gate</LOCATION>. 
A few years ago a study showed that distraught people drive across the Bay Bridge in order to jump off the Golden Gate, one of the world's leading suicide sites. 

   About 20 miles from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the people in <LOCATION>Crockett</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, population 3,000, will be throwing a shindig for the highly untouted <LOCATION>Carquinez</LOCATION> bridge, which turns 60 the week before the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate</ORGANIZATION>'s 50th. 

   The <PERSON>Crockett</PERSON> blowout will feature the release of a couple of thousand pigeons, and its own bridge lighting and rock concert. 
<PERSON>Gene Pedrotti</PERSON>, a local hardware-store owner, arranged for the donation of 500 flashlights and for residents to stand under their bridge and click them on at the same time. 
"We're not a controversial party," he allows. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101889-0071 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 122143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 18, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 7; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
831 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BAY AREA QUAKE; 
</P>
<P>
THE BAY BRIDGE: THE BACKBONE OF S.F. IS BROKEN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KEVIN RODERICK, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
More so than the celebrated Golden Gate, the Bay Bridge is the workaday 
backbone of the huge Bay-Area metropolis. Close to half a million people cross 
it every day, and more than a few probably think about earthquakes as they do 
it. 
</P>
<P>
For several hundred, the seldom-spoken fear struck close during <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> evening 
rush hour when a piece of the upper deck -- five lanes of roadway carrying 
commuters into <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> -- swayed and collapsed in front of motorists 
bound the other way on the lower deck. 
</P>
<P>
No cars pitched over into the dark waters of <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>, but at least 
one motorist was killed in a car trapped by the falling debris. Fate seemed to 
spare many others, since the usual <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> rush-hour traffic was remarkably thin 
for a <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION> is the "other" bridge soaring out of <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION>, but it is actually visible to more of the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> than the <ORGANIZATION>Golden 
Gate</ORGANIZATION>. In recent years, the Bay Bridge spans have been brightly lit at night, 
although <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> the bridge was eerily dark except for the flashing orange 
lights of emergency trucks inching across the two decks. 
</P>
<P>
Motorists who were on the bridge when the quake hit reported confusion in the 
aftermath. Debbie and <PERSON>Thomas Kelly</PERSON> were on the upper deck, trying to return to 
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, when they shot videotape of a car falling through the crevice in 
the roadway. They said the car had been directed back toward safety, but had 
inadvertently turned the wrong way and pitched into the hole. The <PERSON>Kellys</PERSON> said 
as many as 100 cars had driven toward the collapsed section of the road rather 
than back to safety in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It was sort of mass confusion," <PERSON>Thomas Kelly</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
There also were unconfirmed reports from witnesses on the bridge that some 
terrified motorists jumped into the water, but the <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> could find no 
evidence. 
</P>
<P>
Other Bay Area bridges weathered the quake better. The Golden Gate remained 
open, and the <LOCATION>San Mateo Bridge</LOCATION> -- which was closed as a precaution -- is 
expected to reopen today. However, transportation officials advised residents 
to stay home if at all possible today to avoid gridlock on the roads. 
</P>
<P>
But it is the Bay Bridge that will signal the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>'s return to normalcy. 
<ORGANIZATION>Caltrans</ORGANIZATION> announced late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> that the Bay Bridge will be closed at 
least two days, maybe longer if inspectors find major structural problems. If 
no serious fissures are found, the lower deck of the bridge will be opened with 
three lanes going in either direction, allowing at least limited traffic to 
cross. 
</P>
<P>
However, the roadbed leading onto the bridge from the <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> side was buckled 
and torn up, with parts of it under water, witnesses said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. One 
crack in the pavement near the <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> toll booth was about 100 yards long and 
a foot wide. 
</P>
<P>
State emergency officials in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> said they will install temporary <PERSON>Bailey</PERSON> 
bridges to span the collapsed section of the upper deck, and will try to 
operate ferries between the west and east sides of the bay. 
</P>
<P>
The gray Bay Bridge is squatter and less grand than the brightly painted Golden 
Gate. But the <ORGANIZATION>Bay Bridge</ORGANIZATION> is longer by at least double, and is a fitting symbol 
for the World Series between the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>'s baseball teams. 
</P>
<P>
The Bay Bridge carries twice as much traffic as the <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate</ORGANIZATION>, and its 
opening presaged tremendous growth in the <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION>. Oakland is the best-known 
community on the east side of the bay, but the bridge is the conduit that 
allows commuters to live in distant suburbs of <LOCATION>Contra Costa County</LOCATION> and drive to 
jobs in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Some engineers also believe that it is the more notable marvel. The <ORGANIZATION>American 
Society of Civil Engineers</ORGANIZATION> named it one of the nation's seven landmark 
structures, an honor never bestowed on the <LOCATION>Golden Gate</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Bay Bridge and Golden Gate, longtime dreams of the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>'s more 
grandiose thinkers, were both built during the Great Depression, beginning in 
<DATE>1933</DATE>. The Bay Bridge was finished first, opening in a grand celebration <DATE>Nov</DATE>. 
12, <DATE>1936</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
From <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, the bridge is cantilevered over the bay as far as <LOCATION>Yerba Buena 
Island</LOCATION>, where the world's largest bore tunnel was driven through hills. Then 
two suspension spans are attached to moorings in the <LOCATION>Embarcadero</LOCATION> area of 
downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Rocks and dirt from the tunneling were dumped in the bay to create <LOCATION>Treasure 
Island</LOCATION>, site of a 1939-40 World's Fair and now a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> base. 
</P>
<P>
A national survey in <DATE>1986</DATE>, when the Bay Bridge quietly celebrated its 50th 
anniversary, found that less than <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of people asked to name a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 
landmark listed the Bay Bridge, while nearly half mentioned the Golden Gate. 
</P>
<P>
The Bay Bridge's obscurity outside the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> extends to suicide attempts as 
well. More than 800 people have died after jumping from the Golden Gate, 
slightly more than 100 from the Bay Bridge, though the roadways are both 250 
feet above the water. Some who jumped from the Bay Bridge even left notes 
indicating that they believed it was the Golden Gate. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A section of roadway on the San Francisco Bay Bridge collapsed during 
the quake. This photo was taken from a television screen. Associated Press; 
Drawing, San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge, Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO OAKLAND BAY BRIDGE; BRIDGE COLLAPSES; SAN FRANCISCO -- 
TRANSPORTATION; EARTHQUAKES -- SAN FRANCISCO; BRIDGES; GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06258114 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06258114 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BRIDGE; DESIGN; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Mac Silvert, a San Francisco engineer who helped build the Golden Gate Bridge
and later worked on the Panama Canal, has died at age 81.;   Mr. Silvert's
expertise was in constructing cofferdams, structures that keep water out of an
area to allow construction of bridge foundations or dams.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MAC SILVERT, ENGINEER, HELPED BUILD BRIDGES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     He was hired on the Golden Gate Bridge project in <DATE>1936</DATE> and was in charge of
decking for both that project and the Bay Bridge. He later worked on the locks
for the <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> Canal.;   <PERSON>Mr. Silvert</PERSON> died <DATE>Monday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>St. Francis Hospital</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910914  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  92  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, September 14, 1991
00258114,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA020490-0010 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 171152 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 4, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 30; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
124 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CALIFORNIA IN BRIEF; 
</P>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO; 
</P>
<P>
GOLDEN GATE MAY GET WIND STRESS TEST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times staff and Wire reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Golden Gate Bridge may soon undergo modern wind stress tests, partially to 
determine how the 52-year-old span would withstand blustery weather if a second 
deck is added for a rail transit system. A recommendation by chief bridge 
engineer <PERSON>Dan Mohn</PERSON> to study how much wind it would take to damage the suspension 
bridge, which in <DATE>1982</DATE> withstood 70-m.p.h. winds, was endorsed unanimously 
<DATE>Friday</DATE> by a committee of bridge directors. 
</P>
<P>
Under the proposal, wind tests costing <MONEY>$39,863</MONEY> would be conducted in 
conjunction with a <MONEY>$423,640</MONEY> three-dimensional computer study of how a possible 
rail transit system on a lower deck would affect the bridge. The latter study 
is due to be released <DATE>March 25</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>T.Y. Lin International of San Francisco</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE; BRIDGES; WIND; TRANSIT SYSTEMS -- SAN FRANCISCO; RAILROADS 
-- SAN FRANCISCO; TESTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06018262 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06018262 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  PROTEST; FINE; SAN-FRANCISCO; BRIDGE; CONTROVERSY; WAR; IRAQ; MIDEAST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Golden Gate Bridge officials said Thursday they are considering fines of up to
$10,000 for people arrested while blocking the span.;    The move comes in
response to a protest Tuesday against war in the Middle East in which hundreds
of demonstrators paralyzed commuter traffic.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PROPOSED FINE FOR GOLDEN GATE PROTEST: $10,000  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "We are trying to devise some penalty other than a slap on the wrist for
disruption," said <ORGANIZATION>Golden Gate Bridge District</ORGANIZATION> board member <PERSON>Gary Giacomini.</PERSON>;   
"The bridge is a vital artery for many people no matter how noble the cause of
the demonstration.";    Currently, a maximum fine of <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> can be imposed on
bridge trespassers.;    Changes in the law under which penalties are levied
require authorization by the state Legislature.;    The full board will see
the proposed changes <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  San Francisco  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Street  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910118  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  11A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  124  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday January 18, 1991
00018262,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891024-0112 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891024 </DD>
<AN> 891024-0112. </AN>
<HL> Economy:
@  San Francisco's Commuters Triumph
@  In Getting Back to Work After Quake
@  ----
@  A Wall Street Journal News Roundup </HL>
<DD> 10/24/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> PCG PAC </CO>
<IN> TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<DATELINE> SAN FRANCISCO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>


</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ891023-0110 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 891023 </DD>
<AN> 891023-0110. </AN>
<HL> San Francisco Area Commuters Brace
@  For Traffic Gridlock on Major Arteries
@  ----
@  By Marilyn Chase and Carrie Dolan
<DD> 10/23/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<IN> TRANSPORTATION, TRUCK AND SHIP LINES, RAILROADS (TRA) </IN>
<GV> EXECUTIVE (EXE) </GV>
<DATELINE> SAN FRANCISCO  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891020-0231 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-89 2222EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SFQuake-Commuters 2ndLd-Writethru a0817 10-20 0649</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-Commuters, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0817,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts graf on Greyhound suspending service to Santa Cruz,
other communities, after 12th pvs bgng ``The recommended.''</HEAD>
<HEAD>Quake-Hit SF Bay Area Commuters Hunt New Ways To Work</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JACK SCHREIBMAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Like storm-tossed captains plotting a
course around rocks and shoals, a million <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> area
workers _ their normal commute routes ruined by an earthquake _ are
devising new strategies for getting to and from work.
   ``I really don't see how there cannot be gridlock on <DATE>Monday</DATE>,''
said a harried <PERSON>Tom Silvey</PERSON>, a state <ORGANIZATION>Franchise Tax Board</ORGANIZATION> worker now
assigned to the <ORGANIZATION>state Office of Emergency Services</ORGANIZATION>.
   <DATE>Monday</DATE> is considered the region's transportation equivalent of
D-day along 70 miles from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. It includes
a plan for using <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> landing craft to ferry commuters between
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, where four freeways and high-speed
connectors are closed.
   For much of the work force, commute times are expected to
stretch into an extra hour or more each way.
   The Bay Area Rapid Transit, the railroad that travels under <LOCATION>San
Francisco Bay</LOCATION> to connect the city with <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> communities, is
running extra cars and expanding to 24-hour operation. Daily BART
business is expected to double to at least 300,000 person-trips.
   Morning comute tolls have been eliminated on all transbay
bridges except the Golden Gate, where commuters will be excused
from tolls on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>mornings</TIME> only.
   By far the most serious disruption is to the traffic _ 243,000
vehicles each working day _ normally carried by the key
eight-mile-long <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION>. It a major <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> lifeline for food, industrial and other goods, vehicular
traffic from the east, and some half-million people a day.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s quake dumped a 50-foot section of the bridge's top
deck onto the bottom deck of the 52-year-old span, and engineers
estimated repairs might take as long as two months.
   A driver who normally takes the Bay Bridge from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> must now either go 20 miles south and then cross the bay on
the <LOCATION>San Mateo Bridge</LOCATION>, or take the Golden Gate Bridge and drive 18
miles north in <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION> to cross the bay on the <ORGANIZATION>Richmond-San
Rafael Bridge</ORGANIZATION>. The southern route costs an extra 60 miles, the
northern detour an additional 40 miles.
   In <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, the upper deck of a 1\-mile portion of Interstate
880 collapsed onto the lower deck in a deadly vise of concrete and
steel. The roadway, a conduit to and from the <LOCATION>Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East
Oakland</LOCATION>, bay-side cities and points south, will be out of
commission for at least two years.
   In <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, 70 miles south of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the 20,000
people who cross the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION> daily on State Highway 17
to work in <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> must seek alternate routes because
landslides have closed that route.
   The recommended alternates from <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>: South on
101 to Highway 152 west, then north to Highway 1 _ 40 miles extra;
or, west from <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> on Highway 9 _ 20 miles extra.
   <ORGANIZATION>Greyhound Lines Inc.</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Friday</DATE> it had suspended bus
service to <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Watsonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Gatos</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Saratoga</LOCATION> because of the closure of Highway 17.
   In <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, central-city motorists used to zipping down
the hills to the <PERSON>Gough</PERSON> and Oak street connectors to Highway 101
found the on-ramps closed because of structural damage to roadway
underpinnings. They must now travel city streets for a mile or so
to find southbound on-ramps.
   In addition, the city's <ORGANIZATION>Embarcadero Freeway</ORGANIZATION>, which runs on the
edge of the bay, is closed because of structural failure. And the
I-280 extension from downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to 101 near <LOCATION>Candlestick
Park</LOCATION> sustained structural failure and will be closed for several
months.
   Those are the only two other double-deck freeways in <LOCATION>Northern
California</LOCATION> besides I-880.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890213-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-13-89 0516EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CaliforniaQuakes 1stLd-Writethru a0454 02-13 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-California Quakes, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0454,0315</SECOND>
<HEAD>Minor Earthquakes Shake Northern California</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with USGS reducing Richter reading
to 3.0 sted 3.6; picks up 4th graf pvs, ``We had ...''</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BERKELEY, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mild earthquake early today shook a
wide area of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the sixth tremor in <LOCATION>Northern California</LOCATION>
within 24 hours, officials said.
   No damage or injuries were immediately reported from the quakes,
whose magnitudes ranged from 2.4 to 3.0 on the Richter scale.
   The sixth quake struck at <TIME>12:01 a.m.</TIME> and had a magnitude of 3.0
   It was centered west of the Golden Gate Bridge, the same area as
two earlier ones, said seisomologist <PERSON>Anthony Lomax</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University
of California Seismology Station</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We had several calls from all over the city but so far no
reports of damage,'' said a <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> police dispatcher who
declined to give his name.
   The first quake, which measured 2.7 on the Richter scale, struck
at <TIME>11:49 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and was centered about five miles west of the
bridge.
   Within two minutes, two more quakes, measuring 2.6 and 2.4 on the
Richter scale, were felt in southern <LOCATION>Marin County</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Lomax</PERSON> said.
   At <TIME>10 p.m.</TIME>, a magnitude 3.0 quake struck the same general area
off the Golden Gate as the first one, <PERSON>Lomax</PERSON> said.
   A quake that measured 2.9 was centered near <LOCATION>San Leandro</LOCATION>, about 10
miles south of <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, at <TIME>10:41 p.m.</TIME>, he said.
   The Richter scale is a measure of ground motion as recorded on
seismographs. Every increase of one number means a tenfold increase
in magnitude.
   A quake of magnitude 3.5 can cause slight damage.
   The <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> earthquake of <DATE>1906</DATE> measured an estimated 8.3 on
the Richter scale.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891019-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-19-89 0525EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Quake-Freebies     10-19 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Quake-Freebies,0520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Companies Offer To Help Quake Victims</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-SF Quake, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ANTHONY MARQUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the midst of disaster, some companies
have stepped forward to offer free services to those in need, from
legal advice to fresh pasta.
   Lawyer <PERSON>Melvin Belli</PERSON> and his staff set up tables <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME> in front of his downtown offices, offering free legal
counsel to the public, said <PERSON>Marian Ashley</PERSON>, an employee at <ORGANIZATION>Belli</ORGANIZATION>'s
<LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> office.
   <PERSON>Ashley</PERSON> said <PERSON>Belli</PERSON> and his attorneys were not working out of
their office because the building was apparently unsafe.
   <ORGANIZATION>Bechtel Group Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, one of the world's biggest engineering
companies, loaned the city of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> the services of its
civil and structural engineers, said spokesman <PERSON>Larry Miller</PERSON>.
   ``This is our hometown and we'd like to help in whatever way we
can, and we thought this was the best way,'' said <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>. He said
similar assistance was also offered to <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION> and the state.
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Bechtel</ORGANIZATION> started trying to contact its estimated 200
engineers in the <LOCATION>Bay</LOCATION> area beginning <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. As of <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>,
25 to 30 were helping the city inspect buildings.
   He said more engineers would be offered to the municipalities as
they report in to <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> headquarters. The <ORGANIZATION>Bechtel</ORGANIZATION> office
was otherwise closed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``We have got a total of 1,500 projects going on in the world
... so the expertise here is pretty deep,'' said <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>. ``It's a
valuable commodity to have, and we are just happy to loan it to the
city.''
   Cellular One of <LOCATION>Burlingame</LOCATION> offered to lend free cellular phones
to any emergency service agencies that need them, according to
spokeswoman <PERSON>Carolyn Casey</PERSON>.
   The company, which also has an office in <LOCATION>Oakland</LOCATION>, has asked
individual customers to refrain from using the network to give
better access to relief workers.
   She said the company has more than 400 channels, with a capacity
to handle about 200,000 cellular phones.
   ``We've had over 500 phones go out our door, to emergency
agencies all over the <LOCATION>Bay</LOCATION> area,'' said <PERSON>Casey</PERSON>. ``We're doing
everything we can. We have people manning our system 24 hours a
day.''
   The Golden Gate Bridge on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> did not charge a toll for
commuters from <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME> to noon, in an effort ``to help alleviate the
flow of traffic, the traffic crunch that never happened,'' said
<PERSON>Bruce Selby</PERSON>, spokesman for the Golden Gate Bridge and <ORGANIZATION>Highway
Transportation District</ORGANIZATION>.
   The district anticipates much more traffic today because of the
closed Bay Bridge.
   People left hungry got some help from the Aunti Pasta retail
store chain. Every person who entered one of the eight Aunti Pasta
stores in the <LOCATION>East Bay</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> was offered one-third
pound of fresh pasta.
   ``We really want to help people out,'' said <PERSON>Julie Kramer</PERSON>,
manager of one store where at least 30 people in two hours had come
in to get pasta.
   ``I think we all want to help out in whatever way we can,'' said
<PERSON>Kramer</PERSON>. ``It's our little effort.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06079187 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06079187 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  STANFORD; STUDENT; SUICIDE; BRIDGE; SAN-FRANCISCO; MARIN; COUNTY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Stanford University announced Monday that a 24-year-old man who died after
apparently jumping off the Golden Gate Bridge on Thursday was one of its
students.;    Richard Woodland Tanner, a senior majoring in international
relations, was scheduled to graduate in June, according to a university
official.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GOLDEN GATE BRIDGE JUMPER IDENTIFIED AS STANFORD
STUDENT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     A spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>California Highway Patrol</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Tanner</PERSON>'s parked car
was found <DATE>Thursday</DATE> on the Golden Gate Bridge. The <ORGANIZATION>CHP</ORGANIZATION> said an eyewitness saw
him get out of the car, go the guardrail and jump at about <TIME>10:30 p.m.</TIME>;    <ORGANIZATION>The
Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> conducted a search that night but did not find the body, Chief
Warrant Officer <PERSON>Lance Jones</PERSON> said. No further searches are planned.;    <PERSON>Tanner</PERSON>
lived in <LOCATION>Escondido Village</LOCATION> with his wife, <PERSON>Chantal</PERSON>, according to a spokeswoman
for the university. He was an active member of the <ORGANIZATION>Church of Jesus Christ of
Latter-day Saints</ORGANIZATION> and had served a two-year mission for the church.;    He is
also survived by his parents, <PERSON>Dr. William</PERSON> and <PERSON>Elizabeth Tanner</PERSON>, and three
older brothers, <PERSON>W. Brent</PERSON>, Troy, and <PERSON>Steven</PERSON>, all of <LOCATION>Los Angeles.</LOCATION>;    Memorial
services are to be held on campus during the first week in <DATE>April</DATE>, said <PERSON>Jean
Kim</PERSON>, assistant dean of residential affairs.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910319  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  200  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday March 19, 1991
00079187,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891019-0240 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-19-89 2305EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SFQuake-Landmarks 1stLd-Writethru a0792 10-19 0556</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-SF Quake-Landmarks, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0792,0566</SECOND>
<HEAD>Landmarks in Good Shape, Tourists Not Welcome Yet</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING to CORRECT category code; LEADS with 3 grafs
to fix typo in `San Francisco,' some cable car service back; picks up 3rd
pvs: `Automobiles were...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC PREWITT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cable cars returned to the streets of <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, after being stuck in their barn since an
earthquake knocked out electrical power two days earlier.
   By midday, enough traffic signals were working again so that
partial service on the popular tourist attraction could resume.
   Most of the city's landmarks, including the Golden Gate Bridge,
Coit Tower, Mission <PERSON>Dolores</PERSON> and the colorful Victorian-style homes,
were virtually unaffected by the powerful quake and remained
unruffled and picturesque as ever.
   Automobiles were snaking down the ``Crookedest Street in the
World'' of postcard fame, the block of Lombard on Russian Hill.
   ``The traffic hasn't stopped at all, except <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> when
they closed the street off because a cable car was stuck at the top
of the hill,'' said <PERSON>Jason Doty</PERSON>, who lives on the steep, winding
street. ``Our electricity is still out, but there are no other
problems here.''
   Not all the frequently photographed landmarks got through the
earthquake untouched, of course.
   The <LOCATION>San Francisco-Oakland Bay Bridge</LOCATION>, big sister of the more
colorful Golden Gate, was crippled. Some <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> worth of glass was
broken at the <ORGANIZATION>Conservatory of Flowers</ORGANIZATION>, a huge greenhouse in <LOCATION>Golden
Gate Park</LOCATION>. At the bayside end of Market Street, the flag atop the
Ferry Building was tilted and the tower clock was still stuck on
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s late-afternoon earthquake time, <TIME>5:04 p.m.</TIME>
   The Mansion Hotel, a Victorian building in the <LOCATION>Pacific Heights</LOCATION>
district, rode smoothly through its second major quake.
   ``It stood proud, and it's obviously a survivor. It looks
fragile but it isn't,'' owner <PERSON>Bob Pritikin</PERSON> said of the building
completed in <DATE>1887</DATE>. ``The only damage we found was a crack in a
bathroom ceiling.''
   Alcatraz, called ``The Rock'' by those who did chilly hard time
there when it was a federal prison, certainly lived up to its
nickname. Tourists _ though very few of them _ in the Fisherman's
Wharf area <DATE>Thursday</DATE> were pointing their cameras at the bleak island
in the bay.
   ``We like <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Alex Camenisch</PERSON> of Marthalen,
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, said as he and his family strolled through Fisherman's
<LOCATION>Wharf</LOCATION>, where there was no power and almost all businesses were
closed.
   They were not planning on staying overnight, however. ``We were
going to stay at a downtown hotel, but now we're going to stay
somewhere else,'' said <PERSON>Camenisch</PERSON>'s wife, <PERSON>Esther</PERSON>.
   On <LOCATION>Nob Hill</LOCATION>, about half the <ORGANIZATION>Fairmont Hotel</ORGANIZATION>'s 500 rooms were
empty as well as dark <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. A national business group
that had reserved 450 rooms canceled a scheduled meeting.
   ``I was on the phone starting <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> to groups with
reservations here the next 30 days. News reports have made things
sound pretty dismal, and I wanted to let them know the city was not
burning down,'' said <PERSON>Stan Boyd</PERSON>, director of sales for the Fairmont.
   At the <ORGANIZATION>Moscone Center</ORGANIZATION>, the city's largest convention center, one
event ended its run <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. The next, a car dealers' gathering set
for <DATE>Oct. 26</DATE>, is still scheduled, as well as a convention of 5,000
plastic surgeons beginning <DATE>Oct. 27</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901024-0181 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-24-90 2129EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Humphrey 1stLd-Writethru a0758 10-24 0387</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Humphrey, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0758,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Meandering Whale Swims Under Golden Gate and Out to Sea</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with Humphrey swimming under the
Golden Gate and out to sea. Pick up 6th graf pvs, `Humphrey, a...'
Denize cq in 8th graf; Gibeson cq in 14th graf.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto LA1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC PREWITT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Humphrey the wayward whale swam under the
Golden Gate Bridge <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and headed toward the open sea, ending
a four-day visit that saw one wrong turn after another.
   The 45-ton humpback whale passed under the span about <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>,
escorted by a flotilla of small boats, <ORGANIZATION>Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> vessels and
private cruisers.
   People on the bridge cheered as <PERSON>Humphrey</PERSON> swam by.
   He headed back to the ocean where he belongs a day after he was
freed from a stranding on mud flats along the shore of <LOCATION>San
Francisco Bay</LOCATION>.
   For a time, the mammoth mammal seemed to be re-enacting his <DATE>1985</DATE>
tour of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> bay. Then, the wayward whale was tracked by
legions of well-wishers as he meandered, far from the open ocean
where he belongs, for 25 days.
   Anxious rescuers tracked the whale through the day as he seemed
to be headed anywhere but out to sea. First he was seen south of
the bridge, then away to the north.
   Rescuers mobilized to intercept the 45-ton whale and try to
induce him to head out to sea, she said. After the 40-foot <PERSON>Humphrey</PERSON>
was freed from the mud flat <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> evening he seemed to have
gotten his bearings, raising hopes he would join the rest of his
kind, which feed in the bay sometimes, but seldom stay for long.
   ``He was swimming well and going toward the Golden Gate,''
<PERSON>Denize Springer</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>California Marine Mammal Center</ORGANIZATION> said early
in the day. ``Well, he wasn't really going in just one direction.
Whales tend to meander.''
   Humphrey, for some reason attracted to <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION>, has a
history of meandering.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, when the news media gave him his name, he went through
the bay and up the <LOCATION>Sacramento River</LOCATION>, with much of the nation
tracking his wanderings.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Humphrey</PERSON> veered off course again, turning left into
<LOCATION>San Francisco Bay</LOCATION> as his fellow migrating whales continued south
along the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>.
