<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06098170 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06098170 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Associated Press; Janet Evans, who holds three world
records, is one reason the U.S. may be on course to regain a spot atop the
swimming world; PHOTO: Associated Press; RISING STAR -- Anita Nall, 14, has
the second-fastest time in the world in the women's 200-meter breaststroke.
She didn't swim in the world championships in January.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SWIMMING; CHAMPIONSHIP; RESULTS; ANALYSIS  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  It was the Montreal Olympics of 1976, in which the East German women's team
won 10 of 13 possible gold medals, that knocked the United States off its
throne as the world's supreme swimming power.;    But the '92 Olympics in
Barcelona, Spain, may see the United States restored to its former place atop
the swim hierarchy.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  U.S. 'IN PRETTY GOOD POSITION' FOR BARCELONA
SWIMMERS ON WAY BACK  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Olympics/Swimming
See also related story on P. 3D of this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> women won their first world championship since <DATE>1978 last January</DATE>,
and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> men made the meet in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> their sixth straight title.;    "I
think you can read quite a bit into that," said Stanford swimming coach
<PERSON>Richard Quick</PERSON>, who coached the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic team three years ago in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>South Korea.</LOCATION>;    Quick said the world championships were "the major focus of
the year for our premier athletes, and they were against the best athletes in
the world. I think that we're in pretty good position" for Barcelona.;    On
the brink of greatness?;  Part of the story in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> were world records
set by <PERSON>Mike Barrowman</PERSON> (200-meter breaststroke) and <PERSON>Melvin Stewart</PERSON> (200
butterfly). Part was the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> women's performance in recovering from a
disqualification in the 800 freestyle relay, in which they finished first, to
still top the medal and points standings.;    And part was the decline of a
reunited <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, which suffered rather than gained from the change.;   
Although there are doubters -- notably '84 Olympic gold medalist <PERSON>Rowdy Gaines</PERSON>,
now a television commentator -- that the world championships and this week's
strong performances at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Swimming Spring Nationals</ORGANIZATION> are indicative of
Olympic success, many coaches such as Quick see the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> at the brink
of greatness.;    'You just don't know'; "A 16-, 17-year-old girl who set the
world on fire in <DATE>January</DATE> of '91 could be over the hill by the time <DATE>March</DATE> (date
of the Olympic trials) rolls around in <DATE>'92</DATE>," <PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> said. "You just don't
know. Look at <ORGANIZATION>Anita Nall</ORGANIZATION>. Who the heck is she? She came out of nowhere.";   
Actually <PERSON>Nall</PERSON>, 14, came out of <LOCATION>Towson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, and <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Spring
Nationals</ORGANIZATION>, she twice lowered the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> record in 200 breaststroke to the
second-fastest time in the world. The last <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> woman to hold the 200
breaststroke world record was <PERSON>Catherine Ball</PERSON> in <DATE>1968.</DATE>;    <PERSON>Nall</PERSON> wasn't even on
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team at the world championships. That team was led by <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON>,
who won two gold medals and one silver.;    <LOCATION>The U.S.</LOCATION> man-from-nowhere this
week is <PERSON>Joe Hudepohl</PERSON>, 17, of <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, whose 100 freestyle was the
eighth-fastest in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history, though only good enough for third place. He
wasn't at the world championships, either.;    <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> men hold world records in
six of 11 individual Olympic events: <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON> (50 freestyle), <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON>
(100 freestyle), <PERSON>Dave Berkoff</PERSON> (100 backstroke), <PERSON>Barrowman</PERSON> (200 breaststroke),
<PERSON>Pablo Morales</PERSON> (100 butterfly) and <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> (200 butterfly). Only <PERSON>Morales</PERSON> is not
longer competing.;    After <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who holds three world records (400, 800 and
1,500 freestyle), the only ones by an active <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> woman, the top <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> women at
the world championships were <PERSON>Nicole Haislett</PERSON>, who won the 100 freestyle in
national-record time, and <PERSON>Summer Sanders</PERSON>, winner of the 200 butterfly.;    The
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> women topped the medals table 12-9 over <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, the gold medal count 6-4
over <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, and team scoring 395-374 over Germany.;    "I think a lot of
(<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s decline) is the fact they were such rivals before (reunification),"
<PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> said. "It's going to take them a long time to jell as a team.;    "Then
you've got to remember <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> doesn't have the drugs behind them that
they used to, which was quite obvious at the worlds.";    A German magazine
recently documented <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s extensive illegal drug program.;    <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Swimming, the sport's national governing body, has reoriented its entire
training program toward producing gold medals at <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>, including changing
the <ORGANIZATION>Spring Nationals</ORGANIZATION> from the usual 25-yard short course to an international
50-meter course.;    That has upset some coaches and meet directors who
believe it will hurt national age-group development programs and take
big-name, ticket-selling swimmers away from <DATE>summer</DATE> meets.;    "I disagree,"
Quick said. "I think the focus of <ORGANIZATION>United States Swimming</ORGANIZATION> needs to be the
Olympic Games for elite-level athletes. Success at the Olympic Games will do
more for age-group swimming than anything I can think of."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JODY MEACHAM, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Federal Way, Wash.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910407  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  793  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 7, 1991
00098170,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080389-0079 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 90183 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 3, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 1; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
831 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WHARTON BREAKS U.S. RECORD IN 400 MEDLEY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TRACY DODDS, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>David Wharton</PERSON>, competing in his home pool, set the first record of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. 
Swimming Long Course National Championships</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
Wharton lowered his American record in the men's 400-meter individual medley to 
4 minutes 15.93 seconds in the <ORGANIZATION>University of Southern California</ORGANIZATION> pool. 
</P>
<P>
The Trojan star is competing at this meet in the name of <PERSON>Team Foxcatcher</PERSON>, his 
club team back home in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. But he will be back at <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> as a junior in 
the <DATE>fall</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Eric Namesnik</PERSON> pushed <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> to the record, staying with <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> through the 
fastest butterfly leg <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> has ever recorded. Namesnik took the lead on the 
backstroke leg, stayed close through the breaststroke and pushed <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> to his 
fastest freestyle leg ever. 
</P>
<P>
And that's pretty fast, considering <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> once held the world record in the 
400 individual medley. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> said that his first priority was to win the event and secure a berth on 
the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific</ORGANIZATION> team that will be competing in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> next month. "I was kind of 
nervous because I hadn't made the team yet," <PERSON>Wharton</PERSON> said. "Getting the record 
was an added bonus I'll certainly take. 
</P>
<P>
"I felt smooth tonight . . . Coming home I felt really strong." 
</P>
<P>
Wharton won the silver medal in this event in the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic Games, finishing 
behind <PERSON>Tamas Darnyi</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Darnyi</PERSON> set the world record of 4:14.75. 
</P>
<P>
Asked if he will be taking special notice of <PERSON>Darnyi</PERSON>'s time in the upcoming 
European Championships in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wharton</LOCATION> smiled. "Of course," he said. "What 
he's done isn't out of my ballpark yet. . . . My objective will be to go faster 
in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Wharton holds the American records in both the 200-yard and the 400-yard 
individual medleys and has been voted <ORGANIZATION>National Collegiate Athletic Assn</ORGANIZATION>. 
swimmer of the year the <DATE>last two years</DATE>. He said that with the experience he has 
had in international swimming in the last few years, he is starting to feel 
more confident in that arena, too. 
</P>
<P>
He will be swimming the 200-meter individual medley here <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. "I'll be 
a lot more relaxed and confident for the 200, now that I've made the team," he 
said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Fullerton Aquatic Sports Team</ORGANIZATION> won her second national title 
of the meet, in the 400-meter freestyle. But her 4:06.73 was no threat to the 
world record -- 4:03.85 -- that she set in winning the gold medal in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Heike Friedrich</PERSON> of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> chased her in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. And no one chased her 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. She is going to have to get used to that. 
</P>
<P>
Olympians <PERSON>Betsy Mitchell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dan Veatch</PERSON> both came out of retirement to win 
backstroke titles <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> won the women's 100-meter backstroke in 1:02.37, and <ORGANIZATION>Veatch</ORGANIZATION> won the 
men's 200-meter backstroke in 2:02.09. 
</P>
<P>
after only a few weeks of training, beat the 1:02.53 she swam here in '84 to 
win the Olympic silver medal. 
</P>
<P>
Mitchell at one time held world records in both the 100- and 200-meter 
backstrokes and still holds the record in the 200. She was about as burned out 
as a swimmer can get when she scratched from the 200 during the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic 
trials last <DATE>summer</DATE> in her own <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION> pool and then, after 
finishing fourth in the 100 in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, scratched from the medley relay. 
</P>
<P>
"I had a feeling that would come up," <PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> said. "I thought that would 
probably look pretty bad. I wasn't making a statement or anything with that 
scratch. I just felt like I wasn't going to go faster than <PERSON>Beth</PERSON> (<PERSON>Barr</PERSON>) was 
going to go. She was going faster at the time. 
</P>
<P>
"I was at the end of a really long rope . . . 
</P>
<P>
"It wasn't really horrible being at the Olympics, but things were really 
different for me once I was a world record-holder. To tell you the truth, it 
was probably me assuming that people were putting the pressure on me. . . . 
Tonight I had fun swimming for the first time in a long time." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON>, 23, had been coaching at her alma mater, the <ORGANIZATION>Mercersburg Academy</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, when she decided in early <DATE>July</DATE> that she wanted to swim again. She 
drove to <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> in her jeep to work out with her former college coach, 
<ORGANIZATION>Richard Quick</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Brent Lang of Club Wolverine</ORGANIZATION>, a member of the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic team as a relay 
swimmer, won the 100-meter freestyle in 50.17. <PERSON>Nichole Haislett</PERSON> won the women's 
100-meter freestyle in 56.15. 
</P>
<P>
Swimming Notes 
</P>
<P>
The last time <PERSON>Carrie Steinseifer</PERSON> competed in a championship final in the <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> 
pool, she finished in a tie with <PERSON>Nancy Hogshead</PERSON> to win the <DATE>1984</DATE> Olympic gold 
medal in the 100-meter freestyle. Steinseifer finished in a tie for sixth place 
with <PERSON>Janel Jorgensen</PERSON> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. . . . <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON> tuned up for his 50-meter swim 
against <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> by swimming the 100-meter freestyle <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. He 
finished third in 50.4, earning a spot on the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific</ORGANIZATION> team. The top four 
finishers in the 100-meter freestyle make it in order to fill the 400-meter 
freestyle relay. . . . Longhorn Aquatics led the team competition after the 
third day, leading also in both the men's competition and the women's 
competition. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
WHARTON, DAVID; SPORTS RECORDS; SWIMMING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ920309-0071
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
920309-0071.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- On Sports:
   Big Splash at Ooey-Pooey
   ----
   By Frederick C. Klein
</HL>
<DATE>
03/09/92
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A10
</SO>
<LP>
   Indianapolis -- Perhaps the best measure of the strength
of the U.S. Olympic swimming team that was selected by trial
of water here last week was a quip that Eddie Reese, who will
coach the men's team at Barcelona next July, made Friday
morning, after his roster was all but filled. Reese knew he
would have in his charge no fewer than six reigning world
record holders, yet he was able to say, almost
straight-facedly, that he'd "offered Mark Schubert (the
women's team coach) money if he'd switch jobs with me."
   Added Reese, eyes atwinkle: "Most of the talk here has
been about the women, and how tough they look. And, hey, I
agree. I'd have to think hard before I'd put my boys against
them head-to-head."
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Most of the talk was about the women because a couple of
them did their world-record busting at the <ORGANIZATION>Phillips 66
National Swimming Championships</ORGANIZATION> on the campus of <ORGANIZATION>Indiana
natives of the Hoosier metropolis shorten to "Ooey-Pooey."
The meet doubled as the Olympic Trials, with the top two
finishers in each event qualifying.
   Last <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the event's first day, <PERSON>Jenny Thompson</PERSON>, 19, a
blue-eyed blonde from <ORGANIZATION>Stanford U.</ORGANIZATION> via <LOCATION>Dover</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>, churned
the 100-meter freestyle in the unprecedented :54.48. The next
day <PERSON>Anita Nall</PERSON>, a stuffed-owl-loving, 15-year-old wunderkind
from <LOCATION>Towson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, took the 200-meter breaststroke, in a
record 2:25.92. Before the waves died down on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
two more American women's records fell and two others were
nudged severely.
   But this is not to say Our Boys did poorly. Charmin'
<PERSON>Melvin Stewart</PERSON>, a voluble Tennessean, on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> swam
the 200-meter butterfly in 1:55.72, just .03-second above his
own world mark, and a couple hours later <PERSON>Jeff Rouse</PERSON>, a
bespectacled Stanfordian, missed his 100-meter backstroke
record by .14-second, at :54.07.
   And in the highlight of a memorable evening-indeed, maybe
of the whole meet-Matt <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>, the giant (6-foot-7) hero of
the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympics in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> (he won seven medals, five of them
gold), edged world-record-holder <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON> by .05-second in
the 50-meter freestyle final, with his time of :22.12 pacing
the fastest eight-man field in the history of the event.
   "Our goal in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>?" Reese would echo. "To win all the
medals, of course. Although we probably won't do it."
   Chances look good, though, that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> swimmers will do
better at <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> than they did at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, where their
18-medal haul was this country's lowest in 28 years. The rosy
outlook stems partly from the demise of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, which
dominated the women's side of the sport in the <DATE>1976</DATE>, '80 and
'88 Games.
   When the <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> Wall came down, so did the wall of silence
that surrounded steroid use by East German athletes, and the
fact that <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nall</PERSON> broke records formerly held by
East Germans was cause for some breast-beating here. "It's
good to see that drug-enhanced records have been broken by
our girls, swimming clean," said <PERSON>Dennis Pursley</PERSON>, national
team director for <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Swimming</ORGANIZATION>, the sport's domestic
governing body. When pressed, <PERSON>Pursley</PERSON> admitted that drugs
still may be present in the sport. "Techniques to cheat
remain ahead of techniques to test," he allowed. But he
added, "I know our people, and know they'd never use them."
   While <PERSON>Pursley</PERSON> didn't mention it, one American woman,
sprinter <PERSON>Angel Myers</PERSON>, tested positive for steroids after
qualifying for the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic team, and was barred from the
Games. <PERSON>Myers</PERSON> has maintained she never used the drugs. Now 24
years old, married and last-named <PERSON>Martino</PERSON>, she's back in the
sport after serving a suspension. She qualified in the
50-meter free-style and 400-meter free-style relay, but said
that restoring her reputation was not her motive. "I don't
think about that (the <DATE>1988</DATE> incident)," she said quietly.
"Maybe I block it out."
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> swimmers hope they'll have a couple of other things
going for them. One will be the extra training that team
members can glean from having the Trials in early <DATE>March</DATE>,
nearly five months before the Games. The '88 Trials were just
six weeks before the <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> fest, and it turned out that some
swimmers couldn't hold their competitive peaks that long. But
it should be recalled that the '88 format seemed like a good
idea at the time.
   Probably more important will be the results of the
increased financial help available to top <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic
hopefuls over the last quadrennium; whatever other adjectives
might apply to swimmers, "poor" no longer is one of them.
Last year, <DATE>1988</DATE> triple-gold-medal winner <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON>,
breaststroke world-record holder <PERSON>Mike Barrowman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>
each collected more than <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> in aid, and 17 other
swimmers got <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> or more. The upshot is a <DATE>1992</DATE> men's team
that averages 23 years old, and a women's crew that averages
20, both about two years above <DATE>'88</DATE>.
   "I'm here because I love the sport . . . and can afford to
keep pursuing it," affirmed <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>, 26, who qualified for the
50and 100-meter freestyles and the 400-meter freestyle relay.
   The 20-year-old <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> will be back, too, having won the
400- and 800-meter freestyles that she captured at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, but
having failed to qualify in the 400-meter individual medley,
which she also won in <DATE>'88</DATE>. Along with <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nall</PERSON>, much
of the women's spotlight fell on <PERSON>Summer Sanders</PERSON>, a
19-year-old Californian. She qualified impressively in four
individual events and earned other accolades as well.
   "This is not only our best women's team ever, but also the
best looking," declared <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON>. "I'd be willing to grovel
for a date with Summer."
   "Melvin?" responded the dark-haired <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> when informed
of the above. "He hardly talks to any of the girls."
   Swimmingwise, experience was a stronger theme among the
men. Qualifiers included 27-year-old <PERSON>Pablo Morales</PERSON>, whose
<DATE>1984</DATE> world record in the 100-meter butterfly still stands but
who failed to qualify for the '88 team, and <PERSON>David Berkoff</PERSON>,
25, a silver medalist in the 100-meter backstroke at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>
who disgustedly quit the sport for a time after the
underwater technique he'd pioneered was banned.
   But they also include <PERSON>Joe Hudepohl</PERSON>, an 18-year-old
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> high schooler, who won the 200-meter free-style
and later showed there was something else to be said for
youth. Did the "pressure" make the Trials a trial, he was
asked. "Not really," he responded. "Our high school meets are
like this."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072190-0100 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 250424 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 21, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
806 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
GOODWILL GAMES; 
</P>
<P>
BARROWMAN RECORD BRINGS WORLD-CLASS STATURE TO OPENING DAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RANDY HARVEY, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
FEDERAL WAY, Wash. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Hoping for at least one world record <DATE>Friday</DATE> to give Goodwill Games II 
credibility as a world-class athletic competition on its opening day, 
organizers were rewarded for their blood, sweat and deficit-spending with 
three. 
</P>
<P>
Because all three records came in the same race at the <ORGANIZATION>King County Aquatics 
Center</ORGANIZATION>, the impact was somewhat limited. But it was one great race. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mike Barrowman</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> senior from <LOCATION>Potomac</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, won the 
200-meter breaststroke in 2:11.53, bettering the previous record he set last 
<DATE>August</DATE> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> by a staggering 1.36 seconds. No other swimmer had improved the 
record in the event by more than that since <DATE>1976</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Although they did not challenge <PERSON>Barrowman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kirk Stackle</PERSON>, a recent <ORGANIZATION>University of 
Texas</ORGANIZATION> graduate from <LOCATION>Penasquitos</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Sergio Lopez</PERSON>, a Spaniard who 
competes for <ORGANIZATION>American University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, also broke the old record of 
2:12.89. They tied for second place in 2:12.24. 
</P>
<P>
Barrowman, 21, said that he was surprised by his time but not by the fact that 
the race produced a world record. He trains with <PERSON>Lopez</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> under 
Hungarian Coach <PERSON>Jozsef Nagy</PERSON> and knew from recent workouts that they both were 
ready for a fast swim. Lopez's time earned a European record, a first for a 
Spanish swimmer. 
</P>
<P>
"My friend and I have trained a lot harder than we did <DATE>last summer</DATE>," <PERSON>Barrowman</PERSON> 
said. "This is the first time I ever came into a competition not being nervous, 
completely relaxed. Something inside said I knew I was going to swim well and 
don't worry about it. That's very unusual for me. 
</P>
<P>
"But I am very surprised by the time. If somebody had asked me before the race, 
I would have said that we might swim 2:12.88. I would have been happy with 
anything under 2:12. But 2:11.53 is not something I thought was a reality. It 
was more like a dream." 
</P>
<P>
If there was a record to be set on the opening day of the 17-day, 21-sport 
Goodwill Games, organizers anticipated it most likely would come in swimming's 
first event, the 50-meter freestyle. 
</P>
<P>
Considering that the race's co-favorites, <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON>, have 
broken the record in the event eight times since <DATE>1985</DATE>, no one who values his 
money would have bet against it. 
</P>
<P>
In 19 meetings at either 50 meters or 50 yards since <DATE>1984</DATE>, <PERSON>Jager</PERSON>, formerly of 
<ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and now of <LOCATION>Tijeras</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, had won 13 before <DATE>Friday</DATE>. But <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>, who 
graduated from <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> and now lives in <LOCATION>Castro Valley</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, won the big one at 
the <DATE>1988</DATE> Summer Olympics in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. He also won six other medals, five golds. 
</P>
<P>
Many in the sellout crowd of 2,472 were still filing into the new arena between 
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tacoma</LOCATION> when <PERSON>Jager</PERSON> and <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> were scheduled to swim. 
</P>
<P>
Fortunately for some of the late arrivals, there were two false-starts by 
anxious rivals. 
</P>
<P>
"That was their only chance," <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> said, dismissing <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Nils 
Rudolph</PERSON>'s beating both him and Jager this month in <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Before that, <PERSON>Jager</PERSON> had won the last four meetings with <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> and led in this 
one for about 25 meters. But <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> overtook him and then held off a late surge 
about 10 meters from the finish to win in 22.10 seconds. Jager was second in 
22.31, well off his world record of 21.81. Rudolph was fourth in 22.61. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>, who has complained because swimmers are not being paid for competing 
here while athletes in some other sports are receiving thousands of dollars, 
valued the victory as an advertisement for the "Dash for Cash" match races that 
he and Jager are staging. 
</P>
<P>
"It's important for me and for the sport of swimming that I'm seen as a viable 
contender in the 50," he said. "Tom's been beating me up pretty bad. It's good 
for me and for the sport to know that I can beat him." 
</P>
<P>
Interrupted Jager, "It was all planned." 
</P>
<P>
In the other featured event, the women's 800-meter freestyle, <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON>' only 
problem came about 10 meters into the race, when she lost her goggles. She won 
in 8:28.47, and second place <PERSON>Anke Moehring</PERSON> of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> swam 8:33.44. 
</P>
<P>
A closer race was expected. Evans, the gold medalist in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, was joined by 
silver medalist <PERSON>Astrid Strauss</PERSON> of <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> and bronze medalist <PERSON>Julie 
McDonald</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. McDonald was fourth and <PERSON>Strauss</PERSON> fifth. 
</P>
<P>
"I thought the field might have been faster," said <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> sophomore 
from <LOCATION>Placentia</LOCATION>. "I kind of hoped it would be more exciting." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> were stars of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> swimming team in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Barrowman</PERSON> 
was one of its few disappointments. After setting an American record in the 200 
breaststroke at the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> trials in <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex.</LOCATION>, he was favored to win at the 
Olympics. But he finished fourth. 
</P>
<P>
He said the pain has been eased by the three world records he has set since 
then in the event. But he has not forgotten it. 
</P>
<P>
"I hope it continues to haunt me," he said. "If it stops, that means it's time 
to stop swimming. Setting records helps, but I hope it still burns down there." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mike Barrowman celebrates a world-record 2:11.53 in the 200-meter 
breaststroke event Friday in which three swimmers broke the mark. Reuters 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061889-0193 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 71931 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 18, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 11; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
421 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SWIM MEET OF CHAMPIONS; 
</P>
<P>
JAGER BATTLES AGE-OLD ISSUE, AND WINS 50 FREESTYLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AL PRESTON, Special to The Times 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON>, a silver medalist in the <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> Olympics, said he wants to prove that 
older swimmers can compete in a sport dominated by youngsters. 
</P>
<P>
Jager, 24, who works as an aquatics director in <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, showed 
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> that he is fast enough to win major competitions with a victory in the 
50-meter freestyle during the third day of the <ORGANIZATION>International Swim Meet of 
Champions at Mission Viejo</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Jager, who was edged by <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON> for the gold medal in the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic 50, 
was clocked in 23.74 seconds. <PERSON>Brian Kurza</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> finished second in 24.15 and 
<PERSON>Brian Jacobson</PERSON>, 15, of the <ORGANIZATION>Bellflower Aquatic Club</ORGANIZATION> was third in 24.35. 
</P>
<P>
"I may have scrambled a bit much in my race, and that might have slowed me down 
a bit," said <PERSON>Jager</PERSON>, whose 23.60 was the top qualifying time in <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
<TIME>morning</TIME>'s preliminaries. Jager, who wants to break <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>'s world record of 
22.14 set during the <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> Games, said he decided to continue competing to 
serve as a role model for younger competitors as well as help find ways for 
athletes to stay in the sport after they complete their college careers. 
</P>
<P>
"A lot still needs to be done in the sport," <PERSON>Jager</PERSON> said. "United States 
Swimming (the sport's governing body in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>) needs to take better 
care of our athletes than they are doing now so we can continue to train and 
stay in the sport after they complete college." 
</P>
<P>
Still a teen-ager, <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Placentia</LOCATION> need only worry about winning, 
which she did twice <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Evans, the world-record holder in the 400-meter 
freestyle, won that event in 4:13.55. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Laurence Bensimon</PERSON> finished second in 4:19.65 and <PERSON>Francie O'Leary</PERSON> of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Click Tucson Swim Club</ORGANIZATION> was third in 4:19.65. 
</P>
<P>
Evans held off <ORGANIZATION>Mission Viejo High School</ORGANIZATION> senior <PERSON>Suzi Burt</PERSON> to win the 200 
backstroke in 2:18.53. Burt, who stayed with <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> during the first half of the 
race, ns was second in 2:22.27, and <ORGANIZATION>Natalie Norberg of Industry Hills</ORGANIZATION> was third 
in 2:23.51. 
</P>
<P>
"I felt pretty good," said <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who won the 400-meter individual medley but 
finished fourth in the 200 butterfly <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
In the men's 400-meter freestyle, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>'s Artur Wojdat scored his third 
victory of the meet by edging <DATE>1988</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Olympian Dan Jorgensen</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Wojdat, who battled with <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON> for the lead for most of the race, had a 
strong last 100 meters to win. Wojdat was timed in 3:55.09, <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON> 3:56.63. 
</P>
<P>
Wojdat's fellow <ORGANIZATION>Pole and Mission Viejo Nadadore</ORGANIZATION> swim club teammate <ORGANIZATION>Mariusz 
Podkoscielny</ORGANIZATION> was third in 3:57.77, and <PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON>'s younger brother, <PERSON>Lars</PERSON>, was 
fourth in 4:00.80. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061589-0152 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 70562 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 15, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 17; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
933 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SWIMMING / TRACY DODDS; 
</P>
<P>
A BUSY EVANS TO COMPETE IN MEET BEGINNING TODAY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Tracy Dodds 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON>, who took very little time off after the Olympics in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> <DATE>last 
September</DATE> before getting back into her incredible training regimen, somehow 
managed to train, handle a crush of requests for appearances, parades and award 
dinners and still compete for <LOCATION>Placentia</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>El Dorado High School</ORGANIZATION> and her 
<ORGANIZATION>Fullerton Aquatics Sports Team</ORGANIZATION>, knocking off distance swim records all along 
the way. 
</P>
<P>
She's tough over the long haul. 
</P>
<P>
Today, just one day after her high school graduation ceremonies, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> is 
opening her long-course season in the Swim Meet of Champions at <LOCATION>Mission Viejo</LOCATION>. 
Evans will swim the 800 at <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> and will compete every day in the meet that 
continues through <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Evans also plans to swim the 200-meter freestyle, 200-meter backstroke, 
200-meter breaststroke, 200-meter butterfly, 200-meter individual medley, 
400-meter individual medley and the 400-meter freestyle. 
</P>
<P>
Finals start at <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday, Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Evans, who will be attending Stanford in the <DATE>fall</DATE> and swimming there under the 
direction of <PERSON>Richard Quick</PERSON>, former Olympic coach and former women's coach at 
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Texas</ORGANIZATION>, has been working with <PERSON>Don Wagner</PERSON>, the new coach of her 
<ORGANIZATION>Fullerton Aquatics</ORGANIZATION> team. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wagner</PERSON>, a former assistant at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION>, replaced <PERSON>Bud 
McAllister</PERSON>, who coached <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> to three Olympic gold medals before moving on to 
a club in <LOCATION>Orlando</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <DATE>January</DATE>, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> broke the 1,650-yard freestyle record that had been set by 
<ORGANIZATION>Olympian Tiffany Cohen</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE>. She lowered it from 15 minutes 46.54 seconds to 
15:44.98. And in <DATE>March</DATE>, at the <LOCATION>Phillips</LOCATION> 66/U.S. <ORGANIZATION>Swimming Short Course Nationals</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Chapel Hill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, she broke <PERSON>Cohen</PERSON>'s American record in the 1,000-yard 
freestyle. She lowered that record from 9:28.32 to 9:25.49. 
</P>
<P>
It may take her a meet or two to get up to speed in this long-course season, 
but <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> is planning to compete in all the major meets. She is one of the 
stars that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Swimming is planning to use both in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, at the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific</ORGANIZATION> 
meet, and in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, against the Soviets, just days later. 
</P>
<P>
If anyone can do it . . . 
</P>
<P>
The annual meet at <LOCATION>Mission Viejo</LOCATION> has recently acquired <ORGANIZATION>Chrysler</ORGANIZATION> as a sponsor, 
which could mean that it will again be able to pay travel expenses for the top 
caliber swimmers who used to be attracted to the meet when it was sponsored by 
Seventeen magazine. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the swimmers on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> are competing either in the <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> 
meet <DATE>July 7-9</DATE> or in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Invitational <DATE>July 13-16</DATE>. East Coast 
swimmers will be competing in the <LOCATION>Charlotte Ultra</LOCATION> Swim Invitational <DATE>June 22-25</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Invitational</ORGANIZATION>, which will be held at <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, has drawn not only 
<PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, but also Olympian Sylvia Poll of <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>. USC Olympians <PERSON>Dave Wharton</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Dan Jorgensen</PERSON> are also scheduled to compete. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>L.A. Invitational</ORGANIZATION> will be televised by <ORGANIZATION>TBS</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
All of the early <DATE>summer</DATE> meets are tuneups for the Phillips 66/U.S. <ORGANIZATION>Swimming 
Long Course National Championships</ORGANIZATION>, which also will be held at <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>July 
31-Aug</DATE>. 4. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON> is not ready to say when he plans to race again, but there is 
little doubt that he will. Somehow, somewhere and no doubt for some profit, 
<PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> will sprint against his old nemesis, <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
If <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> chooses to skip the long-course national meet and, therefore, the <ORGANIZATION>Pan 
Pacific</ORGANIZATION> meet, it is likely that he will swim a match race with Jager -- a 
prospect that no doubt would attract network television. 
</P>
<P>
Biondi quit the national water polo team last week just before reporting to the 
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> for the filming of a <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> project in which, of course, he swims with the 
dolphins he has grown to love. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> has not raced since his final Olympic event last <DATE>September</DATE>. He swam the 
butterfly leg for the 400-meter medley relay that won gold, and then announced 
that he would be putting all of his athletic efforts into making the national 
water polo team. 
</P>
<P>
Working with the water polo team has kept him in shape, and he would certainly 
be of value to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team -- especially on the relays -- if he did decide to 
qualify for the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific</ORGANIZATION> meet. As <PERSON>Jeff Dimond</PERSON> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Swimming put it: "If 
<PERSON>Matt</PERSON> decides to swim again, we'll be turning cartwheels." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Pat Hines</PERSON> will defend her title as women's champion in the <LOCATION>United States Ten 
Mile Swim</LOCATION> in this year's ocean race along a course that runs between <LOCATION>Huntington 
Beach</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Seal Beach</ORGANIZATION>. Hines is using the race to gain attention for her quest 
to make an endurance swim an Olympic event. 
</P>
<P>
She would like to see a 10-mile swim become a demonstration event in <DATE>1992</DATE> and a 
medal event by <DATE>1996</DATE>. According to <LOCATION>Hines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Swimming and its masters program 
have submitted the event for Olympic consideration. 
</P>
<P>
"Endurance swimming deserves Olympic status," she says. "It is an international 
sport, it demands the highest levels of skill and training, and it is 
incredibly exciting." 
</P>
<P>
Swimming Notes 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> sent a team of swimmers to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for a meet at 
<LOCATION>Tallinn</LOCATION> <DATE>June 2-4</DATE> and the young women fared surprisingly well. They won nine 
gold medals, seven silver and one bronze in the 16 events, including an upset 
gold in the 400-meter medley relay. <PERSON>Pam Minthorn</PERSON>, 18, of <LOCATION>Gaithersburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, who 
swims for <ORGANIZATION>Curl-Burke Swim Club</ORGANIZATION>, won the 200-meter freestyle in 2:02.32, the 
100-meter butterfly in 1:01.5, and the 200-meter butterfly in 2:13.18. Summer 
<PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>, 16, of <LOCATION>Roseville</LOCATION>, who swims for the <ORGANIZATION>California Capital Aquatics</ORGANIZATION>, won 
both individual medleys. . . . <PERSON>Don Gambril</PERSON> has been named coach of the men's 
team and <PERSON>Dick Shoulberg</PERSON> has been named coach of the women's team for the <ORGANIZATION>Pan 
Pacific Games</ORGANIZATION>, the Alamo Cup and the World Cup meet to be held in <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>January</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA040289-0146 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 38901 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 2, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 12; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
659 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NCAA MEN'S SWIMMING CHAMPIONSHIPS; 
</P>
<P>
TEXAS OUTPOINTS STANFORD TO WIN TEAM TITLE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AP 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
INDIANAPOLIS 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Freshman <PERSON>Jeff Rouse</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> won the 200-yard backstroke as Olympic silver 
medalist <PERSON>David Berkoff</PERSON> of Harvard ended his competitive career by placing 
second <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in the men's <ORGANIZATION>National Collegiate Athletic Assn</ORGANIZATION>. Swimming and 
Diving Championships. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, helped by <PERSON>Shaun Jordan</PERSON>'s victory in the 100 freestyle, a first in the 
400-freestyle relay and a second by defending champion <PERSON>Kirk Stackle</PERSON> in the 200 
breaststroke, won the team title for the second consecutive year. The Longhorns 
finished with 475 points. Stanford, which had its string of three consecutive 
titles snapped <DATE>last year</DATE>, was second at 396. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> was third with 315, <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> fourth with 313.5 and <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> fifth with 304. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Eddie Reese</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> was selected coach of the year. 
</P>
<P>
USC's <PERSON>David Wharton</PERSON>, who swept the two medley events earlier in the meet, 
received the swimmer of the year award for the second consecutive year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Rouse</PERSON>, the runner-up to <PERSON>Berkoff</PERSON> when he set an American record in the 100 
backstroke <DATE>Friday</DATE>, won in 1:44.87 seconds. <PERSON>Berkoff</PERSON>, who set a world record in 
the preliminaries of the 100-meter backstroke at the <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> Olympics and won the 
silver medal, finished at 1:45.88. 
</P>
<P>
"The 200 isn't his race," <PERSON>Rouse</PERSON> said. "He's better in the 100, but it does make 
me feel good to beat a world record-holder. I believe I'm a little better at 
the 200 than <PERSON>David Berkoff</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I had a sense of where he was, but I never really looked at him." 
</P>
<P>
Rouse made an error on his final turn. "I jammed the wall," he said. "I was 
expected to take another stroke and all of a sudden, the wall was there. . . . 
I misjudged it. That's happened to me before, but it was a long time ago." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, a member of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic team <DATE>last year</DATE>, took the 100 freestyle in 
42.98. <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Erik Ran</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, who was disqualified in two races 
during the meet, was second in 43.08. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mike Barrowman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, who set an American record in the 200-meter 
breaststroke at the Olympic trials <DATE>last year</DATE> and took fourth at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, won the 
200 breaststroke in 1:55.72 with <PERSON>Stackle</PERSON>, who won the 100 breaststroke <DATE>Friday</DATE>, 
second at 1:57.01. 
</P>
<P>
Arizona freshman <ORGANIZATION>Mariusz Podkoscielny</ORGANIZATION>, a Polish Olympian last year, won the 
<ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> title and was on pace to set a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open and <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> mark in the 1,650 
freestyle until the final 50 yards. His winning time of 14:38.09 was 17 seconds 
faster than the runner-up in his heat and just missed the record of 14:37.87 
set by <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jeff Kostoff</PERSON> in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Witchel</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, who swam his heat earlier, placed second in 14:49.69. 
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Sean Killion</PERSON>, who also raced in an earlier heat, was third in 
14:52.31. 
</P>
<P>
Tennessee's <PERSON>Melvin Stewart</PERSON>, a freshman who was fifth in the 200-meter butterfly 
at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, won the 200 butterfly in a race in which the top three swimmers 
finished within 0.7 of a second of each other. Stewart finished in 1:44.30. 
<PERSON>Bart Pippenger</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nevada Las Vegas</LOCATION> was next in 1:44.60, and <LOCATION>Wharton</LOCATION> was third 
in 1:44.98. 
</P>
<P>
Southern Methodist's <PERSON>Scott Donnie</PERSON> won the 10-meter platform diving with 757.45 
points. <PERSON>Pat Evans</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, who won the three-meter event <DATE>Friday</DATE> and 
placed second on the one-meter <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, was second at 708.80 and was voted 
diver of the year. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hobie Billingsley</PERSON>, retiring after 31 years at <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, tied <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>'s 
<PERSON>Charlie Kasuto</PERSON> for diving coach of the year honors. 
</P>
<P>
There were several surprises in the preliminaries. USC's <PERSON>Dan Jorgensen</PERSON>, the 
defending champion in the 1,650 freestyle, had a time of 15:09.89 and placed 
14th. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Brent Lang</PERSON>, who won the 50 freestyle on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, was disqualified 
for a false start when he tried to defend the 100 free championship. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> diver <PERSON>Mark Lenzi</PERSON>, who won the one meter and finished second at three 
meters, withdrew after injuring his wrist on his third dive off the 10-meter 
platform in the preliminaries. Lenzi attempted one more dive before 
withdrawing. 
</P>
<P>
The injury was not expected to keep <PERSON>Lenzi</PERSON> out of the indoor national 
championships coming up later this month. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Mike Barrowman of Michigan won an NCAA title in the 200-yard breastroke 
in 1:55.72. United Press International 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SWIMMING; SPORTS RECORDS; UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06013103 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06013103 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SPORT; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The United States lived up to its pre-meet billing Saturday at the World
Swimming Championships in Perth, Australia, and Stanford's Janet Evans was one
of the big reasons why.;    Evans won her second gold medal with a meet record
of 8 minutes, 24.05 seconds in the 800-meter freestyle. Evans, who won the 400
freestyle Wednesday, broke the 13-year-old record of 8:24.94 by Australia's
Tracey Wickham.;    The next-to-last night of the meet was a highlight for the
U.S. team. U.S. swimmers won five of six gold medals, with Melvin Stewart in
the 200 butterfly, Tom Jager of the Santa Clara Swim Club in the 50 freestyle,
Evans in the 800 freestyle, Jeff Rouse in the 100 backstroke and the women's
400 medley relay team taking titles.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EVANS CAPTURES SECOND GOLD MEDAL
U.S. SWIMMERS DOMINATE CHAMPIONSHIPS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Sports Digest  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Stewart</PERSON> set a world record and ended an eight-year reign by <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s
<PERSON>Michael Gross</PERSON> as world champion of the 200 butterfly. Stewart overtook the
world and Olympic champion 25 meters from the end to win in 1:55.69, taking
.55 seconds off the record Gross set in <DATE>1986.</DATE>;    Jager retained his title
with a meet record of 22.16 seconds in the 50 freestyle. <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON>, who set
the meet mark of 22.56 in qualifying, was second in 22.26.;    <ORGANIZATION>Rouse</ORGANIZATION> held off
<PERSON>Mark Tewkesbury</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> by .06 seconds in a meet-record 55.23 to win the 100
backstroke.;    The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> overtook <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to win the women's 400
medley relay in 4:06.51.;    The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> also won the team gold medal in
synchronized swimming with 196.144 points. The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team was awarded perfect
scores by all eight judges for artistic impression.;    The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team included
<PERSON>Becky Dyroen</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Santa Clara Aquamaids</LOCATION>, duet gold-medalists
<PERSON>Sarah</PERSON> and <PERSON>Karen Josephson</PERSON>, solo silver-medalist <PERSON>Kristen Babb</PERSON>, <PERSON>Michelle
Svitenko</PERSON>, <PERSON>Nathalie Schneyder</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jill Savery</PERSON> and <PERSON>Heather Simmons</PERSON>. All but <PERSON>Dyroen</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> perform for the <ORGANIZATION>Walnut Creek Aquanuts.</ORGANIZATION>;    In the 200 individual
medley, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s Lin Li won her second gold medal, defeating runner-up <ORGANIZATION>Summer
Sanders of Stanford</ORGANIZATION> by .66 seconds.;  COLLEGE FOOTBALL: <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Jono Tunney</PERSON>
intercepted a pass to set up a <DATE>first-quarter</DATE> touchdown as the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> defeated
the East 20-14 in the <LOCATION>Japan Bowl</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, today. The victory margin
in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>'s 11th win in 16 <LOCATION>Japan Bowls</LOCATION> turned out to be field goals of 42
and 38 yards by <PERSON>Robbie Keen</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>. Tunney's interception set up a touchdown
run by <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Nick Bell</PERSON> for a 17-0 West lead. San <ORGANIZATION>Jose State</ORGANIZATION> quarterback <PERSON>Ralph
Martini</PERSON> also played in the game.; HORSE RACING: Variety Road rallied through
the stretch and won by one length in the <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>William P. Kyne Handicap</ORGANIZATION> at
<LOCATION>Bay Meadows</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910113  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  455  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, January 13, 1991
00013103,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890807-0100 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890807 </DD>
<AN> 890807-0100. </AN>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- On Sports:
@  Teen-Age Girls Star in Off-Year Contest
@  ----
@  By Frederick C. Klein </HL>
<DD> 08/07/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<DATELINE> Los Angeles  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It's quiz time again. 
How many of you can name three famous sporting Blanchards? 

   Of course, there's "Doc" -- real first name <PERSON>Felix</PERSON> -- who won the <DATE>1945</DATE> Heisman Trophy playing fullback for the <ORGANIZATION>U. of Army</ORGANIZATION> football team. 
And <PERSON>Johnny</PERSON>, who played catcher and outfield on a lot of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Yankees</ORGANIZATION>' championship baseball teams of the <DATE>1950s</DATE> and '60s. 
But how about the third? 

   As of last week, you'd have to include <PERSON>Mary Ellen Blanchard</PERSON>, <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>'s 16-year-old granddaughter. 
She showed up at the <LOCATION>Phillips</LOCATION> 66/U.S. 
Swimming Long Course Championships here and came away with a full medal packet: A gold for winning the women's 200-meter breaststroke, a silver for taking second in the 100, and a bronze for a third place in the 200-meter individual medley. 

   Freckled <PERSON>Mary Ellen</PERSON>, from <LOCATION>Norcross</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, emerged not only bemedaled but also bedecked with praise from none less than <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>'s three-golds aquatic queen of the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympics at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
Still giggly despite having achieved the advanced age of 17, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> won four races here, three of them by furlongs instead of body lengths, but edged <PERSON>Blanchard</PERSON> and second-place <PERSON>Summer Sanders</PERSON>, also 16, by only one second and change in the 200 IM. 

   "That was a race]" <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> enthused after the win. 
"It was neat having someone near me at the finish." 
She said she entered the 200, her shortest event ever in a national meet, because she knew that she'd get heat from <PERSON>Blanchard</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>. 
She added: "Usually, the kids who do well the year after an Olympics hang around for the next three years. 
That definitely should include <PERSON>Mary Ellen</PERSON> and <DATE>Summer</DATE>." 

   That this is, indeed, the first (and usually quietest) year of the four-year Olympic cycle that governs swimming and other sports that come to popular life only quadrennially was apparent from a glance at the meet's surrounding. 
Its site was the 50-meter outdoor pool on the campus of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Southern California</ORGANIZATION>, where up to 14,000 people crowded high-rise bleachers for the swimming segment of the <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> Olympics of <DATE>1984</DATE>. 
Now the bleachers are gone, and despite four California-perfect days, the pool's permanent seating of about 2,000 was mostly more than adequate to accommodate the usual complement of parents and teachers. 

   Sad to say, a goodly portion of the throng that showed up on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the final day, went home feeling cheated. 
The day's -- and perhaps meet's -- main event was to be a rematch in the men's 50- meter freestyle between <PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON>, the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic titlist and world's record holder, and <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON>, the runnerup at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION> and the ex-record holder. 
But one false start disqualified Jager and another removed <PERSON>Todd Pace</PERSON>, the fourth-fastest qualifier, cutting the field to six. 
And when the race finally did get off, the 6-foot-7 <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> started a whit slowly, maybe enough to have cost him another mark. 
His winner's time of 22.36 seconds was .22-second over his standard, and he later remarked that his first two starts were better. 

   It's worth noting that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> rule on false starts differs from the international one, which gives fields two misfires before heads are lopped. 
It's also worth noting that a rules issue detracted from another event, the backstroke. 
<PERSON>David Berkoff</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> student, revolutionized that stroke's 100-meter race, and set a world's record last year, by swimming the first 30 or so yards underwater. 
But after the Olympics, the sport's killjoy world governing body, <ORGANIZATION>FINA</ORGANIZATION>, decreed that, henceforth, backstrokers must surface by the 10-meter mark. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> retains the crowd-pleasing unlimited-underwater rule for domestic use, but used the <ORGANIZATION>FINA</ORGANIZATION> statute here because the Nationals were the qualifying race for a team that will compete in the international <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific</ORGANIZATION> meet in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> later in the month. 
Still, the no-false-starts rule wasn't altered. 

   "If we went with <ORGANIZATION>FINA</ORGANIZATION> on the backstroke, why not on the starts, too?" asked Jager afterwards. 
He'd remonstrated with officials after he got the hook -- while fans chanted "Let him swim]" -- but later cooled off and called his disqualification "part of the game." 
No one, however, could answer his question about the rules hodgepodge. 

   As is typical of most post-Olympic-year meets, the swim nationals were contested by a mix of vets and newcomers, and the vets generally posted the best times. 
The stopwatch highlight was a new world's record of 2:12.90 in the men's 200-meter breaststroke by <PERSON>Mike Barrowman</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> student who'd finished fourth in the event at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
He did it in the <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> prelims, and while his time in the afternoon finals was nearly two seconds higher (he said he got water in his goggles) it still earned him a first. 

   "My mother, father and girlfriend hated me this <DATE>summer</DATE> for spending so much time in the pool, but this makes it worthwhile," the slim <PERSON>Barrowman</PERSON> said of his mark. 

   Spending a lot of time in the pool is what swimming is all about. 
It seems like a drag, but some of the returning vets, including <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON>, a seven-medal winner at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, admitted that life without laps wasn't what he thought it might be, so he ended a post-O Game retirement to swim again here. 
<PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who has grown two inches (to 5-foot-6) since <DATE>last year</DATE> and soon will enter <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, said she still enjoys being wet even though she hasn't trained as intensively as she did in <DATE>1988</DATE>. 

   But rest assured that the killer instinct of <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who plans to stick around through <DATE>'92</DATE>, is intact. 
Asked what she thinks about when she turns for home pool-lengths ahead of rivals, she said, "How to get farther ahead." 

   <PERSON>Mary Ellen Blanchard</PERSON> was one of a batch of other teen-aged winners among the women, but if genetics count she well might turn out best. 
Besides grandpa <PERSON>Doc</PERSON>, father Tony and brother <PERSON>Rhett</PERSON> play or played football and mom <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON> and sister <PERSON>Lee Anne</PERSON> are tennis aces. 
"In my family, it's compete or die," she smiles. 
At 5-foot-9 and 127 pounds she has the size of a pool champ, and the proper interests. 
Her hobbies? 
"Music, reading, doing laps." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112990-0172 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 315082 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 29, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
SUMMER SANDERS 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1241 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THERE IS NO TIME LIKE THE PRESENT FOR STANFORD'S SANDERS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THERESA MUNOZ, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
STANFORD 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
While the anthropology professor explained that the expectation level is the 
primary difference between humans and monkeys, a few students skimmed The 
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford Daily</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Others thumbed through the syllabus, making notations for a research paper that 
had just been assigned. 
</P>
<P>
Suddenly, though, the professor made a declaration that caught the attention of 
<PERSON>Summer Sanders</PERSON>, the lanky blonde in the 15th row of the lecture hall. 
</P>
<P>
"Human beings live in a world that doesn't exist," he said. "A world of worries 
and dreams that have not occurred yet. Monkeys live only in the present, not in 
the past or the future." 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>, there is no better time than the present. If her freshman year at 
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> is anything like her freshman year -- which she calls the best year of 
her life -- at <ORGANIZATION>Oakmont High</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Roseville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, she has it made. 
</P>
<P>
Moreover, if she thinks ahead to this weekend's <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open or the World Swimming 
Championships in <DATE>January</DATE> or the <DATE>1992</DATE> Olympic Games, she'll go crazy. 
</P>
<P>
"You only have so much worrying in you," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. "I hate worrying and 
being nervous for races. I like to talk and laugh." 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> can excuse the swimming world for wanting to press fast 
forward. Expectations are high since her triple gold-medal performance in the 
Goodwill Games last <DATE>July</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' clocking of 2 minutes 9.46 seconds in the 200-meter butterfly was the 
second-fastest ever by an American and the fastest in the world in <DATE>1990</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Despite qualifying last in the 200 individual medley, she struck gold again in 
2:14.06, the fastest time by an American since <PERSON>Tracy Caulkins</PERSON>' effort in the 
<DATE>1984</DATE> Olympic Games. 
</P>
<P>
And in the meet's biggest upset, <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> handed <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> her first defeat 
since <DATE>1986</DATE>, knocking an astonishing 8.68 seconds off her 400 individual medley 
best. <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' clocking of 4:39.22 is the fastest in the world this year. 
</P>
<P>
Though <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> is 3.12 seconds shy of <PERSON>Petra Schneider</PERSON>'s <DATE>1982</DATE> world record, 
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford Coach Richard Quick</ORGANIZATION> believes <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> eventually will break it. 
</P>
<P>
"There's absolutely no question in my mind," said Quick, who also serves as 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> national team women's coach. "Summer <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> has the potential in the 400 
individual medley to go under the world record." 
</P>
<P>
Ironically, <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> despises that event, a sequence of 100 meters of butterfly, 
backstroke, breaststroke and freestyle that some coaches call the toughest race 
because of the stroke versatility and stamina it demands. "If I never swam 
another 400 IM in my life, I'd probably be the happiest person in the world," 
<PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. "It is the hardest thing ever." 
</P>
<P>
Like many medley swimmers, <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> was an age-group breast-stroker. A pulled 
muscle prevented her from training in the breast-stroke for a few months and 
sparked her interest in and mastery of the butterfly. 
</P>
<P>
"Her butterfly rivals the efficiency of <PERSON>Mary T. Meagher</PERSON>," Quick said of the 
world record-holder in the 100 and 200 butterfly. 
</P>
<P>
Until recently, <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' second leg was a weak link. But her club coach, <PERSON>Mike 
Hastings</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>California Capital Aquatics</ORGANIZATION>, developed her into a national-caliber 
backstroker. 
</P>
<P>
The third leg, breaststroke, has always been a strength. 
</P>
<P>
All that remains for <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> to improve is her freestyle, a segment that most 
medley swimmers don't struggle with because much of their training is in 
freestyle. Although <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' freestyle is above average, it doesn't compare to 
her other strokes. 
</P>
<P>
Her ability to stave off <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, the world record-holder in three distance 
freestyle events, was a breakthrough. "(Rivals) always pass me," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. 
"I've been passed many times." 
</P>
<P>
The most painful of those occurred at the <DATE>1988</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Olympic</ORGANIZATION> trials in <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. Sanders led by a body length with 50 meters left when <PERSON>Mary Wayte</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Whitney Hedgepeth</PERSON> passed her and became the two representatives the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> sent to <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Oakmont High</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' classmates staged a rally that cheered her up, 
despite her reluctance to be in the spotlight. 
</P>
<P>
"I didn't know about the rally," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said, "because if I'd known about it, 
I wouldn't have shown up. I was kind of embarrassed. I started crying up there 
in front of the whole school. I felt (foolish). But it was nice. . . . I was 
real honored." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> yearns to be accepted, she wants the option of being 
unconventional. That is what binds her family in their own definition of 
togetherness. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' parents divorced when she was 7. 
</P>
<P>
"I had no idea what it was," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. "All I remember is that my friend's 
parents had just gotten divorced. Her parents were buying her all these toys so 
when my parents told me they were getting divorced I said, 'Yes. Toys! Woo!' I 
had no idea what a divorce was." 
</P>
<P>
Sanders found out soon enough that it meant moving from one parent's home to 
the other every six months. 
</P>
<P>
"Every time I would move from one house to another, I seriously probably 
couldn't talk for a day," she said. "I was so sad. I'd sit there and cry for 
about most of the day. You get so used to coming home and there's your dad and 
you do certain things with him, and then you all of a sudden move and your dad 
is not there. And me with my swimming, I didn't see him that much, you know. I 
maybe talked to him a couple times a week. We'd go out to dinner every once in 
a while and go to a movie, but it wasn't the same." 
</P>
<P>
It became more difficult at 15 when her older brother, <PERSON>Trevor</PERSON>, stopped making 
the switch. 
</P>
<P>
"That was kind of a bummer when I had to leave him," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. "But I like 
going to my mom's so I kept at it." 
</P>
<P>
That has been the key to <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' sunny disposition, maintaining warm 
relationships with her father, her mother, her brother and her stepfather. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm really close to all the parts of my family," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. "I think I want 
my kids to have the same family I do. God, they're so laid back. You know, it's 
not like you have to do this, otherwise you'll be a bad person. Like, if you 
want to, you can. It is totally up to us. When I think about church, it was up 
to us. My swimming was up to me. " 
</P>
<P>
Summer <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>, nickname Scum, reveals nothing about swimming on the canvas of 
collegiate personality, her dorm room walls. 
</P>
<P>
They are plastered with <PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON> posters and she wears Air Jordans that 
<PERSON>Trevor</PERSON> gave her on graduation day, the ones she slept in that night. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' roommate didn't even know she was living with a world-class swimmer 
until one of <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON>' swimming friends told her. 
</P>
<P>
Sanders is equally eager to conceal her academic prowess. She makes no mention 
of her <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Swimming Academic All-American status. Sanders is intimidated by 
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"When I first got here, I was real worried because people were using these huge 
words, and I'm into the simple kind of stuff," she said. "One day my friend <PERSON>Lea 
Loveless</PERSON> and I were walking down the hall when someone said something about 
mendicants. 
</P>
<P>
"I said <PERSON>'Lea</PERSON>, my vocabulary is not very good, what is mendicants?' and she 
said, 'Oh God, <DATE>Summer</DATE>, it is a singing group.' " 
</P>
<P>
It is not something she's going to worry about, however. Sanders tries not to 
look back or forward. 
</P>
<P>
Her faithful watch ever on her wrist, she simply follows her demanding academic 
and athletic schedule, including predawn swims while the rest of the campus 
sleeps. 
</P>
<P>
Her idea of a good time? Whatever is going on right now. 
</P>
<P>
"I could just sit here in my dorm room looking at my pictures," <PERSON>Sanders</PERSON> said. 
"I could listen to music. I could read this Homer book ('The Iliad') . . . oh, 
just kidding." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Summer Sanders ; Photo, SUMMER TIME: Expectations are high for Stanford 
swimmer Summer Sanders because of her triple gold-medal performance in the 
Goodwill Games last July. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SWIMMING; COLLEGE ATHLETICS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06099145 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06099145 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; Angel Martino went three years
between wins  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SWIMMING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  It took three years to do it, but Angel Martino, who was disqualified from the
1988 Olympic team, is once again a national champion.;    Martino, of
Tuscaloosa, Ala., won the 50-meter freestyle in the U.S. Swimming Spring
Nationals on the final evening of the meet Sunday in 25.88 seconds.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MARTINO A NATIONAL CHAMPION -- AGAIN  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     She was making her comeback in this meet after serving a suspension for a
positive steroid test following the '88 Olympic trials, when she was unmarried
<PERSON>Angel Myers</PERSON>. Martino had led the first half of the 100 freestyle <DATE>earlier this
week</DATE> but faded to fifth. She was sixth in the 100 butterfly.;    After both
races, she said that lack of training and competition during and after her
16-month suspension had cost her endurance. But the 50, a no-turn dash from
one end of the <ORGANIZATION>King County Aquatics Center</ORGANIZATION> pool to the other, proved to be her
distance.;    "I'm getting there," said <PERSON>Martino</PERSON>, 23, one of the oldest
swimmers at the meet. "I feel old.";    She'll drop the 200 individual medley,
previously one of her best events, from her program because of her age, she
said. But she'll try to qualify for the '92 Olympics in the three races she
swam in this meet.;    <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> won her fourth event of the meet with a
time of 16 minutes, 11.22 seconds in the 1,500 freestyle, the 10th-fastest
time ever. Evans holds four of the top 10 1,500 times, including the world
record at 15:52.10 set at the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic trials. She also earned sixth place
in the 200 backstroke and was the highest point-scorer of the meet, with 80.; 
  "I'm excited to get back to training hard," said <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who is leaving
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> to concentrate on the '92 Games. "I know what I want, I'm going to
work hard for it, and I'm willing to do that.";    No world records fell in
the meet despite it being the qualifier for three <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> teams being sent to
international meets this <DATE>summer</DATE>: the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific Championships</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Edmonton</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alberta</LOCATION>; the <ORGANIZATION>Pan American Games</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Havana</LOCATION>; and the <ORGANIZATION>World University Games</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Sheffield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England.</LOCATION>;    "I think if we hadn't just come from the NCAAs you
would have seen some more American records and world records," said men's 200
<LOCATION>I.M.</LOCATION> winner <PERSON>David Wharton.</PERSON>;    Nevertheless, several <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> marks fell:;   
(check) Women's 200 breaststroke, <PERSON>Anita Nall</PERSON>, 14, of <LOCATION>Towson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION>, 2:27.08,
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> record. (She slashed the previous record by 2.5 seconds, earning her the
performance-of-the-meet award.);    (check) Women's 100 backstroke, <PERSON>Janie
Wagstaff</PERSON>, 16, of <LOCATION>Mission Hills</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, 1:01.10, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> record.;    (check) Men's
200 butterfly, <PERSON>Melvin Stewart</PERSON>, 22, of <LOCATION>Fort Mill</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, 1:56.83, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open
record (fastest time in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> regardless of nationality).;    (check) Men's
200 backstroke, <PERSON>Martin Zubero</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, 1:58.60, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open record.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JODY MEACHAM, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Federal Way, Wash.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910408  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  5D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  478  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 8, 1991
00099145,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080289-0051 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 89761 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 2, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 1; Column 4; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
845 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
EVANS WINS U.S. TITLE IN 400 IM; 
</P>
<P>
TWO OTHER TEENS -- BLANCHARD, KOLE -- ALSO VICTORIOUS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By TRACY DODDS, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
After breezing to another national title in the women's 400-meter individual 
medley <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> night in the <LOCATION>Phillips</LOCATION> 66/U.S. <ORGANIZATION>Swimming Long Course National 
Championships</ORGANIZATION>, 17-year-old <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> said that she was starting to feel old. 
</P>
<P>
Not that she was aching in her bones or gasping for breath. But it's not the 
same as it was in the old days, when she swam in her first long course national 
meet at age 13. When she was a new kid and hung around with the other new kids, 
gawking at the stars. 
</P>
<P>
Now when she walks from the awards stand to the interview room, little girls 
follow along to peek in the windows. 
</P>
<P>
Now she's the star. 
</P>
<P>
The down side to stardom is that there is no one to push her. 
</P>
<P>
She had some competition when she won the gold medal in the 400 IM during the 
Olympic Games in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, enough to push her to a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> record of 4 minutes 37.76 
seconds. <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, she won in 4:39.36 with <PERSON>Michelle Griglione</PERSON> almost eight 
seconds behind her. 
</P>
<P>
The victory, her first of this meet, puts her on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> team that will 
compete at the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific Games</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and then in a dual meet against the 
Soviets. 
</P>
<P>
"It's kind of hard racing against the clock," <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said. "I like to have 
competition. But what can you do? . . . I want to go faster at <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. But there 
probably won't be anyone there, either. I'll have to do it myself." 
</P>
<P>
When it was suggested that she might get some competition when she meets the 
Soviets in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, she brightened. 
</P>
<P>
"Oh, yeah," she said. "There is a Soviet girl who has a really fast 400 IM. I 
hadn't thought about that." 
</P>
<P>
Asked if the excitement and the competition of the Olympic Games made 
everything else seem like a letdown, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> answered with her trademark smile 
and shrug: "The Olympics only come around every four years, and there are a lot 
of other meets in between that." 
</P>
<P>
Two 16-year-olds won the other women's events <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Mary Ellen Blanchard</PERSON> (granddaughter of <DATE>1945</DATE> Heisman Trophy winner <PERSON>Doc 
Blanchard</PERSON>) won the women's 200-meter breaststroke in 2:31.59, and <PERSON>Julie Kole</PERSON> 
(who had won the 1,500-meter freestyle <DATE>Monday</DATE>) won the women's 200-meter 
freestyle in 2:00.95. 
</P>
<P>
Rich <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON>, 27, a swimmer who could tell <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> what it is to feel old on 
the deck, won the men's 100-meter breaststroke. <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON>, who won a gold medal 
with the 400-meter medley relay team in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, has left his job as an 
accountant with <ORGANIZATION>Price Waterhouse</ORGANIZATION> to become a carpenter. He prefers the physical 
work to the hours behind the desk. But his hours for weightlifting and training 
are still limited. 
</P>
<P>
Why does he continue to swim? 
</P>
<P>
"I continue to do it because I thrive on competition," <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON> said. 
"Physically, I don't think I was ready to go 1:02.4, but, boy, I don't like to 
get beat, so I did it. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't know if (the younger guys) like me hanging around, but I want to keep 
them honest. They'll pass me eventually, but they'll have to work for it." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Doug Gjertsen</PERSON>, 22, who won two gold medals on relay teams in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, has 
completed a suspension for his limited involvement in the mask-napping caper in 
<LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, and is again competing for <ORGANIZATION>Longhorn Aquatics</ORGANIZATION>. Gjertsen beat fellow 
Olympian <PERSON>Melvin Stewart</PERSON> in the men's 200-meter freestyle. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wade King</PERSON>, who won the men's 100-meter butterfly, heard <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> saying that she 
felt old and commented: "How does she think I feel?" King is 22 and is just now 
starting to make his mark. 
</P>
<P>
He was thrilled with his national title and the prospect of competing for the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. So far, the highlight of his career has been competing for the 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Am</ORGANIZATION> Games in <DATE>1987</DATE> -- while <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> and company were competing at 
the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific Games</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Brisbane</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
King, who swam for the <ORGANIZATION>University of South Carolina</ORGANIZATION>, explains that swimming 
there is not as "intense" as swimming in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Asked if he planned to retire soon, he said: "Not now. Placing the way I did, 
I'll get a lot more financial support. I'll definitely be able to stay in 
swimming another year." 
</P>
<P>
Wade's time (53.72 seconds) was better than the 54.58 recorded in the 
consolation final by <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympic gold medalist <PERSON>Anthony Nesty</PERSON>. Because he is 
from <LOCATION>Suriname</LOCATION> and is not a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> citizen, <PERSON>Nesty</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION> 
swimmer, was not seeded into the final of this <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> championship meet. 
</P>
<P>
Competition will continue here through <DATE>Friday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Meet Notes 
</P>
<P>
This meet is the selection meet for the <ORGANIZATION>Pan Pacific Championships</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Aug. 
17-20 and most of the swimmers will go directly from <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> for the 
<DATE>Aug. 24-26</DATE> meet (the Alamo Cup) against the Soviet team. The Soviet swimmers 
will be coming from the European championships in <LOCATION>Bonn</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>. . . . 
<PERSON>Mike Bottom</PERSON>, 33, who won the <DATE>1974</DATE> men's national title in the 100-meter 
butterfly with a time of 55.5 seconds and went on to a berth on the <DATE>1980</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>U.S. 
Olympic</ORGANIZATION> team, made the consolation final of the 100-meter butterfly <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> 
night swimming for the <ORGANIZATION>Walnut Creek Aquabears</ORGANIZATION>. He finished 15th in 55.44 -- a 
tick faster than his '74 time. . . . Olympian <PERSON>Dan Jorgensen</PERSON> of Blue Fin Swim 
Team (and USC) was fourth in the men's 200-meter freestyle. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EVANS, JANET; SWIMMING; UNITED STATES ATHLETIC TEAMS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA022390-0007 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 180063 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 23, 1990, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 12; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
962 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SWIMMING; 
</P>
<P>
UCLA WOMEN AIM FOR HIGH PAC-10 FINISH 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By IAN JAQUISS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The seventh-ranked <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> women's team is on a roll going into the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 
Conference swimming meet today through <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>East Los Angeles College</ORGANIZATION> 
pool. 
</P>
<P>
The Bruins defeated <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> two weeks ago, 86-54, and Coach <PERSON>Cyndi Gallagher</PERSON> is 
hoping for a top-three finish this <DATE>weekend</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"We hope to equal last year's performance," she said. "We have four girls 
qualified (for the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> meet in <DATE>March</DATE>) and hope to get a lot more. We were 
third last year and will challenge (<ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>) for that again." 
</P>
<P>
Stanford, ranked No. 1 in the nation, and <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION>, No. 4, will probably contend for 
the team championship. UCLA, <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> will battle for the next 
spots. Oregon dropped its swimming program in <DATE>1986</DATE> so only nine teams will 
compete. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA, 7-2 overall and 3-2 in the conference, finished in a sixth-place tie with 
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> at last year's NCAA meet. The Bruins have five All-Americans and 
several other swimmers who can score in championship meets. 
</P>
<P>
For the Trojans, the performance against the Bruins was encouraging, despite 
the defeat. Going into the meet, <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> Coach <PERSON>Darrell Fick</PERSON> knew that winning would 
be difficult because <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> was giving away so many points in diving. 
</P>
<P>
UCLA has a much stronger diving program than <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, and because two diving events 
are included in dual meets, and scored like the swimming events, the Trojans 
were starting with a 14-point deficit. 
</P>
<P>
The 12th-ranked Trojans (9-6 and 0-5) have three All-Americans and several 
freshmen who have potential to score at the conference and <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> meets. They 
finished fourth in the Pac-10 meet last year and 25th in the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Fick is optimistic that <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> will finish in the top <DATE>five this weekend</DATE> but will 
not be disappointed with a lower placing. Several of <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s top swimmers have 
qualified for the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> meet and they will not be shaving for the conference 
meet. 
</P>
<P>
"We'll be aiming for third or fourth," <PERSON>Fick</PERSON> said. "<LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> are just 
too deep, but we'll be in with <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Fick thinks the <ORGANIZATION>Trojans</ORGANIZATION> will improve on last year's <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> performance, and 
expects his swimmers to finish in the top 10. The team was dealt a setback, 
however, when Australian distance swimmer <PERSON>Janelle Elford</PERSON> changed her mind about 
attending <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> after competing in last month's Commonwealth Games. 
</P>
<P>
Elford, the last person to have beaten <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> in a distance 
freestyle event at a major meet, won a gold, a silver and a bronze at the 
<ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> games, and <PERSON>Fick</PERSON> was counting on her to help the Trojans in both 
meets. 
</P>
<P>
USC's men's team defeated <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, 69-44, and finished the regular 
season unbeaten in 11 meets. The Trojans are ranked second in the nation going 
into the Pac-10 meet <DATE>March 5-7</DATE> at <LOCATION>Belmont Plaza</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>. UCLA, which is 
tied with <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> for fourth, finished its regular season at 9-4 and 3-2. 
</P>
<P>
It was <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>'s fifth consecutive victory over <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION>. USC had two scorers out of a 
possible three in seven of the 11 individual events, including the 1,000- and 
200-yard freestyles, in which it placed first through fourth. 
</P>
<P>
After <ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> had swept <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> two weeks ago, the Bruin-Trojan meet 
looked to be one of the top duals of the year. But the week after the sweep, 
<ORGANIZATION>UCLA</ORGANIZATION> had disciplinary problems and five swimmers were suspended for meets 
against <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>. In addition, freshman backstroke ace <PERSON>Geoff 
Cronin</PERSON> missed those meets and the <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> meet as well because of poor attendance 
at practice. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Matt Biondi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tom Jager</PERSON> will meet again in 50-yard freestyle match races next 
month at <LOCATION>Nevada Las Vegas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. They will swim <DATE>March 2</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>UNLV</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Buchanan 
Natatorium</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$4,500</MONEY> in prizes, <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> going to the winner. That race will be 
held in conjunction with the <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Short Course</ORGANIZATION> championships. 
</P>
<P>
Meet director <PERSON>Dave Marsh</PERSON>, the coach of <LOCATION>Las Vegas Gold</LOCATION> swim team, has also lined 
up a 200-yard butterfly race between retirees <PERSON>Tracy Caulkins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Meagher</PERSON>, 
and a 100-yard freestyle race between <PERSON>Rowdy Gaines</PERSON> and Australian <PERSON>Mark 
Stockwell</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Caulkins won 48 national championships and <PERSON>Meagher</PERSON> is still the world 
record-holder in the 100-and 200-meter butterfly events, and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
record-holder in each the 100- and 200-yard butterfly. Each won three gold 
medals at the <DATE>1984</DATE> Olympics. 
</P>
<P>
The race between <PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stockwell</PERSON> pits the <DATE>1984</DATE> Olympic gold medalist 
against the silver medalist for the first time since those games. In their last 
meeting, <PERSON>Stockwell</PERSON> charged that <PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> jumped the start and should have been 
disqualified. Videotapes showed that <PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> did not come to a full stop before 
the starter started the race but the result stood. 
</P>
<P>
On <DATE>March 28</DATE>, when they meet at <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Biondi</PERSON> and Jager will be joined by <PERSON>Tom 
Williams</PERSON>, the 50-meter freestyle champion at the <DATE>1987</DATE> Pan-American Games. 
</P>
<P>
The race, which will be held in conjunction with the U. S. Swimming Junior 
Olympic championships at the <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION> field house, will have a prize of <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> for 
the winner. As an added incentive, any swimmer who beats 19 seconds will win a 
new car. Biondi holds the American record of 19.15 seconds. Jager and <ORGANIZATION>Williams</ORGANIZATION> 
have swum 19.24 and 19.64 respectively. 
</P>
<P>
Biondi beat Jager in the first match race in <DATE>December</DATE> at <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Swimming Notes 
</P>
<P>
Last month at the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth Games</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Auckland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> sophomore 
<PERSON>Gary Anderson</PERSON> won gold medals in the 200-meter individual medley, the 200-meter 
backstroke, and a silver medal in the 100-meter backstroke while competing for 
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>. . . . Also at the Games, <PERSON>Glenn Housman</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> became the second 
swimmer to break the 15-minute mark in the 1,500-meter freestyle, winning in 
14:55.25. In the same race, 16-year-old <PERSON>Kieren Perkins</PERSON>, also of <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 
became the third swimmer with a time of 14:58.08. <PERSON>Vladimir Salnikov</PERSON> of the 
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> holds the world record, 14:54.76. 
</P></TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA061689-0122 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 71042 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 16, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 12; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
378 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MISSION VIEJO SWIMMING; 
</P>
<P>
AS EXPECTED, EVANS WINS 800 EASILY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AL PRESTON 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Less than 24 hours after receiving her diploma from <ORGANIZATION>El Dorado High School</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> conducted business as usual <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the first day of the <ORGANIZATION>Mission 
Viejo International Meet of Champions</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>Marguerite Recreation Center</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Swimming in the first of eight events in which she is scheduled to compete, 
<PERSON>Evans</PERSON> was hardly challenged as she scored an easy victory in the women's 
800-meter freestyle with a time of 8 minutes 39.58 seconds. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Laurence Bensimon</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, finished second in 8:55.58. 
<PERSON>Sarah Anderson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Riverside</LOCATION> was third (9:00.93). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who last year set her world record of 8:17.12, took an early lead and 
then pulled away from the field. 
</P>
<P>
"It was like a workout swim for me," said <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>, who will attend <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> in 
the <DATE>fall</DATE>. "I just tried to keep getting ahead of my competition and see how far 
along I am in my training. I was happy with the way I swam." 
</P>
<P>
Evans, who will compete in the 400-meter individual medley and 200-meter 
butterfly in the Mission Viejo meet today, the 400-meter freestyle and 200 
backstroke on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and the 200-meter individual medley, 200 breaststroke 
and 200 freestyle on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Reflecting on her graduation experiences the night before, <PERSON>Evans</PERSON> said: "Picking 
up my high school diploma was a little different for me. It was a sad 
experience for me but I was also happy. I'm going to miss high school but I'm 
real excited about starting college at <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> and I'm looking forward to it." 
</P>
<P>
In the men's 800-meter freestyle, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>'s Artur Wojdat survived a strong 
challenge from <ORGANIZATION>Mission Viejo</ORGANIZATION> teammate <ORGANIZATION>Mariusz Podkoscielny</ORGANIZATION> to win in 8:08.62. 
</P>
<P>
Podkoscielny, who stayed with Wojdat until the final 200 meters, was second in 
8:10.79. <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympian <PERSON>Dan Jorgensen</PERSON> came in third in 8:14.86. 
</P>
<P>
"I expected to go about 8:10, so I was happy with my time," <PERSON>Wojdat</PERSON> said. "I'm 
right now where I expected to be when the season started." 
</P>
<P>
Said Podkoscielny: "I'm happy with what I did. I led at the halfway point, but 
I didn't lead by enough, and he won the race with his speed at the end." 
</P>
<P>
Wojdat and Podkoscielny, who competed for <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> during the <DATE>1988</DATE> Olympics, and 
<PERSON>Jorgensen</PERSON>, were among four Olympians in the men's event. <PERSON>Lars Jorgensen</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dan</PERSON>'s 
brother and <DATE>1988</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>U.S.</ORGANIZATION> team member, finished fourth in 8:19.70. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Janet Evans swims to a 16-second victory in the 800-meter freestyle 
Thursday in Mission Viejo. KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Full Run; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
EVANS, JANET; SWIMMING 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121790-0028 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 323454 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 17, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 24; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1062 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SWIMMING / THERESA MUNOZ; 
</P>
<P>
TIMES GET FASTER AFTER HER HEART SLOWS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THERESA MUNOZ 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
It would strike at any time -- the middle of the night, the beginning of 
practice, en route to class on the <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> campus. Without warning, <PERSON>Megan 
Holliday</PERSON>'s heart would begin to race, up to 170 beats a minute. 
</P>
<P>
The freshman distance freestyle swimmer from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ontario</LOCATION>, was born with 
Wolff-Parkinson-White Syndrome, and has an extra muscle fiber connected to the 
upper and lower chambers of the heart that conducts impulses. When the 
pea-sized extra fiber was functioning, it forced <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON>'s heart to beat too 
rapidly. 
</P>
<P>
Holliday noticed the symptoms when she was 11. The rapid heartbeats lasted from 
several minutes to more than an hour, although months would pass without an 
episode. 
</P>
<P>
Her doctor told her it was only a nuisance that she might grow out of, but 
after <ORGANIZATION>Loyola Marymount</ORGANIZATION> basketball star <PERSON>Hank Gathers</PERSON> collapsed and died of a 
heart condition last <DATE>spring</DATE>, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON>'s mother, <PERSON>Susan</PERSON>, ordered more tests for 
her daughter. 
</P>
<P>
The tests revealed that <PERSON>Megan</PERSON> is in a high-risk group and could suffer a heart 
attack at any time. 
</P>
<P>
"I was in shock," <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> said. "I thought all along it wasn't a big problem." 
</P>
<P>
She was given three options: medication, a catheter ablation procedure or open 
heart surgery. 
</P>
<P>
Holliday decided on the catheter ablation procedure, which would destroy the 
superfluous tissue, because it would not require a lengthy recovery. On <DATE>Aug</DATE>. 
20, a Canadian doctor performed the operation, but he was inexperienced with 
the technique and it failed. 
</P>
<P>
Upon her arrival in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> tried medication, but it 
backfired. 
</P>
<P>
"I had attacks more often and I was dizzy so the university pulled me out of 
the water," said <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON>, who had 12 episodes in four days. 
</P>
<P>
"My mom frantically called around to find a doctor who could do the catheter 
ablation procedure. We found one in <LOCATION>Oklahoma City</LOCATION> who had a cancellation, and I 
went on two days' notice." 
</P>
<P>
In a 14-hour procedure, the surgeon, <PERSON>Warren Jackman</PERSON>, positioned a small metal 
electrode into the heart via a catheter. Using a high-frequency electrical 
current, he destroyed the extra fiber. Five days later, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> was back in 
the water. 
</P>
<P>
"I never really thought about it as my life being in danger," she said. "The 
funny thing is, I only worried about not being able to swim. Everyone else 
worried about my health." 
</P>
<P>
Although the procedure was apparently successful, there remains cause for 
concern. 
</P>
<P>
"I still get it going too fast, but after a couple of beats it stops," <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> 
said. "I talked to my doctor (in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>). He said because I'm tuned to my 
heart so well I'm going to be on the alert for anything abnormal." 
</P>
<P>
During Christmas vacation or <DATE>spring</DATE> break, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> will be retested. Her heart 
will be stimulated to race to make sure the fiber has not grown back. There is 
an <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT> recurrence rate, but according to <PERSON>Jackman</PERSON>, there is no recurrence after a 
second procedure. 
</P>
<P>
In the meantime, <PERSON>Holliday</PERSON> is concentrating on swimming. 
</P>
<P>
As a 15-year-old, she won two bronze medals for <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1987</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Pan American 
Games</ORGANIZATION>, but since <DATE>1989</DATE> she had leveled off -- until <DATE>last weekend</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Even after missing a month of practice, she improved her time by 45 seconds in 
the 1,650-yard freestyle in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> National Grand Prix meet at <LOCATION>Belmont Plaza</LOCATION> 
in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Cal's <PERSON>Sarah Anderson</PERSON> swam a meet-record 16 minutes 22.82 seconds in winning the 
1,650 freestyle <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in the Grand Prix meet. Anderson also won the 500 
freestyle handily at 4:46.32, and the third-ranked Bears won in the women's 
division, beating <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, which is ranked fifth nationally, 1,249.5 to 948.5. 
</P>
<P>
Cal and <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> split the four relays, thanks to a strong finish by <ORGANIZATION>Cal</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Amy 
Tidball</PERSON> in the last event of the meet, the 400 freestyle relay. <PERSON>Tidball</PERSON> was 
caught by Trojan anchor <PERSON>Lisa Dorman</PERSON> at the final turn, but <PERSON>Tidball</PERSON> inched ahead 
in the last 10 yards. 
</P>
<P>
"I just held my breath and it really speeded me up," <PERSON>Tidball</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
All was not lost by <PERSON>Dorman</PERSON>, however. She won the 100 freestyle in 50.87 and set 
a school record in the 50 with a 23.18. 
</P>
<P>
On the men's side, <ORGANIZATION>Arizona State</ORGANIZATION> beat <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION>, 1,111 to 1,022.5. The Trojans were 
without five of their top swimmers. Four were benched by Coach <PERSON>Peter Daland</PERSON> for 
missing practice and Olympian <PERSON>Dave Wharton</PERSON>, preparing for the World 
Championships, swam only in the relays. 
</P>
<P>
The individual highlight on the men's side was <PERSON>Glenn Peoples</PERSON>' 1:59.70 in the 
200 breaststroke. The time would have placed him 15th in last season's <ORGANIZATION>NCCA</ORGANIZATION> 
meet, a promising effort so early in the season. 
</P>
<P>
Swimming Notes 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Janet Evans</PERSON> had a sore throat and finished fifth in the 400 individual medley 
and seventh in the 200 freestyle at the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open in <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> <DATE>Nov. 30-Dec</DATE>. 
1. . . . In the 100 butterfly, <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Brian Alderman</PERSON> upset <DATE>1988</DATE> 
