<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-25750 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi114_a_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-114 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> General </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Clinton Welcomes Japanese Emperor </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Clinton Welcomes Japanese Emperor </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW1306170894 Beijing XINHUA in English 1637 GMT 13 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1306170894 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 13</DATE> (XINHUA) -- <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Bill 
Clinton</PERSON> today held a welcome ceremony for Japanese Emperor 
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>White House South Lawn</ORGANIZATION>. 
  "Your Majesties visit us at a moment when it is clear that 
the destinies of our two peoples are inextricably linked," 
<PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> said at the ceremony attended by about 4,000 people. 
  "We share a common vision. It is a vision of democracy and 
prosperity... [ellipses as received], of a world where we trade 
freely in ideas and goods," <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> said. 
  "Our commitment to common ideals is firm, our determination 
to work with you is strong," <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> added. 
  Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> said that "Our two countries have overcome 
the deplorable rupture brought about by war and have forged a 
close and cooperative relationship." 
  "I sincerely hope that this visit will further contribute to 
the promotion of friendship between our two peoples," the 
emperor said. 
  The emperor and empress were greeted with full honors 
including a 21-gun salute. 
  They will attend a state dinner in the <PERSON>Rose Garden</PERSON> of the 
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> hosted by President <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> <TIME>this evening</TIME>. 
  The couple arrived in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> <DATE>June 10</DATE> for the first leg of 
their 16-day tour in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. They plan to visit 11 
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cities. 
  They will leave <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [15 <DATE>June</DATE>] and travel to 
the <ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION> and then on to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-27696 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi039_d_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-039 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Northeast Asia </F>
<H3> <TI>   Zhu Rongji Meets Japanese Economic Figures, Officials </TI></H3>
<H4>   Visits Emperor Akihito </H4>
<F P=102> OW2602084094 Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service in Chinese 1122 
GMT 25 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> OW2602084094 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA Domestic Service </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Chinese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By reporter <PERSON>Zhang Huanli</PERSON> (1728 3562 0448)] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, 25 Feb (XINHUA) -- Chinese Vice Premier <PERSON>Zhu 
Rongji</PERSON>, who is making a formal friendly visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, paid a 
courtesy call on Japanese Emperor Akihito at the palace here 
<TIME>this morning</TIME>. 
  Expressing a warm welcome to <PERSON>Zhu Rongji</PERSON>, <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> 
said: "I was glad to hear that Vice Premier <PERSON>Zhu</PERSON> has met a number 
of people from both <ORGANIZATION>Japanese Government</ORGANIZATION> and nongovernment 
organizations during the past two days and achieved progress in 
promoting bilateral friendship." 
  Zhu Rongji conveyed to Emperor Akihito sincere greetings and 
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> expressed his thanks and asked <PERSON>Zhu Rongji</PERSON> to 
convey his greetings to President <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON> and other Chinese 
leaders. 
  Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> pleasantly recalled his visit to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in 
<DATE>1992</DATE>. He said: "During my trip to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, I went to <LOCATION>Xian</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>. When I was in <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>, I was impressed by <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s 
rapid economic growth." 
  Zhu Rongji briefed <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> on Sino-Japanese 
relations, and particularly the rapid development in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s 
economic cooperation and trade with <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
  Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was pleased with the rapid development of 
Sino-Japanese relations. 
  Present at the meeting was Chinese Ambassador to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> Xu 
Dungxin. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890413-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-13-89 1017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-China 1stLd-Writethru a0487 04-13 0394</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-China, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0487,0405</SECOND>
<HEAD>Chinese Premier Invites Japan's Emperor To China</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Adds 9 grafs after 6th pvs, ``The official...'' to ADD background
on Chinese-Japanese hostility. No Pickup.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Chinese Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> met <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s emperor and
empress today and invited them to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, government officials
said.
   Li made the invitation during a 20-minute meeting with the newly
enthroned monarch at the <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo Imperial Palace</ORGANIZATION>, a senior <ORGANIZATION>Imperial
Household Agency</ORGANIZATION> official said.
   If the invitation is accepted, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> would be the
first Japanese monarch to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   But the palace spokesman said several problems exist and the
visit would have to await the end of a year of court mourning for
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s father, Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died on <DATE>Jan. 7</DATE> at age 87.
   ``Premier <PERSON>Li</PERSON> said that he hoped the royal couple would visit
when the time was right for them. In reply, the emperor thanked him
but said the decision must be made by the government,'' said the
agency official.
   The official, who briefed reporters on condition of anonymity,
said the two also discussed ``their nations' 2,000-year history,
including World War II.''
   Bitter memories of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s actions during World War II often
have clouded Japan-China relations. After sharp criticism by <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>
and other nations, Prime Minister <PERSON>Noboru Takeshita</PERSON> in <DATE>February</DATE>
retrated a statement that future historians must decide whether
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was an aggressor.
   More than 10 million Chinese died during <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 1937-45
invasion of the Chinese mainland. Beijing reacts strongly to any
Japanese attempt to deny responsibility.
   Japanese news reports have speculated that <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> would express
regret over <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s militarist past during today's meeting, but
government officials refused to confirm or deny this.
   ``The emperor expressed his views on the nations' pasts, and Li
welcomed those views,'' said the official.
   Earlier today, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> announced it would lend <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> up to <MONEY>$734
million</MONEY> in the current fiscal year. The loan is to help fund 11
projects for modernization in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, including an expansion of
ports in <LOCATION>Lianyungang</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Qingdao</LOCATION> and construction of a subway in
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>.
   Li is on a five-day official visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> accompanied by
senior officials, including Foreign Minister <PERSON>Qian Qichen</PERSON>, who met
today with his Japanese counterpart, <ORGANIZATION>Sousuke Uno</ORGANIZATION>.
   The last Chinese premier to visit <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was <PERSON>Zhao Ziyang</PERSON>, now
head of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>, in <DATE>May 1982</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-29186 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas031_a_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-031 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Hosokawa: Emperor To Visit U.S. `This Year' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW1102222694 Tokyo KYODO in English 2221 GMT 11 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1102222694 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Emperor 
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will pay a visit to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> this year, Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Morihiro Hosokawa</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> [11 <DATE>February</DATE>]. 
  Hosokawa told President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> of the emperor's 
intention to make the trip during their summit meeting <DATE>Friday</DATE>, 
Japanese officials said. 
  <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> expressed his pleasure at the visit and said the 
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. 
Government</ORGANIZATION> will do everything it can to make the emperor feel 
welcome, a Japanese spokesman said. 
  Hosokawa did not say when the Japanese monarch is expected 
to 
make the trip, but government sources in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> have said it is 
likely to be in <DATE>June</DATE>. 
  Empress Michiko is expected to accompany the emperor. It 
will be the first visit by a Japanese emperor to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> since 
the late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, posthumously called Emperor Showa, 
went there in <DATE>September 1975</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-2299 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi068_v_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> TAIWAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Japan's Emperor Grants Audience to Banker </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Japan's Emperor Grants Audience to Banker </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0704150594 Taipei CNA in English 0807 GMT 7 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0704150594 </F>
<F P=104>  Taipei CNA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <LOCATION>Sofia</LOCATION> Wu] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Taipei</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 7</DATE> (CNA) -- <PERSON>Jeffrey Ku</PERSON>, chairman of 
the Taipei-based <ORGANIZATION>Chinatrust Commercial Bank</ORGANIZATION>, was granted an 
audience with Japanese Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [6 <DATE>April</DATE>]. 
  "I feel honored to have met with the Japanese emperor at his 
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> palace," <PERSON>Ku</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> upon his return from a five-day 
visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
  Ku, also an unpaid advisor to <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>'s Executive Yuan, 
stressed that his visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was private. 
  Ku said Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> expressed his goodwill and regard 
for 
<LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>. "<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was interested in <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>'s current 
developments," he noted. 
  Ku said he briefed the Japanese emperor on <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>'s economic 
strength and its role in Southeast Asian economic development. 
  "We also exchanged views on the possible impact on <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> of 
the <ORGANIZATION>North American Free Trade Agreement</ORGANIZATION> and the prospects for 
the formation of the proposed <ORGANIZATION>East Asia Economic Caucus</ORGANIZATION> and the 
Asian Free Trade Agreement," <PERSON>Ku</PERSON> said. 
  Ku was the first <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> businessman granted a formal 
audience 
with <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> since the emperor took the throne in <DATE>October 1989</DATE>. 
Akihito talked briefly with [passage indistinct]. 
  Political observers said <PERSON>Jeffrey Ku</PERSON>'s meeting with <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> 
would boost the development of substantive ties between <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, even though the Japanese emperor is just a spiritual 
leader and wields no political power. 
  <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> recognizes <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> and has been reluctant to develop 
any official ties with <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION> for fear of offending communist 
Chinese leaders. 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, have sent ministerial-level officials to visit <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>, 
but <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has not followed suit. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-46580 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas001_a_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-001 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Imperial Couple's Year-End Statements Reported </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW3112022293 Tokyo KYODO in English 0150 GMT 31 Dec 93 </F>
<F P=103> OW3112022293 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 1</DATE> KYODO -- The year <DATE>1994</DATE> will be busy 
for Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> with preparations 
proceeding for the couple's visits to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, the first attempt by a Japanese monarch to travel 
overseas twice in one year. 
  In mid-June, the emperor and the empress are expected to 
travel to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, where they will visit eastern, southern and 
western cities. They also plan to make a stopover in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> 
during the journey, official sources said. 
  Preparations are also under way for their trip to <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> 
and 
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>autumn</DATE>, the sources said. 
  It will be the first time that a Japanese emperor will make 
more than one overseas trip in a year, they said. 
  A visit to the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Crown Prince Naruhito</PERSON> and his 
wife, <PERSON>Princess Masako</PERSON>, is also being considered, the first 
overseas trip by the couple since they got married <DATE>last June</DATE>, 
the sources said. 
  Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> spends [as received] the 
New Year's Day at a newly constructed residence within the 
Imperial Palace compound in central <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. 
  On the opening of the New Year, the emperor said in a 
statement that he hopes disaster-stricken people will be able to 
stand firmly on their feet as quickly as possible, saying that 
the past year was full of numerous sufferings. 
  "It is highly regrettable that throughout the world many 
people are still victims of local conflicts," Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> 
said in the statement. "On the other hand, it is gratifying to 
note signs of movement in the right direction, as in the case of 
<LOCATION>Cambodia</LOCATION>." 
  An unusually cool <DATE>summer</DATE> hit the already harsh economic 
environment and more than 400 people died or went missing in an 
earthquake and cloudbursts in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
  On the quake-battered <LOCATION>Okushiri Island</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Hokkaido</LOCATION>, Emperor 
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> said in one of his waka [Japanese-style poem], "I am 
sorrowful, to see the smoke wreaths rising, from things burning 
out, 
  There along the island shore, all strewn with broken 
houses." 
  In <DATE>February</DATE>, the emperor and the empress will visit Iwo Jima 
and the <LOCATION>Ogasawara</LOCATION> islands, where the fiercest fighting in World 
War II took place. The imperial couple will make the visit to 
the islets in the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>, far south of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, to mark the 
25th anniversary of their return by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> in <DATE>1969</DATE>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Imperial Household Agency</ORGANIZATION> officials said. 
  Empress <PERSON>Michiko</PERSON> expressed her joy in her waka at her eldest 
son's marriage to <PERSON>Masako Owada</PERSON>, a former career diplomat. 
  "Hand in hand, may you climb together, 
  The mountain, which, now green with foliage, must be 
garmented in serene beauty," her waka said. 
  Empress <PERSON>Michiko</PERSON>, who collapsed on her <DATE>59th birthday last 
October 20</DATE> and suffered speech impairment, has partially 
recovered her ability to speak, and her condition is slowly 
getting better, doctors said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12124</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJVB5ADGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921022
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 OCT 92 / Thaw after a long winter: Emperor Akihito's historic visit
to China
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROBERT THOMSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Conscious of the weight of history bearing down on him, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Emperor
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> carefully delivers each of his pre-scripted public words,
punctuating the sentences with uncomfortably long silences and filtering the
emotion from a voice still ascribed supernatural qualities.
His tones will be more carefully measured than usual when he arrives in
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> tomorrow for the first visit by a Japanese emperor. The humble <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>
has made clear a sense of deep privilege that his reign should be chosen for
this journey.
The emperor's most obvious task will be to deal with the relatively recent
past, the invasion of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> during the <DATE>1930s</DATE> and <DATE>1940s</DATE>, by delivering an
unambiguous apology and, perhaps, clearing the way for an era in which the
economic potential of the relationship will finally overcome the bitter
memories.
For the Communist party leaders who invited the emperor, the six-day visit
has a less lofty, more immediate purpose. They are still in the process of
convincing the Chinese people that the regime has the respect of the
international community, and any foreign dignitary has been much appreciated
since the <LOCATION>Tiananmen</LOCATION> crackdown of <DATE>1989</DATE>. In these circumstances, a visit by
the emperor is all the more welcome.
The Chinese government is also keen to attract Japanese investment, a
controversial issue during the early <DATE>1980s</DATE> when the revolutionary elders
drew comparisons between Japanese joint ventures in northern <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and the
occupation of <LOCATION>Manchuria</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, an occupation begun in the name of the
then Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, father of Akihito.
It is a sign of the changed times that six leading trading houses, including
<ORGANIZATION>Mitsubishi Corp</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mitsui &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION> yesterday announced a plan to build a
Dollars 4bn petrochemical complex in the northern Chinese province of
<LOCATION>Liaoning</LOCATION>. Japanese trading houses are also developing an industrial park in
the northern city of <LOCATION>Dalian</LOCATION>, and a Japanese trucking company has announced
plans for a transportation network in the north.
In the year of the <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> visit, the 20th anniversary of the restoration of
Sino-Japanese relations, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will become <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s second-largest trading
partner, behind the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, and up from fifth place a year ago. Japanese
investment in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, which rose from <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 349m in <DATE>1990</DATE> to Dollars 579m
last year, is likely to double this year, as manufacturers bruised by
falling profits source more of their components in low-cost and increasingly
reliable <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
The emperor is certain to laud this developing bilateral economic
relationship. But the flow of funds and an apology from the emperor are not
likely to appease a Chinese people raised on horrific tales of the 'burn
all, loot all, kill all' policies of the Japanese military during the second
world war.
Detailing the brutality of that period has served the Communist party's
interests as it highlights the 'heroic' role of revolutionary-era soldiers,
one of whom, <PERSON>Deng Xiaoping</PERSON>, is now an emperor himself in everything but
name. In deference to the Japanese emperor, <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> has barred protests by
private groups seeking war compensation from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and taken much newspaper
space to explain the new, non-political role of <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>.
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s foreign ministry is also emphasising the 'non-political' role of the
emperor, as enshrined in the constitution, and arguing that the event is
nothing more than a 'goodwill visit'. This interpretation is questioned by
some sceptical members of the ruling Liberal Democratic party.
Evidence of the relationship's rich and complex history is shown in the
varied opposition from left, right and middle-ground groups in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. There
are complaints that the timing of the visit violates the emperor's
'non-political' status and about the flattering of a discredited Chinese
leadership.
Then there is concern that the exalted Japanese emperor is travelling to
'pay tribute'. Even at the height of Chinese influence over the <DATE>past two
millennia</DATE>, during which <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> imported a written language and the essence of
its spiritual and philosophic beliefs, no emperor crossed the sea to
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-28539 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas112_a_94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-112 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Emperor, Empress Leave for 17-Day U.S. Tour </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Emperor, Empress Leave for 17-Day U.S. Tour </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW1006024394 Tokyo KYODO in English 0220 GMT 10 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1006024394 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 10</DATE> KYODO -- <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> and <PERSON>Empress 
Michiko</PERSON> left <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Haneda</LOCATION> airport <DATE>Friday</DATE> [10 <DATE>June</DATE>] <TIME>morning</TIME> for 
<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, to begin a 17-day, 11-city visit to the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. 
  The emperor and empress are the first state guests of the 
administration of President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> since he took office in 
<DATE>January 1993</DATE>. 
  In <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, the emperor and empress will meet former 
President <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Coretta Scott King</PERSON>, widow of 
assassinated civil rights leader <PERSON>Martin Luther King</PERSON>, government 
officials said. 
  They will be in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> for <DATE>four days from Saturday</DATE>, and 
will meet President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>, lay a wreath at <ORGANIZATION>Arlington 
Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> and visit an elementary school. 
  <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> will hold a welcoming ceremony for the imperial 
couple <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The couple will also travel to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Longmont</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>. 
  In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, they will meet UN Secretary General Butrus 
Butrus- <PERSON>Ghali</PERSON>, and in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Ronald 
Reagan</PERSON>. 
  In <LOCATION>Honolulu</LOCATION>, they will lay a wreath at the <ORGANIZATION>National Memorial 
Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> but will not visit <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION>, on 
which <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> launched a devastating attack on <DATE>Dec. 7, 1941</DATE>. 
  The government dropped plans for the emperor to visit the 
<ORGANIZATION>USS 
Arizona National Memorial</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION> under pressure from 
conservative Japanese circles, who fear the emperor would be 
expected to make an apology for the attack that pulled the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
into World War II. 
  It is the second visit by a Japanese emperor to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, posthumously known as Emperor Showa, made the 
first such visit in <DATE>1975</DATE>. 
  It is also the imperial couple's first <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tour since the 
emperor succeeded his deceased father in <DATE>January 1989</DATE>, and their 
third official visit to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, which they visited twice as 
crown prince and princess. 
  The couple will return to <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> on <DATE>June 26</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-4379</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFJCMAA5FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940610
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 JUN 94 / Japan's past precedes emperor's US visit: Ambiguity over war
record surrounds imperial tour
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM DAWKINS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> starts his first imperial visit to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE>
with a mixture of friendship and sad wartime memories on his mind.
The emperor's 17-day tour will end with a poignant reminder of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
ambiguous feelings over its wartime record. In this there is a parallel with
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>'s uncomfortable complexes over the recent D-Day landing
celebrations. For <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> the equivalent will come under the spotlight next
year, the 50th anniversary of the end of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> war.
As the <LOCATION>Normandy</LOCATION> surf erases the tracks of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s D-Day celebrations,
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will stop in <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> on his way home to lay a wreath at the
The emperor's gesture, to the sadness of some in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, falls short of
the Japanese government's original plan for him to visit the USS <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>
memorial in <LOCATION>Pearl Harbour</LOCATION>, a battleship sunk by the Japanese attack on
<DATE>December 7 1941</DATE>. That idea was dropped because of fierce objections from
Japanese right-wing politicians and commentators, many of whom believe the
<DATE>1941</DATE> attack was unavoidable, maybe even justified.
Officially, the emperor is so mystically elevated that he must get less
involved in temporal affairs than his high profile counterparts in the
British or Spanish royal families.
So he politely declined last week to comment on whether or not the <LOCATION>Pearl
Harbour</LOCATION> attack could be justified, beyond saying that the war lay heavy on
his heart. 'It is very important to understand historical truths correctly,
but because of my position, I must refrain from touching on this kind of
subject,' he said.
Yet at the same time, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has deliberately descended just a
little closer to earth than his father, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, a mark of the gradual
evolution of the world's oldest unbroken imperial dynasty.
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was the first to ascend the Chrysanthemum throne, in <DATE>1989</DATE>,
as a human symbol of the state, rather than a god. His father, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> was
born the Son of Heaven, but was obliged by the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> occupiers after the war to
renounce his divinity.
As such, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> appears to be trying to play a subtle, yet emotive
role in shaping <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s attempt publicly to come to terms with its wartime
past, the prerequisite for success in its campaign to become a fully fledged
In this, the Emperor is in tune with a gathering mood of wartime regret in
mainstream <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, in line with his traditional role of embodying the
national spirit. Former prime minister <PERSON>Mr Morihiro Hosokawa</PERSON>'s
unprecedentedly explicit apologies over <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s wartime record and the
recent re-writing of school textbooks to include more detail of that record
are the latest signs of this.
While feelings of atonement are on the rise, there is certainly no common
view on war history, one of the several areas in which fault lines are
appearing in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s famous consensus.
There is a dangerous nationalist minority, as shown by the recent gun attack
against <PERSON>Mr Hosokawa</PERSON> by a right-wing protestor, angered at his wartime
apologies. The denial two months ago by a justice minister that an infamous
wartime atrocity never happened, damaged <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s increasingly vital Asian
relations. The minister resigned, but the suspicions he aroused will be hard
to soothe.
To some, the significance of Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s role as a public figure is
ambiguous, as shown by the response of <PERSON>Mr Shintaro Ishihara</PERSON>, a right-wing
member of the opposition Liberal Democratic party, to the aborted <LOCATION>Pearl
Harbour</LOCATION> visit.
'I have never heard of a <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> president visiting the memorial hall in
<LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>,' he said, drawing a temporal comparison. Yet <PERSON>Mr Ishihara</PERSON> a moment
later elevated Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> to semi-divinity. 'The emperor is the only
priest king in the world. I think it is good for the emperor to be mystical.
If the emperor is not mystical, he will no longer be eternal,' he argues.
The emperor has in the first five years of his reign worked hard to
contribute, as a globe trotting ambassador, to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s temporal interests.
He has already visited the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> twice in his official capacity as Crown
Prince. His father made the trip once.
Two years ago, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> became the first Japanese emperor to visit
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, so helping to clear the way for closer economic and diplomatic links.
At the time, he pleased the Chinese government by saying he 'deeply
deplored' the suffering caused during the Japanese occupation. He stopped
short of apologising.
Earlier this year, Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> paid the first
imperial visit to the war memorial of <LOCATION>Iwo Jima</LOCATION>, a small <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island where
many thousands of <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and Japanese were killed. He carefully referred, at the
time, to the dead of both sides.
Akihito hopes that the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> visit will, as the one to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> did, bring closer
ties. Of course he refrains from noting that his US tour is most timely,
just as a growing number of senior <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> government officials are getting
anxious that the strain in trade relations might spill over into political
and security relations.
Accordingly, the imperial couple have accepted a punishing schedule,
including 11 cities, starting in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> today. They proceed to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
tomorrow, where they will be the guests of honour on <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the first
full state dinner of <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>'s presidency, a protocol compliment that
will not be lost on <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s humble emperor.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    JPZ  Japan, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9111 Executive Offices.
    P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 6
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890804-0089 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-89 1859EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Japan-Emperor     08-04 0714</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Emperor,0733</SECOND>
<HEAD>First Televised Imperial News Conference Since 1975</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TOK9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Reporters bowed in respect as <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Emperor
Akihito broke with imperial tradition <DATE>Friday</DATE> and held the throne's
first televised news conference since <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   Akihito, seated beside <LOCATION>Empress Michiko</LOCATION>, began the news
conference by expressing gratitude to 10,000 people who attended
the state funeral and the hundreds of thousands who lined the
streets after his father, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, died in <DATE>January</DATE> at 87.
   ``What I felt while I was in personal contact with Emperor Showa
gives me, I think, an important guideline in what an emperor should
be,'' said <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, referring to <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s posthumous name.
   Hirohito's 62-year reign _ the longest in Japanese history _
covered <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s disastrous war in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and its subsequent rise to
an economic superpower.
   Because of the constitution's strict ban on his exercising
political powers, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> could not comment on the crisis facing
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s governing conservatives, plagued by money and sex scandals.
   He said he would be willing to visit <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> _ two
victims of Japanese aggression _ if the government decided it was
appropriate. He said the same for <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s southernmost
prefecture, where many people remain bitter about the casualties
and destruction they bore in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military assault. Hirohito
never visited <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION> after the war.
   <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> said the Daijo-sai, an elaborate ascension rite with
strong Shinto significance, should be carried out in accordance
with the law. Many critics already argue that by its very nature it
violates the constitution's ban of state involvement in religious
affairs.
   In that mystical ceremony to be held next year, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is to
have his first communion with the gods and then be reborn divine.
Media reports have estimated it could cost as much as <MONEY>$70 million</MONEY>.
The government is studying how to conduct the rite.
   Reporters representing 43 Japanese and 12 foreign news
organizations attended the news conference. Journalists were given
a detailed explanation of when to rise and bow, and who would sit
where in the palace's Stone Bridge Room, a large hall with Japanese
sliding paper doors and Western-style red carpeting.
   Sitting behind a low table draped with gold brocade cloth
embroidered with chrysanthemums, the imperial symbol, the royal
couple spoke slowly and distinctly. At times the empress, wearing a
light green dress, spoke so softly her voice was drowned out by the
clicking of cameras.
   Akihito also spoke in polite but common Japanese, unlike his
father, who often used archaic or stilted words no longer
understood by the general public.
   Akihito repeatedly stressed that his proper role is to uphold
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s postwar constitution, which limits his role to that of a
``symbolic'' figurehead.
   Four of the 12 main questions, all submitted weeks in advance
and subject to government approval, were about <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>. Along with
the main questions, several follow-ups were allowed, but by
pre-decided Japanese questioners.
   One Imperial Household Agency official requested the scheduled
time limit of 30 minutes be carefully observed, because traffic
restrictions had been set for streets on the imperial couple's way
home. The conference lasted 37 minutes.
   Akihito is the first emperor to ascend the throne under the
postwar constitution, which limits his role to mostly ceremonial
tasks. The previous constitution gave <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> nominal powers, and
the wartime government asserted it was acting in his name.
   The constitution also omits all references to the emperor's
special relationship with the gods of Shinto, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s indigenous
religion, which angers some conservatives.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s monarchy can trace its history to at least the <DATE>8th
century</DATE>, and by legend until the <DATE>6th century B.C.</DATE> and <PERSON>Emperor
Jimmu</PERSON>, who is said to have descended from the sun goddess,
<ORGANIZATION>Amaterasu</ORGANIZATION>.
   Michiko, rarely changing her expression of polite concentration,
said that because of her husband's heavy responsibilities she must
``make the home a place where he can...find peace and relaxation
with his family.''
   The royal couple split with the past by raising their two sons
and daughter by themselves. Akihito was raised by chamberlains from
age 3.
   Their eldest son, <PERSON>Crown Prince Naruhito</PERSON>, 29, is now seeking a
bride, and when asked about his growing independence, <PERSON>Michiko</PERSON> said,
``It would make me happy if he would come, even if only from time
to time, to play the viola for us.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900518-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-90 1021EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Nagasaki-Memorial     05-18 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nagasaki-Memorial,0346</SECOND>
<HEAD>Emperor Visits Bomb Memorial With Nagasaki Mayor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAGASAKI, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> today became the first
Japanese monarch to pay tribute at a monument to the 70,000 people
who died in the atomic bomb blast that devastated <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION> 45 years
ago.
   A steady rain fell as <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, accompanied by <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION>,
bowed deeply and placed a bouquet of white flowers on a dark
granite cenotaph before the monument.
   Mayor <PERSON>Hitoshi Motoshima</PERSON> led <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> to the site. <PERSON>Motoshima</PERSON> was
shot in the chest in <DATE>January</DATE> by an ultrarightist for saying the
late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> could have helped end World War II sooner and
spared <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> surrendered six days after the <DATE>Aug. 9, 1945</DATE> atomic bombing.
   Though <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, now known in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>Emperor Showa</LOCATION>, visited
<LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION> for a sporting event in <DATE>1969</DATE>, his son, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, is the
first emperor to present flowers at the Peace Park memorial.
   As the emperor left the park, some of the 2,600 people who
attended sang ``<PERSON>Kimi Ga Yo</PERSON>,'' <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s unofficial national anthem.
Shouts of ``Banzai,'' a wish for long life, rang out when his
20-car motorcade arrived.
   ``The emperor is from a new generation, my generation,'' said
<PERSON>Sachiko Nagata</PERSON>, a store clerk who was seven years old when the bomb
fell. ``I think he has helped heal some of the wounds of the war by
coming here.''
   Police mobilized 4,000 officers to provide security for the
emperor and empress during their four-day visit to the city on the
southern island of <LOCATION>Kyushu</LOCATION>.
   The Roman Catholic mayor drew the ire of rightist groups with
his remarks about <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>. Before being shot, <PERSON>Motoshima</PERSON> received
countless death threats and lost his membership in the governing
Liberal Democratic Party.
   Japanese rightists represent a small minority but maintain a
high profile, dressing in military garb and driving through cities
in convoys of armored, painted trucks blaring march music. They are
staunchly nationalist.
   They also revere the monarchy and chastise those they believe
oppose it.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901112-0030 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-12-90 0507EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-AkihitoProfile     11-12 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Akihito Profile,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Japanese Emperor A Product of Postwar Age</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Japan-Entronement, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has long lived in the shadow of his
father, the late <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON>, and the memories of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
headlong march into the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> War that <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s name evoked.
   But now that <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has assumed the throne left by his father's
death, many Japanese are looking to him as the symbol of a new age
- that of the generation who experienced war as children and
rebuilt the nation in peace.
   <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was 11 at the end of World War II, which Japanese
militarists had urged the nation into in the name of his father.
   The impact of surrender and reform under the guidance of
U.S.-led occupation forces deeply affected his youth.
   Before <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> turned 13, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> made his historic
renunciation of imperial divinity.
   Occupation troops departed <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1952</DATE>, leaving behind them a
democratic constitution that renounced war and defined <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
monarchs as ``symbols,'' not the priest-kings of bygone days.
   That imperial role seems to fit <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, who in one of his first
duties after assuming the throne upon the death of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> in
<DATE>January 1989</DATE> promised to uphold the constitution ``along with the
people.''
   Akihito, born <DATE>Dec. 23, 1933</DATE>, bears a strong physical resemblance
to <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, and has inherited his father's short, almost frail,
build. He also has his father's passion for science, and is a
respected scholar in the study of gobies, a type of mud-sucking
fish.
   Akihito speaks fluent English and is <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s most widely
traveled emperor. He has made official visits to 37 countries, his
first to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for the coronation of <ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   Reflecting the circumstances of his upbringing, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is often
described by former schoolmates and palace officials as a more
democratically-minded, warmer person than the quiet, reclusive
<PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>.
   He has also been far more prone to set his own precedents.
   Just three years after completing his education - <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was
the first emperor schooled alongside commoners - the royal heir
chose a commoner for his bride, making another break from the past.
   The woman, <PERSON>Michiko Shoda</PERSON>, was the daughter of one of the
nation's wealthiest businessmen, but their marriage in <DATE>1959</DATE> sent
shock waves through <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s former nobility.
   To the rest of the nation, however, the wedding was welcomed as
none before. About 500,000 people lined the streets for a chance to
see <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Michiko</LOCATION> in their horse-drawn carriage during a
parade after the ceremony.
   The royal couple again broke with tradition by raising their own
children, a decision prompted in part by <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s desire to have
the family life he was denied as a child, according to <PERSON>Minoru
Hamao</PERSON>, a former imperial chamberlain.
   Taken away from his parents at an early age to be raised by
strangers, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> at times complained of the loneliness he felt
when his classmates would talk to him about their homes, said
<PERSON>Hamao</PERSON>, who served <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> for two decades.
   Akihito's first child and heir, <PERSON>Crown Prince Naruhito</PERSON>, was born
<DATE>Feb. 23, 1960</DATE>. They have another son, <PERSON>Prince Akishino</PERSON>, and
daughter, <ORGANIZATION>Princess Nori</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though the crown prince remains single, Prince <PERSON>Akishino</PERSON> earlier
this year wed <PERSON>Kiko Kawashima</PERSON> - who, like the empress, had no royal
lineage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900517-0104 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-90 1233EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Emperor     05-17 0460</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Emperor,0473</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nothing Left to Chance When Emperor Leaves Palace</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NAGASAKI, Japan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the emperor of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> leaves his
palace in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, nothing is left to chance.
   Determined to eliminate the element of surprise, officials in
this scenic coastal city on the southern island of <LOCATION>Kyushu</LOCATION> have
slaved for months over preparations for the arrival <DATE>Friday</DATE> of
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION>.
   Officials are particularly nervous because the emperor is to
meet Mayor <PERSON>Hitoshi Motoshima</PERSON>, who was shot in the back by a
rightist in <DATE>January</DATE>. The attacker was angry at <LOCATION>Motoshima</LOCATION> for saying
the late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s father, bore some
responsibility for World War II.
   About 4,000 police officers were being mobilized to ensure the
monarch's safety.
   Highlighting the emperor's four-day stay will be a visit to an
atomic bomb memorial at <LOCATION>Peace Park</LOCATION>, and the 41st annual <ORGANIZATION>Arbor Day
Festival</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The emperor, who is to plant a tree and give a short address, is
scheduled to spend less than an hour at the festival, but officials
reportedly are spending <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> to deodorize a nearby pig farm.
   They also are planning to hang a curtain to keep the farm out of
the royal couple's sight, and have told media hoping to cover the
event by helicopter not to create any ruckus that might disturb the
animals.
   ``Sure, if the wind is right it could smell pretty bad at the
festival,'' said <PERSON>Yoichi Tanaka</PERSON>, head of general affairs for the
<ORGANIZATION>Nagasaki Prefectural Trade Union</ORGANIZATION>. ``But it's a pig farm, after all,
and there really isn't any need to try to hide that.''
   The strengthened police presence prompted a local newspaper, the
<ORGANIZATION>Nagasaki Shimbun</ORGANIZATION>, to complain in an editorial <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that
``excessive security'' could dampen ``the <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION> people's natural
desire to welcome their emperor.''
   The editorial, however, acknowledged the need for tight security
wherever the emperor goes. Leftist radicals strongly oppose the
monarchy and often have used violence to gain publicity for their
views.
   The same month that <PERSON>Motoshima</PERSON> was shot, leftists claimed
responsibility for firing projectiles that slightly damaged the
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> home of the emperor's younger brother, <ORGANIZATION>Prince Hitachi</ORGANIZATION>.
   Public opinion polls indicate the overwhelming majority of
Japanese support the monarchy, but there also are painful memories
of World War II, when the emperor's name was used to inspire
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s troops.
   After the war, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, whom the Japanese now call Emperor
Showa, visited all of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s prefectures except <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION>, a string
of southern islands where some of the war's bloodiest battles were
fought and where ill feelings toward <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> still linger.
   Radicals broke through security and hurled firebombs at <LOCATION>Akihito</LOCATION>
and <PERSON>Michiko</PERSON> when they visited <LOCATION>Okinawa</LOCATION> in <DATE>1975</DATE>. Akihito, then crown
prince, and his wife narrowly escaped injury.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901110-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-10-90 1226EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-AkihitoProfile     11-10 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Akihito Profile,0611</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Japanese Emperor Is Product of Postwar Age</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Japan-Entronement</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has long lived in the shadow of his
father, the late <PERSON>Emperor Hirohito</PERSON>, and the memories of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
headlong march into the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> War that <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s name evoked.
   But as <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> officially inherits the throne left by
his father's death, many Japanese are looking to him as the symbol
of a new age - that of the generation who experienced war as
children and rebuilt the nation in peace.
   <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was 11 years old at the end of World War II, during
which Japanese militarists urged the nation to battle in the name
of his father. The impact of surrender and reform under the
guidance of U.S.-led occupation forces deeply affected his youth.
   Before <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> turned 13, <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> made his historic
renunciation of imperial divinity.
   The occupation troops left <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> after seven years in <DATE>1952</DATE> and
left behind them a democratic constitution that renounced war and
defined <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s monarchs as ``symbols,'' not the priest-kings of
bygone days.
   That imperial role seems to fit <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, who in one of his first
duties after assuming the throne upon the death of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> in
<DATE>January 1989</DATE> promised to uphold the constitution ``along with the
people.''
   ``Most grieved by his late majesty's passing, I have succeeded
to the imperial throne in accordance with the constitution of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,'' he said. ``Shrouded in sorrow and overwhelmed by the
responsibilities I undertake, I stand humble before you.''
   Akihito, born on <DATE>Dec. 23, 1933</DATE>, bears a strong physical
resemblance to <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, and has inherited his father's short,
almost frail, build. He also has his father's passion for science,
and is a respected scholar in the study of gobies, a type of
mud-sucking fish.
   Akihito speaks fluent English and is <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s most widely
traveled emperor. He hasa made official visits to 37 countries, his
first to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> for the coronation of <ORGANIZATION>Queen Elizabeth II</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1953</DATE>.
   Reflecting the circumstances of his upbringing, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is often
described by former schoolmates and palace officials as a more
democratic, warmer person than the quiet, reclusive <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>.
   He has also been far more prone to set his own precedents.
   Just three years after completing his education - <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> was
the first emperor schooled alongside commoners - the royal heir
chose a commoner for his bride, making another break from the past.
   The woman, <PERSON>Michiko Shoda</PERSON>, was the daughter of one of the
nation's wealthiest businessmen, but their marriage in <DATE>1959</DATE> sent
shock waves through <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s former nobility.
   To the rest of the nation, however, the wedding was welcomed as
none before. About 500,000 people lined the streets for a chance to
see <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Michiko</LOCATION> in their horse-drawn carriage during a
parade after the ceremony.
   The royal couple again broke with tradition by raising their own
children, a decision prompted in part by <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s desire to have
the family life he was denied as a child, according to <PERSON>Minoru
Hamao</PERSON>, a former imperial chamberlain.
   Taken away from his parents at an early age to be raised by
strangers, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> at times complained of the loneliness he felt
when his classmates would talk to him about their homes, said
<PERSON>Hamao</PERSON>, who served <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> for two decades.
   Akihito's first child and heir, <PERSON>Crown Prince Naruhito</PERSON>, was born
<DATE>Feb. 23, 1960</DATE>. They have another son, <PERSON>Prince Akishino</PERSON>, and
daughter, <ORGANIZATION>Princess Nori</ORGANIZATION>.
   Though the crown prince remains single, Prince <PERSON>Akishino</PERSON> earlier
this year wed <PERSON>Kiko Kawashima</PERSON> - who, like the empress, had no royal
lineage.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010989-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 3361 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 9, 1989, Monday, Late Final Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 2; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
217 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AKIHITO PLEDGES TO SAFEGUARD JAPAN CONSTITUTION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AP 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TOKYO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s new emperor said today he will help safeguard the democratic 
constitution, and leftist politicians urged vigilance against any government 
effort to use the monarchy for "reactionary" ends. 
</P>
<P>
One Communist and five Socialist legislators boycotted the ceremony at which 
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> pledged himself to the constitution imposed by the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> after World War II, but two Socialists did attend. 
</P>
<P>
Those who stayed away said the monarchy's close links to the Shinto religion 
violate the constitutional separation of state and religion. They were invited 
in their capacities as chairmen of parliamentary committees. 
</P>
<P>
Outside the <ORGANIZATION>Imperial Palace</ORGANIZATION>, nearly 315,000 mourners signed registers of 
condolence for Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died of cancer last week at age 87. His 
62-year reign was marked by the rise of militarism, defeat in the war and 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s emergence as a leading economic power. 
</P>
<P>
Akihito, 55, is expected to be closer to the people than his father, who was 
thought a living god until he renounced the concept of imperial divinity after 
World War II. 
</P>
<P>
In his first speech as emperor, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> said he would continue on <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s 
path, "making his desire to constantly be at one with the people my desire as 
well, joining together with you to preserve the constitution of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Taking over -- New Japanese Emperor Akihito, with black-clad Empress 
Michiko, delivers first official statement to government delegates, pledging to 
work for peace and unity. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901122-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-22-90 1959EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Japan-Enthronement     11-22 0488</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Enthronement,0588</SECOND>
<HEAD>Protests, Violence Marks Final Enthronement Ceremony</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> completed a centuries-old
ceremony signifying his accession to the world's oldest hereditary
throne while protests were held against the monarchy and the high
cost of the rite.
   The Shinto ceremony, symbolizing communion with the sun goddess,
has been performed by most of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s emperors since at least the
<DATE>7th century</DATE>, and in the past was believed to give monarchs their
status as living god.
   But demonstrators across the country criticized the ritual as a
violation of the Japanese constitution's separation of church and
state and questioned the use of nearly <MONEY>$17 million</MONEY> in tax money on
the ceremony.
   Other critics of the Daijosai, or <ORGANIZATION>Great Food Offering Ritual</ORGANIZATION>,
also believe holding it indicates a desire within <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s
conservative government to bring back the emperor worship of prewar
days.
   The rite, witnessed by only two female attendants, was held
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and then repeated before dawn <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Anti-monarchy radicals marked the beginning of the ceremony by
launching six mortar-like projectiles at an imperial villa in
<LOCATION>Kyoto</LOCATION>, in western <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, police said.
   Radicals were also believed to have set fires at three Shinto
shrines and four train stations outside of the capital of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>
just after <TIME>midnight</TIME>. No injuries were reported.
   Separate peaceful protests were staged by scholars and labor
unionists, and 1,000 Christians fasted to protest the funding of
the rite.
   Akihito, 56, is the first Japanese emperor to be enthroned since
his father, the late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, assumed the Chrysanthemum
Throne 62 years ago.
   He is also the first to assume the throne under <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s postwar
constitution, which calls him not a god-king but a symbol of his
people's sovereignty.
   Akihito's formal state enthronement ceremony <DATE>Nov. 12</DATE> was viewed
by foreign dignitaries representing 158 countries, but no
foreigners were invited to the communion.
   During the rite, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> offered rice, wine and other foods from
around the country to the sun goddess <ORGANIZATION>Amaterasu</ORGANIZATION>, from whom legend
says the imperial line descended.
   The two women attendants are clad in white and red kimono and
with their hair tied in pony tails nearly 6{ feet long. The
ceremony is held in the torch-lit inner sanctuary of a specially
built hall on the palace grounds.
   The rite is performed only once by each emperor.
   Inside the sanctuary, out of view of the 733 Japanese guests
seated in large tents nearby, the offerings were made to an altar
placed beside a stylized bed, from which the goddess is summoned.
   Scholars before World War II theorized that at one time the
ceremony might have involved the emperor symbolically having sex
with the sun goddess, representing a union with the divine. Palace
officials, however, deny that theory and said the emperor would not
touch the bed.
   The second ceremony was repeated after <TIME>midnight</TIME> in an identical
hall yards from the first one.
   Akihito performs dozens of religious ceremonies at the palace
each year, carrying on the priest-king role that has been handed
down from ancient times.
   That role, however, has periodically come under fire since the
end of World War II.
   <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died in <DATE>1989</DATE> at age 87, renounced the concept of
imperial divinity in <DATE>1946</DATE> at the urging of the U.S.-led occupation
forces. The country's post-war constitution specifies that the
emperor is a national symbol, and not a god-king.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-7281 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas059_a_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-059 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   ROK's Kim, Delegation Conclude Meetings, Visit </TI></H3>
<H4>   Emperor's Visit Request REnewed </H4>
<F P=102> OW2603052794 Tokyo KYODO in English 0507 GMT 26 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2603052794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 26</DATE> KYODO -- South Korean President <PERSON>Kim 
Yong-sam</PERSON> renewed his hope <DATE>Saturday</DATE> [26 <DATE>March</DATE>] for the visit to 
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> and <PERSON>Empress Michiko</PERSON>, a senior 
<ORGANIZATION>Imperial Household Agency</ORGANIZATION> official said. Kim, before departing 
for <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> after a three-day visit to <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, extended the 
invitation again to the imperial couple as they bid farewell to 
<PERSON>Kim</PERSON> and his wife Son Myong-sun at the <ORGANIZATION>Akasaka Palace</ORGANIZATION>, said 
<PERSON>Kiyoshi Sumiya</PERSON>, the agency's grand master of ceremonies. 
  Kim told the couple during the 20-minute meeting that he 
wishes to invite them to visit <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> at a proper time. 
  During an audience at the imperial palace on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the 
president officially invited <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> and Empress Michiko 
to visit <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> to forge a new future-oriented 
relationship. At that time, the emperor replied the Japanese 
Government would decide on whether he will go to <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>. 
  The visit by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s monarch, however, is still a sensitive 
issue in <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, which was under Japanese colonial rule 
from <DATE>1910</DATE> to <DATE>1945</DATE>. 
  During his stay in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> urged <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to work together 
to 
solve <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>'s suspected nuclear weapons development 
program, which has heightened tension on the Korean peninsula, 
and stressed the importance of forward-looking bilateral 
relations. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900526-0052 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-26-90 0910EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Korea 1stLd-Writethru   05-26 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Korea, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0481,0658</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede TOKYO</HEAD>
<HEAD>Roh Invites Japanese Emperor To Make First Visit to Korea</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto TOK3</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 10 grafs to UPDATE with Roh returning home,
clarifies Akihito, Kaifu comment, changes byline. Pickup 8th graf
pvs, `About 20,000...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL SHIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SEOUL, South Korea (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> Tae-woo <DATE>today</DATE> said ``no
amount of apology can be fully satisfactory'' for <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s brutal
colonization of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, but that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s expressions of regret are
the basis for a new relationship.
   Roh returned today from a three-day trip to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, during which
he invited Emperor Akihito to make the first Japanese imperial
visit to <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>.
   The invitation came after <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> expressed regret for the
colonization of <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> nearly half a century ago, and Japanese Prime
Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON> extended ``honest apologies'' for Korean
suffering in the colonial period.
   Roh, upon his arrival in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, said it was time for the two
countries to put the past behind them.
   ``Even if we may feel that the Japanese apologies do not fully
live up to our expectations, we should accept them with magnanimity
and generosity, now that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has forthrightly admitted its
mistakes,'' he said at an airport news conference.
   During the colonial period, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> tried to stifle Korean culture
by banning Koreans from learning their language and forcing them to
adoptJapanese names. Tens of thousands of <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION> were killed after
being drafted for the Japanese war efforts.
   ``I well understand what feelings my fellow countrymen have
about what went on between our country and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in the past. No
amount of apology can be fully satisfactory,'' <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> said.
   Some <PERSON>Koreans</PERSON> said Japanese measures to clear up current sore
points were more important than apologizing for the past.
   There are unresolved disputes over discrimination against
<LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION> living in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, aid to <LOCATION>Koreans</LOCATION> who remain displaced after
being forcibly removed from their homeland to perform wartime labor
for <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and assistance to Korean survivors of the atomic
bombings of <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nagasaki</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> said he had asked <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to move forward on these issues and
   About 20,000 police had been mobilized in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> to provide
security for <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> during his three-day state visit against possible
threats from extreme leftist or rightist groups. But no incidents
were reported.
   Roh's visit to <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> was only the second by a South Korean head
in <DATE>1965</DATE>. Roh's predecessor, <PERSON>Chun Doo-hwan</PERSON>, visited <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> have a long history of enmity and sore points
still linger from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 1910-45 colonization of the <LOCATION>Korean
Peninsula</LOCATION>.
   The centerpiece of <PERSON>Roh</PERSON>'s visit was the <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> state
banquet at which <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> expressed his ``deepest regret'' for the
suffering Koreans endured at Japanese hands. Kaifu offered his
``sincere remorse and honest apologies,'' and said good relations
between <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> are a basis for peace in the region.
   Roh extended the invitation to <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> to
visit <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> during a short meeting with the emperor today at
the <ORGANIZATION>Akasaka State Guesthouse</ORGANIZATION>, said a palace official, who spoke on
condition of anonymity.
   ``After your coronation I am sure that you will visit many
countries, and I hope that you will consider visiting <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>
also,'' the official quoted <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> as saying.
   Akihito, who assumed the throne after the death of his father,
Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, will not travel abroad until after his official
coronation on <DATE>Nov. 12</DATE>. The coronation is traditionally delayed by a
year of mourning for the deceased emperor.
   Akihito would be the first emperor to visit <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> since
its creation after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s defeat in World War II.
   Japanese <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Taizo Watanabe</PERSON> said <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON>
had also accepted an invitation from <PERSON>Roh</PERSON> to visit <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION> at a
mutually convenient time.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901202-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-02-90 1143EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Radicals     12-02 0171</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Radicals,0176</SECOND>
<HEAD>Man Throws Smoke Bomb At Emperor's Motorcade</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two people threw a smoke bomb and a firecracker at
Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s motorcade <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as it headed for the Imperial
Palace in Kyoto after another of the rites of Akihitio's
enthronement, police said.
   A bystander suffered an eye injury as the firecracker landed
among people watching the motorcade pass, said an official of the
Kyoto state police.
   The man and woman, who were arrested immediately, did not
respond to police investigators' questions, the official said.
   He said they might be connected with radical leftists who
declared in leaflets last <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that they would ``completely
crush'' the royal couple's visit to Kyoto and nearby <LOCATION>Nara</LOCATION>.
   Leftist groups oppose the monarchy and say <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s emperor
system is a symbol of militarism.
   The smoke bomb landed in the road, pouring out smoke a minute
before the car carrying Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> reached
the spot, the official said. The car slowed, but <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> might not
have noticed the incident, he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901109-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-09-90 0013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-Enthronement     11-09 0938</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Enthronement,1152</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan To Enthrone First `Symbolic' Emperor</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor Akihito formally assumes the world's oldest
hereditary throne <DATE>Monday</DATE> in lavish ceremonies that also may be an
important rite of passage for postwar <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   No other monarch has ascended the <ORGANIZATION>Chrysanthemum Throne</ORGANIZATION> under the
constitution enacted in <DATE>1946</DATE>.
   For the first time, a Japanese emperor is to be enthroned as
merely a national symbol, as stipulated by the constitution imposed
by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> occupation after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s surrender in World War II.
   Most Japanese appear comfortable with the largely ceremonial
role of their new emperor, a remarkable break with the past. The
late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s father, was enthroned as a living
god and was the object of fanatical devotion.
   Even the official name the government has given <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s reign
- Achieving Peace - reflects a desire to move away from the
turbulent times of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died of cancer early last year.
   The monarchy dates to the 6th or 7th century, but the Japanese
public associates it most closely with <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s 60-year reign. In
that period, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> waged expansionist wars in the name of the
emperor, suffered a crushing defeat and foreign occupation, then
rose to become an economic superpower.
   Akihito, 56, became emperor immediately after his father's
death, but his formal enthronement awaited a year of mourning and
the growing of ``sacred'' rice for a coronation rite.
   During the interval, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has tried to create a softer, more
open image for the often aloof royal family, insisting on fewer
uniformed police along his procession routes and addressing people
with the title ``san,'' a term of respect similar to <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mrs.</PERSON> in
English.
   Reflecting the different times in which they were raised,
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is believed to be more democratic in thinking than his
father, and has pledged to ``protect the constitution along with
the people.''
   Empress Michiko, the first commoner to marry a future Japanese
monarch, is crafting her own quiet revolution inside the royal
household, in large part by providing <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> with a family life
similar to that of ``common'' Japanese.
   She broke tradition, for example, by making clear that her
children would not be taken away and raised by strangers.
   Although the palace remains distant to most Japanese, opinion
polls indicate it has wide public support. Few, however, still see
their monarch as a god.
   Government officials say they have taken pains to adapt the
enthronement ceremonies to a more democratic age. They also have
hewn closely to prewar precedent for the nearly month-long rites,
however, creating widespread concern that the ``new era'' might
actually represent a step backward in time.
   Royalty, heads of state and other dignitaries from more than 150
nations will be in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> when <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> announces his accession on
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The main coronation ceremony will be at the imperial palace, an
oasis of greenery in cetral <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> built in the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>
on the site of a former samurai castle.
   Akihito will ascend a 20-foot-tall throne on a three-layered
dais of black lacquer, beneath an octagonal roof adorned with
golden mirrors and phoenixes.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON> will stand before the throne as
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, in a reddish-brown kimono with a design of paulownia
trees, bamboo and mythical animals, reads an address announcing his
accession.
   Kaifu will lead the Japanese among the 2,500 guests in three
rounds of ``Banzai!'' - a traditional cheer for long life - to
conclude the 30-minute ceremony.
   Officials say <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will read his announcement in colloquial
Japanese, unlike <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s use of stilted classical language most
Japanese cannot understand.
   To reflect the postwar constitution's emphasis on popular
sovereignty, <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> will lead the banzai cheers from a point level
with the throne instead of descending several steps, as his
predecessors did.
   An official in the prime minister's office told reporters a
military salute coinciding with the enthronement would be reduced
from 100 to 21 cannon shots because ``that's the way foreign
dignitaries are received.''
   Aside from such cosmetic adjustments, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s coronation is
expected to be much like those held since his great-grandfather
assumed the throne in the middle of the <DATE>last century</DATE>.
   In what many critics of the government see as a snub to the
constitution, about <MONEY>2.5 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$17 million</MONEY>) in public money
will be spent on a rite steeped in <LOCATION>Shinto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s state religion
until <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   In that rite, to begin 10 days after the main coronation
ceremony, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will step back into the world of myth for a
``communion'' of fresh rice with the sun goddess, from whom the
imperial line is said to have descended, and all the gods of heaven
and earth.
   Opponents say public funding violates the constitutional
separation of church and state. The <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> administration argues
that the money is not being used to promote religion, but to
preserve an important cultural tradition.
   Critics emphasize that the rite has undergone major changes
during its 1,200 years of existence. It was ignored for more than
200 years, beginning in the <DATE>late 15th century</DATE>.
   In response to questions about whether holding the Daijosai, or
<ORGANIZATION>Great Food Offering Ritual</ORGANIZATION>, is intended to restore living-god
status to <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and future emperors, <PERSON>Nobuo Ishihara</PERSON>, the deputy
cabinet secretary, replied:
   ``I am aware that there were some scholars in the prewar period
who claimed that, through performance of the Daijosai, the emperor
assumed a divine nature. However, the government is not in a
position to make any comment as to whether the emperor does or does
not.''
   Police have begun <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest security operation, mainly
because ultra-leftist radical groups have said they will disrupt
the ceremonies. A bomb believed planted by radicals exploded last
week at a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police dormitory, killing one officer and wounding
six other people.
   Late last month, 26,000 <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police officers were mobilized for
security in the capital, and at least 6,000 more have been brought
in since. Nearly <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of the total coronation budget of <MONEY>12.3
billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$94.6 million</MONEY>) is being spent on security.
   A high-ranking <ORGANIZATION>National Police Agency</ORGANIZATION> official, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said the extraordinary security was
justified because leftist radicals ``are planning to attack the
palace with explosive rockets.''
   He said police believe one group has devised mortar-like weapons
with a range of nearly four miles.
   Along with protecting the many visiting dignitaries, including
Prince Charles of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and Vice Presidnt <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, the police
are concerned about security for a parade after the coronation.
   Akihito and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> are to ride in a convertible in the
30-minute procession from the imperial palace to the royal
residence at <ORGANIZATION>Akasaka Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   Officials say about 10,000 officers will line the three-mile
route.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901106-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-06-90 1324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-Japan-Enthronement Adv09   11-06 0949</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Japan-Enthronement, Adv09,1167</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv09</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Friday AMs, Nov. 9, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Japan To Enthrone First `Symbolic' Emperor</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ERIC TALMADGE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor Akihito formally assumes the world's oldest
hereditary throne <DATE>Monday</DATE> in lavish ceremonies that also may be an
important rite of passage for postwar <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   No other monarch has ascended the <ORGANIZATION>Chrysanthemum Throne</ORGANIZATION> under the
constitution enacted in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   For the first time, a Japanese emperor is to be enthroned as
merely a national symbol, as stipulated by the constitution imposed
by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> occupation after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s surrender in World War II.
   Most Japanese appear comfortable with the largely ceremonial
role of their new emperor, a remarkable break with the past. The
late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s father, was enthroned as a living
god and was the object of fanatical devotion.
   Even the official name the government has given <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s reign
- Achieving Peace - reflects a desire to move away from the
turbulent times of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died of cancer early last year.
   The monarchy dates to the 6th or 7th century, but the Japanese
public associates it most closely with <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s 60-year reign. In
that period, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> waged expansionist wars in the name of the
emperor, suffered a crushing defeat and foreign occupation, then
rose to become an economic superpower.
   Akihito, 56, became emperor immediately after his father's
death, but his formal enthronement awaited a year of mourning and
the growing of ``sacred'' rice for a coronation rite.
   During the interval, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has tried to create a softer, more
open image for the often aloof royal family, insisting on fewer
uniformed police along his procession routes and addressing people
with the title ``san,'' a term of respect similar to <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mrs.</PERSON> in
English.
   Reflecting the different times in which they were raised,
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is believed to be more democratic in thinking than his
father, and has pledged to ``protect the constitution along with
the people.''
   Empress Michiko, the first commoner to marry a future Japanese
monarch, is crafting her own quiet revolution inside the royal
household, in large part by providing <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> with a family life
similar to that of ``common'' Japanese.
   She broke tradition, for example, by making clear that her
children would not be taken away and raised by strangers.
   Although the palace remains distant to most Japanese, opinion
polls indicate it has wide public support. Few, however, still see
their monarch as a god.
   Government officials say they have taken pains to adapt the
enthronement ceremonies to a more democratic age. They also have
hewn closely to prewar precedent for the nearly month-long rites,
however, creating widespread concern that the ``new era'' might
actually represent a step backward in time.
   Royalty, heads of state and other dignitaries from more than 150
nations will be in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> when <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> announces his accession on
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The main coronation ceremony will be at the imperial palace, an
oasis of greenery in central <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> built in the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>
on the site of a former samurai castle.
   Akihito will ascend a 20-foot-tall throne on a three-layered
dais of black lacquer, beneath an octagonal roof adorned with
golden mirrors and phoenixes.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON> will stand before the throne as
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, in a reddish-brown kimono with a design of paulownia
trees, bamboo and mythical animals, reads an address announcing his
accession.
   Kaifu will lead the Japanese among the 2,500 guests in three
rounds of ``Banzai!'' - a traditional cheer for long life - to
conclude the 30-minute ceremony.
   Officials say <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will read his announcement in colloquial
Japanese, unlike <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s use of stilted classical language most
Japanese cannot understand.
   To reflect the postwar constitution's emphasis on popular
sovereignty, <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> will lead the banzai cheers from a point level
with the throne instead of descending several steps, as his
predecessors did.
   An official in the prime minister's office told reporters a
military salute coinciding with the enthronement would be reduced
from 100 to 21 cannon shots because ``that's the way foreign
dignitaries are received.''
   Aside from such cosmetic adjustments, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s coronation is
expected to be much like those held since his great-grandfather
assumed the throne in the middle of the <DATE>last century</DATE>.
   In what many critics of the government see as a snub to the
constitution, about <MONEY>2.5 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$17 million</MONEY>) in public money
will be spent on a rite steeped in <LOCATION>Shinto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s state religion
until <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   In that rite, to begin 10 days after the main coronation
ceremony, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will step back into the world of myth for a
``communion'' of fresh rice with the sun goddess, from whom the
imperial line is said to have descended, and all the gods of heaven
and earth.
   Opponents say public funding violates the constitutional
separation of church and state. The <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> administration argues
that the money is not being used to promote religion, but to
preserve an important cultural tradition.
   Critics emphasize that the rite has undergone major changes
during its 1,200 years of existence. It was ignored for more than
200 years, beginning in the <DATE>late 15th century</DATE>.
   In response to questions about whether holding the Daijosai, or
<ORGANIZATION>Great Food Offering Ritual</ORGANIZATION>, is intended to restore living-god
status to <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and future emperors, <PERSON>Nobuo Ishihara</PERSON>, the deputy
cabinet secretary, replied:
   ``I am aware that there were some scholars in the prewar period
who claimed that, through performance of the Daijosai, the emperor
assumed a divine nature. However, the government is not in a
position to make any comment as to whether the emperor does or does
not.''
   Police have begun <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest security operation, mainly
because ultra-leftist radical groups have said they will disrupt
the ceremonies. A bomb believed planted by radicals exploded last
week at a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police dormitory, killing one officer and wounding
six other people.
   Late last month, 26,000 <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police officers were mobilized for
security in the capital, and at least 6,000 more will be brought in
before the main ceremony. Nearly <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of the total coronation
budget of <MONEY>12.3 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$94.6 million</MONEY>) is being spent on
security.
   A high-ranking <ORGANIZATION>National Police Agency</ORGANIZATION> official, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said the extraordinary security was
justified because leftist radicals ``are planning to attack the
palace with explosive rockets.''
   He said police believe one group has devised mortar-like weapons
with a range of nearly four miles.
   Along with protecting the many visiting dignitaries, including
Prince Charles of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, the police
are concerned about security for a parade after the coronation.
   Akihito and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> are to ride in a convertible in the
30-minute procession from the imperial palace to the royal
residence at <ORGANIZATION>Akasaka Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   Oficials say about 7,000 officers will line the three-mile
route.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Friday AMs, Nov. 9</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Emperor Akihito formally assumes the world's oldest
hereditary throne <DATE>Monday</DATE> in lavish ceremonies that also may be an
important rite of passage for postwar <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   No other monarch has ascended the <ORGANIZATION>Chrysanthemum Throne</ORGANIZATION> under the
constitution enacted in <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   For the first time, a Japanese emperor is to be enthroned as
merely a national symbol, as stipulated by the constitution imposed
by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> occupation after <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s surrender in World War II.
   Most Japanese appear comfortable with the largely ceremonial
role of their new emperor, a remarkable break with the past. The
late Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s father, was enthroned as a living
god and was the object of fanatical devotion.
   Even the official name the government has given <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s reign
- Achieving Peace - reflects a desire to move away from the
turbulent times of <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>, who died of cancer early last year.
   The monarchy dates to the 6th or 7th century, but the Japanese
public associates it most closely with <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s 60-year reign. In
that period, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> waged expansionist wars in the name of the
emperor, suffered a crushing defeat and foreign occupation, then
rose to become an economic superpower.
   Akihito, 56, became emperor immediately after his father's
death, but his formal enthronement awaited a year of mourning and
the growing of ``sacred'' rice for a coronation rite.
   During the interval, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> has tried to create a softer, more
open image for the often aloof royal family, insisting on fewer
uniformed police along his procession routes and addressing people
with the title ``san,'' a term of respect similar to <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> or <PERSON>Mrs.</PERSON> in
English.
   Reflecting the different times in which they were raised,
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> is believed to be more democratic in thinking than his
father, and has pledged to ``protect the constitution along with
the people.''
   Empress Michiko, the first commoner to marry a future Japanese
monarch, is crafting her own quiet revolution inside the royal
household, in large part by providing <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> with a family life
similar to that of ``common'' Japanese.
   She broke tradition, for example, by making clear that her
children would not be taken away and raised by strangers.
   Although the palace remains distant to most Japanese, opinion
polls indicate it has wide public support. Few, however, still see
their monarch as a god.
   Government officials say they have taken pains to adapt the
enthronement ceremonies to a more democratic age. They also have
hewn closely to prewar precedent for the nearly month-long rites,
however, creating widespread concern that the ``new era'' might
actually represent a step backward in time.
   Royalty, heads of state and other dignitaries from more than 150
nations will be in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> when <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> announces his accession on
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The main coronation ceremony will be at the imperial palace, an
oasis of greenery in central <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> built in the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>
on the site of a former samurai castle.
   Akihito will ascend a 20-foot-tall throne on a three-layered
dais of black lacquer, beneath an octagonal roof adorned with
golden mirrors and phoenixes.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON> will stand before the throne as
<PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>, in a reddish-brown kimono with a design of paulownia
trees, bamboo and mythical animals, reads an address announcing his
accession.
   Kaifu will lead the Japanese among the 2,500 guests in three
rounds of ``Banzai!'' - a traditional cheer for long life - to
conclude the 30-minute ceremony.
   Officials say <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will read his announcement in colloquial
Japanese, unlike <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON>'s use of stilted classical language most
Japanese cannot understand.
   To reflect the postwar constitution's emphasis on popular
sovereignty, <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> will lead the banzai cheers from a point level
with the throne instead of descending several steps, as his
predecessors did.
   An official in the prime minister's office told reporters a
military salute coinciding with the enthronement would be reduced
from 100 to 21 cannon shots because ``that's the way foreign
dignitaries are received.''
   Aside from such cosmetic adjustments, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON>'s coronation is
expected to be much like those held since his great-grandfather
assumed the throne in the middle of the <DATE>last century</DATE>.
   In what many critics of the government see as a snub to the
constitution, about <MONEY>2.5 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$17 million</MONEY>) in public money
will be spent on a rite steeped in <LOCATION>Shinto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s state religion
until <DATE>1945</DATE>.
   In that rite, to begin 10 days after the main coronation
ceremony, <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> will step back into the world of myth for a
``communion'' of fresh rice with the sun goddess, from whom the
imperial line is said to have descended, and all the gods of heaven
and earth.
   Opponents say public funding violates the constitutional
separation of church and state. The <PERSON>Kaifu</PERSON> administration argues
that the money is not being used to promote religion, but to
preserve an important cultural tradition.
   Critics emphasize that the rite has undergone major changes
during its 1,200 years of existence. It was ignored for more than
200 years, beginning in the <DATE>late 15th century</DATE>.
   In response to questions about whether holding the Daijosai, or
<ORGANIZATION>Great Food Offering Ritual</ORGANIZATION>, is intended to restore living-god
status to <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and future emperors, <PERSON>Nobuo Ishihara</PERSON>, the deputy
cabinet secretary, replied:
   ``I am aware that there were some scholars in the prewar period
who claimed that, through performance of the Daijosai, the emperor
assumed a divine nature. However, the government is not in a
position to make any comment as to whether the emperor does or does
not.''
   Police have begun <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s largest security operation, mainly
because ultra-leftist radical groups have said they will disrupt
the ceremonies. A bomb believed planted by radicals exploded last
week at a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police dormitory, killing one officer and wounding
six other people.
   Late last month, 26,000 <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> police officers were mobilized for
security in the capital, and at least 6,000 more will be brought in
before the main ceremony. Nearly <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> of the total coronation
budget of <MONEY>12.3 billion yen</MONEY> (<MONEY>$94.6 million</MONEY>) is being spent on
security.
   A high-ranking <ORGANIZATION>National Police Agency</ORGANIZATION> official, speaking on
condition of anonymity, said the extraordinary security was
justified because leftist radicals ``are planning to attack the
palace with explosive rockets.''
   He said police believe one group has devised mortar-like weapons
with a range of nearly four miles.
   Along with protecting the many visiting dignitaries, including
Prince Charles of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, the police
are concerned about security for a parade after the coronation.
   Akihito and <ORGANIZATION>Empress Michiko</ORGANIZATION> are to ride in a convertible in the
30-minute procession from the imperial palace to the royal
residence at <ORGANIZATION>Akasaka Palace</ORGANIZATION>.
   Oficials say about 7,000 officers will line the three-mile
route.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54039 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas101_a_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-101 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Reaction to Resumption of U.S. Framework Talks </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Reaction to Resumption of U.S. Framework Talks </PHRASE></F></HT>
<H4>    Ambassador Kuriyama Cited </H4>

<F P=102> OW2505115494 Tokyo KYODO in English 1133 GMT 25 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2505115494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 25</DATE> KYODO -- Japanese Ambassador to the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <PERSON>Takakazu Kuriyama</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [25 <DATE>May</DATE>] <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> 
needs to take steps to significantly reduce its current account 
surplus and implement a market-opening package to successfully 
conclude the trade framework talks with the <LOCATION>U.S. 
  Kuriyama</LOCATION>, who is currently in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to prepare for the 
upcoming <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> visit by <PERSON>Emperor Akihito</PERSON> and <PERSON>Empress Michiko</PERSON>, made 
the remarks at a press conference at the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  He said <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> agreed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to get the 
deadlocked framework talks back on track because both sides 
shared the view that it is undesirable to keep tense economic 
and trade relations "drifting" since that would hurt overall 
bilateral relations. 
  <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> also reached the accord because it 
deepened understanding about each other's positions on the trade 
negotiations, he said. 
  Kuriyama said the greatest problem regarding economic and 
trade relations between <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is that there is a 
lack of mutual trust. 
  <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> fears the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> will try to apply numerical targets to 
measure the openness of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s market and threaten sanctions if 
that target is not met, while the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mistrusts <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> as a 
country always vowing to do something and then not, he said. 
  Opinion polls in both countries also show that trust and 
respect toward each others' nations are waning, <PERSON>Kuriyama</PERSON> said, 
attributing the reason to the failure of the framework 
negotiations in <DATE>February</DATE>. 
  The trade framework talks is aimed at boosting mutual 
understanding, he said. 
  Kuriyama, who is in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> from <DATE>Monday</DATE> through <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, said 
he carried a message to Emperor Akihito from <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Bill 
Clinton</PERSON> welcoming the imperial visit to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
  Emperor <PERSON>Akihito</PERSON> and <PERSON>Empress Michiko</PERSON> are scheduled to visit 
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> from <DATE>June 10</DATE> to 25. 
  Touching on concerns abroad that <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> may come to possess 
nuclear weapons, <PERSON>Kuriyama</PERSON> said he tries to sweep away such 
concern by explaining <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s nonnuclear position and the 
Japanese people's feeling on the matter. 
  The ambassador said it is impossible for <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to possess 
nuclear weapons because an overwhelming majority of the people 
are against it and because <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is a member of the nuclear 
<ORGANIZATION>Nonproliferation Treaty</ORGANIZATION> (NPT) and, therefore, has an 
international obligation not to possess nuclear weapons. 
  Also, not a single country among <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s neighbors support 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> possessing nuclear weapons, he said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-54356 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas103_a_94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-103 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Cabinet Approves Itinerary for Emperor's U.S. Trip </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Cabinet Approves Itinerary for Emperor's U.S. Trip </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2705005894 Tokyo KYODO in English 0036 GMT 27 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2705005894 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 
