<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890915-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-15-89 2250EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HurricaneHugo 3rdLd-Writethru a0767 09-15 0396</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Hugo, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0767,0400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eastern Caribbean Prepares for Hurricane Hugo</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 6th graf, `At 9 p.m. ..., to UPDATE with 10:30 p.m. EDT
position, track</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRIAN MURPHY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After being brushed by several hurricanes this year,
the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands may get the brunt of Hurricane Hugo as
it churns westward with 150 mph winds, forecasters said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``It looks like this one is not going to miss the islands like
the others,'' said <PERSON>Jack Beven</PERSON>, a forecaster at the <ORGANIZATION>National
Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>. ``It's on the most
southerly course of any this year and that should keep it down in
the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> longer.''
   A hurricane warning was posted <DATE>Friday</DATE> from <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>British Virgin Islands</ORGANIZATION>, and a hurricane watch was issued for the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. A tropical storm watch was
issued for the islands of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION>.
   Rough seas have been reported around the islands since <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Forecasters described the force four hurricane as ``extremely
dangerous.'' Category five is the scale's highest rank.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME>, Hugo's center was near 14.9 north latitude and
56.6 west longitude, or about 340 miles east southeast of the French
resort island of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>. The storm was
moving west at 15 mph.
   With nothing in the atmosphere to divert it or sap its power,
Hugo was expected to remain on its westerly course and strengthen
somewhat during the next 24 hours, according to reports from an <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> reconnaissance plane.
   <PERSON>Beven</PERSON> said the center of the system could reach the <LOCATION>Leeward
Islands</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and may move toward <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> over the
weekend. Rainfall amounts of five to 10 inches is expected in the
path of the hurricane.
   Three other hurricanes this year _ Dean, <PERSON>Erin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> _
turned north toward <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION> before reaching the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   But Hugo's southern course is reminiscent of Hurricane Gilbert,
which pounded <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> and the Mexican mainland <DATE>last September</DATE>. Hugo
was upgraded <DATE>Friday</DATE> to a force 4 storm. Gilbert was a 5, the scale's
highest rank.
   Hugo is the eighth named storm of the present <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane
season, which runs from <DATE>June 1</DATE> to <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>. Tropical storms have
maximum sustained winds of 39 mph, and reach hurricane status when
winds reach 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890915-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-15-89 1221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HurricaneHugo 1stLd-Writethru a0505 09-15 0439</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Hugo, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0505,0445</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hugo Picks Up Strength, Heads Toward Caribbean</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with noon location, hurricane watch
posted in eastern Carribbean. Picks up 4th graf pvs, `The only...'. SUBS
8th graf, `Hugo developed...', to add reference to noon wind speed.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TRACY FIELDS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hurricane watch was posted in the eastern
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE> as Hurricane Hugo churned westward with winds of 125
mph and some stregthening predicted, forecasters said.
   The hurricane watch was posted from <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>British
Virgin Islands</ORGANIZATION>, and a tropical storm watch was issued for the
islands of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>National
Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
   ``The fringe effects of the storm are already being felt,'' said
forecaster <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON>. ``The seas are already getting rough off the
islands because of swells emanating off the storm.''
   At noon <ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>, Hugo's center was located near 14.4 north latitude
and 54.1 west longitude, or about 500 miles east southeast of
<LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>. The storm was moving west at 15
mph, down from a peak of 20 mph <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   ``The only way it's going to miss those islands is it's going to
have to swerve northward,'' <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said.
   He added that forecasters saw no indications Hugo would turn that
way. ``We've been lucky this year. We've had two or three storms
head toward the islands and then turn north. Maybe we'll get lucky
again but it doesn't look like it in ths case.''
   Three of this season's <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricanes _ Dean, <PERSON>Erin</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> _ turned north into the open <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> before reaching the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, forecaster <PERSON>Hal Gerrish</PERSON> said.
   Last year, killer Hurricane Gilbert held the westward course,
pounding <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   Hugo developed quickly into a major storm. Its highest sustained
winds rose by more than 35 mph <DATE>Thursday</DATE> alone and were estimated at
120 mph <TIME>this morning</TIME>, inching up to 125 mph at noon.
   ``It really was amazing how fast the eye formed and it almost
doubled its winds,'' <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said. Conditions favored the hurricane's
strengthening today; forecasters expected no change in its motion.
   Hugo's winds classify it as a 3 on the Saffir-Simpson scale, a
sort of Richter scale for storms. Gilbert, the strongest hurricane
on record, was a 5 _ the scale's highest rank.
   A reconnaissance plane was to be dispatched to investigate the
storm, <PERSON>Clark</PERSON> said.
   Hugo is the eighth named storm of the <DATE>1989</DATE> Atlantic hurricane
season. Tropical storms have sustained winds of 39 mph, and reach
hurricane status when winds hit 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 2211EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hugo'sPath 1stLd-Writethru a0638 09-19 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo's Path, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0638,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Forecasters Say Hurricane Could Make Landfall By Week's End</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 2 grafs after 10th, ``We were ..., to UPDATE with report
from Air Force reconnaissance mission.</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Hugo, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forecasters consulted computers, satellites and
yellowing hurricane charts <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in a frantic effort to plot the
course of Hurricane Hugo, which might hit the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> this
<DATE>weekend</DATE>.
   Then again, it might not.
   ``When you look out two to three days in the future, that's when
we have our most difficult problems,'' said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>, director of
the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>. ``We have a
lot of different things going on.''
   Forecasters said <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> residents from the <LOCATION>Florida Keys</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> should watch Hugo's uncertain path carefully. The
hurricane, leaving devastation behind in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, was moving
past the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and could affect <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> by <DATE>Friday</DATE>, forecasters
said.
   They added, however, that it could also miss the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
entirely.
   A variety of weather factors, some as far away as <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Rocky Mountains</LOCATION>, could determine Hugo's course. But the most likely
effect will come from the combination of a low-pressure system
moving west across southern <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> and a broad high-pressure ridge,
the ``Bermuda High,'' to Hugo's north.
   The high-pressure system probably will block Hugo from spinning
harmlessly out into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, as Hurricane <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> did last
week, forecasters said, while the low-pressure system could lure
Hugo westward.
   Forecasters said the varying factors also would affect the
storm's strength, which was slowly rebuilding <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> after falling
from 140 mph winds to 105 mph.
   Forecasters watched data spit out of advanced computers, studied
satellite maps and reconnaissance photos flown back on <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
``hurricane hunter'' planes, and even pulled out old hurricane
charts to see what storms similar to Hugo have done.
   ``We were just looking through a bunch of the old charts,''
Sheets said. ``They've done everything. They've done loopity-loops,
they've gone into south <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, they've gone into central <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>,
all the way up to the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>.''
   An <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> reconnaissance crew that flew into Hugo <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> said
the eye was about 30 to 40 miles across and the pressure had risen
to about 965 millibars _ a sign of weakening.
   ``It's weaker than in the past few days, but it's still a
significant hurricane,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Dave Carlisle</PERSON>.
   Hurricane <PERSON>David</PERSON>, a destructive hurricane that hit eastern
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands 10 years ago, swept past <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, hit the
island of <LOCATION>Hispaniola</LOCATION>, moved through the western <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, then made
landfall on <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s middle east coast.
   So far, <PERSON>Hugo</PERSON> has moved from the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> across <LOCATION>Puerto
Rico</LOCATION>, then away from <LOCATION>Hispaniola</LOCATION> and was headed slightly east of the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Computer models that use all available weather data, past records
and physics equations were laying out conflicting futures for Hugo,
Sheets said.
   The best advice forecasters could offer, Sheets said, was for
coastal residents across the southeastern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to be ready.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890914-0075 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-89 0834EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-HurricaneHugo     09-14 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Hugo,0279</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Hugo Slows, Still Heads Toward Caribbean</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hugo's trek across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> toward the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
slowed today, the storm's 75 mph winds just barely qualifying it as
a hurricane.
   At <TIME>6 a.m. EDT</TIME>, Hugo's center was located near 13.0 north latitude
and 48.0 west longitude, or about 900 miles east of the Lesser
Antilles. The storm was moving west at 17 mph, down from 20 mph
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Its highest sustained winds were just over the 74 mph hurricane
threshold, but the storm was expected to strengthen, forecasters
said. Hugo was expected to hold its course today.
   ``The threat to the islands is kind of delayed some,'' said
forecaster <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban
<LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>. ``A lot of our model forecasts indicate it's going to
slow down even more in the next couple of days.''
developed into a hurricane <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>. Storms are given names
when their sustained winds reach 39 mph, the tropical storm
threshold.
   ``The longer it heads west, the more concern it is to us,'' said
<PERSON>Hal Gerrish</PERSON>, a forecaster at the hurricane center. ``But we're not
sure yet where it will go _ there are too many things that can
happen.''
   The three <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricanes before <PERSON>Hugo _ Dean</PERSON>, <PERSON>Erin</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> _ turned north into the open <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> before reaching the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. But last year's killer Hurricane Gilbert remained on the
westward course, socking <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   They became storms when sustained winds reached 39 mph, and reach
hurricanes status when winds hit 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 0616EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TropicalWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0486 09-19 0190</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tropical Weather, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0486,0189</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Hugo Slows Tropical Storm Iris' Growth</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf to UPDATE with 6 a.m. position; picks up 5th graf
pvs, `The storm...</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Hugo, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Iris and its 60 mph winds swirled in
the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> as Hurricane Hugo devasted the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   Iris' further strengthening was unlikely through <TIME>this evening</TIME>,
according to hurricane specialist <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
   Even so, the governments of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION>
issued warnings for <ORGANIZATION>Iris</ORGANIZATION>, the ninth named storm of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>
hurricane season, which ends in <DATE>November</DATE>. Forecasters warned
residents of the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>, raked by <PERSON>Hugo</PERSON>, to keep an eye on
Iris.
   At <TIME>6 a.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, <PERSON>Iris</PERSON>' center was near 18.7 north latitude
and 57.9 west longitude, or about 265 miles east of the <LOCATION>Leeward
Islands</LOCATION>. It was moving north-northwest at about 17 mph.
   The storm was expected to hold that course at a slightly slower
pace today.
   Tropical depressions become named storms when their top sustained
winds reach 39 mph. Iris became a storm <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890916-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-16-89 1210EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-HurricaneHugo 2ndLd-Writethru a0473 09-16 0634</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Hugo, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0473,0644</SECOND>
<HEAD>Northeastern Caribbean Awaits `Extremely Dangerous' Storm</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3-4th grafs, `At 9 a.m....', to UPDATE location, motion
speed. Picks up 5th graf pvs, `The storm's...'.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MICHAEL WARREN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo, the most powerful storm to hit the
northeastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> in a decade, was bearing down on the <LOCATION>Leeward
Islands</LOCATION> <DATE>today</DATE> with 140 mph winds and a 10-foot wall of water.
   ``This is an extremely dangerous hurricane,'' hurricane
specialist <PERSON>Max Mayfield</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban
<LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION> said. ``This is stonger than Hurricane <PERSON>David</PERSON> back in
<DATE>1979</DATE>,'' which left 1,200 dead in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>noon EDT</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, Hugo's center near 15.6 north latitude and
59.0 west longitude, or about 175 miles east-southeast of the French
resort island of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>. It was expected
to hit the island this afternoon or tonight, said forecaster <PERSON>Martin
Nelson</PERSON>, before moving in the direction of <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   The hurricane was moving west at 14 mph, sending showers and
gusty winds to the eastern edge of the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   The storm's strength flucutated <TIME>this morning</TIME>, dipping from 150
mph at <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME> to 140 mph at <TIME>9 a.m</TIME>. It was expected to continue to do
so as the size of the eye contracts and expands, forecasters said,
but storm-force winds of 39 mph and above extend 150 miles from the
center.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air France</ORGANIZATION> announced it was canceling all three of its
flights scheduled today to <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION> because of the storm.
Miami-based <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> planned no cancellations or reroutings
today, but spokesman <PERSON>Robin Matell</PERSON> said, ``We'll keep monitoring it
very closely.''
   Forecasters won't be able to tell for five or six days whether
Hugo will hit the coastal <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, forecaster <PERSON>Jim Gross</PERSON> said.
   A hurricane warning was posted from <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> north to <LOCATION>St. Martin</LOCATION>
including the <ORGANIZATION>British Virgin Islands</ORGANIZATION>, and a hurricane watch the <LOCATION>U.S.
Virgin Islands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> may be upgraded to a warning today. A
tropical storm watch was in effect for the islands of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION>, according to the hurricane center.
   Forecasters classed the hurricane in Category 4, meaning it is
considered capable of extreme damage. If its sustained winds grow to
155 mph, it would be classified in Category 5, capable of
catastrophic damage. Only two Category 5 hurricanes have hit the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> since record-keeping began; the latest, <PERSON>Camille</PERSON> in
<DATE>1969</DATE>, killed 256 people.
   Islanders were warned to expect rainfall amounts of 5 to 10
inches and a storm surge with waves 10 feet higher than normal.
   <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>'s closest neighbor to the south, has only
recently recovered from the destruction <PERSON>David</PERSON> wrought 10 years ago,
when floods and mud slides poured down from mountains onto coastal
towns and villages.
   On <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION>, the next island in the chain, school officials
canceled classes today.
   A disaster response team from <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Metro Dade Fire Department</ORGANIZATION>
established a communications center in <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION>, about 200 miles
south of Hugo's path, to assess damage and coordinate emergency
medical treatment throughout the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>.
   At the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> station in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>,
guardsmen were preparing for the storm <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   ``You go around and police the area and pick up anything that can
become a missile hazard,'' Petty Officer <PERSON>Alan Burd</PERSON> said.
   The island chain has escaped the worst of previous hurricanes
this year. Dean, <PERSON>Erin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> turned north toward <LOCATION>Bermuda</LOCATION>
before reaching the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. This time, there were no signs of the
lowering atmospheric pressure that veered the others away.
   Hugo is the eighth named storm of the current <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane
season, which runs from <DATE>June 1</DATE> to <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>. Tropical storms have
maximum sustained winds of 39 mph and reach hurricane status when
winds reach 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0097 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 1243EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Hugo 7thLd-Writethru   09-19 1036</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hugo, 7th Ld-Writethru,a0572,1067</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Heads for Bahamas; Forecasters Say Likely To Hit U.S. Mainland</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 30 grafs to UPDATE with quote from witness, French,
British aid; picks up 31st pvs: `Most of...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KERNAN TURNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo spun toward the
<LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> today after thrashing <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> with 125 mph winds,
leaving more than 50,000 people homeless throughout the eastern
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. An official reported at least 25 dead.
   Hugo hit northeastern <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and then skirted its populous
northern coast on <DATE>Monday</DATE>. It roared on to the northwest and toward
open water, its hurricane-force winds missing the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>noon EDT</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>, the hurricane's center was near latitude 22.2
degrees north and longitude 68.5 west, about 175 miles east
northeast of <LOCATION>Grand Turk Island</LOCATION> in the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, according to
the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>. Winds fell to 105 mph.
   Forecasters said it likely would hit the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland later in
the week but said it was too early to predict where. Cruise ships
steamed out of the way, residents prepared along the <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>
coast and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> residents jammed the phone lines of insurance
companies for financial protection.
   ``It's a long way from any potential landfall,'' said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
``Unfortunately, the higher likelihood is that it will turn more
west and could make landfall anywhere from <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION>.''
   At least 25 people in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> died from the storm, said
<PERSON>Cizanette Rivera</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Maria Dolores Oronoz</PERSON>, a spokesman for Gov. <PERSON>Rafael
Hernandez-Colon</PERSON>, said only two people died on <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. The two
died while trying to remove a TV antenna <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in preparation for
the storm, she said. She said no other deaths had been reported in
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> reported its preliminary
statement that said 25 had died on the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth was
incorrect.
   <PERSON>Ms. Rivera</PERSON> gave no breakdown on where the other reported victims
had died, but scattered fatalities were reported throughout the
heavily visited tourist islands of the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   Hugo left a trail of smashed homes, power failures and injuries
in <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION> since
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, and widespread looting by machete-wielding mobs was reported
on the island of <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION>.
   Widespread evacuations apparently lessened the chance of
fatalities.
   Sailboats were blown out of the water and thrown up to 150 feet
on shore in <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>, and some waterfront businesses have
disappeared.
   ``We were all huddled together in the corridor when the wind took
off the roof of the house,'' said 14-year-old <PERSON>Didier Gacoby-Kaoly</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>.
   Cleanup efforts were under way today throughout <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. Gov.
<PERSON>Rafael Hernandez-Colon</PERSON> said at least 27,900 people were left
homeless and asked President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to declare it a disaster area.
   Hugo's winds overturned cars, peeled roofs off houses and office
buildings and sent chunks of concrete plunging into streets in <LOCATION>San
Juan</LOCATION>, where one-third of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth's 3.3 million people
live.
   The winds ripped out glass, walls and furnishings from the top
four floors of a 25-story building in the <LOCATION>Santurce</LOCATION> section, leaving
only beams remaining.
   Fifty airplanes were reported destroyed at the airport in <LOCATION>Isla
Verde</LOCATION>. Looters stripped shops of their goods in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>.
   Officials were working to restore power, which was cut to <PERCENT>75
percent</PERCENT> of the island.
   Police cars with flashing lights patrolled <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> streets early
today. Major streets were cleared, but secondary streets remained
clogged with power lines, tree limbs, sheets of metal and shattered
glass.
   Flooding made many roads impassable, and international
communications were disrupted.
   In the northeast town of <LOCATION>Luquillo</LOCATION>, 10 homes were swept downriver
and six families were reported missing, the weather service office
said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Civil Defense</ORGANIZATION> officials reported <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the homes on the
<LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION> islands of <LOCATION>Vieques</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Culebra</LOCATION> were were either
destroyed or damaged.
   Secretary of the Interior <PERSON>Manuel Lujan</PERSON> said <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> in emergency
assistance funds were released to aid storm-stricken areas of <LOCATION>Puerto
Rico</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION>.
   The weather service said maximum sustained winds had slowed to
near 105 mph with hurricane-force winds extending up to 60 miles
from the center. It was moving to the northwest at 12 mph and was
expected to continue in that direction during the next 24 hours.
   A hurricane watch was in effect for the central <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and
tropical storm warnings for the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Since <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the storm has caused widespread damage in
<LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Kitts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>British
Virgin Islands</ORGANIZATION>.
   Six people were killed and hundreds of buildings were flattened
on the British island of <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, the British government said
<DATE>today</DATE>. It said nearly all of the 12,000 island residents were
homeless.
   Britain reported the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Navy</ORGANIZATION> marines landed on <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION> to
help clear the airport runway so planes could deliver aid supplies.
British Overseas Aid Minister <PERSON>Lynda Chalker</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> would
provide <MONEY>$1.57 million</MONEY> in emergency aid to islands struck by the
hurricane.
   Five people were reported killed, 84 injured and about 15,000
homeless on the French island of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>. Two were killed in
<LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>French Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> assigned 3,000 soldiers,
two military transport aircraft and four cargo vessels to assist in
restoring communications and emergency services to <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>.
French President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> pledged to rebuild ``what was
destroyed.''
   Most of the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>' 106,000 residents live on <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION>, where a ham radio operator said winds had torn off
the roofs of up to <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of the homes.
   Hugo is the fourth hurricane of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane season and
is the most powerful hurricane to hit the region since Hurricane
David in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   That storm killed an estimated 1,200 people in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
watch on the new storm. They said <PERSON>Iris</PERSON>, with 50 mph winds, was about
300 miles east of the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and was moving
north-northwest at about 18 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890918-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-89 2219EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather     09-18 0193</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather,0197</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Iris Follows Hugo's Trail</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Hugo, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Iris gathered 50 mph winds in the
wake of Hurricane Hugo on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and forecasters warned residents on
progress.
   At <TIME>6 p.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Air Force</ORGANIZATION> reconnaissance aircraft
and satellite pictures located the center of the tropical storm near
16.5 north latitude and 56.5 west longitude, or about 300 miles east
of the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION>, a group of islands in the Lesser Antilles of
the <LOCATION>West Indies</LOCATION>.
   The governments of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>St. Vincent</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> issued
warnings for <ORGANIZATION>Iris</ORGANIZATION>, the ninth named storm of this <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane
season.
<PERSON>Iris</PERSON> was moving toward the north-northwest at about 18 mph.
   Swirling weather patterns left behind by Hugo made further
strengthening unlikely through <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, said hurricane
specialist <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON>. Iris was expected to hold its course at a
slightly slower pace during that time.
   Tropical depressions become tropical storms when their top
sustained winds reach 39 mph. Iris became a storm <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0080 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 1110EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Hugo'sPath     09-19 0285</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hugo's Path,0294</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Hugo, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Forecasters Say Hurricane Could Hit U.S. by Week's End</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forecasters <DATE>today</DATE> said deadly Hurricane Hugo could
hit anywhere from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> <DATE>this weekend</DATE> _ or spin
harmlessly away in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
   ``It's a long way from any potential landfall,'' said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
``Unfortunately, the higher likelihood is that it will turn more
west and could make landfall anywhere from <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION>.''
   Sheets added, though, that it's also possible the hurricane could
skirt the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> entirely.
   Forecasters today watched data spit out of computers, studied
satellite maps and reconnaissance photos flown back on <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>
``hurricane hunter'' planes, and even pulled out old hurricane
charts to see what storms similar to Hugo have done.
   The data laid out conflicting futures for Hugo, Sheets said.
   ``We were just looking through a bunch of the old charts,'' he
said. ``They've done everything. They've done loopity-loops, they've
gone into <LOCATION>South Florida</LOCATION>, they've gone into central <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, all the
way up to the <LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>.''
   The main area of agreement on the computer models, Sheets said,
was that Hugo is likely to change from the north-northwest course it
followed overnight after pounding <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   ``Now the question is when is it going to turn more
west-northwest,'' Sheets said. ``There's just not any way to say.''
   Hurricanes are propelled by prevailing winds generated by other
weather systems.
   The most likely impact on Hugo will be a ``Bermuda High,'' a
high-pressure system building to Hugo's northeast, forecasters said.
That system would tend to keep Hugo from veering from the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890920-0200 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-20-89 2204EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hugo-Sheets     09-20 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo-Sheets,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Director of Hurricane Center Thrives in Pressure-Cooker Atmosphere</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SANDRA WALEWSKI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORAL GABLES, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After flying into about 200 hurricanes,
<PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON> doesn't appear at all fazed by his responsibility as
director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> to predict the path of the
ferocious storms.
   Sheets, 52, friendly and low-key, is in his third season as head
of the worldwide command center for hurricane data in this suburb of
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   ``You look out there and see the chaos ... but it really works,''
he said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> while surveying the low-ceiling, wide-open room
jammed with forecasters and reporters, cameramen and photographers
covering Hurricane Hugo.
   Hugo, whose winds dropped to 105 mph after churning through the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, is the most powerful of nine named storms this year, six
of which became hurricanes. Storms like Hugo make Sheets a household
name.
   Killer hurricanes like Hugo, which left at least 25 dead, tens of
thousands homeless and <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in damages in its rampage
through the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, make Sheets a household name when
they threaten the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland.
   A typical half hour for Sheets: do live feeds for the networks
and local television stations; squeeze in a few minutes with a print
reporter; grab a phone to talk with a government official in <LOCATION>Myrtle
Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>; consult with his team of forecasters on incoming data.
   Then it starts all over again.
   ``He's a cool, collected person _ the ideal person for this
pressure job,'' said <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON>, a 34-year veteran of the hurricane
center. ``He's got a real feeling for hurricanes and everything that
goes with it.''
   Sheets also gets high marks from his colleagues for scientific
ability and poise.
   ``He worked here as a forecaster before becoming deputy director
and then director,'' said hurricane specialist <PERSON>Hal Gerrish</PERSON>. ``He's
not just an administrator. He can sit down and be able to pull one
of the shifts with us.''
   One of the biggest pressures on Sheets is to pinpoint where a
hurricane will blast ashore _ a decision that can result in
evacuations and huge expenditures. It is one of his biggest
frustrations.
   ``It's frustrating not to be able to say with a great deal of
confidence this is where it's going to move,'' said Sheets.
   Hugo has been an especially difficult storm to forecast beyond a
couple of days, but he said the devastation in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> had
been lessened because of forecasts and warnings issued by the center.
   Sheets, in 16 years of research flights, had his share of close
calls flying into the eye of hurricanes. He says he finds his
current job very fulfilling despite offers to join reconnaissance
crews checking Hugo.
   ``There's nothing there that I need to go and experience again,''
he said, grinning.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091989-0139 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 109602 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 19, 1989, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 4; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
358 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS HOMELESS IN WAKE OF HUGO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Hurricane Hugo spun toward the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> today after thrashing <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> with 
125 m.p.h. winds, leaving hundreds of thousands homeless throughout the eastern 
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. An official reported at least 25 people dead. 
</P>
<P>
Hugo hit northeastern <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and then skirted its populous northern coast 
<DATE>Monday</DATE>. It roared on to the northwest and toward open water, its 
hurricane-force winds missing the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
At <DATE>midday today</DATE>, the hurricane's center was east-northeast of <LOCATION>Grand Turk Island</LOCATION> 
to 105 m.p.h. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Likely to <ORGANIZATION>Hit Mainland 
</P>
<P>
Forecasters</ORGANIZATION> said it likely would hit the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland later in the week but 
said it was too early to predict where. Cruise ships steamed out of the way, 
residents prepared along the <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION> coast and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> residents jammed 
the phone lines of insurance companies for financial protection. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a long way from any potential landfall," said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>, director of the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION> "Unfortunately, the 
higher likelihood is that it will turn more west and could make landfall 
anywhere from <LOCATION>south Florida</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
Hugo has left a trail of smashed homes, power failures and injuries in 
<LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION> since <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, and 
widespread looting by machete-wielding mobs was reported on the island of <LOCATION>St. 
Thomas</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Sailboats were blown out of the water and thrown up to 150 feet on shore in <LOCATION>St. 
Thomas</LOCATION>, and some waterfront businesses have disappeared. 
</P>
<P>
Cleanup efforts were under way today throughout <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. Gov. <PERSON>Rafael 
Hernandez-Colon</PERSON> said at least 27,900 people were left homeless and asked 
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to declare it a disaster area. 
</P>
<P>
Hugo's winds overturned cars, peeled roofs off houses and office buildings and 
sent chunks of concrete plunging into streets in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, where one-third of 
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth's 3.3 million people live. 
</P>
<P>
The winds ripped out glass, walls and furnishings from the top four floors of a 
25-story building in the <LOCATION>Santurce</LOCATION> section, leaving only beams remaining. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Street surfing -- David Donati uses a rake to paddle his surfboard 
through flooded streets of San Juan today. Many Puerto Rico areas remain 
flooded in wake of Hurricane Hugo. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891130-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-30-89 1159EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-HurricaneSeason 2ndLd-Writethru a0513 11-30 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Season, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0513,0556</SECOND>
<HEAD>Costly 1989 Atlantic Season Ends With Tropical Storm Karen Forming
Near Cuba</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 11 grafs to UPDATE with depression forming into Tropical
Storm Karen, UPDATES total of named storms. PICKS UP 14th graf, `Last year
...'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOAN THOMPSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Asociated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1989</DATE> hurricane season, marked by the costliest
storm in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history, officially ended today with yet another
tropical storm forming in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>8 a.m. EST</TIME>, <ORGANIZATION>Tropical Storm Karen</ORGANIZATION>, with 50 mph winds, was
about 125 miles south-southwest of <LOCATION>Havana</LOCATION> and was not expected to
strengthen, said the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral
Gables</LOCATION>. It was drifttng toward <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> at about 5 mph.
   Depressions become named storms when their sustained winds reach
39 mph; hurricanes have winds of at least 74 mph. <PERSON>Karen</PERSON> is the 11th
named storm of the season, which began <DATE>June 1</DATE>.
   The six-month season was far less deadly than <DATE>1988</DATE>'s, in which
550 people died in storms.
   This year's storms killed 84 people, including 56 in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, said meteorologist <PERSON>Mark Zimmer</PERSON>. Hurricane Hugo was blamed
for 49 deaths, including 21 in this country. It slammed into <LOCATION>South
Carolina</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 21</DATE>.
   ``I've seen greater damage in smaller areas,'' said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>,
director of the hurricane center. ``But I've never seen it on such
a large scale where you go mile after mile with such massive
damage.''
   Overall damage from Hugo totaled about <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY>. In the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, it caused a record storm damage of about <MONEY>$7 billion</MONEY>.
Most of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> damage was around <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION> are racing to recover from Hugo in time
for the tourist season.
   ``We are still in a sense reeling from the effects of Hugo but
that didn't dampen our spirit,'' said <PERSON>Alexander A. Ferrelly</PERSON>,
governor of the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION>. He said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that <LOCATION>St.
Thomas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>St. John</LOCATION> are ready for winter tourists and <ORGANIZATION>St. Croix</ORGANIZATION>
would be ready by early <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   It was the most expensive disaster for the <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION>
since the organization began 110 years ago. Latest figures show the
agency has spent about <MONEY>$38 million</MONEY> in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Carolinas</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Michael Caudill</PERSON>, a spokesman in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   The hurricane season, which began <DATE>June 1</DATE>, had four tropical
storms, counting <PERSON>Karen</PERSON>, and seven hurricanes. The storms also were
stronger than usual, said Sheets.
   Last year, there were seven tropical storms and five hurricanes.
The <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> season usually has 10 named storms. Normally, only
five or six whip up the 74-mph sustained winds to become a
hurricane.
   Hugo, the fifth major <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane in the last decade to
reach <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shores, may have marked the end of a 30-year period of
fewer, weaker hurricanes, Sheets said.
   ``There have been fewer of the stronger hurricanes making
landfall since the <DATE>1960s</DATE>,'' Sheets said. ``Now maybe we're starting
to return to more normal activity like we had in the <DATE>'50s</DATE> and
<DATE>'60s</DATE>.''
   During the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, eight major hurricanes hit the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
while seven struck the following decade.
   After Hugo, the most damaging tropical system this year was
<ORGANIZATION>Tropical Storm Allison</ORGANIZATION>. It dumped large amounts of rain and caused
11 deaths and <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> damage in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900827-0096 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-27-90 1658EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-HurricaneGustav     08-27 0373</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Gustav,0385</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Warnings Come Down As Storm Heads Past Islands</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Gustav curved away from outer <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
islands <DATE>Monday</DATE> and aimed its 105 mph winds toward open ocean.
   Gustav _ which reached hurricane strength <DATE>Sunday</DATE> while heading
west toward the <LOCATION>Leeward Islands</LOCATION> _ turned north onto a path that
would skirt the island chain and take it out into the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>.
Storm warnings in the islands, which stretch north from the
Venezuelan coast, were droppped, but forecasters said rough seas
and surf might be experienced.
   ``They'll probably get a little of the fringe effects,'' said
<PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban
<LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>. ``But the hurricane itself looks like it's going to
pass to the east.''
   At <TIME>3 p.m. EDT</TIME>, <PERSON>Gustav</PERSON> was centered near 17.4 degrees north
latitude and 58.2 degrees west longitude, or about 240 miles east
of <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>. It was moving north at 10 mph and was expected to hold
that course and speed for the next day or two.
   Gustav had hurricane-force winds extending 35 miles from its
center and tropical storm-force winds extending outward 175 miles.
   Over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, islanders with strong memories of last year's
Hurricane Hugo had scrambled to prepare for <ORGANIZATION>Gustav</ORGANIZATION>'s expected
onslaught.
   In <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, a British colony devastated by Hugo, banks,
hardware stores, pharmacies and supermarkets opened <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Utilities called workers back from vacation, and the 100-member
police and 50-strong volunteer army were fully mobilized.
   ``The level of preparedness and the level of activity is
significantly greater than it was last year'' before Hugo, said
<PERSON>Reuben Meade</PERSON>, the government's director of development. ``They are
out there in earnest.''
   Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Tropical Storm Hortense</ORGANIZATION> remained about a thousand
miles to the east in the <LOCATION>mid-Atlantic</LOCATION>, a hindrance only to shipping.
   At noon <ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <PERSON>Hortense</PERSON> had winds of 45 mph. It was moving
north-northwest at about 8 mph.
   The storm was centered near 19.1 degrees north latitude, 41.8
degrees west longitude, or about 1000 miles west of the <LOCATION>Cape Verde
Islands of Africa</LOCATION>. It wasn't expected to gain strength, but
forecasters planned to keep an eye on it.
   Tropical depressions become tropical storms when their sustained
winds reach 39 mph. Tropical storms become hurricanes at 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890913-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-89 1023EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TropicalWeather     09-13 0218</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tropical Weather,0222</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hugo Strengthens While Gabrielle Fades</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Hugo today edged closer to becoming a
hurricane as it began following the path of its predecessor,
<PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON>.
had sustained winds of 65 mph. At <TIME>6 a.m. EDT</TIME> it was centered near
latitude 12.7 north and longitude 42.0 west, 1,300 miles east of the
Lesser Antilles.
   The storm was headed west at about 20 mph and was expected to
hold its course through today, possibly affecting the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> in
four or five days. Forecasters said Hugo could become a hurricane,
with 74 mph winds, within a day or so.
   ``It's not as big a system (as <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON>) and it seems to be
getting better organized,'' said forecaster <PERSON>Gil Clark</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> continued dissolving in the cold water
of the northern <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, about 280 miles south of <LOCATION>Cape Race</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION>.
   The former hurricane's winds today were down to 40 mph, 1 mph
over the minimum for tropical-storm classification, but still
causing 6- to 10-foot swells along <LOCATION>Nova Scotia</LOCATION>. Swells as high as 16
feet from <LOCATION>Gabrielle</LOCATION> were blamed for the disappearances of at least
seven people from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> in the past week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890922-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-22-89 0022EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Hugo 10thLd-Writethru a0404-5 09-22 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo, 10th Ld-Writethru, a0404-5, 2 Takes,0851</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Killer Storm Hits South Carolina Coast</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 17 grafs to UPDATE with eye passing just east of
Charleston, 119 mph winds reported in city, other details. Picks up 19th
graf pvs, `Near its...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos MH2, BEF1, LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHARLESTON, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo struck <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> with
renewed fury <DATE>Thursday</DATE> after thousands of coastal residents in
southeastern states grabbed what they could carry and fled inland on
jammed highways.
   ``This is a disaster staring us right in the eye,'' Mayor <PERSON>Joseph
P. Riley Jr.</PERSON> said from his <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> command post in <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>,
where the hurricane downed power lines, snapped trees and caused
utility transformers to explode.
   ``All we can do now is pray and hope all the precautions we have
taken have been sufficient,'' <PERSON>Riley</PERSON> said as Hugo's eye bore in on
the city. ``I just hope and pray we can get through this without any
loss of life.''
   By <TIME>midnight</TIME>, 119 mph winds were reported in <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>. The roof
cracked at <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION>, a 188-year-old brick building that has
withstood several hurricanes, and torrents of water poured into the
paneled council chamber. Phone and electric service to the command
post was knocked out.
   Hurricane-force winds first hit the coast by <TIME>9:15 p.m. EDT</TIME>, and
about three hours later the eye of the storm passed over the Isle of
Palms just east of <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   The eye was about 10 miles across and top winds were still at 135
mph.
   Hugo was expected to turn gradually to the north, causing severe
flooding as it moved up the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>. The storm posed a <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT>
chance of hitting <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and a <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT> chance of hitting
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> before <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the hurricane center said.
   As Hugo neared the coast, roads from <ORGANIZATION>Hilton Head</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Myrtle Beach</LOCATION>,
200 miles north, were nearly empty, as were the boarded-up resort
towns themselves. Power lines and trees were downed in some spots
and water flooded roads. Stop lights and neon lights were knocked
out in <LOCATION>Myrtle Beach</LOCATION>.
   ``One eyewitness said `It's like a light show,''' said <PERSON>Amy
Garrison</PERSON>, a reporter at WKZQ AM-FM in <LOCATION>Myrtle Beach</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, the hurricane littered streets with tin roofs,
palmetto fronds and chunks of bark. Businesses were closed and
classes at public schools and universities canceled. Riley ordered
residents of one-story homes to evacuate.
   Hospitals stockpiled supplies, discharging any patients well
enough to go and moving others to hospitals inland to make room for
emergency patients, officials said.
   About 12,000 people had checked into 83 shelters across the state
as of <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, and more were expected, said <PERSON>Bennish Brown</PERSON>,
a spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Operations Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Columbia</LOCATION>, 220
miles northwest of here.
   ``We tried to close the doors but people are sneaking in side
doors,'' said <PERSON>Elaine Skelton</PERSON>, a registered nurse working at the
<ORGANIZATION>Conway High School</ORGANIZATION> shelter near <LOCATION>Myrtle Beach</LOCATION>. ``We tried to post
guards at the doors, but people were still coming in.''
   <ORGANIZATION>American Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> relief efforts were buckling under the number
of evacuees, said <PERSON>Brian Ruberry</PERSON>, a spokesman in <LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, who
appealed for help.
   ``Right now the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> is sheltering tens of thousands of
people all along the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> seaboard. This of course is at the same
time that we're sheltering 25,000 people on <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and the
other <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands.
   ``We're beginning to feel the squeeze. Our resources are very
tight. Right now Hugo is shaping up to be one of our biggest relief
operations of the decade.''
   At <TIME>midnight</TIME>, the center of Hugo was near latitude 32.7 degrees
north and longitude 79.9 degrees west, forecasters said. The
hurricane's speed had picked up to 22 mph from 20 mph earlier.
   Near its center, Hugo's muscle reached winds of 135 mph, up from
125 mph earlier in the day and 105 mph the day before. North and
<LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> can expect tornadoes linked to Hugo for the next two
days, according to the hurricane center.
   The coastal area could expect hurricane force winds for 10 to 12
hours once the eye comes ashore, officials said. A hurricane warning
was in effect between <LOCATION>Fernandina Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Oregon Inlet</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>
   By <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>Hugo</PERSON> was upgraded to a category 4 hurricane on
the Saffir-Simpson scale of strength, the second mightiest category,
which indicated it could cause extreme damage.
   ``It strengthened more than we thought it would,'' Sheets said,
adding that Hugo would cause severe flooding as it moved up the
<LOCATION>Appalachians</LOCATION>.
   The timing of the landfall was critical because of the storm's
tidal surge, a dome of water 10 to 15 feet high that would feed a
normal 5-foot high tide that peaks after <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>
   ``On top of that will be waves,'' Sheets said earlier, and in
many places on barrier islands ``the buildings will be swept clean
off.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890918-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-89 1336EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-HurricaneHugo 9thLd-Writethru   09-18 0951</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Hugo, 9th Ld-Writethru,a0566,0978</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hugo Strikes Virgin Islands, 125 Mph Winds Hit Puerto Rico</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with six grafs to UPDATE with damage in British Virgin
Islands; picks up 8th pvs: Five people ...; SUBS 24th graf pvs, `Hugo uprooted
...' with two grafs to conform and add detail; picks up 25th: The Virgin...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX10, LaserGraphic NY17</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The region's mightiest hurricane in
a decade lashed <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> today after battering the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin
Islands</LOCATION> and other tourist havens, leaving at least nine people dead
and thousands homeless.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said Hurricane Hugo hit the eastern
tip of <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and skirted the northern coast, packing 125 mph
winds and a 6-foot tidal surges. Forecasters expected up to 15
inches of rain and flooding and mudslides all over the island.
   ``We're getting ravaged,'' said ham radio operator <PERSON>Fernando
Garcia</PERSON> in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>. ``Part of my aluminum siding is gone, my next
door neighbor's aluminum siding is gone ....''
   There were reports of heavy damage, some looting, no water and no
electricity in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   At noon <ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>, Hugo's center was near latitude 18.6 degrees north
and longitude 66.0 west about 20 miles north of <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, said the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, Hugo plowed west-northwest through the eastern
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, slamming into the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>British Virgin Islands</LOCATION> with
100 mph winds and rains that caused heavy flooding and destroyed
homes.
   Five people were reported killed, 80 injured and more than 10,000
homeless on the French island of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, relief officials said.
Corrugated steel roofs were torn off, power lines ripped free and
crops were destroyed. The airport's control tower was knocked out of
commission, permitting only visual landings by relief planes.
   Two people were killed in <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION> and one in <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>,
according to <ORGANIZATION>Beacon Radio</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Anguilla</LOCATION>. Ham radio operators reported
at least five deaths in <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, but there was no official
confirmation.
   Nearly all of <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>'s 12,000 residents were homeless and
schools, hospitals and the police department all suffered serious
damage, said ham radio operator <PERSON>Stuart Haimes</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   Police said a man was electrocuted in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> when he touched
a power line while removing a TV antenna from his roof in preparing
for the storm.
   Off <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>, charter boat captain <PERSON>O.B. O'Brian</PERSON> told CNN by
ship-to-shore telephone <TIME>this morning</TIME>:
   ``Looking down the lagoon, we see a lot of sailboats intertwined
and a lot of sails ripped and a lot of sails down. It looks pretty
bad ... There was a lot of wind.''
   Most of the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>' 106,000 residents live on <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>.
On <ORGANIZATION>St. Croix</ORGANIZATION>, a ham radio operator said the winds tore off the roofs
from up to <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of the homes.
   Officials said stores in the <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Christiansted</LOCATION> were
heavily damaged, and there were reports of looting. National Guard
Adjutant Gen. <PERSON>Robert Moorehead</PERSON> said 1,000 people were evacuated to
rescue shelters in <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION>.
   Storm watches were in effect for parts of the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>,
and a hurricane warning was issued for the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
including the Turks and Caicos islands.
   Hugo was moving at 10 mph west-northwest alongside <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, a
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth with 3.3 million people. Hurricane-force winds
extended up to 75 miles from its center. The weather service said
winds ripped the roof off a baseball stadium on the offshore island
of <LOCATION>Vieques</LOCATION>, about 10 miles to the east with about 7,000 residents.
   High winds <DATE>Sunday</DATE> blew roofs off six houses in the offshore
island of <LOCATION>Culebra</LOCATION>. Luis <ORGANIZATION>Munoz Marin International Airport</ORGANIZATION>, by far
the region's biggest, was closed, as were schools, banks, courts and
government offices.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> had been mobilized in both the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   Meteorologist <PERSON>Jesse Moore</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> said
it was too early to tell whether Hugo would strike the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
mainland. He said the storm was expected to be off the southeastern
Bahamas by <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and ``after that, it's anybody's guess.''
   Residents of hilly areas where flash floods are a danger were
urged to evacuate, and <ORGANIZATION>Social Services</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Carmen Sonia Zayas</PERSON>
said 11,300 people were moved from flood-prone coastal areas to
rescue shelters.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Port Authority</ORGANIZATION> also said cruise ships scheduled to arrive in
<LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, where one-third of the island population lives, had been
routed elswhere.
   Hugo uprooted trees and knocked out power in the <LOCATION>British Virgin
Islands</LOCATION>. On the resort island of <LOCATION>Tortola</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>British Virgin
Islands</LOCATION>, residents said there were numerous injuries and scores of
homes destroyed.
   ``We are aware of the widespread damage. We may have to declare
the area a disaster area,'' said <PERSON>Louis Walters</PERSON>, education minister
in the <LOCATION>British Virgin Islands</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> were last hit by a major
hurricane in <DATE>1956</DATE>, when <PERSON>Betsy</PERSON> caused extensive damage and killed 11
people in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   Officials in <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> said many buildings were damaged.
   The mayor of <ORGANIZATION>St. Francois</ORGANIZATION>, a village on the island's eastern end,
told <ORGANIZATION>Radio Caraibe Internationale</ORGANIZATION> that there was nothing left of it.
   ``Aside from a few houses, almost all the rest were destroyed,''
said Mayor <PERSON>Ernest Moutoussamy</PERSON>. He said several hotels suffered
serious damage.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, a plane was sent <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with 60 rescue workers and
emergency supplies for <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, and two more were standing by
waiting for <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> airports to reopen.
   Hugo is the fourth hurricane of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane season,
which runs from <DATE>June 1</DATE> to <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>.
   It is the most powerful hurricane to hit the region since
Hurricane David in <DATE>1979</DATE>. That storm killed an estimated 1,200 people
in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890912-0214 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-12-89 2315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TropicalWeather 2ndLd-Writethru a0774 09-12 0266</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0774,0268</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hugo Strengthens While Gabrielle Fades</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout with 10:30 p.m. EDT positions, courses, wind
speeds.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tropical Storm Hugo would soon strengthen into a
hurricane as it churned across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> toward the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>,
forecasters said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, and <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> whipped up heavy swells as
it moved away from <LOCATION>Nova Scotia</LOCATION>.
   Hugo, the eighth named storm of this <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane season,
had winds of 65 mph with stronger gusts in squalls, and forecasters
said conditions were right for it to grow stronger.
   ``It still looks impressive on the satellite imagery, meaning it
has continued to strengthen some,'' forecaster <PERSON>Max Mayfield</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in suburban <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION> said, adding that
Hugo could be up to 74 mph hurricane-strength winds in a day or two.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME>, Hugo's center was near latitude 12.9 north and
longitude 39.0 west, or about 930 miles west-southwest of the
westernmost <LOCATION>Cape Verde</LOCATION> islands. It was headed west at about 20 mph
and was on a path that could take it to the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> in about five
days, forecasters said.
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON>'s winds were down to 40 mph, but still
causing swells as high as 16 feet along the south coast of <LOCATION>Nova
Scotia</LOCATION> and parts of <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, forecasters said.
   Gabrielle was expected to weaken as it accelerated to the
northeast over northern <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> waters.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME>, <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON>'s center was near latitude 41.7
north, longitude 55.0 west, or about 345 miles south southwest of
<LOCATION>Cape Race</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION>. It was drifting east-northeast at about 10
mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901130-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-30-90 0813EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HurricaneSeason     11-30 0372</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hurricane Season,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Atlantic Hurricane Season: A Lot of Sound, Not Much Fury</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KIRK SEMPLE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> Atlantic hurricane season had more storms
than usual and some forecasters predict that's just a hint of more
frequent and more forceful hurricanes in the coming years.
   But this year's batch did not include the devastating storms of
years past and at least one forecaster thinks <DATE>1991</DATE> will be a calmer
year. The season ends today.
   <PERSON>Dr. William Gray</PERSON>, a professor of atmospheric science at <ORGANIZATION>Colorado
State University</ORGANIZATION>, thinks a dry spell in <LOCATION>West Africa</LOCATION> during the past
two decades explained the reduction of storms along the eastern
seaboard in the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE> and <DATE>1989</DATE>, there was near normal rainfall in the <LOCATION>Sahel</LOCATION>,
the semi-arid land on the southern fringe of the <LOCATION>Sahara Desert</LOCATION>.
Some meteorological experts think the rainfall signaled the end of
a 20-year drought - and may have spawned <PERSON>Gilbert</PERSON> in <DATE>1988</DATE> and Hugo
in <DATE>1989</DATE>.
   Gray on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> predicted a below-average hurricane season in
<DATE>1991</DATE>. He based his forecast on several factors, including an
anticipated below-average rainfall in the Sahel.
   But Gray and other forecasters agree that the general outlook
for the <DATE>1990s</DATE> and the early years of the next century is for more
intense hurricanes than those of the <DATE>last two decades</DATE>.
   ``We've been through a real long period of hurricane inactivity
in the '70s and '80s up until <DATE>1985</DATE>, and I think we're coming out of
that,'' said <PERSON>Bob Sheets</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>.
   ``Perhaps the Gilberts and the Hugos were signaling that,'' he
said, recalling Hurricane Gilbert that wracked the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and
Hurricane Hugo that devastated <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> - two of the most
destructive <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricanes ever.
   Hurricanes have been recorded in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> every month except
<DATE>April</DATE>, but are rare outside the hurricane season, <DATE>June 1</DATE> to <DATE>Nov.
30</DATE>.
   In this year's season, there were 14 named storms, eight of them
hurricanes. The average number of storms is nine, with about six
becoming hurricanes. Usually only a couple of those storms strike
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
   While many of the storms spun harmlessly through the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>,
several caused their share of destruction.
   The most deadly storm was Hurricane Diana, which swept into
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> in early <DATE>August</DATE>, resulting in flash floods and mudslides
that killed 96 people and caused extensive damage to roads,
property and agriculture, the weather service reported.
   A weather disturbance becomes a tropical storm, and is given a
name, if its sustained winds reach 39 mph. Storms become hurricanes
if winds reach 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890914-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-89 0119EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-TropicalWeather 1stLd-Writethru a0812 09-14 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Tropical Weather, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0812,0269</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hugo Becomes Hurricane, Further Strengthening Expected</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf to UPDATE with 10:30 p.m. position, speed.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hugo became a hurricane <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> as it sped
westward toward the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, but forecasters said it was too early
to determine whether it was a threat to land.
   ``The longer it heads west, the more concern it is to us,'' said
<PERSON>Hal Gerrish</PERSON>, a forecaster for the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION>. ``But
we're not sure yet where it will go _ there are too many things that
can happen.''
   Hugo's most recent predecessors, hurricanes Dean, <PERSON>Erin and
Gabrielle</PERSON>, turned north into the open <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> before reaching the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gerrish</PERSON> noted. But last year's killer Hurricane Gilbert
remained on the westward course, wreaking havoc on the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME>, Hugo's center was located near 12.9 north
latitude and 46.3 west longitude, or about 965 miles east of the
easternmost Lesser Antilles, and was moving west at 20 mph.
Sustained winds reached 75 mph, just over the hurricane threshold,
and further strengthening was expected.
   Meanwhile, <PERSON>Gabrielle</PERSON> was downgraded to an extratropical storm as
it moved through the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION>, and the center stopped issuing
bulletins on it. Its last position was about 225 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>Cape Race</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, moving northeast at 20 to 25 mph
with winds of 55 mph.
   Gabrielle and Hugo are the seventh and eighth named storms of the
<DATE>1989</DATE> Atlantic hurricane season. They become storms when sustained
winds reach 39 mph and are classified as hurricanes when the
strength increases to 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890917-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-17-89 0154EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-HurricaneHugo 8thLd-Writethru a0646 09-17 0934</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Hugo, 8th Ld-Writethru, a0646,0957</SECOND>
<HEAD>Storm Hits Guadeloupe, Other Eastern Caribbean Islands Brace for
Onslaught</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Leads with 9 grafs to UPDATE with eye of storm over Guadeloupe,
France prepares to send relief aid. Pickup 8th graf ``It's a very...''</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MH3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo ripped away rooftops
and uprooted trees in <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION> early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and
approached other popular resort islands of the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
with deadly winds of up to 140 mph.
   Forecasters described Hugo as ``extremely dangerous'' and said it
could be the most powerful hurricane to hit the region since
Hurricane David in <DATE>1979</DATE>. That storm killed an estimated 1,200 people
in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   ``The eye of the hurricane is directly above <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Israel
Matos</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> bureau in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>,
said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> at <TIME>1:25 a.m. EDT</TIME>. It was impossible to telephone to
<LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> early <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> as telephone circuits were either
jammed or busy.
   At <TIME>midnight EDT</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, Hugo's center was near 16.3 north
latitude and 61.1 west longitude, about 350 miles east-southeast of
<LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>. After hitting the French island it was expected to move
north toward <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, said forecaster <PERSON>Martin Nelson</PERSON> at the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.
   The hurricane was moving west-northwest at 12 mph, sending
showers and gusty winds to the eastern edge of the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and
threatening islands over a 600-mile arc stretching from <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   The storm's effects would start to be felt in the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> by <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> said.
   By midnight there was a blackout in most of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> as
authorities turned off electricity as a precautionary measure,
government radio <ORGANIZATION>RFO</ORGANIZATION> said. The island experienced very strong winds,
which blew the metal roofing off some homes on <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>'s eastern
side late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   In <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION> to the south there were power outages on the island's
north side where strong winds uprooted trees, the radio said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Radio France Internationale</ORGANIZATION> from <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, monitored in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>
shortly before <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, said French authorities were
preparing to send emergency supplies and personnel to <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>.
   ``It's a very dangerous storm, extremely dangerous in fact,''
<PERSON>Nelson</PERSON> said.
   Forecasters said if the storm remains on its northwesterly course
it would pass over <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION> about <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> and continue on to the northeastern coast of <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>
early <DATE>Monday</DATE>. San Juan, the <LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION> capital with a population
of 1.1 million, is on the northeastern coast.
   Earlier, forecasters had said the hurricane was headed for <LOCATION>Puerto
Rico</LOCATION>'s southern coast.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> issued hurricane warnings
at <TIME>3 p.m. EDT</TIME> for the <LOCATION>U.S. Virgin Islands</LOCATION> and for <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, which
previously had been on a hurricane watch. The warnings were posted
from <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION> northward and westward through <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>,
including the British Virgin Islands and <ORGANIZATION>St. Martin</ORGANIZATION> and surrounding
islands.
   Tropical storm watches for the islands of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> and <PERSON>St.
Vincent</PERSON> were discontinued, and a warning for <LOCATION>St. Lucia</LOCATION> was changed
to a tropical storm watch.
   Forecasters said waves 10 feet above normal could be expected
near the eye of Hugo, and warned of heavy rain and flooding.
   In <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION>, the first two islands directly in
Hugo's path, civil defense officials prepared to evacuate people to
rescue shelters.
   <PERSON>Franklin McDonald</PERSON>, head of the Pan-Caribbean Disaster
Preparedness and <ORGANIZATION>Prevention Project</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>, said several relief
teams from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> already were headed to the region.
   State radio said a heavy downpour set off a landslide early
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> on <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION>'s isolated southeast side, which faces the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, partly blocking a road but causing no injuries. The <ORGANIZATION>Public
Works Department</ORGANIZATION> deployed earth-moving equipment at strategic points
across the island.
   Non-critically ill patients at <ORGANIZATION>Princess Margaret Hospital</ORGANIZATION> in the
capital of <LOCATION>Roseau</LOCATION> were sent home late <DATE>Friday</DATE> and early <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to
make room for possible hurricane victims.
   The government of <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION> urged its citizens via radio to take
emergency precautions, and said police were put on alert ``to deal
with any security problem which might arise.'' There was widespread
looting after Hurricane David battered the tiny island of 81,000
people.
   In <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, which has a population of 340,000, heavy traffic
built up in Pointe-a-Pitre, the biggest city, late <DATE>Friday</DATE> as people
rushed supermarkets and hardware stores, stocking up on food,
bottled water and supplies such as flashlights, batteries, timber,
nails and tape.
   The government ordered all pedestrians and cars to be off the
streets by <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> in what amounted to a curfew. The directions were
broadcast on radio stations.
   Residents boarded up doors and windows of their homes and many on
the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> side fled inland.
   At Le <ORGANIZATION>Meridien</ORGANIZATION>, a luxury, 271-room beachfront hotel in <LOCATION>St.
Francois</LOCATION>, a woman who answered the telephone said guests were being
moved from ground-floor rooms and those facing the ocean. But she
said none of the 100 guests had checked out.
   ``Many people are worried; nobody's hysterical,'' said the hotel
employee, who asked not to be identified by name.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air France</ORGANIZATION> canceled all three of its flights scheduled
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> to <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>'s sister island, <LOCATION>Martinique</LOCATION>, and <ORGANIZATION>British
Airways</ORGANIZATION> canceled its flight from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>, where the
airport was closed.
   Officials in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> said up to 6,000 people might have to be
evacuated from flood-prone areas if Hugo passes near the densely
populated island of 3.3 million.
   Hugo is the eighth named storm of the current <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane
season, which runs from <DATE>June 1</DATE> to <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890918-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-89 1833EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Hugo 3rdLd-Writethru a0720 09-18 1115</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0720,1144</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hurricane Lashes Puerto Rico, Leaves At Least 14 Dead in Caribbean</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS graf 13 beginning `At 3 p.m. ...' with two grafs to UPDATE
with latest storm coordinates, wind speed, directions. Picks up graf 14
pvs, `Meteorologist Jesse ...' DELETES final graf to trim.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo's 125 mph winds
pounded <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> after ripping across other islands in
the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>, leaving at least 14 people dead and thousands
homeless.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said Hugo, the most powerful storm
to hit the region this decade, slammed into the eastern tip of
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> and skirted the northern coast before roaring to the
west-northwest toward the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   Hugo also threatens the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>, which shares the
island of Hispaniola with <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION>, and civil defense authorities in
the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION> before dark <DATE>Monday</DATE> declared a state of
emergency.
   <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Airlines</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Karen Ceremsak</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> said the
carrier flew a special <ORGANIZATION>Boeing</ORGANIZATION> 727 charter to the Dominican resort of
<LOCATION>Puerto Plata</LOCATION> <DATE>Monday</DATE> and returned to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> with about 135 vacationers.
   The storm's winds overturned cars and stripped roofs off houses
and office buildings and sent chunks of concrete plunging into
streets in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, where one-third of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> commonwealth's 3.3
million people live. Fifty airplanes were reported destroyed at the
airport in <LOCATION>Isla Verde</LOCATION>.
   There was widespread damage in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Condado Beach</LOCATION> area, the
site of many of the island's large tourist hotels. Shattered glass,
strips of roofing and overturned trees littered the streets, and few
drivers ventured out in their vehicles.
   Hugo cut power and disrupted international communications to the
island.
   One woman in a <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> high-rise told radio station WOSO of
watching sections of the city darken as the first high winds and
heavy rains hit <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>. Widespread power outages also were
reported in the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>.
   There were no immediate reports of casualties in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>
although one man was electrocuted while trying to remove a
television antenna as he prepared for the storm <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Bands of people, mostly youths, looted storm-damaged shops in <LOCATION>San
Juan</LOCATION> and police patrols were reinforced at the main <ORGANIZATION>Post Office</ORGANIZATION>,
political party offices and shopping areas.
   In a boutique on the ground floor of the two-story building
housing <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> bureau in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, young looters
defied winds hitting 100mph at the peak of the storm and carried out
armloads of women's clothing.
   The storm blew out the windows in the AP office on a peninsula
between the sea and <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION> harbor, destroying its computers and
office equipment. One staffer said his furniture was blown out the
windows of his apartment on the 20th story of his building.
   At <TIME>6 p.m. EDT</TIME>, Hugo's center was latitude 19.5 degrees north and
longitude 67.0 west, or 90 miles northwest of <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>, said the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>. It said Hugo was
moving 13 mph in a wobbly, west-northwest to northwest direction.
   Maximum sustained winds declined slightly over the day, to 115
mph, and hurricane-force winds extended up to 75 miles from its
center, the forecasters added.
   Meteorologist <PERSON>Jesse Moore</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> said
it was too early to tell whether Hugo would strike the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
mainland. He said the storm was expected to be off southeastern
Bahamas by <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and ``after that, it's anybody's guess.''
   Five people were reported killed, 80 injured and more than 10,000
homeless <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on the French island of <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>, relief officials
said. Two people were killed in <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Beacon Radio</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Anguilla</LOCATION>, and there were reports of six deaths in <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Richard Weening</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean
Communications Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which operates the <ORGANIZATION>GEM Radio Network</ORGANIZATION> from its
headquarters on <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>, said ham operators linked to the network
said the storm killed six people on the <LOCATION>British Island</LOCATION> and damaged
<PERCENT>95 percent</PERCENT> of the homes and the hospital.
   Nearly all of <LOCATION>Montserrat</LOCATION>'s 12,000 residents were homeless and
without food or fresh water, said ham radio operator <PERSON>Stuart Haimes</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Queens</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>
   Off <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>, charter boat captain <PERSON>O.B. O'Brian</PERSON> told <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> TV
station WTVJ that many boats and homes had been damaged. ``I'd say
the island is pretty well devastated,'' he said.
   Most of the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>' 106,000 residents live on <LOCATION>St. Thomas</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION>. On <ORGANIZATION>St. Croix</ORGANIZATION>, a ham radio operator said the winds
tore off the roofs from up to <PERCENT>75 percent</PERCENT> of the homes.
   Officials said stores in the <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION> town of <LOCATION>Christiansted</LOCATION> were
heavily damaged, and there were reports of looting. National Guard
Adjutant Gen. <PERSON>Robert Moorehead</PERSON> said 1,000 people were evacuated to
rescue shelters in <LOCATION>St. Croix</LOCATION>.
   Storm watches were in effect for parts of the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>,
and a hurricane warning was issued for the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
including the Turks and Caicos islands.
   The weather service said winds ripped the roof off a baseball
stadium on <LOCATION>Vieques</LOCATION>, an island with 7,000 residents 10 miles east of
<LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bernard Sternberg</PERSON>, a Sunrise, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, ham radio operator, said he
talked to a radio operator who was on a boat in the eye of the
hurricane as it passed over <LOCATION>Vieques</LOCATION>. ``He asked us to pray for him
and we did,'' <PERSON>Sternberg</PERSON> said. ``We prayed for all of them.''
   High winds <DATE>Sunday</DATE> blew roofs off six houses in the offshore
island of <LOCATION>Culebra</LOCATION>. San Juan's <ORGANIZATION>Luis Munoz Marin International
Airport</ORGANIZATION>, by far the region's biggest, was closed, as were schools,
banks, courts and government offices.
   <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Lt. Cmdr. <PERSON>Steve Burnett</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Atlantic Fleet</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, reported ``some damage to buildings and housing'' at
<ORGANIZATION>Roosevelt Roads Naval Station</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>'s northeastern coast.
``At this point, we don't know the extent of the damage,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Burnett</PERSON> said all <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> ships that had been operating in the area
moved north over the last 48 hours.
   Residents of hilly areas where flash floods are a danger were
urged to evacuate, and <ORGANIZATION>Social Services</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Carmen Sonia Zayas</PERSON>
said 11,300 people were moved from flood-prone coastal areas to
rescue shelters.
   The <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> were last hit by a major
hurricane in <DATE>1956</DATE>, when <PERSON>Betsy</PERSON> caused extensive damage and killed 11
people in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>.
   Hugo is the fourth hurricane of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> hurricane season and
is the most powerful hurricane to hit the region since Hurricane
David in <DATE>1979</DATE>. That storm killed an estimated 1,200 people in the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>French Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> assigned 3,000 soldiers,
two military transport aircraft and four cargo vessels to assist in
restoring communications and emergency services to <LOCATION>Guadeloupe</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891013-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-13-89 1221EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TropicalWeather 2ndLd-Writethru a0545 10-13 0200</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tropical Weather, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0545,0202</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tropical Storm Jerry Forms in Gulf</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 4 grafs to UPDATE with noon position, landfall forecasts.
Picks up 4th graf pvs, `Jerry is....'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MIAMI (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The season's 10th tropical storm formed today after
a depression strengthened rapidly off the Mexican coast,
forecasters said.
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Jerry</PERSON> had maximum sustained winds of 65 mph and
was moving north through the <LOCATION>Gulf of Mexico</LOCATION> at about 8 mph,
   Forecasters predicted some further increase in <LOCATION>Jerry</LOCATION>'s strength
today. They said there was about a <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> chance of the storm's
center passing within 65 miles of various <ORGANIZATION>Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION> points from
<LOCATION>Brownsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Gulfport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION> by <TIME>7 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   At noon <ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>, the storm's center was located at 22.3 north
latitude and 93.4 west longitude, or about 580 miles
south-southwest of <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>.
   Jerry is the first tropical weather system since Hurricane Hugo
ravaged the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> coast <DATE>last month</DATE>.
   Tropical depressions become named tropical storms when maximum
sustained winds reach 39 mph. Hurricanes are declared when winds
hit 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900828-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-28-90 2130EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HurricaneAlphabet 1stLd-Writethru a0588 08-28 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane Alphabet, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0588,0534</SECOND>
<HEAD>South Carolina Coast Dwellers Eye Their G's and H's</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS grafs 14-15 to update with evening storm positions.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>COLUMBIA, S.C. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricanes beginning with G's and H's tend
to make people along the coast a little nervous. There was Hazel in
<DATE>1954</DATE>, <LOCATION>Gracie</LOCATION> in <DATE>1959</DATE>, <PERSON>Gilbert</PERSON> _ which raked the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
And then there was Hugo.
   It's no wonder people are keeping an eye on <PERSON>Gustav</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hortense</PERSON>,
and an ear to the phone at national hurricane central in <LOCATION>Coral
Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   ``People are saying, `It better not come hit us; we just got our
house put back together,' '' said <PERSON>Darryl Graham</PERSON>, an employee at
<ORGANIZATION>Isle of Palms Hardware</ORGANIZATION>.
   Many residents on the Isle of Palms are still living in houses
with plastic covering the holes left by <DATE>last September</DATE>'s Hurricane
Hugo, which killed 29 people in <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> and caused an
estimated <MONEY>$5.9 billion</MONEY> in damage.
   ``Folks around (here) are planning to load everything up and
head out early if it even looks close, but we aren't selling
batteries and water yet,'' he said.
   Despite word from the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> that Hurricane
Gustav and <ORGANIZATION>Tropical Storm Hortense</ORGANIZATION> will skip the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>,
coastal residents are wary.
   Gustav, with winds of 105 mph, began turning north <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
and <PERSON>Hortense</PERSON> is continuing a northward path that should keep both
well out in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Silvia Graff</PERSON>, a meteorologist
with the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>'s hurricane center in <LOCATION>Coral
Gables</LOCATION>.
   ``Fortunately, it looks like the steering currents will keep
both <PERSON>Gustav</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hortense</PERSON> away from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
islands,'' <PERSON>Ms. Graff</PERSON> said.
   ``At least this time around, it looks like <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION> is off
the hook.''
   <PERSON>Ms. Graff</PERSON> said weather service phones were ``ringing off the
hook,'' with many of the calls coming from <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Jackie Ford</PERSON>, a Lady's <LOCATION>Island Marina</LOCATION> dockmaster who is thought by
many in the area to have a sixth sense when it comes to predicting
the landfalls of large storms, said he spent most of <DATE>Monday</DATE>
puzzling over the storms' directions.
   ``I've got just one pin on the chart, and I don't have a good
feeling for it one way or the other,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> said. ``It's a little
too early to tell, but I guarantee you we will be keeping an eye on
both of them.''
   Meteorologists watching <PERSON>Gustav</PERSON> believe it's unlikely the
hurricane will turn toward the <LOCATION>U.S. East Coast</LOCATION> as it makes its way
north.
   At <TIME>6 p.m. EDT</TIME>, <PERSON>Gustav</PERSON>'s center was located near 22 degrees north
latitude and 58 degrees west longitude, or about 425 miles
northeast of <LOCATION>Antigua</LOCATION>. It was moving north at about 13 mph and was
expected to hold that course and speed through <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Tropical Storm <PERSON>Hortense</PERSON> remained a danger only to shipping. The
storm was centered near 23.2 degrees north latitude and 45.5
degrees west longitude, or about 1,420 miles west-northwest of the
<LOCATION>Cape Verde</LOCATION> islands. Little change in its strength was expected
either.
   Tropical depressions become tropical storms when their sustained
top winds reach 39 mph. Tropical storms become hurricanes at 74 mph.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890919-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-89 2346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hugo-Bahamas     09-19 0525</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo-Bahamas,0544</SECOND>
<HEAD>Residents of Bahamas Brace for Hugo's Passage</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NASSAU, Bahamas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Islanders boarded up their homes and
bought supplies <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as Hurricane Hugo, blamed in at least 25
deaths, swept along the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> after leaving an estimated 50,000
people homeless in the eastern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>.
   Weather officials said the hurricane would begin affecting the
British colony of Turks and <LOCATION>Caicos Islands</LOCATION> southeast of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>
chain on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. The storm was moving on a parallel course
east of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>.
   ``All of the islands at some time or another are going to get
some effects (from Hugo),'' said <PERSON>Noel Risnychok</PERSON>, specialist with the
<ORGANIZATION>National Hurricane Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Coral Gables</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
   Weather officials in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> feared Hugo could drift westward
toward more populated islands, including <LOCATION>New Providence</LOCATION>.
   That island, which includes the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> capital city of <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>,
is the most populated with an estimated 135,000 people.
   The government of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> downgraded the hurricane
watch for the central <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> to a tropical storm warning. A
tropical storm warning remained in effect for the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
though it was discontinued for the Turks and <LOCATION>Caicos Islands</LOCATION>.
   At <TIME>10:30 p.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the hurricane's center was near
latitude 23.8 degrees north and longitude 69.5 west, about 190 miles
east northeast of <LOCATION>Grand Turk Island</LOCATION> in the southern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>,
   Hugo was moving in a northwesterly direction at about 12 miles
per hour with its highest sustained winds at 105 mph.
   Government officials in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION> were monitoring the hurricane but
had not made any special preparations <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for Hugo, said <PERSON>Bill
Kalis</PERSON>, press secretary for the government's information office.
   Residents were told to monitor weather advisories but could go
about their daily businesses, he said.
   ``They were telling everybody to get the water, the lamps
handy,'' said <PERSON>Dorothea Seymour of Naussau</PERSON>, who has a stall at The
<ORGANIZATION>Straw Market</ORGANIZATION> on Bay Street. ``We never had a storm here for some
years. We're always hearing about storms, but they never come.
   ``Some people worry, some people don't,'' she said.
   ``Although the indications are that it's going to move east of
the more populated areas, no one is relaxing their vigil because it
can change direction,'' <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Kalis</PERSON> said residents were gathering supplies in preparation.
   ``The stores have reported brisk sales of supplies such as
flashlight batteries and lumber for boarding up windows,'' he said.
   Weather officials in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> said Hugo's threat to the
northwestern <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> has intensified because of the
west-northwestern drift that the hurricane is expected to take.
   ``This westward drift can spell trouble for the northwestern
Bahamas which includes the bulk of the population,'' said <PERSON>Ken
Lightbourne</PERSON>, chief meteorological officer for the government's
weather agency in <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
   Officials with <ORGANIZATION>Paradise Island Airlines</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fort Lauderdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,
said they had not changed flight schedules yet, but were monitoring
the hurricane's path.
   ``We're just keeping a close eye on it like everybody else,''
said <PERSON>Hugh Riesdorph</PERSON>, director of flight operations for the airlines.
   He said the company makes 11 round-trip flights daily from <LOCATION>Fort
Lauderdale</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Paradise Island</LOCATION>, which is linked by a bridge
to <LOCATION>Nassau</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890920-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-20-89 0002EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Hugo 4thLd-Writethru a0800 09-20 1046</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hugo, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0800,1072</SECOND>
<HEAD>Killer Hurricane Devastates Caribbean; Threatens U.S.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `At 10:30 ..., with 2 grafs to include Hugo's
track, speed; picks up 6th graf: `Hurricane warnings ...</HEAD>
