<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891104-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-04-89 0055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange Bjt   11-04 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange, Bjt,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Panel Hands Agent Orange Decision Back to Derwinski</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> will
have to decide without the guidance he was looking for from an
advisory panel whether to award benefits to some <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans
exposed to Agent Orange.
   Derwinski is expected to make the decision around Thanksgiving
as the result of court-ordered regulations for determining the
relationship between exposure to the herbicide exposure and cancer.
   Nearly 12,000 disability claims once denied by the VA are now
pending as a result of a court order issued in <DATE>May</DATE> by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District
<PERSON>Judge Thelton E. Henderson</PERSON> in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.
   Derwinski was looking for the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Hazards Advisory
Committee</ORGANIZATION>, made up largely of scientists, to clear up some of the
arguments over Agent Orange.
   But the panel, in its first ruling on Agent Orange, acknowledged
<DATE>Friday</DATE> that it couldn't come up with a definite conclusion. The
committee said it ``does not find the evidence sufficient at the
present time to conclude that there is a significant statistical
association between exposure to (Agent Orange) and non-Hodgkins
lymphoma.''
   They added they ``cannot rule out such an association.''
   Veterans' groups blame Agent Orange for cancers that have turned
up years later in former soldiers who were exposed when the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> used it to clear jungle area in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> during the war.
   Veterans say their non-Hodgkins lymphoma, soft tissue sarcoma
and other forms of cancer were caused by the defoliant.
   The government has long said that cancers cannot be definitively
linked to Agent Orange. No studies have been undertaken looking at
veterans who were exposed to the chemical because government
scientists contend they cannot create such a sample.
   In his ruling in <DATE>May</DATE>, <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON> said the VA had used criteria
more stringent than <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> intended in a <DATE>1984</DATE> law that ordered
benefits to veterans exposed to the herbicide.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has said the new regulations give <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> the freedom
to give veterans the benefit of the doubt absent any strong
recommendation by the committee, made up largely of scientists.
   The committee will meet in late <DATE>January</DATE> to address studies
covering Agent Orange exposure and soft tissue sarcomas as well as
porphyria cutanea tarda, an ailment that produces chronic skin
lesions. Those are the other two ailments addressed in <LOCATION>Henderson</LOCATION>'s
court ruling.
   Several of <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>'s actions have been interpreted as signs
that he wants to take action, if only limited, in favor of
veterans. Those include his decision not to appeal the <DATE>May</DATE> ruling,
his appointment of retired Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> as a special
adviser and his statements that he will give veterans the benefit
of the doubt.
   Zumwalt ordered spraying of Agent Orange during the war, and a
son who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> died of a cancer believed linked to
exposure.
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>, which has accused the panel of bias,
criticized <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s statement.
   ``They spent entirely too much time on crossing the t's and
dotting the i's,'' said <PERSON>Richard S. Christian</PERSON>, a deputy director of
the <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>.
   The main suspect in Agent Orange is the contaminant dioxin, a
byproduct of industrial processes known to be an extremely potent
carcinogen in laboratory animals. Its effects on humans are less
well documented.
   Of the roughly 230,000 veterans who have told VA they were
exposed to Agent Orange, 635 have documented cases of non-Hodgkins
lymphoma, the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> says.
   There are 35,000 veterans seeking benefits for problems linked
to Agent Orange exposure.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900517-0022 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-90 0231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange     05-17 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,530</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zumwalt Backs Compensation for Vets With Agent Orange-Related
Illness</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Vietnam veterans who suffered cancer and other
diseases after exposure to Agent Orange should receive disability
payments, says a government adviser who had ordered spraying of the
herbicide.
   Retired Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> told a <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans
Affairs</ORGANIZATION> advisory panel that he believed 27 cases of illness, mostly
cancers, could be sufficiently linked to Agent Orange exposure to
justify compensation.
   Zumwalt spoke to the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Hazards Advisory Committee</ORGANIZATION> as
its newest member and as a personal adviser to Veterans Secretary
<PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski Jr</PERSON>.
   The committee on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> began reviewing scientific evidence
on the health effects of Agent Orange.
   Zumwalt speaks from a unique perspective: as commander of naval
forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, he ordered the spraying of the
dioxin-contaminated herbicide, which was used to deny jungle cover
to the enemy.
   In addition, <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>'s son, who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, died of a
cancer linked to Agent Orange exposure, and a grandson has birth
defects linked to exposure.
   Zumwalt urged the panel to take a fresh look at the scientific
evidence on Agent Orange. He also said a study he conducted for
<PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> parallels the work of an independent group of scientists
hired by three veterans' groups.
   That group, the <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange Task Force</ORGANIZATION>, said this month there
was enough evidence to justify compensation for eight diseases or
ailments that have been linked to exposure. The panel said there
were 13 other health problems, mostly cancers, for which there is
sound evidence of connection but not yet enough evidence to justify
compensation.
   ``I suggest to you that any objective review by knowledgeable
experts in the field would predictably lead to much the same
conclusion,'' <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said. He contended the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> panel lcked a
systematic approach or epidemiological perspective.
   Zumwalt went further, saying he believes 27 ailments, mostly
cancers, could be compensated using VA criteria that were adopted
as the result of a court order last year.
   The main diseases cited by the task force, <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> and others
are non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease, soft tissue sarcoma,
chloracne and other skin disorders, liver disorders, a metabolic
disorder known as porphyria cutanea tarda and birth defects.
   Zumwalt's list includes 13 kinds of cancer in addition to those
already cited.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has said it will come up with final rules this year on
compensation. Derwinski must make the decision based on the
recommendations of the 15-member advisory committee, a panel of
scientists and lay people.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> decided in <DATE>March</DATE> to award compensation for 1,800 <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veterans with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. That decision was based on a
<ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> study that found an increased risk of
the disease among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans as a whole. The study was
inconclusive on Agent Orange exposure.
   About 36,000 claimants have been denied compensation despite
their contention that Agent Orange exposure caused their health
problems. About 240,000 say they have been exposed to the herbicide.
   The Zumwalt statement heartened congressional Vietnam-era
veterans who have pushed for legislation to award compensation.
   ``The evidence is there,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Tom Daschle</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-S.D.</LOCATION> ``The
only question left is whether or not the federal government is
willing to accept its responsibility.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900501-0130 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-01-90 1824EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AgentOrange 1stLd-Writethru a0653 05-01 0787</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0653, 760</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Links Agent Orange to Cancer, Other Diseases</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 11th graf pvs, `About 35,000 ...,' to CLARIFY that those
deal with all illnesses, not just non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. Picks up
12th graf pvs, `About 240,000 ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three kinds of cancer and five other diseases
among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans can be traced to exposure to the defoliant
Agent Orange, according to a scientific report released <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by
veterans groups.
   The report, released on the eve of a congressional hearing on a
bill to pay benefits to Agent Orange victims, produced no new
evidence. Rather, it reviewed existing studies.
   Lawmakers pushing the benefits praised the study by the <ORGANIZATION>Agent
Orange Task Force</ORGANIZATION>, seven scientists assembled by the <ORGANIZATION>American
Services Program</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``It is not only appropriate but it is scientifically correct''
to award compensation to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans exposed to the
dioxin-containing defoliant, said <PERSON>Sen. John Kerry</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Mass.</LOCATION>, a
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran and sponsor of <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> legislation to award
compensation.
   The report said proof exists of a ``significant statistical
association'' between herbicide exposure and non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma; soft-tissue sarcoma; chloracne and other skin disorders;
early liver disease; and porphyria cutanea tarda, a metabolic
disorder.
   The scientists also said there was enough evidence to give the
benefit of the doubt in awarding compensation to veterans who were
exposed and suffer from <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease, neurologic and
reproductive problems and developmental problems with their
offspring.
   They say there's limited evidence of an association between
exposure and a large number of cancers, as well as immunological
abnormalities and psychological problems.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> bill has been passed and a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill introduced to
provide benefits to veterans who claim their diseases were a result
of exposure. The bills differ in cost _ <MONEY>$36 million</MONEY> for the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
version and <MONEY>$89 million</MONEY> for the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> version _ length of coverage
and number of diseases covered.
   A Veterans Affairs subcommittee was scheduled to hear testimony
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill sponsored by Rep. <PERSON>Lane Evans</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Ill.</LOCATION>, a
co-chairman of the Vietnam-Era Veterans in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   Both bills would create an independent panel of scientists under
the auspices of the independent <ORGANIZATION>National Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION> to
review herbicide studies. Critics say the government has
intentionally tried to influence the evidence on Agent Orange to
avoid paying benefits.
   VA Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> has decided to award benefits
to non-Hodgkin's lymphoma sufferers who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. That
decision was made <DATE>March 29</DATE> as the result of a study by the <ORGANIZATION>Centers
for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION>.
   About 35,000 veterans have filed claims asserting a connection
between exposure and a variety of ailments. Only a handful _ those
for chloracne _ have been granted.
   About 240,000 veterans believe they may have been exposed to the
herbicide and have requested physical examinations, <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> says. A
total of 12 million gallons of Agent Orange was sprayed during the
war to remove ground cover and crops.
   Agent Orange is a phenoxyacetic herbicide contaminated with
dioxin during manufacture. Dioxin is the main disease-causing
``probable human carcinogen.''
   The scientists on the panel say an influential private study of
<ORGANIZATION>Nitro</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>W.Va.</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Monsanto</ORGANIZATION> workers exposed to dioxin has been
discredited because of allegations of scientific fraud. So has an
important study of industrial workers in <LOCATION>Ludwigshafen</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION>, they said.
   The scientists were especially critical of the VA and <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> for
ignoring animal studies, especially because agencies such as the
<ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> gives them such strong consideration.
   VA scientists say the animal dioxin studies are less reliable
because of the variety of reactions from species to species, and
because there is documented human exposure, said <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman
<PERSON>Donna St. John</PERSON>.
   The two bills cover only a few of the ailments: non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma, soft-tissue sarcoma, melanoma and chloracne. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
version adds melanoma and basal cell carcinoma.
   <PERSON>Oliver Meadows</PERSON>, the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>'s outside <ORGANIZATION>Environmental
Hazards Advisory Committee</ORGANIZATION>, dismissed criticism in the new report
that it ignored a large number of studies and that it used a
``simplistic tallying system'' to weigh data.
   The panel has only examined the connection between Agent Orange
and non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. The new report covers all the possible
ailments.
   The panel found in <DATE>November</DATE> that an association cannot be proved
or disproved. The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> panel meets later this month to consider other
cancer studies.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study of six kinds kinds of cancer found an increased
risk of only one _ non-Hodgkin's lymphoma _ among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.
It found no such increase in soft tissue sarcoma, <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s
disease, and nasal, nasopharyngeal and primary liver cancer.
   The study looked only indirectly at Agent Orange exposure.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 2339EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AgentOrange 1stLd-Writethru   05-16 0537</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0780,510</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zumwalt Urges Agent Orange Compensation</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: ADDS one graf from a0744, IRS rules certain Agent Orange
payments non-taxable</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Vietnam-era commander who advises the
<ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs Department on Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> veterans
should be compensated for 27 cancers or other afflictions he says
were linked to the herbicide.
   Retired Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON>'s assessment came at the
opening of two days of hearings by a VA advisory committee on
health effects related to herbicide exposure.
   The panel's conclusions will help determine whether the VA will
award service-connected disability payments to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans
exposed to the dioxin-contaminated herbicide.
   The department has already decided to award compensation for one
related cancer, non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. That decision was based on
a congressionally mandated study of cancer among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.
The study, however, was inconclusive on Agent Orange exposure.
   Zumwalt was commander of naval forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and ordered
that the herbicide be sprayed. His son, <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt III</PERSON>, was a
patrol boat commander at the time and died two years ago at age 42
of cancer purportedly linked to exposure. A grandson suffers from a
birth defect also purportedly linked to exposure.
   Zumwalt has recently been an adviser to Veterans Secretary
<PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> and is a member of the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>'s advisory <ORGANIZATION>Committee
on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION>.
   He said his conclusions closely paralleled those of a group of
independent scientists retained by the <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam
Veterans of America</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National Veterans Legal Services
Project</ORGANIZATION>.
   That group said <DATE>earlier this month</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>'s advisory <ORGANIZATION>Committee
on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION> ignored a large body of data. The
scientists said they found evidence to compensate veterans for
eight ailments or diseases, and evidence to consider compensating
for 13 others.
   ``I suggest to you that any objective review by knowledgeable
experts in the field would predictably lead to much the same
conclusion,'' <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said compensation could be justified for 27 afflictions,
including soft-tissue sarcoma, chloracne and other skin disorders,
liver disease, <ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease, neurologic defects, birth
defects, leukemia and 13 other cancers.
   Derwinski was still reviewing the private report from <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>
and could not comment on it, said spokeswoman <PERSON>Donna St. John</PERSON>.
   The government and veterans advocates have been at odds for
nearly a dozen years over the link between Agent Orange and various
diseases. The government <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> has concluded
that there is no way to determine which veterans have been exposed.
   Some <MONEY>12 million gallons</MONEY> of the herbicide was sprayed between
<DATE>1965</DATE> and <DATE>1970</DATE>. The herbicide was contaminated during manufacture
probable human carcinogen.
   More than 36,000 veterans have been denied claims as a result of
the impasse. Derwinski, in deciding not to appeal a court case a
year ago, paved the way for the issue to be reconsidered.
   In another development dealing with <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Internal
Revenue Service</ORGANIZATION> said it has declared non-taxable the payments to
veterans from a fund established in <DATE>1984</DATE> by herbicide manufacturers
as a result of a lawsuit. Some 60,000 servicemen who served in
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> from <DATE>1961 through 1972</DATE> or their survivors are eligible for
payments.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900518-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-18-90 0356EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange     05-18 0628</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Report Criticizes VA's Refusal to Compensate Agent Orange-Related
Illness</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A report to Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J.
Derwinski</PERSON> sharply criticizes the government for its longstanding
refusal to compensate <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans for illnesses linked to
Agent Orange exposure.
   The report by Admiral <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> was released the same
day an advisory panel to the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> paved
the way for compensation to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans suffering from a rare
cancer known as soft-tissue sarcoma.
   Derwinski is expected to decide in late <DATE>May</DATE> or early <DATE>June</DATE>
whether to award compensation for that form of cancer.
   ``I hope this is the beginning of the end of the nightmare Agent
Orange victims have suffered,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Thomas A. Daschle</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-S.D.</LOCATION>, a co-chair of the Vietnam-Era Veterans in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> caucus.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA Advisory Committee on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION> made its
recommendation <DATE>Thursday</DATE> after reviewing scientific studies on the
connection between dioxin and herbicide exposure to soft tissue
sarcoma.
   Zumwalt, one of four lay members of the 15-member panel,
criticized the committee <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for its previous handling of the
Agent Orange question. The panel was created by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> to
investigate the link between exposure and a host of ailments,
largely cancers, that <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans have been complaining about
since the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   A federal court order last year, which <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> declined to
appeal, forced the panel to begin its work anew. Although the last
<ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> was sprayed in <DATE>1971</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has awarded only a handful
of Agent Orange claims, and those were all for a skin condition
called chloracne.
   Derwinski decided in <DATE>March</DATE> that all <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans with
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma should be compensated.
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> Veterans of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and outside
scientists commissioned by the two groups have long criticized the
government's refusal to acknowledge health hazards associated with
<ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION>. The herbicide was contaminated with dioxin, labeled a
``probable human carcinogen'' by the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection
Agency</ORGANIZATION>.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> released a report that <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> compiled for
<PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>.
   ``Were the faulty conclusions, flawed methodology and noticeable
bias of the advisory committee an isolated problem, correcting the
misdirection would be more manageable,'' <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> wrote.
   ``But, experience with other governmental agencies responsible
for specifically analyzing and studying the effects of exposure to
Agent Orange strongly hints at a discernible pattern, if not
outright governmental collaboration, to deny compensation to
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans associated with exposure to dioxin,'' he wrote.
   Zumwalt referred to the <ORGANIZATION>federal Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION>,
given responsibility by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> for conducting Agent Orange
studies because of ``evidence of VA's footdragging.''
   Zumwalt repeated allegations raised in a congressional hearing
last <DATE>summer</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> sabotaged its Agent Orange study, suggesting
``that political pressures once again interfered with the kind of
professional, unbiased review <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> had sought to obtain.''
   Compensation for <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> will cost nearly <MONEY>$90 million</MONEY> for
only a few of the ailments linked to the herbicide, the
<ORGANIZATION>Congressional Budget Office</ORGANIZATION> says.
   <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> has maintained it cannot establish who among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veterans was exposed to Agent Orange, making further study
impossible.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said his own review of the scientific evidence suggests
28 ailments, mostly cancers, can be linked to Agent Orange exposure.
   Zumwalt, commander of naval forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, ordered the
spraying of the defoliant in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and lost a son, a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veteran, to a cancer linked to Agent Orange exposure. Zumwalt has
said he nonetheless would have ordered the spraying because it
ultimately saved more lives than it cost.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said the herbicide was used in undiluted form to remove
enemy cover, destroy enemy crops and clear vegetation around
military installations, landing zones, fire base camps and trails.
   He said more was sprayed than records indicate, because of
unofficial uses of the herbicide.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900627-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-90 0346EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange     06-27 0635</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zumwalt Blasts Government Attitude on Dioxin Dangers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A former commander who ordered the spraying of
Agent Orange in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> says veterans aren't the only ones to
suffer from the government's refusal to recognize the herbicide's
trail of cancer and birth defects.
   Testifying <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> before a <ORGANIZATION>House Government Operations</ORGANIZATION>
subcommittee, retired Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> said the
government's attitude casts doubt on how honestly it is dealing
with dioxin exposure in the environment.
   Agent Orange, used in highly concentrated form to remove crops
and enemy cover, was contaminated during its manufacture with
dioxin, an unwanted byproduct that the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Protection
Agency</ORGANIZATION> considers to be a probable cause of cancer.
   The federal <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION>, however, says it cannot
study the health effects of Agent Orange exposure on veterans
because it is impossible to determine reliably who was exposed when
jungles were sprayed to deprive enemy troops of cover.
   Veterans groups contend that military records can match spraying
activities with troop movements. Agent Orange
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>, who commanded naval forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, reported to
Veterans Affairs Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> in <DATE>May</DATE> that the
government and industry ``intentionally manipulated or withheld
compelling information on the adverse health effects'' associated
with exposure to the ingredients of Agent Orange.
   Key among those ingredients is dioxin, although scientists at
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s hearing said other contaminants may also be blamed for
cancers, birth defects and other afflictions.
   ``... The flawed scientific studies and manipulated conclusions
are not only unduly denying justice to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans suffering
from exposure to Agent Orange, they are now standing in the way of
a full disclosure to the American people of the likely health
effects of exposure to toxic dioxins,'' said <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>.
   He reiterated charges by outside scientists that two influential
industry-sponsored studies on plant accidents used fraudulent data,
and that scientists refuse to use animal data clearly showing a
connection between dioxin exposure and disease.
   ``While dioxin apologists concede dioxin's carcinogenic effects
on animals, they insist that humanity has a miraculous dispensation
from the harmful effects dioxin wreaks on other species of the
animal kingdom,'' he said.
   Derwinski retained <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> last fall as an unpaid adviser to
help resolve the Agent Orange question, which has been debated for
two decades.
   Since <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> took over last year as head of the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans
Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION>, compensation to veterans has begun.
   Without stating outright that Agent Orange exposure was the
cause, the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has decided to compensate the few thousand veterans
with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and soft-tissue sarcomas, both rare
forms of cancer.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said in his report <DATE>May 5</DATE> to <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> that based on his
review of scientific literature, those two cancers and 25 other
afflictions should be considered to be linked to Agent Orange.
   Derwinski chose <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> because of his unique position. As a
commander, he ordered the herbicide to be used. Among those serving
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> at the time were <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>'s son Elmo, who later died of
<ORGANIZATION>Hodgkin</ORGANIZATION>'s disease and non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
   Other witnesses said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that more attention needs to be
focused on both key ingredients of Agent Orange, not just the one,
2,4,5-T, that was contaminated with dioxin.
   They said the other ingredient _ 2,4-D _ causes cancers and
other ailments linked to Agent Orange. Evidence shows that 2,4-D
was also contaminated with harmful compounds, some related to
dioxin, they said.
   A so-called phenoxy herbicide, 2,4-D is sold over the counter to
kill dandelions and other lawn weeds. Farmers use it against weeds
in corn, wheat, rice and sorghum.
   The farm-chemical industry believes further research into 2,4-D
is needed, but the ``weight of the evidence'' so far indicates the
risk of harm is relatively small if it exists at all, industry
spokesman <PERSON>Garry Hamlin</PERSON> said in a telephone interview from
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900519-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-19-90 0317EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange     05-19 0385</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>VA to Pay Vietnam Veterans for Soft Tissue Sarcoma</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Administration</ORGANIZATION> has decided to
allow disability payments to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans with soft-tissue
sarcoma, a rare form of cancer linked to Agent Orange exposure.
   Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> announced the action
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, the second time <DATE>this year</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has decided to award
compensation for cancers linked to exposure to the
dioxin-contaminated herbicide that was sprayed in undiluted form
during the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   On <DATE>March 29</DATE>, <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> announced that veterans suffering from
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma would be eligible for compensation.
   <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s decision was based on the recommendations made by the
<ORGANIZATION>VA's Veterans Advisory Committee on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION>, a panel
of outside scientists and lay people. It found <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that there
is ``at least as likely as not'' a significant statistical
association between the disease and exposure to Agent Orange.
   The ruling in <DATE>March</DATE> was based on a study by the <ORGANIZATION>Centers for
Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> study of selected cancers. Researchers found a <PERCENT>50
percent</PERCENT> increased risk of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veterans, but the study looked only indirectly at whether Agent
Orange was the cause.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study found no such increased risk for soft-tissue
sarcoma. But the advisory committee's examination of other
scientific literature relating to herbicide and dioxin exposure
tilted the balance in favor of compensation.
   ``I believe this is another step forward in resolving a most
difficult and emotional issue,'' <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said. ``We intend to
proceed as quickly as possible to award compensation to these
veterans who are so deserving of our care and concern.''
   For years, Veterans have been seeking compensation for diseases
they say were caused by Agent Orange, a combination of two phenoxy
herbicides, one of which was contaminated with the byproduct dioxin.
   As many as 28 health problems, mostly cancers, can be associated
with exposure, according to Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON>, a special
adviser to <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>.
   VA plans to publish its final compensation regulation for
soft-tissue sarcomas in early fall. An estimated 1,100 veterans or
their survivors are expected to receive compensation for
soft-tissue sarcomas to start with. An additional 50 claims
annually are expected thereafter, given the long latency period for
cancer.
   Soft-tissue sarcomas are a group of malignant tumors found on
muscles and connective tissue or in body fat.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900517-0152 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-90 1710EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-AgentOrange     05-17 0610</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zumwalt Says Much More Defoliant Sprayed Than Recorded</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More Agent Orange was sprayed in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> than
official records show, a former commander said in a report <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
that also suggests ``a discernible pattern, if not collaboration,''
to deny veterans compensation.
   Also, a <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION> panel issued a ruling that
brings compensation closer to veterans exposed to the herbicide who
suffer from soft-tissue sarcoma, a rare cancer.
   Admiral <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON>, in his report to Veterans Secretary
<PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON>, said he was certain from his experience that
more Agent Orange was spread than recorded.
   ``Combat units ... frequently conducted `unofficial' sprayings
of Agent Orange obtained from out of channel, and thus unrecorded
sources.'' said <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>.
   ``Additionally, as commander, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Naval Forces, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, I was
aware that <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> issued to Allied forces was frequently used
on unrecorded missions,'' <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said in the report.
   The report, issued <DATE>May 6</DATE>, was released <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, a day after
<PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> told an advisory panel to the VA he believes that 28
diseases are linked to Agent Orange exposure. Zumwalt, a special
adviser to <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>, was recently named to the department's
<ORGANIZATION>Advisory Committee on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION>.
   The panel on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> determined it is as likely as not that a
significant association exists between soft-tissue sarcoma and
Agent Orange exposure.
   Derwinski is to decide by <DATE>June</DATE> whether to award disability
payments to veterans with that disease. Derwinski decided in <DATE>March</DATE>
that all <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma should be
compensated.
   The advisory committee in <DATE>August</DATE> will examine studies relating
dioxin and herbicide exposure to a skin disease known as chloracne,
and a metabolic disorder known as porphyrea cutanea tarda.
   The two reports make it likely that veterans will be compensated
for soft-tissue sarcoma. VA spokesman <ORGANIZATION>Bonner Day</ORGANIZATION> said the
department had no figure on how many Agent Orange claimants said
they have soft-tissue sarcoma.
   Zumwalt's report said the herbicide was used in strengths far in
excess of that suggested by the manufacturers. The makers have
settled a class-action lawsuit brought by afflicted veterans.
   He also criticizes government actions and studies on Agent
Orange, including the activities of the advisory panel.
   His broadsides backed up claims by veterans who have been trying
to get compensation for more than a decade and who claim the
government has had to be pushed to move and has ignored evidence
supporting links between Agent Orange and cancers.
   ``Were the faulty conclusions, faulty methodology and noticeable
bias of the advisory committee an isolated problem, correcting the
misdirection would be more manageable,'' <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> wrote.
   ``But, experience with other governmental agencies responsible
for ... analyzing and studying the effects of exposure to Agent
Orange strongly hints at a discernible pattern, if not outright
governmental collaboration, to deny compensation to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veterans for disabilities associated with exposure to dioxin.''
   Committee chairman <PERSON>Oliver Meadows</PERSON> said he would not comment on
the Zumwalt report.
   Zumwalt ordered the spraying of the defoliant in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and
lost a son, a <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran, to a cancer linked to Agent Orange
exposure.
   About 12 million gallons of the herbicide, which contained
cancer-causing dioxin, was sprayed from <DATE>1965</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE>, according to
records.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said, however, ``a significant, if not major source of
exposure was from non-recorded, non-Ranch Hand operations.'' Ranch
Hand was the name for the aircraft spraying operation.
   ``Evidence readily suggests that at the time experts knew that
Agent Orange was harmful to military personnel,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> said that in addition to removing enemy cover and
destroying crops, the herbicide was sprayed to clear vegetation
around military installations, landing zones, fire base camps and
trails.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900330-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-30-90 0309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CDC-Veterans     03-30 0651</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC-Veterans,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>VA Compensation Decision Doesn't Resolve Agent Orange Controversy</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The decision by the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs
Department</ORGANIZATION> to award compensation to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans suffering from
one rare form of cancer doesn't resolve the dispute over exposure
to Agent Orange.
   The decision, announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, could make it possible for the
VA to close the doors to compensation for a host of ailments linked
to the herbicide used in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> from <DATE>1965</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE> to deny jungle
cover to the enemy.
   Based on a study released the same day by the federal <ORGANIZATION>Centers
for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON>
said he would award 100 percent disability payments to any <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
veteran suffering from non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
   Payments would be retroactive, and widows and children would
receive survivors' benefits as well. More than 1,800 veterans or
their survivors could receive compensation as a result, according
to <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> data, at a cost of <MONEY>$23 million</MONEY> the first year and about <MONEY>$25
million</MONEY> in subsequent years.
   Veterans advocates were pleased with the immediate decision but
remained skeptical about the study's application to the larger
Agent Orange questions. The government has insisted there is no
scientific proof of a link between the herbicide and a host of
ailments, mostly cancers.
   ``When the study was designed, <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> admitted that the study
population was significantly diluted with unexposed veterans, that
it lacked a meaningful measure of exposure and that it lacked the
statistical power to detect anything less than a <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT>
increase in certain cancers,'' said <PERSON>Sen. Thomas A. Daschle</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Daschle</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-S.D.</LOCATION>, is co-chairman of the Vietnam-Era Veterans in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress Caucus</ORGANIZATION> and wrote legislation to make the disease and
others suspected of having a link with <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> exposure
service-connected.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> ``Selected Cancers Study'' looked at the occurrence of
cancer in all <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans in relation to men who did not serve
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>. Non-Hodgkin's lymphoma was the only cancer found in the
study to have had an unusually high incidence.
   Derwinski was initially very careful to say his decision was not
an Agent Orange decision, but he and his aides were fuzzier in
later remarks.
   Derwinski at one point said he made his determination based at
least in part on the work of a VA-commissioned panel of outside
scientists. That group reported <DATE>last November</DATE> that it could not
find, but neither could it rule out, a statistically significant
association between Agent Orange exposure and non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma.
   As a result of that finding, <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> had said he would
postpone a decision on Agent Orange compensation until after the
<ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study. He had planned, however, to wait for the advisory
panel's recommendation in <DATE>May</DATE>.
   Derwinski jumped the gun <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, but he insisted the panel
would continue its work on the Agent Orange issue. Derwinski is
also consulting with <PERSON>Elmo Zumwalt</PERSON>, the retired admiral who ordered
Agent Orange spraying and whose son died of a cancer linked to
exposure.
   Some 36,000 Agent Orange claims have been made for the lymphoma
and other ailments have been made, and almost all have been
rejected. About 230,000 veterans have asserted they have been
exposed to Agent Orange.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study left some questions unresolved. It noted, for
example, that <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> veterans were more inclined to get the disease
even though they were least likely to have been exposed to Agent
Orange. It also said the lowest incidence was among veterans of <ORGANIZATION>III
Corps</ORGANIZATION>, the area of highest Agent Orange use.
   <PERSON>John Hanson</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION> official, said the study
neglected to point out that the <ORGANIZATION>III Corps</ORGANIZATION> area included <LOCATION>Saigon</LOCATION>,
which wasn't sprayed.
   Deputy Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Anthony J. Principi</PERSON> said VA was making
the presumption that any veteran who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> was exposed
to Agent Orange. But <PERSON>Hanson</PERSON> said such a determination dilutes any
statistical sample to the point where an Agent Orange determination
is impossible.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900626-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-90 2046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgentOrange     06-26 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Testify That Weedkillers May be More Harmful Than
Thought</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Garry in 7th graf and Shelia in 10th graf are cq</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Farmers and homeowners frequently use
weedkillers that contain a key ingredient of Agent Orange that may
be more harmful than previously thought, scientists told a
congressional panel <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``It appears to me that there are other contaminants in
herbicides, as well as herbicides per se, which have not been
adequately evaluated for carcinogenicity in animals let alone
studied for their effect ... in humans,'' <PERSON>Daniel Thau Teitelbaum</PERSON>, a
<LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> physician, told a <ORGANIZATION>House Government Operations</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee.
   Teitelbaum studied industry records as part of the class-action
lawsuit by <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans against the makers of Agent Orange.
   In the 20 years of controversy surrounding whether the
government should pay benefits to ailing <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans who were
exposed to Agent Orange, attention has focused on dioxin
contamination 2,4,5-T _ one of the herbicide's two key ingredients.
``probable human carcinogen'' and 2,4,5-T has been out of
circulation for years.
   But scientists told the subcommittee that the other key
ingredient _ 2,4-D _ causes cancers and other ailments linked to
Agent Orange. Evidence shows that 2,4-D was also contaminated with
harmful compounds, some related to dioxin, according to testimony
on the government handling of Agent Orange research.
   The farm-chemical industry says ongoing research into 2,4-D is
needed but that the ``weight of the evidence'' so far indicates the
risk of harm is relatively small if it does indeed exist, industry
spokesman <PERSON>Garry Hamlin</PERSON> said in a telephone interview from
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>.
   A so-called phenoxy herbicide, 2,4-D is sold over the counter to
kill dandelions and other lawn weeds. Farmers use it against weeds
in corn, wheat, rice and sorghum.
   Teitelbaum, noting that use of 2,4,5-T was first discontinued
because of concern about birth defects, said studies were needed on
possible birth defects resulting from 2,4-D exposure.
   Two <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer Institute</ORGANIZATION> studies have shown an increased
risk of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, a rare cancer, in ``frequent users
of agriculture chemicals,'' said <ORGANIZATION>NCI</ORGANIZATION> researcher <PERSON>Shelia Hoar Zahm</PERSON>.
   The studies of farm workers in <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> found that
the risk grows or drops according to skin exposure and how soon
after exposure the worker changed clothes.
   Vietnam veterans were exposed to Agent Orange in concentrations
far in excess of the normal strength, special adviser <PERSON>Elmo R.
Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> has told the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION>.
   The department said this year it would compensate veterans for
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and for another rare cancer _ soft tissue
sarcoma. However, the government maintains that exposure can't be
documented.
   Zumwalt, a retired admiral, ordered Agent Orange sprayed in
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to clear dense jungle. His son, who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>,
later died of cancer, which <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> attributes to Agent Orange. he
said 27 ailments can be linked to Agent Orange.
   Zumwalt, appearing before the subcommittee on human resources
and intergovernmental relations, reiterated his contention that
government and industry officials ``intentionally manipulated or
withheld compelling information on the adverse health effects
associated with exposure to the toxic contaminants contained in
Agent Orange.''
   In a related matter, Rep. <PERSON>Ted R. Weiss</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-N.Y.</LOCATION>, said his
subcommittee had forced the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> to release a 4-year-old draft
report showing an increase of birth defects among the offspring of
those who handled and sprayed Agent Orange from the air.
   <PERSON>Patti Turner</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force Surgeon General</ORGANIZATION>'s
office, said the conclusions were premature.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891030-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-30-89 0050EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange Bjt   10-30 0739</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange, Bjt,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veterans' Administration to Reconsider Agent Orange Issue</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An advisory committee to the <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> this week may open the door a crack to disability
benefits for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans exposed to Agent Orange.
   Responding to a federal court decision in <DATE>May</DATE>, the 15-member
Veterans' <ORGANIZATION>Advisory Committee on Environmental Hazards</ORGANIZATION> will look
again at scientific papers and studies on the herbicide used to
clear dense foliage that hid the enemy.
   This time, however, the committee will use standards considered
less strict than those used for determining other service-connected
disabilities.
   No one is predicting the outcome. But there is agreement that VA
Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> wants to resolve the issue quickly
and in favor of veterans.
   ``I don't think he's going to fool around very long,'' <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>
spokesman <PERSON>Don Smith</PERSON> said. ``He's so far exhibited a degree of
willingness _ if not impatience _ to go along rather rapidly with
this.''
   Once the committee does its work <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> is ``kind of on his
own as to how he wants to fly on this,'' <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> said. He said
<PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> will make a final determination on the committee's
recommendations within two weeks of receiving results of the
meeting.
   According to one congressional source, <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>'s actions mean
``he's almost promised people'' that he will take some positive
action for veterans.
   Veterans blame exposure to Agent Orange for cancers, skin
diseases and genetic damage leading to miscarriages or birth
defects. The committee will spend its first two days reviewing
about 20 or 30 studies on the connection between exposure and
non-Hodgkins lymphoma, one of the most frequently cited cancers,
then study other diseases at later meetings.
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, it will issue recommendations on non-Hodgkins
lymphoma and Agent Orange.
   The four-year-old advisory committee and government scientists
have thus far rejected a link between Agent Orange exposure and
health problems other than a skin condition known as chloracne.
   The <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>, the prime veterans' group in this dispute,
contends the committee has a longstanding bias against veterans.
   Not so, says <PERSON>Oliver Meadows</PERSON>, the disabled veteran and scientific
layman in charge of the panel. ``Their greatest interest is their
own integrity as scientists,'' he said.
   The government says the main problem with studies up to now is
that there has been no way to verify exposure to dioxin. The
<ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION> and others say the government has detailed records
on spraying activities that can be combined with equally detailed
records on troop movements.
   Agent Orange, an orange-brown liquid that was shipped in
orange-striped barrels, was sprayed in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> from <DATE>January 1965</DATE> to
<DATE>April 1970</DATE>. More than 230,000 veterans have registered with VA
claiming to have been exposed. More than 36,000 veterans have filed
for disability benefits claiming Agent Orange exposure caused their
problems, and two have been granted compensation _ for chloracne.
   Agent Orange is suspect because it contains ``phenoxy''
herbicides associated with certain cancers as well as dioxin, which
has been found to cause cancer in laboratory animals.
   Dioxin's links to human health problems are disputed, although
its links to human birth defects are more firmly established.
   A ruling in <DATE>May</DATE> by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Thelton E. Henderson</PERSON> in
<LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> created a way out of the impasse over <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION>. A
new administration and the elevation of the Veterans'
Administration to cabinet status added another ingredient.
   Henderson ruled <DATE>May 2</DATE> that the VA imposed an ``impermissibly
demanding test'' for linking Agent Orange with health problems.
   Although the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has relied on a ``cause and effect''
relationship in determining service-connected disabilities, the
committee was to use a different standard: ``a significant
statistical association.''
   Derwinski told Attorney General <PERSON>Richard L. Thornburgh</PERSON> on <DATE>May 8</DATE>
that he had decided against an appeal.
   New regulations for reviewing studies using the new standard,
effective <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, say a link will be deemed to exist if the
studies associating Agent Orange with health problems outweigh the
evidence that there is no association.
   The regulations say the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> secretary can give the ``benefit of
the doubt to the conclusion that the association exists.''
   In early <DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> named Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON> as a
special adviser with a specific emphasis on Agent Orange.
   Zumwalt ordered spraying of Agent Orange during <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, and he
lost a son who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to a cancer linked with that
spraying. Zumwalt is known as a veterans' advocate on this issue.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900803-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-03-90 0315EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-AgentOrange     08-03 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agent Orange Compensation Back in Federal Court</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The dispute over compensating <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans
for a host of cancers and other ailments believed to be linked to
Agent Orange exposure is back in federal court.
   In a lawsuit filed here <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, two veterans groups asked that
federal scientists be forced to complete a study on the health
effects of Agent Orange on <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans and their children.
   The suit said the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration ordered the study
canceled in <DATE>1987</DATE>, four years after it began, because of concerns
that civilian claims against government and industry would follow a
decision to compensate veterans.
   The suit was filed in <ORGANIZATION>U.S. District Court</ORGANIZATION> by the <ORGANIZATION>American
Legion</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> Veterans of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, five individual veterans and
four surviving spouses.
   It said that without the study, mandated by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, it
is impossible to persuade the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION> to award
disability and death payments to thousands of veterans who were
exposed to the dioxin-contaminated defoliant.
   The herbicide, used to destroy ground cover and crops, has been
blamed by veterans groups for 19 cancers and a variety of other
health problems, including birth defects.
   The VA this year decided to award compensation for two rare
cancers: soft-tissue sarcoma and non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
   The soft-tissue sarcoma decision was based on the
recommendations of an advisory panel acting under a court order to
reconsider the scientific evidence. The lymphoma decision was based
on a <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> study of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans that
only indirectly looked at Agent Orange exposure.
   Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> said the lawsuit will set
back his effort to resolve the Agent Orange dispute. He began that
effort shortly after he took office by deciding not to appeal a <DATE>May
1989</DATE> federal court ruling that VA standards on Agent Orange
disability claims were too strict.
   The ruling in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> came as a result of a lawsuit filed
by the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Veterans of America</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Now, these organizations have acted to return to the courtroom
with litigation aimed at forcing the scientific conclusions they
want,'' <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said. ``Their suit impugns the integrity of
respected scientists at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> whose
work thus far has added much to what we know about the health of
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION>, in canceling the study, said there was no
scientifically valid way to document who was exposed. The American
Legion and independent scientists say records of troop movements
can be matched with spraying records to find the likely exposed
veterans.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900502-0103 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-02-90 1428EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgentOrange     05-02 0579</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Veterans Department Open to Review of Agent Orange Findings</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> opened the
door <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to independent scrutinity of its effort to determine
whether there is a link between exposure to Agent Orange and a
variety of diseases.
   The offer follows years of challenges to the credibility of the
<ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION>. Critics
have charged the government with ignoring the scientific evidence
of a connection between exposure and cancers and other diseases.
   The offer came during testimony by <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> Deputy Secretary <PERSON>Anthony
J. Principi</PERSON> before a <ORGANIZATION>House Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee.
   Principi told the subcommittee on compensation, pension and
insurance that the department would agree to a review by the
<ORGANIZATION>National Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, to having its own panel of outside
scientific advisers enlarged, or to subjecting its work to outside
review.
   Two Agent Orange compensation bills pending in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> call for
establishment of a scientific review procedure through the <ORGANIZATION>National
Academy</ORGANIZATION>, an independent group of scientists that advises the
government.
   ``Should <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> conclude that the process would be lent
credibility by our consulting with additional outside experts ...
we would be pleased to do so if that kind of consultation would not
unduly delay our progress,'' <PERSON>Principi</PERSON> said.
   But <PERSON>Principi</PERSON> also asked the subcommittee to put off
consideration of a compensation bill. The bill would award
service-connected disability payments to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War veterans who
contend they suffer due to exposure from one of four kinds of
cancer or from a skin disease known as chloracne.
   The bill would also pave the way to compensation for other
ailments as the evidence comes in.
   Principi asked that the law be held in abeyance until the VA
comes up with final regulations <DATE>Oct. 1</DATE> on who should be compensated
and for what diseases. Those regulations depend in part on the
recommendations of <ORGANIZATION>VA's Advisory Committee on Environmental
Hazards</ORGANIZATION>, a 15-member panel of scientists and lay persons.
   The committee meets later this month.
   Veterans Affairs Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> has appointed his
personal adviser on the Agent Orange issue, retired Adm. <PERSON>Elmo
Zumwalt</PERSON>, to fill a vacancy on the committee. Zumwalt ordered
spraying of <ORGANIZATION>Agent Orange</ORGANIZATION> during <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and also lost a son who
served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to cancer.
   ``We have, I believe, more than demonstrated our good faith,''
<PERSON>Principi</PERSON> said, saying the VA set its course a year ago when it
decided against appealing a federal judge's order that it draft new
Agent Orange regulations.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> sponsor of the compensation bill, Rep. <PERSON>Lane Evans</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Ill.</LOCATION>, suggested the VA was trying to further postpone delivering
benefits to veterans. There is no guarantee the department will
decide to award compensation in its final rules.
   ``I think you are proceeding on a good-faith basis, but I
believe the veterans who suffer from Agent Orange can't wait,'' he
said.
   <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>' bill would compensate exposed veterans who suffer from
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, soft-tissue sarcoma, melanoma, and basal
cell carcinoma, as well as chloracne. The measure is expected to
cost <MONEY>$89 million</MONEY> a year.
   About 35,000 veterans have filed claims asserting a connection
between exposure to Agent Orange and a host of ailments. Only a
handful of benefits have been granted, for those suffering
chloracne.
``probable human carcinogen,'' is suspected as the primary but not
the only ingredient causing ailments among veterans exposed to
Agent Orange.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900325-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-25-90 1244EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgentOrange     03-25 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,670</SECOND>
<HEAD>Agent Orange Study Expected This Week</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Government scientists are expected to release
a study this week that will help determine officially whether
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans who were exposed to the herbicide Agent Orange
suffered cancers and other ailments as a result.
<ORGANIZATION>Veterans Affairs Department</ORGANIZATION> says will be released <DATE>Thursday</DATE>,
examines the incidence of five kinds of cancer among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vets.
It is another step in a 12-year battle to gain benefits for
veterans who blame cancers, skin disease and miscarriages in their
spouses on the powerful foliage killer.
   VA Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> last <DATE>November</DATE> said he would put
off a determination on whether to award benefits until after the
study was completed. Following its release, the study must be
reviewed by a VA advisory committee of outside scientists.
   Derwinski will make a determination at the end of <DATE>May</DATE> after the
committee meets, <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Don Smith</PERSON> said last week. Final rules
should be in place in <DATE>October</DATE>. The decision also could influence
legislation in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> requiring compensation to
veterans.
   <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said in a recent interview that the decision on Agent
Orange will be the most difficult he's made since becoming the
first <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> secretary a year ago.
   ``The advice is so terribly conflicting,'' he said. ``There's no
consensus out there.''
   Nearly 35,000 claims have been filed citing Agent Orange as a
cause of disabilities. An additional 230,000 veterans have told VA
they were exposed to the herbicide, which contained highly toxic
dioxin and other suspected harmful ingredients.
   The new Selected Cancers Study by the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> does not
look at whether veterans were exposed to Agent Orange, which was
sprayed to remove foliage and kill crops.
   According to the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>, the new study will determine whether
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans are at higher risk of developing soft-tissue
sarcoma, lymphoma and nasal, nasopharyngeal and liver cancer. The
study began in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Chuck Fallis</PERSON> said he could not confirm that the
study would be released <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the day given by the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> and the
<ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>.
   VA says the study can be combined with other studies, mostly
dealing with the exposure of industrial and farm workers to dioxin,
to tilt the balance one way or the other regarding a possible
connection to disorders.
   The Legion, however, is telling veterans not to hold their
breaths.
   ``The government has ducked the issue of Agent Orange for more
than a dozen years,'' National Commander Miles <PERSON>S. Epling</PERSON> said. ``We
are tired of waiting for more studies, especially irrelevant ones.''
   The Legion contends the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> scuttled an earlier attempt at a
study by saying no reliable sample of veterans can be found. The
<ORGANIZATION>Legion</ORGANIZATION> says <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> has ignored detailed military records of troop
movements and spraying activities that could produce such a study
group.
   A Legion study claims to have established a connection between
Agent Orange and skin rashes and blisters, fatty tissue tumors,
hypersensitivity of the eyes to light, and an increased risk of
miscarriages among spouses. The <ORGANIZATION>Legion</ORGANIZATION> says the study was too
limited to reach further conclusions regarding other cancers.
   VA says scientific advisers to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and the administration
have rejected the Legion study because it relied on questionnaires
filled out by the veterans themselves.
   The Agent Orange issue was revived last <DATE>May</DATE> when <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District
<PERSON>Judge Thelton E. Henderson</PERSON> said VA had used too rigid a standard _
cause and effect between exposure and disease _ in evaluating Agent
Orange studies.
   Derwinski decided not to appeal <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>'s order that the VA
need only find a ``significant statistical association'' between
exposure and disease before determining to award compensation.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>'s outside <ORGANIZATION>Environmental Hazards Advisory Committee</ORGANIZATION> met in
<DATE>November</DATE> to review about 30 studies dealing with herbicide exposure
and its relation to non-Hodgkins lymphoma using the new criteria.
   The group said it could neither find nor rule out a significant
statistical association, giving little guidance to <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said afterward he would wait for the new <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study. He
cited remarks by members of the committee that such a study would
be useful.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900329-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-90 2145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-CDC-AgentOrange 2ndLd-Writethru a0715 03-29 0916</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-CDC-Agent Orange, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0715,0939</SECOND>
<HEAD>CDC: `No Evidence' of Cancer Risk From Agent Orange; Vets Assail
Study</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 25th graf, ``Payments, which...,'' to CORRECT
subsequent-year annual cost from $2 million to $25 million.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A long-awaited government study of cancer among
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans found no evidence linking the disease with
exposure to the herbicide Agent Orange, officials said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The study by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION>, which looked
only indirectly at Agent Orange, did find veterans at increased
risk of a relatively rare cancer called non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. But
researchers noted the risk was greater among veterans who served on
ships than those who served on land, where the herbicide was used.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> quickly
said he would order the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> to pay
disability compensation to vets suffering from non-Hodgkin's
lymphoma.
   The study was immediately attacked by veterans groups, which
complained it failed to sufficiently examine the cancer risks among
the thousands of soldiers who actually worked with the dangerous
herbicide during the war.
   ``It is not an Agent Orange study,'' objected <PERSON>Mary R. Stout</PERSON>,
president of the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Veterans of America</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This is only a look at <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans'' who had cancer,
added <PERSON>John Hansen</PERSON>, spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>.
   And <PERSON>Sen. Tom Daschle</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-S.D.</LOCATION>, co-chairman of the Vietnam-Era
Veterans in <ORGANIZATION>Congress Caucus</ORGANIZATION>, said: ``This action has been a long
time coming. However, it is not the final word. We cannot forget
the many other veterans who are also suffering and dying from Agent
Orange-related diseases and who have just as much evidence
supporting their claims.''
   Agent Orange, sprayed by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military to remove jungle
cover and crops in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, contained dioxin, a highly toxic
chemical which some studies have found to increase cancer risks.
   Criticism of the study focused on its methods, which involved
comparing cancer patients of Vietnam-veteran age to healthy
counterparts.
   The study ``only indirectly evaluated'' Agent Orange exposure,
because of the technical difficulties in determining <DATE>two decades
later</DATE> how much a patient may have been exposed to the herbicide,
the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Specific analysis of dioxin exposure was impractical, partly
because researchers don't know how cancer may skew the results of
blood tests for dioxin levels, said <PERSON>Dr. Daniel A. Hoffman</PERSON>,
assistant director for science at the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Center for
Environmental Health</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Our study was designed to look at <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> experience and
history, and secondly to ascertain the likelihood of exposure,''
<PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> said.
   The study, conducted over five years, surveyed 2,067 cancer
patients who were of approximate <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> service age _ between 15
and 39 in <DATE>1968</DATE>, at the height of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troop involvement. They were
compared to 1,776 men of similar age who had no history of cancer.
   Both groups were studied for risk of six kinds of cancer,
including soft tissue cancer and similar sarcomas, a group of
cancers that the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> concedes has been ``of great concern among
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.''
   Vietnam vets were found to have a roughly <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> increased
risk for non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
   ``The study did not find any evidence that the increased risk
might be due to Agent Orange exposure,'' said <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>William
L. Roper</PERSON>.
   That conclusion, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said, came in part because the cancer
risk among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans ``seemed to be the opposite of the
pattern for use of Agent Orange.''
   Vets from the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s ocean ships had somewhat higher cancer
risks than those who served on land. And veterans from the region
of heaviest Agent Orange use were at ``somewhat lower risk'' than
others, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Specifically, the yearly risk of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma is about
one in 10,000 for men <DATE>35-59</DATE>, the age group of most <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vets.
The risk for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vets overall is about 1.5 per 10,000, <PERSON>Roper</PERSON>
said.
   The risk nearly doubled _ <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> higher _ for <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> veterans
stationed on ocean ships.
   The <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> higher risk is what epidemiologists call ``a weak
association,'' <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> said: It is statistically significant, but
``anything less than a twofold increase can sometimes be caused by
other factors.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> found ``no increased risk'' for sarcomas, usually
cancers of the body's connective tissues, or for other cancer types.
   The VA had been awaiting the study before deciding whether to
award benefits to vets exposed to Agent Orange. Nearly 35,000
claims have been filed citing the chemical as a cause of
disabilities including cancer, skin disease and miscarriages by
soldiers' wives.
   In announcing the non-Hodgkin's lymphoma benefits, <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>
mentioned only the link between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> service and the lymphoma.
He didn't say the connection was because of Agent Orange.
   Payments, which would be retroactive, are expected to cost <MONEY>$23
million</MONEY> the first year and <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> a year in succeeding years,
VA officials said. Based on the study, the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> estimated 1,800
veterans are due compensation, and there will be 450 new cases each
year.
   The complaints before the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> aren't the only ones about Agent
Orange. A class-action lawsuit against the seven manufacturers of
Agent Orange was settled in <DATE>1984</DATE> in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District Court in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, and payments began last year.
   The court has estimated that 30,000 veterans and 18,000 survivor
families would be eligible for benefits from a settlement fund of
at least <MONEY>$240 million</MONEY>.
   The settlement's court-appointed administrator, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
attorney <PERSON>Kenneth Feinberg</PERSON>, had yet to see the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study and
couldn't say what effect, if any, it might have on the case, his
office said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900521-0004
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900521-0004.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   VA to Give Benefits
   To Vietnam Veterans
   With Some Cancers
</HL>
<DATE>
05/21/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A7A
</SO>
<IN>
INSURANCE (INS)
</IN>
<GV>
VETERANS AFFAIRS DEPARTMENT (VET)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Department of Veterans Affairs for the
first time acknowledged a link between cancer and exposure to
Agent Orange, a herbicide used in the Vietnam War, and
announced it will pay disability benefits to Vietnam veterans
with soft-tissue sarcomas.
   In March, the VA said it would grant disability benefits
to Vietnam veterans with non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, another rare
cancer. It was the first time the government recognized a
connection between cancer and service in Southeast Asia. That
conclusion was based on a Centers for Disease Control study
that found a correlation between non-Hodgkin's lymphoma and
service in Vietnam.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study didn't find any connection betwen
exposure to Agent Orange and cancer. Veterans groups have
long contended that exposure to Agent Orange has led to a
higher incidence of cancer among <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans, and in its
ruling <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the VA department conceded that there may be
such a connection.
   The latest decision rejects part of the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study, which
didn't find a link between service in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and five other
cancers, including soft-tissue sarcomas. But a VA advisory
committee reviewed scientific literature on the connection
between soft-tissue sarcomas and exposure to herbicides
containing dioxin and recommended that cancers be considered
service-connected and eligible for benefits.
   The ruling by <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Edward Derwinski</PERSON> means that
approximately 1,100 veterans or their survivors will qualify
for compensation. The department estimates it will recognize
an additional 50 new claims a year for soft-tissue sarcomas,
which are difficult-to-diagnose tumors found on muscles and
connective tissue or in body fat. The VA projects it will pay
about <MONEY>$8 million</MONEY> a year as a result of the decision.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890512-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-12-89 0111EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-VA-AgentOrange Bjt   05-12 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-VA-Agent Orange, Bjt,730</SECOND>
<HEAD>VA to Reopen Agent Orange Files</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX12</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WILLIAM M. WELCH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION> is taking
another look at the cases of all <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans whose benefits
claims due to exposure to Agent Orange were denied, and easing the
standards for receiving compensation.
   The change became known <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Edward
Derwinski</PERSON> said the government will not appeal a federal judge's
decision earlier this week that struck down regulations restricting
compensation for victims of Agent Orange.
   <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>'s decision was seen as a major step toward disability
benefits for some of the more than 34,000 veterans of the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
War who have unsuccessfully sought to have the government admit
their exposure to the toxic herbicide has caused health problems.
   <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> will follow the judge's instructions to
review all previously denied claims and use new, statistical
standards to decide whether specific diseases are presumed to have
been caused by Agent Orange exposure.
   ``It's a very significant step,'' said <PERSON>Mary Stout</PERSON>, president of
the <ORGANIZATION>Vietnam Veterans of America</ORGANIZATION>, a 35,000-member group that filed
suit over the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION>'s denial of benefits in Agent Orange cases. ``I
think it does show that there's a new Veterans Administration and a
new administration that's taking a different view of the Agent
Orange situation.''
   Agent Orange was widely sprayed by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> as a
defoliant. Its medical effects years and decades later on the
soldiers who handled it or were exposed to it have been the subject
of intense legal and scientific debate.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> District <PERSON>Judge Thelton Henderson</PERSON> ruled this week in <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION> the VA had used an ``impermissibly demanding test'' in
requiring proof of a cause-and-effect relationship between exposure
to Agent Orange and specific diseases.
   Instead, he said, the agency should require only a finding of a
statistically significant correlation or ``increased risk of
incidence'' _ a less difficult standard to meet.
   Derwinski, a veteran and former member of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, said he had
begun ``a good hard look'' at the department's Agent Orange policy
even before the federal judge's ruling. He said he concluded it was
not good policy and ``frankly not good politics'' to fight the
ruling.
   VA officials said the department will direct its 11-member
scientific committee that reviews Agent Orange issues to take a new
look at all scientific and medical studies of Agent Orange using
the new statistical standard.
   <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said he expected final decisions on the diseases by
<DATE>October</DATE>.
   Deputy Secretary <PERSON>Anthony Principi</PERSON> said the VA would consider any
veteran who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to have been exposed to Agent Orange
and would not require specific proof they were in an area where the
herbicide was sprayed.
   The department, which until this year was known as the <ORGANIZATION>Veterans
Administration</ORGANIZATION>, has consistently held that only one disease, a skin
condition known as chloracne, was caused by exposure to <ORGANIZATION>Agent
Orange</ORGANIZATION> during military service.
   As a result the <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has denied disability compensation for
veterans who claimed exposure to other diseases, including cancer.
The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> has provided medical treatment for those conditions, however.
   Whether those cancers and other illnesses can be linked
statistically to Agent Orange exposure has been a matter of
dispute. Derwinski's decision puts that question before the VA's
panel of scientists and other experts, which had concluded there
was no scientific link based on the previous standard.
   Derwinski and other VA officials said they had no way to
estimate the potential cost to the government in added benefits to
veterans if the panel agrees to a statistical assumption that
additional diseases were caused by Agent Orange exposure.
   ``The cost is irrelevant,'' <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> said.
   Rep. <PERSON>G.V.</PERSON> ``Sonny'' <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Miss.</LOCATION>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>House
Veterans Affairs Committee</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON>'s decision was in line
with congressional wishes that compensation be decided ``on the
basis of sound scientific and medical evidence.''
   ``The judge has said that the department has written the
regulations too narrowly and the department has agreed to go back
and rewrite them,'' <PERSON>Montgomery</PERSON> said. ``I think the secretary has
made the right decision.''
   Of the claims related to Agent Orange already filed, nearly
7,000 involve three main categories of illness _ non-Hodgkins
lymphoma, soft-tissue sarcoma and a liver ailment known as PCT _
for which some contend links to Agent Orange have been established.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900620-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-90 0231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-VietnamDogs     06-20 0675</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Vietnam Dogs,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Study: Vietnam Military Dogs Had Almost Twice as Many Testicular
Tumors</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Dogs exposed in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> to the same chemical
sprays as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> soldiers developed almost twice as many tumors of
the testicles as military dogs that served only in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, federal investigators report.
   In a study published <DATE>today</DATE> in the Journal of the <ORGANIZATION>National Cancer
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, researchers said the increased number of testicular
cancers among canine veterans of <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> may predict the
development of such tumors among American servicemen who served in
the same country.
   ``The dog is a sentinel model for man,'' said <PERSON>Howard M. Hayes</PERSON>, a
``He could be used to foretell the risks for exposure to the same
chemical insults'' encountered by soldiers in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> and his coauthors examined autopsy records for dogs that
served with American troops in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> from <DATE>1968</DATE> to <DATE>1973</DATE>. They also
examined autopsy records of dogs that served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and later
died elsewhere.
   These records then were compared with those of military dogs
that served only in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> said the dogs serving in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> had <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> more
testis tumors of all kinds than did dogs that served only in the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> dogs also had <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> more seminomas,
a malignant tumor of the testis.
   Dogs serving in <LOCATION>Korea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> had fewer of both
types of tumors than did the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dogs.
   To further verify the risks, <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> said his group examined
records of 96 male dogs that served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and died elsewhere
between <DATE>1974</DATE> and <DATE>1978</DATE>. These records were compared with those of
dogs that served only in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and died during the same
period.
   ``We observed the 96 <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran military working dogs to
have significant excess risk for seminoma, which supported the
findings in the earlier period,'' the report said.
   Additionally, the study showed that dogs that served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
had <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>100 percent</PERCENT> more testicular dysfunction than did
dogs that served only in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> said about <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of the military dogs in the study
were German shepherds, a breed that has a predisposition to
testicular tumors.
   As a result, he said, the dogs ``may be a particularly sensitive
sentinel for exposures leading to increase seminoma risk in man.''
   Dogs in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> said, served side-by-side with infantry
troops and were exposed to the same chemical sprays, such as the
herbicide Agent Orange, as were the soldiers.
   Unlike most of the humans, however, the dogs' tours in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>
were not limited to one year.
   Additionally, <PERSON>Hayes</PERSON> said the dogs in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> were treated
several times with tetracycline, an antibiotic used to control a
tick-borne parasitic disease. The tetracycline, the study said,
``may have contributed to the increased risk of testicular
problems.''
   Veterans' groups have contended for years that soldiers who
served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> have experienced more cancers and other ailments
as a result of their exposure to chemical sprays while in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
Agent Orange, an herbicide widely used to defoliate the jungle, has
come under particular attack by veterans' groups as the cause of
cancers and skin ailments.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans' Affairs</ORGANIZATION> announced earlier this year
that it would provide compensation to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans who have
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma or soft-tissue sarcoma, two cancers that
have been associated with chemicals in Agent Orange.
   Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON>, a special adviser to Veterans
Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON>, said in an interview that there now
is no compensation provided to <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans who develop
testicular cancers. He said the new study may cause tumors of the
testis to be considered as possibly service-related illnesses for
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.
   ``I've already recommended that testicular cancer be included
and this (the <LOCATION>Hayes</LOCATION> study) is powerful evidence in support of it,''
he said.
   Zumwalt had a son who served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and later died of
cancer, which <ORGANIZATION>Zumwalt</ORGANIZATION> attributed to Agent Orange.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900329-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-29-90 1433EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-CDC-AgentOrange 3rdLd-Writethru a0589 03-29 0814</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC-Agent Orange, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0589,0829</SECOND>
<HEAD>CDC Finds `No Evidence' of Vet Cancer Link to Agent Orange</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS three grafs after 12th, `The Veterans...', to UPDATE
with veterans secretary saying compensation would be paid to
veterans suffering from non-Hodgkin's lymphoma. Picks up 13th graf,
`American Legion...'.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease Control</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> its
long-awaited study of Agent Orange shows <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans at
increased risk of only one type of cancer _ and ``no evidence''
that the risk stems from exposure to the dangerous herbicide used
in the war.
   The study, which had been criticized by veterans groups even
before it was released, focused on <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans and cancer, and
``only indirectly evaluated Agent Orange exposure,'' the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   But it added that the cancer risk among the vets in the study
``seemed to be the opposite of the pattern for use of Agent
Orange.'' Veterans who served on <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> ships were somewhat more
likely to get cancer than those who served on land, and veterans
who served in the region of heaviest Agent Orange use were at
``somewhat lower risk'' than others, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Agent Orange, sprayed by the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military to remove jungle and
crops in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, contained dioxin, a highly toxic chemical that
some studies have found to increase the risk of cancer.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study, conducted over five years, surveyed male cancer
patients who were the right age to have served in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, whether
they did serve or not. They were compared with a group of similar
males with no history of cancer.
   The patients' medical records were examined for six kinds of
cancer, including soft tissue cancer and similar sarcomas, a group
of cancers which the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> concedes has been ``of great concern among
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans.''
   Vietnam vets were found to be at a roughly <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> increased
risk for non-Hodgkin's lymphoma, a ``relatively rare'' cancer of
the lymphatic system, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``The study did not find any evidence that the increased risk
might be due to Agent Orange exposure,'' said <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>William
L. Roper</PERSON>.
   There was ``no evidence,'' the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> reported, ``that
non-Hodgkin's lymphoma was more likely to develop in one group of
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans than in another.''
   Specifically, the yearly risk of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma is about
one in 10,000 for men 35 to 59, the age group of most <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vets.
The risk for <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> vets is about 1.5 per 10,000, <PERSON>Roper</PERSON> said.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> found ``no increased risk'' for sarcomas, usually
cancers of the body's connective tissues, or for other cancer types.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Veterans Administration</ORGANIZATION> has been awaiting the study before
making its decision on whether to award benefits to veterans
exposed to Agent Orange. Nearly 35,000 claims have been filed
citing the chemical as a cause of disabilities, including cancer,
skin disease and miscarriages by veterans' wives.
   Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON> said <DATE>today</DATE> that based on
the study he would order compensation paid to veterans suffering
from non-Hodgkin's lymphoma.
   Derwinski, in announcing the move in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, mentioned only
the link between <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> service and the lymphoma. He did not say
the connection was because of Agent Orange.
   His announcement speeds up VA action on the findings; the agency
had said it would submit the study to a review panel.
   American Legion officials told their <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran members in
advance of today's announcement that they should not be too
optimistic about this study, which was mandated by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The government has ducked the issue of Agent Orange for more
than a dozen years,'' said the legion's national commander, <ORGANIZATION>Miles
S. Epling</ORGANIZATION>. ``We are tired of waiting for more studies, especially
irrelevant ones.''
   The legion has accused <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> of ignoring military records that
could have produced a more detailed study.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study found that the risk of non-Hodgkin's lymphoma was
nearly double _ <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> higher _ for <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> veterans stationed on
ocean ships than for non-veterans. That was the only statistically
significant risk for any branch of service, said <PERSON>Dr. Daniel A.
Hoffman</PERSON>, assistant director for science at the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Center for
Environmental Health</ORGANIZATION>.
   For all veterans, the <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> higher risk of that type of
cancer is what epidemiologists call ``a weak association,'' <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>
said. While statistically significant, ``anything less than a
twofold increase can sometimes be caused by other factors,'' he
said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study did not suggest reasons for the increased risk for
one cancer over another, or for the increased risk among <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
sailors at sea.
   The study did not include blood tests to determine the actual
amount of dioxin that might remain in the cancer patients'
bloodstream two decades or more after military service.
   <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> said such tests were not a practical way to determine
dioxin exposure because it is possible that test findings might be
tainted by the patients' illness itself.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890725-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-89 1854EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgentOrange     07-25 0597</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Agent Orange,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>House Members Introduce $40 Million Agent Orange Bill</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<NOTE>ouse Members Introduce $40 Million Agent</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Orange Bill
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Orange Bill
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891006-0170 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-89 1847EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-ZumwaltVA     10-06 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Zumwalt VA,440</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zumwalt Named to VA Post</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GREENE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Adm. <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt Jr.</PERSON>, whose son died of
cancer after being exposed to Agent Orange that his father had
ordered sprayed in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, has been named a senior adviser to
Veterans Affairs Secretary <PERSON>Edward J. Derwinski</PERSON>, the department said
<DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The appointment of <LOCATION>Zumwalt</LOCATION>, 68, is one of several steps the <ORGANIZATION>VA
department</ORGANIZATION> has taken under <PERSON>Derwinski</PERSON> to address the concerns of
veterans who have health problems that they say are linked to
exposure to the defoliant.
   The <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON> will counsel on a variety of issues, but
``the first on the agenda will be Agent Orange.''
   <PERSON>Zumwalt</PERSON>, who retired as chief of naval operations in <DATE>1974</DATE>, was
commander of in-country naval forces in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> in the <DATE>late 1960s</DATE>,
when Agent Orange was sprayed in the <ORGANIZATION>Mekong Delta</ORGANIZATION>.
   His son, <PERSON>Elmo R. Zumwalt III</PERSON>, had served as a patrol boat
commander at the same time. He died in <DATE>August 1988</DATE> of a form of
cancer linked to Agent Orange exposure. He was 42.
   A grandson, <PERSON>Elmo Russell Zumwalt IV</PERSON>, suffers from a congenital
dysfunction of his physical senses. Agent Orange has also been
blamed for birth defects.
   The father has said he still would have ordered spraying the
defoliant because overall casualties were reduced.
   The two co-wrote a book, ``My Father, My Son,'' about the
experience. It was later made into a television movie.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>VA Department</ORGANIZATION> published regulations creating
less-stringent guidelines for determining whether there is a link
between Agent Orange exposure and a host of ailments. A <ORGANIZATION>VA</ORGANIZATION> panel
will re-examine studies in <DATE>November</DATE> in light of the new guidelines.
   Government scientists have said there is no way of determining a
positive link, a position challenged by veterans groups and outside
scientists. The <ORGANIZATION>American Legion</ORGANIZATION>, for example, has released a major
study showing that exposure is related to benign fatty tumors,
adult acne, skin rash with blisters, several other ailments and an
increased risk of miscarriages in wives of veterans.
   Although the study said it couldn't determine a link with cancer
because the sample was too small, the legion said the methodology
proved such a study could be made.
   The new regulations allow for a link to be established if
studies ``permit the conclusion that it is at least as likely as
not that the purported relationship between a particular type of
exposure and a specific adverse health effect exists.''
   Some 35,000 veterans have filed Agent Orange claims, but only
five have been allowed because of the policy that no firm
connection exists. More than 230,000 veterans have reported their
exposure to the <LOCATION>VA</LOCATION>. About 2.6 million personnel served within the
borders of <LOCATION>South Vietnam</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890626-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-89 0015EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AgentOrange     06-26 1154</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Agent Orange,1186</SECOND>
<HEAD>Vietnam Vets Hope Agent Orange Decision Will Open Door for Benefits</HEAD>
<BYLINE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report; dated matter in 22nd graf, `A scientific
...' ^By MITCHELL LANDSBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>David Maier</PERSON> believes he lost his arm in the service of his
country. His country, until now, has disagreed.
   The arm _ a casualty of cancer, not combat _ was amputated at the
shoulder seven years after <PERSON>Maier</PERSON>'s discharge from the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>.
   But the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veteran, now 46 and living in <LOCATION>Bay Village</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>,
puts the blame for his cancer on Agent Orange, the toxic herbicide
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops sprayed over the jungles of southeast <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. He is
convinced it was awash in the coffee-colored <LOCATION>Mekong River</LOCATION> water
pumped aboard his ship for showers.
   Like more than 34,000 other <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> veterans who believe they
have become ill because of Agent Orange, <PERSON>Maier</PERSON> applied for
government disability benefits. And like all but five of those
applicants, he was denied.
   Now <PERSON>Maier</PERSON> hopes his claim will be reconsidered, thanks to a
federal judge's ruling in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE> that found the
government failed to give Agent Orange claimants the benefit of the
doubt.
   To the surprise of many veterans, the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration decided
not to appeal. Instead, Veterans Secretary <PERSON>Edward Derwinski</PERSON>
announced that the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Veterans Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, the new name for
