<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32194 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat023_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-023 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Swears-In New Cabinet </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0202195994 Paris AFP in Spanish 1723 GMT 2 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0202195994 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 2 Feb (AFP) -- Venezuelan President <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON> swore in his new cabinet at <DATE>1645 GMT today</DATE> as his last 
official act of ascension to power. 
  Caldera, 78, was sworn-in mid-morning as the eighth 
president 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s current democratic period in the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> building 
located in <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>' historic center. After taking office and 
addressing the nation, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> laid a wreath in the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> at the tomb of <ORGANIZATION>Liberator Simon Bolivar</ORGANIZATION>. Following this 
act, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> went to the <LOCATION>Miraflores</LOCATION> Presidential Palace, where 
he began his duties. Once installed, he swore-in his new 
ministers. 
  At <DATE>1635</DATE> GMT, the ministerial appointment decrees were read, 
which <ORGANIZATION>Caldera</ORGANIZATION> signed 10 minutes later, before swearing-in the 
ministers. Caldera made official the appointments of nearly all 
of his new ministers <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. Pending are only the culture 
minister and the president of <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Guayana Corporation</ORGANIZATION> 
(CVG), which covers basic nonoil resources (steel, aluminum, 
bauxite, hydroelectricity, and precious minerals). Following is 
the new Venezuelan ministerial team: 
<H5>  Formal Ministries </H5>
  Interior -- <PERSON>Ramon Escovar Salom</PERSON> 
  Foreign Affairs -- <PERSON>Miguel Angel Burelli Rivas</PERSON> 
  Finance -- <PERSON>Julio Sosa Rodriguez</PERSON> 
  Defense -- <ORGANIZATION>General Rafaem Angel Moreno Revette 
  Development</ORGANIZATION> -- <PERSON>Luis Carlos Palacios</PERSON> 
  Education -- <PERSON>Antonio Luis Cardenas</PERSON> 
  Health and Social Welfare -- <PERSON>Vicente Perez Davila</PERSON> 
  Agriculture and Livestock -- <PERSON>Ciro Anez Fonseca</PERSON> 
  Labor -- <PERSON>Juan Nepomuceno Garrido 
  Justice</PERSON> -- <PERSON>Ruben Creixems</PERSON> 
  Energy and Mines -- <PERSON>Edwin Jose Arrieta</PERSON> 
  Urban Development -- <PERSON>Ciro Zaa</PERSON> 
  Family -- <PERSON>Mercedes Pulido de Briceno 
  Secretriat</PERSON> of the Presidency -- <ORGANIZATION>Andres Caldera 
  Environment and Natural Resources</ORGANIZATION> -- <ORGANIZATION>Roberto Perez Lecuna 
<H5>  Ministers Without Portfolios </H5>
  Central Information Office</ORGANIZATION> -- <ORGANIZATION>Guillermo Alvarez Bajares 
  Economic Reform</ORGANIZATION> (new) -- <PERSON>Asdrubal Baptista</PERSON> 
  State Decentralization (existing) -- <PERSON>Jose Guillermo Andueza 
  Youth</PERSON> (new) -- <PERSON>Pilar Iribarren</PERSON> 
  Higher Education, Science and Technology (new) -- <PERSON>Guido 
Arnal 
Arroyo</PERSON> 
  Exceptional (new) -- <ORGANIZATION>Pompeyo Marquez 
  Tourist Corporation</ORGANIZATION> (new) -- <PERSON>Hernan Luis Soriano</PERSON> 
  Venezuelan Investment Fund (existing) -- <PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON> 
  Foreign Investment Institute (existing) -- <PERSON>Alberto Poleto</PERSON> 
  The president also swore in new <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> Governor <PERSON>Asdrubal 
Aguiar</PERSON> (since <DATE>four years ago</DATE>, the rest of the governors are 
elected in their respective jurisdictions). 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32889 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat104_t_94005" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Changes Cabinet In Midst of Crisis </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Changes Cabinet In Midst of Crisis </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA3005222094 Madrid EFE in Spanish 1956 GMT 30 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA3005222094 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 30 <DATE>May</DATE> (EFE) -- Today, Venezuelan President 
<PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> carried out his first cabinet change, only 117 
days after the start of his government and in the mist of a 
profound economic crisis. 
  Caldera, who assumed the presidency on 2 <DATE>February</DATE>, appointed 
<PERSON>Alberto Poletto</PERSON>, <PERSON>Luis Carlos Palacios</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ciro Zaa</PERSON>, and <PERSON>Carlos 
Bernandez</PERSON> as ministers of Development, <ORGANIZATION>Central Office of 
Coordination</ORGANIZATION> and Planning [Cordiplan], <ORGANIZATION>Transport</ORGANIZATION> and 
Communication, and Venezuelan Investment Fund, respectively. 
  Caldera's restructuring of his cabinet has been interpreted 
by local political experts as a sign that the president is 
prepared to make a switch to an economic policy less populist 
than the one he proposed during the elections campaign and 
closer to the neoliberal policy implemented by former president 
<PERSON>Carlos Andres Perez</PERSON>. 
  Apparently, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>, who was one of the most severe critics 
of the free market policy promoted by <PERSON>Perez</PERSON>, has been unable to 
structure an economic formula out of the neoliberal guidelines. 
  <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is living through a difficult economic situation, 
with a fiscal deficit estimated at more than <MONEY>$4.5 billion</MONEY>, a 
severe depreciation of the bolivar, and an explosive social 
situation fueled by a significant fall in the purchasing power 
of the people. 
  President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> put <PERSON>Carlos Bernandez</PERSON> at the head of the 
organization in charge of privatizing state enterprises. 
Bernandez has always been linked to the local banking sector and 
he has been president of the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of Venezuela</ORGANIZATION>, which is one of 
the most important banks in the country. Bernandez has offered 
to increase the privatization process. The local media has 
described his appointment as a victory for the financial sector, 
which was able to produce the departure of <PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON>, a 
politician very close to <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> and to his electoral offer for 
an economy with a human face, from the <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> Investment Fund. 
  Luis <PERSON>Carlos Palacios</PERSON>, the new Cordiplan minister, replaces 
<PERSON>Enzo del Bufalo</PERSON>, a dissonant voice in <LOCATION>Caldera</LOCATION>'s economic team. 
The new minister is closer to the free economy concepts that the 
<PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> administration apparently wants to adopt in this new 
phase. 
  Also, <PERSON>Alberto Poletto</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Trade 
Institute</ORGANIZATION>, will be development minister, which joins these 
departments to create the Industry and <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  <PERSON>Ciro Zaa</PERSON> has been virtually forced to leave the <ORGANIZATION>Urban 
Development Ministry</ORGANIZATION> to take over the <ORGANIZATION>Transport and 
Communication Ministry</ORGANIZATION> vacated by <PERSON>Cesar Quintini</PERSON>, who was 
accused of maintaining an attitude of tolerance in multiple 
cases of corruption in his ministry. 
  Zaa will be replaced by <PERSON>Francisco Gonzalez</PERSON>, former president 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Urban Development</ORGANIZATION> fund. The responsibilities of Special 
Affairs Minister <PERSON>Pompeyo Marquez</PERSON> have been expanded and from now 
on he will also be responsible for the government's social 
programs. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56987 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat091_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-091 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Condemns Illegal Price Increases </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Condemns Illegal Price Increases </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1105040994 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1100 GMT 
10 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1105040994 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Fabiola Vecchionacce</PERSON> from the "Union Radio News" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> attended an event held to 
celebrate the <DATE>50th anniversary of Fedecamaras</DATE> [<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan 
Federation of Associations and Chambers of Commerce and 
Industry</ORGANIZATION>]. President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> criticized price increases 
of certain products as well as profiteering in the sale of 
dollars, which are acts of corruption that should be fought. 
That was part of <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s speech during the celebration of the 
50th anniversary of <LOCATION>Fedecamaras</LOCATION>. President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> pointed out 
that all sectors of society must join Solidarity's efforts so it 
can make progress. 
  Caldera also talked about the importance of opening up 
opportunities for foreign investment by providing greater legal 
guarantees. He said private and public corruption must be 
fought. Let us listen to excerpts of what <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> said. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] We have seen how the prices of 
certain products have been increased. The Venezuelan people are 
undoubtedly being hurt by this. It is an act of corruption that 
we have to fight. We know that [words indistinct]. That is why 
an atmosphere such as this, with a spirit of friendship and of 
solidarity, can lead us to expect that we can all make an 
effort. Just as the Venezuelan private sector condemns a 
government official who steals the people's money through public 
works that are built, it should also condemn a private sector 
member, who buys dollars to resell them for an undue profit. 
[end recording] 
  In addition, President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> agreed with Fedecamaras 
President <PERSON>Edgar Romero Navas</PERSON> that the fight against inflation 
must not be stopped because, according to <PERSON>Romero Navas</PERSON>, the 
country requires a series of changes. <PERSON>Romero Navas</PERSON> also said 
coherence and compromise are needed in the executive cabinet. 
He said our business and political criteria on the handling of 
the country's resources should also be taken into account. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32888 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat104_t_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further on Cabinet Changes </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Further on Cabinet Changes </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2905033794 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 0227 GMT 
29 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2905033794 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> from the "Union Radio News" </F>
newscast; broadcast in progress] 
  [Text] ...the Investment Fund of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> [FIV] and former 
<ORGANIZATION>Bank of Venezuela</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Carlos Bernardez Losada</PERSON> was 
appointed to the post. Observers believe President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s 
decision to remove <ORGANIZATION>FIV</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON> was prompted 
by the way he handled <ORGANIZATION>Aeropostal</ORGANIZATION>'s privatization, which was 
considered a failure because the bid was declared invalid. 
  It is also said the decision was prompted by the rejection 
of 
<ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Commander General <PERSON>Otto Garcia Rivara</PERSON>, who reportedly 
objected to the fact that one of the enterprises participating 
in the bid was a Colombian airline. He believes <ORGANIZATION>Aeropostal</ORGANIZATION> is a 
strategic Venezuelan company, and one must take into account the 
border problems we have with our neighbor. 
  OCI [<ORGANIZATION>Central Information Office</ORGANIZATION>] chief <PERSON>Guillermo Alvarez</PERSON> 
explained that <PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON> will remain in the government 
even though he has left the <ORGANIZATION>FIV</ORGANIZATION>. This means he will possibly be 
appointed to another post in the ministerial cabinet. 
  [Begin recording] [Alvarez] I cannot report new changes. 
These are the ones the president authorized us to announce today. 
  [<PERSON>Briceno</PERSON>] Does this mean <PERSON>Mr. Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON> is now out of 
the government? 
  [<PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>] He is obviously out of the post he held. This does 
not mean he is out of the government. [end recording] 
  <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> announced <PERSON>Alberto Poletto</PERSON> will still be in charge of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Trade Institute</ORGANIZATION> [ICE]. This situation might 
propitiate a merger of the ICE and the <ORGANIZATION>Development Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, 
which would become the industry and commerce ministry. 
  <PERSON>Ciro Zaa Alvarez</PERSON> has been appointed to the MTC [<ORGANIZATION>Ministry of 
Transportation and Communications</ORGANIZATION>]. Zaa was formerly in charge 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Urban Development Ministry</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Francisco Gonzalez</PERSON>, 
current president of the <ORGANIZATION>Urban Development Fund</ORGANIZATION>, was temporarily 
appointed to the post. President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s plans include the 
unification of these infrastructure ministries. 
  Luis <PERSON>Carlos Palacios</PERSON> has been appointed to the <ORGANIZATION>Central 
Office 
of Coordination</ORGANIZATION> and Planning, replacing <PERSON>Enzo del Bufalo</PERSON>, who 
tendered his official resignation to the head of state. Another 
appointment made by President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> was that of <PERSON>Alfredo 
Gruber</PERSON>, current president of Palmaven in the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan 
Petroleum Corporation</ORGANIZATION> who will be in charge of the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan 
Corporation of Guayana</ORGANIZATION>. 
  To conclude, <PERSON>Pompeyo Marquez</PERSON> has been given responsibility 
for coordinating the government's social programs. The new 
ministers will be sworn in by President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> [30 
<DATE>May</DATE>] at <LOCATION>Miraflores</LOCATION> Palace. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34412 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat118_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  17 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera on Wave of Rumors, Economic Crisis </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera on Wave of Rumors, Economic Crisis </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1806000994 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 2200 GMT 
17 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1806000994 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON>; from the "Union Radio News" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has said that the most 
prosperous industry in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is spreading rumors. He added 
that this, however, is countered by reality because our 
democratic system is firm and stable. Caldera made this 
statement during a joint news conference with Portuguese Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Anibal Cavaco Silva</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>Yellow House</ORGANIZATION>. Caldera 
recalled that recently rumors persistently circulated in the 
country about his presumed death, which had to stop when all 
Venezuelans confirmed that he was totally active. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] I am convinced that the democratic 
system in my country is a firm and stable reality, and will be 
maintained despite all the rumors unleashed by those who are 
interested in creating situations of violence and instability, 
taking advantage of the grave circumstances of an economic 
crisis. We are all aware of the seriousness of this crisis and 
we know that we must make great efforts to overcome it. [end 
recording] 
  <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> attributed the fall of the bolivar to the wave of 
rumors, which in turn has increased inflation. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] We are fighting against inflation, 
but rumors are the main cause for its increase. We are facing a 
situation of shortages and price fluctuations in which 
speculators take advantage of any factor or announcement that 
the inflation rate is up to increase prices to unacceptable 
levels. We will handle this problem with courage and 
determination. [end recording] 
  President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> said that despite the crisis in the 
financial system, the fact that foreign investors are still 
interested in investing in our country is proof that <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> 
will be able to overcome this crisis and reactivate its economy. 
  Meanwhile, Portuguese Prime Minister <PERSON>Cavaco Silva</PERSON> said that 
his country is willing to assist <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> under the current 
circumstances and to strengthen commercial ties between both 
countries. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32125 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat022_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-022 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Incoming Defense Minister Says Army To Obey Caldera </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0102195994 Caracas EL NACIONAL in Spanish 31 Jan 94 p D-1 </F>
<F P=103> PA0102195994 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas EL NACIONAL </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Luis Guillermo Acosta</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Maracay</LOCATION> -- The <ORGANIZATION>National Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> [FAN] will 
respect the decision by President-elect <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>, who will 
take the oath of office on 2 <DATE>February</DATE> as president and commander 
in chief of the FAN. 
  This was made clear by Major General <PERSON>Angel Rafael Montero 
Revette</PERSON>, inspector general of the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, who will be the next 
minister of defense according to the statement <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> 
made to the nation. Montero Revette presided over a ceremony in 
this city at the <LOCATION>Maracay Branch</LOCATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Army Noncommissioned 
Officers School</ORGANIZATION>, where he was questioned by some journalists on 
whether there would be problems with the <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> announcement 
regarding changes in the <ORGANIZATION>High Command</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The next defense minister said he thinks there will not be 
problems in the FAN with the appointment of a new military High 
Command, because President-elect <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> knows very well the 
military laws and attributions he will have when he takes over 
as commander in chief. According to Gen. <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON>, FAN 
personnel will begin observing <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>'s decisions at the 
very moment he assumes the presidency of the Republic. He added 
that according to the Constitution, FAN personnel are 
subordinated to the civilian rule exercised by the chief 
executive. Consequently, he concluded, there will be no problems 
in this regard. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32553 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat028_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-028 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera: Stay of Proceedings for Coupists `on Course' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0902151694 Caracas EL GLOBO in Spanish 6 Feb 94 p 2 </F>
<F P=103> PA0902151694 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas EL GLOBO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> said the stay of 
proceedings against the military personnel involved in the 4-F 
[4 <DATE>February 92</DATE>] and 27-N [27 <DATE>November 92</DATE>] events will continue 
on course as it should. 
  The president made these statements in <LOCATION>Valencia</LOCATION> following 
the 
ceremony for the episcopal ordination of <ORGANIZATION>Monsignor Reinaldo Del 
Prette Lissoi</ORGANIZATION>, which the president attended as the guest of 
honor. 
  [<LOCATION>Caldera</LOCATION>] It was a very beautiful, solemn ceremony and a 
fine 
expression of the feeling of the Venezuelan people. It was also 
a recognition of the brilliant figure of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s 
ecclesiastic youth. I am very satisfied because I think it is a 
sign of vitality, force, and faith in the <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> we all want. 
  [EL GLOBO] What can you tell us about the stay of 
proceedings 
against the coupists? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Caldera</ORGANIZATION>] That will continue on course as it should. In a 
way, I am committed to the country. My conscience has committed 
me to solving this problem, which must be solved in a way that 
strengthens peace and unity in the Armed Forces and among the 
Venezuelan people. 
  [EL GLOBO] And what about the salary increase you announced? 
  [<PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>] That is being considered to see how it will be 
processed, because there are various options in the Labor Law. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Labor Ministry</ORGANIZATION> will bring it up at the next cabinet meeting. 
  [<ORGANIZATION>EL GLOBO</ORGANIZATION>] What has the governor of <ORGANIZATION>Carabobo State</ORGANIZATION> proposed 
in terms of decentralization? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Caldera</ORGANIZATION>] It will continue in a constructive manner, because 
we want harmony between national, regional, and municipal 
authorities. 
<H5>  Support From the Governors </H5>
  Carabobo Governor <PERSON>Enrique Salas Romer</PERSON>, president of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Association of Governors</ORGANIZATION> [of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, AVG], said President 
<PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> has "the support of the <ORGANIZATION>AVG</ORGANIZATION> independent of the positions 
its members may have. We maintain our support for the person 
chosen by the people to guide the destiny of the country." 
  <PERSON>Salas Romer</PERSON> said some of the president's statements make him 
feel optimistic about <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s attitude toward the 
decentralization process, which "is not a goal but a reality 
based on the economic, social, educational, and political growth 
of the <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> that extends beyond <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> and which also 
demands the participation of the people of <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-32885 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat104_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Planning Minister Enzo del Bufalo Resigns </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Planning Minister Enzo del Bufalo Resigns </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2705185194 Madrid EFE in Spanish 1613 GMT 27 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA2705185194 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 27 <DATE>May</DATE> (EFE) -- <PERSON>Enzo del Bufalo</PERSON>, minister 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Central Office of Coordination and Planning</ORGANIZATION>, today 
resigned in what appears to the beginning of a crisis in <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON>'s government. 
  Del Bufalo has become the first minister of <LOCATION>Caldera</LOCATION>'s 
government to resign from his post in the 114 days of the 
current administration. Nevertheless, it has been pointed out 
that in the coming hours other officials will leave the cabinet 
team. 
  Christian Democrat Caldera is preparing to make important 
changes in his government team, which in the eyes of his 
political adversaries, has offered an image of contradictions 
with regard to his policies, particularly in the economic field. 
The changes, it appears, are an attempt to revitalize his 
government, which appears trapped between the severity of the 
crisis and social demands. 
  Today, the Venezuelan press points out that all the 
ministers 
will place their posts at the president's disposal, thus making 
it easier for <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>, who assumed power on 2 <DATE>February</DATE>, to make 
the changes he may deem necessary. 
  The opposition has accused Caldera of offering a 
contradictory image with regard to the policies that he insists 
on applying, and his ministers have found themselves in 
seriously contradictory positions. Nevertheless, it is a 
tradition of the old-time politician, who already governed 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> between 1969-74, to make his decisions under total 
secrecy until he decides to inform the nation, such as when he 
designated his cabinet a few hours before assuming the 
presidency. 
  The departure of <ORGANIZATION>Transport</ORGANIZATION> and Communication Minister <PERSON>Cesar 
Quintini</PERSON> has been reported by the Venezuelan media as a fact, 
although he has denied his resignation. Quintini is accused of 
maintaining a tolerant attitude with regard to corruption in his 
ministry. 
  <PERSON>Rafael Irribarren</PERSON>, deputy minister of transport and 
communication, resigned one month ago from his post after 
accusing Quintini of obstructing his efforts to dismantle the 
complex network of corruption that functions in that ministry. 
Irribarren charged that in his ministry, licenses, permits, and 
other official documents are sold and that commission fees are 
charged for granting concessions. 
  Local political sources claim that <PERSON>Quintini</PERSON>'s continued 
presence in his post has created serious doubts about <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s 
will to struggle against corruption, one of the electoral 
banners that took him to the presidency. Other ministers are 
unhappy because they believe they have not received the support 
they need for a successful start to their duties. 
  In almost four months of government, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> has had to face 
a grave economic crisis, with a fiscal deficit of more than <MONEY>$4.5 
billion</MONEY>. The devaluation of the bolivar has become a pressing 
problem for <ORGANIZATION>Caldera</ORGANIZATION>. The dollar, which at the beginning of the 
month had been valued at 127.15 bolivares, this past <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> 
was valued at 175. 
  It appears that Development Minister <PERSON>Luis Carlos Palacios</PERSON> 
and 
Agriculture Minister <PERSON>Ciro Fonseca Anez</PERSON> could also leave the 
government. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33045 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat105_t_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-105 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera To Replace Investment Fund Minister </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera To Replace Investment Fund Minister </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA3105202194 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 2200 GMT 
29 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA3105202194 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Miraflores</LOCATION> Palace; from the </F>
"Union Radio News" newscast] 
  [Text] As we have reported, everything seems to indicate 
that President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> was prompted to replace Venezuelan 
Investment Fund [FIV] Minister <PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON> for failing to 
sell <ORGANIZATION>Aeropostal</ORGANIZATION> through the bidding process. 
  <PERSON>Fernando Egana</PERSON>, deputy minister of the Secretariat of the 
Presidency, has admitted that the chief of state has made this 
decision, because he wants to accelerate the process of 
privatization. He has added the former minister has established 
the bases for this policy and the government will develop it: 
  [Begin recording] [<LOCATION>Egana</LOCATION>] He has established solid and 
important bases, and the government will continue his efforts on 
such bases. 
  [Unidentified reporter] Is there anything concrete in this 
regard? 
  [<LOCATION>Egana</LOCATION>] A plan of privatization is already under way. 
  [Reporter] What is in store for Vivas? 
  [<PERSON>Egana</PERSON>] The president of the Republic will decide. 
  [Reporter] It was said the first attempt at privatization 
has 
failed. Will changes be made? Will a new element be introduced 
to make it more effective? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Egana</ORGANIZATION>] Using the bases already established, the government 
will try to make greater efforts to attract foreign investments 
that are needed at this time. [end recording] 
  When asked whether the MAS [Movement Toward Socialism] will 
have a greater role in the government in view of the changes, 
<PERSON>Egana</PERSON> has said the country has achieved greater participation 
during the administration of President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34926 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat123_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-123 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera To Reveal Economic, Fiscal Measures 1 Jul </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera To Reveal Economic, Fiscal Measures 1 Jul </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2706002394 Mexico City NOTIMEX in Spanish 0247 GMT 26 Jun 
94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2706002394 </F>
<F P=104>  Mexico City NOTIMEX </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 25 Jun (NOTIMEX) -- On 1 <DATE>July</DATE>, President 
<PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> will unveil in <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION> new economic measures with 
which he seeks to overcome the country's economic and financial 
crisis, an official source said <DATE>today</DATE>. <PERSON>Pompeyo Marquez</PERSON>, special 
minister and presidential adviser, said in <LOCATION>Maracay</LOCATION>, an 
industrial city 80 km west of <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, that the plan will focus 
in particular on social programs and reactivating production. 
  To that effect, <PERSON>Marquez</PERSON> said the measures will cover three 
major areas: stockpiles--to prevent hoarding; employment; and 
training. The measures are intended to raise Venezuelans' 
standard of living, although most problems will not be totally 
resolved, <PERSON>Marquez</PERSON> noted. 
  Venezuelans are anxious following the collapse of seven 
banks 
and <DATE>last week</DATE>'s <PERCENT>8.65 percent</PERCENT> devaluation of the bolivar to the 
level of 210 bolivares to the dollar. Local economists have said 
that <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> is leaning toward exchange rate controls, a measure 
the economy minister opposes. <PERSON>Marquez</PERSON> said he supports controls 
on prices and imports because those measures will stamp out 
speculation and capital flight. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32491 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat027_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-027 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  9 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Cuba's Lage Says Oil Accord Not Discussed With Caldera </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0902023694 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 0051 GMT 9 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0902023694 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Raima Rondon</PERSON> from "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Cuban Vice President <PERSON>Carlos Lage Davila</PERSON> said after 
meeting with President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> that so far no petroleum 
cooperation agreement has been reached among <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, and 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, although the possibility has not been ruled out. 
  The Cuban official said talks are currently under way among 
the three states for a possible petroleum cooperation agreement 
and that each is prepared to establish a commercial operation 
that is favorable to the three countries. The Cuban vice 
president stressed, however, that the issue was not discussed 
with President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> because the tour of South American 
countries is focused on strengthening relations with <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
  [Begin Lage recording] We did not discuss the issue with 
President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>. As President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> said at the beginning, 
we discussed general issues. We thanked him for his position 
against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade on <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. We also expressed our 
satisfaction with his election and stressed our desire for a 
better future for Venezuelans. [end recording] 
  In the short 24-hour visit to <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, the Cuban vice 
president noted his interest in strengthening ties between 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> [sentence as heard]. To that end, he 
held meetings with the ministers of tourism, foreign affairs, 
and communications and transportation and with the president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Investment Fund</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32552 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat028_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-028 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  10 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Cuba's Lage Says Oil Accord Not Discussed With Caldera </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0902023694 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 0051 GMT 9 Feb 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0902023694 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Raima Rondon</PERSON> from "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Cuban Vice President <PERSON>Carlos Lage Davila</PERSON> said after 
meeting with President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> that so far no petroleum 
cooperation agreement has been reached among <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, and 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, although the possibility has not been ruled out. 
  The Cuban official said talks are currently under way among 
the three states for a possible petroleum cooperation agreement 
and that each is prepared to establish a commercial operation 
that is favorable to the three countries. The Cuban vice 
president stressed, however, that the issue was not discussed 
with President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> because the tour of South American 
countries is focused on strengthening relations with <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. 
  [Begin Lage recording] We did not discuss the issue with 
President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>. As President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> said at the beginning, 
we discussed general issues. We thanked him for his position 
against the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> blockade on <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>. We also expressed our 
satisfaction with his election and stressed our desire for a 
better future for Venezuelans. [end recording] 
  In the short 24-hour visit to <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, the Cuban vice 
president noted his interest in strengthening ties between 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION> [sentence as heard]. To that end, he 
held meetings with the ministers of tourism, foreign affairs, 
and communications and transportation and with the president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Investment Fund</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-51070 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat009_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-009 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  13 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   President-Elect Caldera To Seek Suspension of VAT </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA1301003594 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 1550 GMT 12 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1301003594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] President-elect <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has insisted he will 
do everything possible to fulfill his electoral promise of 
suspending the controversial value-added tax [VAT]. 
  Caldera made this statement during a ceremony in his honor 
given by members of the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Academy of Language</ORGANIZATION>. The 
ceremony was also attended by Venezuelan President <PERSON>Ramon J. 
Velasquez</PERSON> and other representatives from the Executive and 
Judicial Branches. <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> pointed out that as soon he 
starts his administration, he will present several proposals to 
the new parliament in an effort to make the VAT more just. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] I hope <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will accept this. 
I have heard that some groups seem to be interested in learning 
more about my proposal and in accepting it in principle. I hope 
this will be the case. [end recording] 
  When consulted about the possibility of dismissing charges 
against the individuals involved in the massacre at <LOCATION>El Amparo</LOCATION>, 
the president-elect emphasized that the current government 
should be very careful in this respect. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-11323 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat054_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-054 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Health, Social Welfare Minister Resigns </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA1903002394 Caracas EL GLOBO in Spanish 18 Mar 94 p 46 </F>
<F P=103> PA1903002394 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas EL GLOBO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Article by <PERSON>Liz Martinez</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] Health and Social Welfare Minister <PERSON>Vicente Perez 
Davila</PERSON> presented his irrevocable resignation yesterday. Health 
problems related to his gastrointestinal system have forced the 
minister to resign. 
  <PERSON>Perez Davila</PERSON> coordinated the health area of President <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON>'s government and later headed the liaison commission 
with the <ORGANIZATION>Health and Social Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  In spite of his youth and having a good professional record, 
today <PERSON>Perez Davila</PERSON> is leaving the ministry for health reasons. 
He expressed his regrets to President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>. It was 
learned yesterday morning that <PERSON>Perez Davila</PERSON> sent a letter to the 
president of the Republic in which he explained the reasons for 
his resignation. In that letter he told President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> 
that he is sure the work of the new authorities at the <ORGANIZATION>Health 
and Social Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> will be successful, because the 
persons working in the ministry are highly qualified and 
motivated. 
  President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> will now have to appoint a new health and 
social welfare minister, which must be a person highly qualified 
to direct a ministry confronting a serious hospital crisis. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-51146 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat010_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-010 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Reaction to Institution of Value-Added Tax </TI></H3>
<H4>   Caldera To Seek Suspension </H4>
<F P=102> PA1301003594 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 1550 GMT 12 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1301003594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] President-elect <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has insisted he will 
do everything possible to fulfill his electoral promise of 
suspending the controversial value-added tax [VAT]. 
  Caldera made this statement during a ceremony in his honor 
given by members of the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Academy of Language</ORGANIZATION>. The 
ceremony was also attended by Venezuelan President <PERSON>Ramon J. 
Velasquez</PERSON> and other representatives from the Executive and 
Judicial Branches. <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> pointed out that as soon he 
starts his administration, he will present several proposals to 
the new parliament in an effort to make the VAT more just. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] I hope <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will accept this. 
I have heard that some groups seem to be interested in learning 
more about my proposal and in accepting it in principle. I hope 
this will be the case. [end recording] 
  When consulted about the possibility of dismissing charges 
against the individuals involved in the massacre at <LOCATION>El Amparo</LOCATION>, 
the president-elect emphasized that the current government 
should be very careful in this respect. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57957 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat103_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-103 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  26 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   OCI Director Denies Rumors of Cabinet Changes </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    OCI Director Denies Rumors of Cabinet Changes </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2605150494 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1100 GMT 
26 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2605150494 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Union Radio News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] <PERSON>Guillermo Alvarez Bajares</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Central Information 
Office</ORGANIZATION> [OCI] director, has said that, so far, the alleged 
removal of ministers from the executive cabinet are merely 
rumors, which must be denied because there are no official 
statements about it; in other words, the government is denying 
the continuous rumors on an alleged cabinet reshuffle reportedly 
planned by President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>. <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> has the 
story: 
  [Begin recording] [Briceno] <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> reported that 
<ORGANIZATION>Transportation</ORGANIZATION> and Communication Minister <PERSON>Cesar Quintini Rosales</PERSON> 
still heads that ministry, but <PERSON>Quintini</PERSON>, who was at <ORGANIZATION>Miraflores 
Palace</ORGANIZATION> apparently attending a <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers</ORGANIZATION> meeting on 25 
<DATE>May</DATE>, refused to deny reports of his alleged removal from the 
cabinet. Alvarez noted that any governmental change is the 
decision of the president alone, thereby explaining that 
ministers are not hired, nor do they buy their posts. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>OCI</ORGANIZATION> chief rejected the existence of any ambiguity as a 
result of the division in the economic cabinet by ironically 
stating that the only division at the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Ministers is 
Defense Minister Division General Rafael Montero</ORGANIZATION>. 
  [<PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>] There were rumors on a subject inherent to the 
president: the change, dismissal, or removal of ministers. No 
one else can make this decision. Therefore, these are 
unofficial rumors. 
  [<PERSON>Briceno</PERSON>] Despite the <ORGANIZATION>OCI</ORGANIZATION> director's statements, it is a 
fact 
that President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> could be thinking about revamping the 
executive cabinet. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34422 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat118_t_94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-118 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  18 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Former Coupist Implicates Defense Minister </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Former Coupist Implicates Defense Minister </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1806191794 Paris AFP in Spanish 1627 GMT 18 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA1806191794 </F>
<F P=104>  Paris AFP </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 18 Jun (AFP) -- The controversy regarding 
possible coup attempts in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> heightened this <DATE>weekend</DATE> with 
new charges that implicate Defense Minister <PERSON>Rafael Montero 
Revette</PERSON>, despite denials by President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>. 
  Retired Lieutenant Colonel <PERSON>Hugo Chavez</PERSON>, head of the thwarted 
<DATE>February 1992</DATE> military coup, charged in a communique to the 
media that Minister <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON> conspired last year against 
the then <ORGANIZATION>Defense Minister Radames Munoz</ORGANIZATION> in an alleged coup that 
did not materialize. 
  "Current Defense Minister Gen. <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON> was involved 
up to his neck in the military coup that Vice Admiral <PERSON>Radames 
Munoz</PERSON> was going to carry out last <DATE>December</DATE>," <PERSON>Chavez</PERSON> states in 
his communique. The retired military officer also maintains that 
"there is plenty of evidence. The (provisional) government of 
Dr. (Ramon) <PERSON>Velasquez</PERSON> (<DATE>1993</DATE>) had the evidence, and his interior 
minister was fully aware of that conspiracy." 
  According to <PERSON>Chavez</PERSON>, the former minister was "protected" on 
that occasion by the ruling political parties, because "a coup 
of that sort would maintain the status quo, corruption, and the 
privileges of ruling political and economic groups and would 
quell the struggle of the people to improve their welfare." 
  Chavez was imprisoned after the coup attempt until his 
release two months ago, when he benefited from a presidential 
amnesty granted by President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>, within the framework of 
the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>' peace process. This amnesty led to the release 
of virtually all those implicated in the <DATE>February</DATE> and <DATE>November 
1992</DATE> coup attempts. 
  A few days before taking office last <DATE>February</DATE>, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> asked 
Vice Admiral <PERSON>Munoz</PERSON> and the ranking military command accompanying 
him to resign. He appointed <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON>, who until that 
time was <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> commander, the new defense minister. Although, 
with the change in the military high command and release of the 
coupist officers, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> managed to maintain a period of calm 
in the military sector for several months, charges of new 
conspiracies surfaced this week. 
  <PERSON>Alberto Muller</PERSON>, retired general and current senator, charged 
that <PERSON>Munoz</PERSON> is preparing a new coup, while <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON> said 
that "rightist and leftist" groups are conspiring. Montero 
Revette mentioned <PERSON>Chavez</PERSON> and the "Red Flag" organization, among 
other leftist groups. 
  This wave of rumors was denied this week by <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>, who 
said 
that "the most prosperous industry in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> is spreading 
rumors." Caldera said: "I am convinced that the democratic 
system in my country is a firm and stable reality." <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, 
which has been a representative democracy for 36 years, 
experienced two thwarted coups in <DATE>1992</DATE>, and since then coup 
rumors have surfaced periodically in the country. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34224 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat117aa_94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-117 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera, Gaviria, Salinas View G-3 Trade Accord </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera, Gaviria, Salinas View G-3 Trade Accord </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1606132494 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1100 GMT 
15 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1606132494 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON>; from the "Union Radio News" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has said the bolivar 
fluctuations will not affect the future of the <ORGANIZATION>Group of Three</ORGANIZATION> 
[G-3] free trade agreement. He made this statement at a joint 
news conference in <LOCATION>Cartagena de Indias</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, where the G-3 
countries are meeting and where the Fourth Ibero-American Summit 
is taking place. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] Bolivar fluctuations will not 
affect the G-3 free trade agreement, because there will always 
be ways to prevent any eventuality from obstructing the basic 
element: trade among sister nations. [end recording] 
  Meanwhile, Colombian President <PERSON>Cesar Gaviria</PERSON> has said the 
trade agreement will come into effect soon due to the rules 
previously stipulated in the treaty signed by <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>. The first reaction to this treaty will 
come from investors of the three countries. 
  [Begin Gaviria recording] Although an immediate deregulation 
was included in the agreement, the G-3 free trade agreement is 
of utmost importance for a number of products. We must bear in 
mind the lifting of customs duties will take 10 years; this is 
why free trade will be progressive. I believe, however, the 
same thing that happened when <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> signed a free trade 
agreement with <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> will happen again: the doubling in trade 
within a year, because the expectations and clear-cut rules have 
made businessmen aware that there were regulations that would 
control trade and make trade grow. We hope the agreement among 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>, and <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> will yield very significant 
results soon. [end recording] 
said the prospects of this agreement regarding larger markets 
and production are compelling mechanisms with which to defeat 
poverty. The Aztec head of state was questioned about the G-3's 
contribution to help fight poverty. 
  [Begin Salinas recording] We in <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> are convinced the 
only 
way to permanently defeat poverty is to recover sustained 
economic growth, because without well-paying jobs there are no 
possibilities of permanently eradicating poverty. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-10894 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat075_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-075 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Caldera on Constitutional Amendments </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Caldera on Constitutional Amendments </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1604162794 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 1550 GMT 15 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1604162794 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has emphasized that 
constitutional amendments must include provisions for an 
impeachment referendum, that is, the possibility that people 
could impeach any government official, including the president, 
who fails to perform his duties. He made these statements at the 
opening of a play called "<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, Political Crisis, and 
Constitutional Reforms." He also said that participative 
democracy must be the main aspect of the amendments to ensure 
that people will have a say in the nation's important 
sociopolitical issues. He also rejected all doubts that the 
community will not be able to understand the amendments due to 
the large number of articles. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] People will not discuss the 
amendments article by article; they will merely reply yes or no, 
as is done in every democratic country. They will ratify or 
reject the amendments drafted by the <ORGANIZATION>National Congress</ORGANIZATION>. [end 
recording] 
  He also said that it is necessary to give the Venezuelan 
people a greater opportunity to participate and more power in 
view of the situation the country is currently experiencing. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57877 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat102_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-102 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Blames Pressure on Currency for Increasing Deficit </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Blames Pressure on Currency for Increasing Deficit </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2505195194 Caracas REPORTE DE LA ECONOMIA in Spanish 23 
May 94 p 2 </F>

<F P=103> PA2505195194 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas REPORTE DE LA ECONOMIA </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Jaqueline Aponte</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] Venezuelan President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has said the 
country's fiscal deficit is worsening mainly because of the 
crisis in the banking sector -- a crisis he says has prompted 
irregular, unjustifiable, and perverse pressure on Venezuelan 
currency to convert it to foreign currency, which is 
impoverishing our nation. 
  He said the state currently does not have a plethora of 
resources as it did in the past when resources were squandered 
and used to encourage physical and moral corruption. He said: 
"We do not have a great deal of money in our budget; instead, we 
have found a tremendous deficit that is getting worse for a 
thousand reasons." 
  Speaking at the <DATE>Saturday</DATE> inauguration of a newly built 
section of the Trapichito neighborhood in <LOCATION>Valencia</LOCATION>, President 
<PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> noted that although resources are scarce, there still 
exists a great deal of hope, desire, and a strong work ethic in 
the nation. He added that, through the joint efforts of various 
state offices that deal with public housing and slums, the 
nation will face these social problems, which it still considers 
a priority. 
  "I feel a special calling to resolve the housing and slum 
problems, and the government I head is committed to this and 
intends to struggle and open the way to clean up slums 
throughout the country and boost housing at every level in 
accordance with the economic needs of the dwellers," <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> 
concluded. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33056 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat105_t_94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-105 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  29 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Participants in Coup Attempts To Be Promoted </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Participants in Coup Attempts To Be Promoted </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA3105154594 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 0200 GMT 
29 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA3105154594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Union Radio News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Defense Minister General <PERSON>Rafael Angel Montero 
Revette</PERSON> has said certain officers involved in the <DATE>1992</DATE> coup 
attempts will be promoted to the next rank on 5 <DATE>July</DATE> after the 
head of state approved the list proposed by the qualifying board 
and the four branches of the military institution. 
  [Reporter <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON>] Gen. <PERSON>Montero Revette</PERSON> has made the 
announcement from <LOCATION>Miraflores Palace</LOCATION>, disclosing the decision by 
the president with whom he met for approximately three hours to 
review the military promotions that will be submitted to 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in the coming days. 
  Through the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Committee of Defense</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will 
study the appropriate files. Montero has reported the approval 
of the following promotions: 30 brigade generals, 10 of which 
are in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, six in the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION>, eight in the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Guard</ORGANIZATION>, and six <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> rear admirals. 
  Also up for promotion are 120 colonels, broken down as 
follows: 40 in the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, 25 in the aviation division, 35 in the 
<ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION>, and 20 ship of the line captains in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>. 
  As the minister explained, the promotions to the ranks of 
vice admirals and division general were left pending for next 
week because President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> was unable to review them. 
Montero has said that based on a decision by the president, a 
group of officers from the four branches who participated in the 
<DATE>1992</DATE> coup attempts will also be promoted on that same date. 
  [Begin Montero recording] These officers, primarily from the 
<ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>, rejoined the force more than two years ago and are working 
in troop commands in different posts of the organization. They 
have the same rights and duties of other officers. For that 
reason, those entitled to a promotion are evaluated. He may or 
may not be promoted, but not due to the coup attempts, because 
that is over for us. [end recording] 
  [<PERSON>Briceno</PERSON>] The defense minister has added that, like the 
officers who participated in the <DATE>1992</DATE> coup attempts, the 
enlistees who joined them in these actions will also be 
promoted. President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> has dropped the charges against 
these soldiers. 
  Commenting on the return to the country of General <PERSON>Francisco 
Viconti</PERSON>, <PERSON>Montero</PERSON> has said President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>, as Armed Forces 
commander in chief, and the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> have felt his 
return to military active duty is impossible; for that reason, 
he will be discharged. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32248 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat024_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-024 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Injured in Minor Traffic Accident </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0302185194 Madrid EFE in Spanish 1805 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA0302185194 </F>
<F P=104>  Madrid EFE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 3 Feb (EFE) -- A day after his inauguration 
and following a military parade in his honor, Venezuelan 
President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> today was involved in a minor traffic 
accident as his vehicle was leaving the Plaza de los Proceres in 
<LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>. 
  According to eyewitnesses, a television cameraman, while 
filming <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>'s departure, approached a horse of the Honor 
Guard escorting the presidential car, spooking the animal and 
prompting it to rear. 
  According to sources close to the president, the president's 
chauffeur was forced to brake abruptly to avoid hitting the 
horse. In the mishap, <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> received a blow so sharp that it 
broke his pen into three pieces. 
  The president, who complained about pain in his ribs, will 
be 
examined by doctors at the <LOCATION>Miraflores Palace</LOCATION>, seat of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Government</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-11506 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat082_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-082 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Government Unveils New Economic Plan </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Government Unveils New Economic Plan </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2804012094 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 2350 GMT 27 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2804012094 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Ligia Moreno</PERSON> and <PERSON>Aneris Gonzalez</PERSON> from "The News" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] [<PERSON>Moreno</PERSON>] The economic cabinet of President <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON> today announced the general strategy or guidelines of 
the economic plan to be implemented over the next five years. 
One of the highlights is that <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Petroleum</ORGANIZATION> will give <PERCENT>10 
percent</PERCENT> of its shares to its employees. Other major points 
include an emphasis on decentralization and private investments. 
Various sectors support the plan and think President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> is 
on the right track. Time will tell, however, and we have to wait 
and see how the economic plan proposed by the <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> cabinet 
works. 
  [<PERSON>Gonzalez</PERSON>] It is worth mentioning that a large number of 
people from all sectors--namely, CTV [Confederation of 
Venezuelan Workers], Consecomercio [<ORGANIZATION>National Council of Commerce 
and Services</ORGANIZATION>], and <PERSON>Fedecamaras</PERSON> [<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Federation of 
Associations and Chambers of Commerce and Industry</ORGANIZATION>]--have 
gathered here at the Eurobuilding Hotel, as you can see your 
screen, to discuss and review the entire economic program. As 
you rightly pointed out, <LOCATION>Ligia</LOCATION>, the opening to private 
investment is one of the highlights of this strategy, and, in 
some way, it has grabbed the attention of all sectors of society. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-32037 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat021_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-021 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  1 Feb 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Cabinet Members Discuss Immediate Plans </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0102033894 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 2350 GMT 31 Jan 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0102033894 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Members of the executive cabinet of President-elect 
<PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> will work in coordination in order to reactivate 
the country's productive apparatus. Here is a report on the 
plans of the new ministers, to whom we wish lots of success. 
  [Begin recording] [Unidentified reporter] First, we will 
interview Foreign Minister <PERSON>Miguel Angel Burelli Rivas</PERSON>. What are 
your first measures going to be? 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Burelli</ORGANIZATION>] Work. 
  [Reporter] What are your plans? 
  [<PERSON>Burelli</PERSON>] Reinforce or restore <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s image abroad, 
which has recently deteriorated. 
  [<PERSON>Enzo del Buffalo</PERSON>, nominee for chief of the <ORGANIZATION>Central Office 
of 
Coordination</ORGANIZATION> and Planning of the Presidency] We will try to 
conduct profound reforms in the basic industries and oil 
sectors. We will try to complement those reforms with policies 
consonant with the current circumstances in order to stabilize 
the foreign exchange rate, control inflation, and reduce fiscal 
deficits through austerity measures already announced. 
  [<PERSON>Rafael Angel Montero Revette</PERSON>, nominee for defense minister] 
We will review the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> plans and above all, we will 
reactivate and improve the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> social welfare plan. 
This includes the areas of health and housing, so our soldiers 
can live and work under better conditions. 
  [<PERSON>Abdon Vivas Teran</PERSON>, nominee for president of the Venezuelan 
Investment Fund] We will strengthen the privatization process. 
We will try to promote it on the basis of solid, technical, 
conceptual, and at the same time participative plans. We 
believe that participation will serve to increase the state's 
efficiency, distribute wealth, and make the productive apparatus 
more efficient. 
  [<PERSON>Ciro Anez Fonseca</PERSON>, nominee for agriculture and livestock 
minister] My priorities will be based on the president's 
interest to encourage productive sectors, particularly the 
agricultural sector, which has suffered difficulties during the 
past few years which we hope to resolve in the near future. 
  [German <PERSON>Luis Soriano</PERSON>, nominee for tourism minister] One of 
the most important activities in the country's economic 
development in the next few years will be developing tourism as 
an activity that not only will create new jobs but will also 
help develop important regions in the country that have been 
neglected in the past. 
  [<PERSON>Juan Nepomuceno Garrido</PERSON>, nominee for labor minister] The 
social welfare plan must be defined by the president of the 
Republic. So far we have not.... [pauses] I know his opinion 
and he knows mine, we both know what the country's current 
situation is. You can be sure that President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> will have 
in me a faithful, loyal minister, who is willing to work, follow 
his policies, and lead the country to a path of well-being. 
  [<PERSON>Ruben Creixems</PERSON>, nominee for justice minister] What was not 
done in 20 years cannot be done overnight. We must, however, 
work hard to attain our goals. 
  [<PERSON>Julio Sosa</PERSON>, nominee for finance minister] I believe 
balancing the budget is fundamental to curbing inflation, or at 
least reducing it to an acceptable level. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57895 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat102_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-102 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Reportedly Preparing To Remove Ministers </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Reportedly Preparing To Remove Ministers </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2605013394 Caracas ECONOMIA HOY in Spanish 25 May 94 p 5 </F>
<F P=103> PA2605013394 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas ECONOMIA HOY </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <PERSON>Gregorio Salazar</PERSON>] </F>
  [Text] Judging from unofficial yet reliable information 
circulating yesterday among journalists at <ORGANIZATION>Miraflores Palace</ORGANIZATION>, 
<PERSON>Cesar Quintini Rosales</PERSON>, transportation and communications 
minister, will not be the only one to leave President <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON>'s executive team. 
  Quintini will reportedly be joined by Development Minister 
<PERSON>Luis Carlos Palacios</PERSON>; <PERSON>Ciro Anez Fonseca</PERSON>, agriculture and 
livestock minister; and <PERSON>Roberto Perez Lecuna</PERSON>, environment and 
natural renewable resources minister 
  Development Minister <PERSON>Palacios</PERSON> has apparently followed the 
government's general guidelines in the commerce and industries 
sector, and certain people say the tendency will be to fall back 
and return to subsidies. Labor unions have criticized the 
minister, and it is believed that he is trying to absorb 
organizations like the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Consumer Education and 
Protection</ORGANIZATION> (IDEC) and the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Business Competition</ORGANIZATION>. 
  No one knows if the minister's problems stem from actions 
taken by his brother. Rumor has it that the minister's brother 
went to the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Business Competition</ORGANIZATION> and demanded that 
the organization change its decision to prevent the merger of 
<PERSON>Heinz</PERSON> and Yukery "because he is the minister's brother." 
Environment Minister <PERSON>Perez Lecuna</PERSON> has been forced to face the 
critical problem created by the water shortage. The extended 
drought has spread a desperation among the people that has not 
been seen in many years. Nevertheless, there is no information 
on any errors or omissions on the minister's part that could 
serve as the basis for his removal. 
  As for the agriculture and livestock minister, organizations 
like <PERSON>Fedeagro</PERSON> [<ORGANIZATION>National Federation of Agricultural-Livestock 
Producers</ORGANIZATION>], <PERSON>Fedenaga</PERSON> [Venezuelan Cattlemen's Federation], and 
Fedenaca [<ORGANIZATION>Peasant Union</ORGANIZATION>] have demanded <PERSON>Ciro Anez Fonseca</PERSON>'s 
removal, bitterly complaining about the minister's inability to 
act as a mediator to renegotiate the 143 billion bolivar debt in 
the agriculture sector and obtain a higher preferential rate to 
finance this year's harvest. 
  <PERSON>Cesar Quintini Rosales</PERSON>' problems in the <ORGANIZATION>Transportation and 
Communications Ministry</ORGANIZATION> are well known. They began with the 
resignation of deputy minister <PERSON>Rafael Iribarren</PERSON>, who reported 
the existence of corrupt groups supported by high-ranking 
officials. Quintini is not alone. Rumor has it that he is 
supported by <PERSON>Hugo Perez La Salvia</PERSON>, a member of the commission 
conducting the investigation of <PERSON>Iribarren</PERSON>'s charges, the results 
of which remain unknown. Journalists report that he was fired, 
but yesterday Quintini denied dismissing him. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57876 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat102_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-102 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Discusses `Abnormal Situation,' Two Crises </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Discusses `Abnormal Situation,' Two Crises </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2405151294 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 2200 GMT 
22 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2405151294 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Union Radio News"] </F>
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has indicated that in 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, there is a high demand for foreign exchange by 
speculators and that his government has been questioned for 
political rather than economic reasons. Caldera stated that an 
abnormal situation prevails in the country but added that his 
government will win the confidence battle. 
  Caldera emphasized the fact that there are currently two 
crises. One is the institutional crisis resulting from the 
trials of former Presidents <PERSON>Jaime Lusinchi</PERSON> and <PERSON>Carlos Andres 
Perez</PERSON> and the transitional government led by <PERSON>Jose Ramon 
Velasquez</PERSON>, which gave public employees a salary increase without 
enough available funds. The other is the economic crisis 
resulting from the intervention involving <ORGANIZATION>Banco Latino</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-10955 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat076_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-076 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuala </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Caldera on Constitutional Amendments </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Caldera on Constitutional Amendments </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1604162794 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 1550 GMT 15 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1604162794 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has emphasized that 
constitutional amendments must include provisions for an 
impeachment referendum, that is, the possibility that people 
could impeach any government official, including the president, 
who fails to perform his duties. He made these statements at the 
opening of a play called "<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, Political Crisis, and 
Constitutional Reforms." He also said that participative 
democracy must be the main aspect of the amendments to ensure 
that people will have a say in the nation's important 
sociopolitical issues. He also rejected all doubts that the 
community will not be able to understand the amendments due to 
the large number of articles. 
  [Begin Caldera recording] People will not discuss the 
amendments article by article; they will merely reply yes or no, 
as is done in every democratic country. They will ratify or 
reject the amendments drafted by the <ORGANIZATION>National Congress</ORGANIZATION>. [end 
recording] 
  He also said that it is necessary to give the Venezuelan 
people a greater opportunity to participate and more power in 
view of the situation the country is currently experiencing. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-33396 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat108_t_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-108 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Minister Downplays IMF, UN, World Bank Advice </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Minister Downplays IMF, UN, World Bank Advice </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0506201994 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1100 GMT 
3 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0506201994 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By <PERSON>Vicenter Briceno</PERSON> from the "Union Radio News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Central Information Office Minister <PERSON>Guillermo 
Alvarez Bajares</PERSON> today downplayed the suggestion by (Rutillier 
Orloge), adviser to the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>World 
Bank</ORGANIZATION>, that the government freeze prices, salaries, and the 
exchange rate for two months. 
  <PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON> said the expert's recommendation contradicts the 
economic policy of President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> as well as the 
economic policy of private economic organizations, such as the 
<ORGANIZATION>Higher Institute of Administration Studies</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Iesa</ORGANIZATION>, and the 
<ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan-American Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, Venamcham. The adviser 
participated in the forum: "Post-Sosa Plan Alternatives for 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>," where he said that President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> should adopt 
these measures, otherwise, the crisis will deepen and [words 
indistinct] stabilization in a more radical manner. 
  [Begin recording] [<PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>] That is the center of the 
economic opposition to the current government. It seems that the 
man went [words indistinct] rope at the house of the hanged. 
  [Reporter] [Words indistinct] all economic proposals of.... 
  [<ORGANIZATION>Alvarez</ORGANIZATION>, interrupting] No, quite the opposite; it disagrees 
with sectors of the private economy. 
  [Reporter] I meant the government's economic policy. 
  [<PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>] The government's economic policy is absolutely 
independent from what <PERSON>Mr.</PERSON> [name indistinct], the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Venamcham</LOCATION>, 
and <ORGANIZATION>Iesa</ORGANIZATION> might say. Absolutely different. 
  [Reporter] [Words indistinct] break from <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION>? 
  [<PERSON>Alvarez</PERSON>] No, perhaps a break between the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Iesa</ORGANIZATION> and 
Venamcham. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-10382 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat044_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-044 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera, Brazil's Franco To Increase Cooperation </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  PA0503223594 Caracas Venezolana de Television Network in 
Spanish 2350 GMT 4 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0503223594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Venezolana de Television Network </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Spanish </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "The News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] Brazilian President <PERSON>Itamar Franco</PERSON> and Venezuelan 
President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> agreed, during a meeting held at La 
Guzmania presidential residence, to increase bilateral 
cooperation and fully use consultation and political dialogue 
mechanisms. 
  The two presidents decided to create a high-level binational 
commission that will be chaired by their foreign ministers and 
comprised of the ministers in charge of bilateral cooperation 
issues. The presidents also agreed to hold the second meeting 
of the Venezuela-Brazil political consultation mechanism in our 
country. Furthermore, they issued instructions to authorities 
in the foreign trade sector to assess and step up the 
negotiations to reach an economic complementation agreement 
within the <ORGANIZATION>ALADI</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Latin American Integration Association</ORGANIZATION>] 
framework. 
  Even though no agreements were signed in the meeting, it 
helped establish the groundwork for common projects in different 
sectors. In the highway sector they agreed to finish highway 
BR-174 and to broaden a land transportation agreement. In the 
electric sector they reached an agreement for the purchase of 
Venezuelan energy. In the hydrographic sector the topic was 
mining sector they will work jointly to protect Indians at the 
border area. In the ecology sector the issue was ecological 
tourism in a joint action to recover areas degraded by illegal 
miners. In the steel works sector the <ORGANIZATION>SIDOR</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Orinoco Iron</ORGANIZATION> and 
Steel Works] furnaces will manufacture iron and manganese alloys. 
  Later, during a news conference, the Brazilian president 
said 
his government is carefully analyzing border problems with our 
country, adding that neither <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> nor <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> should neglect 
looking into these issues because they might cause an atmosphere 
of uncertainty in the relations between the two nations. 
Moreover, President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> said that following the 
talks with his counterpart he is fully convinced the current 
Brazilian Government is clearly inclined to adopt the necessary 
measures to prevent illegal mining on Venezuelan territory. 
  [Begin recording] [Franco, in Portuguese] It is clear that 
the border problem between <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> will be 
carefully analyzed. We have a very extensive border with 
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, a border that was abandoned by our peoples. Now with 
the presence of President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> and with the presence 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Government</ORGANIZATION>, we will be able to study and 
carefully analyze those aspects which today cause problems in 
our relations. 
  [<LOCATION>Caldera</LOCATION>] I am fully convinced that the current Brazilian 
Government is clearly inclined to adopt all the measures 
possible to prevent the garimpeiros' [Brazilian gold seekers] 
illegal mining activities in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> -- both by watching the 
border and by adopting precautionary measures in the State of 
<LOCATION>Roraima</LOCATION> and other border states where they may have their 
operations centers and by enforcing legal measures through 
Brazilian courts against those who have perpetrated illegal 
actions in this area. [end recording] 
  Referring to the first meeting held between the heads of 
state of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gilberto</PERSON> [as heard] <PERSON>Poletto</PERSON>, 
minister of state and president of the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Trade Institute</ORGANIZATION>, 
and <PERSON>Andres Velasquez</PERSON>, governor of <ORGANIZATION>Bolivar State</ORGANIZATION>, agreed that new 
roads have been opened to strengthen bilateral relations. 
  [Begin recording] [<PERSON>Poletto</PERSON>] There was talk about stepping up 
the negotiations to sign an economic cooperation agreement 
between <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> because this had been discussed a 
couple of years ago. This will bolster the partial agreement we 
currently have, perhaps by adding more products and including 
some additional norms. The goal is to consolidate and improve 
trade relations between <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, which have 
recently increased but are still insufficient compared with the 
immense possibilities we have in different trade sectors. 
  [<PERSON>Velasquez</PERSON>] Specifically referring to the Brazilians' case, 
I have had the opportunity to discuss a specific proposal. All 
the agreements that the <ORGANIZATION>Venezuelan Government</ORGANIZATION> has to establish 
with the <ORGANIZATION>Brazilian Government</ORGANIZATION> should include a specific 
agreement with the <ORGANIZATION>Roraima State Government</ORGANIZATION>, because we believe 
<ORGANIZATION>Roraima State</ORGANIZATION> has become an excellent supply center, or 
logistics support center, for illegal miners, meaning the 
garimpeiros. In addition, this has to be discussed at length 
because the latest information we have, based on investigations 
that have been conducted, is that the garimpeiros are not just 
involved in illegal gold mining activities. They also act as 
scouts and guard beachheads for drug trafficking activities, and 
the illegal landing strips built by them are later used for drug 
trafficking. [end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-10180 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat068_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Former Minister Examines Possibility of Coup </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Former Minister Examines Possibility of Coup </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0704231594 Caracas EL DIARIO DE CARACAS in Spanish 2 Apr 
94 p 3 </F>

<F P=103> PA0704231594 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas EL DIARIO DE CARACAS </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Article by General <PERSON>Fernando Ochoa Antich</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s </F>
former defense and foreign minister: "The Coup d'Etat"] 
  [Text] I read <PERSON>Hilarion Cardozo</PERSON>'s statements with great 
interest, not only because of their striking content but because 
he has always accurately interpreted the Venezuelan military's 
thinking and feelings. His position is clear. He says there 
are three groups in the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>. The first one, described 
as conservative, will follow ideas similar to the ones endorsed 
by the 27 <DATE>November</DATE> coup leaders and which are close to economic 
right-wing groups. Another one is located, as far as I 
understand, in the organization's middle ranks and has 
progressive tendencies. It maintains contacts with radical 
groups in our political sector. A third group prefers to give 
the <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> government the military strength to face the current 
crisis. Cardozo is right. Three groups exist and have existed 
in the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1958</DATE>. 
  We recall the initial efforts of <PERSON>Rodolfo Jose Cardenas</PERSON>, the 
right-wing trend of the conspiracy against <PERSON>Luis Herrera</PERSON>, and the 
first basis of military support for <PERSON>Romulo Betancourt</PERSON> when he 
decided to put a stop to leftist congressmen of the era 
following the Encanto train attack. I believe it is necessary to 
clairfy <PERSON>Cardozo</PERSON>'s proposal. Two groups have always existed in 
the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION>, united by a national feeling: one, a majority 
devoid of political passion, which carries out its professional 
military job, and the other, which thinks the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> is 
the path to power. 
  What <PERSON>Cardozo</PERSON> failed to explain in his statement is that the 
politically-influenced group requires sufficient social 
deterioration to convince the majority of the Armed Forces of 
the need for a coup d'etat. Without those special conditions 
existing in the country, a coup simply would fail and would not 
be more than a coffee shop conspiracy. President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON> and 
his government have sufficient political experience to prevent 
the forming of support around the minority group that might 
stage such a coup d'etat. I am certain of that. What does 
concern me is the vast popular unrest that exists against the 
leadership sectors for maintaining excessive privileges and 
unbridled ambitions. We Venezuelans blame that leadership for 
the misguided administration of the country. Until <DATE>1970</DATE>, we had 
faith in creating a modern, developed, and different society. 
Expectations ended in utter failure and frustration. That 
perception permeated the <ORGANIZATION>Armed Forces</ORGANIZATION> and was the cause of the 4 
<DATE>February</DATE> and 27 <DATE>November</DATE> coups. The prospect that <PERSON>Rafael 
Caldera</PERSON> would come to power, with all his moral authority and 
abilities, calmed the country during those historic moments and 
again created new confidence in the Armed Forces. That is the 
true origin of the existing institutional stability. 
  Certainly, <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> must reestablish a national 
consensus to avert a coup d'etat. <PERSON>Hilarion Cardozo</PERSON> is clear on 
this, but he does not interpret or say this consensus can only 
be secured by achieving profound national change. That is the 
government's dilemma. If it does not face the existing 
political, financial, labor, and judicial state of affairs and 
continues with sweeping reforms, popular resentment will again 
infiltrate the Armed Forces' ranks, creating the climate for a 
coup d'etat -- hence the real fear of <PERSON>Hilarion Cardozo</PERSON> and 
traditional party leaderships. They know the first obligation 
of a politician, moreso if he is a chief of state, is to 
preserve power. What will <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> do if he feels that 
the very basis of his government is threatened? Will he permit 
a climate for conspiracy or, on the other hand, will he prefer 
to lead the national resentment, conducting the big changes 
required by the country? Only time will tell. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-11507 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat082_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-082 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Names FOGADE, Bank Directors </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Names FOGADE, Bank Directors </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2804001194 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1600 GMT 
27 Apr 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2804001194 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> from the "Union Radio Noticias" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has sworn in new directors 
for <ORGANIZATION>FOGADE</ORGANIZATION> [Deposit Guarantee and Banking Protection Fund] and 
the <ORGANIZATION>General Bank Superintendency</ORGANIZATION>--<PERSON>Norys Aguirre</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tesalio 
Cadenas</PERSON>, respectively. After they were sworn in, both officers 
ruled out controls on foreign exchange. They also said they 
intend to evaluate the assistance given to banks as well as the 
proposals made by <PERSON>Gustavo Roosen</PERSON>, special commissioner for 
financial reforms. 
  <ORGANIZATION>FOGADE</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Norys Aguirre</PERSON> stressed her institution's 
duty 
to restore confidence in the financial system, and she said that 
currently the state is the greatest <ORGANIZATION>FOGADE</ORGANIZATION> contributor. She 
referred to strategies by the leadership of <ORGANIZATION>FOGADE</ORGANIZATION> by announcing 
reforms to the law that created this fund. 
  [Begin Aguirre recording] Basically there are two 
strategies. 
One is the short-term strategy, and this is the immediate 
solution to the current banking crisis. The long-term strategy 
deals with reforms, and if these are needed I will be the first 
person to propose them, as I have done up to now, through 
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to the government, in due course. I am not afraid to 
make changes. If a complete <ORGANIZATION>FOGADE</ORGANIZATION> reorganization is needed, 
this will be done. [end recording] 
  For his part, <PERSON>Tesalio Cadenas</PERSON> admitted that the <ORGANIZATION>General Bank 
Superintendency</ORGANIZATION> had faults that failed to prevent greater 
control--in other words, stricter control--of the Venezuelan 
financial system. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-34713 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat121_t_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-121 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Orders Release of 2d Coup Attempt Leader </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Orders Release of 2d Coup Attempt Leader </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2206171894 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 2200 GMT 
21 Jun 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA2206171894 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [From the "Union Radio News" newscast] </F>
  [Text] President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has ordered the release of 
General <PERSON>Francisco Visconti</PERSON>, leader of the second coup attempt 
who was in exile in <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> for more than a year. 
  Visconti has received the presidential pardon in exchange 
for 
a discharge from the Armed Forces as part of the conditions the 
government had demanded to approve the pardon. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-57302 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat096_t_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-096 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  16 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Escovar Decries Existence of a `Rumor Mill' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Escovar Decries Existence of a `Rumor Mill' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA1705153394 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 2200 GMT 
16 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA1705153394 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> from the "Union Radio News" </F>
newscast] 
  [Text] Interior Minister <PERSON>Ramon Escovar Salom</PERSON> has described 
the rumor mill as a criminal tactic to undermine the country's 
prestige abroad and the calm of citizens. He noted that the 
rumor mill has been active these past few days, and that even 
the health of President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> has been questioned. 
  Escovar Salom gave no information on the inquiry conducted 
on 
a destabilization plan that includes this chain of rumors but 
termed them sources of unrest that seek to crumble the public's 
support for the Caldera government. He insisted this thing about 
the bogeyman is no cliche, but rather a conspiracy that involves 
a manipulation of the public and in no way is related to social 
unhappiness or protests over the water shortage. 
  [Begin <PERSON>Escovar Salom</PERSON> recording] Some people have made the 
absurd assertion that I want to explain the social crisis by 
blaming the bogeyman. I never said that. You are the first to 
know that is not so. You clearly heard what I said. The social 
crisis, which the government acknowledges, the economic crisis, 
and severe difficulties the country is experiencing is one 
matter. The manipulation and tactics by some sectors that have 
an interest in heightening the crisis and seeking other goals is 
another matter. That is what these sectors are trying to do. The 
events that took place over the weekend are clear proof that my 
remarks were serious and justified. I mean the rumor campaign. 
This rumor mill is criminal. I mean all these announcements of 
the future of the bolivar, devaluation, and alleged financial 
and fiscal measures the government is purportedly going to take. 
[end recording] 
  Commenting on the resignation of some members of the 
cabinet, 
<PERSON>Escovar Salom</PERSON> said any decision on the matter falls solely 
within the purview of President <PERSON>Caldera</PERSON>. On another matter, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Interior Minister</ORGANIZATION> commented on the border dispute between <LOCATION>Merida</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Zulia States</LOCATION>. He noted this problem must be handled with 
utmost caution and prudence. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-35051 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat124_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-124 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  27 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   President Caldera To Announce Economic Measures </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    President Caldera To Announce Economic Measures </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2706232094 Hamburg DPA in Spanish 2202 GMT 27 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> PA2706232094 </F>
<F P=104>  Hamburg DPA </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, 27 Jun (DPA) -- The administration of 
President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON> will implement controls on prices and 
on the dollar exchange to cope with the severe financial and 
monetary crisis in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, congressmen from three political 
parties announced after meeting with the chief of state. 
  Spokespersons for the ruling <ORGANIZATION>National Convergence</ORGANIZATION>, the 
Movement Toward Socialism (MAS), and the opposition workers 
<ORGANIZATION>Radical Cause Party</ORGANIZATION> expressed their support today at <LOCATION>Miraflores</LOCATION> 
Palace for the government's "emergency" measures and requested 
tighter controls on the banking system. One-third of the 
country's banks ended up in state hands due to the liquidity 
crisis at nine institutions. 
  The opposition <ORGANIZATION>Social Christian Party</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Copei</LOCATION>, and the social 
democratic <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Action Party</ORGANIZATION> did not express their 
position on the new official measures of <LOCATION>Caldera</LOCATION>, who began his 
second government term on 2 <DATE>February</DATE>. The 78-year-old president 
will address the country on a television network tonight to 
announce the new measures. 
  As a reflection of the severe situation, the dollar has 
jumped from 117 bolivares (national currency) in <DATE>late April</DATE> to 
200 <DATE>last Thursday</DATE>. The government has availed itself of a 
prolonged banking holiday that began on <DATE>Friday</DATE> to draft the new 
measures. 
  According to commentators, the Venezuelan state provided 
assistance "without sufficient guarantees" to new banks in 
crisis on the order of <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY>. This "financial crack" began 
last <DATE>January</DATE> with the intervention at <ORGANIZATION>Banco Latino</ORGANIZATION>, until that 
time considered the country's second most important bank. The 
state intervened at eight other banks two weeks ago. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-56646 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat088_t_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-088 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Banking Leader Says Exchange Market Controlled </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Banking Leader Says Exchange Market Controlled </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA0505150694 Caracas Union Radio Network in Spanish 1100 GMT 
4 May 94 </F>

<F P=103> PA0505150694 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas Union Radio Network </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by <PERSON>Vicente Briceno</PERSON> from <LOCATION>Miraflores</LOCATION> Palace for the </F>
"Union Radio News" newscast -- live] 
  [Text] The situation recently provoked by the abrupt 
increase in the dollar's price, from 118 to 127 bolivares, 
prompted a meeting between President <PERSON>Rafael Caldera</PERSON>; <PERSON>Jose Bouza 
Izquierdo</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>National Banking Council</ORGANIZATION>; and <PERSON>Berend 
Roosen</PERSON>, commissioner for financial reforms; as well as <PERSON>Andres 
Caldera</PERSON>, minister of the Presidency Secretariat, and <PERSON>Ciro Anez 
Fonseca</PERSON>, minister of agriculture and livestock. 
  The well-known banker attributed <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s decrease in the 
rhythm of the devaluation, from <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>2.5 percent</PERCENT>, to 
actions that were coordinated by the <ORGANIZATION>Central Bank of Venezuela</ORGANIZATION> 
and private banks. This has managed to positively control the 
dollar's exchange rate which has prevailed since last week. 
  [Begin Bouza Izquierdo recording] Nothing new or different 
is 
happening. The government has just ratified one more time that a 
foreign exchange control or a maxi-devaluation are not part of 
our current plans. I believe this is enough to believe we do not 
have to rush out and buy foreign currency with anguish, under 
pressure, or with nervousness. In fact, this only pushes the 
price upward and people who go to the parallel market will pay 
amounts that far exceed the foreign currency's real value. The 
banks are within the limitations that are characteristic of the 
operations we carry out, supplying the foreign currency that the 
<ORGANIZATION>Central Bank of Venezuela</ORGANIZATION> passes on to us. Our actions are 
within an absolutely regular scheme. I do not think we should 
feel concerned or nervous. That will only worsen the situation. 
[end recording] 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-11083 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drlat077_t_94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-LAT-94-077 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> Venezuela </F>
<H3> <TI>   Caldera Says Constituent Assembly Will Not Solve Problems </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Caldera Says Constituent Assembly Will Not Solve Problems </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   PA2004163094 Caracas EL DIARIO DE CARACAS in Spanish 15 Apr 
94 p 27 </F>

<F P=103> PA2004163094 </F>
<F P=104>  Caracas EL DIARIO DE CARACAS </F>
<F P=105>  Spanish </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 
