<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901001-0164 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-01-90 1756EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Jews-Vichy     10-01 0551</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Jews-Vichy,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>France Recalls Vichy's Anti-Semitic Laws</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Acts of persecution and harsh anti-Semitism among
Nazi collaborators were relived and re-examined <DATE>Monday</DATE>, 50 years
after the start of a notorious crackdown that led to the deaths of
more than 73,000 French Jews.
   ``We must not blame the (Nazi) occupation for what was the sole
responsibility of the legitimate French government. The laws met
only utter silence from the French people,'' said former Justice
Minister <PERSON>Robert Badinter</PERSON>, who presided over the daylong symposium
on ``The Vichy Laws.''
   ``Vichy was obsessed with taking measures against Jews,''
<PERSON>Badinter</PERSON> told about 250 people at the conference.
   ``The Vichy Laws,'' named for the <ORGANIZATION>Vichy Government</ORGANIZATION> that
controlled unoccupied <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and territories from <DATE>1940</DATE> to <DATE>1943</DATE>,
prevented <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s 350,000 Jews from holding public office,
teaching, attending university, owning stores and working in the
media. It was implemented 11 weeks after <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> fell to the Germans.
   The laws, later reinforced by measures to send Jews to
concentration camps, defined ``who is a Jew,'' using criteria far
more sweeping than the racial laws drafted by the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>.
   Nazi hunter <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON> estimated 3,000 Jews died from cold
and starvation from <DATE>1940</DATE> to <DATE>1942</DATE> in French-run camps ``where there
wasn't a single German soldier.''
   In all, 76,000 Jews were deported to death camps from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
About 2,500 survived, historians estimate.
   ``The Jewish Laws did not come out of the blue because
anti-Semitism existed in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> well before the German victory in
<DATE>June 1940</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Henri Amouroux</PERSON>, a historian at the symposium,
sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Contemporary Jewish Documentation</ORGANIZATION> and
the Sons and <ORGANIZATION>Daughters of Jews Deported</ORGANIZATION> from the <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   ``Anti-Semitism developed in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> in a climate of economic
and social crisis. Thousands of Jews, chased out of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, fleeing the <LOCATION>Nazis</LOCATION>, came to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and were accused of
taking jobs,'' he said.
   Historians say the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> laws were a cornerstone of a right-wing
ideology that sought to undo the liberalizing, human
rights-oriented reforms of the French Revolution.
   ``The laws erased the advances made during the Age of
Enlightenment,'' said <PERSON>Zev Sternhell</PERSON>, a history professor at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Jerusalem</ORGANIZATION>. ``They reflect a new concept of the
nation, not as a melting pot but as an extended family with
everybody having the same blood.''
   For historian <PERSON>Denis Peschansky</PERSON>, the laws were a way for Marshal
<PERSON>Philippe Petain</PERSON>, <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>'s leader, to explain the French military
defeat and punish those deemed responsible.
   ``<PERSON>Petain</PERSON> had to find reasons within French society for the
debacle - he certainly couldn't blame the army because it was in
power - so he blamed the Jews, Communists, Freemasons and other
foreigners,'' <PERSON>Peschansky</PERSON> said.
   The laws also revoked the citizenship of about 400,000 Jews in
colonial <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Morocco</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tunisia</LOCATION>, which were French
protectorates.
   ``My mother, who had six small children and worked in the
arsenal in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>, was fired immediately,'' said a woman in the
audience.
   Other survivors described the discrimination and persecution
that followed.
   In <DATE>September 1943</DATE>, <PERSON>Samuel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rachel Ewenczyk</PERSON> closed their dry
goods store in <LOCATION>Grenoble</LOCATION>, fleeing to the Alps to escape deportation.
   ``One week later, thanks to the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> laws, the French police
requisitioned the store as a Jewish store, and sold it to a
non-Jewish person,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Ewenczyk</PERSON>, 78, recalled.
   After <LOCATION>Grenoble</LOCATION> was liberated by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops in <DATE>August 1944</DATE>, the
family returned to claim the property.
   ``The man in the shop protested, saying he had bought the shop,
but my husband asked, `Who did you buy it from? I never sold it.'
We were back in business <DATE>a week later</DATE>,'' she said.
   The <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government, named for a city in central <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, was
never recognized by the Allies. The Nazis annulled the armistice
with <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> after the Allies invaded <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> in <DATE>November 1943</DATE>
and occupied <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-12325</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DGYABADBFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930724
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  24 JUL 93 / Victims of Vichy, victims of France: Suppressing Vichy's
shame helped restore French morale and unity after the war. But how, 50
years on, can the Republic now respond honourably to the suffering of
victims? asks Robert Cottrell
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ROBERT COTTRELL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IF THE deranged killer of <PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, the former <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government police
chief, acted criminally in the eyes of the French authorities, it must also
be said that he acted conveniently. Bousquet's murder on <DATE>June 8</DATE> came barely
a month before <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s first annual day of official remembrance for victims
of <ORGANIZATION>Vichy</ORGANIZATION>'s 'racist and anti-semitic persecutions.'
As a result, when prime minister <PERSON>Edouard Balladur</PERSON> delivered his remembrance
day speech in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 16</DATE>, he was no longer obliged to explain how the
man who had organised many of those 'racist and anti-semitic persecutions'
was still leading, at 84, the comfortable life of a retired banker barely a
mile away on the <ORGANIZATION>Avenue Raphael</ORGANIZATION>.
Though coincidental, the death of <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> and the introduction of a
remembrance day for <ORGANIZATION>Vichy</ORGANIZATION>'s victims have dramatised a national dilemma for
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in which history, morality and politics each plays a part: the
dilemma of whether <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>, the wartime government of Marshal <PERSON>Philippe Petain</PERSON>,
which sought to lead a defeated and part-occupied <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> along the 'way of
collaboration' with <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>, is a chapter of French history best remembered,
or best forgotten.
The inaugurating of a remembrance day may argue that the first of those
sentiments - to remember - has gained the high ground. But <PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON>,
while he lived, proved the enduring power of those who would rather forget.
He displayed to his end a grim confidence that he would never be required to
face trial for his part in the deportation of some 75,000 Jews from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
to the Nazi death-camps.
'If they want to mess with me,' he said shortly before his death, 'then fine
. . . I will defend myself, and I have the material to do so. But I will be
utterly astonished if the trial takes place.'
It was with <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>'s authority that French police arrested 13,000 Jews in
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 16-17 1942</DATE>, including 4,000 children whom even the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> had
been willing to spare. Most were held in the Velodrome d'Hiver, a
since-demolished bicycle-track, before being sent to French-run
concentration camps south of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> - and thence to <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION>.
The date of the start of that round-up having been fixed for the new
remembrance day, the ceremony in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> was held at the site of the
<LOCATION>Velodrome</LOCATION>, where unofficial ceremonies have taken place in past years. In
the course of a short and solemn speech, the prime minister declared that
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was 'in mourning,' and repeated the promise given by President
<PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> that a monument would be erected 'to perpetuate the
memory of what took place here.'
Until that monument arises, the perpetuation of memory will rest heavily on
the work of <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, the French lawyer and Nazi-hunter who published
his investigation of Bousquet 10 years ago in a book called Vichy-Auschwitz.
Impelled by <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON>, the French public prosecutor eventually charged
<PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> in <DATE>1991</DATE> with 'crimes against humanity' (which under French law
enjoy no statute of limitation); but the case vanished into such thickets of
procedural delay that the prospective defendant was not alone in his doubts
that it would ever reach court.
Bousquet had already walked free from one post-war trial in <DATE>1949</DATE> because the
courts at that time were concerned with treason, not genocide, even though
the leaders of Vichy had furthered both causes. A half-century later, he was
the last survivor of those who planned the worst of Vichy's persecutions. To
that extent, his death has given one irreversible victory to those who think
Vichy best forgotten.
The possibility has been lost for ever of a great pedagogical trial which
might have examined and judged not only <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> himself, but also, through
him, the regime of which he was a part. French courts may yet try <PERSON>Paul
Touvier</PERSON>, a former officer in the collaborationist <LOCATION>Militia</LOCATION>, for alleged war
crimes. But <PERSON>Touvier</PERSON> was a relatively low-level figure, and is in any case
charged with acting on the orders of the <ORGANIZATION>Gestapo</ORGANIZATION>, not of Vichy.
To explain the last and decisive hesitations of French justice in respect of
the <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> case, <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> and others have pointed a finger at President
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>, who worked for the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government from 1941-42 before entering
the resistance. Mitterrand reputedly met <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, and they moved
in the same political circles after the war.
Klarsfeld suggests that <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> may nurse a 'nostalgia for his youth.' It
is, at any rate, an observable truth that the further the French president's
motives and actions extend into his past, the more impenetrable they become.
If <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> did indeed choose discreetly to discourage <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>'s trial,
then he may well have done so partly out of a political judgment that such a
trial would not be in the public interest; partly out of a personal loyalty;
and partly out of that strange private reservoir of affections which has
also led him to send a bouquet of roses to <PERSON>Marshal Petain</PERSON>'s tomb each
<DATE>November 11</DATE>, the anniversary of the ending of the first world war.
Only after a barrage of criticism from his friends as well as political
rivals last <DATE>November</DATE> did the president finally concede that he would have to
find a way of managing differently the 'contradictions of history.' His
decree, <DATE>three months later</DATE>, instituting the remembrance day for <PERSON>Marshal
Petain</PERSON>'s victims, must be read as a realisation of that promise.
In opposing a judicial reopening of the great questions of <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, President
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> would also have been echoing the policy of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> since the
Liberation. It was <ORGANIZATION>General de Gaulle</ORGANIZATION> who recognised in <DATE>1944</DATE> that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
could scarcely take its place among the victors of the second world war if
it also acknowledged the realities of the armistice and the collaboration
over which the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government had presided.
His response was to decree that the French Third Republic had assigned power
unconstitutionally to <PERSON>Marshal Petain</PERSON> in <DATE>June 1940</DATE>; that the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government
had been illegal from its formation; and that the armistice concluded by
<PERSON>Petain</PERSON> with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> had been void. To efface what had once been the
substance of <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, the Gaullists substituted their insistence that the
'true' <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had never surrendered; that the flame of legitimate government
had been carried through its dark hour by de Gaulle's Free French forces;
and that the mass of ordinary people remaining in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had manifested
their loyalty by resisting the Nazi occupant.
It necessarily followed from the Gaullist version of history that atrocities
which had taken place in wartime <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> must have been attributable to
Germans, not Frenchmen. The plain fact that the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government had devised
and implemented a policy of Jewish persecution, initially of its own
volition and later as the French contribution to the Nazi genocide, was -
with its potentially devastating implications for <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s reputation - the
most taboo subject of all, and one which the specially-convened <ORGANIZATION>High Court
of Justice</ORGANIZATION> showed absolutely no disposition to pursue in its post-war trials
of Vichy officials.
Thus <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>, among the last defendants to go before the court, faced no
serious questioning about his role in the arrest and deportation of Jews
from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and the documentary evidence in his prosecution file went
unexamined.
Suppressing the shame of Vichy helped restore the morale and the unity of
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. But it also impeded the drawing of lessons about how and why the
machinery of French government had in reality passed very smoothly into
<PERSON>Petain</PERSON>'s hands.
Not until <DATE>May 1992</DATE>, for example, did the national training centre for the
French police force feel able to conduct its first internal seminars on
police work during the war, the Ministry of the <ORGANIZATION>Interior</ORGANIZATION> having judged,
according to <PERSON>Le Monde</PERSON>, 'that the wounds were sufficiently healed for
reflection to be undertaken at the institutional level.'
Those who attended the seminars were reminded that <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION> had been
able, with only 3,000 members of its own security services operating in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, to secure the arrest and deportation from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> of 75,000 Jews and
40,000 resistants, as well as to supply itself with 650,000 French forced
labourers.
Had the French police refused to do the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>' work, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> would have been
obliged either to commit much more of its own manpower to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, or else
reduce the scale of its oppressions there.
Today, if arguments still rage about the motives and the intentions of
<PERSON>Petain</PERSON>'s government, the concrete actions of Vichy are neither denied nor
deniable.
The problem which remains is one of political acceptance. The victims of
Vichy were persecuted on French soil, by agents of a French government, in
conformity with the French law of the day.
Can a formula be found by which the Republic of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> may respond
honourably to the suffering of <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>'s victims, and yet still, as it
believes it must, avoid identifying their tormentors at least to some degree
with <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> itself?
According to <PERSON>Jean-Pierre Chevenement</PERSON>, the former French defence minister,
the danger of blurring the distinction between the '<PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>' and the '<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'
of 1940-44 remains that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> would then 'stand with <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in the fascist camp which lost the second world war . . . Her
permanent membership of the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations Security Council</ORGANIZATION>, with right of
veto, would lose its justification . . . By going down that road, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
would abdicate its place in the world.'
If <PERSON>Chevenement</PERSON>'s warnings appear exaggerated, they reflect well enough
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s acute sensitivity to its 'rank,' particularly in relation to
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> within <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Yet as the decades pass, and as death claims both the tormentors and
survivors of <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, the justification for denying Vichy so absolutely must
appear increasingly open to question, if the legacy and the lessons of <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>
are to be rooted enduringly in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s memory.
In the view of <PERSON>Alfred Grosser</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s leading political scientist: 'Let us
not make-believe that the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> regime was a little island standing apart
from French society, or that the ruling class of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> went into
hibernation until the parenthesis was closed and the Republic could resume
its interrupted life.
'The victims of <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, French and non-French alike, were indeed the victims
of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. A <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> with a twisted expression, but a <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> which stands
clearly within the continuity of its own history.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9211 Courts.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page I
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900710-0072 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-10-90 1231EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Vichy     07-10 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Vichy,0599</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opponents of Collaboration Honored On Vichy's 50th Anniversary</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID CRARY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> observed the 50th anniversary of the
formation of the collaborationist <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and
honored the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> members who opposed Marshal <PERSON>Philippe
Petain</PERSON>'s ascension to power.
   Petain, a grandfatherly World War I hero, was installed as
all-powerful leader of the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> regime by a 569-80 vote on <DATE>July
10, 1940</DATE>.
   Three of the legislators who voted ``no'' survive, and two
attended commemorations at <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Grand Casino</LOCATION>, where the vote was
taken. <PERSON>Maurice Montel</PERSON>, 90, and <PERSON>Emile Fouchard</PERSON>, 88, were joined by
Parliamentary Affairs Minister <PERSON>Jean Poperen</PERSON>.
   Poperen said the 80 lawmakers, acting ``with lucidity and
courage, against all the appearances and the evidence of the
moment, have earned the eternal recognition of the nation.''
   Vichy's mayor, <PERSON>Claude Malhuret</PERSON>, described the votes against
<PERSON>Petain</PERSON> as ``one of the first acts of resistance in our country.''
   Malhuret also said <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> should be vigilant in countering a
resurgence of racist and anti-Semitic rhetoric ``such as we heard
before the war.''
   <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>, who signed an armistice with the Germans on <DATE>June 22</DATE>, was
84 at the time, but widely respected across <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. He was
convinced <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> would win the war and that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had no
alternative but to cooperate with <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s government, including Parliament members, had fled from
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> as German forces approached, going first to Tours on <DATE>June 10</DATE>,
then to <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> on <DATE>June 14</DATE> and <DATE>two weeks later</DATE> to <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>, a
tranquil health spa.
   On <DATE>July 10</DATE>, the parliamentary majority adopted a text which
said: ``The <ORGANIZATION>National Assembly</ORGANIZATION> gives all power to the government of
the <LOCATION>Republic</LOCATION>, under the authority and the signature of <PERSON>Marshal
Petain</PERSON>, for the purpose of promoting a new constitution of the
French state.''
   Of the 80 legislators who opposed <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>, 31 were incarcerated
or put under house arrest during the war, two were killed and five
died in captivity.
   Since the war, <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> has struggled to live down its association
with Nazi collaboration.
   In the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, the town ranked as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s No. 1 mineral springs
resort. Now it ranks 14th, and unemployment in the town of 30,500
is estimated at <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>.
   Malhuret described as ``irritating'' the link between <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> and
the collaborationists.
   ``If the town of <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> was partly responsible, it would be less
``But that isn't the case. Nobody in <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION> went out in search of
the government and the assembly.''
   The <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government received little in return for its
collaboration, exporting goods and labor to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> in exchange for
the privilege of running day-to-day administrative affairs. Only
two-fifths of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was under <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>'s jurisdiction, the rest was
occupied territory.
   In <DATE>August 1944</DATE>, as Allied forces swept through <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>
fled <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> and was arrested, then was allowed to leave for
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
   He returned voluntarily to <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>April 1945</DATE>, was tried for
treason and sentenced to death. Charles De Gaulle commuted the
sentence to life imprisonment and <PERSON>Petain</PERSON> died in <DATE>1951</DATE> on the Isle
of Yeu, off <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> coast.
   In <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, officials of the <ORGANIZATION>French Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
celebrated the 50th anniversary of an appeal by the outlawed
Communist underground for resistance against <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>.
   Communist legislator <PERSON>Andre Lajoinie</PERSON> said the men who isssud the
appeal represented ``the first resistance base on national
territory.'' A radio appeal for Frenchmen to resist the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> had
been broadcast from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> on <DATE>June 18</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-685</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EI1EIAC1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940928
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  28 SEP 94 / Vichy casts a shadow: France still refuses to accept shared
responsibility for its past
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By IAN DAVIDSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Revelations that President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> had murky links
with the right wing before, during and after the second world war have sent
the French political class into a buzz of shock and horror. Socialists are
dismayed that this latest blow to the reputation of their one-time leader
will further contaminate their own damaged credibility. But not even his
rightwing critics have crowed too loudly, for no political clan is quite
comfortable when the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> era is under discussion.
That is the point of this controversy: it is not what it reveals about the
dubious political debut of <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON>, but what it reveals about
the feelings of the French today towards that inglorious chapter of their
history. They still have difficulty facing up to what happened between the
<DATE>fall</DATE> of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> in <DATE>1940</DATE> and the liberation of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1944</DATE>, when the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>
government of <PERSON>Marshal Petain</PERSON> submitted to the Nazi victors.
Every so often old wounds are reopened by a new investigation, and each time
the French react with consternation, as if they had never heard of that
traumatic era. Then the shock dies away, and the unacceptable past is again
buried.
So it is with the new book by <PERSON>Pierre Pean</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Une Jeunesse Francaise*</ORGANIZATION>. It
provides the fullest account yet of <LOCATION>Mitterrand</LOCATION>'s early career, with many
previously unpublished details. But most of the story has long been known:
that <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> came from a conservative, bourgeois background, and started
his political career far to the right of centre; that before joining the
Resistance he worked for the <PERSON>Petain</PERSON> government, and was awarded the top
Vichy decoration, the 'Francisque'; and that he remained right of centre
after the war.
What is most disturbing about the book is not mainly what it reveals about
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> then, but what it reveals about <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> now. Pean clears him
of any anti-semitism under <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>; but it is dismaying that today <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>
should still be pretending that he did not then know about <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>'s
anti-semitic laws, even though they led to the deportation of thousands of
Jews to German extermination camps.
Given his bourgeois, provincial background in the unstable years before the
war, it is not surprising that <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> should have flirted as a young man
with the far right; but the fact that his friends continued to include
people from the far right, not just after the war but into the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, will
reinforce his opponents' conviction that <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> has few political
principles.
Perhaps the bottom line is that the president refuses to accept <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s
historical and political responsibility for the debacle of 1940-44. As far
as he is concerned, <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> was a different regime, and nothing to do with the
republic - in fact, nothing to do with us today. It is as if <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> were an
accident, without organic origins in French political history, for which no
one was responsible.
It is in such terms that the French have repeatedly refused to accept shared
responsibility for their history. Throughout the political instability of
the <DATE>19th century</DATE>, each succeeding regime was permanently under attack in
terms of its essential legitimacy; and the rightwing tradition which
rejected the legitimacy of republican democracy eventually erupted in the
anti-semitism of the <ORGANIZATION>Dreyfus</ORGANIZATION> case in <DATE>1894</DATE>, when the Jewish army officer was
falsely accused of spying for <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
The <PERSON>Petain</PERSON> regime was no doubt exceptional; it was not an accident. Like the
nationalism of the <DATE>late 19th century</DATE>, it was a reaction to humiliating
defeat by the Germans. The French have since tried to exorcise it as
illegitimate; but unless they find some way of accepting collective
responsibility for it, the struggles between rival concepts of political
legitimacy will rage on, threatening instability.
Throughout the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, de Gaulle denounced the illegitimacy of the <ORGANIZATION>Fourth
Republic</ORGANIZATION>, of which <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> was a leading figure; throughout the <DATE>1960s</DATE>,
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> denounced the illegitimacy of de Gaulle and the Fifth Republic;
and throughout the past 14 years the Gaullists have denounced the
illegitimacy of President <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>.
This process is gathering momentum once more, in the run-up to next <DATE>spring</DATE>'s
presidential election. The conservatives ought to win that election easily.
Yet they are split on ancestrally visceral grounds, and could throw it all
away.
If they were to unite behind the candidacy of Prime Minister <PERSON>Edouard
Balladur</PERSON>, he would surely win. But it seems more likely that there will be
up to six rival candidates.
Personal ambition is not the only factor. <PERSON>Jacques Chirac</PERSON>, leader of the
Gaullist party, has been trying and failing to be president since <DATE>1981</DATE>, and
he will not give way now. But the undertow of the Chirac-Balladur struggle
is political legitimacy. Chirac has as few political principles as anyone;
but his claim to legitimacy and the loyalty of his party is that he is an
inheritor of genuine Gaullism, while <PERSON>Balladur</PERSON> is merely a modernising
conservative.
In <DATE>1988</DATE>, <PERSON>Chirac</PERSON> conducted his presidential campaign as farce. He frenziedly
paced up and down, calling on President <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> to come out and fight.
Naturally, <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> waited until Chirac had worn himself out, and then
took him to the cleaners.
Today Chirac is again frenziedly pacing up and down, calling for the
election to begin; once again he is likely to wear himself out - and split
the Gaullist party in two.
This intra-conservative struggle should be interesting and possibly
entertaining. We should remember that its historic roots pass through the
unexorcised trauma of Vichy.
*<ORGANIZATION>Une Jeunesse Francaise</ORGANIZATION>: <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> 1934-1947, by <PERSON>Pierre Pean</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Fayard</ORGANIZATION>, FFr160
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P2731 Book Publishing.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 24
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-9998</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHAAFADHFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920801
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  01 AUG 92 / As They Say in Europe: French replay a war crime
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES MORGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
READING newspapers on holiday is the kind of activity for which there used
not to be a word. Today, we have re-invented 'disjunctive.' At least, I
think that is the word because it implies a lack of coherence between what
one is doing and the circumstances in which it is being done.
For the past two years, many have been alarmed on exotic beaches by reports
of distant crises, first in <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> then in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. This time, we hoped to
avoid these guns of <DATE>August</DATE> by going to the <LOCATION>Dordogne</LOCATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>. But instead of
the echoes of present crises, the papers were full of the tragedy of half a
century before.
Most years at this time, there is mention of events in <DATE>July 1942</DATE> when the
French police rounded up thousands of naturalised French Jews and their
children and sent them to the death camps. Generically, the episode is known
as the Vel' d'Hiv', this being the abbreviation of the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> winter cycling
stadium where the victims were held before transportation.
The 50th anniversary occasioned more heart-searching than ever. On <DATE>July 16</DATE>,
Liberation headlined its front page: '<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> faces up to its crimes.'
Figaro, meanwhile, interviewed the nazi-Hunter, <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, who said
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> could not be blamed. More Jews had survived there than in other
occupied countries.
The debate dominated even the provincial press: Sud-Ouest ran related
stories for several days, headlining the 'lively polemic' the anniversary
had generated, along with President <PERSON>Mitterand</PERSON>'s presence at a commemorative
ceremony in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
One question at issue was the nature of the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government, the
collaborationist regime that was presented by <PERSON>Marshal Petain</PERSON> as the true
successor of the 'Vraie <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.' Vichy also was implicated in the atrocities
of the Vel' d'Hiv'. But were they the result of defeat and 'the criminal
madness of the occupying power,' as the mayor of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jacques Chirac</PERSON>, put
it? Or was it all, in a sense, a French responsibility?
This debate impinged on our holiday in a graphic manner. We were staying a
mile north of the <LOCATION>River Dronne</LOCATION>; the nearest town was Riberac, on the
southern bank. The <PERSON>Dronne</PERSON> was the frontier between occupied and <PERSON>Vichy
France</PERSON>, and the old <ORGANIZATION>Gestapo</ORGANIZATION> headquarters is one of the last buidings before
crossing into Riberac. A little to the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> is the glade containing the
graves of the resistants shot by the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>.
What the newspapers were agonising over was whether that was a national
frontier - whether <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> existed south of the Dronne. It was this debate
that was more intense than on the other anniversaries of the events of <DATE>1942</DATE>.
This is partly because one or two of the most notable figures involved are
still at large, having sometimes been protected by the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>
 -as the <ORGANIZATION>Church</ORGANIZATION>'s own astounded report showed earlier this year.
Opinion in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> has, if anything, hardened against the perpetrators in the
face of judicial complacency: almost three-quarters of the people want them
punished. The other quarter, one assumes, are don't-knows or supporters of
Jean-Marie Le Pen and the <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION>.
The strength of the Front today has itself contributed to the debate over
the French past. The party stands for that constant strand in French
politics which, to say the least, is ambiguous about the Revolution.
It flaunts its sentimental religiosity, built around the cult of <PERSON>Joan of
Arc</PERSON>, and is a successor to the xenophobia of 'Action francaise' and the
racism of the <DATE>19th century</DATE>. Its ambiguous relationship with <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Marshal Petain</PERSON> is, therefore, a living embodiment of the debate.
A little over a year ago, the <ORGANIZATION>Frankfurter Allgemeine Zeitung</ORGANIZATION> ran a cartoon
showing history drawing a line under a page marked 'Post-war period.' That
optimistic assessment has turned out to be inaccurate.
The post-war period was frozen out by the Cold War and - as events all over
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> now show - has, in fact, only just begun.
<PERSON>James Morgan</PERSON> is economics correspondent of the <ORGANIZATION>BBC World Service</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901028-0026 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-28-90 1424EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-WarCrimes     10-28 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-War Crimes,0635</SECOND>
<HEAD>Authorities Accused Of Reluctance To Try War Crimes Cases</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Lawyers and human rights activists say the
prosecution of three alleged Nazi collaborators has been stalled or
dragged out because of a reluctance to expose French complicity in
the <LOCATION>Holocaust</LOCATION>.
   War crimes charges against one of the men, <PERSON>Maurice Papon</PERSON>, have
been pending for seven years. Another, <PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, was
implicated in <DATE>1949</DATE> for his activities as police chief in the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>
regime, but only now faces the possibility of a trial.
   The third alleged war criminal, <PERSON>Paul Touvier</PERSON>, is on trial for
his activities as a pro-Nazi militia chief in <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>.
   Representatives of the <ORGANIZATION>International Federation of Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>
say authorities have failed to relieve the judge of other cases to
make the trial move more swiftly.
   ``We believe it is no accident that these three men have not
been tried,'' said <PERSON>Yves Jouffa</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>French League of
Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>, at a recent news conference.
   ``It is because they are part of what the English call the
establishment, whether it be in politics, business, industry or
high society.... This milieu does not want to see its dirty laundry
washed in public.''
   Bousquet, 81, headed the national police during the Nazi
occupation. State prosecutors last month asked that he be
investigated in connection with the deportation of 194 Jewish
children during the war.
   A <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> criminal court court ruled <DATE>Oct. 19</DATE> that <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> could
only be tried by the High Court of the Liberation, formed in <DATE>1944</DATE>
to prosecute officials of the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> regime. The Liberation court
has been defunct for decades, and the ruling by the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> judges
indicated <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> would escape prosecution.
   However, at the request of state prosecutors, an appeals court
plans to make a final ruling on the jurisdiction issue <DATE>Nov. 19</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, a lawyer and prominent Nazi hunter, said senior
government officials, including President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON>,
appear reluctant to pursue the case.
   ``I think <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> doesn't want this trial to open,''
<PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said. ``I can only hypothesize that there is a certain
indulgence toward <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>.''
   Should the case go to trial, <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> would be the highest
ranking French official in the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government to be tried for
crimes against humanity.
   Bousquet was condemned in <DATE>1949</DATE> for his activities under Nazi
occupation, but the decision was reversed for ``acts accomplished
in favor of the Resistance'' - namely, his decision to free some
jailed resistance fighters.
   Jouffa, who spent part of World War II in a French internment
camp, said none of the high-ranking French political figures with
direct roles in deporting and arresting 100,000 Jews during the war
have been brought to justice.
   He said the recent trial of the <ORGANIZATION>Gestapo</ORGANIZATION> chief in <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Klaus
Barbie</PERSON>, ``was the trial of <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION>, not collaborationist
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   The human rights federation said it had organized an inquiry
commission to determine why the cases were taking so long. Their
report is being submitted to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> and the Council of
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
   ``We hope that the very fact that we have carried out this
mission will be enough to create movement in high places and allow
these proceedings to be accelerated,'' <PERSON>Jouffa</PERSON> said.
   Papon, a former budget minister, has been accused of
responsibility for the arrests and deportations of 1,700 Jews while
an administrator in <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> during the war. Now 81, he served in
many high-profile positions after the war, including a stint as
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> police chief.
   Touvier, 75, worked with <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>. He went into hiding in
<DATE>1973</DATE>, and was arrested in <DATE>May 1989</DATE> at a priory in Nice run by
followers of Archbishop <PERSON>Marcel Lefevbre</PERSON>, the fundamentalist Roman
Catholic leader.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901119-0177 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-19-90 2135EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-WarCrimes     11-19 0348</FIRST>
<SECOND>M-France-War Crimes,0393</SECOND>
<HEAD>Court Says Vichy Official Can be Tried for War Crimes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TERRIL JONES</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A court ruled <DATE>Monday</DATE> that a Frenchman accused of
sending 194 Jewish children to their deaths in <LOCATION>Nazi</LOCATION> camps can be
tried for war crimes.
   <PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, 81, who is accused of crimes against humanity,
was national police chief under the collaborating <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government
in World War II.
   Appeals Court <PERSON>Judge Albert Moatty</PERSON> decided <DATE>Monday</DATE> that <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>
can be tried by an ordinary court.
   State prosecutors in <DATE>September</DATE> asked that <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> be
investigated in connection with the childrens' deportation.
   A lower court held in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> last month that <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> could be
tried only by the High Court of the Liberation, formed in <DATE>1944</DATE> to
prosecute officials of the government under Nazi occupation. That
court has been defunct for decades.
   Moatty's ruling allowed state prosecutors to resume their
investigation of evidence uncovered by Nazi-hunters.
   The <ORGANIZATION>International League Against Racism</ORGANIZATION> and Anti-Semitism hailed
the decision. ``<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> is a great country, capable of looking into
the dark times of its past,'' the group said in a statement.
   The lower court's ruling had infuriated human rights activists,
who feared <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> would escape prosecution.
   Rights leaders say no high-ranking French officials directly
involved in deporting and arresting 100,000 Jews during the war
have been brought to trial.
   <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, a lawyer and prominent Nazi-hunter, has said
senior government officials, including President <PERSON>Francois
Mitterrand</PERSON>, appear reluctant to pursue the case.
   Bousquet was condemned in <DATE>1949</DATE> for alleged collaboration with
the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>, but was freed for ``acts accomplished in favor of the
Resistance.'' He freed some jailed Resistance fighters when he was
ousted from his post.
   A federation of human rights groups organized an inquiry
commission to determine why cases against <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> and two other
suspected war criminals, <PERSON>Paul Touvier</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maurice Papon</PERSON>, have taken
so long.
   Touvier, 75, is being prosecuted for his activities as a
pro-Nazi militia chief in <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>. He was captured last year after
spending years hiding out with the help of right-wing Roman
Catholic monks.
   Charges against <PERSON>Papon</PERSON>, a former budget minister, have been
pending for seven years. He has been accused of being responsible
for the arrests and deportations of 1,700 Jews while a wartime
administrator in <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-3527</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EINDHAAPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940914
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 SEP 94 / Mitterrand's 'clarification' adds to confusion: After 14
years in power, the man and his image are crumbling fast
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BUCHAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Think of all those between the ages of 15 and 20. Ever since they became
conscious of the political life of their country, all they have ever seen is
me.
Two months since saying this, and in the 14th year of his presidency,
President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> and his image seem to be crumbling fast.
On <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the French president underwent 90 minutes of questioning on
television, ostensibly to clarify comments he had made about his health and
his political past.
Yet, still, he raised more questions than he answered. This was probably
inevitable in the case of his health, given that the precise pace of <PERSON>Mr
Mitterrand</PERSON>'s prostate cancer is unknown. But what he has done is plunge
French politicians into an early race to take his place in the <LOCATION>Elysee</LOCATION> next
<DATE>May</DATE> - or earlier.
The revelations could prove a setback for his own Socialist party - and
perhaps give a boost to the far right.
Immediate reactions to <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>'s TV interview were mixed. Some praised
the president's courage in talking about his cancer, and his candour in
tracing his move from the political right to the left; from his pre-war
conservative upbringing eventually to socialism.
Others said they were moved, but used the word 'pathetic'.
<PERSON>Mr Rene Monory</PERSON>, the centrist president of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> who would take over as
interim head of state if the president died in office or resigned, said: 'I
was a little sorry to see the president explain himself in such a way . . .
it does not usually end this way'.
Others complained that <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON> was over-stretching their credulity in
asserting that, when he went to work for the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> collaborationist
government in <DATE>1942</DATE>, he knew nothing of the anti-semitic laws it had passed
in <DATE>1940</DATE>; and that only in <DATE>1986</DATE> did he have cause to break off contact with
<PERSON>Mr Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, the ex-Vichy police chief. But even yesterday <PERSON>Mr
Mitterrand</PERSON> had a Jewish defender in <PERSON>Mr George Kiejman</PERSON>, his former justice
minister, who came to his aid against sharp criticism from <PERSON>Mr Serge
Klarsfeld</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s best-known Nazi hunter.
But much of the French right believes the left has walked into its own trap
in identifying itself so strongly with the resistance. Certainly, some
Socialists - though not those at the very top - were yesterday expressing
their 'disgust and bitterness' at <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>, and calling for 'a break
with Mitterrandism'. This is defined as a form of persistent 'ambiguity' in
personal and political relations.
The fact that this ambiguity seems to have persisted right into the
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> presidency appears most to upset the French Communist party,
which was only allowed by <ORGANIZATION>Stalin</ORGANIZATION> to enter the anti-German resistance after
<DATE>1941</DATE>.
In a new book on the president entitled 'The Right Hand of God', three
French journalists claim <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON> has consistently sought to divide the
right by promoting and wooing <PERSON>Mr Jean-Marie</PERSON> Le Pen's <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION>.
In <DATE>1982</DATE>, they claim, President <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> arranged for the <ORGANIZATION>NF</ORGANIZATION> to get
increased coverage on state television; and between the two rounds of the
<DATE>1988</DATE> election, asked <PERSON>Mr Le Pen</PERSON> to swing his vote behind him rather than the
gaullist candidate, <PERSON>Mr Jacques Chirac</PERSON>. These claims are denied by close
Mitterrand associates. But it is true that the introduction of proportional
representation in the <DATE>1986</DATE> parliamentary elections, designed primarily to
minimise Socialist losses, had the side effect of helping the <ORGANIZATION>NF</ORGANIZATION>.
Yesterday a senior <ORGANIZATION>NF</ORGANIZATION> party official suggested that 'if <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON>
was elected despite his real flirt with <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>, then Jean-Marie Le Pen can be
elected despite his false image as a Vichyist'. This, too, stretches belief.
But it is likely that <PERSON>Mr Le Pen</PERSON>, who is due next <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to become the first
declared candidate for the <DATE>1995</DATE> presidential race, will try to turn <PERSON>Mr
Mitterrand</PERSON>'s revelations to his own benefit.
Meanwhile, Prime Minister <PERSON>Edouard Balladur</PERSON> will try to keep his government
ticking over until early <DATE>1995</DATE> when he intends to announce his own
presidential candidacy, against, among others, that of <PERSON>Mr Chirac</PERSON>.
But the weekly cabinet meetings on <DATE>Wednesdays</DATE>, over which <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>
presides, will become even more curious affairs. The president will be
watching for divisions in the government which he might divulge publicly, as
he did last week to Le Figaro newspaper. Among his ministers, the rival
Balladur and Chirac clans will be on the lookout for any sign of increasing
presidential infirmity to send them to the hustings.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9111 Executive Offices.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>PEOP  People.
</TP>
<XX>
People:-
</XX>
<PE>Mitterrand, F French President.
</PE>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 2
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901119-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-19-90 1104EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-France-WarCrimes     11-19 0382</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-France-War Crimes,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ruling Paves Way For Action in War Crimes Case</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PATRICK McDOWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An appeals court today gave ordinary criminal
courts jurisdiction to try a former French official accused of
sending 194 Jewish children to their deaths in concentration camps
during World War II.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Paris Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> overturned a lower court ruling last
month <PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON> could only be tried by the High Court of the
Liberation, formed in <DATE>1944</DATE> to prosecute officials of the
collaborationist <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government. The court has been defunct for
decades.
   Court of Appeals President <PERSON>Albert Moatty</PERSON> ruled today that the
length of time required to reconstitute the court could preclude
justice in the case of <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>, who is 81.
   With <ORGANIZATION>Moatty</ORGANIZATION>'s ruling, state prosecutors can resume their
investigation of evidence on <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON>'s case that was provided by
Nazi hunters.
   Bousquet headed the national police during the Nazi occupation
of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. State prosecutors in <DATE>September</DATE> asked that he be
investigated in connection with the deportation of 194 Jewish
children during the war.
   Should the case go to trial, <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> would be the
highest-ranking official of the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government to be tried for
crimes against humanity.
   But <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, a lawyer and prominent Nazi hunter, has
said senior government officials, including President <PERSON>Francois
Mitterrand</PERSON>, appear reluctant to pursue the case.
   Bousquet was condemned in <DATE>1949</DATE> for his wartime activities, but
the decision was reversed due to ``acts accomplished in favor of
the Resistance'' - namely his decision to free some jailed
Resistance fighters at the time he was ousted from his post.
   Human rights leaders say none of the high-ranking French
political figures with direct roles in deporting and arresting
100,000 Jews during the war has been brought to justice.
   <PERSON>Yves Jouffa</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>French League of Human Rights</ORGANIZATION>, has
said the recent trial of the <ORGANIZATION>Gestapo</ORGANIZATION> chief of <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Klaus Barbie</PERSON>,
``was the trial of <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION>, not collaborationist <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.''
   A federation of human rights groups has organized a commisison
of inquiry to determine why action against <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> and two other
suspected war criminals, <PERSON>Paul Touvier</PERSON> and <PERSON>Maurice Papon</PERSON>, has taken
so long.
   Touvier, 75, is being prosecuted for his activities as a
pro-Nazi militia chief who worked with <ORGANIZATION>Barbie</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Lyon</LOCATION>. He was
captured last year after spending years in hiding under the shelter
of right-wing Roman Catholic monks.
   Charges against <PERSON>Papon</PERSON>, a former budget minister, have been
pending for seven years. He has been accused of responsibility for
the arrests and deportations of 1,700 Jews while an administrator
in <LOCATION>Bordeaux</LOCATION> during the war.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900616-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-16-90 1115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-France-DeGaulle Bjt   06-16 0693</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-De Gaulle, Bjt,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>French Commemorate Charles De Gaulle's Call To Arms Against Nazis</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The French are celebrating with unprecedented
fanfare the 50th anniversary of <PERSON>Charles De Gaulle</PERSON>'s historic appeal
for armed resistance against Nazi tyranny.
   Yet few people actually heard the radio broadcast, and many
French people _ though they might deny it now _ were content with
the leaders who had just surrendered to Hitler.
   Known as the ``appel'' of <DATE>June 18</DATE>, De Gaulle's fervent,
four-minute speech was addressed to soldiers and civilians in
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   In a deep, gravelly voice edged with tension, he asked: ``Must
we abandon all hope? Is our defeat final? No! ... <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> is not
alone! ... The flame of French resistance must not and shall not
die!''
   But the army was in disarray, and most civilians were fleeing
their homes. The chaos and panic were such that 90,000 families
reported having lost children during the mass exodus.
   Many of those who did manage to tune in the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> on their wartime
wireless radios sought assurances from 84-year-old <PERSON>Philippe Petain</PERSON>,
a bemedalled World War I field marshal who had urged Premier <PERSON>Paul
Reynaud</PERSON> to sign the armistice the previous day.
   <PERSON>Regis Debray</PERSON>, a former adviser to President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON>,
has suggested in a recent book that in <DATE>June 1940</DATE>, nine out of 10
French supported <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>. In fact, by the end of the <DATE>summer</DATE>, only
7,000 people had reached <LOCATION>De Gaulle</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> headquarters.
   The vast majority of the French saw De Gaulle as a brash rebel
who fled his native soil hours after <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> capitulated _ to join
forces with an old enemy, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   By contrast, the grandfatherly, taciturn <PERSON>Petain</PERSON>, known as ``the
hero of <LOCATION>Verdun</LOCATION>,'' urged an end to the conflict, which he believed
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> could never win.
   Petain's popularity began to fade only after Vichy-led police
zealously rounded up Jews for deportation to concentration camps _
123,000 died _ and began sending French workers to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>.
   Fifty years later, the French are celebrating their national
hero unreservedly _ with virtually no reminders of the
collaborationist regime or tolerance of Nazism that De Gaulle
vigorously condemned.
   Instead, politicians try to capitalize on his legacy, each vying
to appear as his heir.
   Sound and light extravaganzas will re-enact the dramatic moments
of the war, including the Nazi invasion, the <DATE>June 18</DATE> appeal and the
liberation.
   <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> has been plastered with 6,000 posters recalling the
highlights of De Gaulle's career. Art exhibitions, documentaries
and television specials _ even a computer game _ recapture the
grandeur and charisma of ``le General.''
   A giant replica of the wireless _ the kind that ordinary
citizens would later risk their lives listening to _ will be
erected at the <ORGANIZATION>Place de la Concorde</ORGANIZATION> and will broadcast De Gaulle's
wartime speeches from dawn to dusk on <DATE>June 18</DATE>.
   Retired Gen. <PERSON>Andre Delpech</PERSON>, a resistance fighter who was
tortured and sent to <LOCATION>Dachau</LOCATION> in <DATE>1944</DATE>, remembers the excitement of
the <DATE>June 18</DATE> appeal. He was then 15.
   ``Somehow, news had reached our remote hamlet that some general,
whose name we didn't know, was going to make an important speech
from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. We could barely make out his voice... Afterwards, the
adults stayed up long into the night discussing the few sentences
they managed to decipher.''
   Meanwhile, radio announcers reread the appeal during the evening
and into the wee hours of the <TIME>morning</TIME>. The following day De Gaulle
again took the microphone to express his firm belief that he
``spoke in the name of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.''
   ``Ici Londres'' _ ``This is <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'' _ became a codeword for the
resistance, opening nightly broadcasts that provided news from the
free world and transmitted coded messages to underground networks
in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   Political journalist <PERSON>Robert Quiriconi</PERSON> was a high school student
in <LOCATION>Algeria</LOCATION> when De Gaulle founded the Free French movement and
hoisted the French tricolor over his <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> home.
   ``At flag-raising ceremonies, we were supposed to sing a song
praising <PERSON>Petain</PERSON> instead of the `Marseillaise,''' he said. ``I had
heard about De Gaulle from my classmates, and from then on, we were
Gaullists, and refused to sing.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900618-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-18-90 2131EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-France-DeGaulle 1stLd-Writethru a0600 06-18 0506</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-De Gaulle, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0600,0516</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hundreds Pay Tribute to Leader on Anniversary of Anti-Nazi Appeal</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with show on the Seine, CORRECT
spelling of first name of Philippe De Gaulle, minor editing. No
pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR4</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of former resistance fighters joined
political and church leaders <DATE>Monday</DATE> at a tribute to <PERSON>Charles De
Gaulle</PERSON> on the 50th anniversary of his historic radio appeal for
armed struggle against the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Notre Dame Cathedral</ORGANIZATION> was filled with an audience that included
Premier <PERSON>Michel Rocard</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Jacques Chirac</PERSON> and British
Ambassador Sir <PERSON>Ewen Fergusson</PERSON>. De Gaulle's son, <LOCATION>Philippe</LOCATION>, also was
there.
   Roman Catholic Cardinal <PERSON>Jean-Marie Lustiger</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> praised De
Gaulle's crucial role in the struggle ``for the dignity of all men
aganst inhuman and totalitarian ambition.''
   Later, many dignitaries and resistance veterans looked on as
President <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> unveiled a plaque at the Arc de
Triomphe inscribed with the text of <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>'s appeal. Church
bells throughout <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> chimed to mark the occasion.
   Thousands of tourists and Parisians flocked <DATE>Monday</DATE> to the <ORGANIZATION>Place
de la Concorde</ORGANIZATION>, where a 115-foot-high replica of a <DATE>1940s</DATE> radio
re-broadcast the <DATE>June 18</DATE> call from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and other well-known De
Gaulle speeches.
   Few of <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>'s countrymen actually heard his dramatic
appeal, in a voice edged with tension: ``Has the last word been
said? Must we abandon all hope? Is our defeat final? No! ... <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
is not alone ... the flame of the resistance must not and shall not
die.''
   Many of those who did manage to tune in the <ORGANIZATION>BBC</ORGANIZATION> to hear it knew
little about the general claiming to represent <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. Instead,
they preferred the grandfatherly reassurances of <PERSON>Philippe Petain</PERSON>, a
World War I field marshal, who urged surrender to the Germans.
Petain became the head of the collaborationist <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> regime.
   De Gaulle's fervent, four-minute speech helped change the course
of French history.
   The resistance movement played a critical role in the Allied
victory. After the war, De Gaulle founded a political party and
served as president from <DATE>1959</DATE> to <DATE>1969</DATE>. He died a year later.
   Daylong celebrations of <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>'s broadcast culminated <DATE>Monday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME> with a sound and light extravaganza on the <LOCATION>Seine River</LOCATION>.
   More than 100,000 spectators crowded onto river banks and
bridges to watch as scores of barges floated down the Seine
carrying torches, flags and hundreds of performers in period
costume reenacting the German invasion of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>'s
flight to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, D-Day and the liberation.
   The show included simulations of the bombings raids that
terrified civilians when <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> fell. At that time, three-fifths of
the population took to the roads in cars, wagons, bicycles and even
wheelbarrows to escape the German onslaught.
   The show, which also celebrates the centenary of <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle</ORGANIZATION>'s
birth, cost <MONEY>$5.7 million</MONEY>, raised from private sources by <ORGANIZATION>De Gaulle
Centenary Association</ORGANIZATION>.
   Early <DATE>Monday</DATE>, vandals demaged and defaced De Gaulle memorials in
three communities on the northern outskirts of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, police said.
No arrests were reported.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890803-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-03-89 1338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-50YearsOn-Legacy Adv13   08-03 1215</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-50 Years On-Legacy, Adv 13,1246</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv13</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Aug. 13, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Legacy of World War II Shapes Thinking to This Day</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphics, LaserPhotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KEVIN COSTELLOE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Savagely attacking <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> a
half-century ago, <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON>'s armies sparked a conflagration
that killed more than 50 million people and spread worldwide in
history's costliest war.
   World War II drew in every major power, leaving behind a bitter
legacy from fighting and Holocaust that shape the thinking of
nations to this day.
   The reverberations range from the tensions between the
capitalist West and communist East to lingering uneasiness over the
possibility of ever reunifying the two Germanys.
   And there are more individual problems, such as in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, with
the diplomatic difficulties that arose over the attendance of
foreign dignitaries at the funeral of Emperor <PERSON>Hirohito</PERSON> last
<DATE>February</DATE>, and in <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, where President <PERSON>Kurt Waldheim</PERSON>'s war
record as a German officer is under divisive scrutiny.
   The Holocaust _ the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>' extermination of an estimated 6
million Jews _ shocked the world like no other atrocity known to
mankind and still casts the longest shadow of the war.
   Last <DATE>November</DATE>, <PERSON>Philipp Jenninger</PERSON> had to resign as speaker of the
West German Parliament just 48 hours after making a clumsily worded
speech that sought to explain the German people's anti-Semitism and
fascination with <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>.
   However good his intentions, Jenninger offended many Germans,
Jewish and non-Jewish.
   The war is remembered, too, in small, day-to-day details, like
the seats reserved for war invalids on French trains, or the
Christmas tree in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Trafalgar Square</LOCATION>, an annual gift from a
grateful Norwegian people for the British war effort.
   It was an arena for giants, good and bad: Hitler, <ORGANIZATION>Winston
Churchill</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Josef Stalin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Franklin Roosevelt</PERSON>. And it produced
postwar leaders such as <PERSON>Charles de Gaulle</PERSON>, architect of modern
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Marshal Josip Broz Tito</PERSON>, who ruled <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION> until his
death in <DATE>1980</DATE> and helped found the movement of non-aligned nations.
   Every nation shapes its own lessons from the war, often with
distortions or exaggerations.
   For the French, there is the painful knowledge that one's
parents or grandparents may have collaborated with their Nazi
conquerors.
   For <LOCATION>Eastern Europe</LOCATION>, decades of official hero-worship of the
Soviet forces are giving way to greater objectivity, in large part
as a result of Soviet President <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON>'s policy of
openness.
   ``In the vision of the war we used to get, only the Russians
were brave in fighting the Germans,'' said <PERSON>Anna Radziwill</PERSON>, who has
taught high school history for 30 years and was elected to <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>'s
newly created <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``The vision of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> was that they were just sending us
canned food,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Radziwill</PERSON>, a member of one of <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>'s old
noble families.
   German sailors aboard the old battleship Schleswig-Holstein
fired the first shots of World War II, shelling a small Polish
garrison at <LOCATION>Westerplatte</LOCATION> near the <ORGANIZATION>Free City of Danzig</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>4:45 a.m.</TIME>
on <DATE>Sept. 1, 1939</DATE>. The German army poured across the Polish frontier
while <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s warplanes pounded the country from overhead.
   Two days later <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> declared war on <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. But
not until <DATE>1941</DATE> did the fighting become a true world war, with the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> fleet at <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION>. In all, more than 50 nations joined the
fighting.
   Still uneasy neighbors 40 years after their creation, the two
Germanys present vastly different accounts of World War II and its
causes.
   In communist <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, a high school textbook from <DATE>1986</DATE>
states: ``World War II was unleashed by German imperialists and
militarists,'' spurred by a desire for profits and conquests.
   But just over the border, teen-agers in <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s Hesse
state are taught that Nazism was an all-embracing affair, ``a
terrible aberration to which an entire people was able to be driven
by ideological blindness, ignorance and cowardice.''
   Revised history books for Soviet high school students still
insist <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s forces defeated <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> virtually single-handed, even
though the <ORGANIZATION>Kremlin</ORGANIZATION> did not declare war on <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> until three days
after a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> bomber dropped an atomic bomb on <LOCATION>Hiroshima</LOCATION>.
   The textbook for the 11th grade says that ``the use of the
atomic weapon was not militarily necessary.''
   ``By this crime, unprecedented in the history of mankind,
imperialist circles in the <LOCATION>U.S.A.</LOCATION> wanted to demonstrate its
then-strategic superiority before the whole world,'' the textbook
says.
   But Soviet students do learn that their country's agreement to
divide up <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> with the Germans was unjust.
   In <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION>, a newly emboldened Communist government is moving
closer to blaming the Soviets for the massacre of more than 4,000
Polish officers in <LOCATION>Katyn</LOCATION>. To reverse the official line _ that the
<PERSON>Nazis</PERSON> did it _ would constitute a monumental act of historical
revisionism in East European minds.
   <PERSON>Momo Kapor</PERSON>, a best-selling Yugoslav author and satirist, summed
up the distortions of the past this way: ``During the past 40 years
or so, grandpas and grandmas, uncles and old aunts have been
correcting, secretly, official lessons from textbooks.
   ``From our earliest days, to finish school somehow, we had to
pretend that we believed in official stories, while in fact we
believed in things that were forbidden,'' <PERSON>Kapor</PERSON> said in a recent
column in the <LOCATION>Belgrade</LOCATION> daily newspaper Politika.
   While <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> remains unabashedly proud of its wartime role,
other Western European nations, such as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, have had
to face up to the darker side of their war record.
   <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> was easily defeated in <DATE>1940</DATE> and was then divided into an
occupied zone and a French puppet regime headquartered in the town
of <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>. The Germans later occupied the whole country.
   Historian <PERSON>Henri Rousso</PERSON> said in an interview that many fellow
Frenchmen have long thought their country was made up mostly of
brave resistance fighters who ultimately helped the Allied victory.
He said textbooks began to tell a different story in the early
<DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   French Nazi hunter <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON> said many French people do
not know that the country ``actively collaborated with the Germans.
And thanks to de Gaulle's diplomatic genius, many French people
think that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> really won the war.''
   ``The period was like a civil war, with two opposite camps: de
Gaulle and the resistance on one side, and the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>
collaborationist regime on the other,'' <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said in an
interview.
   <PERSON>Alessia Jannece</PERSON>, a high school student in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, said: ``They
really don't teach us much about fascism. I learn mostly from TV or
what I remember from middle school.''
   The lessons are important for a country haunted by its past
under fascist dictator <PERSON>Benito Mussolini</PERSON>. Professor <ORGANIZATION>Renzo De
Felice</ORGANIZATION>'s highly respected <DATE>1982</DATE> biography of <PERSON>Mussolini</PERSON> contends
there was general consensus for fascism in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
   Last year's 50th anniversary of <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>'s annexation by <LOCATION>Nazi
Germany</LOCATION> and a select commission's finding that <PERSON>Waldheim</PERSON> was in
``close proximity'' to <ORGANIZATION>Nazi</ORGANIZATION> war crimes also prompted soul-searching.
   ``Although the <ORGANIZATION>Second World War</ORGANIZATION> is now far distant, its shadows
are long, its echoes loud,'' British historian <PERSON>Martin Gilbert</PERSON> says
in a new history of the war. ``How else could it be with an event,
lasting for nearly six years, in which courage and cruelty, hope
and horror, violence and virtue, massacre and survival, were so
closely intertwined?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Aug. 13</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-478</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BELAGACZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910511
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 MAY 91 / Books: Murky Vichy water - Britain's murderous involvement
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   BY ZARA STEINER
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
ASSASSINATION IN <LOCATION>ALGIERS</LOCATION> by <PERSON>Anthony Verrier Macmillan</PERSON> Pounds 20, 302 pages
ON CHRISTMAS Eve, <DATE>1942</DATE>, 21-year-old <PERSON>Fernand Bonnier</PERSON> fired two shots into the
stomach of <PERSON>Jean-Francois Darlan</PERSON>, the Vichy leader in <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION>. Two hours
later Admiral <PERSON>Darlan</PERSON> died. The assassin, who had expected to escape, was
shot after a court martial in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>. Behind this assassination was a
complex and tangled story which <PERSON>Anthony Verrier</PERSON> has tried to unravel using
British and American secret service papers and interviews with informed
British and French respondents to compensate for the lack of officially
available documents.
The <PERSON>Darlan</PERSON> saga was part of a series of conflicts not easy to explore in a
short book. The most important was the growing divergence between the
pro-Vichy and savagely anti-Gaullist <PERSON>Roosevelt</PERSON>, who believed Darlan could
deliver <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> into Allied hands, and <ORGANIZATION>Winston Churchill</ORGANIZATION>, favourably
disposed towards de Gaulle despite moments of irritation bordering on fury
and with a far more realistic view of the Vichy gamble. Having persuaded the
Americans to invade <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Churchill</ORGANIZATION> found it necessary to propitiate
Roosevelt by acquiescing in the president's pro-Vichy line without
abandoning his preferred alternative.
The divisions between Frenchmen were even more complicated. The situation in
<LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> differed markedly from that in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. The main contenders for
control in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Darlan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Giraud</PERSON> and de Gaulle, each had wider political
ambitions which made control of <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> pertinent to the French
situation. In <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, the London-backed Resistance looked to de Gaulle, and
by <DATE>1942</DATE> the British were pledged to the Gaullists though many had strong
doubts about their leader.
In the overwhelmingly pro-Vichy <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION>, the Gaullist element
represented a tiny minority. Time and circumstance determined local
loyalties; supporters hedged their bets and changed sides. Roosevelt's
political emissary, <PERSON>Robert Murphy</PERSON>, was lost in this quagmire of shifting
political alliance. He ultimately opted for Darlan who, as <ORGANIZATION>Verrier</ORGANIZATION> confirms,
ran circles around the American. The British had no equivalent political
figure in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION> until <PERSON>Harold Macmillan</PERSON> in <DATE>1943</DATE>, but they had two SOE
missions in place, '<PERSON>Brandon</PERSON>' and '<PERSON>Massingham</PERSON>', building up an anti-Vichy
front.
The real Anglo-American divide came with the bargain struck in <DATE>November,
1942</DATE> between Darlan and General <PERSON>Mark Clark</PERSON> confirming the former's authority
over <LOCATION>North Africa</LOCATION> in return for a French ceasefire. Eisenhower, in command
of 'Torch', was to remain loyal to this bargain despite growing doubts about
<PERSON>Darlan</PERSON>'s loyalty. On the British side, after months of equivocation in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, it was agreed that <PERSON>Darlan</PERSON> was an impossible choice. The British were
committed to de Gaulle and the Free French.
Diplomatic pressure from the British and Gaullists failed to move the
Americans. In this unequal contest, the British felt forced to turn to
clandestine operations. It is at this point that <PERSON>Verrier</PERSON>'s account is of
gripping interest and where his reconstruction of events, if accurate, makes
for fascinating reading. All the tangled threads are brought together. If,
as the author argues, there was no concerted plan to eliminate <PERSON>Darlan</PERSON>, the
measures taken by <ORGANIZATION>British Intelligence</ORGANIZATION> described in this chapter made his
assassination inevitable.
<PERSON>Desmond Morton</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Churchill</ORGANIZATION>'s chief intelligence adviser, was involved, and
<PERSON>Colonel Keswick</PERSON>, second in command of '<PERSON>Massingham</PERSON>', began new operations in
the murky world of <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION>. There was a key meeting in <LOCATION>Gibraltar</LOCATION>, on
<DATE>December 4</DATE>, with <PERSON>Morton</PERSON> present, for those to be involved in <LOCATION>Darlan</LOCATION>'s
removal. <PERSON>Henri d'Astier</PERSON>, an equivocal figure serving on <ORGANIZATION>Darlan</ORGANIZATION>'s staff, was
recruited to operate covertly with the British and given funds by <ORGANIZATION>OSS</ORGANIZATION>; his
brothers, <PERSON>Jean Bernard</PERSON> and General <PERSON>Francoise d'Astier</PERSON>, were with de Gaulle;
the latter was sent to <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION> for discussions with an unwelcoming
<PERSON>Eisenhower</PERSON> but also to warn <PERSON>Henri</PERSON> that the Gaullists should lie low,
The final role was played by <PERSON>Bonnier</PERSON>, one of a small group of young
anti-Darlan Frenchmen, who had been given uniforms, rations and pay by
'<PERSON>Brandon</PERSON>'. On <DATE>November 18</DATE>, <PERSON>Bonnier</PERSON> to his horror drew the short straw.
Verrier cannot say what or who finally pushed <PERSON>Bonnier</PERSON> over the edge. Giraud,
though absent from <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION> at the time, took power, wasting little sympathy
on Darlan but demanding that Bonnier be tried. At his court martial the
young man claimed to have acted alone. It was decided by d'Astier that he
was not to be rescued. The Darlanites had a victim; the anti-Vichyites a
youthful martyr. Verrier provides vivid descriptions of the clean-up
operations in <LOCATION>Algiers</LOCATION> and the subsequent contest between <PERSON>Giraud</PERSON> and de
Gaulle.
There is much new material here and the discriminating reader will be richly
rewarded. The difficulty is that this book falls between two stools. Despite
<PERSON>Verrier</PERSON>'s efforts and simplification, the general reader will find this a
tangled trail to follow. The better informed will bridle at some of the
author's unqualified generalisations and at the lack of any but the most
perfunctory scholarly apparatus.
The author has shown in previous studies that he has special access to
intelligence sources. Many of his most startling disclosures have been
confirmed by papers that have come into the public domain. In this account,
however, references to open sources are unacceptably sparse, irregular, and
incomplete. The notes are tantalisingly brief. No one is helped by the fact
that this book is badly written. One cannot help but feel that <PERSON>Verrier</PERSON> had a
different book in mind. The result is everyone's loss.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XXIV
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-2679</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIRAQAECFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940917
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 SEP 94 / As They Say in Europe: A French youth, free of innocence
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES MORGAN
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Suppose <PERSON>Edward Heath</PERSON>, the British prime minister from <DATE>1970</DATE> to <DATE>1974</DATE>, had been
mixed up with <PERSON>Oswald Moseley</PERSON>'s fascist movement in the <DATE>1930s</DATE> and had helped
draw up a list of undesirables to help an eventual occupying power.
Even in secretive <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> it might have emerged that he was not, perhaps, a
wholly suitable potential leader. At the very least the cabinet secretary
would have been tipped off by the head of MI5: 'Ted hasn't got 20 shillings
for the pound,' or some such argot would have scuppered him.
In <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, things are different. A bit of fascist collusion for a man of
<PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON>'s generation was not exceptional. Then a bit of light
work on the other side and one could emerge from the cocoon of collaboration
as a butterfly of the resistance. But <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>, at a time of his own
choosing, has co-operated in revealing the truth about his past. Admittedly
the French president did wait until the last days of his presidency and
maybe his life, to come clean, but come clean he did in backing the now
well-known book by <PERSON>Pierre Pean</PERSON>, Une jeunesse francaise.
That, and the serious worries about his health, led to a long television
interview on <DATE>Monday</DATE>. There, <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> argued that he had not done much that
was wrong. He had been a bit late in changing sides. He had befriended the
man who had been the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>' manager of the Holocaust in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rene
Bousquet</PERSON>. But <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> had been publicly cleared, even though his associates
had left nobody in any doubt as to his central role in the matter.
The newspapers reacted diversely. Liberation said that anyone looking for a
mea culpa when it came to <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> might well have spared themselves the
trouble. One provincial paper thought the president could end his term with
a clear conscience.
There was alarm about the role of the press in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, but even that took
different forms. Le <PERSON>Figaro</PERSON> said the press had turned on <LOCATION>Mitterrand</LOCATION> as it had
turned on other presidents at the end of their reign. But, as is usual with
<PERSON>Le Figaro</PERSON>, the reality is different. Most facts about <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>, it seems,
were, by and large, in or near the public domain. It would not have taken
much to show he was on the fringes of the nastier xenophobic groups in the
<DATE>1930s</DATE> and that he dined with <PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. After all, he put a
wreath on the tomb of the Vichy leader, <PERSON>Marshall Petain</PERSON>, annually until
public opinion forced a change a few years ago.
So the question is, why was it that the truth did not come out until
<PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> licensed it? Only Le <PERSON>Monde</PERSON> has taken this question to heart. Its
in-house ombudsman, <PERSON>Andre Laurens</PERSON>, wrote a 5,000 word piece headed:
'<PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> under the eye of Le Monde.' He explained how the paper
had played a vital role in exposing the many scandals of his reign and got
into trouble as a result: 'The irony is that the paper is reproached on the
one hand for not having told what it did not and could not know, and on the
other for not having believed the statements of public figures.'
Those who expose unpleasant secrets in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> do get into trouble. But the
problem of <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> runs deeper than that. The French cannot resolve it.
They like to think <PERSON>Charles de Gaulle</PERSON> was the presidential incarnation of
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, but of course the truth is that <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> is the mirror of the
nation. He is the two <PERSON>Frances</PERSON>, the nation of the enlightenment, the
revolution and liberty. And of xenophobia, anti-republicanism and
intolerance.
Mitterrand symbolises the contradictory aspects of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s recent past  -
the ideological opportunism and the unique nature of French collaboration
with the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>, the myths of the resistance, the creation of a successful
modern state and the continuity of pointless minorities on the far left and
far right.
The <ORGANIZATION>National Front</ORGANIZATION> leapt to his defence. Its weekly, <ORGANIZATION>National-Hebdo</ORGANIZATION>, ran the
headline, 'Nothing to get excited about' and reported that anybody who had
read the far-right press would have been familiar with all <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON>'s
transactions with the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> regime and he had done nothing wrong anyway.
The curious fact is that <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s great figures, unlike <LOCATION>Mitterrand</LOCATION>, always
emerge from some glorious national salon des refuses. They are outsiders -
<PERSON>Henri IV</PERSON> and <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON>, or rejects and rebels - <ORGANIZATION>Voltaire</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Lavoisier</PERSON>, <PERSON>Victor
Hugo</PERSON> and de Gaulle.
In <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, by contrast, all national heroes - <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION> I, <ORGANIZATION>Shakespeare</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Adam Smith</PERSON> - were heroes to their contemporaries. Sometimes that is a fluke
of history. No British leader could have faced the choices that confronted
Mitterrand: none could have supplied appropriately damaging material for a
sensational political biography called 'A Youth of an Englishman'. So no
Englishman can master the arcane intellectual skills that come so easily to
the French. He has no need of them.
<PERSON>James Morgan</PERSON> is economics correspondent of the <ORGANIZATION>BBC World Service</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>FRZ  France, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page VIII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900428-0149 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-28-90 0103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Holocaust     04-28 0399</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Holocaust,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Magazine Recounts France's Deportation of 3,500 Jewish Children</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nazi hunter <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> hailed a
magazine report as the first French media account of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s role
in the roundup and deportation of 3,500 Jewish children who later
died at <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION>.
   ``The episode in well-known to historians,'' <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said in
an interview, ``but this is the first time a journalist has ever
gone to the scene of the crime to interview people who lived
there.''
   The cover story in this week's L'Express magazine, published
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>, details the role of the French police in the roundup.
   <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON>, who tracked down the <ORGANIZATION>Lyon Gestapo</ORGANIZATION> chief <PERSON>Klaus Barbie</PERSON>,
said he hoped the article would help speed court action against
<PERSON>Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, 80, charged with crimes against humanity.
   Bousquet was chief of the national police during the
deportations, which <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said were conducted by the
collaborationist <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government to curry favor with the Nazi
occupiers.
   <PERSON>Eric Conan</PERSON>, a reporter for <ORGANIZATION>L'Express</ORGANIZATION>, visited the towns of
Pithiviers and Beaune-la-Rolande, sites of two French concentration
camps where the children spent their last days before being shipped
to the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION>' <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION> death camp.
   ``In Pithiviers, nothing, absolutely nothing, officially
commemorates the agony experienced by the children before their
deaths,'' he wrote.
   A collective gravestone in Beaune-la-Rolande shows three small
children died at that time. The stone reads simply, ``Victims of
Hitler's barbarism.''
   ``This is false: they were under the auspices of the French
government until the moment they died,'' <PERSON>Conan</PERSON> wrote.
   The children were arrested in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> with their families <DATE>July
16-17</DATE>, <DATE>1942</DATE>, in the infamous ``Vel d'Hiv Roundup,'' named for their
destination, a large cycling stadium.
   The families were kept kept at the stadium for days without
food, water or sanitary facilities. They were transferred to
<ORGANIZATION>Pithiviers</ORGANIZATION> and Beaune-la-Rolande. The adults were sent directly on
to <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION>, but the children, including babies and toddlers,
remained for weeks in the camps, where many died of starvation and
disease.
   They were later shipped to <LOCATION>Auschwitz</LOCATION> and sent to the gas
chambers on arrival.
   <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said French authorities ordered the deportations of
the children. The Nazis, he said, had issued orders for the roundup
of only Jews over age 16 for fear of inciting the occupied
population.
   ``They never would have taken the risk of arresting and dragging
children into the streets of <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Klarsfeld</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-5134</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDPBVACOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910416
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  16 APR 91 / International Company News: Perrier wins trickle from a
Catalan source
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER BRUCE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   MADRID
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
THE FRENCH may not have won a battle this important in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> since they took
<LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> in the War of the Spanish Succession 277 years ago.
A Catalan court has ruled that the French mineral water giant, <ORGANIZATION>Perrier</ORGANIZATION>, had
a rightful claim to a small fee for every litre of water sold by the only
producer of naturally carbonated water outside of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Vichy Catalan</PERSON>.
Although <ORGANIZATION>Perrier</ORGANIZATION> will earn a mere Dollars 1,040 a year from the ruling, the
victory is an important legal foothold from which to press its attack on
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s fastest growing mineral water market. It has taken the French much
of this century to break through the Catalan defences.
The story begins in <DATE>1881</DATE>, when a Catalan doctor, Modest Furest i Roca,
discovered a <DATE>spring</DATE> near <LOCATION>Gerona</LOCATION> whose waters resembled those he had once
enjoyed in <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. His enthusiasm for the bicarbonated waters
persuaded some Catalan businessmen to back his plans to bottle it.
Furest apparently registered the name <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> first. Today the
company is the biggest supplier of fizzy and still mineral waters in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
Since <ORGANIZATION>Perrier</ORGANIZATION> took over management of <PERSON>Vichy Celestins</PERSON> more than 40 years ago
it has tried desperately to enter the Spanish market with a vichy water.
Catalan courts have handed down victory after victory to the home team.
In <DATE>1988</DATE>, however, the stalking French managed to buy about 6 per cent of
Vichy Catalan from one of the five Furest descendants, for about <ORGANIZATION>Dollars
2.5m. Since</ORGANIZATION> then it has argued in the courts that it has a right to the
canon each of the descendants gets on a litre of Vichy Catalan sold (one
fifth of a peseta per litre) and to inspect production.
Last year a lower court in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> would not admit the acquisition. But
<ORGANIZATION>Perrier</ORGANIZATION> appealed and, though the higher court would not allow it to inspect
production, it has recognised the right to a share of the sales.
Vichy Catalan is saying nothing.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 25
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890704-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-04-89 2017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Obit-Leguay 1stLd-Writethru   07-04 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Obit-Leguay, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0634,0316</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nazi Collaborator Dies While Awaiting Trial</HEAD>
<HEAD>EDS: SUBS 2nd graf, `Leguay died...' to ADD day of death.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nazi collaborator <PERSON>Jean Leguay</PERSON>, charged with
committing crimes against humanity, has died in a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> hospital,
his lawyer said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. He was 79.
   Leguay died <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after a year-long battle with liver cancer,
his lawyer, <PERSON>Yves Jaffre</PERSON> said.
   Leguay was a senior police official in the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> government,
which collaborated with the <ORGANIZATION>Nazis</ORGANIZATION> during their World War II
occupation of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. He faced two charges for aiding in the
deportation of French Jews but neither came to trial.
   In <DATE>1979</DATE>, he was charged for his role in the <DATE>July 1942</DATE> roundup of
12,884 Jews _ including 4,051 children _ who were gathered in a
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> cycling stadium, the Velodrome d'Hiver, and deported to <ORGANIZATION>Nazi</ORGANIZATION>
death camps.
   The second set of charges, filed in <DATE>1986</DATE>, involved the
deportation of 444 Jews from <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>August 1942</DATE>.
   Leguay was deputy police chief in the occupied zone at the time
of the deportations.
   When he was charged in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <PERSON>Leguay</PERSON> issued a statement saying he
``never had any concern from <DATE>1940</DATE> to <DATE>1944</DATE> other than protecting the
French from their occupants.'' He was detained briefly in that year
then released pending trial.
   <PERSON>Serge Klarsfeld</PERSON>, the French lawyer who led the effort to bring
criminal charges against <PERSON>Leguay</PERSON>, described him as ``a political
police officer charged with negotiations with the Germans.''
Klarsfeld accused <PERSON>Leguay</PERSON> of persuading the Germans to include Jewish
children as well as adults in the roundups.
   Lawyer <PERSON>Jaffre</PERSON> said <PERSON>Leguay</PERSON> ``did nothing but obey the orders of
the <ORGANIZATION>Interior</ORGANIZATION> Secretary at the time.'' That the investigation
``dragged on for 10 years clearly proved there was nothing in the
dossier,'' he said.
   Under French law, there is no time limit on prosecutions for
crimes against humanity.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-5830</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CKYCPAA3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921125
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  25 NOV 92 / Mitterrand to rebuild Mideast relations
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By WILLIAM DAWKINS
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
PRESIDENT <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> and four senior government ministers today
begin a four-day tour of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, in an attempt to rebuild
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s weakened influence in the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>.
He will visit <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> for the first time since <DATE>1982</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON> was
the first serving French president to do so, thus opening a reconciliation
between the two countries. <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> has been eager to forge closer ties since
the <DATE>June</DATE> election victory of an <ORGANIZATION>Israeli Labour</ORGANIZATION> administration, committed to
progress in peace talks with the Arabs.
However, the tour comes at a sensitive moment in relations with <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>,
because of <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>'s recent refusal to apologise for the wartime <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON>
regime's persecution of French Jews and his decision to send a wreath to the
tomb of Marshal <PERSON>Philippe Petain</PERSON>, the Vichy leader.
French influence in the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION> has dwindled since the Gulf war, because
of its arms sales to <ORGANIZATION>Iraq</ORGANIZATION>, and the country has played only a minor role in
the Arab-Israeli peace talks.
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> has accordingly started to play an important part in encouraging
talks on economic matters between the two sides, having hosted last month an
economic conference of Israelis and Palestinians in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. The French
government tabled a plan to rebuild the regional rail network and plans to
promote this idea on the coming tour.
The 150-strong delegation, which includes senior industrialists, will focus
on immediate rail projects, such as for a link to the Red Sea port of <LOCATION>Eilat</LOCATION>
and the electrification of a line from <LOCATION>Haifa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Tel Aviv</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>, who last week called for an end to the 'unacceptable,
immoral' Arab boycott of <LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION>, will meet Palestinian leaders tomorrow. He
will then move on to <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON>, a long-standing French ally. He is due to
discuss the progress of the peace talks with <PERSON>King Hussein</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 4
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-4160</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EIKACAAWFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940910
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 SEP 94 / Mitterrand wields double-edged sword: Ailing French
president prepares the ground for the judgment of history
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By DAVID BUCHAN
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   PARIS
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
In recent days <PERSON>Francois Mitterrand</PERSON> has been behaving like a man clearing his
desk, putting a gloss on his presidential record for posterity, and emptying
out dusty drawers before the historical cleaners arrive to uncover more
murky incidents in his past.
One of his doctors affirmed yesterday that the president, whose 78th
birthday falls next month and who has been suffering from prostate cancer
for at least two years, was 'fine'. And indeed on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON> was
in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> to take the farewell to his country's troops there, and he was
back in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> yesterday to greet President <PERSON>Jiang Zemin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, with whom
he will sign some big-figure trade contracts today.
But what the president has told Le Figaro newspaper in two long interviews
this week, and <PERSON>Mr Pierre Pean</PERSON>, the author of a startling book on the 1936-47
period of his youth, has left an extraordinary ambiguity around everything,
including his health. He told Le Figaro that he reckoned his cancer 'will be
obliging enough for me to finish my term' which ends next <DATE>May</DATE>, but also said
he was conscious that he would only be around 'for a few months or years'.
As <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>, a specialist in ambiguity, well realises, such comments
only fuel the uncertainty in the markets and the French political world
about an early election. In addition, the Socialist president has managed to
spray criticism and praise around in such a way as to help destabilise
French conservatives. This would be wholly welcome to his own party, if it
were not for the fact that revelations about his right-wing and Vichyist
associations before, during and after the second world war have shocked many
Socialists.
It was already known that the young <PERSON>Mitterrand</PERSON> participated in some
right-wing movements before the war, and that after his escape from a German
prisoner camp in <DATE>1941</DATE>, he worked for the <PERSON>Vichy</PERSON> administration for a year or
so before sliding into the resistance.
But what has shocked many French is the disclosure of <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>'s
friendly associations with <PERSON>Mr Jean-Paul Martin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mr Rene Bousquet</PERSON>, senior
officials in the <LOCATION>Vichy</LOCATION> police. <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON>, while president, apparently
attended <PERSON>Mr Martin</PERSON>'s funeral in <DATE>1986</DATE>. He also told <PERSON>Mr Pean</PERSON> that he
considered <PERSON>Mr Bousquet</PERSON> 'sympathetic'; yet as president he inaugurated a day
of national mourning for one of the Jewish deportations in <DATE>1942</DATE> of which
<PERSON>Bousquet</PERSON> was accused. The latter was assassinated last year before he could
face war crimes charges.
In the same interviews, <PERSON>Mr Mitterrand</PERSON> also delves into his more recent past.
