<DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-47574 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas010_a_94018" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-010 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  14 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Population Symposium To Prepare for UN Forum </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW1201135294 Tokyo KYODO in English 0940 GMT 12 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1201135294 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

organizations (NGOs) will discuss problems resulting from the 
growing world population at a symposium from <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in 
preparation for a <ORGANIZATION>United Nations Conference on Population and 
Development</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, later this year, organizers said 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [12 <DATE>January</DATE>]. 
  The symposium, which will be held at <ORGANIZATION>Waseda University</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, is co-organized by the "Peoples' Forum <DATE>2001</DATE>," an <ORGANIZATION>NGO</ORGANIZATION> 
umbrella organization, and "<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Network for Women and 
Health," which aims at increasing women's representation at the 
<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> conference. 
  Panelists will include <PERSON>Makoto Ato</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Health and 
Welfare Ministry's Institute of Population Problems</ORGANIZATION>, Assistant 
Prof. <PERSON>Chizuko Ueno</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo University</ORGANIZATION> and representatives of 
the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Population Fund</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The symposium will adopt an appeal urging the Japanese 
Government to include <ORGANIZATION>NGO</ORGANIZATION> and women representatives in its 
delegation for the <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> conference. The suggestions will be 
submitted to the government-organized "<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> Wise Men's 
Conference on Population and Development," which will be held on 
<DATE>February 26</DATE> and 27. 
  "Population growth in developing countries is a result of 
environment destruction by developed countries. There the 
Japanese bear responsibility too," said <PERSON>Shunsuke Iwasaki</PERSON>, 
assistant professor at <ORGANIZATION>Tsukuba University</ORGANIZATION> and head of the 
Peoples' Forum <DATE>2001</DATE>. 
  "This problem is not that simple that it could be solved by 
just providing means for birth control. As the <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> conference 
is drawing closer, we want to make the first step to give 
ordinary people a say (in these matters)," <PERSON>Iwasaki</PERSON> said in 
explaining the objectives of the symposium. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> holds its international <ORGANIZATION>Conference on Population 
and 
Development</ORGANIZATION> every ten years. This year's conference, from 
<DATE>September 5</DATE> to 13, will adopt an action program seeking to 
establish a sustainable balance between the soaring population, 
scarce resources and an increasingly damaged environment. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> estimates that the world population will grow by a 
record 93 million to over 5.7 billion in <DATE>1994</DATE>, with the majority 
of the growth occurring in developing countries. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-47210 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas007_a_94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-007 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  11 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Tokyo To Host Population, Development Forum </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW1101110194 Tokyo KYODO in English 0959 GMT 11 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1101110194 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 11</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> will cosponsor an 
eminent persons' meeting on the subjects of population and 
development on <DATE>January 26</DATE> and 27 in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> 
spokesman <PERSON>Terusuke Terada</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [11 <DATE>January</DATE>]. 
  The meeting will formulate its recommendations to a 
UN-sponsored conference in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> next <DATE>September</DATE>. 
  Some 20 high-level scholars, academics and political leaders 
who are well-versed in the problems of population will attend 
the meeting at the <ORGANIZATION>UN University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Terada</PERSON> said. 
  Participants will include such prominent figures as 
<PERSON>Miguel</PERSON> de la <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>, former <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Robert McNamara</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Taro Nakayama</PERSON>, former Japanese foreign minister. 
  The meeting is to be held under the cosponsorship of the 
<ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> 
Population Fund (<ORGANIZATION>UNFPA</ORGANIZATION>), the <ORGANIZATION>UN University</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign 
Ministry</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Japanese Prime Minister <PERSON>Morihiro Hosokawa</PERSON> will address the 
opening ceremony. 
  The participants are expected to adopt a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> declaration 
on 
the closing day. 
  The deliberations at the meeting will be recommended to the 
Development</ORGANIZATION>, which is to be held in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE> to 
discuss measures for problems related to the rapidly increasing 
world population. 
  <PERSON>Terada</PERSON> said <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is by far the largest donor country for 
<ORGANIZATION>UNFPA</ORGANIZATION>, donating <MONEY>59 million dollars</MONEY> in <DATE>1992</DATE> and as much as <MONEY>63 
million dollars</MONEY> in <DATE>1993</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-27959 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas022aa_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-022 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  2 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   UN Population Meeting Ends With Declaration </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW2701092894 Tokyo KYODO in English 0652 GMT 27 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2701092894 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 27</DATE> KYODO -- A <ORGANIZATION>United Nations-sponsored</ORGANIZATION> 
meeting on population and development concluded <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [27 
<DATE>January</DATE>] with a declaration urging governments to curb 
population growth. 
  The two-day conference was held at the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations 
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. 
  "Population growth is a major obstacle to the alleviation of 
poverty, sustained socioeconomic development, and the 
improvement of the status of women," said the draft text of the 
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> declaration of the meeting of eminent persons on 
population and development. 
  The meeting, also sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, was 
held 
in preparation for the <ORGANIZATION>International Conference on Population 
and Development</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>ICPD</ORGANIZATION>) slated for <DATE>September</DATE> in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>. 
  "We...call upon all governments and intergovernmental and 
nongovernmental organizations to do their utmost to make the 
(<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>) conference a milestone in the global effort to eradicate 
poverty and socioeconomic inequality, to achieve sustained 
economic growth and sustainable development, to improve the 
status and role of women and to reduce population growth," it 
said. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> has predicted the world population, now 
at 
<MONEY>5.6 billion</MONEY>, will increase to 10 billion by <DATE>2050</DATE>. 
  The declaration urged developing countries to integrate 
population issues into national development planning, and 
developed nations to change their patterns of consumption and to 
curb overproduction in order to reduce the impact on the 
environment and on the use of resources. 
  It also urged "the world community...to increase their 
financial commitment to population and related activities in 
developing countries in order to reach the estimated amount of 
approximately <MONEY>13 billion dollars</MONEY>...by the year <DATE>2000</DATE> and 
approximately <MONEY>17 billion dollars</MONEY> by the year <DATE>2015</DATE> annually." 
  At a news conference held immediately after the meeting 
<PERSON>Fred Sai</PERSON>, vice chairman of the <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> meeting, said, "one thing 
which has come out here...is that...we have to start addressing 
population issues much more seriously." 
  He said the other point stressed through the discussion was 
the importance of "partnership between the developed and 
developing countries." 
  The news conference was also attended by <PERSON>Nafis Sadik</PERSON>, 
executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Population Fund</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>U.N. University 
Rector Heitor Gurgulino de Souza</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Population 
Council</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General <PERSON>Maher Mahran</PERSON> [name as received] and 
former Japanese Foreign Minister <PERSON>Taro Nakayama</PERSON>, chairman of the 
gathering. 
  The 14-member panel of the meeting debated sustainable 
development, family planning and the status of women in relation 
to population. 
  The panel also included former <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Robert 
McNamara</PERSON>, former Mexican President Miguel de la <PERSON>Madrid Hurtado</PERSON> 
and former <LOCATION>Kiribati</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Jeremia T. Tabai</PERSON>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-21491 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten004__l94001" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-004-L </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  1 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> JAPAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Report to UN Population Conference Expected To Cause `Stir' </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Report to UN Population Conference Expected To Cause `Stir' </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0403123494 Tokyo MAINICHI SHIMBUN in Japanese 1 Mar 94 
Evening Edition p 1 </F>

<F P=103> OW0403123494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo MAINICHI SHIMBUN </F>
<F P=105>  Japanese </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The contents of a draft report the government plans 
Development" (<ORGANIZATION>ICPD</ORGANIZATION>), which is to be held this <DATE>September</DATE> in 
<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, was revealed on 1 <DATE>March</DATE>. In the report, the government 
touches on such issues as population trends and reduced birth 
rates. Regarding environmental hazards brought about by 
population growth concentrated in particular regions, the 
government concludes that "A high standard of education has 
enabled the nation to overcome such problems rather quickly." 
However, the government completely fails to touch on 
environmental issues which large cities face, such as huge 
amounts of garbage and air pollution. This stance is expected 
to cause a stir, inasmuch as the main theme of the <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> 
conference includes "population, development, and environment." 
  The government's draft report consists of 17 pages of text 
divided into four major sections: 
  1) population trends and future outlook; 
  2) current situation regarding government policies related 
to 
population trends; 
  3) international cooperation regarding population issues; 
and 
  4) summary and conclusion. 
  Seven sets of graphical data, such as that showing trends in 
average lifespans, are also included in the draft report. 
  Regarding problems resulting from population movements 
within 
the nation, the government, in the report, refers to the cases 
of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Osaka</LOCATION>, and Kyoto as examples. It points out that in 
these cities, "the population began growing in the <DATE>1960</DATE>'s due to 
the development of heavy chemical industries and the urban 
living environment rapidly deteriorated." It adds that the 
nation "was able to proceed with economic development in harmony 
with environmental preservation, after succeeding in overcoming 
population, developmental, and environmental crises rather 
quickly through public support and government efforts." 
  In the report, the government contends that the nation was 
able to overcome such crises due to "an especially high standard 
of education." It adds that "putting emphasis on education and 
the government's effective use of information play an invaluable 
role in international efforts to help developing countries with 
their population problems." 
  In <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and other major cities, the problem of securing 
garbage disposal sites has become very serious. Nitrogen oxide 
emissions accompanying the sharp increase in automobile traffic 
have led to air pollution. The government fails to take up 
these issues in its draft report. In this regard, an official 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Health and Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> explained: "It is impossible 
to cover all population-related issues, and there is also a 
limit to the report's length." 
  However, greater interest has been shown in developing 
countries concerning air pollution and garbage issues because 
recently, the environment has been deteriorating in these 
countries due to a rapidly growing population concentrated in 
cities. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-5387 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas045__a94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-045-A </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> ANNEX </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Report to UN Population Conference Previewed </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0403123494 Tokyo MAINICHI SHIMBUN in Japanese 1 Mar 94 
Evening Edition p 1 -- FOR OFFICIAL USE ONLY </F>

<F P=103> OW0403123494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo MAINICHI SHIMBUN </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Japanese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] The contents of a draft report the government plans 
Development" (<ORGANIZATION>ICPD</ORGANIZATION>), which is to be held this <DATE>September</DATE> in 
<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, was revealed on 1 <DATE>March</DATE>. In the report, the government 
touches on such issues as population trends and reduced birth 
rates. Regarding environmental hazards brought about by 
population growth concentrated in particular regions, the 
government concludes that "A high standard of education has 
enabled the nation to overcome such problems rather quickly." 
However, the government completely fails to touch on 
environmental issues which large cities face, such as huge 
amounts of garbage and air pollution. This stance is expected 
to cause a stir, inasmuch as the main theme of the <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> 
conference includes "population, development, and environment." 
  The government's draft report consists of 17 pages of text 
divided into four major sections: 1) population trends and 
future outlook; 2) current situation regarding government 
policies related to population trends; 3) international 
cooperation regarding population issues; and 4) summary and 
conclusion. Seven sets of graphical data, such as that showing 
trends in average lifespans, are also included in the draft 
report. 
  Regarding problems resulting from population movements 
within 
the nation, the government, in the report, refers to the cases 
of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Osaka</LOCATION>, and Kyoto as examples. It points out that in 
these cities, "the population began growing in the <DATE>1960</DATE>'s due to 
the development of heavy chemical industries and the urban 
living environment rapidly deteriorated." It adds that the 
nation "was able to proceed with economic development in harmony 
with environmental preservation, after succeeding in overcoming 
population, developmental, and environmental crises rather 
quickly through public support and government efforts." 
  In the report, the government contends that the nation was 
able to overcome such crises due to "an especially high standard 
of education." It adds that "putting emphasis on education and 
the government's effective use of information play an invaluable 
role in international efforts to help developing countries with 
their population problems." 
  In <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and other major cities, the problem of securing 
garbage disposal sites has become very serious. Nitrogen oxide 
emissions accompanying the sharp increase in automobile traffic 
have led to air pollution. The government fails to take up 
these issues in its draft report. In this regard, an official 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Health and Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> explained: "It is impossible 
to cover all population- related issues, and there is also a 
limit to the report's length." 
  However, greater interest has been shown in developing 
countries concerning air pollution and garbage issues because 
recently, the environment has been deteriorating in these 
countries due to a rapidly growing population concentrated in 
cities. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880705-0089 </DOCNO>
<HL> Three Billion Day Approaches in Asia And Causes Concern --- China Presses Birth Control; Responses on Global Level Urged at Meeting in Japan </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST </CO>
<DATELINE> TOKYO (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven babies are born every second in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, and the continent may be only days away from reaching three billion inhabitants. 
This is causing some concern in the world's most crowded corner. 

   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> greeted the prospect with a ceremony and speeches that urged its citizens to keep practicing birth control. 
In <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, a group of experts gathered to debate the significance of the approaching milestone, its effects on the family and the growing problem of feeding all those people. 

   <PERSON>Takashi Sato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s minister of agriculture, said <DATE>Friday</DATE> that "excessive population growth will result in shortages of food, resources and energy . . . and environmental destruction beyond national boundaries. 

   "Without global-level responses to the issues of population, food, environment and development," he said, "it would be difficult for the world to welcome a peaceful 21st century." 
<PERSON>Mr. Sato</PERSON> is chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Asian Forum of Parliamentarians on Population and Development</ORGANIZATION>, which sponsored the conference. 

   In <DATE>July 1987</DATE>, the world's population passed five billion, double the population in <DATE>1950</DATE>. 

   According to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> estimates, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s population will reach three billion on <DATE>Aug. 10</DATE>. 
Asia experts, however, predict the milestone will be reached within days. 

   Prof. <PERSON>Gayl D. Ness</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION>, a sociologist and researcher on Asian population, estimated that <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s population would grow to 3.5 billion by the end of the century -- and to 4.5 billion by the year <DATE>2025</DATE> while the world population reaches 8.2 billion. 

   Rice production will have to increase <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> by <DATE>2025</DATE> to feed the continent, Prof. <PERSON>Ness</PERSON> said, but great gains already have been registered by farmers in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. 

   The 21st century targets, he said, "are well within the realm of possibility if the agricultural transformation continues; this, of course, requires sensitive government policies." 

   <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, said Prof. <PERSON>Ness</PERSON>, has made "substantial progress" in lowering fertility rates, and Asian countries were the first to adopt policies to limit population growth. 

   But he noted disparities between regions of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. 
East Asian countries such as <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, which has 1.08 billion people, and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, which has 122 million, have rapidly declining fertility rates. 
But in <LOCATION>South Asia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is still experiencing <PERCENT>2.08%</PERCENT> annual growth in its current population of 818 million; <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>3.45%</PERCENT> growth with 115 million people; and <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> has a <PERCENT>2.67%</PERCENT> growth rate from a current base of 110 million, according to <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> figures. 

   "The challenge lies ahead in completing the demographic transition and bringing birth rates down to match the fall in the death rates," Prof. <PERSON>Ness</PERSON> said. 

   He and other panelists were critical of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for withdrawing money from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Fund</ORGANIZATION> for Population Activities because of the fund's support for abortion. 

   The population growth also has caused some social changes. 

   Prof. <PERSON>Toshio Kuroda</PERSON>, director emeritus of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Population</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Nihon University</ORGANIZATION>, noted that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> "expects the family to care for the aged . . . but the family is undergoing tremendous change in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> with the one-child family." 

   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, the world's most populous country, has since the early <DATE>1980s</DATE> limited most families to one child. 
But the limit has been widely flouted in the past two years. 

   In <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, Chinese officials heralded the <ORGANIZATION>Day of Three Billion</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> with a ceremony in the <PERSON>Great Hall</PERSON> of the People. They handed out cassette players to 18 family planning workers, doctors and others for "outstanding performance in implementing our population policy." Speakers warned that rapid population growth poses a threat to economic development. Said <PERSON>Hu Keshi</PERSON>, forum vice chairman:
   "We cannot think that we can have more children because of economic development . . . nor can we relax our efforts because of progress in family planning." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-22387 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten008___94020" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-008 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  9 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> JAPAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Scientists To Study Shanghai, Bangkok Environments </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0903063594 Tokyo KYODO in English 0613 GMT 9 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0903063594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 9</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> will 
be the subject of a three-year study by a group of Japanese 
scientists to help curb environmental destruction in the face of 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s rapidly expanding population, officials of the <ORGANIZATION>Health and 
Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [9 <DATE>March</DATE>]. 
  The study will be launched later this year and will focus on 
the impact of urbanization and population growth on consumption 
of energy, a main source of emissions of carbon dioxide and 
other greenhouse gases believed to cause global warming, the 
officials said. 
  Scientists say the change in climate could ultimately turn 
entire regions into deserts. 
  The team of scientists from the ministry's <ORGANIZATION>Institute of 
Population Problems and Institute of Public Health</ORGANIZATION> hope to 
improve long-term forecasts for greenhouse gas emissions in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> 
by examining the causes of population growth and the impact of 
rural migration to cities, they said. 
  The group will also look at how global warming affects the 
spread of malaria, they said. 
  The results of the study will be used to draw up population 
and energy conservation policies that could help reduce the 
impact of global warming. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>Environment Agency</ORGANIZATION> will incorporate the findings in its 
"Eco- <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> 21 Plan" and will try to enlist support from other 
Asian countries, the officials said. 
  World population is expected to increase to 6.3 billion by 
the turn of the century from 5.3 billion in <DATE>1990</DATE>. According to 
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> population fund forecasts, it will further swell 
to <MONEY>8.5 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>2025</DATE>, with more than half of the growth 
occurring in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, mainly <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. 
  Rural migration is likely to continue, raising the portion 
of 
people living in Asian cities from <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of total 
population to over <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>2020</DATE>. 
that <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s energy consumption will show annual growth rates of 
<PERCENT>3.2 percent</PERCENT>, far outstripping the world average of <PERCENT>1.6 percent</PERCENT>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880701-0271 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-88 1335EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-AsiaPopulation     07-01 0647</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Asia Population,0669</SECOND>
<HEAD>Asia's Growing Concern: 3 Billion's A Crowd</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: also on general news wires.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By LARRY THORSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven babies are born every second in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the
continent may be only days away from reaching 3 billion
inhabitants, an occasion causing some concern in the world's most
crowded corner, experts said <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, faced with a motherlode of maternity, marked the occasion
with a ceremony and speeches that urged its citizens to keep
practicing birth control. In <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, a group of experts gathered to
debate the significance of the approaching milestone, its effects
on the family and the growing problem of feeding all those people.
   <PERSON>Takashi Sato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s minister of agriculture, said ``excessive
population growth will result in shortages of food, resources and
energy ... and environmental destruction beyond national boundaries.
   ``Without global-level responses to the issues of population,
food, environment and development, it would be difficult for the
world to welcome a peaceful <DATE>21st century</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Sato</PERSON>, chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>Asian Forum of Parliamentarians on Population and Development</ORGANIZATION>,
which sponsored the conference.
   In <DATE>July 1987</DATE>, the world's population passed 5 billion, double
the population in <DATE>1950</DATE>.
   According to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> estimates, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s population will
reach <MONEY>3 billion</MONEY> at <TIME>47 minutes after midnight</TIME> <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION> Mean Time on
<DATE>Aug. 10</DATE> (<TIME>8:47 p.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Aug. 9</DATE>). Asian experts, however, predict the
milestone will be reached within days.
   Professor <PERSON>Gayl D. Ness</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Michigan</ORGANIZATION> estimated
that <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s population would grow to 3.5 billion by the end of the
century and to 4.5 billion by <DATE>2025</DATE>, while the world population
reaches 8.2 billion.
   Rice production will have to increase <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> by <DATE>2025</DATE> to feed
the continent, <PERSON>Ness</PERSON> said, but great gains already have been
registered by farmers in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>.
   The 21st century targets ``are well within the realm of
possibility if the agricultural transformation continues. This, of
course, requires sensitive government policies,'' said the
sociologist and researcher on Asian population.
   <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> has made ``substantial progress'' in lowering fertility
rates, and Asian countries were the first to adopt policies to
limit population growth, he said.
   But Ness noted disparities in different regions of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>. East
Asian countries such as <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, which has 122 million
people, have rapidly declining fertility rates.
   But in <LOCATION>South Asia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is still experiencing <PERCENT>2.08 percent</PERCENT>
annual growth in its population of 818 million; <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>3.45
percent</PERCENT> growth with 115 million people; and <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> has <PERCENT>2.67
percent</PERCENT> growth rate from a current base of 110 million, according
to <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> figures.
   ``The challenge lies ahead in completing the demographic
transition and bringing birth rates down to match the fall in the
death rates,'' <PERSON>Ness</PERSON> said.
   He and other panelists were critical of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> for
withdrawing money from the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Fund</ORGANIZATION> for Population Activities
because of the fund's support for abortion.
   The population growth also has caused some social changes.
   Professor <PERSON>Toshio Kuroda</PERSON>, director emeritus of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Institute
of Population</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Nihon University</ORGANIZATION>, noted that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> ``expects the
family to care for the aged ... but the family is undergoing
tremendous change in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> with the one-child family.''
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, the world's most populous country with 1.08 billion
people, has since the early <DATE>1980s</DATE> limited most families to one
child. But the limit has been widely flouted in the past two years.
   In <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, Chinese officials marked the Day of 3 Billion In
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> with a ceremony in the <PERSON>Great Hall</PERSON> of the People.
   They handed out cassette players to 18 family planning workers,
doctors and others for ``outstanding performance in implementing
our population policy.''
   Speakers warned that rapid population growth poses a threat to
economic development.
   ``We cannot think that we can have more children because of
economic development ... nor can we relax our efforts because of
progress in family planning,'' said <PERSON>Hu Keshi</PERSON>, forum vice chairman.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-48309 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas016_a_94014" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-016 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  25 Jan 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Norwegian Prime Minister Cancels Tokyo Trip </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW2501051694 Tokyo KYODO in English 0403 GMT 25 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2501051694 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> KYODO -- Norwegian Prime Minister 
<PERSON>Gro Brundtland</PERSON> has canceled a visit to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to attend a <ORGANIZATION>United 
Nations-sponsored</ORGANIZATION> meeting because of illness, UN officials said 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [25 <DATE>January</DATE>]. 
  Brundtland was scheduled to participate in the meeting of 
eminent persons on population and development at the <ORGANIZATION>United 
Nations University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. She was also to speak at the 
opening ceremony of the gathering. 
  The meeting, to be held in preparation for the international 
conference on population and development slated for <DATE>September</DATE> in 
<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, will discuss sustainable development, family planning and 
the status of women in relation to population. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-51839 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas086_a_94019" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-086 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Further Decline Reported in Young Population </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Further Decline Reported in Young Population </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0405092294 Tokyo KYODO in English 0905 GMT 4 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0405092294 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 4</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s young population 
declined further to total 20.59 million children under the age 
of 15 as of <DATE>April 1</DATE>, down 500,000 from a year ago, the 
<ORGANIZATION>Management and Coordination Agency</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [4 May], a day 
before <DATE>Children's Day</DATE>. As of <DATE>April 1 this year</DATE>, children 
accounted for <PERCENT>16.5 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's 125 million 
population, down 0.4 percentage points from the previous year, 
the agency said. 
  Since <DATE>1975</DATE>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has witnessed a steady decline in its 
population of children, a trend often referred to as <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 
aging society. 
  The largest portion of the nation's children, some 1.62 
million, are already teenagers aged 14. Reflecting the 
declining birth rate over the <DATE>last decade</DATE>, the younger the 
child, the fewer peers in his age group. 
  About 1.2 million children belong to each age group between 
1 
and 4. Children under 1 year old numbered 1.19 million. 
  <LOCATION>Okinawa Prefecture</LOCATION> was <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s "youngest" prefecture with 
more than one in five persons, or <PERCENT>22.8 percent</PERCENT>, under 15, 
according to statistics as of <DATE>October 1, 1993</DATE>. Following were 
<ORGANIZATION>Saga Prefecture</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Miyazaki Prefecture</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>18.9 percent</PERCENT> each. 
  In contrast, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> with more than 11 million inhabitants had 
the lowest share of children with some <PERCENT>13.9 percent</PERCENT>. A slightly 
higher percentage of young people were living in <LOCATION>Toyama</LOCATION> 
prefecture, with <PERCENT>15.8 percent</PERCENT>, and <LOCATION>Kanagawa Prefecture</LOCATION>, with 
<PERCENT>15.9 percent</PERCENT>. 
  In all 47 prefectures, the share of children was lower than 
the previous year. 
  Compared with other aging industrialized nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> came 
third after <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, where children under 15 accounted 
for <PERCENT>16.3 percent</PERCENT> of the national populations, based on <DATE>1991</DATE> and 
<DATE>1992</DATE> surveys, respectively. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5066 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas067_a_94029" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-067 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  5 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Well-Being of Hokkaido's Ainu Population Viewed </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Well-Being of Hokkaido's Ainu Population Viewed </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0504113294 Tokyo KYODO in English 1038 GMT 5 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0504113294 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Sapporo</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 5</DATE> KYODO -- Most of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s minority 
Ainu remain dissatisfied with their standard of living, 
according to a survey released by the prefectural government on 
<ORGANIZATION>Hokkaido</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s northernmost main island. The survey showed 
that <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> of the Ainu families interviewed on <ORGANIZATION>Hokkaido</ORGANIZATION> 
said they find it "tough" to make ends meet, while another <PERCENT>44 
percent</PERCENT> opted to characterize it as "somewhat difficult." 
  A total of 300 Ainu families in <LOCATION>Hokkaido</LOCATION>, where most of 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Ainu live, were interviewed last <DATE>June</DATE> for the survey, 
which has been conducted every seven years since <DATE>1972</DATE>. Despite 
complaints about difficulties in earning a livelihood, the 
survey showed that ratio of Ainu receiving welfare payments from 
the government fell from 60.9 per 1,000 population in the last 
survey, undertaken in <DATE>1986</DATE>, to 38.8 per 1,000 population in the 
current survey. 
  The survey said <ORGANIZATION>Hokkaido</ORGANIZATION>'s Ainu population stood at 23,830, 
or a decrease of 551 over the last survey. 
  There are few remaining full-blooded Ainu in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Counted 
as <ORGANIZATION>Ainu</ORGANIZATION> in the survey were those thought to have at least some 
Ainu blood or those living in families with members who have 
Ainu blood. 
  The survey said the percentage of Ainu children going on to 
senior high school increased by 9 points to <PERCENT>87.4 percent</PERCENT>, though 
it fell short of the <PERCENT>96.3 percent</PERCENT> overall figure for Hokkaido 
children. A bigger gap surfaced in the figures for those 
children proceeding to university or college, with <PERCENT>11.8 percent</PERCENT> 
for the relevant Ainu population compared with <PERCENT>27.5 percent</PERCENT> for 
the overall population. 
  In a questionnaire targeting Ainu aged 15 and older, only 
<PERCENT>7.3 
percent</PERCENT> said they faced incidences of discrimination over the 
past six or seven years, while <PERCENT>62 percent</PERCENT> said they had not. 
  Officials said the <ORGANIZATION>Hokkaido Prefectural Government</ORGANIZATION> intends 
to 
use the survey in planning its future Ainu welfare policies. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880811-0079 </DOCNO>
<HL> Population of Asia Reaches Three Billion, Regional Report Says </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST JAPAN </CO>
<DATELINE> TOKYO (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The population of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> has reached three billion, according to a report released by a group of politicians representing 19 Asian nations. 

   The Asian Forum of Parliamentarians on <ORGANIZATION>Population and Development</ORGANIZATION> report, based on data compiled by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, said this mark was reached at <TIME>47 minutes after midnight</TIME> <LOCATION>Greenwhich</LOCATION> Mean Time yesterday. 

   <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, the world's most populous region, accounts for <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the total global population, which passed the five billion mark in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>. 
Seven babies are born in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> every second -- or 150,000 each day, the report said. 

   The forum, headed by <PERSON>Takashi Sato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Agriculture Minister, issued the report at an international conference in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE>, heralding the Day of the <ORGANIZATION>Three Billion</ORGANIZATION>. 
The forum includes 19 Asian nations from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Syria</LOCATION>. 

   "The designation of a day marking the birth of the three-billionth baby in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is very symbolic," <PERSON>Shigemi Kono</PERSON>, director general of the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Population Problems</ORGANIZATION>, said. 
"But I personally think it is nonsense, because there is no way of actually knowing when the three-billionth baby was born." 

   Skepticism about calculations aside, however, <PERSON>Mr. Kono</PERSON> agrees there are serious population problems in the region. 

   "Though we have come close to solving the fertility rate problem in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, serious questions remain in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>," he said. 

   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, with a population of 818 million, has an annual growth rate of <PERCENT>2.08%</PERCENT>. 
The rate in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, with a population of 115 million, is <PERCENT>3.45%</PERCENT>, and in <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, with 110 million people, it is <PERCENT>2.67%</PERCENT>, according to <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> estimates. 

   By the <DATE>year 2025</DATE>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> will have 4.5 billion inhabitants, said an official with the nonprofit, <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo-based Asian Population and Development Association</ORGANIZATION>. 
The estimated growth in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is roughly equal to the increase in the total world population from <DATE>1950</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>, she added. 

   Specialists have predicted that rice production will have to increase <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> by <DATE>2025</DATE> to feed the continent. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880810-0240 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-88 2022EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Asia-Population 1stLd-Writethru   08-10 0281</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Asia-Population, 1st Ld - Writethru,a0672,0283</SECOND>
<HEAD>Population of Asia Population Reaches 3 Billion</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New grafs 1-3 DELETE population figure containing typo in 3rd
graf. Picks up 4th graf pvs, The designation ...</NOTE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The population of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> topped 3 billion on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> estimates.
   The report, issued by the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION>'s Asian Forum of Parliamentarians
on <ORGANIZATION>Population and Development</ORGANIZATION>, estimated that the population hit
the <MONEY>3 billion mark</MONEY> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>12:47 a.m. Greenwich Mean Time</ORGANIZATION>
(<TIME>8:47 p.m. EDT</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>).
   Seven babies are born every second in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, and the continent
accounts for about <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the global population, according
to the forum, which represents 19 Asian countries.
   ``The designation of a day marking the birth of the 3 billionth
baby in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is very symbolic,'' said <PERSON>Shigemi Kono</PERSON>, director of
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Population Problems</ORGANIZATION>. ``But I
personally think it is nonsense, because there is no way of
actually knowing when the 3 billionth baby was born.''
   Among Asian countries, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> face the
most serious population growth problems, <PERSON>Kono</PERSON> said.
   U.N. figures show that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, with 818 million people, has an
annual population growth rate of <PERCENT>2.08 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, with a
population of <MONEY>115 million</MONEY>, has a <PERCENT>3.45 percent</PERCENT> growth rate and the
110 million population of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> is growing at a <PERCENT>2.67 percent</PERCENT>
rate, according to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>. By the <DATE>year 2025</DATE>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> will
have 4.5 billion inhabitants, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo-based Asian
Population and Development Association</ORGANIZATION> _ roughly equal to the
increase in the total world population from <DATE>1950</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   The world population passed the <MONEY>5 billion mark</MONEY> in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>,
according to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880810-0301 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-10-88 1037EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f BC-Japan-AsiaPopulation     08-10 0352</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Japan-Asia Population,0362</SECOND>
<HEAD>Asian Population Hits 3 Billion</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Forty-seven minutes after the clock struck <TIME>midnight</TIME>
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the population of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> reached 3 billion, according to a
report released by a group of politicians representing 19 Asian
nations.
   The Asian Forum of Parliamentarians on <ORGANIZATION>Population and
Development</ORGANIZATION> report, based on data compiled by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>,
said the population of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> hit the <MONEY>3 billion</MONEY> mark at <DATE>0047</DATE>
<ORGANIZATION>Greenwhich Mean Time</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>, the world's most populous region, accounts for <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT>
of the global total, which passed the <MONEY>5 billion mark</MONEY> in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>.
Seven babies are born in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> every second _ or 150,000 each day _
the report said.
   The forum, headed by <PERSON>Takashi Sato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s Agriculture Minister,
issued the report at an international conference in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>last
month heralding the Day</DATE> of the <ORGANIZATION>Three Billion</ORGANIZATION>. The forum groups 19
Asian nations from <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Syria</LOCATION>.
   ``The designation of a day marking the birth of the 3 billionth
baby in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is very symbolic,'' said <PERSON>Shigemi Kono</PERSON>, director
general of the <ORGANIZATION>National Institute of Population Problems</ORGANIZATION>. ``But I
personally think it is nonsense, because there is no way of
actually knowing when the 3 billionth baby was born.''
   Skepticism about calculations aside, however, Kono agrees there
are serious population problems in the region.
   ``Though we have come close to solving the fertility rate
problem in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, serious questions remain in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, with a population of 818 million, has an annual growth
rate of <PERCENT>2.08 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, with a population of <MONEY>115 million</MONEY>,
has a 3.45-percent growth rate and <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>, with 110 million
people, has <PERCENT>2.67 percent</PERCENT>, according to <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> estimates.
   By the <DATE>year 2025</DATE>, <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> will have 4.5 billion inhabitants, said
an official with the non-profit, <ORGANIZATION>Tokyo-based Asian Population and
Development Association</ORGANIZATION>. The estimated growth in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is roughly
equal to the increase in the total world population from <DATE>1950</DATE> to
<DATE>1980</DATE>, she added, speaking on condition of anonymity.
   Experts have predicted that rice production will have to
increase <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> by <DATE>2025</DATE> to feed the continent.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-2157 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi044_a_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-044 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> General </F>
<H3> <TI>   Asian Meeting on Population, Development Closes in Beijing </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0403132394 Beijing XINHUA in English 1243 GMT 4 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0403132394 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 4</DATE> (XINHUA) -- The 10th Asian 
Parliamentarians' Meeting on Population and Development (APPD) 
closed here today. 
  The meeting has further promoted mutual understanding and 
friendship among the participants from 15 countries including 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> after their discussions on issues of population and 
development and women's position and role. 
  <PERSON>Fukusaburo Maeda</PERSON>, chairman of the Asian population and 
development association, described the two-day meeting as 
significant. 
  He said that in <DATE>September this year</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Third International 
Conference on Population and Development</ORGANIZATION> will be held in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, 
at which a policy on population is expected to be approved. 
  He expressed the hope that this policy will become a program 
for actions of all countries in the next 20 years. 
  <PERSON>Hao Yichun</PERSON>, deputy head of the delegation of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>National 
People's Congress</ORGANIZATION> (NPC) and vice-chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>NPC Education</ORGANIZATION>, 
Science, Culture and <ORGANIZATION>Public Health Committee</ORGANIZATION>, said with the 
common efforts by the Asian parliamentarians, the meeting has 
achieved a complete success. 
  Noting that <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> is the most populous region in the world, 
<PERSON>Hao</PERSON> said the solution of the Asian population problem will be of 
great importance to peace, prosperity and development of <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> 
and the rest of the world. 
  She said many Asian countries have already adopted proper 
measures to reduce the birth rate and have achieved significant 
results. 
  However, <PERSON>Hao</PERSON> said the trend of rapid population growth has 
not yet been checked and the task of improving the quality of 
human resources is still arduous. 
  The solution of population problems requires the common 
efforts from Asian parliaments, governments, non-governmental 
organizations as well as the people from every Asian country, 
she added. 
  After the meeting <PERSON>Fukusaburo Maeda</PERSON> and leaders from the 
Asian 
forum and the <ORGANIZATION>UN Population Fund</ORGANIZATION> gave a press conference and 
answered questions on cooperation between <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>UN 
Population Fund</ORGANIZATION>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-46698 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas002_a_94020" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-002 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Births Hit Historic Low; Divorces, Marriages Up </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW3112075293 Tokyo KYODO in English 0721 GMT 31 Dec 93 </F>
<F P=103> OW3112075293 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE> KYODO -- Despite a wedding every 40 
seconds, fewer babies than ever were born in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in <DATE>1993</DATE> and a 
record number of couples ended up in divorces, the <ORGANIZATION>Health and 
Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> [31 <DATE>December</DATE>]. 
  With 9.6 babies born per thousand people the birth rate hit 
a 
historic low. The number of births fell by 24,000 to 1.19 
million, sinking below the 1.2 million mark for the first time, 
the ministry said in announcing the estimate for this year. 
  The statistics were projected for the whole calendar year 
based on the number of births, deaths, marriages, and divorces 
registered between <DATE>January 1</DATE> and <DATE>October 31</DATE>. 
  The low birth rate is expected to further reduce the 
fertility rate, which represents the average number of children 
a woman gives birth to in her life, from its all-time low last 
year of 1.5 children, officials said. To maintain the current 
population over the long run the rate must be 2.1 or above. 
  Apparently sparked by the <DATE>June</DATE> wedding between <PERSON>Crown Prince 
Naruhito</PERSON> and <PERSON>Masako Owada</PERSON>, 38,000 more couples tied the knot 
than in <DATE>1992</DATE>. The number of marriages has been continuously on 
the rise over the <DATE>last six years</DATE>, reaching 792,000 in <DATE>1993</DATE>. 
  The wedding fever was especially strong in <DATE>June</DATE>, which saw 
an 
increase by 10,000 marriages over last year. On <DATE>June 9</DATE> alone, 
the day of the royal wedding, 13,000 couples started married 
life. However, the country also experienced a second divorce 
boom following a first peak in <DATE>1983</DATE>. After a continued rise 
over the <DATE>last three years</DATE>, divorces peaked at 189,000, an 
all-time high. Some 10,000 more couples decided to separate than 
last year, amounting to a divorce every 2 minutes 47 seconds. 
  While births still outstripped deaths, the natural 
population 
increase further slowed to an all-time low 302,000 people, 
50,000 less than in <DATE>1992</DATE>. Partly due to an influenza epidemic 
in <DATE>January</DATE> and <DATE>February</DATE>, deaths soared by 26,000 to a record 
883,000. 
  As to the causes of death, cancer ranked top with 237,000 
cases, followed by 183,000 deaths resulting from heart diseases, 
and some 120,000 people dying from cerebrovascular diseases. 
The pattern remained unchanged since <DATE>1985</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-29965 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas121aa_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-121 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  22 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Meeting Urges Sustainable Cities </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Meeting Urges Sustainable Cities </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2206143594 Tokyo KYODO in English 1126 GMT 22 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2206143594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Omiya</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 22</DATE> KYODO -- Representatives from 
16 countries in the <LOCATION>Asia-Pacific</LOCATION> region ended a two-day 
environmental meeting <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> [22 <DATE>June</DATE>] with a call for the 
development of sustainable cities and the protection of island 
nations from the effects of global warming. 
  The call was included in a document adopted at the 
environment congress for <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> (Eco <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> `94) in 
<LOCATION>Omiya</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Saitama Prefecture</LOCATION>. 
  Senior officials from 16 governments, including five 
ministers, as well as representatives from eight international 
organizations attended the congress. 
  The congress, the third since <DATE>1991</DATE>, reviewed progress in 
achieving environmentally sustainable development in the region 
(<ORGANIZATION>UNCED</ORGANIZATION>), otherwise known as the earth summit, in <LOCATION>Rio de Janeiro</LOCATION> 
in <DATE>June 1992</DATE>. 
  The document, issued in the name of the conference 
chairwoman, Environment Agency Director General <PERSON>Toshiko 
Hamayotsu</PERSON>, said the region needs to shift from theoretical 
considerations to "concerted political and practical actions, 
international cooperation, and sufficient institutional and 
capacity building." 
  Countries represented at the congress are home to more than 
half the world's population, with millions of people 
concentrated in rapidly growing cities. 
  The document notes the concern of delegates over pollution 
and urban crowding in the region caused by rapid economic 
development at the expense of the environment. 
  It urges, for the first time at an <LOCATION>Eco Asia</LOCATION> meeting, the 
development of the concept of sustainable cities. 
  It also calls for developed countries to "change their mass 
consumption lifestyles, provide support for realization of 
export of pollution." 
  "Solid waste disposal has become a critical issue in this 
region," the document says. 
  The document also incorporates a call made <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> by 
Indonesian Environment Minister <PERSON>Sarwono Kusumaatmaja</PERSON> to "tackle 
the problems" of small island states. 
  <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> and a number of other Pacific nations incorporate 
thousands of small, low-lying islands which could be threatened 
if global warming causes a rise in sea levels. 
  Although many delegates favored establishment of an <LOCATION>Eco Asia</LOCATION> 
secretariat in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, opinion was not unanimous and the document 
merely calls for "development mechanisms for smooth and 
effective implementation of <LOCATION>Eco Asia</LOCATION> activities." 
  Malaysian Environment Minister <PERSON>Hieng Ding Law</PERSON>, who served as 
congress co-chairman, told a press conference after the congress 
that there was "a general feeling that Eco <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> should continue." 
  "It is high time <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> should play a more significant role 
in 
implementing <ORGANIZATION>UNCED</ORGANIZATION>," Law said. "It is important to have a 
secretariat and a data bank." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-27218 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas104_a_94051" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-104 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  31 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Three-Phase Optical Cabling Project Announced </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Three-Phase Optical Cabling Project Announced </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW3105065794 Tokyo KYODO in English 0606 GMT 31 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW3105065794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 31</DATE> KYODO -- A Japanese Government 
advisory panel on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [31 <DATE>May</DATE>] proposed a three-stage scheme 
to build a nationwide optical-fiber telecommunications network 
by <DATE>2010</DATE> as part of efforts to facilitate the shift to an 
information-oriented society in the next century. 
  The scheme would create jobs for 2.43 million people by 
boosting <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s multimedia market by <MONEY>56 trillion yen</MONEY> to <MONEY>123 
trillion yen</MONEY> by the targeted year, said the <ORGANIZATION>Telecommunications 
Council</ORGANIZATION>, an advisory body to the posts minister. 
  The council said the telecom project would help correct the 
over- centralization of information in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, quicken economic 
restructuring in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> through the creation of new business and 
expand leisure time of the Japanese people as a result of an 
expected diffusion of "satellite" remote offices. 
  The scheme is also designed for the efficient use of natural 
resources and energy, contributing to a solution of 
environmental issues, one of the biggest global problems toward 
the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. 
  In the recommendation presented to Posts and 
Telecommunications Minister <PERSON>Katsuyuki Hikasa</PERSON>, the council called 
for the laying of a core optical-cable network linking the 
prefectural capitals by <DATE>2000</DATE>, in a first-phase project that 
would cover <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's population. 
  A second-stage network should be built by <DATE>2005</DATE> to connect 
cities with populations of over 100,000 for a population 
coverage of <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT>, the council said. 
  Nationwide hookup is set for the year of <DATE>2010</DATE> when <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 
population is expected to peak, it said. 
  Apart from the three-stage scheme, an optical cable network 
to link major public organs, like schools, libraries, hospitals 
and welfare facilities, should be built by <DATE>2000</DATE>, accompanied by 
the development of application software for use at such 
institutions, the council said. 
  "Based on the council proposal, the posts ministry will push 
for various measures to implement the program, including further 
deregulation in telecom fields and an ample amount of budgetary 
allocation by the <ORGANIZATION>Finance Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, an official at the posts 
ministry told a press conference. 
  <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s proposal has been apparently prompted by "the 
information superhighway scheme" unveiled earlier by the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION>. 
  As under the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scheme, the Japanese project is expected 
to 
provide a wide range of multimedia services in the next century, 
which the council says would make Japanese people's livelihood 
"dramatically more comfortable." 
  As possible multimedia services under the scheme, the 
council 
cited remote medical checking, video-on-demand services, home 
shopping, electronic libraries, virtual reality leisure parks, 
interactive access to administrative information and remote 
education services. 
  The proposed optical-fiber network is projected to cost <MONEY>53 
trillion yen</MONEY> when the single-star (SS) system, the most 
sophisticated optical cable networking method, is used at 
subscribing companies and households, the council said. 
  The cost would be lower at <MONEY>33 trillion yen</MONEY> if networking is 
done with a combination of the SS system and a less 
sophisticated system, a more practical approach in view of 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s current technological level. 
  The council said the private sector should play a key role 
in 
developing related application software. But government support 
is also necessary in the inititial stage of networking that 
focuses on infrastructure improvement. 
  The task of laying the core part of the fiber cable network 
should be basically entrusted to either telecommunications 
companies like <ORGANIZATION>Nippon Telegraph and Telephone Corp.</ORGANIZATION> (NTT) or 
cable television operators, the council said. 
  The posts ministry official avoided stating a specific role 
by <ORGANIZATION>NTT</ORGANIZATION> in the fiber project, noting that further discussion 
needs to be conducted to decide who should take charge of the 
task. 
  "To create a business environment that maximizes competition 
among various sectors would eventually serve the interest of 
general users," the council said. 
  It said interest-free loans and tax incentives should be 
provided to entities participating in costly infrastructure 
improvement projects in the scheme. 
  The optical-fiber network scheme is most likely to produce 
various social, legal and security problems that the Japanese 
people have rarely experienced in the past -- those uniquely 
inherent in the nature of multimedia services. 
  Among them are an unintended violation of individual privacy 
and intellectual property rights. The legal framework should be 
upgraded to cope with these problems, the council said. 
  The council also called for the standardization of telecom 
  The concept of "universal services" should be introduced for 
the new telecom scheme, in which services are equally offered 
across the nation at reasonable prices, the council said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-47957 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas014_a_94028" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-014 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 January 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Consumption Tax May Reappear as `Welfare Tax' </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW2001040494 Tokyo KYODO in English 0323 GMT 20 Jan 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2001040494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> KYODO -- The consumption tax may be 
renamed the "welfare tax" in a bid to win public support for 
raising it, government sources said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [20 <DATE>January</DATE>]. 
  The issue has been deliberated within government circles for 
some time, the sources said. 
  The governing coalition has been under pressure to clarify 
the purpose of the tax in light of the rapid aging of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s 
population, they said. 
  It is also being argued that a name change could help win 
support for raising the current rate from <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT>, a move that 
is strongly opposed by the <ORGANIZATION>Social Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> [of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>], 
the largest party in Prime Minister <PERSON>Morihiro Hosokawa</PERSON>'s 
coalition government. 
  The idea has met with criticism from some people engaged in 
various welfare programs, who fear that the amount of tax 
collected under that name might be regarded as a ceiling for 
welfare spending. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-22602 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptep007___94012" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEP-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Epidemiology 

<DATE1>  11 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> JAPAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Tokyo, U.S. To Provide 12 Billion Dollars To Fight AIDS </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0302114594 Tokyo KYODO in English 1124 GMT 3 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0302114594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 3</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 
on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [3 <DATE>February</DATE>] agreed to provide a total of <MONEY>12 billion 
dollars</MONEY> from now until the year <DATE>2000</DATE> for projects aimed at 
curbing the spread of AIDS and bringing the global population 
growth under control, Japanese officials said. 
  The agreement emerged from the bilateral "framework" trade 
negotiations under way in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, and will be officially 
announced after the meeting between Prime Minister <PERSON>Morihiro 
Hosokawa</PERSON> and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON> slated for <DATE>February 11</DATE> 
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
  Under the scheme, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> will give <MONEY>3 billion dollars</MONEY> and the 
<ORGANIZATION>U.S.</ORGANIZATION> <MONEY>9 billion dollars</MONEY> over the seven years. 
  The sums compare with <MONEY>70 million dollars</MONEY> in annual financial 
aid extended by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> for such purposes and <MONEY>600 million dollars</MONEY> 
by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
  The sharply boosted aid will be used to try to find an AIDS 
cure, supply developing nations with condoms, and enlighten 
people there about the disease. 
  The money will also finance projects designed to spread 
knowledge of family planning and help poor countries compile 
more reliable population statistics. 
  According to data by the <ORGANIZATION>World Health Organization</ORGANIZATION> (WHO), 
the 
world's HIV carriers number 14 million at present and are 
projected to rise to 30-40 million by the year <DATE>2000</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-27987 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas109_a_94011" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-109 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  7 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Solicits APEC Membership Support </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Solicits APEC Membership Support </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0706065094 Tokyo KYODO in English 0624 GMT 7 Jun 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0706065094 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 7</DATE> KYODO -- Peruvian President <PERSON>Alberto 
Fujimori</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> solicited <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s continued support for his 
country's bid to become a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Asia-Pacific Economic 
Cooperation</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION>) forum. 
  <PERSON>Fujimori</PERSON>, who arrived in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for a four-day 
unofficial visit, made the call in a meeting with former Prime 
Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON>, aides to the Japanese political leader 
said. 
  Kaifu was quoted as saying that <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION>, established in 
<DATE>November 
1989</DATE> as a loose consultative body, should be open in nature. He 
offered to convey <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION>'s desire to concerned parties. 
  <ORGANIZATION>APEC</ORGANIZATION>, which currently has 17 members representing about <PERCENT>40 
percent</PERCENT> of the world's population, agreed last <DATE>November</DATE> to 
freeze new membership for three years. 
  It links <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Brunei</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Malaysia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Papua New Guinea</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Singapore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> 
and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Chile</LOCATION> will be made a full member at an 
informal summit in <DATE>November</DATE>. 
  While <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> has urged fellow members to allow <LOCATION>Peru</LOCATION> to 
participate in the forum's working group meetings, no consensus 
has been reached on the matter. 
  Fujimori is due to leave <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> for <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> for an official 
visit. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-22661 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jptep007___94071" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEP-94-004 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Epidemiology 

<DATE1>  11 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL </F>
<H3> <TI>   Paris Plans AIDS Meeting To Tackle Epidemic at Political Level </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0803102794 Tokyo KYODO in English 1003 GMT 8 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0803102794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 8</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> will host a 
17-nation AIDS summit in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>November</DATE> because the AIDS 
epidemic is now too serious to leave to medical experts alone, 
an emissary for the French health minister said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [8 
<DATE>March</DATE>] in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. 
  Jean <PERSON>Francois Girard</PERSON>, director general of health in the 
<ORGANIZATION>French Ministry of Social Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, Health and <LOCATION>City</LOCATION>, told a news 
conference that the one-day summit will bring together heads of 
at least 17 nations to consider ways to fight the AIDS epidemic 
on a global level. 
  "Till now, health problems have been treated by doctors, but 
AIDS is too serious to be treated only by doctors," <PERSON>Girard</PERSON> said. 
  "For the first time in the history of the world, heads of 
government will be considering a health problem. It will be a 
historic turning point." 
  Girard visited the <ORGANIZATION>Health and Welfare Ministry</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> and 
the <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to explain the goals and solicit 
participation. 
  He said the 17 countries to be invited include those whose 
contribution to the international fight against AIDS is the 
greatest. Among them are <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>, the Scandinavian countries and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. 
  He said <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> Secretary General Butrus Butrus-Ghali 
has indicated he would like to attend. 
the <ORGANIZATION>World Health Organization</ORGANIZATION> (WHO), the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Education</ORGANIZATION>, 
Children</ORGANIZATION>'s Fund (<ORGANIZATION>UNICEF</ORGANIZATION>), the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Fund</ORGANIZATION> for Population 
Activities (<ORGANIZATION>UNFPA</ORGANIZATION>) and the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> will have input into 
planning the summit agenda. 
  He said experts in many other AIDS-affected countries who 
are 
not invited will be consulted at the preparatory stage. 
  French Prime Minister <PERSON>Edouard Balladur</PERSON> will chair the 
summit, 
for which no final date has been set. 
  The gathering was originally scheduled for <DATE>June</DATE>, but <PERSON>Girard</PERSON> 
said it was postponed because many heads of state could not come 
in <DATE>June</DATE> and because <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> will host an international meeting of 
AIDS experts, including doctors, researchers, and AIDS 
sufferers, in <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION> in <DATE>August</DATE>. 
  About 10,000 people from more than 140 countries, including 
some 1,000 AIDS patients and carriers of the AIDS-causing human 
immunodeficiency virus, are expected to attend the <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION> 
meeting. 
  <PERSON>Girard</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> AIDS summit will be able to capitalize 
on decisions made at the <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION> conference. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-29134 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas031_a_94010" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-031 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  15 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   More Reports on U.S. Summit Results, Reaction </TI></H3>
<H4>   Cooperation Agreement in 15 Fields </H4>
<F P=102> OW1202023594 Tokyo KYODO in English 1121 GMT 11 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW1202023594 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> agreed <DATE>Friday</DATE> [11 <DATE>February</DATE>] to cooperate on global issues 
in 15 fields, including AIDS and population problems, saving the 
bilateral framework talks from ending in a complete flunk. The 
two governments agreed on the global cooperation, one of three 
pillars in the trade framework negotiations along with 
macroeconomic and microeconomic areas, at the summit talks 
between Japanese Prime Minister <PERSON>Morihiro Hosokawa</PERSON> and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
President <PERSON>Bill Clinton</PERSON>. 
  Under the accord, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> together will offer <MONEY>12 
billion dollars</MONEY> over seven years to tackle issues involving AIDS 
and population problems. Of the total amount, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is to 
disburse <MONEY>9 billion dollars</MONEY> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> will offer <MONEY>3 billion 
dollars</MONEY>. 
  The two countries will also cooperate in developing 
environmental technologies and developing human resources. 
  <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> failed to strike a deal on the other 
areas of the framework talks to slash <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s huge trade surplus 
and boost the share of imports in its markets. The two sides 
remain deadlocked over the definition of "objective criteria" in 
accessing foreign access to Japanese markets such as autos and 
auto parts, insurance and government procurement of 
telecommunications and medical equipment. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-6843 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas055_a_94020" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-055 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  20 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   New Candidates Challenge Incumbent in Yokohama </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW2003153494 Tokyo KYODO in English 1009 GMT 20 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2003153494 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 20</DATE> KYODO -- Two new faces <DATE>Sunday</DATE> 
[20 <DATE>March</DATE>] filed as candidates to challenge the incumbent in the 
<DATE>April 3</DATE> mayoral election in <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s second most 
populous city. 
  The three men who filed candidacy papers were incumbent 
mayor 
<PERSON>Hidenobu Takahide</PERSON>, 64, and challengers <PERSON>Toshihiko Izu</PERSON>, 67, and 
<ORGANIZATION>Takashi Nomura</ORGANIZATION>, 40. 
  All three are independents. 
  <PERSON>Takahide</PERSON>, who is seeking a second four-year term of office, 
has gained the backing of the <ORGANIZATION>Liberal Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, the 
Social Democratic Party, <LOCATION>Komeito</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Shinseito</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Japan Renewal 
Party</ORGANIZATION>) and the Democratic Socialist Party. 
  Izu, a professor emeritus at <ORGANIZATION>Yokohama City University</ORGANIZATION>, is 
backed by the Japanese Communist Party, while <ORGANIZATION>Nomura</ORGANIZATION>, a former 
<ORGANIZATION>Home Affairs Ministry</ORGANIZATION> bureaucrat, has garnered support from new 
party Sakigake and the <ORGANIZATION>United Social Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
  <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, the largest international port city in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, has 
a 
population of 3.3 million, ranking second after <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> which has 
a population of more than eight million. 
  The challengers have accused <PERSON>Takahide</PERSON> of having received a 
huge amount of election campaign funds from general contractors. 
Takahide denies the allegation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-30067 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas121_a_94014" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-121 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  23 Jun 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Lower House Approves Representation Bill </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Lower House Approves Representation Bill </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2306044994 Tokyo KYODO in English 0403 GMT 23 June 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2306044994 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> of Representatives overwhelmingly 
approved a bill <DATE>Thursday</DATE> [23 <DATE>June</DATE>] to reduce the current 6.5 to 
1 disparity in the weight of a vote in various <ORGANIZATION>House of 
Councillors</ORGANIZATION> constituencies to 5 to 1. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>House of Councillors</ORGANIZATION> approved the bill <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
  The amendment bill cleared the lower chamber's plenary 
session with the backing of almost all political parties and 
parliamentary groups except the <ORGANIZATION>Japanese Communist Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
  An upper house poll in the <DATE>summer of 1995</DATE> will be held under 
the new electoral system. 
  The bill adds one seat to each of four underrepresented 
upper 
chamber constituencies in <LOCATION>Miyagi</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Saitama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kanagawa</LOCATION> and Gifu 
prefectures, while taking away two seats from the 
overrepresented Hokkaido electorate and one each from the 
prefectures of <LOCATION>Hyogo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Fukuoka</LOCATION>, legislators said. 
  The bill alleviates the current situation under which some 
relatively sparsely populated constituencies have more 
representation in the upper house than more densely populated 
constituencies, mainly in or near urban areas. 
  The amendment was submitted after a <DATE>1993</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Osaka High Court</ORGANIZATION> 
ruling that the current maximum disparity of 6.48 to 1 violates 
the constitutional principle of equality for all under the law, 
the legislators said. 
  The amendment would reduce the maximum disparity to 4.81 to 
1, they said. 
  The bill was initially introduced in the upper chamber under 
the cosponsorship of the <ORGANIZATION>Liberal Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Social 
Democratic Party</ORGANIZATION> [of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>], Komeito [Clean Government Party], 
the <ORGANIZATION>Niin Club</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Shin Ryokufu Kai</ORGANIZATION> -- a parliamentary group 
comprising the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Socialist Party</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Japan New Party</ORGANIZATION>, 
<ORGANIZATION>Shinseito</ORGANIZATION> [<ORGANIZATION>Japan Renewal Party</ORGANIZATION>] and the <ORGANIZATION>Democratic Reform Party</ORGANIZATION>. 
  Goken Liberal No Kai, a five-legislator group of the upper 
chamber, balked at the bill, saying it is not enough to 
accomplish fairness in voting power. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-5237 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas068_a_94022" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-068 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   Kazakh President Addresses National Press Club </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Kazakh President Addresses National Press Club </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0804095794 Tokyo KYODO in English 0934 GMT 8 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0804095794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 8</DATE> KYODO -- Kazakh President <PERSON>Nursultan 
Nazarbayev</PERSON> warned <DATE>Friday</DATE> [8 <DATE>April</DATE>] that some leading Russian 
politicians' attempts to stir up nationalistic sentiments among 
Russians residing in <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION> and other former Soviet 
republics may trigger an exodus of refugees. 
  "If Russians, Ukrainians and Germans residing in <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION> 
took Russian politicians' campaigns at face value and opted to 
move to <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> or other areas, they would plunge into a more 
severe situation than now," <PERSON>Nazarbayev</PERSON> said. 
  "Although such an exodus has not yet begun, my biggest 
anxiety comes from this issue," <PERSON>Nazarbayev</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>Japan 
National Press Club</ORGANIZATION> on the final day of his four-day visit to 
<LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
  At present, some 5 million Russians, or more than a quarter 
of <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION>'s population, reside in the country which has a 
population of 17 million. Germans and Ukrainians each account 
for some <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of the populace. Under the 19-century 
colonial policy of <LOCATION>Czarist Russia</LOCATION>, Russians were ordered to move 
to the central Asian country. 
  Nazarbayev accused Russian Foreign Minister <PERSON>Andrey Kozyrev</PERSON> 
and other politicians of having tried to rekindle Russian 
nationalist sentiments in a bid to lure Russian voters during 
<DATE>1993</DATE> parliamentary election campaigns. 
  Kozyrev said <DATE>last November 22</DATE> -- three weeks before the 
parliamentary vote -- that <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> would "protect the Russian 
population and <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>'s interests in a tough manner, wherever it 
is needed and whoever is concerned, even if it (concerns) our 
friends." 
  "The treatment of official Russian representatives, 
servicemen and our compatriots on the territory of any state, be 
it near or far abroad, is the litmus paper on which good 
neighborly relations with any state will be tested," <PERSON>Kozyrev</PERSON> 
said. 
  <PERSON>Nazarbayev</PERSON> told the press conference, "these Russian 
politicians tried to draw strength from the theme of the 
interests of '<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>' in view of the <DATE>December 11</DATE> parliamentary 
election." 
  <PERSON>Nazarbayev</PERSON> said there is no rationale for any calls for an 
exodus of Russians from <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION>, as the <ORGANIZATION>Kazakh Government</ORGANIZATION> has 
taken a "policy of providing free plots of land to enable all 
residents to build homes and plow fields," whatever ethnic group 
they may belong to. 
  Nazarbayev refused to comment on press reports that <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> 
and the former <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> bought <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> security secrets from 
alleged <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Central Intelligence Agency</ORGANIZATION> turncoat <PERSON>Aldrich Ames</PERSON> 
over the past eight years for <MONEY>2.5 million dollars</MONEY>. 
  Asked about <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> congressional arguments calling for a halt 
to aid to <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION> following the reported espionage case, 
<PERSON>Nazarbayev</PERSON> said, "I am not in a position to give advice to other 
countries on their aid policy to <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>." 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-4583 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas039_a_94039" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-039 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  28 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NORTHEAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> Japan </F>
<H3> <TI>   70 Percent of New Districts Follow Kaifu Plan </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW2602080794 Tokyo KYODO in English 0754 GMT 26 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2602080794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <DATE>Feb. 26</DATE> KYODO -- <PERCENT>Seventy percent</PERCENT> of 300 
single- seat constituencies being set up under new political 
reform bills will be redrawn according to a <DATE>1991</DATE> plan presented 
to then Prime Minister <PERSON>Toshiki Kaifu</PERSON>, according to a survey 
released <DATE>Saturday</DATE> [26 <DATE>February</DATE>]. 
  A KYODO NEWS SERVICE survey of politicians and people 
concerned in 47 prefectures found that more than 200 new 
single-seat districts will be invented according to the draft 
plan. 
  Only 60 to 70 districts, mostly in the densely populated 
Kanto and Kinki regions, will be newly created under legal 
procedures after the expected passage of an amendment of the 
package of political reform bills in early <DATE>March</DATE>. 
  The political reform bills, which were approved in <DATE>January</DATE> 
after a long battle in the Diet, calls for replacing the present 
511 multiseat constituencies for the lower house with a mix of 
300 single-seat constituencies and 200 proportional 
representation seats. 
  In about 45 new single-seat constituencies, the ruling 
coalition parties must single out their candidates since they 
have more than one incumbent lower house member in corresponding 
present multiseat districts. 
  The opposition <ORGANIZATION>LDP</ORGANIZATION>, which was ousted from power last <DATE>August</DATE> 
hosokawa, must make similar adjustments of their candidates in 
about 35 single-seat districts. 
  Totally new districts in which there are virtually no 
"incumbent" members will come into existence as well, with the 
number of such districts reaching more than 90 for the ruling 
parties and nearly 120 for the <ORGANIZATION>LDP</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The <ORGANIZATION>8th Election System Council</ORGANIZATION>, a government advisory 
council, submitted the draft plan for redrawing electoral 
districts for the lower house in <DATE>June 1991</DATE> to <LOCATION>Kaifu</LOCATION>, then prime 
minister and <ORGANIZATION>LDP</ORGANIZATION> president. 
  In drawing up the 300 single-seat constituencies, the 
council 
set 549,000 as an upper limit for the population of a voting 
district and 274,000 as a lower limit. 
  The population of six of the proposed constituencies will be 
allowed to remain below 274,000 as exceptions. 
  On the council's plan, many of those surveyed complained 
that 
it ignores regional history and geographical conditions, but 
some said another plan would cause problems such as 
contradiction of the weight of vote per voter. 
  Kaifu and his <ORGANIZATION>LDP</ORGANIZATION> successor <PERSON>Kiichi Miyazawa</PERSON> were dislodged 
from power due to their failure to achieve political reform. 
  Kaifu, speaking to the <ORGANIZATION>LDP</ORGANIZATION>'s local convention in <LOCATION>Nagoya</LOCATION>, 
central <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Saturday</DATE> politicians should not intervene in 
redrawing the single-seat districts. 
  The government "should redraw (the electoral districts) 
fairly by entrusting the task with a third organization," he 
said. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-45613 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten015___94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-015 </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  24 May 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> EAST ASIA </F>
<F P=101> JAPAN </F>
<H3> <TI>   Tokyo, Washington To Cooperate on Polio, AIDS, Environment </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Tokyo, Washington To Cooperate on Polio, AIDS, Environment </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW2505000694 Tokyo KYODO in English 2309 GMT 24 May 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW2505000694 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 24</DATE> KYODO -- <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> vowed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> [24 May] to create a joint health program 
for children to stamp out polio from the face of the world by 
the year <DATE>2000</DATE>. 
  "We believe (this goal) is technically feasible," said 
<ORGANIZATION>Undersecretary of State for Global Affairs Timothy Wirth</ORGANIZATION> in 
announcing the joint program. 
  The program is a new "common agenda" initiative the two 
countries created <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as part of a year-old bilateral accord 
to promote cooperation on global social and environmental issues. 
  <PERSON>Wirth</PERSON> said the two countries also agreed to pool their aid 
resources and launch a second child health initiative to develop 
an inexpensive, "one-fits-all" children's vaccine to fight 
disease in developing countries. 
  In addition, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> agreed to expand 
their "common agenda" plan on narcotics control, the protection 
of coral reefs, and the expansion of global changes research in 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>, the two sides said in a statement 
released after a general meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-Japan Common Agenda 
for Global Cooperation</ORGANIZATION>. 
  The "common agenda" program is the least controversial part 
of a highly contentious framework agreement the two countries 
concluded in <DATE>July last year</DATE> to define a "new economic 
  By stepping up bilateral cooperation on global 
social-economic issues while fighting on the trade front, the 
two countries have shown that "you can walk and chew gum at the 
same time," <PERSON>Wirth</PERSON> said. 
  The two countries have not yet worked out details of their 
new child health program, but <PERSON>Wirth</PERSON> said it involves bilateral 
cooperation in research and development, plus production and 
distribution of children's vaccines for use in developing 
countries. 
  "We believe that aggressive cooperation between the two 
countries...can lead to the eradication of polio worldwide by 
the year <DATE>2000</DATE>," <PERSON>Wirth</PERSON> said. 
  Under the "common agenda" program, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> have already agreed to pool their resources to control 
global population growth, battle the AIDS epidemic in developing 
countries and promote worldwide environmental projects. 
  A new environmental program approved <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> calls for 
providing financial aid to the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> to build a 
biodiversity training site at <LOCATION>Subic Bay</LOCATION> to protect lowland rain 
forests. 
  The two countries also pledged to finance a community 
resource conservation and development program in <LOCATION>Papua New 
Guinea</LOCATION> aimed at encouraging tribal clans to preserve endangered 
forests by promoting income alternatives. 
  On the AIDS front, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> agreed to put 
six countries -- the <LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ghana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> -- on their "priority" lists for a joint U.S.-Japan 
AIDS-fighting assistance program. 
  The two countries have so far pledged to provide up to <MONEY>12 
billion dollars</MONEY> by the year <DATE>2000</DATE> to fight AIDS and control 
exploding population growth in the developing world. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-2020 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi043_a_94003" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-043 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> General </F>
<H3> <TI>   Li Peng Urges Regional Cooperation in Family Planning </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  HK0403080294 Beijing CHINA DAILY in English 4 Mar 94 p 1 </F>
<F P=103> HK0403080294 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing CHINA DAILY </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [By staff reporter <PERSON>Ma Chenguang</PERSON>: "Asian Family Planning </F>
Urged--Conference Pushes More Regional Cooperation"] 
  [Text] Premier <PERSON>Li Peng</PERSON> yesterday called for greater 
regional cooperation to stem the population tide sweeping across 
<LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> -- home to <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the world's populace. 
  He pledged that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will continue its efforts at 
population 
control by sticking to its family planing policy; those efforts 
help develop the economy and improve people's daily lives. 
  And other Asian nations should formulate their own 
strategies. But their plans need to be developed according to 
individual characteristics, he said in a written statement to an 
Asian Pacific population seminar. 
  The question of population is a question of development in 
essence, the Premier added, and can only be tackled at its root 
according to each country's natural conditions, tradition and 
economic level. 
  The 10th Asian Parliamentarians Meeting on <ORGANIZATION>Population and 
Development</ORGANIZATION> is seeking solutions to Asian population problems. 
  More than 50 parliamentarians and scholars from 17 nations 
were drawn to the two-day seminar, organized by the <ORGANIZATION>Asian 
Population and Development Association</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>APDA</ORGANIZATION>) based in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and 
the Education, Science, Culture and <ORGANIZATION>Public Health Committee</ORGANIZATION> 
(ESCPH) of the <ORGANIZATION>National People's Congress</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. At the 
opening of the meeting, <ORGANIZATION>APDA</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Fukusaburo Maeda</PERSON> said 
controlling <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION>'s population is a decisive global issue. Its 
populace is expected to top 3.34 billion people this year. 
  It has six of the 10 most populated countries in the world: 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>. 
  Maeda praised <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s efforts to contain its birth rate, an 
"unmatched success in population policy while proceeding with 
rapid economic growth." 
  The population by the end of last year was <MONEY>1.18 billion</MONEY>, 
according to the newly published statistics. 
  The birth rate fell from 33.43 per thousand in <DATE>1970</DATE> -- 
before 
family planning -- to 18.09 in <DATE>1993</DATE>. And natural population 
growth has continued its <DATE>fall</DATE>, from 14.55 per thousand in <DATE>1981</DATE> 
down to last years 11.45. 
  Without the policy 15 million more babies would have been 
born over the past five years. 
  <PERSON>Maeda</PERSON> said quick solutions to overpopulation in <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> would 
help ensure domestic stability. 
  Analysts recommended controlling the birth rate eradicating 
poverty, creating sufficient food and job opportunities, 
improving education standards, literacy rates and living 
conditions. 
  Chinese ESCPH Chairman <PERSON>Zhao Dongwan</PERSON> said that the nation's 
ultimate goal is to educate and explain to the people why family 
planning is so important. That way, he said, future generations 
will carry on the practice on their own. 
  He admitted that obstacles to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s development and 
population quality still exist, including economic and social 
  <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, by sharing problems of unbalanced population problems 
and socio-economic development with other developing Asian 
countries, needs to strengthen cooperations with them to further 
contain its expansion of population. 
  Also yesterday, <ORGANIZATION>NPC Standing Committee</ORGANIZATION> Chairman <PERSON>Qiao Shi</PERSON>, 
parliamentary leader, met with the Asia-Pacific parliamentarians 
and scholars at the <PERSON>Great Hall</PERSON> of the People. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-5204 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "dreas043aa_94002" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-EAS-94-043 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  4 March 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<H3> <TI>   Asia-Pacific Environmental Meeting Scheduled </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0403075794 Tokyo KYODO in English 0738 GMT 4 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0403075794 </F>
<F P=104>  Tokyo KYODO </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 
