<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06116166 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06116166 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: (Peter Sellers as Dr. Strangelove)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MENTAL; DISEASE; UNUSUAL; HUMAN; VIOLENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  No one who has seen the film classic "Dr. Strangelove" will forget the
inspired lunacy when the arm of a character played by Peter Sellers takes on a
life of its own, flipping Nazi salutes and attempting to strangle the
wheelchair-bound defense adviser while Sellers struggles to control the
demented digits with his other hand.;    As far-fetched as that portrayal may
seem, there is apparently more than a grain of truth in it.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BIZARRE DISORDER CAN GET OUT OF HAND
FREEWHEELING FINGERS TURN INTO A NUISANCE
-- OR A DANGER  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     As many as several thousand Americans may suffer from a little-known
neurological disorder called "alien hand syndrome," in which their left hands
literally don't know what their right hands are doing, said neurologist
<PERSON>Rachelle Doody</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Baylor University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. Doody discussed the syndrome
least severe forms of the syndrome, one of the patient's hands may flop about
aimlessly.;    In more severe cases, it may try to do the same things the
opposite hand is doing or attempt to counter them. In the worst cases, the
hand may become aggressive, pinching, slapping or punching the patient -- and
in at least one recorded case even trying to strangle its owner.;    The
syndrome appears to be caused by damage to certain areas of the brain and is
often temporary, disappearing a few months after the damage occurs. It can be
reproduced in animals by damaging the same areas of the brain.;    There is no
treatment for the syndrome, but those animal studies suggest that it
eventually may be possible to develop surgical techniques to minimize the
symptoms, <ORGANIZATION>Doody</ORGANIZATION> said.;    The disorder can be frightening for patients, said
neurologist <PERSON>Ramone Leiguarda</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Neurological Research</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION>. Leiguarda recounted a written description of the
disorder by what he termed a "typical patient.";    "I was traveling on a
bus," the patient wrote, "when I noticed a hand approaching me from the right
from behind and trying to catch me. After grasping my trouser leg, the hand
would not release it. At first I thought somebody was robbing me, but then I
realized it was my own right hand. . . . I couldn't sleep at all that night
because I was terrified my abnormal hand would assault me while I was
sleeping.";    Usually the symptoms are not so dramatic, but they are
disconcerting nonetheless. In all cases, <ORGANIZATION>Doody</ORGANIZATION> said, the affected limb feels
foreign or alien to the patient, as though it is not part of the same body.;  
 Often, the affected hand will mirror what the normal hand is doing.;    "If
the right hand goes to do something, the left hand tries to beat it," <PERSON>Doody</PERSON>
said. This can make it difficult, for example, to dial a telephone.;    But
more often, the affected hand will try to do the opposite of what the normal
hand is doing, <PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> said.;    "If a person is trying to button a shirt
with one hand, the other hand will follow along and undo the buttons," he
said. "If one hand opens a book, the other will shut it. If one hand pulls up
trousers, the other will pull them down.";    Neurologists are not sure of the
precise mechanism by which the phenomenon operates, but it can be caused by
strokes, degenerative diseases or anything that causes damage to certain areas
of the brain, especially the thalamus, which coordinates sensory perceptions,
and the corpus callosum, which connects the two spheres of the brain.;   
<PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> said the syndrome is a frequent complication when surgery is
performed on the corpus callosum to alleviate severe epileptic symptoms.;   
Usually the phenomenon disappears in a few weeks to a few months after the
brain reorganizes itself to bypass the damage, <PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> said. "Usually, but
not always," he added.;    <ORGANIZATION>Doody</ORGANIZATION> has never seen "<PERSON>Dr. Strangelove</PERSON>," and
<PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> has not heard of it. But <PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> noted that he had been searching
through history and mythology without success to find a name for the disorder.
"Perhaps the 'Strangelove Syndrome' is not such a bad name," he mused.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910425  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  681  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 25, 1991
00116166,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06116227 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06116227 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; A LIFE OF ITS OWN -- Peter Sellers
played a character in 'Dr. Strangelove' whose arm refused to be tamed of its
Nazi salutes and murderous attacks on the defense adviser. Now, it appears
that the condition has some truth to it.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MENTAL; DISEASE; UNUSUAL; HUMAN; VIOLENCE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  No one who has seen the film classic "Dr. Strangelove" will forget the
inspired lunacy when the arm of a character played by Peter Sellers takes on a
life of its own, flipping Nazi salutes and attempting to strangle the
wheelchair-bound defense adviser while Sellers struggles to control the
demented digits with his other hand.;    As far-fetched as that portrayal may
seem, there is apparently more than a grain of truth in it.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BIZARRE DISORDER AFFLICTS HANDS
'DR. STRANGELOVE' CONDITION NO JOKE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     As many as several thousand Americans may suffer from a little-known
neurological disorder called "alien hand syndrome," in which their left hands
literally don't know what their right hands are doing, said neurologist
<PERSON>Rachelle Doody</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Baylor University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. Doody discussed the syndrome
least severe forms of the syndrome, one of the patient's hands may flop about
aimlessly.;    In more severe cases, it may try to do the same things the
opposite hand is doing or attempt to counter them. In the worst cases, the
hand may become aggressive, pinching, slapping or punching the patient -- and
in at least one recorded case even trying to strangle its owner.;    The
syndrome appears to be caused by damage to certain areas of the brain and is
often temporary, disappearing a few months after the damage occurs. It can be
reproduced in animals by damaging the same areas of the brain.;    There is no
treatment for the syndrome, but those animal studies suggest that it
eventually may be possible to develop surgical techniques to minimize the
symptoms, <ORGANIZATION>Doody</ORGANIZATION> said.;    The disorder can be frightening for patients, said
neurologist <PERSON>Ramone Leiguarda</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Neurological Research</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Buenos Aires</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Argentina.</LOCATION>;    Usually the symptoms are not so dramatic, but
they are disconcerting nonetheless. In all cases, <ORGANIZATION>Doody</ORGANIZATION> said, the affected
limb feels foreign or alien to the patient, as though it is not part of the
same body.;    Often, the affected hand will mirror what the normal hand is
doing.;    "If the right hand goes to do something, the left hand tries to
beat it," <PERSON>Doody</PERSON> said. This can make it difficult, for example, to dial a
telephone.;    But more often, the affected hand will try to do the opposite
of what the normal hand is doing, <PERSON>Leiguarda</PERSON> said.;    "If a person is trying
to button a shirt with one hand, the other hand will follow along and undo the
buttons," he said. "If one hand opens a book, the other will shut it. If one
hand pulls up trousers, the other will pull them down.";    Neurologists are
not sure of the precise mechanism by which the phenomenon operates, but it can
be caused by strokes, degenerative diseases or anything that causes damage to
certain areas of the brain, especially the thalamus, which coordinates sensory
perceptions, and the corpus callosum, which connects the two spheres of the
brain.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910425  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  531  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday April 25, 1991
00116227,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910417-0170
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910417-0170.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Law:
   Justices Tighten
   Rules for Appeals
   From Death Row
   ----
   By Stephen Wermiel
</HL>
<DATE>
04/17/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B8
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<NS>
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES, HEARINGS, RULINGS, LEGISLATION (LAW)
</NS>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Supreme Court made it tougher for
convicted criminals, especially those on death row, to file
repeated challenges to the constitutionality of their
convictions.
   By a 6-3 vote, the high court ruled that a Georgia inmate,
Warren McCleskey, convicted in 1978 of a murder the same
year, abused the legal process known as habeas corpus by
filing a second round of legal challenges to his conviction.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   A petition for habeas corpus is a civil action by a state
or federal prisoner normally filed after the prisoner has
been convicted and has had that conviction upheld on appeal.
The habeas corpus petition goes beyond asserting that
evidence didn't support a conviction and attacks the
constitutionality of any number of police, lawyer or judicial
practices that allegedly violated the defendant's rights.
   Conservatives on the court, in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and in the
executive branch have complained for years that prisoners and
their lawyers are dragging out death sentences by filing a
succession of habeas corpus petitions that rehash old issues
or raise new ones that could have been raised earlier. Both
the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration and some lawmakers have proposed
legislation to limit the number of habeas petitions and the
length of time for filing them in death penalty cases.
   Yesterday, in a decision written by Justice <PERSON>Anthony
Kennedy</PERSON>, the court set a legal standard that will make it
significantly harder for prisoners to file more than one
petition for habeas corpus. The decision prompted a strong
dissent by Justice <PERSON>Thurgood Marshall</PERSON>, joined by Justices
<PERSON>Harry Blackmun</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Stevens</PERSON>.
   The high court ruled that when a prisoner files a second
habeas corpus petition in federal court, the prosecutor must
document which legal claims are being raised for the first
time. The prisoner must then provide good reasons why the
issues, such as interference by law enforcement officers or
unavailability of factual or legal information, weren't
raised in the first petition. The prisoners also must show
that the case was actually prejudiced by the alleged
constitutional violations.
   In <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s case, rather than allowing a lower federal
court to apply this new standard, the court ruled that
<PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s second petition was an abuse of habeas corpus.
(<ORGANIZATION>McCleskey vs. Zant</ORGANIZATION>)
                                                                                                       

   Attorney's Fees
                                                                                                       

   By a 9-0 vote, the justices ruled that a lawyer who
represents himself in a civil rights case can't take
advantage of the federal law that allows successful parties
in civil rights lawsuits to collect their attorneys fees from
the losers. The decision, written by <PERSON>Justice Stevens</PERSON>, was a
defeat for a lawyer who successfully challenged a <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>
law that kept his name off the <DATE>1980</DATE> Democratic presidential
primary ballot. (Kay vs. Ehrler)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910422-0168
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910422-0168.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Law -- Washington Docket:
   Supreme Court Conservatives Play Role
   Of Legislators on Death Penalty Issue
   ----
   By Stephen Wermiel
</HL>
<DATE>
04/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B5A
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<NS>
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES, HEARINGS, RULINGS, LEGISLATION (LAW)
</NS>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
EXECUTIVE (EXE)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- It has long been a hallmark of Supreme Court
conservatives to complain that their liberal colleagues are
acting more like legislators passing laws than justices
interpreting them.
   Last week, the roles were reversed. Apparently impatient
with the slow pace of congressional efforts to truncate the
system of appeals in death-penalty cases, the court's
conservative majority decided not to wait any longer and did
it themselves.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   This departure from the traditional conservative approach
was vividly highlighted when the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION>,
just two days after the court's ruling, held its first
hearing of the year on proposed crime legislation. Among the
proposals by the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration is one that would do
what the court in effect has already donelimit the number of
death-penalty appeals.
   The controversy is over the centuries-old system of
federal habeas corpus, a civil lawsuit generally filed by a
prison inmate who has been convicted and who has had his
conviction upheld on appeal. A state prisoner files a habeas
corpus petition first in state court and then federal court
to argue that his constitutional rights were violated by
police or prosecutors or trial judges.
   Conservatives, led by <ORGANIZATION>Chief Justice Rehnquist</ORGANIZATION> on the court
have long maintained that in deathpenalty cases, the habeas
corpus system has been badly abused by prisoners and their
lawyers who file one petition after another, raising new and
old legal issues, and delaying executions for years.
report of a task force appointed by Chief Justice <PERSON>Rehnquist</PERSON>
and headed by retired <ORGANIZATION>Justice Lewis Powell</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> report recommended time limits on filing habeas
corpus petitions and would have made it difficult to file
more than once. It formed the basis for legislation proposed
by the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration and its allies in the last
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. Indeed, <ORGANIZATION>Chief Justice Rehnquist</ORGANIZATION> caused a stir by
sending the <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> report to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> before the <ORGANIZATION>Judicial
a chance to vote on it.
   But liberals, while acknowledging the need to clear up
post-conviction appeals, opposed the <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> recommendations
as far too restrictive of habeas corpus, which is virtually
the only way a convicted prisoner has to protect against
law-enforcement abuses. The result was that the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passed different versions of habeas corpus
legislation. Both were dropped from the final bill <DATE>last year</DATE>,
and action was put over for the new <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> this year.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, however, chose not to wait. By a 6-3
vote, the justices adopted a new legal standard for reviewing
second and subsequent habeas corpus petitions that will
virtually eliminate them, except in the most extraordinary
cases.
   "This is an attempt to do through court decision what they
haven't been able to do through legislative action," said
<PERSON>John Boger</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of North Carolina</ORGANIZATION> law professor and
experienced appellate lawyer in capital cases. <PERSON>Mr. Boger</PERSON>
represented <PERSON>Warren McCleskey</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> prisoner in the
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> case.
   The new legal standard puts the burden on the prisoner to
prove that there is good reason the habeas corpus claim in a
second petition wasn't raised in the first petition. Even
then, the prisoner must show that the trial was prejudiced by
the allegedly improper action by police and prosecutors that
is the basis of the petition.
   It is a very tough standard to meet and goes beyond what
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> prosecutors sought in their brief in the <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>
case.
   The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration apparently doesn't think it goes
far enough, however. President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s new crime bill proposes
a new standard for first-time federal habeas corpus petitions
in death cases that an <ORGANIZATION>American Bar Association</ORGANIZATION> briefing
paper says "would virtually eliminate the federal courts'
authority" to rule once the issues have been considered in
state court.
   Ironically, this proposal goes too far even for <ORGANIZATION>Chief
Justice Rehnquist</ORGANIZATION>. Although he helped ignite the present
furor for limits on habeas corpus, last <DATE>May</DATE> he criticized the
approach that is now at the heart of the president's crime
bill.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900514-0083
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900514-0083.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Ending Abuse of Death Penalty Appeals
   ----
   By Charlotte Low Allen
</HL>
<DATE>
05/14/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A18
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<GV>
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<LP>
   These days, a sentence to death is more like a sentence to
a decade on death row. The average capital case takes 106
months from crime to execution, a committee headed by former
Justice William Lewis F. Powell Jr. reported in a study
issued last September.
   The investigation of the crime, the trial and sentencing,
the direct appeal to the highest court in the state followed
by a bid for U.S. Supreme Court review -- all this accounts
for only 48 of the 106 months. Most of the remaining time
goes to fashioning, presenting and litigating petitions for
habeas corpus.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Inmates in state prisons can file their petitions in both
state and federal court. But state courts tend to give the
petitions short shrift, especially second and third petitions
after the first has been denied. The major delaying factor in
death cases, accounting for more than <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the average time
capital inmates spend on habeas corpus, is the federal writ.
There are no time deadlines for habeas corpus. The typical
"deadline" in capital cases is a looming execution date,
which usually sets off a new round of writs.
   This ability to spend years in the federal court system
long after a conviction has become final is a bonanza of the
<PERSON>Earl Warren</PERSON> era. In <DATE>1963</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> handed down two
important rulings that opened the floodgates for writ
petitions from state prisoners. The first relaxed a
once-ironclad rule that required them to exhaust state-court
remedies first. The second allowed prisoners to raise
constitutional issues piecemeal over a series of writs,
trying out some issues in the first writ, others later. The
only bar is "abuse of the writ," deliberately holding back a
claim in order to manipulate the legal system.
   Few death row prisoners are executed these days without
having made at least two trips to the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> on
federal habeas corpus writs. Few prisoners are executed,
period. Since <DATE>1976</DATE>, when the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> reapproved the
death penalty in a <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> case, there have been only 124
executions. Most of the rest of the total <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> death row
population of more than 2,327 is in court. In <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>,
prosecutors and defense lawyers are still litigating
execution cases dating from <DATE>1974</DATE>, when its new death law went
into effect.
   This has led to calls for reform in the federal habeas
system. Next week the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> is scheduled to hear two
separate and competing reform packages by <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary</ORGANIZATION>
Chairman <PERSON>Joseph Biden</PERSON> and ranking Republican <PERSON>Strom Thurmond</PERSON>.
Both packages would set time deadlines -- strict in the
<PERSON>Thurmond</PERSON> bill, less so in the <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> bill -- for filing writ
petitions. In the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION>'s courts
subcommittee plans to start hearings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> on habeas
corpus.
   But congressional reforms may not be necessary. In fact,
if <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> passes the <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> bill, the effect may well be to
sabotage the gradual course of federal habeas corpus reform
that the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> has undertaken on its own starting
when <PERSON>Warren Burger</PERSON> replaced <PERSON>Earl Warren</PERSON>, and accelerating
since <PERSON>William Rehnquist</PERSON> succeeded <PERSON>Mr. Burger</PERSON>.
   The court has removed entire congeries of legal issues,
such as those pertaining to the legality of state search
warrants from federal habeas corpus purview. In a doctrine
called "procedural default," the justices have refused to let
federal courts review questions that the defendant's lawyers
did not raise properly at earlier stages in the proceedings.
   In <DATE>February 1989</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> handed down a sleeper
decision, <PERSON>Teague</PERSON> v. Lane, holding that state prisoners could
not use federal habeas corpus as a vehicle for making new
constitutional law unless the proposed new rule (with some
exceptions), pertained to "bedrock" constitutional rights,
presumably on the order of the right to counsel. The ruling
effectively told state inmates to raise such claims in state
court on direct appeal or forget about them.
   On <DATE>March 5 of this year</DATE>, the justices issued two more
rulings extending <PERSON>Teague</PERSON> v. Lane to capital cases. Two other
death cases with <PERSON>Teague</PERSON> issues were argued in <DATE>February</DATE> and
<DATE>April</DATE> and are awaiting decision.
   The seemingly endless case of <PERSON>Robert Alton Harris</PERSON>, set for
argument <DATE>Monday</DATE> before the <ORGANIZATION>9th U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION>
is a case study in the way the current open-ended
post-conviction review system works in capital cases. <PERSON>Mr.
Harris</PERSON> was tried and sentenced to death in <DATE>1979</DATE> for the
murder of two teen-age boys at <LOCATION>Miramar Lake</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> in
<DATE>July 1978</DATE>. In <DATE>1981</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>California Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> affirmed his
conviction and sentence -- one of only four such affirmations
during the tenure of liberal <ORGANIZATION>Chief Justice Rose Bird</ORGANIZATION>.
   The gruesome details of the murders and of <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s
criminal career in general -- the eight shots he plugged into
the boys before finishing off the hamburgers they had been
eating, the fact that he was already on parole for beating a
neighbor to death and trying to set him afire, the forcible
sodomy he committed on a fellow inmate while awaiting trial
-- can be read in the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> high court's <DATE>1981</DATE> opinion.
Suffice it to say that <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s wife testified for the
prosecution at his sentencing hearing.
   During the 11 years since his conviction, <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> and
his lawyers have filed seven petitions for habeas corpus,
four in state court, three in federal court. Over the years
he has alleged: that his sentence was out of proportion to
his crimes; that the trial judge refused to give a
"diminished capacity" instruction to the jury based on <PERSON>Mr.
Harris</PERSON>'s smoking two joints of marijuana before the murders;
that, although <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> is white, he was the victim of a
racially discriminatory capital sentencing system in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. He won some court victories that higher courts
later reversed. By the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>, it seemed he had
exhausted all possible avenues of legal relief. An <DATE>April 3</DATE>
execution date was set. He was to be the first criminal to go
to the gas chamber in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> since <DATE>1967</DATE>.
   Just a week before <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s scheduled execution date,
his attorneys filed the seventh and latest petition, winning
a stay of execution. The grounds for the newest writ? Two
court-appointed psychiatrists who examined <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> before
the sentencing hearing failed to discern any signs of organic
brain damage. His lawyers now say that <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> was a
victim of fetal alcohol syndrome, hyperactivity and other
brain disorders.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> ruled that a defendant
facing a death sentence has a right of access to the services
of a "competent" court-appointed psychiatrist. So why didn't
<PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> raise this ground in <DATE>1985</DATE> or earlier rather than
on the eve of his execution in <DATE>1990</DATE>? "We've been trying to
get the court to pay for an EEG since <DATE>1982</DATE>, but the court
refused," is the response of <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s lead lawyer,
<PERSON>Charles Sevilla</PERSON>. "Finally last year, we paid for one
ourselves."
   The issue of <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON>'s mental state now and in <DATE>1978</DATE> is
murky. He raised an alibi defense at trial and a marijuana
intoxication defense sometime later in the writ process. An
electroencephalogram administered to him before the <DATE>1979</DATE>
sentencing hearing yielded normal results, although a <DATE>1971</DATE>
EEG had shown abnormalities a probation officer attributed to
chronic glue-sniffing. At any rate, the murders, which
occurred so <PERSON>Mr. Harris</PERSON> and his brother could obtain a getaway
car for a bank robbery they had planned and rehearsed for
weeks, did not exactly bespeak a disordered brain.
   The <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> case has all the earmarks of a candidate for
quick termination under <PERSON>Teague</PERSON> v. Lane: an attempt to
establish a new rule of law via federal habeas corpus long
after the time for direct appeal has expired. That is where
the <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> bill would come into play. While setting a one-year
time limit at the end of direct appeal (subject to numerous
exceptions) for getting all federal habeas claims on file, it
also contains language that effectively overrides both <PERSON>Teague</PERSON>
v. Lane and the procedural default rule the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> set
earlier. The <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> bill is to the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s recent
habeas corpus decisions what the pending Kennedy-Hawkins
civil rights bill is to its affirmative action rulings.
   Fortunately for prosecutors, the <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> bill has little
chance of passing, mostly because of a controversial
amendment by <PERSON>Sen. Edward Kennedy</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>) that would
effectively bring racial quotas to state death penalty laws
by allowing statistical challenges to them. (The tougher
<PERSON>Thurmond</PERSON> bill is also said to have little future.) This may
be all for the best, for the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> seems to be moving
efficiently on its own toward putting an end to open-ended
death appeals.
   ---
   <PERSON>Mrs. Allen</PERSON> is an editor at Insight magazine.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06107233 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06107233 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COURT; WASHINGTON-DC; RULING; DEATH; SENTENCE; TRIAL; TIME; RELATION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Supreme Court, in a ruling that could hasten many executions, today cut
back on the rights of death row inmates to make repeated appeals of their
convictions.;    The 6-3 ruling in a case from Georgia was denounced by the
dissenters as a drastic curtailment of the rights of criminal defendants.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DEATH ROW APPEALS CUT BACK BY COURT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The court rejected arguments by death row inmate <PERSON>Warren McCleskey</PERSON> that
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> officials violated his rights when they failed to give him a written
statement from the inmate to whom <ORGANIZATION>McCleskey</ORGANIZATION> allegedly confessed the <DATE>1978</DATE>
slaying of an <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> police officer.;    Justice <PERSON>Anthony Kennedy</PERSON>, writing for
the court, said <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s failure to raise the issue during an earlier
appeal in <DATE>1981</DATE> disqualified him from trying to use it in subsequent appeals.; 
  <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON> said the burden is on defendants in such cases to prove they had
good reason for not raising the issue initially and that their failure to do
so has prejudiced their ability to defend themselves.;    For example, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
said, the prisoner must prove that state officials deliberately interfered
with his ability to raise the issue.;    It is not necessary for the state to
prove that the defendant deliberately abandoned the issue in an earlier appeal
to raise it subsequently, <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> added.;    The only exception to the new
restrictions are those rare instances in which the defendant can show he is
probably innocent of the crime, <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> said.;    He said the new rules
"should curtail the abusive petitions that in recent years have threatened to
undermine the integrity of the habeas corpus process.";    Under habeas
corpus, convicted defendants can appeal to the federal courts for help when
they claim their constitutional rights have been violated.;    A proposal in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to limit habeas corpus petitions was introduced after a special study
committee appointed by Chief Justice <PERSON>William H. Rehnquist</PERSON> recommended time
limits on death row appeals.;    Justice <PERSON>Thurgood Marshall</PERSON>, in a dissenting
opinion, said <DATE>today</DATE>'s ruling "encourages state officials to conceal evidence
that would likely prompt" prisoners to appeal their convictions.;    The court
"tosses aside established precedents without explanation . . . and applies
(new) rules in a way that rewards state misconduct and deceit," <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON>
said.;    <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s murder conviction was overturned in <DATE>1989</DATE> by a federal
judge who ruled the state had violated his rights in obtaining his confession
to <PERSON>Offie Evans</PERSON>, a fellow prison inmate.;    But the 11th <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court of
Appeals</ORGANIZATION> reinstated the conviction, ruling <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> forfeited his right to
challenge the constitutionality of the confession by failing to raise the
issue in <DATE>1981.</DATE>;    <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s lawyers said they lacked evidence to challenge
the confession until <DATE>1987</DATE>, when they obtained <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>' written statement after
the <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> ordered police records made public.;    The defense
lawyers said <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>' statement gave them the first clue that the inmate had
been coached by <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> police to elicit a confession from McCleskey.;   
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> officials said the state had not deliberately concealed <PERSON>Evans</PERSON>'
statement from the defense. They said <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s lawyers neglected to ask for
it.;    Today's ruling marks the second time the high court has reviewed
<PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s case. The court, in an important ruling in <DATE>1987</DATE>, rejected
<PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s arguments that state death penalty laws are unconstitutional if
statistics show they are being applied in racially biased ways.;    Studies
have shown that killers of whites in <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> draw the death penalty far more
often that do killers of blacks.;    The case acted on today is <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> vs.
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, 89-7024.;     Other actions;    Other decisions today by the Supreme
Court:; (box)Cable TV -- The justices ruled that states may tax cable
television operators without having to levy the same tax on all other news
media. The 7-2 decision upheld an <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION> sales tax on cable service.;
(box)Attorney fees -- The court ruled that lawyers who represent themselves in
successful civil rights lawsuits cannot collect attorney fees from the losing
side.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910416  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  648  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 16, 1991
00107233,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890218-0014 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-18-89 1127EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-OriginalRainMan     02-18 0752</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Original Rain Man,0773</SECOND>
<HEAD>Savant Who Served As Model For `Rain Man' Called `Island of Genius'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto upcoming</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILARY ISRAELSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SALT LAKE CITY (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When screenwriter <PERSON>Barry Morrow</PERSON> first met
Kim, his original model for the central character in ``Rain Man,''
Kim already knew <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON>'s past and present phone numbers and the
number of freeway exits to his house.
   They met in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> where Kim and his father, Fran, were attending
a <DATE>1984</DATE> meeting of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of Retarded Citizens</ORGANIZATION>.
Kim, 37, is an extremely rare prodigious savant, capable of
recalling virtually anything his senses have ever told him.
   But while <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> has a seemingly unlimited ability to absorb and
recall facts and figures, he has limited reasoning power and his IQ
is a below-average 88. He always has lived with Fran in the <LOCATION>Salt
Lake City</LOCATION> area, accompanying him on frequent business trips since a
<DATE>1981</DATE> divorce from Kim's mother.
   ``I am Rain Man,'' <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> said in an interview. ``This is an
important time for me. I have many talents now.''
   <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON>, who calls Kim ``an island of genius,'' believes the movie
has changed Kim.
   ``When I first met him, after he talked to me he dashed across
the room and made low moaning sounds,'' <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> said. ``Now, he would
walk into a room and offer you his hand.''
   Kim's father, who asked for privacy reasons that his and <PERSON>Kim</PERSON>'s
last name not be used, agrees that his son is changing. After a
special screening of ``Rain Man'' for the <ORGANIZATION>Utah Legislature</ORGANIZATION>, Kim
stood up and stressed the importance of understanding the needs of
the handicapped.
   ``I had no idea he could talk to those guys that way,'' <PERSON>Fran</PERSON>
said. ``He is really learning to put his thoughts together.''
   After meeting father and son, <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> decided he would pair a
savant like Kim _ trusting and sometimes childlike _ with a greedy,
self-centered and impatient brother.
   ``Then I put them in a car and had them drive across the country
together,'' said <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON>, nominated for an Oscar for his screenplay.
It chronicles the relationship between <PERSON>Raymond Babbit</PERSON>, an autistic
savant played by <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON>, and his brother, <PERSON>Charlie</PERSON>, played by
<ORGANIZATION>Tom Cruise</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``I don't want to take away from the other people that helped
<PERSON>Dustin</PERSON> create the character,'' <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> said by telephone from
<LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, ``but Kim was the first inspiration for the
story.''
   Coincidentally, Fran and Kim were rolling down the freeway when
they heard the news last week that ``Rain Man'' had been nominated
   Kim has seen the movie three times, the first seated at the
premier between <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> and Fran. Kim stared at his hands and the
floor during most of the movie. When <PERSON>Morrow</PERSON> asked him why, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> told
him he had seen it with his ``heart.''
   While there are behavioral similarities between Kim and <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON>'s
film character, <PERSON>Kim</PERSON> is far more outgoing. Two years ago he spent an
afternoon with <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> on a movie set, the actor mimicking his
movements and his walk.
   When it was over, Kim recalls, <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> said, ``I may be the star,
but you are the heavens.''
   <PERSON>Daniel Christensen</PERSON>, medical director of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Institute of
Neuropsychiatry</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Utah</ORGANIZATION>, has made a thorough study
of Kim.
   ``He has a photographic memory, but no way to minimize stimuli,''
<PERSON>Christensen</PERSON> said. ``He's the closest I've seen to a human
computer,'' unable to filter or forget information, or assign it
relative importance.
   He can answer untold thousands of questions covering history,
sports, maps, literature, mathematics and other subjects.
   ``You'd expect someone with these mental skills to have something
extra in his brain, but there's actually something missing,''
<PERSON>Christensen</PERSON> said. Brain scans show an absence of the bundle of nerve
fibers _ the corpus callosum _ that connects the two halves of the
brain.
   ``Kim is probably one in 10 million,'' he said.
   Morrow offers another insight. ``Kim has been called a savant
with some autistic characteristics, but the real answer is that,
like all of us, Kim defies human labels.''
   The screenwriter said <PERSON>Hoffman</PERSON> has received a flood of mail from
people touched by the movie, people who know other Rain Men. Morrow
takes little credit for the response.
   ``That was an accident,'' he said. ``The bigger story, bigger
than the movie, is that people are coming out of their prisons and
growing. The awards will go away, but the people like Kim will not.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910528-0122
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910528-0122.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   The Death Sentence
   And the State Courts
</HL>
<DATE>
05/28/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A23
</SO>
<IN>
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
</IN>
<NS>
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES, HEARINGS, RULINGS, LEGISLATION (LAW)
</NS>
<GV>
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
</GV>
<LP>
   Your April 22 column concerning the long-overdue decision
of the Supreme Court in McCleskey v. Zant (McCleskey's second
habeas case in that court), wrongly accuses the majority of
acting as legislators in that case. The radical expansion of
federal "habeas corpus" jurisdiction to review judgments of
state criminal courts was the product of a pair of cases
decided in 1963, by the revisionist Warren court: Fay v. Noia
and Townsend v. Sain. Subsequent legislation on the subject
merely codified what Congress apparently perceived as minimum
constitutional standards imposed by the Supreme Court.
   The McCleskey case does no more than address the
persistent abuse of the writ in intervening years by
activists seeking to overturn death sentences by any means.
Restoration of the tradition of respect for state court
judgments that was reflected in the Judiciary Act of 1789 can
hardly be considered judicial legislation. Contrary to your
ill-considered statements, federal habeas corpus jurisdiction
is not and never has been "virtually the only way a convicted
prisoner has to protect against law-enforcement abuses."
State courts can and do protect the rights of the parties
before them, and did so largely without federal oversight
until 1963.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Robert H. Dierker Jr</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Circuit Judge
   Twenty-Second Judicial Circuit of Missouri
   St. Louis</ORGANIZATION>
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06284120 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06284120 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Rep. Don Edwards; ... An unpopular crusade  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; CONGRESS; OFFICIAL; SAN-JOSE; ...; PRISON; DEATH; SENTENCE; LAW; RIGHT;
CAMPAIGN  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  For years, the federal courts have stood between many death row inmates and
execution. Now what stands there is Don Edwards.;   At a time when the
popularity of capital punishment runs high, the San Jose congressman is
leading a quixotic effort to protect what he calls "a venerable right": the
broad right of these inmates to appeal their sentences. Today in Washington,
he is announcing the formation of a national committee that will seek to
persuade other members of Congress not to limit death row appeals.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EDWARDS' DEATH ROW CAMPAIGN
CONGRESSMAN FIGHTS FOR INMATES' RIGHT TO APPEAL
SENTENCES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     It is not an effort likely to enhance <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>' popularity. Nor is it
certain to produce victory when the <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> votes on the
issue later this month.;   Growing numbers of self-styled crime fighters --
including President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> -- now finger protracted appeals as the major
impediment to an effective death penalty. They point most often to
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Robert Alton Harris</PERSON>, whose murder conviction has been snarled in
federal court for more than nine years.;   That <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> has a chance against
these forces is a tribute to the respect he has garnered in his 29-year
career, and to the persuasiveness of his argument that society must be sure
before it condemns a person to death.;   But it is also testament to the
convoluted workings of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. Here, well-placed representatives can often
block the most popular initiatives through procedural sleight-of-hand. <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>
and his allies did just that last year, killing appeals limits that had
previously won approval on the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> floor.;   "<PERSON>Don Edwards</PERSON>, God bless him, is
very sincere about this issue, and I respect that," said <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Attorney
General <PERSON>Dan Lungren</PERSON>, a leading critic of the death row appeals process. "But
there's something wrong with a situation that allows <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to reject the
will of the public in its decision-making.";   <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> responds that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
must also defend the rights of unpopular minorities. But he acknowledges that
his safe district in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> makes it easier for him to lead this particular
charge. "They just shrug," he said of his constituents. "They say, 'There goes
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> again.' ";   The right <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> defends goes by a Latin name, habeas
corpus, and refers to proceedings in which a prisoner argues that he or she is
in custody in violation of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Constitution.;   Virtually all of the
nation's 2,300 death row inmates pursue such claims. A 2-year-old study of
Southern capital cases suggests these proceedings delay execution, on average,
by eight years. Inmates can file more than one as long as they are alleging
different constitutional violations: <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> has filed eight state habeas
corpus petitions and three federal petitions.;   <LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION>'s most
well-known death row inmate, <PERSON>David Luther Ghent</PERSON>, is also pursuing habeas
corpus claims in federal court. He wants a new trial so a jury can consider
whether post-Vietnam stress syndrome drove him to murder his neighbor in
<DATE>1978.</DATE>;   Conservatives have tried for years to limit such appeals. In recent
years they've gotten closer, helped by a more conservative <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>, and
by their own success in humanizing the issue.;   <PERSON>John Collins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
representative for Citizens for Law and Order, breaks through the legal
technicalities by talking of his daughter, murdered in <DATE>1985</DATE>. "When there's no
end to the appeals, there's never an end to a family's grief," he says.;  
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> came to lead the opposing side because of his chairmanship of the
high-profile help: the <ORGANIZATION>Emergency Committee</ORGANIZATION> to Save Habeas Corpus he is
announcing today is chaired by former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Attorneys General <PERSON>Elliott
Richardson</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Benjamin Civiletti.</ORGANIZATION>;   Statistics gathered by the group
indicate <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of habeas corpus appeals are successful -- illustrating,
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> says, that habeas corpus works to ferret out constitutional blunders,
not simply to delay. Among the convictions overturned was that of a <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>
man whose jury consisted mostly of friends of the county sheriff.;   Yet
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> and his supporters are running scared. The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> has already approved
language in this year's crime bill that limits death row inmates to one
federal appeal, or no appeal if a judge finds an inmate got a "full and fair
hearing" in state court. The <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> opted for an
Edwards-drafted alternative, which preserves broader rights while placing a
one-year time limit on the filing of appeals.;   That sets the stage for a
pair of showdowns, first on the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> floor and second in a <ORGANIZATION>House-Senate</ORGANIZATION> panel
that will negotiate a final crime bill. Though <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>' liberal allies killed
habeas corpus limits in a similar panel <DATE>last year</DATE>, they may spark wider
outrage if they employ the tactic again.;   "It is a desperate situation,"
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> said. "But in all candor, I think I have enough experience to see its
importance and make this fight. You know, everyone else around here just talks
about <PERSON>Clarence Thomas</PERSON>. This is more important than <PERSON>Clarence Thomas</PERSON>."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BERT ROBINSON, Mercury News Washington Bureau  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911010  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  830  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, October 10, 1991
00284120,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA091390-0011 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 275193 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 13, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 7; Column 2; Op-Ed Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
831 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PERSPECTIVE ON CAPITAL PUNISHMENT; 
</P>
<P>
WOLVES FIGHTING CRIME GO 'B-A-A-A'; 
</P>
<P>
IT'S ONE THING TO OPPOSE THE DEATH PENALTY, ANOTHER TO PRETEND SUPPORT WHILE 
ERECTING RULES TO THWART IT. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> is poised to take a major step backward in the 
fight against violent crime. In a bill purporting to be an anti-crime measure, 
the <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> has sent to the floor a proposal that would 
effectively abolish the death penalty in this country. 
</P>
<P>
An overwhelming majority of Americans believe that the death penalty is a just 
punishment for the most heinous crimes. Thirty-six states have adopted capital 
punishment. Yet, for more than a decade, these laws have been rendered almost 
unenforceable by a system that allows convicted murderers to delay 
indefinitely, and ultimately to avoid, imposition of their sentences. After 
exhausting all appeals, murderers are allowed to file endless habeas corpus 
petitions in state and federal court, raising largely technical challenges to 
their convictions and sentences. 
</P>
<P>
The writ of habeas corpus originally was a legal device used to challenge 
attempts by the government to seize and detain an individual without trial. 
During the Warren court era, the writ was converted into a right to multiple 
appeals of issues already decided. This radical expansion of the scope of 
habeas corpus has allowed inmates sentenced to death to nullify their sentences 
through strategic delay. 
</P>
<P>
As of <DATE>1988</DATE>, the average delay from time of sentencing to time of execution of a 
capital sentence was almost seven years. In that same year 296 individuals were 
convicted of first-degree murder and sentenced to death while only 11 capital 
sentences were actually carried out. Obviously, such delay undermines the 
deterrent and retributive force of the death penalty and breeds frustration and 
disrespect for our criminal justice system. 
</P>
<P>
The case of <PERSON>Robert Alton Harris</PERSON> illustrates the point. In <DATE>1978</DATE>, while on parole 
for voluntary manslaughter, <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> shot two teen-age boys to steal their car 
for a robbery. Later, he confessed to the murders. He was convicted of 
first-degree murder and sentenced to death by a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> jury in <DATE>1979</DATE>. In 
<DATE>1981</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>California Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> upheld this conviction and sentence, finding 
that "none of the many contentions raised by (<PERSON>Harris</PERSON>) has merit." Since that 
time, <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> has filed several state and four federal habeas petitions, each of 
which has been rejected. His sentence has still not been carried out. 
</P>
<P>
A panel of jurists chaired by retired <PERSON>Justice Lewis F. Powell Jr.</PERSON> has offered a 
solution to this problem. If a state provides those on Death Row with counsel 
at state expense in state habeas corpus proceedings, the prisoner will get only 
two "bites at the apple" -- one state proceeding and one full federal review. 
No further habeas corpus petitions could be filed unless a claim of factual 
innocence were raised. The <PERSON>Bush Administration</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Assn. of Attorneys 
General</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National District Attorneys Assn.</ORGANIZATION> support the principles behind 
<ORGANIZATION>Justice Powell</ORGANIZATION>'s reform proposals. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill, far from curing present 
abuses, would make matters worse. 
</P>
<P>
First, the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> proposal rejects the <ORGANIZATION>Powell Committee</ORGANIZATION>'s quid pro quo 
principle. It affirmatively encourages the filing of successive habeas corpus 
petitions containing claims unrelated to guilt or innocence. At the same time, 
it imposes requirements for state-appointed counsel that very few lawyers can 
meet and even fewer state taxpayers can afford. Under the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> proposal, 
convicted murderers like <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> would go on avoiding punishment by raising 
alleged technical "defects" in their sentences -- "defects" that have nothing 
to do with their guilt or innocence. 
</P>
<P>
Second, the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> proposal overrules two recent <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> decisions that 
attempt to provide some reasonable safeguards against habeas corpus abuse. In 
<ORGANIZATION>Teague vs. Lane</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> held that prisoners cannot use habeas corpus 
to challenge their convictions based on judicial decisions that were not even 
rendered at the time of their trial and appeals. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> proposal overrules 
<PERSON>Teague</PERSON>, and thus renders every criminal conviction in the nation subject to 
constant challenge based on cases that have not yet even been decided. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION> proposal also overrules the court's decision in <LOCATION>Wainwright</LOCATION> 
vs. <PERSON>Sykes</PERSON>. The <PERSON>Sykes</PERSON> decision requires that defendants follow state procedural 
rules in order to preserve claims for federal review, thus preventing criminal 
defendants from "sandbagging," that is, from holding back their claims in state 
court only to raise them years later in a federal proceeding. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> 
proposal would effectively reward defendants who ignore state procedural rules. 
</P>
<P>
It is one thing to openly and honestly oppose the death penalty outright -- a 
position the American people have rejected. It is another thing entirely to 
proclaim support for the death penalty in order to curry political favor while 
at the same time voting to erect a labyrinth of procedural rules to prevent the 
penalty from ever being applied. This crime bill is a sheep in wolf's clothing. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, WILLIAM BARR ; Drawing, "I'm going to see that you don't get any more 
than 12-stays-of-execution for this, Muggsy!" 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Opinion 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06108016 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06108016 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Kennedy; PHOTO: Harris  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  CIVIL; RIGHT; ...; US; COURT; RULING; PRISON; DEATH; SENTENCE; STATE; LAW;
CHANGE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  In a decision likely to speed executions of death row inmates, the Supreme
Court on Tuesday made it tougher for prisoners to make repeated federal
appeals of their convictions.;    The ruling was a victory for police and
prosecutors, but criminal defense lawyers charged that the decision
drastically curbed the rights of criminal defendants.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COURT LIMITS ON APPEALS COULD SPEED EXECUTIONS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Mercury News wire services contributed to this report.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     It will have the greatest impact on more than 2,400 prisoners living on
death row, where the average time between conviction and execution has been
eight years and four months.;    The 6-3 Supreme Court ruling was the latest
in a series of decisions by the court's conservative majority that, taken
together, have sharply limited the ability of state prisoners to obtain
federal reviews of their convictions and sentences.;    Those decisions dealt
with the scope of petitions for writs of habeas corpus, the method by which
state prisoners, after exhausting their appeals in state courts, may claim in
federal courts that their convictions and sentences violated the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
Constitution.;    The writ is considered a bulwark of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> liberties. Criminal
defense and civil liberties lawyers say the liberal use of the writ in the
past has uncovered a high proportion of serious errors.;    On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>,
Justice <PERSON>Anthony M. Kennedy</PERSON>, writing for the court majority, noted that
successive petitions also delay justice, promote disrespect for the law and
waste court resources.;    The new criteria; Under a new rule announced by
<LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>, a criminal defendant cannot raise a new claim in a second federal
appeal until proving that (1) there was a good reason -- such as a government
coverup of evidence -- for not doing so earlier, and (2) the omission
seriously hurt the defense.;    A defendant who cannot pass that test may be
heard only by showing a probability of innocence.;    The new rule, <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
said, "should curtail the abusive petitions that in recent years have
threatened to undermine the integrity of the habeas corpus process." He was
<PERSON>Sandra Day O'Connor</PERSON>, <PERSON>Antonin Scalia</PERSON> and <PERSON>David H. Souter.</PERSON>;    But Justice
<PERSON>Thurgood Marshall</PERSON>, joined by <PERSON>Harry A. Blackmun</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Paul Stevens</PERSON>, accused
the court majority of abandoning precedent, creating "a near-irrebuttable
presumption that omitted claims are permanently barred" and encouraging
government "misconduct and deceit.";    <PERSON>Mary Broderick</PERSON>, a director of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Legal Aid and Defender Association</ORGANIZATION> declared: "It's just another notch
in the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION>'s effort to close the coffin on habeas corpus, another
example of the majority's willingness to ignore serious constitutional
errors.";    <ORGANIZATION>Inmate</ORGANIZATION>'s second defeat;  The decision was a second high court
defeat for <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> death row inmate <PERSON>Warren McCleskey</PERSON>, a black man convicted of
murdering a white off-duty police officer during a <DATE>1978</DATE> furniture store
robbery.;    In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the justices rejected his attempt to prove racial
discrimination in death sentences. On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, in <ORGANIZATION>McCleskey vs. Zant</ORGANIZATION>, 89-7024,
they barred <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> from claiming in a second federal petition that a
confession used at his trial was obtained in violation of his Sixth Amendment
right to a lawyer.;    He had made such a claim in state appeals but not in
his first federal appeal. McCleskey argued that he had new evidence that had
been withheld by the state: a 21-page statement of the inmate who had heard
<PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON>'s confession and reported it to state officials.;    But <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>
concluded that because <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> "knew everything in the document," its
unavailability did not prevent him from raising his Sixth Amendment claim in
his first federal petition.;     <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s decision also may have dimmed
condemned murderer <PERSON>Robert Alton Harris</PERSON>' chances of getting a federal court to
overturn his <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> death sentence.;    Out of more than 300 prisoners on
death row in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, only <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> could be affected immediately, since he
is the only one whose case has progressed beyond a first round of federal
court challenges.;    Prosecutor's case bolstered;  A state prosecutor,
preparing for a crucial hearing in <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>' case, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s ruling appears
to strengthen his argument that the defense had waited too long to raise
allegations of perjury by a cellmate of Harris.;    <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> was convicted of
the <DATE>1978</DATE> murders of two <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> teen-agers whose car he wanted to use in a
bank robbery.;    After an unsuccessful appeal in state court and two rounds
of challenges in federal courts, he came within days of the state's first
execution since <DATE>1967 last April</DATE>. But he was granted a stay in a new federal
appeal that raised two principal issues: ineffective assistance at trial by
psychiatrists, who allegedly failed to detect brain damage, and new evidence
that a cellmate who became a prosecution witness had committed perjury.;   
The 9th <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> has ordered a hearing <DATE>May 7</DATE> before a
federal judge in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> on the question of whether the cellmate, <PERSON>Joey
Abshire</PERSON>, was acting as a secret informant for police when he talked to <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>
about the killings and later testified about <PERSON>Harris</PERSON>' statements.;    <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION>
lawyers have produced a recent statement from <PERSON>Abshire</PERSON> saying his questioning
of <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> was prompted by police, who had told him to deny their involvement.
That allegation could upset the capital murder convictions, but <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s
ruling appeared to increase the possibility that the evidence will be thrown
out of court.;    Under the high court's standard, <PERSON>Harris</PERSON> "has to show that he
could not have raised that issue" in his two earlier federal challenges,
Deputy Attorney General <PERSON>Louis Hanoian</PERSON> said.; STANDARDS FOR DEATH-ROW APPEALS;
Justice <PERSON>Anthony Kennedy</PERSON>, writing for the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> majority, outlined new
criteria for allowing second federal appeals to prisoners.;    Prisoners can
appeal again only if:;    (box) They can prove that they had a good reason for
not presenting the claim in the first appeal, and;    (box) That the omission
seriously hurt their defense.; Or if:;     (box) They have evidence that will
show probable innocence.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  AARON EPSTEIN, Mercury News Washington Bureau  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910417  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  984  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday April 17, 1991
00108016,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880917-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-17-88 0139EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Hurricane-Surfers     09-17 0421</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hurricane-Surfers,0433</SECOND>
<HEAD>Windsurfers, Others Get Close At Hurricane's Fringe</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CC1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF AWALT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CORPUS CHRISTI, Texas (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Nancy Clark</PERSON> rode her sailboard over
the northern edge of Hurricane Gilbert on <DATE>Friday</DATE> to the cheers of a
surfside crowd that gathered after word their city would be spared
the brunt of the hurricane.
   Much of <LOCATION>Corpus Christi</LOCATION> seemed abandoned <DATE>Friday</DATE>, but <ORGANIZATION>Ocean Drive</ORGANIZATION>
was jammed with traffic as residents and tourists flocked to the
city's seawall with the news that <PERSON>Gilbert</PERSON> would hit farther south
than expected.
   The eye of the hurricane came ashore <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> about 120
miles south of <LOCATION>Brownsville</LOCATION>, or about 280 miles from <LOCATION>Corpus Christi</LOCATION>.
   Scores of cars cruised up and down the windy beachfront road in
<LOCATION>Corpus Christi</LOCATION>, as bicyclists, joggers and windsurfers were joined
by crowds of residents complaining of cabin fever in their
boarded-up homes.
   ``This is definitely the advanced class,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Clark</PERSON>, a
legal investigator who took her sailboard into 35-mph winds after
fleeing <LOCATION>Port Isabel</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Brownsville</LOCATION>.
   ``This definitely rates a `10'. But it's also a good day for
conservative, positive sailing,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Corpus Christi</ORGANIZATION> architect
<PERSON>Robert Jones</PERSON>, one of about a half-dozen surfers who rode high tides
at 4 feet above normal levels.
   ``I was sitting in the house with the windows boarded up,
getting kind of bored,'' said <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>. ``I decided I'd just get out
here and see what the winds were like.''
   Many of the residents and tourists who decided to stay in <LOCATION>Corpus
Christi</LOCATION> had heard repeated warnings that <PERSON>Gilbert</PERSON> would likely turn
toward the north, striking land near <LOCATION>Brownsville</LOCATION> and bashing <LOCATION>Corpus
Christi</LOCATION> with heavy wind and rain.
   But when the hurricane stayed on its course toward <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, the
seawall swelled with confident crowds.
   ``Most people probably wouldn't expect to see this many people
down here in a hurricane, but once you've lived in <LOCATION>Corpus Christi</LOCATION>
for a while, you come to expect the unusual out of the residents,''
said <PERSON>Russ Roland</PERSON>, who was enjoying his daily bicycle ride along the
seawall.
   Families gathered along the seawall as the waves lapped at the
concrete steps, and children danced along the edge of the churning
water, mugging for cameras.
   Many, including <PERSON>Doug Reiter</PERSON>, said they just grew tired of
sitting inside a house darkened by plywood-covered windows.
   ``I think everybody is just bored, and this is kind of a release
from being cooped up,'' he said. ``You can only take that sort of
thing so long before you start getting stir crazy.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06137213 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06137213 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: Signe Wilkinson -- Philadelphia Inquirer  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COURT; WASHINGTON-DC; RULING; TREND; HUMAN; RIGHT; ANALYSIS; OPINION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE U.S. Supreme Court is out of the closet. The myth that it is only liberals
who are judicial activists stands exposed.;    The Supreme Court has never
acted in as nakedly activist a manner as did the Rehnquist court last month in
a case known as "McCleskey II" (McCleskey vs. Zant). No longer will it be
possible for conservative politicians to proclaim that the appointees of
Presidents Nixon, Reagan and Bush believe in judicial restraint.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  HIGH COURT'S NAKED ACTIVISM  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Stephen Reinhardt is a judge of the United States Court of Appeals for the
Ninth Circuit. He wrote this article for the Los Angeles Times.
Commentary  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     In <ORGANIZATION>McCleskey II</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> unabashedly legislated drastic
restrictions on one of our most fundamental rights -- the writ of habeas
corpus. The great writ, which dates back to the time of the <ORGANIZATION>Magna Carta</ORGANIZATION>,
entitles every person to challenge his or her unlawful confinement. It is the
basic check on a police state.;    Overturning long-established judicial
doctrine, the court held in <PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> II that a person who is sentenced to die
following a prosecution tainted by serious governmental misconduct may not
file a petition for habeas corpus if he previously filed one and failed to
complain of the government's conduct -- even though he was unaware of the
critical facts because the government had deliberately concealed them from
him.;    In the name of efficiency and speed, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> deliberately
chose to sacrifice fairness and due process.;    It is not surprising that the
court led by Chief Justice <PERSON>William H. Rehnquist</PERSON> has, in a series of cases,
systematically gone about the process of dismantling habeas corpus. This court
has shown little concern with individual rights or personal freedom. Rather,
it has sought to increase the authority of government over the private lives
of individuals and to undermine historic protections against police abuse.;   
Only a week before <PERSON>McCleskey II</PERSON>, in the case of <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> vs. <PERSON>Fulminante</PERSON>, one of
the court's most conservative justices, <PERSON>Byron R. White</PERSON>, made it clear that
even he could not stomach some of the more extreme activism of the
Rehnquist-led majority.;    Regarding the court's ruling that the use of a
coerced confession does not necessarily render a trial unfair, White
caustically observed, "Today, a majority of the court, without any
justification, overrules this vast body of precedent without a word and in so
doing dislodges one of the fundamental tenets of our criminal justice
system.";    On <DATE>April 16</DATE>, a day that judicial scholars and defenders of civil
liberties will long remember, the right wing of the court, with <ORGANIZATION>Justice White</ORGANIZATION>
back in the fold, did by judicial fiat what Chief Justice <PERSON>Rehnquist</PERSON> had been
unable to accomplish through other means.;    The events leading up to
<PERSON>McCleskey</PERSON> II are extraordinary. In his eagerness to limit the right of death
justice of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> undertook several unusual steps.;    First, he
appointed a committee of five judges from the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>, where almost all recent
executions have occurred, to conduct a congressionally mandated study of how
death-penalty appeals could be curtailed. The committee, headed by former
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court Justice Lewis Powell</ORGANIZATION>, brought forth precisely the type of report
that might have been anticipated. The chief justice immediately forwarded it
to Congress.;    The <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> report recommended prohibiting a second habeas
corpus challenge to a death sentence, even when the state had knowingly used
perjured testimony or had otherwise wrongfully concealed from the defendant
facts that would require reversal of the sentence.;    When the chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>Senate Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Joseph Biden</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Del.</LOCATION>, questioned <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> about
this patently unfair provision, <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> replied that his report couldn't
possibly mean what it said. Moments later, the chief staff member of the
<PERSON>Powell</PERSON> committee corrected his boss; he told <PERSON>Biden</PERSON> that <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> had made an
error, that the rights of unconstitutionally sentenced death row defendants
would indeed be cut off under the <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> proposal.;    The Rehnquist-endorsed
plan quickly suffered a series of resounding defeats.;    First, a majority of
the members of the <ORGANIZATION>Judicial Council</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, a body composed of
the nation's most senior judges, a group that ordinarily ratifies with
enthusiasm any suggestion by a chief justice, rejected the most controversial
parts of the <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> report.;    Then <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, despite intense lobbying by the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> attorney general and state prosecutors, refused to include any part of
the <PERSON>Powell</PERSON> committee's recommendations in the <DATE>1990</DATE> crime bill.;    A few
months later, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> struck back. Having failed to obtain from
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> the legislation the chief justice sought, the "conservative" majority
adopted the rule rejected by <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, not only for death sentences, but also
for all convictions.;    The long-run consequences of this exercise in
judicial activism remain to be seen. At the least, one might hope that in the
future, frank discussion of the role of judicial philosophy and attitudes in
decision-making will be possible, and attacks on liberal judges by demagogic
office-seekers will be seen for the arrant hypocrisy they have always been.;  
 It is clear what we can expect from the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> for the foreseeable
future. In four or five years, the "conservative" majority has overturned
decades of civil-rights rulings, eliminated fundamental deterrents to unlawful
police practices, gutted the longstanding protection of religious practices by
persons other than those belonging to a "majority" religion, sanctioned the
invasion of the bedroom and the criminalization of homosexual conduct, and
proclaimed its eagerness to overturn the right to abortion as soon as one more
vote can be garnered.;    Certainly, today's majority is no believer in
judicial precedent. Nor does it follow the doctrines of "judicial restraint"
or "strict construction." A far different term from "conservative" is needed
to describe the activist right-wing majority that is rewriting constitutional
law in its own image.;    The judicial and political ideology that drives the
<ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> does not portend well for individual rights or fundamental
freedoms in these <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  STEPHEN REINHARDT  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910516  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  998  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday May 16, 1991
00137213,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060789-0063 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 66974 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 7, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
638 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIGH COURT ACTS TO SPEED ITS REVIEW OF CAPITAL CASES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By PHILIP HAGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SAN FRANCISCO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Over objections from two justices, the state <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> issued 
new procedural rules designed to speed the review of death-penalty cases. 
</P>
<P>
The new standards require defense attorneys to ensure that habeas corpus 
petitions -- in which condemned prisoners raise new issues that go beyond 
claims in their direct appeals to the court -- are filed "without substantial 
delay." 
</P>
<P>
Until now, these secondary appeals, which raise such issues as inadequate trial 
counsel or newly discovered evidence, ordinarily have not been filed until 
after the defendant's direct appeal has been decided by the high court. Under 
the new rules, both such appeals ordinarily will have to be filed at virtually 
the same time, enabling the justices to consolidate their review of the 
appeals. 
</P>
<P>
The rules, announced in a statement by Chief Justice <PERSON>Malcolm M. Lucas</PERSON>, were 
issued in the wake of widespread concern among legal authorities over delay and 
uncertainty in the review of capital appeals. Lucas is co-chairman of an 
<ORGANIZATION>American Bar Assn.</ORGANIZATION> task force studying the problem in both state and federal 
courts. 
</P>
<P>
However, Justices <PERSON>Stanley Mosk</PERSON> and <PERSON>Allen E. Broussard</PERSON>, two liberals on a 
conservative-dominated high court, dissented from the rules "on various 
grounds," <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s cryptically worded statement said. 
</P>
<P>
Mosk, it said, "particularly opposed" provisions that would impose new time 
standards requiring that, with some exceptions, habeas corpus petitions must be 
filed within 60 days after final briefs are due in the defendant's direct 
appeal. 
</P>
<P>
Broussard "primarily objected" to applying the new standards to pending cases, 
<PERSON>Lucas</PERSON>' statement said. 
</P>
<P>
The new regulations also drew sharp criticism from <PERSON>Michael D. Laurence</PERSON>, 
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Death Penalty Project of American Civil Liberties Union of 
Northern California</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Laurence warned that requiring defense attorneys to investigate cases and 
prepare briefs in direct appeals and habeas appeals at the same time could 
jeopardize the quality of a defendant's legal representation. 
</P>
<P>
"There is a risk that innocent people may be rushed through the system because 
an appellate attorney was rushed through the system," he said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Michael G. Millman</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>California Appellate Project</ORGANIZATION>, a nonprofit 
group that assists lawyers in capital appeals, said the new standards will be 
"helpful in clarifying the expectations" of defense counsel. 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Millman</PERSON> voiced concern about the fairness of applying to pending cases new 
rules that appear to represent "a significant break" from past procedures. 
</P>
<P>
On a different front, state Deputy Atty. Gen. <PERSON>Dane R. Gillette</PERSON> expressed doubt 
that the new rules would weaken the quality of habeas corpus petitions. And he 
welcomed the new policy as one that would improve the speed and efficiency of 
the whole capital appeal process. 
</P>
<P>
"We're enthusiastic about the new rules," <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> said. "By combining the 
habeas proceedings with the direct appeal, we can get these cases through the 
state system much more expeditiously. . . . Overall, it will benefit the 
criminal justice system." 
</P>
<P>
The new rules say that habeas corpus petitions that are not filed within 60 
days of final briefs in direct appeals can be denied as "untimely." But the 
court will allow exceptions to the limit when defense counsel can show that 
petitions were filed within a "reasonable time" after they became aware of new 
facts or legal issues about a case. 
</P>
<P>
The rules also require court-appointed counsel to represent condemned prisoners 
all the way through direct and secondary appeals in state and federal court 
and, if necessary, to seek clemency from the governor for an inmate who faces 
imminent execution. 
</P>
<P>
The justices will consider replacing such attorneys "only if appropriate 
replacement counsel is ready and willing" to take over the job, <PERSON>Lucas</PERSON> said in 
the statement. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
CALIFORNIA SUPREME COURT -- RULINGS; CAPITAL PUNISHMENT -- CALIFORNIA; COURT 
REFORM 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900607-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-07-90 0200EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-DeathAppeals     06-07 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Death Appeals,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Administration Faults Plans to Speed Death Penalty Appeals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> opposes congressional
proposals aimed at eliminating lengthy delays of death penalty
appeals.
   A <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan would have the reverse effect of stringing out the
appeal process, and a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> plan has technical defects, Deputy
Assistant Attorney General <PERSON>Paul L. Maloney</PERSON> told a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> panel
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> plan, cosponsored by Sens. <PERSON>Arlen Specter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>, and
<PERSON>Strom Thurmond</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-S.C.</LOCATION>, is designed to shorten death penalty delays
by replacing state habeas corpus proceedings with a single federal
court review.
   Habeas corpus proceedings are used by defendants who have been
sentenced to death and are trying to win new trials or sentences.
The Specter-Thurmond amendment was defeated, then passed 12 hours
later on <DATE>May 24</DATE>, allowing it to be added to a comprehensive <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
anti-crime bill.
   The amendment would require federal habeas corpus petitions to be
filed within 60 days after final action by state courts.
   The amendment raises ``interesting possibilities'' for reducing
appeals delays ``through a stronger, more comprehensive system of
time limitation rules,'' <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> told a <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee.
   But he added, ``We do find that there are some defects, some
technical problems if you will.'' Under questioning, he said the
amendment was still under review and that he was not prepared to
specify what the problems were.
   The two proposals are among several under consideration in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to speed up death penalty appeals while ensuring
defendants' rights.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan, sponsored by Rep. <PERSON>Robert Kastenmeier</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
would give death row inmates new appeal rights while ensuring that
their attorneys met strict experience and performance standards.
   The bill also aims to end appeals delays by restricting multiple
prisoner petitions, and establishing a one-year limit within for
inmates to file for federal habeas relief.
   But <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said the measure ``multiplies the opportunity for
delay and abuse'' in capital cases.
   He quoted retired <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> Justice <PERSON>Lewis F. Powell</PERSON>, who said
recently that a vote for <PERSON>Kastenmeier</PERSON>'s bill ``would in practical
effect be a vote to eliminate capital punishment in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.''
   The department would recommend that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> veto the bill
if it passed <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> in its present form, <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said.
   But the bill was backed during <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s hearing by civil
Leadership Conference</ORGANIZATION>. He said a broader supervisory role by the
federal judiciary was needed to stop the ``inexhaustible litany of
racial discrimination cases in the courts in the rural South.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900310-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-90 0216EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-MCorp-CorpusChristi     03-10 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-MCorp-Corpus Christi,0372</SECOND>
<HEAD>MCorp Sells Bank in Corpus Christi</HEAD>
<DATELINE>DALLAS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   MCorp will sell its interest in MBank <LOCATION>Corpus
Christi</LOCATION> to the bank's managers, company officials said <DATE>Friday</DATE>. It
would be the second such transaction in less than two weeks.
   The deal, which is subject to regulatory and bankruptcy court
approvals, would leave <ORGANIZATION>MCorp</ORGANIZATION>, once the state's second-largest bank
holding company, with three subsidiaries to sell.
   A group of investors led by <PERSON>Jerry Gates</PERSON>, chairman and chief
executive officer of <ORGANIZATION>MBank Corpus Christi</ORGANIZATION>, will become the bank's
owner under an agreement with <ORGANIZATION>MCorp</ORGANIZATION>. The sale is expected to be
complete by <DATE>July 31</DATE>.
   The bank had assets of <MONEY>$582 million</MONEY> and deposits of <MONEY>$502 million</MONEY>
on <DATE>Dec. 31, 1989</DATE>.
   The bank's name will be changed to <ORGANIZATION>Corpus Christi National Bank</ORGANIZATION>,
the name under which it was originally chartered 100 years ago.
   ``Over the past few months, as events unfolded which made it
appear that local ownership of the bank was a possibility, we've
received hundreds of comments from customers and community leaders
expressing their support for the return of <ORGANIZATION>Corpus Christi National
Bank</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> said.
   Terms of the agreement call for <ORGANIZATION>MCorp</ORGANIZATION> to receive an undisclosed
amount of assets, mostly loans and real estate, for the bank's
stock. MBank <ORGANIZATION>Corpus Christi</ORGANIZATION> will simultaneously issue <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>
in new stock.
   MCorp, which has been in bankruptcy proceedings since <DATE>March
1989</DATE>, last week said it had reached an agreement to sell <ORGANIZATION>MBank El
Paso</ORGANIZATION> to its managers.
   The Dallas-based firm is trying to sell its remaining banking
subsidiaries in <LOCATION>Brownsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Braunfels</LOCATION> and Waco.
   ``We are looking to sell those assuming we can get what we view
as adequate or proper value for the benefit of our shareholders,''
said <ORGANIZATION>MCorp</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Doug Hughes</PERSON>.
   The five banks remained with <ORGANIZATION>MCorp</ORGANIZATION> after the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Deposit
Insurance Corp.</ORGANIZATION> stripped it of 20 banking subsidiaries following
the bankruptcy filing. Those 20 banks were bought by <ORGANIZATION>Banc One
Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, an <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> banking company, and now operate as <ORGANIZATION>Bank One-Texas</ORGANIZATION>.
   MCorp's federally assisted bailout was the third largest in
history after those of <ORGANIZATION>Continental Illinois</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>First
Republic Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION> in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06288091 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06288091 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  EDITORIAL; US; PRISON; LAW; RIGHT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  'THIS is more important than Clarence Thomas," Don Edwards keeps insisting.
And for death row prison inmates, the San Jose Democrat's latest cause is,
literally, a matter of life and death.;   Edwards is trying to block a Bush
administration bid to cut off most state prisoner appeals to federal courts.
The congressman and other members of an "Emergency Committee to Save Habeas
Corpus" say that 40 percent of such appeals are upheld, proving their merit.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Editorial  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ONE LAST CHANCE
PRISONERS' APPEALS TO FEDERAL COURT SHOULD BE
LIMITED, NOT ELIMINATED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Edwards is pushing a more moderate reform endorsed by the <ORGANIZATION>American Bar
Association</ORGANIZATION> and other legal organizations. Instead of virtually ending federal
habeas corpus proceedings, they would limit prisoners to one petition each and
impose a one-year deadline for filing.;   Latin for "you should have the
body," habeas corpus is a centuries-old defense against illegal imprisonment.
It applies to all inmates, but appeals from those sentenced to death are
especially numerous.;   We have no doubt that such appeals are flooding our
courts, state and federal, and that some prisoners have used them to delay
their executions for years. But for a society that aspires to justice, the
proper response is not to abolish the right of appeal, but to restrict its
abuse.;   <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> finds himself in this fight for two reasons. He chairs the
civil and constitutional rights subcommittee of the <ORGANIZATION>House Judiciary Committee</ORGANIZATION>.
And as a long-time champion of civil liberties -- and dean of the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
delegation -- he's ideologically willing to take on an unpopular cause, and
politically powerful enough to get away with it.;   <ORGANIZATION>The Senate</ORGANIZATION>, swept along on
get-tough-on-crime sentiments, has passed the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> version. Let's hope the
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> will be wiser, and opt for the more moderate course urged by <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911014  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  286  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 14, 1991
00288091,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911023-0084
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911023-0084.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Politics &amp; Policy:
   House Approves
   Anti-Crime Bill
   In 305-118 Vote
   ----
   By Paul M. Barrett
</HL>
<DATE>
10/23/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A16
</SO>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<RE>
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The House passed an anti-crime bill that
would expand the federal death penalty and increase spending
for local law enforcement and state prisons.
   The package, approved 305-118, differs in several aspects
from legislation passed by the Senate in July. Lawmakers must
iron out those differences in a conference before sending a
bill to President Bush.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The major point of contention at the conference probably
will be how much to curb state prisoners' rights to file
appeals in federal courts on constitutional grounds. The
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> version would limit the availability of these so-called
habeas corpus petitions in many cases. The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> version, in
contrast, would in effect eliminate these appeals, according
to Democratic lawmakers. President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> favors the more
stringent approach.
   Last year, both houses passed anti-crime bills, but
conferees were unable to work out compromises; the final
package was stripped of its most controversial provisions,
including those limiting habeas corpus petitions.
   Compromise is somewhat more likely this year. For one
thing, the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> passed death-penalty provisions similar to
those approved in the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>. Both versions would expand the
federal death penalty to cover 50 additional crimes,
including murder of high government officials, espionage and
certain drug crimes. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>, as the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> did earlier,
struck from its bill language that would have allowed a
defendant to avoid execution if he could prove that capital
punishment had been applied in a racially disproportionate
fashion in that jurisdiction.
   The passage of the death-penalty provisions, stripped of a
"racial justice" defense, is a major victory for President
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, who has made capital punishment a centerpiece of his
anti-crime program. Eager to appear just as "tough" as
Republicans, most Democrats supported the death-penalty
provisions.
   Both houses also have passed variations of a weeklong
mandatory waiting period for handgun purchases. <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> has
said he will sign such a gun-control provision only if
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> presents him with death-penalty and habeas corpus
measures to his liking. The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> passed a ban on nine types
of semi-automatic "assault" weapons; the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> rejected a
similar provision.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> bill includes a broader exception to the
so-called exclusionary rule, under which judges prevent
illegally gathered evidence from being admitted in court. The
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> version would allow admission of such evidence when
police made a "good faith" mistake but did seek a search
warrant. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> version would apply even when police
didn't get a warrant.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900606-0167 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-90 2035EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-DeathPenaltyAppeals     06-06 0453</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Death Penalty Appeals,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Justice Department Opposes Additional Death Row Inmate Appeals</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JEFF BARKER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> it
opposes a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan backed by some federal judges to give death row
inmates more appeal rights than they now have.
   The department said also that it had ``technical problems'' with
a Senate-adopted amendment to shorten death penalty delays by
replacing state habeas corpus proceedings with a single federal
court review.
   Defendants sentenced to death sometimes use habeas corpus
hearings in attempts to win new trials or sentences. The <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>
amendment was defeated, then passed 12 hours later on <DATE>May 24</DATE> as part
of a comprehensive anti-crime bill.
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> proposals are among several under
consideration in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to speed up death penalty appeals while
ensuring defendants' rights.
   Deputy Assistant Attorney General <PERSON>Paul L. Maloney</PERSON> told a <ORGANIZATION>House
Judiciary</ORGANIZATION> subcommittee that the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan would cause delays and
repetition in appeals, and that the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> proposal contained
``defects.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> plan is sponsored by Rep. <PERSON>Paul Kastenmeier</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Wis.</LOCATION>,
would give death row inmates new appeal rights while ensuring that
their attorneys met strict experience and performance standards.
   The bill also aims to end appeals delays by restricting multiple
prisoner petitions, and establishing a one-year limit for inmates to
file for federal habeas relief.
   But <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said the measure ``multiplies the opportunity for
delay and abuse'' in capital cases.
   He quoted retired <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> Justice <PERSON>Lewis F. Powell</PERSON>, who said
recently that a vote for <PERSON>Kastenmeier</PERSON>'s bill ``would in practical
effect be a vote to eliminate capital punishment in the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>.''
   The bill was backed during <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s hearing by <PERSON>Joseph Lowery</PERSON>,
broader supervisory role by the federal judiciary was needed to stop
the ``inexhaustible litany of racial discrimination cases in the
courts in the rural south.''
   The bill also has the support of several federal judges,
including <PERSON>Gilbert Merritt</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, chief judge of the
6th <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Circuit Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said also that the department was not ready to support
the amendment requiring the filing of habeas corpus petitions within
60 days after final action by state courts. The amendment was
authored by Sens. <PERSON>Arlen Specter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Strom Thurmond</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-S.C.</LOCATION>
   The Specter-Thurmond amendment raises ``interesting
possibilities'' for reducing appeals delays ``through a stronger,
more comprehensive system of time limitation rules,'' <PERSON>Maloney</PERSON> said.
   But he added, ``We do find that there are some defects, some
technical problems if you will.'' Under questioning, he said the
amendment was still under review and he was not prepared to specify
what the problems were.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06162017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06162017 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Map; MAP: Knight-Ridder News Service; DEATH PENALTY APPEALS MAY BE CURBED.
Almost 40% of death penalty convictions have been reversed by U.S. appeals
courts in the past 15 years. The Bush administration has proposed legislation
to limit appeals of the death sentence.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  DEATH; SENTENCE; TREND; US  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Death row prisoner Douglas W. Thompson won a new trial in Missouri because the
jury that convicted him was loaded with friends of the sheriff.;    Death row
prisoner Jack Carlton House won a new trial in Georgia because his lawyers had
prepared no strategy, sought no witnesses, failed to discover useful evidence
in police files, and summed up the case to the jury with a short verse from
the Bible. "Both of us were too busy," one of the defense lawyers explained.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CURBS URGED IN DEATH-ROW APPEALS
LAWYERS FEAR LOSS OF RIGHTS FOR INMATES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Death row prisoner <PERSON>Dennis Wayne Smith</PERSON> won a new trial in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> because
his jury hadn't been told that the only witness to place <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> at the scene of
the crime had failed to mention <PERSON>Smith</PERSON> at all in his first statement to the
police.;    Constitutional blunders like these -- all of which survived state
court review and were remedied only in the federal courts -- are not
uncommon.;    But correcting them could get much more difficult if the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration succeeds with new legislation it is pushing, say many experts.;
   The administration bill would drastically curb a legal process known as
federal habeas corpus, designed to protect prisoners against injustices in
state courts.;    Over the past 15 years, federal judges have reversed
convictions, sentences or both in nearly <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> of all the death penalty
cases brought before them under this process.;    Critics of the
