<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA041989-0032 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 45832 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 19, 1989, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 9B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
633 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SPORTS ET CETERA: ATHLETES IN ACTION WILL MOVE OPERATION TO CINCINNATI 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Athletes in Action will move its operation from <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> this 
<DATE>summer</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>AIA</ORGANIZATION>, a Christian-advocacy organization that played a schedule of 
college teams in exhibition games, had moved from <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>San 
Diego</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The move comes as part of a structural and leadership change within the 
national organization. The national offices also will be moved to <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> 
from <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>AIA</ORGANIZATION> will operate a <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> branch in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> and continue to offer 
<DATE>summer</DATE> camps and its three-on-three tournament. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>AIA</ORGANIZATION> will move to <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> with no coach and only one confirmed player -- 
<PERSON>Lorenzo Romar</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Coach <PERSON>Rle Nichols</PERSON> left the team in <DATE>January</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>AIA</ORGANIZATION> is searching for a coach and 
general manager. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>AIA</ORGANIZATION> was 83-49 in four seasons in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. The organization was in <LOCATION>Vancouver</LOCATION> 
for eight years. 
</P>
<P>
TENNIS 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Steffi Graf</PERSON>, the top-ranked women's tennis player in the world, will compete in 
the <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> <ORGANIZATION>Great American Bank Tennis Classic</ORGANIZATION> at the <LOCATION>San Diego Tennis</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Racquet Club</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>July 31</DATE> to <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Graf became only the fifth player to win tennis' Grand Slam -- the Australian, 
French, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Open and <LOCATION>Wimbledon</LOCATION> -- last year. This will be her only tournament 
appearance on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> this year. 
</P>
<P>
COLLEGE SIGNINGS 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Michael Hudson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shawn Jamison</PERSON>, both of <ORGANIZATION>Pratt Community College</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Wichita</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Kan.</LOCATION>, signed national letters of intent with <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jamison</PERSON>, 6-foot-8, had verbally committed to the <LOCATION>Aztecs</LOCATION> <DATE>last Tuesday</DATE>. He 
averaged 19.9 points and 9.2 rebounds for <ORGANIZATION>Pratt</ORGANIZATION>. Hudson, a 6-2 guard, averaged 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jamison</PERSON> is a graduate of <ORGANIZATION>Gahr High</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cerritos</LOCATION>. Hudson prepped at <LOCATION>Los Angeles 
Washington</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1987-88</DATE>, both played at <ORGANIZATION>Casper College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> where they 
finished sixth in the national community college tournament. Last season, they 
led Pratt to a fourth-place finish in the national tournament. 
</P>
<P>
GOLF 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Judy Furst</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Palm Desert</LOCATION> holds a two-stroke lead going into today's final 
round of the <LOCATION>San Diego Women</LOCATION>'s Classic at the <ORGANIZATION>Chula Vista Golf Course</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Furst shot a 37 on the front nine <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, then came back with a 35 on the back 
nine for a combined score of 72. <PERSON>Teresa Schreck</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kim Saiki</PERSON> followed at 75. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Shelly Tulao</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Chula Vista</ORGANIZATION> amateur, is among a group of three golfers three 
back at 75. 
</P>
<P>
BASEBALL 
</P>
<P>
UC <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> scored seven runs in the third inning, including back-to-back home 
runs by <PERSON>Gary Fessia</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jim Martinez</PERSON>, to lift the Tritons over visiting 
Pomona-Pitzer, 9-3. 
</P>
<P>
Also in the third, eight batters reached base, the first seven scoring, before 
<ORGANIZATION>Fessia</ORGANIZATION>'s grand slam and <PERSON>Martinez</PERSON>'s solo home runs. The Division III 
eighth-ranked Tritons improved to 18-14. Pomona-Pitzer dropped to 7-21-1. <PERSON>Rick 
Rupkey</PERSON> (8-3) picked up the win. 
</P>
<P>
Freshman <PERSON>Bruce Moutaw</PERSON> hit a three-run homer in the ninth to get <ORGANIZATION>US 
International</ORGANIZATION> close, but the Gulls (16-27) still fell to <LOCATION>UC Riverside</LOCATION>, 7-5, in 
a nonconference game. <PERSON>Scott Einhorn</PERSON> hit a solo homer for <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> broke its 15-game losing streak by winning the second 
game of a doubleheader with UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>, 1-0. UC <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION> won the opener, 3-1. 
</P>
<P>
DISTANCE RUNNING 
</P>
<P>
Ultra distance runner <PERSON>Sarah Fulcher</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pacific Beach</LOCATION> will run in the 
Soviet-sponsored Pravda International Super Marathon <DATE>June 15-30</DATE> in <LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Fulcher, an assistant track coach at <LOCATION>Mission Bay High</LOCATION>, is one of 10 Americans 
on a relay team that will run 1,000 miles -- approximately 20 miles a day per 
runner -- beginning in <LOCATION>Tynda</LOCATION>, 200 miles east of <LOCATION>Lake Baykal</LOCATION> in eastern <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>. 
The marathon will finish at <LOCATION>Pyongyang</LOCATION>, on the border of <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
There are 12 teams, mostly <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> bloc countries, running in the relay, 
according to <PERSON>Fulcher</PERSON>, 27. The race is a warmup to the <DATE>May 1990</DATE> "Run Down 
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>," a 16-city, 3,100-mile, four-month race that <PERSON>Fulcher</PERSON> has spent five 
months organizing. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031890-0173 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 191461 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 18, 1990, Sunday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 15; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
701 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO SPORTS ET CETERA: PLNC WOMEN FIRST IN CONFERENCE TRACK MEET 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The Point <LOCATION>Loma Nazarene</LOCATION> women's track team won the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State Athletic 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> championships at <ORGANIZATION>UC Santa Barbara</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, edging <LOCATION>Azusa Pacific</LOCATION>, 
128-120. 
</P>
<P>
The Crusaders won seven events, and the two-mile relay team of <PERSON>Melissa Mabe</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Sandy Cuevas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Vanessa Couch</PERSON> and <PERSON>Annette Ronnerman</PERSON> set a GSAC record of 9:40.6. 
</P>
<P>
Triple event winners were Ronnerman (also on the 400-meter and mile relays), 
<PERSON>Mabe</PERSON> (400 hurdles, mile relay) and <PERSON>Aminda Sloan</PERSON> (100 meters and 400 and mile 
relays). 
</P>
<P>
PLNC's men finished second to <LOCATION>Azusa Pacific</LOCATION>, 169-79. GSAC marks were 
established by Goshu Tadese in the 10,000 (31:38.60) and <PERSON>Dan Ratjes</PERSON> in the high 
jump (7-2 1/2). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Darla Vaughn</PERSON> won the 100 meters (12.2 seconds), 100 hurdles (14.38), and 200 
meters (24.75), but <LOCATION>San Diego State</LOCATION> lost to host USC 62-61, in a four-way meet 
that included <ORGANIZATION>Long Beach State</ORGANIZATION> (31) and <LOCATION>Cal State Los Angeles</LOCATION> (19). 
</P>
<P>
In the non-scoring men's meet, <PERSON>Brian Craft-Negrete</PERSON> high-jumped 7-0 1/4. <PERSON>Pat 
Thiss</PERSON> won the hammer at 193-9. 
</P>
<P>
BASEBALL 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kurt Archer</PERSON> threw a five-hit shutout as <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State</ORGANIZATION> defeated <ORGANIZATION>Sacramento 
State</ORGANIZATION>, 5-0, in a nonconference game at <ORGANIZATION>Charlie Smith Field</ORGANIZATION>. Archer improved to 
1-1, striking out five and walking four. He did not allow more than one hit in 
an inning. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Scott Dennison</PERSON> was three for four and scored a run for the Aztecs (16-8). 
<PERSON>Anthony Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Brian Grebech</PERSON> were each two for four. SDSU, which also won 
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, completes the three-game series with <ORGANIZATION>Sacramento State</ORGANIZATION> today at <TIME>1 p.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
Tom Cheek won the first game and lost the second as the <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> 
split a <ORGANIZATION>West Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION> doubleheader at <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Cheek threw 2 2/3 innings in the first game as USD (11-4, 7-7) scored five runs 
in the first inning and won, 5-3. In the second, <ORGANIZATION>Cheek</ORGANIZATION> (7-3) came on in the 
bottom of the ninth inning of a tie game and allowed a two-out home run to <PERSON>Mark 
Lewis</PERSON> as <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> (13-12-2, 8-5-1) won, 12-11. 
</P>
<P>
USD's <PERSON>Tony Moeder</PERSON> had a two-run homer to cap its five-run first in the first 
game. <PERSON>Rick Doane</PERSON> was three for four with two runs batted in, and <PERSON>Kevin Herde</PERSON> 
was three for five in the second game. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Scott Sharts of Cal State Northridge</ORGANIZATION> hit three home runs to power the Matadors 
past <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> International, 9-1, at <ORGANIZATION>Northridge</ORGANIZATION>. It was <PERSON>Shart</PERSON>'s second three-homer 
game of the season; he has 13. Northridge is 13-12, <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION> 8-15-1. 
</P>
<P>
SOFTBALL 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>San Diego State</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Michelle Wesson</PERSON> threw a three-hitter, and the Aztecs defeated 
<PERSON>Chapman</PERSON>, 4-0, in the first game to split a nonconference doubleheader. Wesson 
(5-7) allowed only four base runners and got all the support she needed when 
<PERSON>Julie Myers</PERSON> hit a run-scoring triple in the first. <PERSON>Stephanie Chapel</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tracy 
Stowe</PERSON> added RBIs. 
</P>
<P>
The Aztecs got only two hits, by <PERSON>Tonya Chamberlain</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Sue Campbell</ORGANIZATION>, in a 2-1 
loss in the second game. SDSU entered the day having won four of six games and 
is 6-15. Chapman is 20-8. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Cindy Oliver</PERSON> (4-6) struck out six in a three-hitter as <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION> broke an eight-game 
losing streak with a 4-0 victory over <ORGANIZATION>St. Mary</ORGANIZATION>'s at <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION> (7-14) hadn't scored a run in 42 innings until <PERSON>Michelle Hagen</PERSON> sacrificed 
and scored <PERSON>Karen Winkler</PERSON> in the first inning. 
</P>
<P>
MEN'S TENNIS 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>SDSU</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Ricardo Herrera</PERSON> lost in No. 1 singles to <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Jorge Ortega</PERSON>, 6-3, 
3-6, 6-4, but the Aztecs outlasted the <LOCATION>Lobos</LOCATION>, 5-3 in a <ORGANIZATION>Western Athletic 
Conference</ORGANIZATION> match at <ORGANIZATION>SDSU</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
No. 2 <ORGANIZATION>Tole Marinkovic</ORGANIZATION> defeated <ORGANIZATION>NM</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Warren Fulgenzi</PERSON>, 7-6, 6-0, and teamed with 
<PERSON>Herrera</PERSON> in No. 1 doubles for a 6-4, 6-3 victory over <LOCATION>Ortega</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Fulgenzi</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
SDSU (11-4, 5-0) meets co-WAC leader <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> (4-0) <DATE>Monday</DATE> at 2 in the final WAC 
match of the year before the tournament <DATE>April 30</DATE> -- <DATE>May 5</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Colorado State</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> advanced to the finals of the <ORGANIZATION>USD Invitational</ORGANIZATION> 
tournament with a 6-3 victory over <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>. The Toreros got victories at Nos. 1 
and 2 singles as <PERSON>Jose Luis Noriega</PERSON> defeated <PERSON>Thomas Adler</PERSON>, 6-4, 6-3, and <PERSON>Dan 
Mattera</PERSON> defeated <PERSON>Jay Maltby</PERSON>, 7-5, 7-6. 
</P>
<P>
Yale, a 6-3 winner over <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, faces 25th-ranked USD (13-2) today at 2. 
</P>
<P>
WOMEN'S TENNIS 
</P>
<P>
Seventh-ranked <LOCATION>Cal</LOCATION> defeated <LOCATION>San Diego State</LOCATION> 6-3 in a nonconference match. <PERSON>Dorey 
Brandt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nicole Storto</PERSON> won singles matches in straight sets for the 
18th-ranked Aztecs (6-7). Storto and <PERSON>Susan Hawke</PERSON> also won in doubles, 6-4, 6-2. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06091222 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06091222 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Mercury News Photographs by Michael Rondou; THE LOOKS OF
SPEED AT STANFORD; Jim Cramton of Stanford (far left) PHOTO: and Anne Lee of
Palo Alto High show their determination during the Stanford Track Challenge.
Cramton hands the baton to William Knight of Washington State during the
Pac-10-Big Ten mile relay. Lee jumps a personal-best 37 feet, 3 3/4 inches to
finish third in the high school girls' triple jump.; PHOTO: Ceci Hopp (215)
passes exhausted ex-Stanford teammate PattiSue Plumer, who won the mile in
4:31.53  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TRACK; CONTEST; RECORD; COLLEGE; STANFORD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Stanford Stadium mile record had stood for 11 years, but Kenya's Samuel
Kibiri, racing for Washington State, not only smashed it Saturday, he also
dragged the next two finishers across the line in what would have been record
time, too.;    Kibiri's 3-minute, 57.84-second finish on the climactic day of
the Stanford Track Challenge was nearly two seconds faster than ex-Arizona
State miler Ray Wicksel's 3:59.7 run in 1980. Indiana's Robert Kennedy crossed
second in 3:59.03 and Matt Giusto, the fourth-ranked American in the 1,500
meters last year, was third in 3:59.18.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  KENYAN BREAKS STANFORD STADIUM MILE RECORD
KIBIRI'S 3:57.84 SMASHES MARK  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Track and Field/Colleges  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>PattiSue Plumer</PERSON>, named the world's top woman middle-distance runner last
year by <ORGANIZATION>Track &amp; Field News</ORGANIZATION>, easily won the women's mile in 4:31.53.;    "I
never knew about the record," said <PERSON>Kibiri</PERSON>, whose victory added to the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>
10 Conference's winning margin over the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> in the Pac-10-Big Ten
Challenge portion of the meet. "Yesterday I was having problems with a hip
injury, and I just wanted to run a good race.";    <PERSON>Kibiri</PERSON> was third in the
mile at the recent <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> indoor championships, and his previous best for the
distance was 3:58.41.;    Comfortable pace;  "The pace (set the first two laps
by 800-meter runner <PERSON>Ray Brown</PERSON>) was very comfortable," <PERSON>Kibiri</PERSON> said. "I felt the
runners would leave too fast out of the start, but they never did.";    <ORGANIZATION>Kibiri</ORGANIZATION>
will return this <DATE>summer</DATE> to the Kenyan national team for the African
championships and the world championships in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, both in <LOCATION>August.</LOCATION>;   
<ORGANIZATION>Plumer</ORGANIZATION>'s race opened what will be a busy outdoor season after a fall and
winter mostly spent off the track. But that respite -- part intentional, part
accidental -- will be her last until after the Olympics next <DATE>summer</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Barcelona.</LOCATION>;    "From now until '92 there's not much down time," she said. "I
can't take two months off this <DATE>fall</DATE> like I did <DATE>last fall</DATE>.";    That layoff was
extended by moving at Thanksgiving, the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION>'s cold weather at <LOCATION>Christmas</LOCATION>
and flu in <DATE>January</DATE> that tempted her to skip much of the indoor season.;   
"But I didn't because I had already committed to those meets, the tickets had
been bought, the promotions done," she said.;    Middle-distance emphasis; 
Pointing toward The <ORGANIZATION>Athletics Congress</ORGANIZATION> nationals in <DATE>June</DATE> and then <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Plumer</PERSON> said she plans to continue her concentration on the 3,000 meters and
5,000 meters, in which she earned her top ranking last year.;    She's working
this <DATE>spring</DATE> as an assistant to Stanford track coach <PERSON>Brooks Johnson</PERSON>, who is her
personal coach, in addition to her law practice.;    "I wanted to go out a
little faster, a 2:12 instead of a 2:14. But running by myself and it being so
breezy, it was a good run," she said.;    "I'm frankly happy with a 4:31 on
this track (her personal best is 4:29). I trained pretty hard for the last
four weeks. I'm not ecstatic by any means, but this is a tough place for me to
run. On one hand, I don't want to lose on my home course. But this is where I
train every day, so it's tough coming in here and feeling like I'm not just on
another training run.";    <PERSON>Plumer</PERSON> won against the wind, measured at 3.1 meters
per second in the women's 100 meters shortly before her race, and outdistanced
<PERSON>Tina Colebrook</PERSON>, second in 4:39.23, and <PERSON>Ceci Hopp</PERSON>, a former teammate at
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, third in 4:41.99.;    That wind, however, did little to slow
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> sprinter <PERSON>Chryste Gaines.</PERSON>;    <PERSON>Gaines</PERSON> won the Pac-10-Big Ten women's
100 in 11.67 seconds, two-hundredths off her personal best, defeating <ORGANIZATION>Ohio
State</ORGANIZATION>'s Sue <PERSON>Walton</PERSON> in 11.98.;    The Pac-10 women defeated the Big Ten women
77-69. The Pac-10 men beat the Big Ten men 110-86.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JODY MEACHAM, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910331  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  722  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 31, 1991
00091222,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06206103 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06206103 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mary Neinast -- Mercury News  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFILE; PALO-ALTO; LAW; PROFESSIONAL; FITNESS  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AGE: 29;    HEIGHT: 5 feet 9  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SUSAN GOLDFARB  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Health &amp; Fitness
How I Stay Fit  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     WEIGHT: 128;    PERSONAL: Single and lives in <LOCATION>Menlo Park</LOCATION>;    OCCUPATION:
Corporate legal assistant for <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION> firm of <ORGANIZATION>Wilson, Sonsini, Goodrich &amp;
Rosati.</ORGANIZATION>;    FITNESS BACKGROUND: <PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON> says she is naturally athletic
because everything she has tried -- like snow skiing at age 4 -- she has done
well. As a youngster, her playtime was always centered on running games and
swimming. At 13, she took to tennis.;    "When you run or swim you don't have
to think about what you're doing. But in tennis, there is a mental challenge.
You always have to be thinking about strategy, what you need to do to win and
be able to adjust your game as you go through the process." After a few
lessons, she played pretty well.;    She'd taken quite a few lessons by the
time she entered high school. While playing competitively during the school
year, she also ran and worked out with weights. Every <DATE>summer</DATE>, she attended
tennis camp and swam.;    All was fine for a while with her routine at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of California</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>. She was playing intramural tennis three
times a week, swimming laps, using her bike for transportation and running
four to five miles on pavement four times a week. In spite of discomfort in
her ankle, she continued running until "incredible shooting pains" forced her
to seek medical attention. It took two surgeries, casts, crutches and nearly
four years before her rehabilitation from what turned out to be stress
fractures was complete.;    And it was another two years before she developed
the confidence to step on the court again. To deal with the disappointment,
she swam six days a week during her long recovery. "It got awfully old not
being able to do what I wanted to do, but at least I had that.";    REGIMEN:
<PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON> returned to tennis a year ago and has been playing four times a week.
A "power player" and a "hard hitter," she says she prefers a singles match
because she gets a better workout. She and her <ORGANIZATION>United States Tennis
Association</ORGANIZATION> A-ranked women's team won a divisional championship recently. "The
competition is very local for now.";    She takes an aerobics class once a
week and, to give her body a break from her high-impact activities, she still
swims a mile once or twice a week and enjoys bike riding with friends on
weekends.;    RESULTS: <PERSON>Goldfarb</PERSON> hasn't quite shaken the fear that she could
re-injure her ankle. "But I've learned to listen to what my body tells me. And
no more running for me. I used to enjoy it, but now I don't even want to
try.";    GOALS: "To play tennis consistently and avoid mistakes.";   
OBSTACLES: "When I take the game too seriously and feel bummed after losing a
match, I have to remind myself how lucky I am to be playing again." Also
frustrating, she says, is getting tied up at work and having to miss a planned
workout.;    TIPS AND COMMENTS: "I like to swim and bicycle, but what I like
the most is tennis." If she had to give it up, she'd replace it with other
activities -- like more swimming and bicycling, she says, because, in addition
to staying healthy and feeling fit, working out is her favorite way to have
fun and make friends.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Sue Chenoweth  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910724  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  567  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday July 24, 1991
00206103,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06054196 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06054196 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Allison  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPORT; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Noureddine Morceli, the sensational 20-year-old Algerian, made a serious run
at the world indoor mile record, but settled for meet and track marks in
winning at the World Indoor Track and Field Championships Friday night in New
York.;    Morceli led throughout the race and was on pace to break Eamonn
Coghlan's world record of 3 minutes, 49.78 seconds going into the final
quarter mile.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MORCELI MISSES IN BID FOR INDOOR-MILE MARK
ALLISON GAINS SECOND POLE OF THE SEASON  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Sports Digest  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     But without anyone to push him, he slowed and finished in 3:52.99.;    In
another meet highlight, <PERSON>Lance Deal</PERSON> shattered the world indoor record in the
35-pound weight throw twice, reaching 79 feet, 3 3/4 inches on his final
throw.;     MOTOR SPORTS: <PERSON>Davey Allison</PERSON> made it two for two this season in
NASCAR Cup Series qualifying by wheeling his <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> to the pole for <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s
400-mile race in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>. Allison also won the pole for last week's
<LOCATION>Daytona</LOCATION> 500.;  TENNIS: Top-seeded <PERSON>Ivan Lendl</PERSON> and No. 5 <PERSON>Michael Chang</PERSON> rolled to
straight-set victories in a <MONEY>$750,000</MONEY> tournament in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, advancing
to the semifinals. Lendl powered his way past <PERSON>Darren Cahill</PERSON> 7-6 (7-2), 6-3,
and <PERSON>Chang</PERSON> dispatched <PERSON>Jeff Tarango</PERSON> 6-3, 7-5. . . . <PERSON>Stefan Edberg</PERSON> cruised into
the semifinals of a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> tournament in <LOCATION>Stuttgart</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> with a 6-2,
6-3 triumph over <PERSON>Magnus Gustafsson</PERSON>. . . . <PERSON>Mary Joe Fernandez</PERSON>, the fifth-ranked
women's tennis player in the world, withdrew from a <MONEY>$350,000</MONEY> women's
tournament set to begin <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION> because of influenza.; 
COLLEGES: Ten days after cutting four sports, <ORGANIZATION>William &amp; Mary</ORGANIZATION> President <PERSON>Paul
Verkuil</PERSON> said the college would reinstate women's basketball, men's wrestling
and men's and women's swimming. . . . <PERSON>Bump Elliott</PERSON>, the dean of <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION>
athletic directors who has guided <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>'s athletic department for 21 years, is
retiring. He is 66.;  FOOTBALL: Former Stanford linebacker <PERSON>Eric Snelson</PERSON> was
drafted by the <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> Surge in the third round of the <ORGANIZATION>WLAF</ORGANIZATION>'s linebacker
draft. . . . Former <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> investment broker <PERSON>Oscar Ayala Jr.</PERSON>, convicted of
defrauding clients, including 20 former and current pro football players, of
more than <MONEY>$2.4 million</MONEY>, has been sentenced to 41 months in federal prison.; 
MISCELLANY: <PERSON>Jess Stayrook</PERSON> rolled his second 300 game in as many days and is
the No. 1 seed for today's final round of the <ORGANIZATION>Professional Bowlers Association</ORGANIZATION>
<MONEY>$130,000</MONEY> Flagship City Open in <LOCATION>Erie</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION> . . . The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, a favorite
to win the first women's world soccer championship, was drawn into a
qualifying group with <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>. The first <ORGANIZATION>FIFA</ORGANIZATION>
women's championship is scheduled to be played in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> from <DATE>Nov. 16-30</DATE>. . . .
<PERSON>Kenny Dalglish</PERSON>, the coach of English soccer champion <LOCATION>Liverpool</LOCATION>, quit because
of what he said was the constant pressure of the job.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Mercury News Wire Services  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910223  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  472  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday February 23, 1991
00054196,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06360027 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06360027 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Apichell has found the Bay Area to be 'bicycle heaven.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HEALTH; FITNESS; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AGE: 41 on Friday;   HEIGHT: 5-feet-5  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LOUISE APICHELL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Health &amp; Fitness; How I Stay Fit  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     WEIGHT: 118 pounds;   PERSONAL: Single and lives in Mountain View;  
OCCUPATION: Senior technical writer who was laid off last month.;   FITNESS
BACKGROUND: There weren't girls to "pal around with" in the rural area of
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> where she grew up, so Apichell joined the boys for football,
baseball and basketball. She played varsity basketball as a freshman, pitched
and played shortstop for the softball team and would have loved the
opportunity to excel at track and field, she says, because she loved to run.
But the school didn't have a track. During the <DATE>summer</DATE> she worked as a
lifeguard, taught swimming and competed in springboard diving.;   Except for
intramurals, sports were on the back burner during college because "my
demanding English major required reading too many books and writing too many
papers." But during the summers, while her friends were working as waitresses,
she used the facilities at the swim and tennis club where she worked.;  
Before returning to school to earn a second degree in journalism, <PERSON>Apichell</PERSON>
taught high school English, coached basketball, ran in 5K and 10K races and
played rugby for the <ORGANIZATION>University of Maryland</ORGANIZATION> for eight years. She also taught
freshman English at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION>, where she played rugby, took up
triathlons and competed in co-ed soccer.;   It was "all soccer" when she moved
to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE> and joined an over-30 women's team. Because the goal of
the team was to win the national cup, they averaged three two-hour practices a
week year-round. And many of the practices were preceded by four-mile runs to
warm up. In <DATE>1988</DATE> they made it to the national tournament, but lost by one
goal.;   As new teammates in their early 30s seemed to be getting "younger and
faster," Apichell started looking for new outlets. While phasing out soccer,
she found "bicycle heaven" in the <LOCATION>Bay Area</LOCATION> and has been riding and running
ever since. The past year, she completed about 10 100-mile century rides and
placed in several biathlon competitions that combine running and bicycling.;  
REGIMEN: When employed, <PERSON>Apichell</PERSON> ran three to four miles every day during her
lunch hour and rode her bike in the evening until sundown. Now that it's dark
in the <TIME>evening</TIME>, she has upped her daytime distance to six miles and has
replaced cycling in the evening with a few hours of tennis. Weekends are still
the same, she says -- bike rides of 40 to 60 miles each day along steep routes
that include Page Mill and <LOCATION>Kings Mountain</LOCATION> roads, <LOCATION>Tunitas Creek</LOCATION> and Mount
Tamalpais.;   RESULTS: Being in good physical condition has carried over
mentally and spiritually, she says. "My health is excellent, my self-esteem is
high and, when I go into a job interview, I feel confident and proud of my
abilities.";   GOALS: To win a biathlon -- because second place is not good
enough -- and to be able to finish all five mountain passes in the 147-mile
<LOCATION>Markleeville Death Ride</LOCATION> in <DATE>May</DATE>. "And I've always wanted to try kayaking.";  
OBSTACLES: "Sometimes I wish I had a buddy to run or bicycle with regularly.
But the independence is nice. I have from sunrise to sundown to plan my
workout.";   TIPS AND COMMENTS: "I am not a quitter. Sports has taught me to
hang in there until the whistle is blown. I don't give up."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Sue Chenoweth  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911225  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4E  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  586  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, December 25, 1991
00360027,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06136168 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06136168 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Connor plays tennis against younger men every weekend.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FITNESS; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AGE: 72;    HEIGHT: 5-feet-10 1/2  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BILL CONNOR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Health &amp; Fitness
How I Stay Fit  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     WEIGHT: 170 pounds;    PERSONAL: Married 48 years. He has three children,
four grandchildren and lives in <LOCATION>Portola Valley.</LOCATION>;    OCCUPATION: Owner, <ORGANIZATION>Alpha I
Insurance Brokers Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>;    FITNESS BACKGROUND: Growing up in
<LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>, he spent a lot of time bodysurfing and playing volleyball
on the beach at <LOCATION>Santa Monica</LOCATION>. "In those days, we'd chip in a nickel each for
<MONEY>20 cents</MONEY>' worth of gas to get there and back. When we didn't have enough
money, we'd ride our bikes like hell for 20 miles to get there instead.";   
He's never been a speedster, he says, but he's been active and competitive
throughout his life in many sports -- with one exception, the time his B-17
was shot down during World War II and he spent nine months in a German prison.
Normally, he played touch football on weekends and did a lot of snow skiing
with his family. But when a two-man volleyball game in the sand "ruined my
weekend" 26 years ago, he decided his physical routine was insufficient. He
started running in the mornings and felt a tremendous difference right away,
he says.;    REGIMEN: <PERSON>Connor</PERSON> is still running 2 1/2 to three miles starting at
<TIME>5:15 a.m</TIME>. When he gets home, he does 200 strokes on a rowing machine, a series
of sit-ups, leg-ups, push-ups, stretching exercises, a weight routine with
40-pound barbells and by 6:10 he's in the shower.;    <PERSON>Connor</PERSON> started playing
tennis at 50. "I play every chance I get, and every <DATE>Saturday</DATE> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
morning with a group of younger guys." He's a proficient skier who, since the
age of 66, has won gold, silver and bronze medals -- plus a few personal
"crash and burn awards" -- in <ORGANIZATION>NASTAR</ORGANIZATION> downhill racing. He says he's only a
recreational swimmer, but he placed first in 50-meter freestyle swimming and
second in tennis in the Palo Alto/Stanford Senior Olympic Games two years
ago.;    "Alcohol makes me feel like I'm pulling a trailer," he says, so he's
given it up. And because he believes it's important not to overeat, "I never
go back for seconds.";    RESULTS: "It's been a lot of fun feeling 40 for the
past 30 years!";    GOALS: "To live long enough to get even with my kids by
seeing their children turn into teen-agers.";    OBSTACLES: "A flu bug or an
injury. It's hard to start all over again if you lay off too long. I don't run
if it rains, but I think I live in the eye of the hurricane because it never
seems to rain when I run.";    TIPS AND COMMENTS: "Fifty years ago I thought
it would be great to live to the year <DATE>2000</DATE> and, if I can buy some more time,
it looks like I'm going to make it. But if it ended tomorrow, I'd have had a
great time."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Sue Chenoweth  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910515  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  498  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday May 15, 1991
00136168,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06051206 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06051206 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Tennis player Sylvano Simone takes a break from the courts only
on Sundays.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HEALTH; FITNESS; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AGE: 27;    HEIGHT: 5 feet, 9 1/2 inches  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SYLVANO SIMONE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Health &amp; Fitness
How I Stay Fit
How do you keep in shape? Send us a brief letter of explanation and recent
full-length photograph, along with your address and telephone number. We'll
print profiles on other personal fitness programs in future issues. Write to:
How I Stay Fit in care of the Health &amp; Fitness section, the Mercury News, 750
Ridder Park Drive, San Jose 95190.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     WEIGHT: 165 pounds;    PERSONAL: "Very single," he says, which is good
because he has to travel a lot. He lives in <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>;    OCCUPATION:
Professional tennis player;    FITNESS BACKGROUND: While growing up in a house
next door to the Los Altos Golf and <ORGANIZATION>Country Club</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Simone</PERSON> says he loved to
watch people play tennis. At age 7, he got his turn with a racket he retrieved
from a trash can there. For the next two years, <PERSON>Simone</PERSON> collected tennis balls
on the courts in exchange for lessons. He played well in all the sports
offered in school, he says, but during the summers he lived on the tennis
court for 4 to 6 hours each day.;    "I always felt there was something
special about me as an athlete," says <PERSON>Simone</PERSON>. And it was confirmed when he was
offered a scholarship after his junior year in high school to <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s
prestigious <ORGANIZATION>Bollettieri Tennis Academy</ORGANIZATION> -- "a concentration camp," he says,
referring to its intense program.;    After graduation from high school, he
competed in the French circuit before returning to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to continue his
education. At <ORGANIZATION>Foothill College</ORGANIZATION> he was part of the second-ranked doubles team
in the nation among junior colleges. This impressed the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arkansas</ORGANIZATION>
and earned him another scholarship. Simone was there a year, earning A's and
B's and juggling his studies, his sport and his social life, when he decided
to quit -- temporarily -- a year short of earning degrees in philosophy and
psychology in order to pursue tennis professionally.;    For the past year and
a half, he has competed in satellite circuits throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
abroad. His goal is to qualify for the <ORGANIZATION>Volvo</ORGANIZATION> men's tournament in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>
next year. He's currently ranked 787th in the world.;    REGIMEN: After a
stretching and stationary bicycle workout at an athletic club six mornings a
week, he's on the court by <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> for 2 1/2 hours of tennis. He spends two
hours, three afternoons a week with his coach in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. And when he
gets home, he runs five to seven 6-minute miles around a track. (If he's
tired, he slows his pace to a 7- or 8-minute mile.) An hour of weight training
at the club on alternative days is followed by speed and balance drills on the
tennis court with an aerobics teacher. Because the sport is so intense, he has
started practicing yoga to learn to relax. He sleeps from <TIME>9 p.m.</TIME> to 7 a.m
during the week, but on <DATE>Sundays</DATE>, "My racket and tennis shoes are locked in the
closet!";    RESULTS: "I feel like a gladiator with a net. Everything is in
balance physically, mentally, nutritionally and holistically and I am ready to
win.";    GOALS: "To play center court against the top seed at <LOCATION>Wimbledon</LOCATION>. And
I'll have to win more than once -- otherwise, people will think it was a
fluke!";    OBSTACLES: "Some mornings I wish it was raining because I don't
want to get out of bed. But because I have pushed myself to the limit many
times, I know what my body can do and when it needs a rest.";    TIPS AND
COMMENTS: "My full-time love and commitment is to tennis for now. I've always
been a good student, so when my peak has passed professionally, I will finish
school."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  -- Sue Chenoweth  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910220  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  642  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday February 20, 1991
00051206,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA080290-0118 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 255922 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
August 2, 1990, Thursday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 4; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
606 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PEOPLE: DISTANCE RUNNER: 49 ONLY A NUMBER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HERBERT J. VIDA 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
At a time when most men are slowing down, <PERSON>Jurgen Ankenbrand</PERSON>, 49, is stepping up 
the pace. 
</P>
<P>
He recently was one of 14 men and two women out of a field of 22 who completed 
the torturous 146-mile Death Valley-to-Mt. Whitney run. 
</P>
<P>
Now he wants to visit <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> for a 50-mile race alongside the canal. 
</P>
<P>
"That's the kind of thing I'm looking for, something different," said the 
<LOCATION>Fountain Valley</LOCATION> man who started competitive running only three years ago, about 
the same time that he was divorced. 
</P>
<P>
"I had to do something to use up my energy," said Germany-born Ankenbrand, who 
claims he never participated in sports as a youngster. Or for that matter, 
until he was 30 years old. 
</P>
<P>
"I was always working and never had time for sports," he said in a thick German 
accent. 
</P>
<P>
Before his current job as food services director for <ORGANIZATION>El Acanto Convalescent 
Home</ORGANIZATION> in the <ORGANIZATION>City of Industry</ORGANIZATION>, Ankenbrand worked as a chef at some of the 
leading hotels in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I got tired of working nights and weekends. It didn't leave much time for 
other things," said the one-time food services director at <LOCATION>Cal State Long 
Beach</LOCATION>, where co-workers urged him to try long-distance running. 
</P>
<P>
Ankenbrand had been playing seven sets of tennis every <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for 20 years with 
the same partner (<PERSON>Don Ogden</PERSON> of Orange), "so they thought I was in good enough 
shape to run a marathon." 
</P>
<P>
That was three years ago and without much training, Ankenbrand has run in 16 
marathons in an average time of 4 hours and 10 minutes, finishing them all. 
</P>
<P>
But he has cut his tennis playing to only five sets each <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, noting that 
"tennis is now my second sport." 
</P>
<P>
Unlike other marathoners, who run upwards of 100 miles a week, "I don't like 
regimented workouts. Maybe I'm lazy," he said, noting that he runs only 20 
miles a week, in training or not. 
</P>
<P>
However, at this point in his life, Ankenbrand is getting bored with marathons. 
</P>
<P>
"It's no longer a challenge," he said, pointing out that <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of all marathon 
runners finish. 
</P>
<P>
"I need something more challenging," said <PERSON>Ankenbrand</PERSON>, who has run the <LOCATION>Los 
Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> marathons and two 50-mile races this year. 
</P>
<P>
That was the reason for the 146-mile Death Valley run last month. 
</P>
<P>
"It was my most challenging race and there were times when I wanted to stop," 
he admits. "The heat was up to 115 degrees and I had so many blisters on my 
feet." 
</P>
<P>
Some of the other runners in the international field of competitors dropped 
out. Most of the other athletes were in their 30s. 
</P>
<P>
"I was hurting and my body was telling me to quit, but I had the determination 
and will power you get from maturity," he said. "I just kept going." 
</P>
<P>
It's that philosophy that keeps Ankenbrand running. 
</P>
<P>
"You have to have a positive attitude," he said. "It has never occurred to me 
that I would not finish a race." 
</P>
<P>
And now, <PERSON>Ankenbrand</PERSON> said, all his races will be 50 miles or longer and he feels 
his age is not a factor. 
</P>
<P>
"I'm 49, but I think of myself as younger than that," he said. "The number 49 
doesn't mean anything to me. It's just a number." 
</P>
<P>
And just to prove it, he plans to compete in a triathlon in <DATE>August</DATE>, the 
100-mile Angeles Crest Trail Run in <DATE>September</DATE> and the San Juan 50-Mile Trail 
Run in <DATE>November</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Ankenbrand has also learned that rewards are not substantial for long-distance 
running. 
</P>
<P>
He received a T-shirt for finishing the 146-mile Death Valley-Mt. Whitney Run. 
</P>
<P>
Acknowledgments -- <PERSON>Suzanne Schultz</PERSON>, who teaches special education students at 
<ORGANIZATION>Springbrook Elementary School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Irvine</LOCATION>, was named Teacher of the Year by the 
school and later received a letter from <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON>, lauding her for the 
honor. "Thank you for caring," wrote the First Lady. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Jurgen Ankenbrand has finally found time for sports at 49. ROBERT 
LACHMAN / Los Angeles Times; Photo, COLOR, PEOPLE: At a time when most people 
are slowing down, Jurgen Ankenbrand, 49, above, is just cranking up. He became 
a marathon runner 3 years ago and is now looking for other challenges. Herbert 
J. Vida's column. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900123-0226 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-23-90 1145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-PRI--Athletes Adv25-1stLd-Writethru b2060 01-23 0959</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-PRI--Athletes, Adv 25 - 1st Ld-Writethru, b2060,0987</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv25</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thursday, Jan. 25, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Age-Group Competition Soars Among Older Athletes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT that Nicklaus' birthday Sunday sted
Monday</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SHEILA NORMAN-CULP</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Jack Nicklaus</PERSON> can scorch the fairways like
practically no one else, but this month he became just another
statistic in a growing trend.
   <PERSON>Nicklaus</PERSON>, who turned 50 on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, is now eligible to join the
PGA Seniors tour. He's also joining _ albeit with not quite as much
fanfare _ the exploding number of older Americans who compete in
age-group sports.
   The attraction is simple: try your hardest, be your best, and in
five to 10 years be reborn into an older group. Masters swimmers,
for example, compete in five-year intervals up to 90-94. The <ORGANIZATION>United
States Tennis Federation</ORGANIZATION> sanctions matches for men 85 and older and
women 75 and older. Age-group competitions also are organized in
bicycling, track and field, marathons and triathlons.
   The system encourages older Americans to keep competing, because
at least once every few years they get to be the youngest kid on
the block.
   ``You like to come in at the bottom of your age group and blow
them away,'' said <PERSON>Dr. George McVey</PERSON>, 62, of <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, who has
competed for 17 years in masters swimming and has been
internationally ranked in the breaststroke.
   ``It's amazing _ the condition of these people,'' he said of
those attending national masters swim meets.
``Seventy-five-year-olds can go up and down the pool like you
wouldn't believe.''
   ``A couple of years ago, our oldest category was 50-plus,'' said
<PERSON>Gary Scott</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Triathlon Federation@USA</ORGANIZATION>. ``Now it's 70-plus.''
   These older triathletes aren't running mini-events, either. They
are in the same grueling races attempted by athletes 50 years their
junior.
   ``We had one 64-year-old woman who finished in a decent time at
the Ironman,'' <PERSON>Scott</PERSON> said. ``She beat a lot of men in their
thirties.''
   The Ironman is one of the world's most prestigious triathlons,
held in <LOCATION>Kailua-Kona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, each year. The woman, <PERSON>Joanita Reed</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, swam a 2.4-mile ocean race, cycled 112 miles over
hills and ran a 26.2-mile marathon, all in the same day. She
finished in 14 hours, 31 minutes and 55 seconds.
   ``We have experienced a dramatic increase in masters riders in
the last five years,'' agreed <PERSON>Kyle Woodlief</PERSON>, spokesman for the
<ORGANIZATION>United States Cycling Federation</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colorado Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION> ``Our
oldest licensed racer is 93.''
   That rider, <PERSON>Fred Knoller</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Lauderdale-By-The-Sea</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>,
competed in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Nationals from <DATE>1976 to 1985</DATE>, when he was 89.
Knoller has stopped competing but is still a big fan of the move
toward smaller age-group categories.
   ``When I was in my 50's, I was still racing against
40-year-olds,'' he said. He keeps his membership to get the
newsletter and find out how friends are doing. ``Some of these boys
60, 65, are really good. Real pros.''
   Last <DATE>June</DATE>, the cream of American senior athletes gathered to go
for the gold in <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, at the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Senior Olympics</ORGANIZATION>.
The 3,452 athletes, ranging from 55 to 91, earned the chance to
compete through strong performances at qualifying meets, where more
than 100,000 seniors tested their mettle.
   ``You know the saying, `If you don't use it, you lose it,'' said
<PERSON>Sylvia Auerbach Swartz</PERSON>, 77, who with her sisters Rose, 74, and
<LOCATION>Pearl</LOCATION>, 68, earned 12 medals at the Senior Olympics. ``It's
important not to let the joints get stiff. You've got to keep them
going.''
   Swartz, of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, said a youthful diet of volleyball,
softball, basketball, lacrosse and speedball, along with some
middle-aged tennis and ping-pong laid the base for her success.
Medals in field events came from weekly training, pointers from
local coaches, and encouragement from her sisters.
   ``We don't compete against each other, though,'' she said.
``That's why we are still talking.''
   At the <ORGANIZATION>VIII World Veterans Championships</ORGANIZATION> last <DATE>summer</DATE> in <LOCATION>Eugene</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION> _ billed as the largest track meet in history, former Olympic
athletes faced top-flight but unknown competitors from around the
world. Many of the 4,950 athletes produced times and distances that
were the talk of the meet.
   <PERSON>Paula Schneiderhan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> produced a world record in
the womens' 65-69 200-meter sprint with a time of 31.65 seconds.
   Although seniors are still a rather small segment of the sports
population, one industry expert says when they do enjoy a sport,
they go at it with gusto.
   ``The mature market incidence in most sports is pretty low,''
said <PERSON>Harvey Lauer</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>American Sports Data Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a
research firm in <LOCATION>Hartsdale</LOCATION>.
   ``But if you look at the people who do run, for example, and are
over 55, they do it with a vengeance,'' he said. ``Tennis players
over 55 play tennis more than tennis players in general. It's a
time factor.''
   Although some age-group seniors were top athletes in their prime
_ like <PERSON>Rose Auerbach</PERSON>, national AAU javelin champ in <DATE>1937</DATE> and <DATE>1938</DATE> _
many more found the joy of competition much later in life. The
80-to-84 category, for example, is the fastest-growing age group at
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Masters Swimming</ORGANIZATION> meets.
   <PERSON>Dan Gruender</PERSON>, the president of <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Masters Swimming</ORGANIZATION>, began
competing only after following his wife, <PERSON>Edie</PERSON>, to <ORGANIZATION>Masters</ORGANIZATION> swim
meets. At 61, <PERSON>Mrs. Gruender</PERSON> is internationally ranked in the
butterfly, freestyle and individual medley.
   ``As the greying of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> takes place, people realize that
staying active is the one way to improve the quality of your life.
It's also very satisfying. And that's what it's all about,'' he
said. ``Self-improvement is the touchstone we push. We don't care
if it takes you 3 minutes to swim a lap. Next time make it 2:59.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 25</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050290-0034 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 212662 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 2, 1990, Wednesday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 5B; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
683 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
COLLEGE NOTEBOOK: TOP ATHLETES EAGER TO TRY FAST TRACK AT UCSD 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JIM LINDGREN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
What started out as a "last chance" track and field meet for college athletes 
to gain national qualifying times is turning into an international gathering of 
world-class talent. 
</P>
<P>
UC <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION> is host for the meet at <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
It was designed as an opportunity for college athletes to qualify for their 
national meets. But word got around to some top-notch talent that <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION>'s new 
state-of-the-art track was again going to be made available. 
</P>
<P>
Soon, <PERSON>Brazilian Joaquim Cruz</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>American Ocky Clark</ORGANIZATION> wanted in on the 800-meter 
run. Likewise, <PERSON>Steve Scott</PERSON>, the American record-holder in the mile, and <PERSON>Dub 
Myers</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> champion from <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, wanted to run the 1,500. 
</P>
<P>
Canadians <PERSON>Ray Lazdins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rob McManus</PERSON>, conveniently training in the area, 
decided to enter the discus. 
</P>
<P>
But the kicker might be a small contingent of Estonian javelin throwers, who 
came to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> to begin training for the European season. Sulev Lepik, 
<PERSON>Meelis Jaarv</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Toivo Moorast</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Donald Sild</PERSON> will compete in the their 
specialty. 
</P>
<P>
They will also be holding a javelin clinic this afternoon at <TIME>1:30</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Juri Tamm</PERSON>, bronze medalist for the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> in the hammer throw in <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>, will also 
be on hand today. He and world-renowned coach <PERSON>Anatoli Bondartchouk</PERSON> conducted a 
hammer clinic <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"These guys (Soviets) are the lords of hammer throwing," said <PERSON>Tony Salerno</PERSON>, 
<ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> throwing coach. 
</P>
<P>
Last week, <ORGANIZATION>Point Loma Nazarene</ORGANIZATION> freshman <PERSON>Ronnie Skold</PERSON> won six events -- the 100, 
200, long jump and triple jump, the 100 hurdles and 400 relay -- at the first 
City Collegiate Championships at <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION>. He could conceivably enter eight -- 
adding the 400 hurdles and 1,600 relay -- in the <ORGANIZATION>NAIA District III</ORGANIZATION> meet but 
probably will not enter the sprints. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>San Diego State</LOCATION> junior <PERSON>Mike Magruder</PERSON> had just two at-bats with one single and a 
run batted in heading into his first start in <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s opening game of a 
doubleheader against <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Magruder responded by going two for four with a double and a home run -- rare 
because of the way it happened. 
</P>
<P>
In the sixth inning with two on, <PERSON>Magruder</PERSON> was instructed to bunt to move the 
runners over, but <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> was thinking the same the thing and had both the 
first baseman and third baseman charging. 
</P>
<P>
Magruder squared to bunt, noticed what was going on and pulled his bat back. 
The result was a three-run homer over the left center field fence. 
</P>
<P>
What are the odds of such an occurence? Ask <PERSON>Magruder</PERSON>. He's an engineering major 
who graduated first in his class at both <LOCATION>Ellensburg</LOCATION> High in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Taft 
Community College</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ed Collins</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> was named the District <PERSON>VIII</PERSON> coach of 
the year by the <ORGANIZATION>Intercollegiate Tennis Coaches Assn</ORGANIZATION>. Collins is under 
consideration for national coach of the year. 
</P>
<P>
In 12 years at <ORGANIZATION>USD</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Collins</PERSON> is 262-119, including 21-5 this year. The Toreros, 
champions of the <ORGANIZATION>West Coast Conference</ORGANIZATION>, are ranked 17th and should be selected 
for the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA Tournament</ORGANIZATION> next week. 
</P>
<P>
The women's tennis teams at <ORGANIZATION>SDSU</ORGANIZATION> (ranked 12th) and USD (14th) are expected to 
receive <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> bids this week. 
</P>
<P>
SDSU won the <ORGANIZATION>Big West Conference</ORGANIZATION> title for the fifth year in a row last week in 
<LOCATION>Ojai</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Carol Plunkett</PERSON> was chosen the Big West coach of the year. 
</P>
<P>
USD finished second in the <ORGANIZATION>WCC</ORGANIZATION> tournament, but not until <ORGANIZATION>Pepperdine</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Ginger 
Helgeson</PERSON> defeated <ORGANIZATION>USD</ORGANIZATION>'s Sakolwan Kacharoen, 3-6, 6-1, 6-4, in the singles final 
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>San Diego Tennis &amp; Racquet Club</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The tournament was held two weekends ago at <ORGANIZATION>St. Mary</ORGANIZATION>'s, but rain caused the 
delay of the singles and doubles finals. Kacharoen, a sophomore from <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> 
and seeded seventh, could have given USD a tie if she had upset top-seeded 
<PERSON>Helgeson</PERSON>, who is ranked fourth in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
In the two-year existence of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Coast Volleyball Conference</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Nate 
Brown</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UCSD</ORGANIZATION> has been selected the player of the year twice. And <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> is just 
a sophomore. UCSD went undefeated for the second year in a row and won the PCVC 
Tournament <DATE>Saturday</DATE> at <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
UCSD's women's water polo team is No. 1 ranked and seeded first heading into 
the <ORGANIZATION>USA National Tournament</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>this weekend</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION>. UCSD is 21-0-1. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06088256 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06088256 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  STANFORD; COLLEGE; TRACK; SPORT; MARKETING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The Pac-10-Big Ten challenge is a gimmick. Even Stanford track coach Brooks
Johnson concedes that. The question is whether the gimmick is a
crowd-pleaser.;    For Johnson, the three-day Track Challenge that begins this
afternoon at Stanford Stadium presents solutions to a couple of critical
problems. It's an attempt to focus public attention on track. And it's an
attempt to make money.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE REAL CHALLENGE IS SELLING TRACK
STANFORD SEEKING FANS AND MONEY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on this page.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> says the sport needs both badly, and among the 3,500 athletes
expected to compete are several <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> champions and Olympians he hopes will
boost the gate and give television something entertaining to broadcast.;   
"Track and field has been the object of too much media-bashing lately because
our meets are dying," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. "Non-revenue (college) sports are going to
have to pull their own wagon or stay parked. If they don't, universities are
going to eliminate non-revenue sports as we know them.";    The athletes will
represent 35 colleges and more than 200 high schools.;    But the key is the
Pac-10-Big Ten rivalry <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, which actually will be played out by athletes
from <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Washington State</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> 10 Conference
against those from <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> of the <ORGANIZATION>Big
Ten.</ORGANIZATION>;    The Pac-10-Big Ten aspect enabled <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> to sell his meet to the
<ORGANIZATION>Pacific Sports Network</ORGANIZATION>, a cable TV producer, which will televise portions of
the meet live or tape-delayed to about 40 states. And TV brought in a
sponsor.;    "I think by the time we start selling tickets, we will have
covered the rest of our costs," <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> said. "I just hope we'll have good
weather.";    The Pac-10-Big Ten competition will be in a men's and women's
two-mile relay, men's and women's 100 meters, men's and women's shuttle
hurdles relay, men's and women's mile and men's 3,000-meter steeplechase.;   
In addition, there will be invitational miles for women and men, with
Olympians <PERSON>PattiSue Plumer</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jeff Atkinson</PERSON> heading the respective fields.
There will also be a 40-yard dash for football players including <PERSON>Glyn Milburn</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Stanford</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sheldon Canley</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Jose State</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mike Mayweather</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>Robert Smith</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Ohio State</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JODY MEACHAM, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910328  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  372  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday March 28, 1991
00088256,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050689-0048 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 53391 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 6, 1989, Saturday, San Diego County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 9B; Column 5; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
580 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAN DIEGO SPORTS ET CETERA: AZTECS USE HOME RUNS TO SWEEP BYU 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The knock against <ORGANIZATION>San Diego State</ORGANIZATION>'s baseball team this season has been its lack 
of power. Tell that to <ORGANIZATION>Brigham Young</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Aztecs swept a <ORGANIZATION>Western Athletic Conference</ORGANIZATION> doubleheader <DATE>Friday</DATE> from <ORGANIZATION>BYU</ORGANIZATION>, 
6-2 and 7-6, by hitting four home runs in the first game and three in the 
second, including <PERSON>Brian Lutes</PERSON>' game-winning three-run homer in the top of 
seventh and final inning. 
</P>
<P>
Heading into another doubleheader against BYU <DATE>today</DATE> in <LOCATION>Provo</LOCATION>, SDSU is 33-20, 
14-6. BYU fell to 40-14, 18-7. The Aztecs, <ORGANIZATION>BYU</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> (35-19, 17-5) are 
battling for first place in the WAC with six games remaining for each. 
</P>
<P>
SDSU trailed, 6-2, entering the seventh of the second game. After <PERSON>Brian Dunn</PERSON> 
reached base on an error, and <PERSON>Jeff Barry</PERSON> singled with one out, <PERSON>Harry Henderson</PERSON> 
singled in <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>. One out later, <PERSON>Lutes</PERSON> homered to center to give the Aztecs a 
7-6 lead. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Marshall</PERSON> (3-3) was the winner in relief. 
</P>
<P>
In the first game, <PERSON>Henderson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Billy Miller</PERSON> (three for three), <PERSON>Anthony Johnson</PERSON> 
(three for three) and <PERSON>Barry</PERSON> hit home runs, accounting for all six runs. <PERSON>Rob 
Brown</PERSON> (9-4) pitched a four-hitter, struck out seven and yielded just one earned 
run. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> scored four runs in the bottom of the eighth to 
escape with a 9-8 victory. <PERSON>Chris Stout</PERSON> (three hits) and <PERSON>Parris Sarianell</PERSON> (two 
doubles) led USD (22-30-1). Riverside scored five runs in the ninth. <PERSON>James 
Ferguson</PERSON> came in with one out in the ninth to pick up his third save. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Cal State San Bernardino</LOCATION> defeated Point <LOCATION>Loma Nazarene</LOCATION>, 6-2, in a nonconference 
game. Senior <PERSON>Tony Nobinsky</PERSON> had an <ORGANIZATION>RBI</ORGANIZATION> and scored a run for PLNC, which finished 
the year 20-28 overall. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. International University</ORGANIZATION> swept a nonconference doubleheader from <ORGANIZATION>Southern 
Utah State</ORGANIZATION>, 13-3 and 14-1, at <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION>. The Gulls' <PERSON>Kevin Tahan</PERSON> was five for eight 
with a home run, his 15th, and nine RBIs in the two games. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Beto Rodriguez</PERSON> was four for four with three doubles and a triple in the first 
game, which was won by starter <PERSON>Mike Whisonant</PERSON> (6-5) with a four-hitter. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Bruce Moutaw</PERSON> was four for six, and <PERSON>Jeff Oswalt</PERSON> (6-7) the winner in the second 
game. <ORGANIZATION>USIU</ORGANIZATION> improved to 20-32. <ORGANIZATION>Southern Utah State</ORGANIZATION> is 21-29. 
</P>
<P>
TENNIS 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> will send two players into the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> Division I 
individual tennis tournament to be held at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Gainesville</LOCATION> beginning <DATE>May 15</DATE>. <PERSON>Jennifer Larking</PERSON> (17-7), ranked 30th in the 
nation, will play in both the singles and doubles. Aby <PERSON>Brayton</PERSON> will be 
Larking's partner in doubles. The two have compiled a 14-6 record this year. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Point Loma Nazarene</ORGANIZATION> women head into today's final day of the <ORGANIZATION>NAIA District 
3 Championship Tournament</ORGANIZATION> tied for first place with <ORGANIZATION>Westmont College</ORGANIZATION>. Both have 
12 points. 
</P>
<P>
In doubles, <PERSON>Kim Wright</PERSON> and <PERSON>Shannon Anderson</PERSON> will play <PERSON>Carolyn Clayton</PERSON> and 
<PERSON>Lelisa Wolters</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Westmont</ORGANIZATION>, which is hosting the tournament on its <LOCATION>Santa 
Barbara</LOCATION> campus. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Robert McDonald of San Diego</ORGANIZATION> advanced to the semifinal round in the Men's 70s 
division of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hardcourt Tennis Championships</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>La Jolla Beach 
and Tennis Club</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>McDonald defeated Bernie Terrell of El Cajon</ORGANIZATION>, 6-4, 7-5. 
</P>
<P>
In the women's 60s, <PERSON>Liz Harper</PERSON> of La Jolla topped her quarterfinal opponent, 
<PERSON>Dot Hogan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Encinitas</LOCATION>, 6-1, 6-0. 
</P>
<P>
MEN'S <ORGANIZATION>GOLF 
</P>
<P>
San Diego State</ORGANIZATION>'s men's golf team fell from first to third in the second round 
of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Athletic Conference</ORGANIZATION>'s golf championships in <LOCATION>Albuquerque</LOCATION>. The 
Aztecs shot a 295 in the second round for a 585 total. With two rounds to go, 
they trail host <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> (575) and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> El Paso (577). 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Game Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06165243 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06165243 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (10); PHOTO: (June Anderson); PHOTO: (Marc Jensen); PHOTO: (Ed
Bautista); PHOTO: (Steve McInaney); PHOTO: (Donna Berry); PHOTO: (Shirley
Reekie); PHOTO: (Conrad Boisvert); PHOTO: (Steven Sokol); PHOTO: (Howard
High); PHOTO: (Jim Wiltens)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  RECREATION; WRITING; PROFESSIONAL; NAME; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  JUNE ANDERSON; June's interests include basketball, rugby, cross-country
skiing, cycling, triathlons, tennis, soccer and running. June runs "Fitness
for Success," a business designed to help people develop and achieve health
and fitness goals.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Venture  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  VENTURE ADVISORY PANEL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>   ED <LOCATION>BAUTISTA</LOCATION>; Ed's interests include softball, basketball, soccer, volleyball,
tennis and running. Ed is a recreation specialist for the San Jose Parks and
<ORGANIZATION>Recreation Department</ORGANIZATION>. He is the department's supervisor for a number of
programs, including the <LOCATION>San Jose Triathlon.</LOCATION>;  <PERSON>DONNA BERRY</PERSON>; <PERSON>Donna</PERSON>'s interests
include swimming, cycling and skiing. Although <PERSON>Donna</PERSON> has degenerative
peripheral neuropathy -- which means her peripheral nerves are dying -- she is
a self-described "jock." She says that "as a result of my activities, I am
sensitive to the increased number of athletic organizations for 'special
needs' athletes or the options offered by adaptive equipment.";  <PERSON>CONRAD
BOISVERT</PERSON>; <ORGANIZATION>Conrad</ORGANIZATION>'s interests include cycling and tennis. Conrad is the author
of two books on cycling, "South Bay Bike Trails" and "Peninsula Bike Trails."
An electrical engineer, he also plays tennis at least five times a week and
regularly participates in recreational leagues and tournaments.;  HOWARD HIGH;
<ORGANIZATION>Howard</ORGANIZATION>'s interests include hunting, dog training, skiing and fly-fishing.
Howard, who is a corporate spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION>, is a judge in the <ORGANIZATION>AKC</ORGANIZATION> hunting
test program and hunts for birds regularly. He and his wife, a marine
biologist, are always on the lookout for outdoor activities they can do with
their three-year-old child.;  <PERSON>MARC JENSEN</PERSON>; <PERSON>Marc</PERSON>'s interests include rock
climbing and hiking. <PERSON>Marc</PERSON>, who has a degree in materials engineering from <LOCATION>San
Jose State</LOCATION>, has been climbing for 13 years and is the author of "Bouldering,
Buildering and Climbing in the <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay Region</LOCATION>.";  <PERSON>STEVE MCINANEY</PERSON>;
<PERSON>Steve</PERSON>'s interests include rafting and kayaking. <PERSON>Steve</PERSON>, who teaches biology at
<ORGANIZATION>Fremont High School</ORGANIZATION>, has been a professional whitewater river guide for eight
years, both in <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. He is a facilitator/instructor for
<ORGANIZATION>Pro-Action Associates</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Colma</LOCATION>, with emphasis on teambuilding, leadership,
communication and risk taking. He also was an instructor for <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Crest
Outward Bound.</ORGANIZATION>;  <PERSON>SHIRLEY REEKIE</PERSON>; <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>'s interests include sailing. <PERSON>Shirley</PERSON>,
who teaches physical education/sports history and international physical
education/sport in the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Human Performance</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>San Jose State
University</ORGANIZATION>, has been a sailing instructor for 20 years and is the author of a
book, "Sailing Made Simple," and numerous articles on sailing. She is coach of
the SJSU racing team and admits that she also plays cricket.;  <PERSON>STEVEN SOKOL</PERSON>;
<PERSON>Steven</PERSON>'s interests include endurance sports. Steve holds more than 20 world
records in ultra-marathon events, including 52,003 consecutive sit-ups, 30,000
jumping jacks and biking 500 miles non-stop from <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>.
Billed as the world's most fit man, he is the author of the book, "The Fitness
Formula.";  <PERSON>JIM WILTENS</PERSON>; <PERSON>Jim</PERSON>'s interests include backpacking, canoeing,
martial arts (Tae Kwon Do black belt, <LOCATION>Shotokan</LOCATION> brown belt), windsurfing, SCUBA
and back-country skills. Jim is the director/owner of <ORGANIZATION>Deer Crossing Wilderness
Camp</ORGANIZATION>, which offers a variety of outdoor activities with emphasis on
youngsters. He is a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Mountain Rescue Unit</ORGANIZATION> and a
contributing editor to <ORGANIZATION>Wilderness Trails</ORGANIZATION>.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910613  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  551  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 13, 1991
00165243,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06235201 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06235201 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2), Map; PHOTO: IN TRAINING -- Ken and Dexter Dobberpuhl both will
compete in this year's triathlon. (color); PHOTO: The World's Toughest
Triathlon begins with a two-mile swim in Lake Tahoe; MAP: Chuck Eichten --
Mercury News; World's Toughest Triathlon; Stage 1: Swim course; A two-mile
course in Lake Tahoe.; Stage 2: Running Course; The 18.6-mile run is a loop
that features 1,700 feet of climbing, including 1,000 feet in one mile to the
Angora Ridge Fire Lookout Station.; Stage 3: Cycling course; One hundred
miles, climbing from Lake Tahoe to Luther Pass, then down through Markleeville
and once again into a tough climb to the top of Monitor Pass. The course
retraces itself back to Woodfords, does a loop along the Emigrant Trail, and
then goes over Luther Pass once again to return to the starting point at Lake
Tahoe. The total vertical gain is 7,173 feet.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  LAKE-TAHOE; SWIMMING; RUNNING; BICYCLE; RACING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  BOBBI POLLOCK is in the World's Toughest Triathlon this year "because it
licked me last year." At 59, she's the oldest female competitor in the race at
Lake Tahoe this Saturday.;    Todd Zeman is half Pollock's age. He trained for
the "World's Toughest" by taking part in the "Death Ride."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Venture  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WORLD'S TOUGHEST?
THAT'S NO IDLE BOAST FOR TRIATHLON AT LAKE TAHOE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Venture -- Celebrating the Active Life;  SETTING THE RECORD STRAIGHT (publ.
8/23/91, pg. 2D);  Because of an editor's error, the sequence of events in the
World's Toughest Triathlon at Lake Tahoe on Saturday was incorrect in a
graphic in Thursday's Venture section. The swimming segment will be followed
by cycling and then running.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Dexter Dobberpuhl</PERSON> watched her husband, <PERSON>Ken</PERSON>, finish second in his age
division (he's 42) last year and figured, "Why should he have all the fun?" So
this year both of them are participating.;    Whether the World's Toughest
Triathlon actually is the world's toughest triathlon may be arguable. But none
of the 500 participants has any doubt that it is a very tough race.;    The
first leg is a two-mile swim in <LOCATION>Lake Tahoe</LOCATION>. The lake sits at 6,200 feet, well
above the 5,000-foot level where most athletes begin to feel the effects of
altitude.;    In addition, water temperature ranges between 58 and 62 degrees,
cold enough so organizers require full wet suits and neoprene swim caps for
the athletes.;    Leg two is a 100-mile bike ride. This isn't just another
"century" ride, it is 100 miles of grueling pedaling that climbs over three
Sierra peaks for a total vertical gain of 7,173 feet. Once again, altitude
plays a crucial part since the climbs are to the tops of Monitor Pass at 8,134
feet and Luther Pass, 7,740 feet high.;    These passes are included in the
infamous <LOCATION>Markleeville</LOCATION> "Death Ride" -- a climb over Monitor, Luther and <LOCATION>Ebbetts</LOCATION>
passes that is known as one of the toughest cycling events around. A number of
the athletes taking part in the "World's Toughest," including <PERSON>Zeman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dexter</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Ken Dobberpuhl</PERSON>, did the "Death Ride" as part of their preparation.;    The
final leg of the race is an 18.6-mile run. The total vertical climb is 1,700
feet, but 1,000 of it occurs in one mile, up a trail of switchbacks on <ORGANIZATION>Angora
Ridge</ORGANIZATION>. Coming after the swim and cycle ride, it is a killer for the athletes,
the place where many drop out.;    TOP ATHLETES, and some teams, finish the
race in just over eight hours. The last finisher should be across the line at
about 15 hours. There are cutoff times for the swim, cycling and running
portions -- those who haven't finished the leg by that time are pulled from
the race.;    <LOCATION>Pollock</LOCATION>, from <LOCATION>Claremont</LOCATION>, has been racing in triathlons for seven
years and has taken part in the famous <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> Ironman four times. Her best
finish was second in her age division.;    Last year she took part in in the
"World's Toughest" for the first time. "It licked me last year," she says. "I
got in 10 minutes late on the bike leg, so I couldn't run.";    At 59,
organizers say she is the oldest woman ever to take part in the race. She's
been doing triathlons for seven years.;    "I had a disc removed from my spine
10 years ago," <PERSON>Pollock</PERSON> says. "Two years after that I met Jesus and he healed
me completely. I started running, cycling and swimming through a co-worker and
got interested in the endurance events.";    Her 24-year-old son isn't
interested in triathlons -- "he wants to be a pro tennis player" -- and her
husband is just a "good rooter.";    <PERSON>Zeman</PERSON>, 28, got the bug to try the
"World's Toughest" two years ago when he watched it.;    <PERSON>Zeman</PERSON>, who owns a
construction firm in <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, said he's been training heavily since May.;   
"I've been working my way up, I'm ready," he said. "I did the <LOCATION>Markleeville</LOCATION>
Death Ride, so I'm not too worried about the altitude. After that ride I felt
the World's Toughest would be a piece a cake.";    The Dobberpuhls, who are
from <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION>, have been taking part in triathlons together since <DATE>1982</DATE>. "<PERSON>Ken</PERSON>
took part last year, and I was totally inspired," <PERSON>Dexter Dobberpuhl</PERSON> said. "I
have a hard time watching, so I decided, why should he have all the fun?"  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Bill Sunderland, Venture Editor column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910822  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1G  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  865  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, August 22, 1991
00235201,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111790-0095 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 309383 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 17, 1990, Saturday, Valley Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 17; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
863 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ARREOLA LOOKING FOR FAST FINISH; 
</P>
<P>
CROSS-COUNTRY: NORTHRIDGE SENIOR EXPRESSES DISAPPOINTMENT WITH HER SEASON 
HEADING INTO DIVISION I CHAMPIONSHIPS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN ORTEGA, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
No <ORGANIZATION>Cal State Northridge</ORGANIZATION> athlete appeared as prepared for the move from the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA 
Division II</ORGANIZATION> ranks to Division I this fall as distance runner <PERSON>Darcy Arreola</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Arreola, the <DATE>1989</DATE> Division II cross-country champion, had won three individual 
Division II track titles, had earned nine Division II All-American certificates 
in track and cross-country, and had placed third in the 1,500 meters in the 
<DATE>1989</DATE> Division I track championships since arriving at <ORGANIZATION>Northridge</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>five years 
ago</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
This cross-country season, however, has been frustrating for Arreola, who will 
compete in the <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> Division I championships at <ORGANIZATION>Pine Lakes Golf Course</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>, on <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I've been disappointed," said <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON>, the lone <ORGANIZATION>Northridge</ORGANIZATION> qualifier for the 
national meet. "I think that's why I'm really looking forward to nationals and 
the end of the season. I know that's not the greatest attitude to have going 
into nationals, but I haven't won a race yet. And I haven't improved as much as 
I wanted to." Last season <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> won four of five cross-country races, 
including the <ORGANIZATION>California Collegiate Athletic Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, Division II West regional 
and Division II titles. 
</P>
<P>
This season she has finished second once, third twice and fourth twice. 
</P>
<P>
After falling behind in her races, <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> has been forced to battle for second 
-- or worse. It is a notion as foreign to <LOCATION>Arreola</LOCATION> as liberalism is to 
Republicans. 
</P>
<P>
"Before the season began, I thought I had a chance at winning Division I," 
<PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> said. "But after (the) <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> (Invitational), I started to realize 
that that probably won't happen." 
</P>
<P>
Arreola has had her best cross-country season -- lowering her personal best on 
the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> course by 39 seconds -- but after being a dominant force in 
Division II, she won't be one of the favorites when the women's 5,000-meter 
race begins at <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME> (EST) <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's hard to accept that I'm one of the unknowns," the 22-year-old <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> 
said. "It puts less pressure on me, but it's hard to accept that you're not 
going to be one of the ones they're looking at. 
</P>
<P>
"In the school newspaper the other day, (<ORGANIZATION>Northridge Coach Don</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON> said 
that a good goal would be the top 10. I saw that and said, 'Top 10?' But then I 
realized that I'm going to be running against a lot of good girls that I've 
never run against, and that a top-10 finish would probably be a good goal." 
</P>
<P>
Arreola, a fifth-year senior, was a well-beaten third in the <ORGANIZATION>Stanford 
Invitational</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Oct. 6</DATE>, 29 seconds behind winner <PERSON>Suzy Favor</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION> and 22 
seconds behind <PERSON>Buffy Rabbitt</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>UC Irvine</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"<PERSON>Suzy</PERSON> was just so far ahead of me," <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> recalled with a laugh. "And she 
probably won't be the No. 1 favorite on <DATE>Monday</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
That role will fall to <PERSON>Michelle Dekkers</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, the <DATE>1988</DATE> 
NCAA Division I champion who defeated Favor for the <ORGANIZATION>Big Ten</ORGANIZATION> and District 4 
titles. 
</P>
<P>
"Dekkers appears to be the favorite," <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON> said, "with (District 8 winner) 
<PERSON>Rabbitt</PERSON> looking for a finish in the top seven. . . . But a lot can happen in 
cross-country." 
</P>
<P>
Strametz linked <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON>'s early-season difficulties to her 70-miles-a-week 
regimen, more than she has ever run before. 
</P>
<P>
"She was training through the meets," <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON> said. "She was racing tired. She 
was not as fresh as some of the people she was running against." 
</P>
<P>
Arreola, the 10th ranked 1,500-meter runner in the country in <DATE>1989</DATE>, concurred 
with <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I kept telling myself, 'Don't worry about it. Just think about regionals and 
nationals, that's all that matters.' " she said. 
</P>
<P>
Based on <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON>'s fourth-place finish in the District 8 meet at <LOCATION>Fresno</LOCATION>'s 
Woodward Park last week, <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON> figures that things are going according to 
plan. 
</P>
<P>
He has tapered <PERSON>Arreola</PERSON>'s training to less than 50 miles a week, and with a 
little fine-tuning, he expects her to be firing on all cylinders <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"She ran her best race of the season at districts," he said. "But she's capable 
of running better. Physically, she was ready to run a great race at districts, 
but mentally she wasn't all there. 
</P>
<P>
"There were certain mental things that she didn't do, like accelerating out of 
the curves. If she runs a great mental race at districts, she runs 15-20 
seconds faster." 
</P>
<P>
The mental aspect of cross-country running is something that Arreola admittedly 
has never mastered. She made marked improvement in that area last season, but 
she has never been as aggressive in cross-country as in track. 
</P>
<P>
"You put her within 10 feet of a track during track season and she becomes an 
animal," <PERSON>Strametz</PERSON> said. "In cross-country, she works hard, but her attitude 
isn't as intense. She is disciplined, but her work ethic has to go to another 
level to reach her potential." 
</P>
<P>
Arreola is aware of her mental shortcomings, but she is hopeful of rectifying 
them by the time she races in <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think I've been anywhere close to being mentally there (this season)," 
<PERSON>Arreola</PERSON> said. "I think (<PERSON>Strametz</PERSON>) would like to think that I'm a lot closer 
than I am. I'm really trying to improve in that area, but it's just been hard 
this season. . . . It seems like I keep thinking about track when I should be 
concentrating on cross-country. 
</P>
<P>
"Hopefully, I can end the season on a good note." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Darcy Arreola will be seeking her first win of the season in Monday's 
Division I championships. MARC YVES REGIS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880722-0147 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- On Sports: Our Distance Runners Come Up Short </HL>
<AUTHOR> Frederick C. Klein </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Indianapolis  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For sports chauvinists, which is to say most of us, the great thing about <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Olympic Trials meets, like the one for track and field in progress here, is that Our Boys and Girls always win. 
We also always take second, third, fourth and all the other places. 
There are no tricky foreign names to unscramble, no East Bloc types to ruin the fun. 

   Trouble is, in many events the fun ends as soon as the rest of the world gets into the act. 
Such has been the case in running events of 800 meters or longer, which is to say most of them. 
The poop-out level of our Olympians seems to arrive about as quickly as does yours or (certainly) mine. 

   In terms of Olympic gold, the principal measure of such accomplishments, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> has been an underdeveloped country in recent years. 
Our men have won but two gold medals in 800-meter-and-over chases since <DATE>1964</DATE>, and our women the same. 
Curiously, two of those four triumphs were in marathons, which at 26 miles and change are the longest of the long. 
Frank Shorter led the panting pack at <LOCATION>Munich</LOCATION> in <DATE>1972</DATE>, and <PERSON>Joan Benoit</PERSON>, who is shorter still, did it in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>. 

   It would be pleasant to report that this sad state is due for an abrupt change in this quadrennial year, but present evidence supports no such conclusion. 
Our sprinters are burning up the <ORGANIZATION>Indiana University</ORGANIZATION> track here, setting or imperiling world's records every time a car backfires, but our distance persons continue to labor in obscurity. 
Even the sport's bureaucracy gives them short shrift. 

   "It took me two hours to get my pass here <TIME>this morning</TIME>. 
The guy behind the desk wanted to cancel me out because I hadn't phoned ahead," noted <PERSON>Jim Spivey</PERSON> at a <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> meeting with the press. 
"I told him my coach was a lawyer, and that he'd make big trouble if they didn't clear things up. 
That got the guy's attention." 

   Spivey's exasperation was justified, because he has been one of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s two best milers for most of this decade. 
The other is <PERSON>Steve Scott</PERSON>. 
Assuming that all goes well in the preliminary heats that began <TIME>last night</TIME>, the two are favored to represent the Stars and Stripes once again in the metric mile (1,500 meters) at <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>. 

   The business about the pass was doubly off-putting because the bright-eyed, 28-year-old <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> came to <LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION> full of vinegar, eager to make his mark on the national consciousness. 
One reason for this was his quick heal from a weird injury that had threatened his Olympic dream with a premature wake-up call. 
Another is that he's running under the tutelage of not just one lawyer, but two. 

   The injury was a stress fracture to a "non-weight bearing" bone in his left leg. 
It was discovered last <DATE>spring</DATE> after he complained his back was going "out of kink." 
He says that tests and X-rays not only showed that he had a fracture but also revealed that his left leg was three-eighths of an inch shorter than his right -- the result of the lifetime of left turns that distance-running dictates. 
Rest cured the bone, and a shoe-insert heel lift evened off his pins. 

   The lawyers are <PERSON>Ken Popejoy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mike Durkin</PERSON>, both national-class milers in their Big Ten salad days in the '70s (<PERSON>Popejoy</PERSON> went to <ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Durkin</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>). 
They now litigate in and around <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. 
Indiana-grad <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON>, also a Chicago-area native, sought out <PERSON>Durkin</PERSON> for coachly counsel because he was tired of coming up short in his races and recalled <PERSON>Durkin</PERSON> as "someone who might not have had all the ability in the world, but always peaked at the right time." 
Durkin later invited his friend <PERSON>Popejoy</PERSON> to be co-counsel. 
Spivey is their only athletic client. 

   Their arrangement is that <PERSON>Durkin</PERSON> maps <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON>'s training regimen and <PERSON>Popejoy</PERSON> helps carry it out, running stride-for-stride with the miler. 
"I do the workouts, and feel fatigue at the same points <PERSON>Jim</PERSON> does. 
That lets me give feedback to both him and <PERSON>Mike</PERSON>," explains <PERSON>Popejoy</PERSON>. 
"As far as we know, our deal is unique." 

   The plan the three have plotted calls for longer, slower workouts than most <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> milers undertake, and fewer races. 
"It's basically a European approach," <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> notes. 
It also involves a change in <LOCATION>Spivey</LOCATION>'s former racing strategy. 

   "I tend to wait too long before starting my kick, and <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> has tried to cure me of that," <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> says. 
"I mean, that's nothing startling, <PERSON>Sam Bell</PERSON>, my coach at <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, used to be on me about it all the time. 
But I guess hearing it from a former runner like <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> made more of an impression on me." 

   The collaboration paid off first at the World Championships in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> <DATE>last September</DATE>, when <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> copped a surprise bronze medal in the 1,500. 
That was the best American showing in an important international mile-or-thereabouts since <PERSON>Jim Ryun</PERSON> placed second in the <DATE>1968</DATE> Olympics. 
This year, even after a layoff for the leg injury, <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> ran a 3:50 mile (albeit in a sixth-place finish) against a crack field in <LOCATION>Oslo</LOCATION>. 
He also got off a personal-best two mile and his second-fastest 800. 

   "I'm 28, about the age where I ought to be running my best, and I am," <PERSON>Spivey</PERSON> says. 
"I won a couple of <ORGANIZATION>NCAA</ORGANIZATION> championships when I was younger, and that set me up for the kind of financial support that enabled me to get this far, which makes me lucky. 
I think the main trouble with American milers, and our distance runners in general, is that that kind of support is so hard to come by." 

   Spivey believes that running-shoe companies, the primary support of many <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> track athletes (his angel is <ORGANIZATION>Nike</ORGANIZATION>), lack the patience to nurture slow-developing distance runners. 
The same goes for official <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> track sources. 

   "I'm a proven commodity and a veteran of the <DATE>1984</DATE> Olympics {where he placed fifth in the 1,500}, so I get <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY> every month from the Olympic committee's 'Operation <LOCATION>Seoul</LOCATION>.' 
That's fine, but I really think the money might be better spent if they gave me, maybe, <MONEY>$400</MONEY>, and split the rest among five or six other people. 
For a young fellow, with few expenses, even <MONEY>$100</MONEY> or <MONEY>$125</MONEY> a month is a lot of money. 
It might keep him in the sport. 
And then we might not have to ask ourselves why we don't win medals in the distances." 
