<DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06107226 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06107226 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Lean  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY; LONDON  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Sir David Lean, who directed "Bridge on the River Kwai," "Lawrence of Arabia"
and "Doctor Zhivago," died in London today at the age of 83, his lawyer
announced.;    The lawyer, Tony Reeves, issued a statement that did not
disclose the cause of death. Lean reportedly had been ill for some time.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DAVID LEAN, 'ZHIVAGO' DIRECTOR, DIES  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     As a director, Lean brought a jeweler's precision to sweeping film epics.
<PERSON>Robert Mitchum</PERSON>, who starred in "Ryan's Daughter," said working for him was
"like trying to build the Taj Mahal with matchsticks.";    Lean's directorial
career began in collaboration with <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON> and progressed to acclaimed
adaptations of <PERSON>Charles Dickens</PERSON>' "Great Expectations" and "Oliver Twist.";   
He was best known for the wide-screen spectaculars, which began with "Bridge
on the River Kwai" and included "Doctor Zhivago" and "A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.";   
In <DATE>March</DATE>, he was to have begun filming "Nostromo," a project based on <PERSON>Joseph
Conrad</PERSON>'s novel that had been several years in the works. On <DATE>Jan. 8</DATE>, his French
producer <PERSON>Serge Silberman</PERSON> said Lean had been taken ill and that he was
undergoing medical tests. Work on the film was suspended.;    "I just love
telling stories," he said in a <DATE>1990</DATE> interview with the Times of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the
city where he made his home.;    Born <DATE>March 25, 1908</DATE>, in <LOCATION>Croydon</LOCATION>, south of
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, Lean went to work in <DATE>1928</DATE> for <ORGANIZATION>Gaumont Studios</ORGANIZATION> as a number-board boy.
He soon displayed an aptitude for editing and was put in charge of <ORGANIZATION>Gaumont
Sound News</ORGANIZATION>, for which he also wrote scripts and provided narration.;    Lean
<DATE>1938</DATE> and <ORGANIZATION>Shaw</ORGANIZATION>'s "Major Barbara" three years later.;    In <DATE>1942</DATE>, his reputation
as a technician led to his being named co-director with <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON> of "In
Which We Serve," an award-winning drama of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Navy</ORGANIZATION> in World War II.;   
Coward was pleased with the results and gave Lean permission to film any of
his plays. Lean and two others formed a production company that brought
<ORGANIZATION>Coward</ORGANIZATION>'s "This Happy Breed" to the screen in <DATE>1944</DATE>, followed a year later by
"Blithe Spirit" and "Brief Encounter.";    "Great Expectations," released in
<DATE>1946</DATE>, won three <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>, plus Lean's first nomination as best
director.;    "The Bridge on the River Kwai" in <DATE>1957</DATE> was Lean's first great
success. The film won seven <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>, including best director.;   
"Lawrence of Arabia," which made a film star of <PERSON>Peter O'Toole</PERSON>, followed in
<DATE>1962</DATE>. It also won seven <LOCATION>Oscars</LOCATION>, including one for Lean as director.;   
Ironically, this film was cut by others, losing about 20 minutes in the
process, and reappeared in its original form in <DATE>1989.</DATE>;    Though Lean regarded
"Lawrence" as his best film, he had his greatest commercial success in <DATE>1965</DATE>
with "Doctor Zhivago," based on <ORGANIZATION>Boris Pasternak</ORGANIZATION>'s novel. The film won three
<PERSON>Oscars</PERSON> and a best-director nomination for Lean.;    "Ryan's Daughter" in <DATE>1970</DATE>
was a critical disaster and something of a personal disaster as well. Lean did
not make another film for 14 years, though he tried in the mid-1970s to make a
film of the mutiny on the HMS Bounty but couldn't reach agreement on backing.;
   He returned to the screen in <DATE>1984</DATE> with "A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>," based on <PERSON>E.M.
Forster</PERSON>'s novel. Lean and the picture were both nominated for Academy Awards.;
   "Nostromo" was years in preparation, and Lean's style of craftsmanship took
its toll. Screenwriter <PERSON>Christopher Hampton</PERSON> left after a year of work.;    "I
drove poor <PERSON>Christopher Hampton</PERSON> mad," Lean said in an interview with the <ORGANIZATION>Sunday
Times</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in <DATE>1990.</DATE>;    "We'd finish a large chunk and I'd say, 'Let's go
back to scene one.' He hated that. But that's me. I understand people not
wanting to go back to scene one, but you've got to if you want to do something
special.";    Lean was knighted in 1984.;    In <DATE>1990</DATE>, he was honored with a
life achievement award from the American Film Institute.;    Married five
times, Lean had a son from his first marriage.;     <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>'s films; The
major films directed by David Lean:; (box)"In Which We Serve" (with <ORGANIZATION>Noel
Coward</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>1942</DATE>; (box)"This Happy Breed," <DATE>1944</DATE>; (box)"Blithe Spirit," <DATE>1945</DATE>;
(box)"Brief Encounter," <DATE>1945</DATE>; (box)"Great Expectations," <DATE>1946</DATE>; (box)"Oliver
Twist," <DATE>1948</DATE>; (box)"One Woman's Story" <DATE>1949</DATE>; (box)"Madeleine," <DATE>1950</DATE>;
(box)"Breaking the Sound Barrier," <DATE>1952</DATE>; (box)"<PERSON>Hobson</PERSON>'s Choice," <DATE>1954</DATE>;
(box)"Summertime," <DATE>1955</DATE>; (box)"The Bridge on the River Kwai," <DATE>1957</DATE>;
(box)"Lawrence of Arabia," <DATE>1962</DATE>; (box)"Doctor Zhivago," <DATE>1965</DATE>; (box)"Ryan's
Daughter," <DATE>1970</DATE>; (box)"A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>," <DATE>1984</DATE>; Source: <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  London  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910416  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  750  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday April 16, 1991
00107226,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA093089-0120 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 114444 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 30, 1989, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 5; Page 1; Column 4; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
650 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AFI LIFE ACHIEVEMENT AWARD TO BE GIVEN TO DAVID LEAN 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JACK MATHEWS, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Omar Sharif</PERSON>, his face caked and glistening with ice crystals, plodding through 
the snow to get to <PERSON>Julie Christie</PERSON>. A black dot wavering in the heated desert 
air, coming closer and growing larger until we see it is actually a man riding 
a camel. A proud <PERSON>Alec Guinness</PERSON> leading his troop of POWs through a Japanese 
compound as they whistle the "Col. Bogey <DATE>March</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>American Film Institute</ORGANIZATION> is going to have some great clips to show at its 
<DATE>March 8</DATE> dinner next year. Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>, the director of such wide-screen 
epics as "Doctor Zhivago," "Lawrence of Arabia" and "The Bridge on the <LOCATION>River 
Kwai</LOCATION>," has been named by the institute as the 18th recipient of its prestigious 
Life Achievement Award. 
</P>
<P>
The 81-year-old Englishman, who is still looking ahead to his planned 
adaptation of the <PERSON>Joseph Conrad</PERSON> novel "Nostromo," is the eighth director and 
the first foreigner to be honored by the <ORGANIZATION>AFI</ORGANIZATION> since it began presenting its 
"living legend" award in <DATE>1973</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Director <PERSON>John Ford</PERSON> was the <ORGANIZATION>AFI</ORGANIZATION>'s first Life Achievement Award recipient and 
<PERSON>Gregory Peck</PERSON> its most recent. In between, the honor -- presented at a glamorous 
A-list Hollywood dinner that is taped for later network broadcast -- has gone 
to such actors as <PERSON>James Cagney</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lillian Gish</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bette Davis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Fred Astaire</PERSON>, <PERSON>Gene 
Kelly</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barbara Stanwyck</PERSON>, and to directors <LOCATION>Orson Welles</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Alfred Hitchcock</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Billy Wilder</PERSON>, <PERSON>William Wyler</PERSON>, <PERSON>John Huston</PERSON> and <PERSON>Frank Capra</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"Lean joins a distinguished group of individuals who have made enormous 
contributions to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s film heritage," said <ORGANIZATION>AFI</ORGANIZATION> chairman <PERSON>Gene Jankowski</PERSON> in 
announcing the name of the institute's <DATE>1990</DATE> winner. 
</P>
<P>
Lean, a <ORGANIZATION>Quaker</ORGANIZATION> who was not allowed to see movies as a child, stepped through 
the looking glass at the age of 19 when he got a job serving tea at an English 
studio and actually had to rise to the job of gofer. He later finagled work as 
an assistant film editor, working on newsreel footage captured during the early 
'30s, and was the credited film editor on the <DATE>1938</DATE> "Pygmalion." 
</P>
<P>
His began his directing career doing the action sequences for the <DATE>1942</DATE> war film 
"In Which We Serve," but his first step toward an <ORGANIZATION>AFI</ORGANIZATION> award came with his <DATE>1945</DATE> 
adaptation of <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON>'s "Brief Encounter." The film earned the then 
37-year-old Lean the first of six Oscar nominations. 
</P>
<P>
He received his second nomination the following year for "Great Expectations," 
and 10 years later began a streak that included nominations for "The Bridge on 
the River Kwai" (<DATE>1957</DATE>), "Lawrence of Arabia" (<DATE>1962</DATE>), "Dr. Zhivago" (<DATE>1965</DATE>), and 
"A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>" (<DATE>1984</DATE>). He won the Oscar for "Kwai" and "Lawrence." 
</P>
<P>
The only film he has done since <DATE>1957</DATE> that did not earn him an <ORGANIZATION>Academy Award</ORGANIZATION> 
nomination was the <DATE>1970</DATE> Irish landscape spectacle "Ryan's Daughter." 
</P>
<P>
Critics are divided on Lean's overall position on the honor roll of film 
directors. Certainly, his epics show the deliberateness of a visual stylist and 
a meticulous storyteller; Lean has managed only 16 movies in 47 years of 
directing. 
</P>
<P>
For Hollywood, he was definitely the right director at the right time. With 
television spawning <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first generation of couch potatoes, the big 
screen had to get a lot bigger, and with "The Bridge on the River Kwai," Lean 
gave audiences plenty to look at while managing to keep the story as big as the 
image. 
</P>
<P>
Lean has not worked as much as he might have liked in the <DATE>last two decades</DATE>, 
because of the prohibitive costs of his kind of spectacle. For years, he and 
his writing collaborator, <PERSON>Robert Bolt</PERSON>, were planning an authentic historical 
version of "Mutiny on the Bounty." At one time, it was going to be done as two 
movies, each one costing about <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, then as an eight-hour miniseries. 
</P>
<P>
Lean abandoned the project when it was clear no one would put up the money he 
needed to realize his vision. The film was eventually made in <DATE>1984</DATE> by director 
<PERSON>Roger Donaldson</PERSON> for <ORGANIZATION>Orion Pictures</ORGANIZATION> under the title "The Bounty." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Director David Lean, 81, will be 18th recipient of film institute honor. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LEAN, DAVID; AMERICAN FILM INSTITUTE; MOTION PICTURE DIRECTORS; HONORS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06108086 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06108086 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Director David Lean was a consummate craftsman and a
stickler for detail; PHOTO: Omar Sharif and Geraldine Chaplin starred in
Lean's 1965 epic, 'Doctor Zhivago.'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; LIST; PERSON; CELEBRITY; PROFILE; AGE; OBITUARY; DEATH  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  ABOUT TWO YEARS AGO, David Lean was bivouacked in a hotel on a remote stretch
of Spanish coast, contemplating his 19th feature film, based on Joseph
Conrad's "Nostromo." Yes, Lean assured me long-distance, it would be a big
film (costing more than $30 million). Yes, it would deal with such favorite
themes as honor and responsibility. And, yes, he was expecting it to be a
"bugger of a nightmare" logistically, just as his Oscar-winning "Lawrence of
Arabia" and "The Bridge on the River Kwai" were.;    For a Steven Spielberg or
a James Ivory or a Bernardo Bertolucci, three of the many directors inspired
by Lean, the challenges would have been daunting but not insurmountable. But
Lean was two weeks shy of 81. How could he possibly handle the strain of
another monster production?  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  DIRECTOR STARRED IN EPIC OF A LIFETIME
DAVID LEAN'S WORK OUTLIVES STORYTELLER  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Longevity runs in family;  Lean waved off the question. "Both my mother and
father died after they were 95," replied the warm, clipped voice on the other
end. "That's a help. Also, I've had a wonderful life in movies. I've gone to
an awful lot of places. It keeps you in trim.";    Lean didn't make it quite
as far as his parents.;    The self-described storyteller died <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> at his
home in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> at age 83. The cause of death was not disclosed, but <PERSON>Stephen
Silverman</PERSON>, a biographer of Lean, said he died of pneumonia.;    Lean had been
hospitalized in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE> after being stricken on the set of
"Nostromo." Work on the film had since been suspended.;    But before his
illness, you can bet Lean was happy and busy. A consummate craftsman and a
stickler for detail, he didn't know how to quit dreaming in 24 frames a
second.;    Lean doesn't leave behind a large body of work, but it is
considerable from an artistic standpoint.;    He was born <DATE>March 25, 1908</DATE>, in
<LOCATION>Croydon</LOCATION>, south of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, and got into the movie business in <DATE>1928</DATE> as a
number-board boy at Gaumont studios. He displayed an aptitude for editing, and
was put in charge of <ORGANIZATION>Gaumont Sound News</ORGANIZATION>, for which he also wrote scripts and
provided narration.;    After apprenticing as editor (on such classics as
"Pygmalion" and "One of Our Aircraft is Missing"), he made his solo directing
debut in <DATE>1944</DATE> on the very English, very stiff-upper-lip "This Happy Breed," by
playwright <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON>, who would continue to provide source material.;   
<PERSON>Dickens</PERSON> adaptation;  In <DATE>1946</DATE>, Lean oversaw "Great Expectations," arguably the
best of the <PERSON>Dickens</PERSON> adaptations. The opening scenes on the moor, wherein young
Pip falls into league with a scurrilous escaped convict, have been discussed
and written about endlessly as the perfect fusing of studio ambiance,
performance and editing.;    Indeed, many critics argued that Lean was at his
best when working on a smaller scale, on more intimate social satires, such as
"<PERSON>Hobson</PERSON>'s Choice" (<DATE>1954</DATE>, with <PERSON>Charles Laughton</PERSON>) and "Summertime" (<DATE>1955</DATE>, with
<PERSON>Katharine Hepburn</PERSON>).;    Lean disagreed. In his mind he was born to play a
composite of <PERSON>D.W. Griffith</PERSON>, <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rommel</PERSON> of the <LOCATION>Desert</LOCATION>. Lean, in his
mid-40s, found his kindred spirit in British Col. <PERSON>Nicholson</PERSON>, the never-say-die
POW in "River Kwai," which won seven <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>, including those for best
picture, actor (<PERSON>Alec Guinness</PERSON>) and director. Nicholson as played by <ORGANIZATION>Guinness</ORGANIZATION>
is anything but your typical wartime hero. In the killing heat of the Burmese
jungle, he becomes the victim of his own obsession. The enemy bridge -- a
miracle of Allied engineering -- becomes bigger than the war, or any
discussion of morality.;    Metaphor for Lean's life;  That bridge, you could
argue, became an apt metaphor for Lean's own life -- a life filled with
exhilarating feats and fueled by an obsessive drive for perfection.;    That
mix of bravura and fanaticism found a new face in <ORGANIZATION>T.E. Lawrence</ORGANIZATION>, played by
<PERSON>Peter O'Toole</PERSON> in Lean's <DATE>1962</DATE> award-winner "Lawrence of Arabia." Considered
Lean's masterpiece by many, "Lawrence" has become the standard for all
wide-screen epics, a three-hour-plus mix of intimate character detail and
panoramic desert vistas. Lean described it simply as "the story of a man who
failed. . . . They (the critics) said it was lacking in humanity. I think it
may have been ahead of its time.";    The distinctive Lean touch seemed to
atrophy in the '60s as the film maker went on to such visually ambitious but
dramatically overwrought works as "Doctor Zhivago" and "Ryan's Daughter." The
latter, featuring a miscast <PERSON>Robert Mitchum</PERSON> as a cuckolded Irish schoolteacher,
brought the worst reviews of Lean's career.;    Defends 'Zhivago';  "I tried
to make it over-the-top romantically," Lean acknowledged, "but didn't tell the
audience what I was doing. But I don't think they were correct on 'Zhivago.'
If you're going to make a film of a long book, you've got to make changes. . .
. I'm not ashamed of that one at all.";    Sadly, Lean's labor of love was
never made, at least as Lean envisioned it. After years of pre-production work
on a revisionist, two-part "Mutiny on the Bounty," scripted by regular
collaborator <PERSON>Robert Bolt</PERSON>, producer <PERSON>Dino De Laurentiis</PERSON> moved forward without
Lean. A shorter version with <PERSON>Mel Gibson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Anthony Hopkins</PERSON> was released as
"The Bounty" in <DATE>1984.</DATE>;    Lean never got over the humiliation and attacked De
Laurentiis publicly whenever offered a forum.;    "He (De Laurentiis) pulled
the carpet from under me. I think that was the best script <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and I ever
did. It was heartbreaking to watch it go under.";    Comeback;  In <DATE>1984</DATE>, at
age 76, he made a comeback with a sumptuous adaptation of <PERSON>E.M. Forster</PERSON>'s "A
Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>." A dramatization of a scandal that rocked colonial <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,
the film combined the scope and exacting craftsmanship of the old Lean and
went on to earn 11 Oscar nominations.;    After the <PERSON>Forster</PERSON> adaptation, Lean
plotted his next adventure in film-making, collected a steamer trunk full of
lifetime achievement awards -- including the <ORGANIZATION>American Film Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s -- as
well as a knighthood, and held forth on how the industry was going to hell in
a hand basket.;    "Look at O'Toole in 'Lawrence.' Looks, talent and screen
presence. It's all there. Today, all we have are talking heads. I don't think
that's the way ahead for the cinema. Telling a story with pictures -- that's
movie-making. . . .;    "Whatever you think of 'Lawrence' as a movie, it's a
visual meal.";    And Lean was one of the cinema's great chefs.; FILMOGRAPHY;
The principal films directed by David Lean:; (box)"In Which We Serve" (with
<ORGANIZATION>Noel Coward</ORGANIZATION>), 1942.; (box)"This Happy Breed," 1944.; (box)"Blithe Spirit,"
1945.; (box)"Brief Encounter," 1945.; (box)"Great Expectations," 1946.;
(box)"Oliver Twist," 1948.; (box)"One Woman's Story" <DATE>1949</DATE>,; (box)"Madeleine,"
1950.; (box)"Breaking the Sound Barrier," 1952.; (box)"<PERSON>Hobson</PERSON>'s Choice,"
1954.; (box)"Summertime," 1955.; (box)"The Bridge on the River Kwai," 1957.;
(box)"Lawrence of Arabia," 1962.; (box)"Dr. Zhivago," 1965.; (box)"Ryan's
Daughter," 1970.; (box)"A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>," <DATE>1984.</DATE>; Source: <ORGANIZATION>Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENN LOVELL, Mercury News Film Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910417  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,183  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday April 17, 1991
00108086,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031090-0103 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 187582 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 10, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
573 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WARM AFI TRIBUTE TO DAVID LEAN; 
</P>
<P>
MOVIES: CREATOR OF 'LAWRENCE OF ARABIA' AND 'DR. ZHIVAGO' MIXES HUMOR WITH 
CRITICISM OF COMMERCIALISM. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By KEVIN THOMAS, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Lectures, like loin of lamb, are best served warm, and those people at the 
<ORGANIZATION>American Film Institute</ORGANIZATION>'s tribute to <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON> at the <ORGANIZATION>Beverly Hilton Hotel</ORGANIZATION> on 
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> got both. 
</P>
<P>
The 81-year-old Lean, whose wide-screen masterpieces include "Lawrence of 
Arabia," "The Bridge on the River Kwai" and "Doctor Zhivago," mixed wry British 
humor with the stern tone of a schoolmaster in lecturing his high-powered and 
captive Hollywood audience for its cautious, commercially homogenized films. 
</P>
<P>
Lean, asking to be forgiven his presumption, said that he got the green light 
for his long-planned adaptation of <PERSON>Joseph Conrad</PERSON>'s "Nostromo" just two hours 
before arriving at the hotel, and it was high time, indeed. 
</P>
<P>
"After months and months of talk," he said, "(it's) sort of asinine (to get the 
go-ahead for a film) only two hours before receiving this great honor." 
</P>
<P>
Lean -- taking the podium after a parade of tributes from old friends and such 
contemporary film makers as <PERSON>Steven Spielberg</PERSON>, <PERSON>Martin Scorsese</PERSON> and <PERSON>Lawrence 
Kasdan</PERSON> -- tempered his scorn for the greed that he says governs Hollywood with 
his own passion for the medium. "I speak from the heart and because I love 
movies," he said, before delivering his apparently off-the-cuff lecture. 
</P>
<P>
Lean quoted <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON>, with whom he made his directorial debut in the <DATE>1942</DATE> 
wartime drama, "In Which We Serve," as telling him to "always come out of 
another hole," to be surprising and daring. "We don't come out of any more new 
holes," Lean said. "We come out with Parts One, Two, Three and Four, and I 
think it's terribly sad." 
</P>
<P>
Lean said a staple diet of repeated themes "will sink us" and urged the studios 
to take risks, especially with young talent. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't mind for old birds like me -- we can take it -- but we have to protect 
our young. Please, you chaps in the money department, look out for the young 
ones. . . . This business lives on creative pathfinders." 
</P>
<P>
Coming from Lean, especially in the wake of clips from such films as "Kwai," 
"Lawrence," "Brief Encounter," "Great Expectations" and "Oliver Twist," the 
blunt criticism of current film making was taken enthusiastically. Lean had 
made similar comments during a tribute at <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> and left that 
audience aghast. 
</P>
<P>
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s industry crowd was treated to one of the briskest and most 
seriously reverent tributes in the award's 18-year history. <PERSON>John Mills</PERSON>, whose 
<PERSON>David Lean</PERSON> films included "Ryan's Daughter" and "Great Expectations," flew 22 
hours "with no pay at the end of it" to honor Lean in person. Also on hand was 
composer <PERSON>Maurice Jarre</PERSON> ("<PERSON>Dr. Zhivago</PERSON>," "Lawrence of Arabia"), who spoke of 
Lean's lessons in "humility, tenacity and perfectionism." 
</P>
<P>
One of the evening's highlights was the appearance -- live via satellite from 
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, where it was <TIME>4 a.m.</TIME> -- of <PERSON>Omar Sharif</PERSON>, who portrayed Zhivago, and <PERSON>Peter 
O'Toole</PERSON>, who co-starred with <PERSON>Sharif</PERSON> in "Lawrence of Arabia." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Steven Spielberg</PERSON> told Lean and the audience that "Bridge on the River Kwai" and 
"Lawrence of Arabia" were the two films "that most made me want to be a film 
maker." <PERSON>Lawrence Kasdan</PERSON> told of how he and his brother had arrived seven 
minutes late for a showing of "Lawrence" and decided to wait six hours for it 
to begin again rather than go in late because "every moment" of a David Lean 
movie mattered. <PERSON>Martin Scorsese</PERSON> spoke of Lean's "landscapes of the spirit -- 
there's no such thing as an empty landscape in a David Lean film." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, David Lean says repeated themes in films "will sink us" and urges 
industry risk-taking, particularly on the young. ANACLETO RAPPING / Los Angeles 
Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AMERICAN FILM INSTITUTE; LEAN, DAVID; MOTION PICTURE DIRECTORS; HONORS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06117223 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06117223 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Lean; PHOTO: Omar Sharif, left, and Peter O'Toole were only
two of the brilliant assets in David Lean's remarkable 'Lawrence of Arabia,'
which received four Oscars in 1962.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  MOVIE; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; CHRONOLOGY; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE passing last week of David Lean at age 83 removes yet another esteemed
figure from the art of motion pictures. Few directors can claim a track record
as successful as Lean's (a record that includes two best-director Academy
Awards for films that won a total of 28 Oscars). Fewer still can claim a body
of work so unflaggingly intelligent and meticulously crafted.;    But the fact
that most of Lean's films are available on video is a mixed blessing at best.
While every one of the pictures below ranks high on the "must see" list of
true film lovers, Lean's works since 1957 are so expansive, so sweeping, so
grandly scaled that they achingly emphasize the main drawback of home video:
We watch these films on a tiny TV set, rather than on the huge theatrical
screen for which they were intended. Can one be overwhelmed by the scope and
grandeur of Lawrence's Arabia, or by the vast landscapes of Zhivago's Russia,
when seen on a 27-inch TV screen? Simply, no.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Weekend  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LEAN'S LEGACY MIXED BLESSING IN ITS BIG WAY
SOME OF DIRECTOR'S WORK OUTGROWS SCOPE OF
VCR  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Apel, Mercury News video columnist, hosts KTEH-TV's science-fiction programs
on Sunday nights.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     With this caveat, we present our fat primer of Lean films. To view the
final five, might I suggest finding a friend with a large-screen,
surround-sound TV, or perhaps writing the Camera One and Camera 3 people to
suggest a Lean retrospective or festival at their beautifully renovated Towne
Theater? ("Lawrence of Arabia" is scheduled there in <DATE>June</DATE>.) To see these epics
in any other way is to emaciate them and destroy their potent emotional
impact.;     (box) "In Which We Serve" (<DATE>1942</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>Embassy</ORGANIZATION>). Intensely patriotic
and compassionate statement about war, co-directed by its
writer-producer-star, <PERSON>Noel Coward.</PERSON>;     (box) "Blithe Spirit" (<DATE>1945</DATE>; IDK).
<PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON>'s romantic comedy became a vehicle for  <PERSON>Rex Harrison</PERSON>, as a man
haunted by the ghost of his first wife, who is intent on breaking up his
second marriage.;     (box) "Brief Encounter" (<DATE>1945</DATE>; Paramount). Classic
five-hanky romance about two ordinary people in war-torn <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> who enter
into a poignant and ultimately doomed affair.;     (box) "Great Expectations"
(<DATE>1946</DATE>; Paramount) and "Oliver Twist" (<DATE>1948</DATE>; Discount). Two superb <PERSON>Dickens</PERSON>
adaptations, both starring <PERSON>Alec Guinness.</PERSON>;     (box) "<PERSON>Hobson</PERSON>'s Choice" (<DATE>1954</DATE>;
HBO). <PERSON>Charles Laughton</PERSON> is brilliant in this period comedy about a domineering
father running roughshod over his daughters' love lives.;     (box)
"Summertime" (<DATE>1955</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>Embassy</ORGANIZATION>). Another romantic idyll; <PERSON>Katharine Hepburn</PERSON> plays
a spinster who falls in love in Venice.;     (box) "The Bridge on the River
Kwai" (<DATE>1957</DATE>; RCA/Columbia). British POWs are forced into slave labor in <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>
to build a railroad trestle vital to Japanese supply lines in this
unforgettable epic of courage and obsession, which won many Oscars, including
best picture, director and actor (<ORGANIZATION>Alec Guinness</ORGANIZATION>).;     (box) "Lawrence of
Arabia" (<DATE>1962</DATE>; RCA/Columbia). Lean turned the fascinating saga of enigmatic
English soldier <ORGANIZATION>T.E. Lawrence</ORGANIZATION> into an archetypal epic: intelligent, grandiose,
breathtaking and spellbinding. Oscars for best picture, direction, photography
and music. A must for the big-screen treatment; do not attempt to watch this
on video.;     (box) "Dr. Zhivago" (<DATE>1965</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>MGM/UA</ORGANIZATION>). Pasternak's novel comes
lucidly alive in this panoramic tale of romance and revolution in Russia.;    
(box) "Ryan's Daughter" (<DATE>1970</DATE>; <ORGANIZATION>MGM/UA</ORGANIZATION>; rated R). Sprawling but overlong
romantic melodrama, full of spectacular pastoral scenery of Ireland.;    
(box) "A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>" (<DATE>1984</DATE>; <LOCATION>RCA/Columbia</LOCATION>; PG). Fourteen years after the
critical failure "Ryan's Daughter," Lean emerged to display his mastery of the
medium in this multi-leveled, lushly photographed tale of cultural clashes
between the British and "the mysterious East."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  D. Scott Apel column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910426  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  618  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 26, 1991
00117223,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06242095 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06242095 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, Map; MAP: Associated Press; Bridge on the River Kwai; PHOTO: Vernon
Loeb -- Knight-Ridder News Service; BRIDGE OVER TOURIST WATERS -- The 'real'
Bridge on the River Kwai appears calm, but isn't during a festival that
includes sound effects of bombing and anti-aircraft fire.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  THAILAND; PAST; BRIDGE; RIVER; MULTIPLE; DEATH; CONSTRUCTION  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE TRAIN to Nam Tok rumbles over the Bridge on the River Kwai, still in use
though Alec Guinness blew it up at the end of the classic 1957 movie.;   It
didn't really happen that way, of course. It was actually the Americans who
bombed the bridge near the end of World War II.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SYMBOL OF TRAGEDY TARNISHED BY TRINKETS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The real story is an epic in its own right, and the real bridge, a black
steel expanse repaired after the war, remains an enduring monument to the
Allied prisoners of war and Asian laborers who died building it for the
Japanese.;   Unfortunately for their memory, the Bridge on the <LOCATION>River Kwai</LOCATION> has
also become a tourist trap, much to the dismay of many who come to visit the
site of their relatives' graves.;   From the bridge's graceful,
crescent-shaped spans, visitors can look out across the <ORGANIZATION>Kwai</ORGANIZATION>'s waters and see
souvenir stands selling Bridge on the River Kwai T-shirts, <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Pepsi</ORGANIZATION>
signs in Thai, a foreign exchange van and a dozen speedboats moored in front
of a floating restaurant waiting to whisk tourists down the river.;   Why not
a River Kwai bumper sticker? Or maybe River Kwai tumblers, ashtray or baseball
cap? How about a documentary video for only <MONEY>$12</MONEY>? "Excellent souvenir," a sign
says.;   "The bridge itself is absolutely soured by the tourism and the
mercenary way the people are exploiting it," said <PERSON>Brian Kettell</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
academic, on vacation here. "But this is <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION>, I suppose.";   <PERSON>Kettell</PERSON> was
drawn to the bridge, in part, by what he called its "tremendous
popularization" in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> by <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>'s <DATE>1957</DATE> movie.;   <PERSON>Kettell</PERSON> conceded
that the film was not historically accurate.;   "But it's not totally
inaccurate, either," he said. "It does give a flavor of the story. There was a
bridge built, there was horrible suffering and the bridge was blown in the
end, albeit by the Americans, not by the British.";   A sense of that
"horrible suffering" -- and how it lives on -- is still to be felt in this
provincial city, 90 miles west of <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION>, despite the blatant tourist
exploitation that includes a 10-day Bridge on the River Kwai festival every
fall, complete with sound effects of bombing and anti-aircraft fire.;   A mass
grave containing the skeletons of hundreds of Asian laborers was discovered
last year, right before the annual bridge bash, a major tourist event.;  
While cynics noted how convenient the timing was, finding the grave site did
help underscore the fact that more than 100,000 Asians -- Indians, Burmese,
<LOCATION>Malays</LOCATION>, Indonesians, Chinese and Thais -- perished while building the
so-called Death Railway, a 260-mile line connecting <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> and Burma.;  
After invading and occupying <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>, the Japanese ordered construction
of the route in <DATE>1942</DATE> in preparation for an invasion of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. They completed
the line, which most said would take five years to hack through dense jungle
and mountain rock, in 13 months -- at tremendous human cost.;   Much better
known, of course, are the 16,000 Allied prisoners of war who died as well,
mostly British, Australian and Dutch, with several hundred Americans among the
victims.;   <PERSON>Trevor Dakin</PERSON> decided to retire in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> after visiting the
bridge as a tourist five years ago. <PERSON>Dakin</PERSON>, a former prisoner of war,
immigrated to <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> after the war and worked as a salesman for
an air-conditioning manufacturer. He figured his small pension would go a lot
further in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> than in <LOCATION>Canada.</LOCATION>;   <PERSON>Dakin</PERSON> also had a feeling that something
was beckoning him to return.;   "I have an affinity for this country," <PERSON>Dakin</PERSON>,
71, said. " . . . There were many times, my friend, when we would lie there in
the jungle and say, 'This is a beautiful country. I would like to see it in
better circumstances.' These 48 years later are the better circumstances."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  VERNON LOEB, Knight-Ridder News Service  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Kanchanaburi, Thailand  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910829  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  681  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, August 29, 1991
00242095,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-4841</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDQBPAE3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910417
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 APR 91 / Arts: Sir David Lean - Obituary
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s most celebrated film director, Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>, died in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
yesterday after a long illness.
Sir <PERSON>David</PERSON>, 83, whose screen triumphs included Lawrence of Arabia, The Bridge
On The River Kwai and <PERSON>Dr Zhivago</PERSON>, was taken ill earlier this year while
working on a Pounds 23m project in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. He was flown home from the south
of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> for treatment but never recovered, his lawyer <PERSON>Mr Tony Reeves</PERSON>
announced. A private funeral will be held and a memorial service is to be
arranged.
Sir <PERSON>David</PERSON>, who married for the fifth time in <DATE>December last year</DATE> to <PERSON>Sandra
Cooke</PERSON>, had just completed work on the script of his adaptation of <PERSON>Joseph
Conrad</PERSON>'s Nostromo. Its future is now in doubt.
Sir <PERSON>David</PERSON>'s films won a total of 26 Oscars, making him one of the most
successful directors despite long periods of inactivity.
After learning his trade in the <DATE>1920s</DATE> as a clapperboard boy and a 'wardrobe
mistress' he took charge of editing and commentary for <ORGANIZATION>Gaumont Sound News</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>1930</DATE> - later moving to <ORGANIZATION>British Movietone News</ORGANIZATION>.
Within a few years he was <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s highest-paid film editor, working on
successes like <ORGANIZATION>French Without Tears</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Pygmalion</LOCATION> and 49th Parallel.
He was invited to co-direct with <PERSON>Noel Coward</PERSON> the story of wartime life in
the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Navy</ORGANIZATION>, In Which We Serve. Its success in <DATE>1942</DATE> led him to direct
three other films written by <ORGANIZATION>Coward</ORGANIZATION> - This Happy Breed, <ORGANIZATION>Blithe Spirit</ORGANIZATION>, and
the widely acclaimed Brief Encounter - by <DATE>1946</DATE>.
The early post-war years saw the critical and box office successes Great
Expectations, still regarded by many as his finest achievement, and Oliver
Twist.
His Dr Zhivago in <DATE>1965</DATE> was to earn more money than all his other films put
together. Another of his box office successes was Ryan's Daughter in <DATE>1970</DATE>.
He was upset by the cool critical response the film received and did not
make another until A Passage To <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
But recognition of his achievements continued. In <DATE>1973</DATE> he received the
<ORGANIZATION>Directors Guild of America</ORGANIZATION>'s highest accolade, the D W <ORGANIZATION>Griffith Award</ORGANIZATION>.
In <DATE>1983</DATE>, the year before he was knighted, he was given one of the first
fellowships awarded by the British Film Institute.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 13
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890929-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-29-89 1510EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-People     09-29 0795</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0834</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SEATTLE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BLOOMSBURG, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Syndicated advice columnist <PERSON>Abigail Van Buren</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Dear Abby</PERSON> to millions of newspaper readers, said people often ask
if she makes up the letters she prints.
   ``I couldn't begin to make up anything half as good as I get in
my morning mail,'' she said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Miss <PERSON>Van Buren</PERSON>, who began writing her column 33 years ago, said
she has fun with her responses, but takes her advice
responsibilities seriously.
   ``I never sacrifice sound judgment just for the sake of humor,''
she said.
   While the answers are her own, <PERSON>Miss Van Buren</PERSON> consults with
lawyers, doctors and other professionals.
   ``I don't write for laughs. My primary motive is not to
entertain. It's to inform,'' she told a group of newspaper
publishers.
   Miss Van Buren receives 10,000 to 15,000 letters each week.
   ``The best ones I can't print,'' she said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901118-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-11-18-90 1147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Thailand-Grave Bjt   11-18 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Thailand-Grave, Bjt,0653</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mass WWII Grave Found Near Site of `Bridge Over the River Kwai'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BK1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TAVORN TUMMACHARTVIJIT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KANCHANABURI, Thailand (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A mass grave has been discovered
near the site where more than 100,000 Asian slave workers and
Allied prisoners died building a railroad for the Japanese during
World War II.
   The remains of several hundred people have been dug up since
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, when the excavation began. It is being carried out by the
<ORGANIZATION>Pothipawana Songkroh Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which for religious reasons wants
to provide proper burials.
   Several dozen workers were digging <DATE>Sunday</DATE> in a sugar cane field
in <LOCATION>Kanchanaburi</LOCATION> province, about 70 miles west of <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION>. One skull
was left out overnight - but workers first covered it with paper so
it would not be cold.
   About half the small plot has been excavated.
   The mass grave is about three miles from a bridge made famous in
the <DATE>1957</DATE> Hollywood movie, ``Bridge Over the River Kwai,'' which
celebrated the heroism of the war captives.
   A foundation official, <PERSON>Santi Assawaseeyotin</PERSON>, said it appeared
the bones had been ``dumped into the ground, because they were
found in some disorder.''
   <PERSON>Santi</PERSON> said the bones were dating back to the World War II era.
   ``We believe they were bones of Asian people as the skulls found
were not big,'' he said. ``There also were children's bones.''
   He said the remains were being brought to the foundation's
office in <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION>, where they will be cleaned and cremated.
   There was no direct evidence the bones belonged to the World War
II prisoners. No such remains have been found in <LOCATION>Kanchanaburi</LOCATION> in
recent years.
   Also recovered were metal plates and bowls; on the back of
several were written Made in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> or Made in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>. The
<ORGANIZATION>Bangkok Post</ORGANIZATION> newspaper said some had the year <DATE>1939</DATE> imprinted on
them.
   More than 100,000 Chinese, Indian, <LOCATION>Malay</LOCATION>, Burmese and other
Asian slave laborers lost their lives building the railway in
<DATE>1942-43</DATE>, along with more than 16,000 British, Dutch, Australian,
<ORGANIZATION>American</ORGANIZATION>, and <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> prisoners of war.
   They died of disease, malnutrition, exhaustion, beatings and
executions.
   The Japanese had the 268-mile line connecting <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>
built for their planned invasion of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ladda Matcha</PERSON>, 38, who lives near the grave, said the owner of a
motorcyle repair shop also near there recently dreamed that the
dead told him they could not breathe and asked him for help.
   The man contacted the foundation, whose representatives secured
permission from the landowner to dig, <PERSON>Mrs. Ladda</PERSON> said. The owner
knew of the remains on her plot, but used it to grow sugar cane.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Ladda</PERSON>'s mother, <LOCATION>Pab Borngern</LOCATION>, 77, said the Japanese
constructed a military camp and tunnel in the area during the war.
   ``When the Indians (workers) died, they just carried them into
the hole they dug up,'' she said. ``At the place where they found
the bones, that was thousands of people buried there. Those peple
died because of fever.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bangkok Post</ORGANIZATION> quoted the landowner's sister, <LOCATION>Lek Pailom</LOCATION>, 64,
as saying field hospitals for Asian slave workers were in the area.
   ``Every morning, the Indians dug a hole in this area to bury
dead bodies in the evening,'' she said. ``Some days, two or three
bodies were buried, some days more than five.''
   ``This happened throughout the period of the railway
construction,'' she said.
   The discovery of the remains came just before the annual 11-day
River Kwai Bridge Festival. This major tourist attraction of
special shows and exhibitions is scheduled to begin <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   In <DATE>March</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Prime Minister Chatichai Choonhavan</ORGANIZATION> responded to
objections by Australian veterans groups and Prime Minister <PERSON>Bob
Hawke</PERSON> by barring shows that a tourism company planned along the
railway. They were to have featured Japanese soldiers supervising
work gangs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA100290-0197 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 287531 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 2, 1990, Tuesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 10; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
120 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHORT TAKES; 
</P>
<P>
DAVID LEAN TO WED FOR 6TH TIME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LONDON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>, the 82-year-old director whose films have won 27 <ORGANIZATION>Academy 
Awards</ORGANIZATION>, is planning to marry for the sixth time, his lawyer said <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Lean will wed 51-year-old interior designer <PERSON>Sandra Cooke</PERSON> before <DATE>Christmas</DATE>, said 
attorney <PERSON>Michael Gee</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The couple met five years ago in the frozen-food section of Harrods department 
store, where <PERSON>Cooke</PERSON> went up to Lean and asked when his next film was due, said 
<ORGANIZATION>Daily Mail</ORGANIZATION> columnist <PERSON>Nigel Dempster</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Lean and <PERSON>Cooke</PERSON> are vacationing in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, Gee said. The director's next film 
project will be an adaptation of <PERSON>Joseph Conrad</PERSON>'s novel "Nostromo." 
</P>
<P>
Lean is the director of such classics as "The Bridge on the River Kwai," 
"Lawrence of Arabia" and "Great Expectations." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, David Lean 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890327-0191 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-27-89 1434EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--TVWeek Adv09   03-27 0672</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--TV Week, Adv 09,0692</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv09</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, April 9</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w photo.)</HEAD>

<NOTE>By JERRY BUCK</NOTE>
<NOTE>AP Television Writer</NOTE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>

<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, April 9</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890928-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-28-89 0641EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Columbia-History     09-28 0713</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Columbia-History,0733</SECOND>
<HEAD>Purchase of Columbia Gives Sony Some America's Most Treasured Movies</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Columbia-Analysis, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BOB THOMAS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HOLLYWOOD (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With the purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Sony
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is acquiring some of the most treasured American films ever
made, from the classic drama ``Lawrence of Arabia'' to the classic
slapstick of ``The Three Stooges.''
   The giant Japanese electronics manufacturer announced the <MONEY>$3.4
billion</MONEY> deal <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, giving it another foothold in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
entertainment industry.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> bought <ORGANIZATION>CBS Records</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> last year while looking
for properties to provide records and movies it hoped consumers
would use with its stereos and videocassette recorders.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> deal will give it control of a major production
studio, a film library of 2,700 movies and 23,000 episodes of
television programming in 260 series.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> was attractive because of its successful stable of
television productions and its two film studios, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures</ORGANIZATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Tri-Star</ORGANIZATION>.
   Among <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>'s new holdings will be 11 films that have won Academy
Awards as Best Picture, including two with themes that were
anti-Japanese. ``From Here to Eternity'' in <DATE>1953</DATE> climaxed with the
Japanese bombing of <LOCATION>Pearl Harbor</LOCATION> that drew the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> into
World War II. ``The Bridge on the River Kwai'' in <DATE>1957</DATE>, portrayed
inhumane conditions in a Japanese-run prison camp.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s other Best Picture winners were: ``It Happened One
Night,'' <DATE>1934</DATE>; ``You Can't Take it With You,'' <DATE>1938</DATE>; ``All the
<PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Men,'' <DATE>1949</DATE>; ``On the Waterfront,'' <DATE>1954</DATE>; ``Lawrence of
Arabia,'' <DATE>1962</DATE>; ``A Man For All Seasons,'' <DATE>1966</DATE>; ``Oliver,'' <DATE>1968</DATE>;
``<PERSON>Kramer vs. Kramer</PERSON>,'' <DATE>1979</DATE>; and ``Gandhi,'' <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> began in <DATE>1920</DATE> as the <ORGANIZATION>C.B.C. Film Sales Co.</ORGANIZATION>, using the
initials of its founders, brothers <PERSON>Harry</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jack Cohn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harry
Brandt</PERSON>. The founders changed the name to <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1924</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Harry Cohn</PERSON> led <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s rise in a tiny studio on <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s
Poverty Row, and the company's growth accelerated with the <DATE>1928</DATE>
arrival of <PERSON>Frank Capra</PERSON>, who promptly directed seven films.
   Capra's movies of the <DATE>1930s</DATE> _ including ``It Happened One
Night,'' ``Lost Horizon'' and ``You Can't Take it with You'' _
helped establish <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> as a major studio.
   Cohn and <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> produced some of the most popular and
sophisticated films of the <DATE>1930s</DATE> and 40s _ ``One Night of Love,''
``The Awful Truth,'' ``Here Comes <PERSON>Mr. Jordan</PERSON>,'' ``The Jolson
Story,'' ``Cover Girl,'' ``All the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Men.'' Among <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s
stars were <PERSON>Rita Hayworth</PERSON>, <PERSON>Glenn Ford</PERSON>, <PERSON>William Holden</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kim Novak</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Broderick Crawford</PERSON> and <PERSON>Judy Holliday</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1952</DATE>, <PERSON>Cohn</PERSON> formed a subsidiary, Screen Gems, to produce TV
series. The film division continued to thrive with such hits as
``Born Yesterday,'' ``The Caine Mutiny'' and ``The Bridge on the
River Kwai.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s television arm remains hugely profitable, making <MONEY>$155
million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$620 million</MONEY> in the company's last fiscal
year, ended <DATE>Feb. 28</DATE>.
   The television division has been boosted by newer shows such as
``Who's the Boss?,'' ``227'' and ``Designing Women,'' while
continuing to receive revenue from such older productions as its
more than 200 ``Three Stooges'' shorts. The films, made between
<DATE>1934</DATE> and <DATE>1958</DATE>, are frequently shown on television.
   With <PERSON>Harry Cohn</PERSON>'s death in <DATE>1958</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> became host to
independent producers such as <PERSON>Sam Spiegel</PERSON> (``Lawrence''); <PERSON>Ray Stark</PERSON>
(``Funny Girl,'' ``The Way We Were''); <PERSON>Carl Foreman</PERSON> (``The Guns of
Navarone''); <PERSON>Otto Preminger</PERSON> (``Anatomy of a Murder''); and <PERSON>Stanley
Kramer</PERSON> (``Guess Who's Coming to Dinner'').
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> sold its Sunset and <PERSON>Gower</PERSON> studios in the heart of
Hollywood in the late <DATE>1960s</DATE> and moved production to <ORGANIZATION>The Burbank
Studios</ORGANIZATION>, which it shares with <ORGANIZATION>Warner Bros</ORGANIZATION>. Inc.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola Co.</ORGANIZATION> purchased <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1982</DATE>.
   Despite the soft-drink empire's attempts to inject its
production and marketing techniques into the movie business, its
film divisions declined. Tri-Star could not produce a solid hit and
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> sponsored the disastrous ``Ishtar.''
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> combined <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and Tri-Star into a new
company, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures Entertainment</ORGANIZATION>, and retained a <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT>
interest while distributing part interest to <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> shareholders.
   During <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION>'s ownership, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Loews Theatre
Management Corp.</ORGANIZATION> took off. <ORGANIZATION>Loews</ORGANIZATION>, acquired in <DATE>1986</DATE>, is among the
nation's five biggest theater chains, with more than 800 screens in
220 locations.
   Still, <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s motion-picture arm has drifted in recent
years, with projects like ``Ghostbusters II,'' ``The Karate Kid
III'' and ``Casualties of War,'' failing to become runaway hits.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031290-0051 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 188402 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part C; Page 2; Column 3; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
493 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MORNING BRIEFING: THEY JUST HAVE TO MAKE SURE HE DOESN'T GET TO EAT FIRST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HARLEY TINKHAM 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
They call him Conan the Destroyer and his appetite is legend. He's <PERSON>Brian 
Conlan</PERSON>, an all-star offensive lineman from <ORGANIZATION>South Delta High School</ORGANIZATION> in <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>, 
<LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>. He's headed for the <ORGANIZATION>University of Washington</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Says Conlan: "One time my mom cooked this big roast chicken and set it down on 
the table. Boy, was she surprised when I ate the whole thing." 
</P>
<P>
His mother then watched him go through several helpings of rice, pasta and 
bread, all washed down with a quart of milk. 
</P>
<P>
Says <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Don James</PERSON>: "Obviously what we like about him is that he 
doesn't have to get a whole lot bigger." 
</P>
<P>
Conlan is 6-5 and 285. 
</P>
<P>
Yuk, yuk: <PERSON>Bob Weiss</PERSON>, assistant coach of the <LOCATION>Orlando Magic</LOCATION>, was a teammate of 
<LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Jerry Sloan</PERSON> when <PERSON>Sloan</PERSON> was named to six All-NBA defensive teams 
while playing with the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Bulls</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said <PERSON>Sloan</PERSON>, in his prime, could 
handle <PERSON>Michael Jordan</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Really? 
</P>
<P>
"Of course." <PERSON>Weiss</PERSON> said. "Jordan would have been 12 then." 
</P>
<P>
Add Jordan: Asked after the last Chicago-Boston game if he thought <PERSON>Larry Bird</PERSON> 
had lost a step, he did a double-take and said, "He scored 38." 
</P>
<P>
Trivia time: What do <PERSON>Arnold Palmer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Hugh McElhenny</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Elvis Presley</ORGANIZATION> have in 
common? Historic shot: Adding to his accomplishments on the tour, <PERSON>Gary Player</PERSON> 
the golf architect says, "I was the first golfer to hit a ball over the River 
Kwai." 
</P>
<P>
Player told the <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Journal that he's building his own bridge across the 
river in <LOCATION>Thailand</LOCATION> where <PERSON>Alec Guiness</PERSON> and <PERSON>William Holden</PERSON> emoted so brilliantly 
in the movie, "Bridge Over the River Kwai." 
</P>
<P>
Oh, by the way, the shot carries 120 yards. 
</P>
<P>
Homebody: The most productive player in baseball? How about <PERSON>Bip Roberts</PERSON>, 
utility man for the <LOCATION>San Diego Padres</LOCATION>? Last year, he scored 81 runs in only 329 
at-bats. Give him 600 at-bats and you get 148 runs. 
</P>
<P>
Golden harvest: The most productive draft in <ORGANIZATION>NFL</ORGANIZATION> history? How about 
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s in <DATE>1974</DATE>? The <ORGANIZATION>Steelers</ORGANIZATION> landed <PERSON>Lynn Swann</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jack Lambert</PERSON>, <PERSON>John 
Stallworth</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mike Webster</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
He plays <PERSON>Bach</PERSON>, too: <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION> Spur Coach <PERSON>Larry Brown</PERSON>, on <PERSON>David Robinson</PERSON>: 
"This is no ordinary kid. Asked why he blocked a shot, or defended a player so 
well, he says, 'Well, I couldn't let them drive the lane with impunity.' When 
was the last time you heard that?" 
</P>
<P>
Scavengers: Said football Coach <PERSON>Mike Kelly</PERSON> of Division III Dayton after the 
conclusion of Division I recruiting: "The big dogs finished eating. Now, we're 
out to pick at the bones." 
</P>
<P>
Never enough: <PERSON>Billie Jean King</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>: "The only thing I 
regret is not making more money at the end of my career. One time I had some 
exhibitions lined up against <PERSON>Chris Evert</PERSON> at <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> a match, but <PERSON>Chris</PERSON> said 
she didn't want to lose to me in exhibitions at that stage of her career. I 
understood, but that would have been good money." 
</P>
<P>
Trivia answer: All three were called The King. 
</P>
<P>
Quotebook: Senior golfer <PERSON>Chi Chi Rodriguez</PERSON>: "We have three tours. The senior 
tour, the super-senior tour and the Lee Trevino tour." HARLEY TINKHAM 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900321-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-21-90 0649EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WKD--HomeVideo Adv00   03-21 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-WKD--Home Video, Adv 00,0868</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv00</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Anytime</NOTE>
<HEAD>AP WEEKEND ENTERTAINMENT AND ARTS</HEAD>
<HEAD>Video View: Home Video News and Reviews</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DOLORES BARCLAY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Arts Editor</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   No one ever agrees on what movie should win the coveted Oscar.
Still, everyone has a favorite movie or two that won the Academy
Award in the past.
   And with Oscar approaching on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, here's what's available in
video to quench the Oscar thirst:
   _``Wings'' (<DATE>1927</DATE>): First best picture winner, about World War I
fighting buddies.
   _``All Quiet on the Western Front'' (<DATE>1930</DATE>): <PERSON>Lewis Millstone</PERSON>'s
anti-war movie.
   _``Cimarron'' (<DATE>1931</DATE>): Western based on <PERSON>Edna Ferber</PERSON> novel.
   _``Grand Hotel'' (<DATE>1932</DATE>): Life in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> following World War I,
starring <PERSON>Greta Garbo</PERSON>.
   _``It Happened One Night'' (<DATE>1934</DATE>): <PERSON>Clark Gable</PERSON> and <PERSON>Claudette
Colbert</PERSON> in romantic comedy.
   _``Mutiny on the Bounty'' (<DATE>1935</DATE>): The original <PERSON>Bligh</PERSON> and
Christian with <PERSON>Charles Laughton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Clark Gable</PERSON>.
   _``The Great Ziefeld'' (<DATE>1936</DATE>): Biography of legendary showman
starring <PERSON>William Powell</PERSON>.
   _``The Life of Emile Zola'' (<DATE>1937</DATE>): <PERSON>Paul Muni</PERSON> stars as the <DATE>19th
century</DATE> French author.
   _``Gone With the Wind'' (<DATE>1939</DATE>): Rhett and <PERSON>Scarlett</PERSON> _ the South
will never be the same. Also, <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>'s finest movie year.
   _``Rebecca'' (<DATE>1940</DATE>): A gothic romance by <PERSON>Daphne du Maurier</PERSON>,
translated to the screen by <PERSON>Alfred Hitchcock</PERSON> and starring <PERSON>Laurence
Olivier</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joan Fontaine</PERSON>.
   _``Casablanca'' (<DATE>1942</DATE>): The only way to see it is in its
original black and white version. Skip the limp colorized version.
   _``Going My Way'' (<DATE>1944</DATE>): <PERSON>Bing Crosby</PERSON>'s laidback priest.
   _``The Lost Weekend'' (<DATE>1945</DATE>): Hollywood gets serious with
alcoholism.
   _``The Best Years of Our Lives'' (<DATE>1946</DATE>): <PERSON>William Wyler</PERSON>'s
compassionate look at returning vets.
   _``Hamlet'' (<DATE>1948</DATE>): <PERSON>Laurence Olivier</PERSON> takes on the <LOCATION>Bard</LOCATION>.
   _``All the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Men'' (<DATE>1949</DATE>): <PERSON>Robert Penn Warren</PERSON>'s story about
a corrupt politician.
   _``All About Eve'' (<DATE>1950</DATE>): Sharp tongues and acid looks from
<PERSON>Bette Davis</PERSON>, <PERSON>George Sanders</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thelma Ritter</PERSON>.
   _``The Greatest Show on Earth'' (<DATE>1952</DATE>): <PERSON>Cecil B. DeMille</PERSON>'s
circus.
   _``From Here to Eternity'' (<DATE>1953</DATE>): World War II smolders and
simmers. The beach will never be the same.
   _``On the Waterfront'' (<DATE>1954</DATE>): <PERSON>Marlon Brando</PERSON> toughs it out on
the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> waterfront.
   _``Marty'' (<DATE>1955</DATE>): Two lonely people fall in love.
   _``Around the World in 80 Days'' (<DATE>1956</DATE>): All over the globe with
stars, stars, stars.
   _``The Bridge on the River Kwai'' (<DATE>1957</DATE>): <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>'s powerful
war epic.
   _``Gigi'' (<DATE>1959</DATE>): <PERSON>Leslie Caron</PERSON> comes of age in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> of the
<DATE>1900s</DATE>.
   _``Ben-Hur'' (<DATE>1959</DATE>): <PERSON>William Wyler</PERSON>'s epic about a Jewish
nobleman during the time of <LOCATION>Christ</LOCATION>, winner of 11 Oscars.
   _``The Apartment'' (<DATE>1960</DATE>): <PERSON>Billy Wilder</PERSON>'s tender look at
philandering executives and a sensitive mistress.
   _``West Side Story'' (<DATE>1961</DATE>): Movie version of the hit Broadway
musical.
   _``Lawrence of Arabia'' (<DATE>1962</DATE>): one of the most brilliant movies
of all time, by <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON> and starring <PERSON>Peter O'Toole</PERSON>.
   _``Tom Jones'' (<DATE>1963</DATE>): A bawdy romp through 18th century <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.
   _``My Fair Lady'' (<DATE>1964</DATE>): <PERSON>Henry Higgins</PERSON> and <PERSON>Eliza Doolittle</PERSON> on
the big screen with <PERSON>Rex Harrison</PERSON> and <PERSON>Audrey Hepburn</PERSON>.
   _``The Sound of Music'' (<DATE>1965</DATE>): Kind of syrupy, but nice music
and nice <PERSON>Julie Andrews</PERSON>.
   _``A Man for All Seasons'' (<DATE>1966</DATE>): No one makes intelligent
films like this anymore. Sir Thomas More refuses to help <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON>
sever ties with the <ORGANIZATION>Roman Catholic Church</ORGANIZATION>.
   _``In the Heat of the Night'' (<DATE>1967</DATE>): Southern murder mystery
with redneck sheriff and black detective from the North.
   _``Oliver!'' (<DATE>1968</DATE>): <PERSON>Charles Dickens</PERSON>' classic set to music.
   _``Midnight Cowboy'' (<DATE>1969</DATE>): Perhaps <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON>'s best role
_ the sleazy <PERSON>Ratso</PERSON>.
   _``Patton'' (<DATE>1970</DATE>): Brilliant interpretation of the
controversial general by <PERSON>George C. Scott</PERSON>.
   _``The French Connection'' (<DATE>1971</DATE>): Next to ``Bullitt,'' the best
car chase in movie history.
   _``The Godfather'' (1972): The Mafia like you've never seen it
before. Brando is wonderful as the don.
   _``The Sting'' (<DATE>1973</DATE>): <PERSON>Paul Newman</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert Redford</PERSON> in a
delightful scam.
   _``The Godfather Part II'' (<DATE>1974</DATE>): More of the Corleones.
   _``One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest'' (<DATE>1975</DATE>): Getting mental with
<PERSON>Jack Nicholson</PERSON>.
   _``Rocky'' (<DATE>1976</DATE>): A feel-good movie that's not the greatest
flick ever made, but its sequels make it look like ``Lawrence of
Arabia.''
   _``Annie Hall'' (<DATE>1977</DATE>): A romantic comedy by <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON> with
the usual sturm und drang.
   _``The Deer Hunter'' (<DATE>1978</DATE>): <PERSON>Michael Cimino</PERSON>'s haunting look at
the <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   _``<PERSON>Kramer</PERSON> vs. Kramer'' (<DATE>1979</DATE>): Divorce, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> style.
   _``Ordinary People'' (<DATE>1980</DATE>): <PERSON>Robert Redford</PERSON>'s debut as a
director.
   _``Chariots of Fire'' (<DATE>1981</DATE>): An inspiring tale of Olympic
runners.
   _``Gandhi'' (<DATE>1982</DATE>): A majestic epic of the Indian leader's life,
with an unforgettable performance by <PERSON>Ben Kingsley</PERSON>.
   _``Terms of Endearment'' (<DATE>1983</DATE>): A sappy movie about a tragic
mother-daughter relationship, saved only by fine performances.
   _``Amadeus'' (<DATE>1984</DATE>): Music, majesty and <PERSON>Mozart</PERSON> fun.
   _``Out of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'' (<DATE>1985</DATE>): A romantic adventure with <PERSON>Robert
Redford</PERSON> and Meryl Streep.
   _``Platoon'' (<DATE>1986</DATE>): <PERSON>Oliver Stone</PERSON>'s realistic treatment of war
in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>.
   _``The Last Emperor'' (<DATE>1987</DATE>): The awesome life of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s last
monarch.
   _``Rain Man'' (<DATE>1988</DATE>): <PERSON>Dustin Hoffman</PERSON> as the autistic brother of
<ORGANIZATION>Tom Cruise</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Release Anytime</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900313-0187 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-90 2329EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e AM-APArts:Oscars-Invasion Adv19   03-13 1161</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-AP Arts: Oscars-Invasion, Adv 19,1198</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv19</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday AMs, March 19, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>THE OSCARS 1990: And the Winner Is ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Foreign Invasion: Foreign Films Popular at Oscars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HILLEL ITALIE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON> can only laugh at how calmly
Hollywood is taking this year's ``foreign invasion'' of the Academy
Awards:
   ``My Left Foot'' from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, five nominations including best
picture; <PERSON>Camille Claudel</PERSON>'' from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, two nominations including
best foreign film; ``Henry V'' from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, three nominations
including best director.
   Yet, it's business as usual at the <LOCATION>Oscars</LOCATION>. There are, of course,
the usual arguments over who made it and who didn't, but nothing
like the press conference called by <PERSON>Samuel Goldwyn</PERSON> in <DATE>1946</DATE>, when
Lean's ``Brief Encounter'' and <PERSON>Laurence Olivier</PERSON>'s ``Henry V'' were
among several foreign films enjoying critical and commercial
success.
   ``Hollywood is facing a challenge,'' said <PERSON>Goldwyn</PERSON>, producer of
such films as ``Wuthering Heights'' and ``The Little Foxes.''
   ``Today it is by the British, tomorrow it may be the French or
the Italians or the Russians. To maintain it's place, <ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION>
must set aside the old formulas. It must find honest stories,
stories with something important to say, stories that reflect these
disturbing times in which we live.''
   Lean was amazed by <PERSON>Goldwyn</PERSON>'s warning because he was sure ``Brief
Encounter'' would flop. After all, the film had closed down after
three days in one Italian city because, the British filmmaker had
heard, leading man <PERSON>Trevor Howard</PERSON> was too ugly.
   So when ``Brief Encounter'' was previewed at a tiny screening
room in <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, Lean did his best to slip in and out unnoticed.
It didn't work.
   ``I waited until the lights went out and snuck in the back
because I just wanted to see what sort of print would be there,''
Lean said in a recent phone interview from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, where he
received the American Film Institute's annual Life Achievement
Award.
   ``When the lights went up, I sneaked out. I got a few steps down
the passage, and a voice said, `Hi, excuse me.' It was the critic
from <ORGANIZATION>Time</ORGANIZATION>. `He said, `Tell me, did you direct that?' And I said,
`You're right, I did,' thinking he was going to say God knows what.
He said, `Let me shake your hand, that was marvelous.'
   ``And that was the first time I knew I was going to get a break
in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.''
   ``Brief Encounter'' received three nominations (but won no
Oscars) and Lean eventually felt right at home at the <ORGANIZATION>Academy
Awards</ORGANIZATION>, totaling 56 nominations and 27 awards for such films as
``Great Expectations,'' ``A Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>,'' ``The Bridge on the
River Kwai'' and ``Lawrence of Arabia.''
   Since <DATE>1932</DATE> when <PERSON>Charles Laughton</PERSON> won best actor for the title
role in a British production of ``The Private Life of <PERSON>Henry VIII</PERSON>,''
Oscar has had an ambivalent relationship with foreign movies.
Hollywood preferred American products to win, but constantly
recognized worthy foreign efforts.
   Foreign films, especially British, have won various prizes from
cinematography (``Black Narcissus'') to best picture (``Hamlet''),
from screenwriting (``The Search'') to costume design (``La Dolce
Vita'').
   In <DATE>1956</DATE>, foreign language film became a separate category.
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>'s ``La Strada'' won that year. But that didn't stop the
<ORGANIZATION>Academy of Motion Picture Arts</ORGANIZATION> and Sciences from nominating foreign
films and filmmakers in other categories. In <DATE>1966</DATE>, the French film
``A Man and a Woman'' won a screenplay Oscar and was also named
best foreign film. In <DATE>1973</DATE>, <PERSON>Sven Nykvist</PERSON> won the cinematography
award for <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s ``Cries and Whispers.''
   The British have dominated the Oscars on several occasions,
including ``Lawrence of Arabia'' in <DATE>1962</DATE>, ``Tom Jones'' in <DATE>1963</DATE>,
``Chariots of Fire'' in <DATE>1981</DATE> and ``A Room With a View'' in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   ``The Academy Awards in some ways is the absolute tops for a
moviemaker; you can't do better,'' Lean said. ``It's terrific to
get and I never thought I would get one.''
   Lean's favorite of his own films is ``Lawrence of Arabia,''
which was released in <DATE>1962</DATE> and earned seven <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>,
including best picture and director.
   An ``adventure of a lifetime'' is how Lean remembered the 19
months of location work for the film. ``Anybody who can go out and
live in the desert for a year is a lucky man,'' he said of the
title character.
   For the starring role, he wanted <PERSON>Albert Finney</PERSON>, one of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s
hottest young actors at the time, but after four days of testing,
<PERSON>Finney</PERSON> turned him down. Lean took a chance and cast a then unknown
<PERSON>Peter O'Toole</PERSON>.
   ``I was desperate because I didn't have a leading man,'' Lean
said. ``I went to a theater in the West End and I saw a film called
`The Day They Robbed the <ORGANIZATION>Bank of England</ORGANIZATION>,' and in it was <PERSON>Peter</PERSON>
playing a small part. I had never seen him before. As he came on
the screen, I thought, `Wait a minute, that's a star.'''
   But it's not as much fun anymore, insists Lean, who has made
just two films in the past 20 years: ``Ryan's Daughter'' and ``A
Passage to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.'' There's too much talk about money, and ever
since ``Easy Rider'' in <DATE>1969</DATE>, producers have been looking for hit
films that cost little to make.
   The director even longs for the return of bosses such as
<PERSON>Goldwyn</PERSON>, tirades and all.
   ``Hollywood was something special,'' Lean said. ``Those chaps
like <PERSON>Goldwyn</PERSON>, they were uneducated, but all of them, however tough,
whatever they were, they just loved movies and sought quality. Now,
it's, `How much?'''
   Lean spoke of a recent dinner with <PERSON>Billy Wilder</PERSON>, another
Oscar-winning director and <ORGANIZATION>AFI</ORGANIZATION> honoree who has struggled to find
work. They talked about the problems of being part of Hollywood
history in a business that's always looking ahead.
   ``When you get over 80 the pressures are worse than they ever
were,'' said Lean, who turns 81 on <DATE>March 25</DATE>, the day before the
<ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION> presentation.
   ``<PERSON>Billy</PERSON>'s bright as a button, really entertaining and really
quick. You would think by the way he's treated, he's just
beginning. Anybody who makes `The Apartment' and `Some Like It Hot'
should be up in the highest position.''
   Fortunately, <PERSON>Lean</PERSON> said, he likes the young directors who greeted
him so warmly on his recent trip. He is especially enthusiastic
about <PERSON>Oliver Stone</PERSON> and predicts that <ORGANIZATION>Stone</ORGANIZATION> and other directors will
eventually take control of Hollywood from the agents and lawyers.
   Stone recently won the <ORGANIZATION>Directors Guild</ORGANIZATION> award for his ``Born on
the <DATE>Fourth of July</DATE>,'' which has received eight Oscar nominations
including best picture.
   ``The filmmakers in Hollywood I think are very special. They're
really keen and they're all bright and intelligent and they've got
a sense of humor. They are full of enthusiasm that doesn't seem to
be at all envious of others,'' Lean said.
   ``They just give it to you on a plate. It's very nice for an old
bird to get that.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday AMs, March 19</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901218-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-18-90 1440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     12-18 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Charlton Heston</PERSON> predicts that epic films
like ``<PERSON>Ben Hur</PERSON>'' or ``Lawrence of Arabia'' will soon be as obsolete
as silent movies.
   The movie, ``Honey, I Shrunk the Kids' cost more than `<PERSON>Ben Hur</PERSON>,'
so that means they don't makemovies like that,'' <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said in an
interview this week on the syndicated television show
``Personalities.''
   ``They will never make a `Lawrence of Arabia' again. They will
never make `Bridge on the <ORGANIZATION>River Kwai</ORGANIZATION>' again, which is too bad,''
<PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said. ``But we got to make those movies and I'm glad we did.
   ``People make fewer films now,'' <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said.
   Heston, 67, also decried the high price of a movie ticket.
   ``You know, I just found out - because I get into a lot of
movies for free - that they're charging <MONEY>$7</MONEY> to go to a movie in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> now. Now, that's terrible.''
   Heston won an <ORGANIZATION>Academy Award</ORGANIZATION> for his role as <PERSON>Judah Ben Hur</PERSON>. The
film, about Roman rivalries in Jesus' day, is known for an
11-minute chariot race that <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> has said is the greatest action
sequence ever filmed.
   ---
   <LOCATION>MEMPHIS</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION> (AP) - Country entertainers <PERSON>Waylon Jennings</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Willie Nelson</PERSON> are joining forces to develop a club where they can
perform from time to time.
   The club, to be called ``<PERSON>Waylon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Willie</PERSON>'s Cafe,'' will be on
the city's <LOCATION>Mud Island</LOCATION> tourist park which is undergoing renovation
as a companion project to the Great American Pyramid.
   The pyramid, a 32-story, stainless steel structure, is scheduled
to open next <DATE>summer</DATE>. Mud Island, a struggling nearby tourist park,
is being refurbished to become ``<LOCATION>Festival Island</LOCATION>.''
   The island and pyramid, though both owned by local government,
will be run by private companies controlled by businessman <PERSON>Sidney
Shlenker</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Jennings</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> for a performance <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, said the
club he plans with <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION> will have about 200 seats. <PERSON>Jennings</PERSON> said
he and <ORGANIZATION>Nelson</ORGANIZATION> will perform there several times a year, but he
didn't say exactly how many that meant.
   Mud Island is a three-mile-long sandbar in the <LOCATION>Mississippi
River</LOCATION>. Most of the island is being developed as residential
property.
   ---
   <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> (AP) - Singer <PERSON>Julio Iglesias</PERSON> says he knows his
limitations and that means his world is on a sound stage, not a
movie set.
   Iglesias said he decided not to pursue an acting career because
``I am the worst actor on earth,'' the singer confessed in an
interview to be shown on ``The <PERSON>Joan Rivers</PERSON> Show.''
   ``I did a film 20 years ago and when I saw the film again, I
felt guilty and embarrassed,'' he said.
   ``I need to sing,'' <PERSON>Iglesias</PERSON> told <PERSON>Rivers</PERSON>, but ``I don't need to
spend two hours singing in a movie.''
   Iglesias admits he would ``love to do that - it's such a nice
situation to be an actor,'' but he says, ``I can't make it.''
   ---
   <LOCATION>CHICAGO</LOCATION> (AP) - <PERSON>Patrick Lilley</PERSON>, the actor who played <PERSON>Eddie
Munster</PERSON> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> television series, ``The Munsters,'' has
pleaded innocent to charges that he robbed his limousine driver
outside a suburban gas station.
   <PERSON>Lilley</PERSON>, 37, of <LOCATION>Gardenia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, entered the plea <DATE>Monday</DATE> before
<ORGANIZATION>DuPage County Circuit Judge Edward Kowal</ORGANIZATION>.
   The actor and <PERSON>John P. Sullivan</PERSON>, 32, of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, were in a rented
limousine <DATE>Nov. 2</DATE> when they allegedly robbed the driver of <MONEY>$140</MONEY>,
authorities said.
   <PERSON>Lilley</PERSON>, who used the stage name <PERSON>Butch Patrick</PERSON> in the hit
television series, was in the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> area making appearances at
Halloween parties and signing autographs for fans, police said. He
had been to two bars and was on his way to a <LOCATION>Naperville</LOCATION> hotel when
the robbery occurred.
   Police said no weapons were involved in the robbery.
   <PERSON>Sullivan</PERSON> also has pleaded innocent.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA121990-0155 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 324593 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 19, 1990, Wednesday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part P; Page 10; Column 1; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
137 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHORT TAKES; 
</P>
<P>
NO 'BEN HURS,' HESTON LAMENTS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Staff and Wire Service Reports 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Actor <PERSON>Charlton Heston</PERSON> predicts that epic films like "<PERSON>Ben Hur</PERSON>" and "Lawrence of 
Arabia" will soon be as obsolete as silent movies. 
</P>
<P>
"The movie, 'Honey, I Shrunk the Kids' cost more than '<PERSON>Ben Hur</PERSON>,' (in <DATE>1959</DATE> 
dollars) so that means they don't make movies like that," <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said in an 
interview this week on the syndicated television show "Personalities." 
</P>
<P>
"They will never make a 'Lawrence of Arabia' again. They will never make 
'Bridge on the <ORGANIZATION>River Kwai</ORGANIZATION>' again, which is too bad," <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said. "But we got 
to make those movies, and I'm glad we did. 
</P>
<P>
"People make fewer films now," <PERSON>Heston</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
Heston, 67, also decried the high price of a movie ticket. 
</P>
<P>
"You know, I just found out -- because I get into a lot of movies for free -- 
that they're charging <MONEY>$7</MONEY> to go to a movie in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> now. Now, that's 
terrible." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890319-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-19-89 2253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Britain-FilmAwards 1stLd-Writethru a0796 03-19 0606</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Film Awards, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0796,0616</SECOND>
<HEAD>``The Last Emperor'' Tops ``A Fish Called Wanda'' at Awards</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 7th graf, ``Michael Palin, with 1 graf to CORRECT details
of Palin's role. Pick up 8th pvs, ``It was</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EDITH M. LEDERER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   ``The Last Emperor,'' which swept last year's
Academy Awards, won this year's top British film award <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>,
while two stars from ``A Fish Called Wanda,'' won top acting awards.
   The Danish movie ``Babette's Feast'' won as best foreign language
film and <PERSON>Louis Malle</PERSON> took top directing honors for ``Au Revoir Les
Enfants.'' Both movies had also been nominated for best film of <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Sir <PERSON>Alec Guinness</PERSON>, the 74-year-old veteran actor, received the
British Academy of Film and Television Arts' most prestigious award,
becoming a fellow of the academy. It was presented by Oscar-winning
director Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON> instead of fellow director Sir <PERSON>Richard
Attenborough</PERSON>, who was hospitalized <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> for suspected
kidney stones.
   Guinness, who won an Oscar for ``The Bridge on the River Kwai''
in <DATE>1957</DATE>, has been nominated for another Oscar this year for his
supporting role in ``Little Dorrit.'' The Academy Awards will be
presented in <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 29</DATE>.
   Comedian <PERSON>John Cleese</PERSON> was chosen best actor as the reserved
English lawyer who lost his inhibitions to an American woman thief,
played by <PERSON>Jamie Lee Curtis</PERSON>, in ``A Fish Called Wanda.''
   Cleese, accepting the award from actor <PERSON>Dudley Moore</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION>, said in a closed-circuit TV relay he thought it should have
gone to co-star <PERSON>Kevin Kline</PERSON>, who was also nominated for his role as
a manic jewel thief. Kline is nominated for an Oscar but <PERSON>Cleese</PERSON> is
not.
   <PERSON>Michael Palin</PERSON>, the movie's stuttering animal lover who was forced
to watch his goldfish swallowed and to accidentally cause the deaths
of several dogs, got the best supporting actor award.
   ``It was a marvelous film to work on _ except if you're a fish or
a dog,'' he joked in accepting the award. ``I want to thank <PERSON>John
Cleese</PERSON> who upgraded me from a pet salesman to a pet murderer and all
the doggies who gave their lives.''
   The <PERSON>Michael Balcon</PERSON> award for outstanding British contribution to
cinema went to <PERSON>Charles Crichton</PERSON>, director of ``A Fish Called Wanda''
and more than a score of other films.
   Two of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s leading ladies walked off with the best actress
awards, <PERSON>Maggie Smith</PERSON> for her starring role as a spinster piano
teacher in <LOCATION>Dublin</LOCATION> in ``The Lonely Passion of <PERSON>Judith Hearne</PERSON>'' and
<PERSON>Dame Judi Dench</PERSON> for her supporting role as the pushy mother in ``A
Handful of Dust.'' Both are previous British award winners.
   <PERSON>Ms. Smith</PERSON> skipped the ceremony because of a broken shoulder.
   <PERSON>Bernardo Bertolucci</PERSON>, accepting the best picture award for his
epic film ``The Last Emperor'' about Chinese Emperor <PERSON>Pu Yi</PERSON>, praised
the important British contribution to the movie's technical and
acting success, including actor <PERSON>Peter O'Toole</PERSON>, who lost out in the
best supporting actor competition.
   ``A World Apart'' won for best original screenplay, ``The
Unbearable Lightness of Being'' for best adapted screenplay,
``Empire of the Sun'' for best score, and ``Defense Counsel <PERSON>Sedov</PERSON>,''
a Soviet movie about the righting of injustice, as best short film.
   The main Oscar nominees _ ``Rain Man,'' ``Dangerous Liaisons,''
``<LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> Burning,'' ``The Accidental Tourist'' and ``Working
Girl'' _ were ineligible for the British awards because they were
not released in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> during <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   More than 2,300 people packed the grand ballroom at the <ORGANIZATION>Grosvenor
House Hotel</ORGANIZATION> for the ceremony. Actors <PERSON>Ben Kingsley</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Edward Fox</ORGANIZATION> and
actresses <PERSON>Shirley Maclaine</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hayley Mills</PERSON> were among the
celebrities who presented awards.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890929-0251 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-29-89 1331EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-Sony Bjt   09-29 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sony, Bjt,0769</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sony Won't Make Rambo a Samurai After Buyout of Columbia Pictures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN MOFFAT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When the next Hollywood blockbuster hits American
movie screens, you may be able to say, ``It's a <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony Corp.</ORGANIZATION> says its <MONEY>$3.4 billion</MONEY> purchase of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures
Entertainment Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which follows its <DATE>1987</DATE> buyout of <ORGANIZATION>CBS Records</ORGANIZATION>,
is aimed at getting involved in making ``software'' to use in the
audio-visual equipment it sells.
   But don't worry about Rambo decked out as a samurai next time
around, or <PERSON>Michael Jackson</PERSON> singing in Japanese.
   What <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> wants out of these American companies, say analysts,
is for them to keep doing what they're best at _ turning out the
American-style entertainment that dominates cinema and music
markets worldwide.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>'s recent wheeling and dealing involved some of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
pop icons: Rambo, <PERSON>Bruce Springsteen</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola Co.</ORGANIZATION>, to name a
few.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> it is buying the <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> studios, home
of Rambo. Two years ago it plunked down <MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY> for <ORGANIZATION>CBS Records</ORGANIZATION>,
which has contracts with stars such as <PERSON>Springsteen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Michael
Jackson</PERSON>.
   Meanwhile, <ORGANIZATION>Coca-Cola</ORGANIZATION> stands to collect <MONEY>$1.45 billion</MONEY> from
selling its <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT> share in <LOCATION>Columbia</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>.
   But while a few American pundits have raised concerns that <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>
may use its new media clout for ``propaganda'' purposes, industry
analysts in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> scoff.
   ``I don't think they would be so stupid,'' says <PERSON>Martin
Beresford</PERSON>, a senior analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Jardine Fleming Securities</ORGANIZATION>.
Propaganda films probably wouldn't be great hits at the box office,
he notes, and censorship would be too dangerous.
   ``<ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> is far too sophisticated to consider something as
blatantly inappropriate (as propaganda or censorship) ... they know
that even the merest whiff of that would constitute an enormous
public relations risk.''
   Analysts say <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> has taken a hands-off policy at <ORGANIZATION>CBS Records</ORGANIZATION>,
leaving the music-making to Americans while providing Japanese
financial backing. So far this formula has made the <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> venture far
more profitable than analysts had expected.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>'s last annual report noted with satisfaction that ``a large
number of hit albums'' from <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION> contributed to a <PERCENT>37.9 percent</PERCENT>
annual increase in overall sales, which hit <MONEY>$16.2 billion</MONEY> in the
year ended <DATE>March 31</DATE>. The company's net income, at <MONEY>$549 million</MONEY>, was
up <PERCENT>94.6 percent</PERCENT> from the previous year.
   ``As is the case with <ORGANIZATION>CBS Records</ORGANIZATION>, we would intend to operate
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> as a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> company with <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> management,'' <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> President
<PERSON>Norio Ohga</PERSON> said.
   In effect, <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> wants to sell American ``software'' _ what used
to be known as movies and television shows _ in new forms, such as
laser disks and 8mm video tapes.
   Analysts say it's a rational division of labor.
   While Japanese electronics companies are crack manufacturers and
exporters of gee-whiz technology, the Japanese film and music
industries are about as competitive in world markets as American
soy sauce makers.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> movies, by contrast, are one of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s biggest export
success stories from <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Bangkok</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Katmandu</LOCATION>. Hollwood is
dream-seller to the world, with entertainment ranking as <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
second largest export, netting <MONEY>$5 billion</MONEY> annually.
   Rambo can be seen (surreptitiously) in even isolationist <LOCATION>Burma</LOCATION>;
``The Last Emperor,'' also a <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> film, was shown in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. In
<LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>, American films are so popular that alleged agents of
local filmmakers, fearing competition, released snakes and tear gas
into theaters to discourage people from seeing directly distributed
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> films.
   The reception in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> is friendlier. Japanese love American
films as much as Americans love Japanese electronics. America
exports more movies to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> than to any other single market;
entertainment is one area in which the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> enjoys a
surplus with its economic archrival.
   ``For many Japanese, `movies' means American movies. They don't
think of American films as foreign films,'' says <PERSON>Hidekazu Tanaka</PERSON>,
an official at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Pictures</ORGANIZATION>' <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> branch.
   Among films shown in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> last year, 289 were American,
were Japanese.
   The top four grossing films in Japanese history were ``E.T.,''
``Star Wars,'' ``Jaws,'' and ``Ghostbusters,'' according to
industry statistics.
   ``Ghostbusters,'' a <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> release, brought in profits of
<MONEY>$17.8 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1984</DATE>. ``Fatal Attraction'' recovered all of its
production costs in Japanese theaters alone.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> is reportedly eager to expand the number of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s
library of more than 2,700 movies available on laser disk and 8mm
video. Classic <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> films popular in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> include ``Bridge
over the <LOCATION>River Kwai</LOCATION>,'' ``Lawrence of Arabia,'' and ``On the
Waterfront.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901001-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-01-90 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     10-01 0813</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1063</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Sir <PERSON>David Lean</PERSON>, the 82-year-old director whose
films have won 27 <ORGANIZATION>Academy Awards</ORGANIZATION>, is planning to marry for the
sixth time, his lawyer said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Lean will wed 51-year-old interior designer <PERSON>Sandra Cooke</PERSON> before
<DATE>Christmas</DATE>, said attorney <PERSON>Michael Gee</PERSON>.
   The couple met five years ago in the frozen-food department of
Harrods department store where <PERSON>Ms. Cooke</PERSON> went up to Lean and asked
when his next film was due, said The Daily Mail's columnist <PERSON>Nigel
Dempster</PERSON>.
   Lean and <PERSON>Ms. Cooke</PERSON> were vacationing in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, Gee said. The
director's next film project will be an adaptation of <PERSON>Joseph
Conrad</PERSON>'s novel ``Nostromo.''
   Lean is the director of such classics as ``The Bridge on the
River Kwai,'' ``Lawrence of Arabia'' and ``Great Expectations.''
   ---
   <LOCATION>NEW YORK</LOCATION> (AP) - <ORGANIZATION>NBC</ORGANIZATION> newswoman <PERSON>Jane Pauley</PERSON>, who has interviewed
hundreds of celebrities, says she's still waiting to land an
elusive scoop: her husband, <PERSON>Garry Trudeau</PERSON>.
   ``I have thought about asking him,'' said <PERSON>Pauley</PERSON>, ``but a) he
would never do it, and b) I would not ultimately do it. But I know
it's a neat story.''
   Trudeau, the Pulitzer Prize-winning cartoonist, celebrates
<ORGANIZATION>Doonesbury</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>20th anniversary this month</DATE>.
   In an interview in the <DATE>Oct. 8</DATE> issue of People magazine, <ORGANIZATION>Pauley</ORGANIZATION>
