<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890206-0216 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-89 1332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-WildlifeResearch Adv12   02-06 1080</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Wildlife Research, Adv 12,1109</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv12</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Feb. 12, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Scientists Work to Preserve Animals in South African Reserve</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: An accompanying item is BC-Wildlife-Wild Dogs, b0778</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LAURINDA KEYS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SKUKUZA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An American inventor and wildlife
researchers at <ORGANIZATION>Kruger National Park</ORGANIZATION> say they have achieved a major
breakthrough in conservation _ an immunization system that can stop
epidemics in free-ranging animals.
   The breakthrough is the bio-bullet, a vaccine in a biodegradable
projectile that can be fired by an air rifle from a helicopter. It
has been used for three years to immunize animals ranging from
warthogs to elephants against diseases that have nearly wiped out
species in the park, a 7,800-square-mile reserve.
   Anthrax is endemic in the northern part of the park, an area
where 200 rare roan antelope roam. Before <DATE>1970</DATE>, when the park began
an inoculation program by firing disposable darts at the animals
from the air, severe outbreaks had affected most of the herd animals.
   ``If we have another major outbreak, we have a method now of
controlling the epidemic,'' said <PERSON>Valerius de Vos</PERSON>, head of research
at <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>. ``I consider this a major breakthrough. ... It will be
used widely in the future.''
   How widely depends to some extent on politics. While <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>'s wildlife management program is regarded as the best on the
continent, its experts seldom visit other African countries where
similar problems exist. Black African governments restrict contact
with <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> because of apartheid, its system of racial
separation.
   ``It's a pity,'' de Vos said. ``The rest of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> needs us and
we need them. We've got expertise and we need interaction.''
   For instance, the numbers of endangered black rhinos are
increasing in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> but declining elsewhere. Due to South
African conservation efforts, the white rhino was removed from the
endangered category worldwide.
   Representatives of private wildlife groups sometimes come to
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, and exchanges take place by mail, but many Western
universities won't send copies of research papers to <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>'s
scientists.
   <PERSON>Gus Mills</PERSON>, the chief predator researcher, made a tape recording
of hyena territorial cries and plays it from a jeep at night.
   ``All the hyena in the area come around to listen and we can
count them,'' he said. ``I've sent my tape to <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> and now Kenyan
hyenas are listening to South African hyenas.''
   De <PERSON>Vos</PERSON> said the air-rifle that fires the bio-bullet can be
locally produced, but not the bullet itself. He worries what
sanctions could disrupt the immunization program.
   There has been talk of banning shipments of four-wheel drive
vehicles to <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, because they have military
potential.
   ``That's going to affect us,'' de Vos said. ``I don't know what
we're going to do, but I guess we can keep going with two-wheel
drive vehicles.''
   In <DATE>1973</DATE> de Vos and his team began inoculating large mammals by
firing dart-syringes from the air. Disadvantages included large
numbers of plastic darts left on the ground, and the time and cost
of manufacturing the syringes.
   De Vos found <PERSON>Fred Paul</PERSON>, an inventor from <LOCATION>White Bear Lake</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>,
who had developed the bio-bullet and used it to vaccinate domestic
livestock and wild bighorn sheep. Paul came to <ORGANIZATION>Kruger Park</ORGANIZATION> to assist
the research, which includingfiring different-sized bullets at
varying velocities until the right size and shape were determined.
   The bullet can be fired rapidly, allowing marksmen to inoculate
about 1,500 animals a day with <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy. The material, a
cellulose polymer, dissolves inside the animal, releasing the
vaccine.
   Vaccinating 1,500 animals a day with <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> accuracy is
``impressive, to say the least. ... That's a lot of animals,'' said
<PERSON>Maurice LeFranc</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute for Wildlife Research</ORGANIZATION>, a
branch of <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The South African park lends itself to such an effort because it
has wide open spaces and concentrations of animals, <PERSON>LeFranc</PERSON> said in
<LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va</LOCATION>.
   The project illustrates the place that South African wildlife
researchers have in the forefront of species preservation and the
<ORGANIZATION>National Park Board</ORGANIZATION>'s philosophy about when to let nature take its
course and when man should intervene.
   ``<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> has taken a real strong leadership in the
preservation and conservation of their wildlife,'' said <PERSON>Dr. Werner
Heuschele</PERSON>, an endangered species specialist at the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION> in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>. ``Some of their game parks are among the best managed in
the world.''
   One researcher at <ORGANIZATION>Kruger</ORGANIZATION> is capturing impala to find a cure for a
human-caused stress disease that occurs when antelope are chased for
long distances and caught in a net. In the wild, predators chase
impalas only for short distances.
   The main form of research at <ORGANIZATION>Kruger</ORGANIZATION> is surveillance _ taking
aerial photos of vegetation, counting animals, taking blood levels
of elephants to see if car exhaust affects them. The data is fed
into computers to help determine what projects are needed in the
park, a fenced area the size of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   Roads affect the natural spread of fire, so controlled fires are
set deliberately. Fenced animals cannot migrate during drought, so
dams are built.
   In the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, wildebeest rapidly diminished. A new fence
around the park had cut off one herd's traditional migration route,
and heavy rainfall encouraged long grass, rather than the short
grass the wildebeest like.
   Managers could have set fires to eliminate the tall grass.
Instead, they decided to kill off lions and hyenas who preyed on the
wildebeest.
   To prevent the need for such action in the future, <PERSON>Mills</PERSON> and his
team spend two weeks at a time following lions, cheetah and
leopards, to monitor their eating habits.
   ``Are they depressing the prey in large numbers or living in
harmony with their environment?'' Mills says researchers want to
know.
   Although anthrax and foot-and-mouth disease are natural African
diseases, they are controlled because it would take 20 to 30 years
for the herds to recover after an endemic.
   ``Drastic fluctuations in animal populations are part of nature,
but we can't afford that,'' said de Vos.
   ``We cull (shoot) buffalo and elephant, and sometimes hippo.
These are species that can outgrow the system. The rest of the
animals are controlled by the system. Drought, predation, disease
all act as controls. For the buffalo and elephant the main predator
in the past was man. We have taken man out of it, so now we're
bringing man back in, in a controlled way.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Feb. 12</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900907-0087 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-90 1247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i BRF--HyenaHouseGuest     09-07 0182</FIRST>
<SECOND>BRF--Hyena House Guest,0183</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hyena Trapped in Bathroom Floods Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SKUKUZA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hyena that accidentally locked
itself in the bathroom at a game park got the last laugh _ it tore
the room apart and opened the shower tap, flooding the house.
   The Star newspaper said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the hyena spent 24 hours in the
bathroom <DATE>last weekend</DATE> at the house in <LOCATION>Skukuza</LOCATION>, a village in <LOCATION>Kruger
National Park</LOCATION> in eastern <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. It apparently wandered into
the house while the occupants were away.
   The hyena pulled down curtains, ripped the medicine chest from
the wall, smashed the toilet seat, damaged a towel rail and bit
into aerosal shaving cream and deodorant cans, the Star said.
   It also turned on the shower, causing overflowing water to seep
under the door into the rest of the house, the newspaper said.
   Neighbors saw water coming out from under the front door and
alerted game rangers, who shot the hyena with a tranquilizer dart
through the bathroom window. Tests on the animal indicated no
serious injuries, and the hyena was released.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900907-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-90 1308EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--HyenaHouseGuest     09-07 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Hyena House Guest,0191</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hyena Trapped in Bathroom Floods Home</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Retransmitting a0575 to restore cycle designator.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>SKUKUZA, South Africa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A hyena that accidentally locked
itself in the bathroom at a game park got the last laugh _ it tore
the room apart and opened the shower tap, flooding the house.
   The Star newspaper said <DATE>Friday</DATE> the hyena spent 24 hours in the
bathroom <DATE>last weekend</DATE> at the house in <LOCATION>Skukuza</LOCATION>, a village in <LOCATION>Kruger
National Park</LOCATION> in eastern <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. It apparently wandered into
the house while the occupants were away.
   The hyena pulled down curtains, ripped the medicine chest from
the wall, smashed the toilet seat, damaged a towel rail and bit
into aerosal shaving cream and deodorant cans, the Star said.
   It also turned on the shower, causing overflowing water to seep
under the door into the rest of the house, the newspaper said.
   Neighbors saw water coming out from under the front door and
alerted game rangers, who shot the hyena with a tranquilizer dart
through the bathroom window. Tests on the animal indicated no
serious injuries, and the hyena was released.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-17525</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EDCACAEPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940402
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 APR 94 / Travel: Survival is a dogfight for the wild bunch - Wild
dogs in Africa may become rarer than the rhino. Michael J Woods tracked them
down
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MICHAEL J WOODS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
There was a dull pock, like the sound of a tennis ball bouncing lightly on
grass, as the compressed air-gun expelled its tranquilliser dart. The
African wild dog sprang to its feet as if it had been stung. With a yelp it
dashed off, a red woollen tassel dangling from the syringe in its shoulder.
'It won't go far,' said Dr <PERSON>Gus Mills</PERSON>, and we sat in his truck for the 10
minutes needed for the drug to work. It took a little time to find the
sleeping dog in the thick bush, as its black, white and tan blotched coat
blended remarkably well with the broken shadows cast on the grey dusty soil.
Once located, though, a radio collar was swiftly fitted, a sample of blood
taken and the antidote injected. In less than a minute the dog was on its
feet and had gone to join the rest of Mbyamiti pack, which now had two dogs
carrying radio transmitters.
<PERSON>Gus Mills</PERSON> is a scientist who works in <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON> national park, a long
rectangular area about the size of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> on the eastern boundary of <LOCATION>South
Africa</LOCATION>. He has been researching African wild dogs, also known as <LOCATION>Cape</LOCATION>
hunting dogs, for some years. His subjects are rangy animals with noticeably
large rounded ears, three-coloured coats and a height of a little over 2ft.
They are efficient hunters, running as a pack and killing at dawn and dusk
if they can, and lying-up in shade during the heat of the day. Only for the
short breeding period are they tied to a den; for the rest of the year they
are nomadic and appear to need a large territory to survive.
There are only about 360 wild dogs in <LOCATION>Kruger</LOCATION>; the lion and hyena populations
both top 2,000 for the same area. All is not well with wild dogs. They have
become very scarce in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> - rarer, some say, than the rhino, which makes
them <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s most threatened large carnivore.
Historically, their undeservedly bad reputation has led to persecution by
farmers. Until 20 years ago, they were even shot in some national parks.
There are still farmers who will not tolerate dogs and consider them vermin,
so that packs straying from conservation areas are at risk.
Only big stretches of protected wilderness will suffice to provide wild dogs
with enough space to survive. The national parks in the north of <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> and in the south of <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> fulfil these requirements, and
contain reasonable numbers of dogs. But these very extensive areas are
largely unpenetrated by roads and, for the discerning visitor, for whom a
glimpse of a dog is more exciting than any of the big five (lion, leopard,
elephant, rhino, buffalo), spotting one is extremely difficult.
Things seem to be slightly easier in <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>. Finding them by radio is the
only way that researchers such as <PERSON>Gus Mills</PERSON> can ensure that packs are
monitored on a regular basis, and dogs are often seen by visitors to the
park. In fact, <PERSON>Gus</PERSON> was able to use tourist sightings of wild dogs to obtain
a measure of the number of animals in the park.
By offering a free film for every usable photograph of a dog, he soon had
pictures of almost every animal. The dog population in <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON> is one of the
densest so far recorded in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, and the extensive network of roads is
frequently used by packs on the move.
'Morning and evening are the best times to look for dogs,' Gus told me.
'That is when they hunt, for they rest in the heat of the day and then their
low profile and disruptive coloration make them almost impossible to spot.'
<PERSON>Kruger</PERSON> has much to offer in addition to wild dogs. I came across lions and
elephants in abundance along with rhino and giraffes. Many of the smaller
animals, so often missed elsewhere, are visible here, too. I found a dwarf
mongoose den by the roadside and was able to watch the lightning activities
of its delightful inhabitants as they foraged through the undergrowth and
then rocketed across open areas for fear of raptors.
On two occasions I had to wait for leopard tortoises to cross the track and
once swerved to avoid a chameleon, bright green against the khaki sand,
rocking its way so very slowly over the ruts.
But it was wild dogs I wanted to see, and the more I questioned <PERSON>Gus Mills</PERSON>,
the more mysteries I encountered. Packs, for instance, fluctuate markedly in
size, and <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>'s <LOCATION>Skukuza</LOCATION> pack, which numbered 40 dogs in <DATE>1989</DATE>, now
consists of just three males.
Dogs disappear in large numbers for no apparent reason, and bodies are
rarely found. This was the reason for putting a collar on a second animal of
the Mbyamiti pack, as an insurance against the death or disappearance of the
dog already collared.
In <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>, a wild dog's expectation of life is unusually short - rarely
beyond four years (a hyena's is about 15). Gus has heard several accounts of
lions killing both adults and pups, and would like to investigate more fully
the role lions play in the lives of dogs.
Fortunately, international awareness is growing. The <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON> wild dog study
is funded by the <ORGANIZATION>National Parks Board</ORGANIZATION> and the independent <PERSON>Stuart Bromfield</PERSON>
Wild Dog Fund of the <ORGANIZATION>Endangered Wildlife Trust</ORGANIZATION>. This trust also finances
other wild dog projects in <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, along with the newly-established
Licaone Fund in <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>.
published an action plan for African wild dogs, so there is considerable
hope for the future.
I spent a week in <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON>, and it wasn't until my last day that I found dogs
for myself. The sun was sinking and, briefly, painting the bush a golden
green. The insects were tuning up for their evening chorus and the cacophony
of guinea fowl was at its loudest. There was a sudden snort from an impala
ram in the undergrowth beside the vehicle and he quickly made himself
scarce.
Then I was aware that, coming towards me along the road ahead, were a dozen
lean dark silhouettes with familiar big round ears. The long legs carrying
those lithe bodies touched the ground so lightly that the animals almost
seemed to float along in a distance-devouring trot. I stopped quickly and
the grinning dogs went by. The sun lit them for a second, then they wheeled
and melted into the trees - a moment of pure magic.
<PERSON>Michael Woods</PERSON> was a guest of the <ORGANIZATION>South African Tourism Board</ORGANIZATION> (<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> tel:
081-944-8080) and <PERSON>Kruger</PERSON> national park.
He flew from <LOCATION>Bristol</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Amsterdam</LOCATION> with <ORGANIZATION>KLM</ORGANIZATION> and then caught its long-haul
flight to <LOCATION>Johannesburg</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>KLM</ORGANIZATION> runs a similar service from 16 UK regional
airports, thus avoiding the often time-consuming journey to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and the
two-hour check-in.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>ZAZ  South Africa, Africa.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06128186 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06128186 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SCIENCE; MEDICAL; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  THE question of who first isolated the AIDS virus, a subject of heated debate
between researchers in France and America for more than six years, may have
been at least partly resolved Monday.;    A major puzzle emerged when the two
original strains isolated by Dr. Robert Gallo of the National Institutes of
Health and Dr. Luc Montagnier of the Pasteur Institute in France turned out to
be virtually identical.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Science &amp; Medicine  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CLUES EXPLAIN AIDS CO-DISCOVERY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Briefs
Science Scene
Compiled by Sylvia Wright from Mercury News wire services.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     According to a paper to be published this week in Science magazine, a new
finding by Montagnier points strongly to lab contaminations. Both sides now
seem to agree that a particularly fast-multiplying strain of the virus
apparently contaminated samples in <LOCATION>Montagnier</LOCATION>'s lab. Unaware the contamination
had occurred, the French lab sent the samples to <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON>'s lab. The aggressive
strain then apparently contaminated samples in the American lab as well.;   
Both labs ended up reporting virtually identical strains, and accusations of
misappropriation flew.; Bugs defended; A plan to turn insects into astronauts
is bugging animal rights activists.;    Amateur rocketeers plan to launch
model rockets filled with bees and grasshoppers next year in recognition of
the 500th anniversary of <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>' arrival in the <LOCATION>New World.</LOCATION>;   
High school and college students would build the rockets for experiments in
which they would measure temperature, air pressure and radiation surrounding
the rockets and observe the insects through video cameras.;    The creatures
and the equipment would parachute back to earth. But the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society</ORGANIZATION> and
other groups say blasting bugs is cruel and a waste of time.; New telescope;
An <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> array of radio telescope antennas will be built atop <PERSON>Mauna Kea</PERSON>,
announced Monday.;    The antennas will work together as a single unit, to be
called the <ORGANIZATION>Submillimeter Telescope Array</ORGANIZATION>. They will operate in a narrow band
of short wavelengths between infrared and radio in the electromagnetic
spectrum. With this band scientists can look into the center of exploding
galaxies and pierce the halos of comets and the atmospheres of planets.; Hyena
siblicide; Carrying sibling rivalry to an extreme, hour-old spotted hyenas
routinely attack their younger siblings just moments after birth, report
been observed in some birds but never before in mammals. <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> zoologist
<PERSON>Dr. Laurence G. Frank</PERSON> speculated that the attacks might be due to high levels
of two male hormones present at birth in both males and females.;    Spotted
hyenas normally give birth to litters of two cubs. Both are born with open
eyes and a full set of incisors and are immediately capable of strong,
coordinated action.;    In the wild, the attacks can result in death from
infection or the inability to nurse. At <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION>, the scientists filming the
births in pens rescued the second cub. Their findings are reported in the
current issue of Science.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910507  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  487  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday May 7, 1991
00128186,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011490-0067 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 161841 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 14, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 29; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1090 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TRAVEL VIDEOS: FROM AFRICAN PLAINS TO THE JUNGLE OF COSTA RICA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BETTY MARTIN, Martin is a former staff member of the Travel Section. Her 
column on travel videos appears monthly. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
This month we'll study a couple of new -- and excellent -- videos, one dealing 
with <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, the other with <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>. And while both deal with wildlife 
conservation, the <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION> video involves other subjects as well. 
</P>
<P>
"Africa" (two videos), <LOCATION>Eco Ventures</LOCATION>, 45 minutes each (<DATE>1988</DATE>). These two 
remarkable videos, produced by <PERSON>Megan Epler</PERSON> Wood and narrated by <PERSON>George 
Plimpton</PERSON>, will be of special interest to African safari planners and 
ecology-minded armchair travelers. Each video combines spectacular scenery with 
a detailed study of the animals found in parks along the Tanzania-Kenya border. 
</P>
<P>
The first tape opens with stunning views of the vast, 10,000-square-mile 
Serengeti Plain and a map showing the path of migration that the hundreds of 
thousands of zebra, wildebeest and gazelles make on their annual search for 
grasslands and water. According to the narration, it's an ecological cycle that 
has continued for 10 million years. 
</P>
<P>
The camera follows the trek and shows how the animals surmount the incredible 
hardships of their long journey, including the constant threat of predators -- 
hyenas, wild dogs and lions. 
</P>
<P>
You get contrasting, touching scenes of the family-oriented zebra grooming each 
other and the birth of a soon-doomed wildebeest. 
</P>
<P>
The sound and sight of the thundering herd as it struggles across the swiftly 
flowing <LOCATION>Mara River</LOCATION> are a video highlight that <PERSON>Plimpton</PERSON> calls "one of the 
greatest wildlife spectacles on earth." 
</P>
<P>
Later, <ORGANIZATION>Wood</ORGANIZATION> captures some poignant and amusing scenes of the six-ton elephants 
splashing and playing as they cool off in the mud holes of <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli National 
Park</ORGANIZATION> at the foot of <LOCATION>Mt. Kilimanjaro</LOCATION>. Elephant teen-agers are shown 
trunk-wrestling, and at an elephant family gathering, viewers watch seniors 
embracing each other as if greeting old friends. Other animals shown in the 
park include flamingoes, cape buffalo, wart hogs and ostriches. 
</P>
<P>
The video concludes with a discussion between <PERSON>Plimpton</PERSON> and <PERSON>Russell Train</PERSON>, 
chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>World Wildlife Fund/The Conservation Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, on the threat 
from poachers to this one-great concentration of elephants. 
</P>
<P>
The second tape opens with film clips of an Osa and <PERSON>Martin Johnson</PERSON> safari of 
the <DATE>1920s</DATE>, then concentrates on following the social structure and daily life 
of a pride of lions. 
</P>
<P>
Viewers follow the female as she stalks her prey, while the male spends his day 
lying around surveying his realm, and the cubs wrestle and explore. The pride 
survives in spite of the fact that, according to <PERSON>Plimpton</PERSON>, the female is a poor 
huntress, missing five out of six tries. There also are brief scenes of some of 
the other cats in the <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara Game Reserve</ORGANIZATION>, including leopards and cheetahs. 
</P>
<P>
Later, producer Wood opens with early film from the movie "<LOCATION>King Kong</LOCATION>," 
comparing it with the gentle mountain gorillas found in the <LOCATION>Virunga Mountains 
of Rwanda</LOCATION>, where the late anthropologist <PERSON>Dian Fossey</PERSON> lived and died studying 
them. 
</P>
<P>
The gorillas, which usually live at an altitude of 8,000 to 10,000 feet, don't 
survive in captivity. Viewers will see the females flirting with the males, and 
the majestic silverback males protecting their territory. 
</P>
<P>
Mountain gorillas are vegetarians, and scenes show them munching on the 
greenery and lolling in the sun, a favorite activity, while young ones stumble 
and frolic as they leave their mother to explore. 
</P>
<P>
Plimpton and Train conclude this segment with a discussion on preserving the 
mountain gorilla and the part that tourism plays in making the world aware of 
the nened for conservation. 
</P>
<P>
The tapes are available from Eco Ventures, <DATE>2021</DATE> L. Street <LOCATION>N.W.</LOCATION>, Suite 250, 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION> 20036. Call toll-free (800) 862-8900. Price: <MONEY>$29.95</MONEY>, or two 
for <MONEY>$49.95</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
"Costa Rica" (<ORGANIZATION>Megaview Productions International</ORGANIZATION>), <DATE>1988</DATE>, 34 minutes. This is 
one of the few videos on <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>, and it's remarkably good. For those who 
have been there, for those planning a trip or for those just curious, it's a 
worthwhile addition to a travel video collection. 
</P>
<P>
Against a montage of quick scenes showing some of the beauty and appeal of this 
Central American country -- lush green forests, rivers, volcanoes, gambling 
casinos and fishing -- the narrator gives viewers a bit of history as well as 
vital statistics on the high literacy rate, climate, number of bird species 
(850), national parks (26), which airlines fly there and an overview of the 
type of its hotels, facilities and restaurants. 
</P>
<P>
The major part of the video, however, takes viewers on a series of tours that 
cover the most popular tourist attractions. 
</P>
<P>
These include a tour of the capital, <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, showing scenes of the shopping 
district, central market place, national museum, national theater and 
restaurants. Side trips from <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> include a visit to Sarchi and its ox-cart 
factory, where the colorful native souvenirs, as well as other crafts, are made 
and sold, and a visit to the enchanting <LOCATION>Orosi Valley</LOCATION> on the tumultuous 
<LOCATION>Reventazon River</LOCATION> for scenes of an exciting river rafting trip. This is followed 
by a tour to <LOCATION>Tiquicia</LOCATION>, "Tico" country, to a typical adobe farm-ranch restaurant 
to enjoy scenes of native food and entertainment. 
</P>
<P>
Irazu volcano, topping 11,000 feet and from which you can see both the 
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>, is another tour destination, as is a visit to the 
rim of the awesome, still-active Poas volcano. At <LOCATION>Cartago</LOCATION>, at the foot of 
Irazu, viewers also see the <LOCATION>Basilica de Los Angeles</LOCATION>, where the La Negrita (the 
Black Virgin) statue is enshrined and to whom miracles have been attributed. 
</P>
<P>
A video highlight is the ride on the jungle train that connects Limon to <LOCATION>San 
Jose</LOCATION>, passing through coffee and banana plantations and small villages of the 
interior. 
</P>
<P>
Other tours include a jungle adventure launch ride along the <LOCATION>Colorado River</LOCATION> and 
canals, with a stop at a lodge in the town of <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, and trips to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Monteverde Cloud Forest</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Carara Biological Reserve</ORGANIZATION> to view some of the 
many examples of the colorful and unusual plants, birds and animals being 
protected in <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Nature lovers also will be rewarded with film and narration on the leatherback 
turtles seen laying their eggs on the beach. A final stop is at <LOCATION>Lake Arenal</LOCATION>, 
where fishermen are seen big-game fishing. 
</P>
<P>
Although the production was filmed in cooperation with the <ORGANIZATION>Swiss Travel 
Service</ORGANIZATION>, a tour company of <LOCATION>Costa Rica</LOCATION>, there are no blatant commercial plugs 
and no tie-ins with hotels or other tourist facilities. 
</P>
<P>
Tapes are available from <ORGANIZATION>Megaview Productions</ORGANIZATION>, 255 <ORGANIZATION>N. El Cielo Road</ORGANIZATION>, Suite 155, 
<LOCATION>Palm Springs</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> 92262, (619) 366-8464. Price: <MONEY>$25</MONEY>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A lion on the Serengeti Plain appears oblivious to the hot-air balloon. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Recording Review 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032590-0057 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 194571 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 25, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 1; Column 6; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1957 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WET &amp; WILD; 
</P>
<P>
AFRICA BY CANOE; 
</P>
<P>
GLIDING AMONG THE RICH WILDLIFE OF BOTSWANA'S OKAVANGO DELTA 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LYNDON STAMBLER, Stambler is a Santa Monica free-lance writer. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
MAUN, Botswana 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Later I got used to not caring a damn, just to walking and staying put when I 
had walked far enough, at some village of which I didn't know the name, to 
letting myself drift with <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. -- <PERSON>Graham Greene</PERSON>, "Journey Without Maps" 
</P>
<P>
Drifting with the currents on <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION>, gliding through 
channels choked by papyrus and lily pads is like a journey without maps. 
</P>
<P>
I found myself in unfamiliar territory, not caring about anything but sitting 
back and enjoying the sky, the clouds and the birds as our canoe passed red and 
yellow reeds, swamp grasses, sausage trees and fields of maize. 
</P>
<P>
I watched wallowing hippos, heard the screech of baboons and, in the <TIME>evening</TIME>, 
fell asleep to a symphony of swamp sounds. I was not oblivious to the dangers 
of this watery wilderness, but it was hard to feel threatened in such pristine, 
even hypnotic, surroundings. 
</P>
<P>
Before <DATE>1923</DATE> there were no comprehensive maps of the <ORGANIZATION>Okavango Delta</ORGANIZATION>, a lush 
waterway on the edge of the <LOCATION>Kalahari Desert</LOCATION>. It's nearly impossible to 
accurately map an area that changes so dramatically with the seasons. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Okavango River</LOCATION>, which begins in the <LOCATION>Angola Highlands</LOCATION>, swells during the 
rainy season (<DATE>November</DATE> to <DATE>April</DATE>) and floods over a depression in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, 
forming the world's largest inland delta: 6,500 square miles of inlets, flood 
plains, lagoons and islands. 
</P>
<P>
I went on a four-day water safari last <DATE>May</DATE>. It was a good time to visit. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> was in full flood, lush with vegetation, and the weather was dry and warm 
but never too hot. 
</P>
<P>
I saw lots of wildlife, though I probably would have seen more at the end of 
the dry season in <DATE>September</DATE> and <DATE>October</DATE> when herds of animals come to the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> 
in search of water. 
</P>
<P>
Canoes, which are like water taxis, are the only way to get around much of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. They transport people from village to village, to fishing or hunting 
areas. Polers are the taxi drivers, having grown up navigating the channels. 
They stand in the stern, moving the canoe forward with a long forked pole (a 
ngashi). 
</P>
<P>
 My journey began when two friends -- <PERSON>Katie Janssen</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>John Blank</ORGANIZATION> -- showed up 
at my door in <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>. They had just finished a year teaching in 
Kenyan villages. I was on a six-month trip to <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION>, visiting a friend who 
works there. 
</P>
<P>
Katie and <PERSON>John</PERSON> were driving through eastern and southern <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and suggested a 
trip to the <LOCATION>Okavango</LOCATION> -- the "Serengeti of Swamps" they called it. I was game. 
</P>
<P>
It's hard to stick to a timetable when you're traveling in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> in a '67 Land 
Rover. Every time we hit a rut I braced myself to avoid hitting my head on the 
roof. We stalled each time mud splashed on the spark plugs, which was often. 
</P>
<P>
It took three days to make the 700-mile trip to the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. We passed through 
customs behind a huge bus of Zimbabweans going to <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> to shop. 
</P>
<P>
Later, <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION> soldiers stopped us at a roadblock. They were apparently making 
a routine check for South African secret agents who conduct undercover 
operations in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, trying to find <ORGANIZATION>African National Congress</ORGANIZATION> guerrillas. 
They let us pass. 
</P>
<P>
After a long drive along the northern edge of the surprisingly lush <LOCATION>Kalahari 
Desert</LOCATION> it was a relief to see water. We had reached <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION>, the gateway to the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> is a patchwork of old and new, with posh hotels going up next to 
traditional villages. 
</P>
<P>
Herero women, refugees from <LOCATION>Namibia</LOCATION>, wander the streets dressed in colorful 
long dresses adopted from 19th-Century German colonists, but decorated with 
African patterns. 
</P>
<P>
Our home base was 7 1/2 miles north of <LOCATION>Maun</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Island Safari Lodge</ORGANIZATION>. We shared a 
campsite with several <LOCATION>South Africans</LOCATION> speaking <LOCATION>Afrikaans</LOCATION>. They tried to convince 
us that apartheid doesn't exist, and that they weren't such "bad guys." They 
regaled us with tales of traversing the African bush. 
</P>
<P>
But we were more interested in water and canoes than Afrikaner tales. So we 
decided to hire a canoe and poler for four days through Island Safaris, at the 
lodge. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Kay Potter</PERSON>, who operates the lodge with her husband <PERSON>Phil</PERSON>, recommends using 
Fiberglas canoes rather than the traditional mokoros, which are carved from 
sausage trees. 
</P>
<P>
"You have to chop down a sausage tree to make a mokoro," she said. "Before long 
the trees will be gone. Besides, you get a wet bum in a mokoro. I guarantee 
it." We were to get "wet bums" anyway. 
</P>
<P>
The next day a speedboat took us into the <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. As we went deeper, the winding 
pathway through the lily pads grew narrower. The boatman moved expertly through 
the tortuous channels at breakneck speed. Every so often he would stop and 
reverse the motor, when the prop became clogged with reeds. 
</P>
<P>
After two hours we reached an island inhabited by polers who were sitting 
around a fire making coffee in tin cans and cooking mielie meal. Mielie meal, 
the staple food in <LOCATION>sub-Saharan Africa</LOCATION>, is like thick grits. It fills you up but 
won't put meat on your bones. A telltale sign: There wasn't an overweight man 
among the polers. 
</P>
<P>
They didn't pay much heed to us when we arrived. But eventually <PERSON>Kenneth Monare</PERSON>, 
a tall, barefoot man wearing shorts and a blue T-shirt, approached us. He would 
be our pilot and guide for the next four days. 
</P>
<P>
We were lucky. Kenneth spoke English and enjoyed practicing it with us. He also 
taught us a few <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION> phrases. Although English is the official language of 
<LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION>, a Bantu language of the <LOCATION>Tswana</LOCATION> tribe, is spoken by <PERCENT>90%</PERCENT> of 
its population. 
</P>
<P>
Monare's friend Kid, a shorter man wearing a <ORGANIZATION>BMW</ORGANIZATION> jacket, piloted the other 
canoe in our party, which also included a Canadian couple who were traveling 
around the world. 
</P>
<P>
When the polers were ready, we glided out into a channel bound for Chief's 
<LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, the main island in <ORGANIZATION>Moremi Wildlife Reserve</ORGANIZATION> (set up by the <LOCATION>Tswana</LOCATION> tribe 
in <DATE>1962</DATE> to protect the animals) and one of the best game reserves in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Kenneth stood in the stern and began rhythmically poling us forward. The prow 
of the canoe parted the reeds that sprouted like stubble from the water. 
Sometimes a spider, while stretching a web between the reeds, would fall into 
our canoe. 
</P>
<P>
The spiders were fat, dark and fuzzy, though non-poisonous. We would either 
toss them out of the canoe or carry them along with us to another part of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION>. The webs were often so beautiful that I felt sad, as if we had destroyed 
a work of art. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Delta</ORGANIZATION> is a palette of colors: yellow water lilies, white and pink flowers 
against the reeds, tiny green frogs on lily pads. 
</P>
<P>
When we passed another canoe <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> would greet his fellow poler with a hearty 
"dumela!" ("hello" in <LOCATION>Setswana</LOCATION>). I marveled at how he could navigate the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> 
maze in which channels become dead ends clogged by vegetation. Some of the 
channels are kept open only because hippos break through the reeds. 
</P>
<P>
We reached our first campsite on Chief's <LOCATION>Island</LOCATION> after three hours and a bit too 
much sun. Later, we took the canoe out to get water for cooking and to 
photograph the sunsets. The nights, what with the campfires and the stars, 
reminded me of my childhood camping trips. 
</P>
<P>
When we were quiet we were treated to a cacophony of exotic sounds: the screech 
of baboons . . . hippo grunts . . . the plaintive songs of crickets, frogs, 
birds . . . an insect that sounded like the tinkling of a toy piano, and the 
eerie cackling of hyenas. 
</P>
<P>
As we brushed our teeth we saw two yellow eyes of a bush baby, a nocturnal 
primate, staring at us through the trees. 
</P>
<P>
The sounds of mosquitoes were considerably less exciting. I was glad that I was 
wearing mosquito repellent and taking anti-malaria medication. Malaria is the 
main hazard in the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION>. It's unlikely that one would be bitten by tsetse 
flies, crocodiles, lions, leopards or poisonous snakes, but anyone who goes 
into the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> and doesn't take precautions against malaria is foolish. 
</P>
<P>
In the morning <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> took us to another spot on the northern part of Chief's 
<LOCATION>Island</LOCATION>, a place that abounds with game. We passed a deep pool where hippos were 
wallowing. Kenneth and Kid kept their distance. I was aware that an angry hippo 
could smash a canoe to bits. But <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON>, with typical African tour guide 
aplomb, said there was little danger. 
</P>
<P>
"They're very frightened," he said, as a snort came up from a hippo. Nine times 
out of 10 he's right. Of course I'd hate to be too close on that occasion when 
a hippo does decide to charge. 
</P>
<P>
As we approached our destination <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> and Kid found that the channel had 
shifted and was only a few inches deep. The thick swamp grasses made it 
impossible to move forward. After a futile effort, <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> gave us the command: 
"Get out!" 
</P>
<P>
We rolled up our pants legs and began to push the canoes through the reeds. We 
splashed through the mushy swamp. Now, I'm not one who particularly enjoys 
sticking his feet into swamp water. I had visions of leeches covering my 
calves. I feared it might be time for the crocodiles to have a picnic. I guess 
I identify more with <PERSON>Woody Allen</PERSON> than <ORGANIZATION>Indiana Jones</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
We reached our campsite tired but exhilarated. I looked back at the area we had 
just crossed -- a field of tans and yellows fading into the blue sky. 
</P>
<P>
This part of the island was deserted except for the animals. We followed 
<PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> on walking safaris. He led us for hours as he followed smells, tracks 
and droppings through the brown grass and gnarled trees. He had to quiet us 
several times to avoid frightening the animals. 
</P>
<P>
At one point, after hours of walking, he put up his hand to halt us. Several 
zebra, wildebeest, tsesebe antelope and warthogs came out in front of us, no 
more than 10 feet away. 
</P>
<P>
We were on the trail of an elephant. We could smell its musk-like odor but we 
never found it. I had seen elephants before, but always from the safety of a 
vehicle. I feared the possibility of coming face to face with one of the huge 
animals. 
</P>
<P>
But we probably were safe in <LOCATION>Kenneth</LOCATION>'s hands. He had a keen sense of the smells 
and sounds of the <ORGANIZATION>delta</ORGANIZATION> -- where to go and, perhaps more important, where not 
to go. His calm and self-confidence was reassuring. 
</P>
<P>
On our <TIME>last night</TIME> I realized why <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> wanted Kid to come along. They joked 
and laughed together, making the trip relaxed and fun for all of us. But Kid 
was also a master fisherman. He took a drop line, crouched by the water's edge 
and snared 20 fish. 
</P>
<P>
Kid and <PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> used four of the fish to make a stew for themselves, and saved 
the rest for their fellow polers. I feared that perhaps the fish would be the 
appetizer and we would be the main course for some predator -- a leopard, 
baboon or hyena, whose jaws are said to be the strongest of all animals. 
</P>
<P>
Indeed, hyenas are known to attack humans while they sleep, which is why it's 
important to keep your tent flap zipped up. But in the morning the fish were 
still dangling on the line. 
</P>
<P>
Kenneth showed us his calloused hands, which told the story of his years as a 
poler. The lodge pays him 5 pula (about <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY>) a day plus food. (Passengers are 
expected to tip their poler at the end of the trip.) 
</P>
<P>
He told us that someday he would like to own his own mokoro. But you need to 
pay a teacher 200 to 300 pula to show you how to build one. Besides that, 
<PERSON>Kenneth</PERSON> had to think about saving enough pulas to someday pay for a bride. 
Payment to the parents of the bride used to be in cattle; now you can pay in 
pulas (or VCRs in some parts of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>). 
</P>
<P>
I was happy I didn't have to worry about a bride's price. Then again, I would 
soon return to a complex world of jumbo jets and grid-locked cities, and 
somehow the life of the poler seemed more civilized and appealing. 
</P>
<P>
As we rode back to the <ORGANIZATION>Island Safari Lodge</ORGANIZATION> in a powerboat at what now seemed 
like a frenetic pace, I hoped that there would always be room in this world for 
the polers, expertly plying the uncharted delta waters. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Above, polers guide visitors through the Okavango Delta,; Photo, 
COLOR, often close to native fauna such as the crocodile.(right); Map, 
Botswana, VICTOR KOTOWITZ / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Main Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06278013 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06278013 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Zabriskie; PHOTO: Lena Horne appears on '60 Minutes'  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TELEVISION; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  HARD-CORE news purists always have given CBS's "60 Minutes" gang a bad time
over the show's frequent "soft" interviews with show-business celebrities, but
now those show-biz interviews are beginning to look like solid gold.;   Case
in point: Tonight's two-hour CBS special, "60 Minutes: The Entertainers,"
culling some of the very best moments from all the show-biz interviews the
show has done over the past couple of decades. This is a terrifically
entertaining show, probably because the good parts of those interviews are so
good, and the bad parts were left behind in the archives.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WEEKEND'S DOCUMENTARIES DELIGHTFUL, FICTION
DOUBTFUL  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Television; THE NEW SEASON; (box) 60 MINUTES: THE ENTERTAINERS; Tonight at 9
on Chs. 5, 46; (box) BEYOND REALITY; Tonight at 9 on USA (cable); (box)
SERVANTS OF TWILIGHT; Tonight at 9 on Showtime (cable); (box) ZEBRAS: PATTERNS
IN THE GRASS; Sunday night at 6 on TBS (cable); (box) PLAYED IN THE USA;
Sunday night at 7, The Learning Channel (Cable)  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Among the memorable moments:;   (check) <PERSON>Hume Cronyn</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jessica Tandy</PERSON>
faking out a startled <PERSON>Mike Wallace</PERSON> by pretending they'd decided to separate
because, as Cronyn put it, "<PERSON>Jess</PERSON> has her eye on another fellow, and I'd like
to play the field while I'm still vertical.";   (check) <PERSON>Lena Horne</PERSON>, at 64,
telling <PERSON>Ed Bradley</PERSON> she still sings earthy songs because "you can't help your
sexual nature.";   (check) Opera immortal <PERSON>Beverly Sills</PERSON> comparing herself to
"a fairly decent plumber.";   (check) <PERSON>Paul Simon</PERSON> grieving over the breakup of
his marriage to <PERSON>Carrie Fisher</PERSON> and celebrating a long overdue rapport with his
father.;   (check) <PERSON>Jackie Gleason</PERSON> explaining <PERSON>Ralph Kramden</PERSON>'s true character to
<ORGANIZATION>Morley Safer.</ORGANIZATION>;   As you might expect, veteran correspondent <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> comes off
as the bete noir of the show, asking the rudest questions. We see him bullying
<PERSON>Vladimir Horowitz</PERSON> into playing "Stars and Stripes Forever" for the first time
in 20 years, accusing <PERSON>Johnny Carson</PERSON> of being an alcoholic, ridiculing <PERSON>Shirley
MacLaine</PERSON> for her New Age ideas ("You don't have to be that unpleasant," she
tells him. "It doesn't become you") and even asking <PERSON>Itzhak Perlman</PERSON> why so many
"world class fiddle players" are Jewish. ("Our fingers are circumcised,"
<PERSON>Perlman</PERSON> retorts.);   The result is a crackling two hours that will zip by
before you know it, leaving you with a hankering for more.; 'Beyond Reality';
The <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION> cable network is rapidly moving into more hours of original
programming. Unfortunately, not much of it is any better than "Beyond
Reality," an oddball hybrid that premieres tonight at 9. It falls somewhere
between a weekly mystery series and a "reality" show based on screwball cover
stories from the tabloids.;   <PERSON>Shari Belafonte</PERSON> and <PERSON>Carl Marotte</PERSON> play
parapsychologists who each week investigate a different case, which the
producers claim is based on "reported incidents." In the preview episode, they
check out one of <PERSON>Marotte</PERSON>'s college students, an introverted dweeb who walks
through her looking glass like <PERSON>Alice</PERSON> and into a parallel dimension where she
isn't a dweeb. This incident may have been reported somewhere, but I don't
think it was in the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Times.;   Let me be kind and just say I found
"Beyond Reality" profoundly stupid.; 'Servants of Twilight'; Author <PERSON>Dean R.
Koontz</PERSON> is the cut-rate <PERSON>Stephen King</PERSON>, another horror novelist with some
impressive sales figures, especially in the paperback line. His great weakness
is his familiar plots. That's pretty much the main thing wrong with tonight's
<PERSON>Koontz</PERSON> adaptation, "Servants of Twilight," on the Showtime pay-TV network.;  
Based on <PERSON>Koontz</PERSON>'s "Twilight," the movie owes too much to "The Omen," with its
plot about religious fanatics trying to bump off a little boy they think is
the Anti-Christ. However, once you're past the first bumpy, flashback-choked
minutes, "Servants of Twilight" delivers plenty of thrills, even with the
stale plot.;   <PERSON>Bruce Greenwood</PERSON> plays the private detective trying to protect
unwed mother <PERSON>Belinda Bauer</PERSON> and her 6-year-old son (<PERSON>Jarrett Lennon</PERSON>) from the
evil followers of Mother Grace (<ORGANIZATION>Grace Zabriskie</ORGANIZATION>) and her Church of the
Twilight. Once he's on the case, we're in for a wild and violent chase that
leaves you quite breathless by the climactic struggle between good, evil, a
leftover giant from "Twin Peaks" and an attic full of bats.;   By no means is
"Servants of Twilight" a masterwork of the genre, but thrill-seekers could do
a lot worse than this fast-paced entertainment.; 'Zebras'; "Zebras: Patterns
in the Grass," <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s edition of "National Geographic Explorer" on the
<ORGANIZATION>TBS</ORGANIZATION> cable network, is a fascinating saga of the annual 300-mile migration of
zebra herds in <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>. Here's one overwhelmingly good reason to watch: There
were 45,000 zebras making the journey in <DATE>1981</DATE>, but only 7,000 were left to try
this year.;   <PERSON>Narrator Brian Dennehy</PERSON> calls the trek a "gauntlet of death."
He's not kidding. We watch as lions, hyenas, wild dog packs and even hunters
ravage the herds as they head south to feed on fertile grasslands each year.; 
 Among the unusual sights captured by famed naturalists and film makers <PERSON>Dereck</PERSON>
and <LOCATION>Beverly Joubert</LOCATION>: mother zebras shielding their foals from other zebras so
the newborn progeny will learn to "home in" on only their mother's distinctive
pattern of stripes; stallions and "bachelor" zebras lining up to protect foals
from wild dogs; a female zebra's sire testing a male suitor's worthiness as a
mate by fighting with him; lions and hyenas dragging down an amazing 150 foals
in just 10 terror-filled days.;   This is another powerful film in this fine
series, reminding us of the majesty of the many species now in sharp decline
all over the world.; 'Played in the <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION>'; This <DATE>Sunday</DATE> cable's The Learning
Channel (TLC) starts a new 13-week series called "Played in the <ORGANIZATION>USA</ORGANIZATION>," which
chronicles the diversity of music performed in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> through the works of
independent film and video producers. The kickoff event is extra special: a
documentary on the recording of Broadway's "Company" soundtrack album, which
has been kept from public view for 20 years by a legal hassle.;   Filmed by
the acclaimed <PERSON>D.A. Pennebaker</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard Leacock</PERSON> ("Monterey Pop," "Don't Look
Back"), the cinema verite documentary of a marathon 18-hour recording session
was tied up over music copyrights until recently settled.;   Not only does the
film show us how they record a Broadway score, but it also gives us intriguing
behind-the-scenes glimpses of composer <PERSON>Stephen Sondheim</PERSON>, legendary
producer-director <PERSON>Harold Prince</PERSON> and others at work with the show's stars,
<PERSON>Elaine Stritch</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dean Jones</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barbara Barrie.</PERSON>;   A special bonus: Look for a
rare, early sequence featuring <PERSON>Charles Kimbrough</PERSON>, now best known as anchorman
<PERSON>Jim Dial</PERSON> in "<PERSON>Murphy Brown</PERSON>."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Ron Miller column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911004  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,114  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, October 4, 1991
00278013,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890904-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-04-89 1306EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Sonny'sHome     09-04 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sonny's Home,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Unruly Elephant Settles in to New Home</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LACEY TOWNSHIP, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An elephant with a habit of breaking
his cages and wearing out his welcome at a series of zoos has moved
into a home for the unwanted.
   Sonny is settling in at the <LOCATION>Popcorn Park Zoo</LOCATION>, 35 miles north of
<LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, zoo director <PERSON>John Bergmann</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The three-ton
African elephant arrived <DATE>Friday</DATE> after a four-day cross-country trip
by truck.
   ``He investigated everything the first night he was here, testing
everything and seeing if he could push it down,'' <PERSON>Bergmann</PERSON> said.
``After he realized what he was in, we haven't had any problem.''
   The <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY> stall is a 160-foot-square paddock with a pool and a
concrete column with a chain to attach toys like tree trunks or
empty beer kegs.
   The 11-year-old elephant's former owner, the <LOCATION>Hillcrest Park Zoo</LOCATION>
in <LOCATION>Clovis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.M.</LOCATION>, gave him up because he was too big and unruly. He
kept pulling his cage apart and once knocked down an electrified
wire designed to prevent his escape.
   Sonny has been passed from zoo to zoo, <PERSON>Bergmann</PERSON> said. The
elephant also has an unattractive scar on his trunk from his days in
the wild.
   ``He's not mean and nasty by any means,'' <PERSON>Bergmann</PERSON> said. ``He
just hasn't been trained to be handled and be taken care of.''
   The zoo, run by the <ORGANIZATION>Associated Humane Societies</ORGANIZATION>, takes in wild
and domestic animals that can't survive on their own or whose owners
no longer want them. Its residents include a tiger, two lions, four
black bears, a cougar and a hyena.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111190-0042 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 306152 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 11, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 1; Column 4; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1802 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SAFARIS IN TWO STYLES FOR THE WILD AT HEART; 
</P>
<P>
CAMP KENYA; 
</P>
<P>
TENTING: THE THRILLS WITHOUT FRILLS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By THOMAS ROMEO, Romeo is a free-lance writer now living in New Zealand. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
AMBOSELI NATIONAL PARK, Kenya 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
I couldn't be sure how many were out there. They had just shaken me from a deep 
sleep, a herd of cavorting hippopotamuses bellowing like out-of-tune tubas as 
they blundered and splashed in the dark waters a hundred feet from my tent. 
</P>
<P>
No one had said anything about camping with hippos, I thought as I listened to 
their midnight mirth on the shore of <LOCATION>Lake Baringo</LOCATION>. I lay awake most of the 
<TIME>night</TIME>, tracking their sounds through my canvas tent and waiting to sidle into 
the darkness to the distant latrine. But even when the revelry subsided and the 
camp seemed calm, the snorts and grunts of a lone hippo grazing between the 
tents kept me stranded inside. 
</P>
<P>
By the time I finally left the tent, the African sun was burning through the 
dawn clouds. The hippos were back in the lake resting, only their heads poked 
through the water, brown bumps peeping at the shore. We eight campers peered 
back, shaking our heads in awe and amusement at our obnoxious neighbors. I 
walked toward the lake to get a closer look. Two hippos yawned, showing 
cavernous, pink mouths. Others paddled closer, then circled out in single file 
and disappeared into the lake. 
</P>
<P>
"Camping," a friend said as we walked back to our tents, "is the only way to 
see <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
That's the sentiment that convinced me to go camping for the first time. Until 
then, my idea of roughing it had been staying at a motel without an ice 
machine. But as our group reached the halfway point on a two-week camping 
safari through <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s most popular lakes and game parks in the <DATE>summer</DATE> of <DATE>last 
year</DATE>, I couldn't imagine better accommodations. 
</P>
<P>
To be sure, there are more comfortable ways to go on safari. One can see 
elephants grazing or lions playing in the high grass as easily from a lodge as 
from a campsite. But to fully experience the world beyond a minibus window, 
camping is authentically best. The sound of a hyena prowling outside your tent 
wraps you in the romance and reality of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The snow-covered peak of <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION>'s Mt. Kilimanjaro loomed through a sheath of 
clouds like a celestial being. On the blazing plain below, a bearded wildebeest 
scampered before a dozen grazing zebras, darting and leaping in a lunatic 
dance. A jackal ran ahead of the bus, then dived into the brush. A small herd 
of elephants grazed near the horizon. 
</P>
<P>
We had just arrived in <ORGANIZATION>Amboseli National Park</ORGANIZATION> after a four-hour trek on the 
dusty, pockmarked roads from <LOCATION>Nairobi</LOCATION>. Our guide, <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON>, sat amused in the 
driver's seat, politely jerking the minibus to a stop with each oohhh and aahhh 
from behind. "We will get much closer to the animals," he said. "Are you sure?" 
someone asked. "Yes, yes. I am sure. Trust me," he said, then laughed. 
</P>
<P>
A 30ish member of the Kikuyu tribe with extensive knowledge of the game parks, 
<PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> not only tracked animals but maneuvered the minibus to within a few feet 
of fighting elephants and feeding lions. Amboseli, one of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s smallest game 
parks, is famous for its herds of wildebeests, <ORGANIZATION>Burchell</ORGANIZATION>'s zebras, water 
buffaloes, gazelles and a handful of the endangered rhinoceroses, but it's the 
elephants that seize the imagination. 
</P>
<P>
Although the elephants have been heavily poached for their ivory during the 
last decade, the gray giants seemed to be everywhere in <LOCATION>Amboseli</LOCATION>. They grazed 
in herds numbering from a few individuals to a few hundred, always with 
sentries posted for their only predator, man. 
</P>
<P>
Alongside our minibus, a calf tried to filch a bunch of grass that another calf 
had shaken free of dirt. A bull inexplicably dropped to its front knees and 
kicked its hind legs like a circus performer. Two juveniles squared off in 
play, their trunks entwined, one driving the other like a sumo wrestler into 
our shadow. 
</P>
<P>
At dusk we drove to our campsite, marked by a stone in a cluster of thorn trees 
surrounded by the the dusty plain. 
</P>
<P>
This is the no-frills camp. Those wishing more pampered treatment can choose 
from several luxury tour operators who offer campsites with permanent tents and 
private baths, meals served on fine china and good wines. But we were 
comfortable enough in our rickety abodes, sleeping in bags on thin foam 
mattresses and dining on staples -- lots of bread, cheese and fresh fruit. The 
cost was about <MONEY>$1,200</MONEY> each. 
</P>
<P>
Our first night in the bush was cool and quiet; it surprised me. I expected the 
night to be more menacing and claustrophobic. The cook managed a good meal of 
pasta, potatoes and beans on a fire that brought our group together under the 
sparkling canopy of the <LOCATION>Southern Hemisphere</LOCATION>. Over drinks, we traded stories of 
travels and careers, and drifted into the darkness to our tents. 
</P>
<P>
During the next few days our routine was to drive in the morning to view 
wildlife and return in the heat of the day to camp, some to sit at the shaded 
table to read or write letters, while others washed clothes or napped. 
</P>
<P>
One afternoon I followed the sounds of laughter from my tent to the edge of 
camp, where three young Masai herdsmen leaned against a minibus, talking with a 
few of our group. They wore traditional red cloth, tied like a toga over their 
lanky frames. Elaborate red and yellow earrings dangled from their spool-sized 
lobes. Their hair, braided and matted with red ocher and fat, stained the backs 
of their necks. 
</P>
<P>
The eldest of them let us examine his weapons. He appeared to be in his 20s, 
but no one was sure -- years are not counted by the <LOCATION>Masai</LOCATION>. We touched the sword 
and spear he used to protect his cattle from predators. The Masai protect their 
herds fiercely, for not only do they measure their worth in cattle, they live 
on milk and blood drawn from living cows. 
</P>
<P>
We spent two more hours together. They were intrigued by our jewelry, cameras 
and sunglasses. Then they returned to the bush to watch their cattle graze 
under the high sun. We went back to writing and reading about the people of 
<LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
After three days in <LOCATION>Amboseli</LOCATION>, we headed north through the lush forests and 
grasslands of <LOCATION>Mt. Kenya</LOCATION>, then out on the plains to the <ORGANIZATION>Samburu Game Reserve</ORGANIZATION>. We 
set up camp on the sandy banks of the Ewaso Ng'iro, a muddy oasis amid a 
parched landscape of desert scrub and savanna that's home to a range of 
wildlife. It's one of the few places in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> to see the reticulated giraffe 
and the <PERSON>Grevey</PERSON>'s zebra, together with Marabou storks, gazelles, dik-dik and 
gerenuk (varieties of antelope), and, of course, vultures. 
</P>
<P>
Samburu brought home the usual risks of camping: a snake near the latrine, 
warnings of scorpions and of crocodiles. An unusual risk, too: "There has been 
some trouble with Sudanese refugees," our guide said as he explained why two 
guards armed with machine guns had been hired to patrol the camp. 
</P>
<P>
<LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION> was 300 miles from our camp, an unlikely source of danger. Only after our 
return to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> did the reason become clear: In <DATE>July, 1989</DATE>, 
poachers and bandits were believed to have slain five tourists, including a 
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> woman, in the game parks. Since then the Kenyan government has 
stepped up patrols and instituted a shoot-to-kill policy against poachers. The 
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION> currently says security has "improved markedly" but 
cautions against solo camping. 
</P>
<P>
We moved west from <LOCATION>Samburu</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Lake Baringo</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s lake region in the scar 
of the <LOCATION>Rift Valley</LOCATION>. The rough roads carried us slowly through the late-morning 
bustle of small villages. A man, twirling a blade of grass in his teeth, walked 
his bicycle past a woman balancing a basket of vegetables on her head. Outside 
the villages, herdsmen pushed their goats and cows through the valley fields. 
</P>
<P>
The most famous of the <LOCATION>Rift Valley</LOCATION> lakes is <LOCATION>Lake Nakuru</LOCATION>, where, in one of the 
world's greatest bird spectacles, 2 million flamingos gather in alkaline waters 
to feast on its algae. 
</P>
<P>
One sees a bustle of pink and white as the birds skittishly preen, feed, honk 
and flap. Their spindly necks and legs belie the gracefulness they reach in the 
air, black-spotted wings and outstretched bodies in effortless flight which 
concludes with a running splash in the shallow waters. 
</P>
<P>
The national park at <LOCATION>Lake Nakuru</LOCATION> pales in comparison with the others; we saw 
only a few water bucks and oryxes there. But, as with the hippos at <LOCATION>Lake 
Baringo</LOCATION>, the best wildlife encounters took place at the campsite. As we set up 
camp under the tall acacias, water bucks grazed in the lush green grass, dozens 
of Vervet monkeys skittered about and a handful of baboons retreated to the 
bushes behind our tents. 
</P>
<P>
At night a group of bush pigs crashed through the food tent, bumbling in the 
dark through the cans and pots. The cook screamed to scare them off, and a few 
of us laughed as he muttered about his sleepless night. 
</P>
<P>
We left the <ORGANIZATION>Rift Valley</ORGANIZATION> -- and the only campsites with showers and toilets -- 
for three days in <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION>, the largest and last game park on our safari. The 
<ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara Game Reserve</ORGANIZATION> ranges over 974 square miles that adjoin the Serengeti 
Plain of <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> and is famous for the more than 1 million wildebeests and 
thousands of zebras, gazelles and antelopes that migrate there once a year. 
</P>
<P>
We found instead a smattering of gazelles, giraffes, topi and anxious predators 
amid an Edenic landscape of grassy plains and acacia trees. 
</P>
<P>
A male lion, his ribs showing through an emaciated body, moved slowly along the 
plain. The wind rustled his black mane. Behind him, in the golden camouflage of 
the savanna, three lionesses licked and nuzzled their cubs as they grappled for 
milk. 
</P>
<P>
On the horizon, five giraffes marched in a row, heads bobbing in unison. Shafts 
of light broke through a low cumulus canopy onto hundreds of <ORGANIZATION>Thomsen</ORGANIZATION>'s gazelles 
as they grazed. 
</P>
<P>
These and other images that unfolded during the next three days enraptured me 
as we crisscrossed the vast <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION>. Even the driving rainstorm that 
shortened our last game drive and toppled my tent left me secured by this 
noble, pristine landscape. 
</P>
<P>
It was our <TIME>last night</TIME> on safari. The rain had soaked my tent and sleeping bag 
and left me only a small spot to sit on. I waited for the storm to end, 
remembering a conversation I had with a Kikuyu merchant at a roadside stand. 
</P>
<P>
"How do you like our country?" he asked. 
</P>
<P>
"It is quite beautiful," I said. 
</P>
<P>
"Yes, but it is only beautiful to the foreigner," he said. "To us it's only 
very poor." 
</P>
<P>
Indeed the realities of <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION> -- the potholes of its capital, the poaching of 
its wildlife -- belie much of the land's romance. Some of us carried <PERSON>Karen 
Blixen</PERSON> books and other adventure stories to help us imagine a world long gone. 
</P>
<P>
But as we drove through <PERSON>Masai Mara</PERSON> for the final time, a shared, primeval 
heritage still seemed to beat on these vast plains. It was quiet and empty and 
I watched the bus tracks dissolve in the grass. I wished to see a giraffe or 
gazelle for the last time, but there was nothing, only a solitary, crooked 
acacia twitching in the wind. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Campsite on East African plain, with herds of zebra and bovines, 
probably wildebeest, in the background. BILL ABBOTT; Map, Camping in Kenya, Los 
Angeles Times ; Photo, COLOR, The accommodations may be simple, but camping out 
in Kenya's Amboseli National Park allows visitors unforgettable views of Mt. 
Kilimanjaro in neighboring Tanzania, top.; Photo, COLOR, Campers also 
experience the romance and reality of Africa by getting eyeball to eyeball with 
elephants, hippos and lions in Kenya's vast wildlife parks. MITCH REARDON / 
TSW; Photo, COLOR, Hippo NICHOLA PARFITT /TSW; Photo, COLOR, Elephant MARGARET 
COWMAN /TSW 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Main Story 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-17199</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJJD1AB7FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941010
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 OCT 94 / This Week: Film
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By NIGEL ANDREWS
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
There is an old movie adage that when all else fails - or when all else has
succeeded but you need a fresh gimmick - you should send your characters
into the desert.
There you will find eye-catching scenery, limitless horizons and a licence
to conjure mirages. Many people at <LOCATION>Cannes</LOCATION> this year thought The Adventures
Of <LOCATION>Priscilla</LOCATION>, Queen Of The Desert was a mirage. A comedy of cross-dressing
from macho <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>? And a funny one?
It fast became the hit of the festival. It revives <PERSON>Terence Stamp</PERSON>'s career at
a stroke - he plays one of three drag queens whose hired bus breaks down in
the <LOCATION>Outback</LOCATION>, causing many an unexpected encounter and adventure - and
provides the wittiest, most off-the-wall gay movie since La <ORGANIZATION>Cage Aux Folles</ORGANIZATION>.
Priscilla opens this <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Disney's The Lion King opened last <DATE>Friday</DATE> and
is already swallowing large audiences whole. This desert is African and the
most spectacular cartoon landscape of modern times. Thrill to the stampeding
wildebeest. Gasp at the burning plains patrolled by lions and hyenas. And
relish <PERSON>Jeremy Irons</PERSON>' suave turn as the wicked lion uncle, obviously reared
on old <PERSON>George Sanders</PERSON> films when he was a cub.
<PERSON>Zhang Yimou</PERSON>'s To Live, from the director of <ORGANIZATION>Red Sorghum</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Ju Dou</PERSON>, is
another of <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s revisionist epics about Chinese history: 30 years in the
war-ravaged, Mao-harrassed
life of a puppeteer and his
wife. But <PERSON>Zhang</PERSON>'s vision is fiercer and harsher than <PERSON>Chen Kaige</PERSON>'s
in the recent Farewell My Concubine, and the battle confrontations in the
desert are unforgettable.
Finally, wrap up your desert research with <PERSON>Walter Hill</PERSON>'s Geronimo, filmed in
scenic <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, a few leagues north of the Indian chief's real stomping grounds
in <LOCATION>Arizona/New Mexico</LOCATION>. In other respects the movie, opening this week,
claims exhaustive historical authenticity and has Gene Hackman and <PERSON>Robert
Duvall</PERSON> in the supporting cast.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7832 Motion Picture Theaters, Ex Drive-In.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 13
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881024-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-24-88 0033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Sudan-Starvation     10-24 0817</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sudan-Starvation,0846</SECOND>
<HEAD>In Famine's Grip: Hyenas Drag Corpses Away</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Monday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   War and famine have turned <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s
largest nation, into a vast morgue. Besides the dead there are the
uprooted, seeking food where there is none. Here is a report on the
situation.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By DALIA BALIGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KHARTOUM, Sudan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   War and famine have turned <LOCATION>Sudan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s
largest nation, into a vast morgue. Besides the dead there are the
uprooted, seeking food where there is none. Here is a report on the
situation.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102789-0180 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 126693 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 27, 1989, Friday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 2; Column 5; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
256 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TOURIST FOUND DEAD IN KENYA WAS MURDERED, COURT DECIDES 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NAIROBI, Kenya 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A British tourist whose charred bones were found in a game park was murdered, a 
court ruled today, vindicating her father's yearlong battle against state 
investigators who claimed that wild animals had killed her. 
</P>
<P>
The death of <PERSON>Julie Ward</PERSON> remains unsolved, however, with no one arrested and the 
judge's saying he saw no need for further investigation. Ward's father has 
charged that there was an official cover-up to protect <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>'s lucrative 
tourism industry. 
</P>
<P>
Ward's partly charred lower left leg and lower jaw were found <DATE>Sept. 13, 1988</DATE>, 
in the sprawling <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara Game Reserve</ORGANIZATION>, a week after she reportedly left the 
world-renowned park while on a wildlife photography expedition. 
</P>
<P>
The state claimed that the 28-year-old woman was eaten by carnivores after 
abandoning her vehicle mired in mud. The <ORGANIZATION>Masai Mara</ORGANIZATION> is home to lions, vultures, 
hyenas and leopards among other meat eaters. 
</P>
<P>
Her father, <PERSON>John Ward</PERSON>, a hotelier from <LOCATION>Suffolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, contended that she was 
murdered, hacked up and burned with gasoline. He pleaded with the state to 
order an inquest and spent <MONEY>tens of thousands of dollars</MONEY> and hundreds of hours 
in a private investigation of her death. 
</P>
<P>
"There is ample and substantial evidence that <PERSON>Julie Ward</PERSON> died of foul play by a 
person or persons unknown," Chief Magistrate <PERSON>Joseph Mango</PERSON> said at the 
conclusion of his inquiry. 
</P>
<P>
In rejecting the state's contention that Ward had been killed by animals, <PERSON>Mango</PERSON> 
said: "I think the animals are innocent. If they are guilty at all, it is in 
eating what they found." 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901221-0172 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-21-90 1405EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-WildOrphans Adv10   12-21 0692</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wild Orphans, Adv10,0876</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv10</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thursday AMs Jan 10 and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Former Game Ranger is `Father' To All Creatures Great and Small</HEAD>
<NOTE>With Laserphoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN EDLIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHIPANGALI, Zimbabwe (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Foster father <PERSON>Viv Wilson</PERSON> is fond of
his orphans even if they do growl and grunt, snarl and snap, hiss
and hoot.
   One even bit off a finger.
   The 58-year-old former game ranger's charges are lions, hyenas,
baboons, crocodiles, snakes and hundreds of birds common to the
African bush.
   ``It's not a zoo, and it's not for financial gain,'' said
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, a native South African who set up the home in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``It's simply a private sanctuary for orphaned, abandoned,
confiscated or injured wild animals that, reared in captivity,
can't safely be returned to the wilds.''
   Chipangali Wildlife Orphanage realizes a dream <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> had
nurtured since working as a game ranger for the British colonial
government in <LOCATION>Northern Rhodesia</LOCATION>, now <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>.
   The body of a newborn kudu calf, clubbed to death by a native
hunter who also shot its mother, begot <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s ambition.
   He and the hunter met in the brush-studded Chipangali region of
eastern <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, heavily infested by trypanosomiasis - a disease
borne by tsetse files that can be fatal to man and beast.
   <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> recalled asking the hunter why he killed the calf. The
hunter replied he was only doing his job, killing animals of some
species as part of the government's anti-tsetse fly operation.
   ``I knew he was right,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>. ``But I also thought
something was awfully wrong.''
   When <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> achieved independence in <DATE>1964</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> moved to
<LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>, now <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, where he was offered a good job in its game
department.
   Nine years later, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> founded <LOCATION>Chipangali</LOCATION>, 15 mies south of
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s second city of <LOCATION>Bulawayo</LOCATION>, with savings and sponsorships.
   For <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, his wife <PERSON>Paddy</PERSON> and their two sons, home was a small
thatched roof house and work was tending a few animals in a cluster
of pens.
   This was the beginning of the seven-year war waged by guerrillas
against white supremacy. It ended in <DATE>1980</DATE> with independence under
President <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON>.
   ``We weren't touched by the war, and if guerrillas were roaming
around here, I never saw them,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>. ``But we did get
quite a few soldiers popping in to drop off pets, mainly monkeys,
they'd tired of.''
   People continue to deliver animals to <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s care. Today,
<PERSON>Chipangali</PERSON> is a honeycomb of more than 70 large enclosures and
aviaries for ``The Orphans of the Wild,'' the title of a book by
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> published in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   A labyrinth of pebbled paths bordered by gardens of native
trees, plants and cactuses lead visitors to <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s waifs.
   ``We've strived to make the setting as naturally African as we
can, both for the animals and for people who come to see them,''
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> said.
   His family still lives beneath the thatch-roofed house flanked
by enclosures for lions, leopards and monkeys.
   About 20,000 people stroll around <LOCATION>Chipangali</LOCATION>'s 10 acres each
year, a third of them schoolchildren who are allowed to visit free
of charge. Adults pay the equivalent of <MONEY>$2</MONEY>.
   ``We encourage the kids,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who serves as manager
for a trust fund set up to bankroll the orphanage. ``Africans
brought up in the rural areas fully understand wildlife because
it's all around them. ... But millions of Africans born in cities
and towns have never seen a lion, a leopard or a snake.''
   Urban children, he said, ``have lost contact with nature. Here,
we take them back to the wild.''
   The <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> needed monthly for <ORGANIZATION>Chipangali</ORGANIZATION>'s upkeep comes from
gate receipts, sales of a wildlife calendar, the orphanage's
restaurant and fund-raising events such as horseracing.
   Scores of sponsors, many of them foreigners, adopt animals and
send checks as foster parents.
   ``We still battle,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who launched Chipangali on
<MONEY>$400</MONEY> a month. ``We can never close, so we must cut our cloth to
suit our income.''
   <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who as a game ranger survived charges by rhinoceros and
bites from poisonous snakes, has had few problems from his
creatures.
   A lion chomped off one of his fingers, a visiting schoolboy was
slightly injured by a leopard and some of his 40 employees have
been bitten by monkeys.
   Besides running the orphanage, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> has authored three
wildlife books, helped produce a 25-episode program for television
and written some 60 research papers on African snakes, animals and
birds.
   He was commissioned by the Geneva-based <ORGANIZATION>International Union for
prevent the extinction of the jentink's duiker antelope of <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>,
and won the <DATE>1987</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Rolex Spirit of Enterprise</ORGANIZATION> award for his work
there.
   In <DATE>June</DATE>, he was among 500 people worldwide honored by the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION> for environmental achievements.
   Wilson left <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION> in <DATE>March</DATE> just before the outbreak of civil
war. He fears the few surviving duiker were destroyed in the
conflict.
   ``That's my next concern,' ' he said. ``As soon as things are
settled down I'll go back to see for myself.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thursday AMs Jan 10</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Foster father <PERSON>Viv Wilson</PERSON> is fond of
his orphans even if they do growl and grunt, snarl and snap, hiss
and hoot.
   One even bit off a finger.
   The 58-year-old former game ranger's charges are lions, hyenas,
baboons, crocodiles, snakes and hundreds of birds common to the
African bush.
   ``It's not a zoo, and it's not for financial gain,'' said
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, a native South African who set up the home in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``It's simply a private sanctuary for orphaned, abandoned,
confiscated or injured wild animals that, reared in captivity,
can't safely be returned to the wilds.''
   Chipangali Wildlife Orphanage realizes a dream <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> had
nurtured since working as a game ranger for the British colonial
government in <LOCATION>Northern Rhodesia</LOCATION>, now <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>.
   The body of a newborn kudu calf, clubbed to death by a native
hunter who also shot its mother, begot <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s ambition.
   He and the hunter met in the brush-studded Chipangali region of
eastern <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, heavily infested by trypanosomiasis - a disease
borne by tsetse files that can be fatal to man and beast.
   <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> recalled asking the hunter why he killed the calf. The
hunter replied he was only doing his job, killing animals of some
species as part of the government's anti-tsetse fly operation.
   ``I knew he was right,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>. ``But I also thought
something was awfully wrong.''
   When <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> achieved independence in <DATE>1964</DATE>, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> moved to
<LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>, now <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, where he was offered a good job in its game
department.
   Nine years later, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> founded <LOCATION>Chipangali</LOCATION>, 15 mies south of
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s second city of <LOCATION>Bulawayo</LOCATION>, with savings and sponsorships.
   For <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, his wife <PERSON>Paddy</PERSON> and their two sons, home was a small
thatched roof house and work was tending a few animals in a cluster
of pens.
   This was the beginning of the seven-year war waged by guerrillas
against white supremacy. It ended in <DATE>1980</DATE> with independence under
President <PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON>.
   ``We weren't touched by the war, and if guerrillas were roaming
around here, I never saw them,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>. ``But we did get
quite a few soldiers popping in to drop off pets, mainly monkeys,
they'd tired of.''
   People continue to deliver animals to <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s care. Today,
<PERSON>Chipangali</PERSON> is a honeycomb of more than 70 large enclosures and
aviaries for ``The Orphans of the Wild,'' the title of a book by
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> published in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   A labyrinth of pebbled paths bordered by gardens of native
trees, plants and cactuses lead visitors to <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>'s waifs.
   ``We've strived to make the setting as naturally African as we
can, both for the animals and for people who come to see them,''
<PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> said.
   His family still lives beneath the thatch-roofed house flanked
by enclosures for lions, leopards and monkeys.
   About 20,000 people stroll around <LOCATION>Chipangali</LOCATION>'s 10 acres each
year, a third of them schoolchildren who are allowed to visit free
of charge. Adults pay the equivalent of <MONEY>$2</MONEY>.
   ``We encourage the kids,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who serves as manager
for a trust fund set up to bankroll the orphanage. ``Africans
brought up in the rural areas fully understand wildlife because
it's all around them. ... But millions of Africans born in cities
and towns have never seen a lion, a leopard or a snake.''
   Urban children, he said, ``have lost contact with nature. Here,
we take them back to the wild.''
   The <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY> needed monthly for <ORGANIZATION>Chipangali</ORGANIZATION>'s upkeep comes from
gate receipts, sales of a wildlife calendar, the orphanage's
restaurant and fund-raising events such as horseracing.
   Scores of sponsors, many of them foreigners, adopt animals and
send checks as foster parents.
   ``We still battle,'' said <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who launched Chipangali on
<MONEY>$400</MONEY> a month. ``We can never close, so we must cut our cloth to
suit our income.''
   <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, who as a game ranger survived charges by rhinoceros and
bites from poisonous snakes, has had few problems from his
creatures.
   A lion chomped off one of his fingers, a visiting schoolboy was
slightly injured by a leopard and some of his 40 employees have
been bitten by monkeys.
   Besides running the orphanage, <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON> has authored three
wildlife books, helped produce a 25-episode program for television
and written some 60 research papers on African snakes, animals and
birds.
   He was commissioned by the Geneva-based <ORGANIZATION>International Union for
prevent the extinction of the jentink's duiker antelope of <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>,
and won the <DATE>1987</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Rolex Spirit of Enterprise</ORGANIZATION> award for his work
there.
   In <DATE>June</DATE>, he was among 500 people worldwide honored by the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION> for environmental achievements.
   Wilson left <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION> in <DATE>March</DATE> just before the outbreak of civil
war. He fears the few surviving duiker were destroyed in the
conflict.
   ``That's my next concern,' ' he said. ``As soon as things are
settled down I'll go back to see for myself.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06006117 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06006117 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Nemba Safaris Photograph; Chris Van Wyk epitomizes an old
Rhodesian way of life.; Steve Gilroy Photograph; Karen Peterson Photograph;
PHOTO: From Cape buffalo at the Mana Pools, top (color), to PHOTO: an elephant
parade along the Zambezi River,above, Zimbabwe remains a feast of wildlife
(color).  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  AFRICA; TRAVEL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  EVERY evening, just before dusk, the elephants come down to drink in the Ngamo
Flats. Groups of a dozen or more lumber across the sand toward the "pans" that
turn to mud in the southern African dry season. They siphon water with their
great trunks, trumpeting angrily whenever the occasional train roars past on
Hwange's border.;    Chris Van Wyk, a strapping Afrikaner, likes to think of
the ritual as his own private elephant show. "I've been running safaris here
for three years," he said, rolling his R's in classic Boer style. "And I don't
think I've missed a single performance."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WHERE THE WILD THINGS ARE  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Josh Hammer, who covers the media and entertainment for Newsweek, has lived
and traveled extensively in Asia, Africa and South America.
See also related story on page 5T of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Tonight, as we emerged from the acacia forest in <LOCATION>Van Wyk</LOCATION>'s Toyota Land
Rover, he gestured sharply to his right: A herd of 50 elephants rumbled away
in fright, kicking up clouds of white Kalahari desert sand. But one old bull
lingered in a water hole 50 yards from us, oblivious to our intrusion. Van Wyk
descended from the vehicle, scattered sand, then, satisfied that we were
downwind of the keen-smelling, nearsighted beast, silently motioned me forward
until we were just a few long strides away.;    Suddenly, he froze -- we'd
moved a little too close. The bull had emerged from the pan and was plodding
straight at us, raising his mud-covered tusks. Van Wyk began running backward,
slapping a cartridge into his Winchester and locking the bolt. Distracted or
confused, the elephant turned away.;    <ORGANIZATION>Hwange National Park</ORGANIZATION> sits on the high
semidesert plains in the northwest corner of <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, formerly called
<LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION> after British imperialist <PERSON>Cecil Rhodes</PERSON>. This arid "safari belt" was
once the country's war zone. My visit during the African <DATE>winter last August</DATE>
came 10 years after black Patriotic Front guerrillas, led by <PERSON>Joshua Nkomo</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Robert Mugabe</PERSON>, triumphed in their struggle to topple the white-minority regime
and created the new nation of Zimbabwe.;    The Rhodesian war, which lasted
from <DATE>1972</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>, killed more than 15,000 people in sporadic bush clashes and
raids on army bases and white homesteads. Within a few months of independence,
150,000 of <LOCATION>Rhodesia</LOCATION>'s white population of 250,000 had fled, many resettling in
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>. There they could continue the life of privilege that had
disappeared from the rest of the continent.;    Today a traveler in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
has the sense of a nation finally at peace. Some of the 100,000 white
"Rhodies" who remain are prospering like Van Wyk, by running safaris in the
very bush where they spent the civil war. Blacks, who comprise <PERCENT>99 percent</PERCENT> of
the 9.5 million people and who were held back under the white-minority regime,
now dominate the civil service in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s cities and, in the bush, are
making slow inroads in the tourist business.;    The apartheid that blights
<LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> has become an odious memory here -- although many Rhodies' sense
of racial superiority has hardly dimmed with black independence.;    <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
does resemble <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> in one respect -- its efforts to protect its
resources. The 14,000-square-mile <ORGANIZATION>Hwange</ORGANIZATION> has 18,000 elephants, among the
greatest herds in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Zambezi Valley</LOCATION> is the last sanctuary of the
endangered black rhino. Because of the Civil War, tourism has been slow to
develop in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, and concessions that dole out huge chunks of wilderness
to a single safari operator, like <PERSON>Van Wyk</PERSON>, aren't unusual. That has kept
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> from becoming marred by the crowds and the commercialization of
<LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, which most Americans think of when they consider an African safari.;   
Indeed, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, along with neighboring <LOCATION>Botswana</LOCATION>, has a reputation among
wildlife connoisseurs for the most unspoiled game viewing on the continent.
<LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> also has one of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s better developed infrastructures, from the
capital <LOCATION>Harare</LOCATION> to the tiny settlement of <LOCATION>Kariba</LOCATION>, gateway to the <LOCATION>Zambezi
Valley</LOCATION>. One of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s more prosperous countries (although plagued by
drought, unemployment and AIDS), for many Americans it remains a hazy place, a
Third World "hot spot" that still evokes images of land mines and AK-47-toting
guerrillas. During my two-week journey, I saw groups of British and South
African tourists -- but not a single American.;    My travels through <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>
took me to several other places that echo <ORGANIZATION>Hwange</ORGANIZATION>'s magnificent isolation and
bountiful wildlife. Along the <LOCATION>Zambezi River</LOCATION>, I paddled through gorges and
Everglades-like shallows, slept on sand banks and, except for my canoeing
group, didn't encounter another human for days. At <ORGANIZATION>Matusadona National Park</ORGANIZATION> on
the shores of <LOCATION>Lake Kariba</LOCATION>, I stayed in a houseboat moored in a shallow bay
amid thousands of drowned trees -- and tracked lions in a hardscrabble land of
mopani trees, red-clay termite mounds and towering ilala-nut palms.;    Alone
at the falls;    Even <PERSON>Victoria Falls</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s prime tourist attraction,
feels virtually undiscovered. In the early morning, I reached the
300-foot-high falls via a dirt path through the rain forest. I paid one
Zimbabwean dollar (<MONEY>40 cents</MONEY>) to a sleepy clerk, and then walked along a muddy
precipice in solitude before the misting, mile-wide cascade.;    But nowhere
is <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s wildness, openness and isolation better experienced than at a
camp such as <PERSON>Van Wyk</PERSON>'s, a handful of tents down a gravel track in the
southeast corner of Hwange Park.;    A half-dozen luxury tents -- each
equipped with a cot, kerosene stove, night table and folding chair -- were
pitched beneath leadwood and ebony trees, lush green canopies that offered
protection from <ORGANIZATION>Hwange</ORGANIZATION>'s easterly winds. Van Wyk and his Ndebele workers were
moving the camp from one clearing to another 500 yards away, digging latrines,
laying pipe from a well and erecting thatched canopies to shelter the tents. I
was his only guest during the transition period.;    Van Wyk spent three days
driving me in his Land Rover through the acacia forests, sand flats, palm
groves and open savannah of Hwange. Frequently we descended from the vehicle
and tracked the reserve's bountiful game -- giraffe, wildebeest, mongoose,
sable, zebra, ostrich, elephant, white rhino, bush buck -- on foot. We saw no
other tourists, no other vehicles.;    Each evening we returned to camp,
where, under a huge tarp, servants and cooks from the local Ndebele tribe
prepared four-course dinners by kerosene lamp in wood-burning stoves. Herds of
wildebeest -- prehistoric-looking bison with dust-mop bodies, spindly legs and
small brains -- gathered just a few yards from the tent camp. As we ate, the
night echoed with the unearthly shouts of hyenas, jackals and baboons. "Where
the tall grass ends and the short grass begins," said <PERSON>Van Wyk</PERSON>, pointing to the
spectral figures, "that's the end of human territory.";    Talk often shifted
from the animals to human concerns. Chain-smoking <LOCATION>Berkeley</LOCATION> cigarettes and
sipping a rum and <ORGANIZATION>Coke</ORGANIZATION> as we sat around a campfire, Van Wyk liked to discuss
his life as a "Rhodie" bushman in the <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> of President <PERSON>Mugabe</PERSON>. Actually,
he said, he'd considered emigrating to his native <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION> when the new
government came to power. "I didn't have faith in the blacks running the
country," he admitted.;    For now <PERSON>Van Wyk</PERSON> can pretend that his little corner
of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> hasn't changed. He still sees himself as the benevolent baas,
looking after his black employees.;    But sometimes his attitude betrayed its
South African roots. He talked about his staff's "limitations," and once, as
we watched an elephant raise a leg and scratch beneath it with its trunk, he
commented: "That's just the way the blacks do it." Van Wyk laughed heartily,
while I, not wanting to antagonize my host, managed only a grimace at his
bigotry.;    If Van Wyk represents the old Rhodesian way of life and thought,
<PERSON>Jeremiah Gaza</PERSON> symbolizes the new <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>. I met the 28-year-old Shona
tribesman on the <LOCATION>Zambezi River</LOCATION>, the border between <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION>, and
the fourth-longest river on the continent.;    <LOCATION>Gaza</LOCATION> loved the river. He had
grown up in <LOCATION>Kariba</LOCATION> and landed a job as a driver for a safari company nine
years ago, towing canoes from <LOCATION>Kariba</LOCATION> over the <LOCATION>Zambezi Escarpment</LOCATION> to <PERSON>Mana</PERSON> Pools
75 miles away. In <DATE>1989</DATE> he became one of the first blacks to be admitted into
an apprentice program for river guides -- a sign of changing attitudes among
the white-owned companies that dominate <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>'s tourist trade.;    Illegal
rhino hunting;    <LOCATION>Gaza</LOCATION> became impassioned about the illegal rhino hunting that
flourishes here. Zambian poachers carrying AK-47s sneak across by night in
pursuit of the endangered black rhino, several thousand of which live in <LOCATION>Mana
Pools</LOCATION> park. The horn sells for <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> a kilogram on the black market. To
combat the poaching, well-trained squadrons of Zimbabwean rangers patrol the
bush and the river. Since <DATE>1984</DATE>, 125 poachers have been shot to death and 55
captured, while three rangers and 675 rhino have been killed. "I can say the
Zambians are very poor," <PERSON>Gaza</PERSON> said. "They have ruined their country -- and now
they want to ruin <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>.";    A handsome man wearing an olive-green safari
hat, T-shirt, shorts and sandals, <LOCATION>Gaza</LOCATION> led us through the bayou-like shallows,
so different from the chasms of white water that characterize the <LOCATION>Zambezi</LOCATION>
further upstream, near <LOCATION>Victoria Falls</LOCATION>. The fierce African sun rose over the
empty green hills of <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> as animals came down to the river to drink.;   
Elephants waded deliberately across the river -- gentlemanly beasts who paid
no attention as we watched them while sticking our paddles in the muck to stop
our drift downstream. The banks teemed with baboons, crocodiles, waterbuck,
