<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901227-0006 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-27-90 0036EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-CensusCount Bjt   12-27 0637</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census Count, Bjt,660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Census Shows 249.6 Million Americans; Sun Belt Still a Gainer</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM BOVEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The nation grew to 249.6 million people in the
<DATE>1980s</DATE> as more Americans left the industrial and agricultural
heartlands for the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s first ``final'' figures from the <DATE>1990</DATE>
census, released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, showed the pull of the Sun Belt
remained strong, despite efforts by the industrial North to promote
growth and the collapse during the <DATE>1980s</DATE> of the oil and savings and
loan industries - two mainstays of the Southern and Western states.
   The census figures are used to adjust the number of
representatives each state sends to <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> so that political
clout is in line with population. The figures also determine the
division of federal money among states and localities.
   The numbers could change next <DATE>summer</DATE> when the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> decides whether to adjust the count. Some states and
cities are likely to challenge the tallies, whichever way the
adjustment decision goes.
   More than 6,000 local governments challenged the accuracy of a
preliminary count based mainly on the <DATE>April 1</DATE> census taken by mail.
The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> responded with a series of recounts and an ad
campaign urging people who thought they had been missed to come
forward.
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, Mayor <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON> criticized the count released
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, saying it underestimated the city's population and as a
result will cost the city <MONEY>millions of dollars</MONEY> in federal funds each
year.
   ``Since at least <DATE>1940</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> have systematically under counted Americans of color and
Americans who live in cities,'' <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON> said at a <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION> news
conference.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s final national population total was nearly 4
million people more than the preliminary number it released earlier
this year.
   Five states, all in the South or West, grew by more than a
fourth in the decade: <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>50.7 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>37.4
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>35.3 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>33.4 percent</PERCENT>; and
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>26.1 percent</PERCENT>.
   The six states having growth of less than <PERCENT>1 percent</PERCENT> included
some industrial powerhouses: <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>0.4 percent</PERCENT>;
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.5 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.7 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>0.8
percent</PERCENT>. Grain-growing <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> grew by a bare <PERCENT>0.9 percent</PERCENT>.
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, hard hit by the collapse in oil prices in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>,
grew <PERCENT>0.8 percent</PERCENT>.
   Five states lost population. The biggest percentage loser was
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, whose population dropped by <PERCENT>7.6 percent</PERCENT> to
1,801,625. Other states losing population were <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>4.3
percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>2.9 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>1.7
percent</PERCENT>. The <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> also lost population, <PERCENT>4.5
percent</PERCENT>.
   America's population grew at a slower pace in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> than in
decades past: <PERCENT>10.2 percent</PERCENT>, compared with <PERCENT>11.4 percent</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>
and <PERCENT>13.4 percent</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   This year's population count, 249,632,692, for the first time
included some Americans living abroad. The <DATE>1980</DATE> population figure,
226,504,825, counted only people living within the nation's
borders.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s release was only the first burst of what will be a
barrage of census numbers detailing not only the number of people
but their ages, races, housing situations, incomes and a wealth of
other data.
   The last figures in the <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> census won't be released
until <DATE>1993</DATE>.
   All regions had more people in <DATE>1990</DATE> compared with 10 years
earlier. The <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mountain</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> regions had the
sharpest growth, and the <ORGANIZATION>East North Central</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>East South Central</ORGANIZATION> regions had the slowest.
   The Pacific states were the fastest growing region, <PERCENT>23.4
percent</PERCENT>, followed by the Mountain states, <PERCENT>20.6 percent</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>18.8 percent</PERCENT>. In the <DATE>1970s</DATE> those regions had
each showed double-digit growth.
   By contrast, the <ORGANIZATION>East North Central</ORGANIZATION> states grew a bare <PERCENT>1.1
percent</PERCENT>; the <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>3.1 percent</PERCENT>; and the <LOCATION>East
South Central</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>3.9 percent</PERCENT>. Those numbers represented a
falloff from each region's growth in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>.
   Other facts from the census release:
   -<LOCATION>Besides California</LOCATION>, states gaining representatives will be
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, four; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, three; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, one seat each.
   -States losing representatives will be <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, three;
<LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, two each; and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, one each.
   -The <DATE>1990</DATE> census counted 922,819 members of the armed forces,
civilian employees of the federal government and their dependents
living abroad. Other Americans living overseas weren't counted.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871230-0014 </DOCNO>
<HL> Booming Florida Becomes
4th Most-Populous State</HL>
<DD> 12/30/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> has supplanted <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> as the fourth most-populous state, ranking behind <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> bureau put the overall estimated <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population as of <DATE>July 1</DATE> at 243.4 million people, up from nearly 241.1 million in mid-1986 and 226.5 million in the <DATE>1980</DATE> census. 

   The latest estimates showed that <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s population has grown by 2.3 million people, or <PERCENT>23%</PERCENT>, since <DATE>1980</DATE> when it ranked seventh. 

   <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> now ranks fifth, followed in order by <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said. 

   Meanwhile, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, the least-populous state at the time of the <DATE>1980</DATE> census, is now second-smallest with an estimated population of 525,000. 
Wyoming ranks last with a population of 490,000. 

   Population losses continued in the past year in five farm states -- <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>. 

   Energy-depressed states, including <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, also showed losses, and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> grew far more slowly than earlier in the decade, the agency said. 

   The new figures are only estimates. 
The government will conduct a fullfledged census in <DATE>1990</DATE>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06025100 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06025100 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; Mercury News File Photograph; New York grew almost 4 percent, the
census says  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; CITY; POPULATION; SURVEY; STATISTIC; INCREASE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  New York City grew by nearly 4 percent in the 1980s while other large cities
in the East and Midwest shrank during the decade, the Census Bureau said
Thursday.;    On the second day of a three-day roll-out of population counts
for more than 39,000 localities, the National League of Cities said that
three-fourths of the nation's municipal leaders believe the 1990 census was
inaccurate.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  CENSUS: N.Y. GREW; OTHER BIG CITIES SHRANK
MUNICIPAL LEADERS DISPUTE THE FIGURES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     These are the final numbers of the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s national count.;    In
addition to releasing the numbers for <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and many other cities, the
bureau released head counts for 16 states -- <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and Utah.;    <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s
mayor, <PERSON>David Dinkins</PERSON>, first complimented the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s work, then
reiterated the criticism he has leveled at the agency throughout the <DATE>1990</DATE>
count.;    "After much prodding, we are pleased that the bureau no longer is
headed in the wrong direction, is no longer statistically shrinking a city
which actually is growing," said <PERSON>Dinkins</PERSON>. "But even today's bureau report
falls short -- far short -- of the number of people who live in <LOCATION>New York
City</LOCATION>.";    <ORGANIZATION>The Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said 7,322,564 people lived in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. That
number was higher by about 290,000 than a preliminary figure released <DATE>last
year</DATE> and 250,925 higher than the final figure from the <DATE>1980</DATE> census.;    The
two other big cities on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s list showed sharp declines. <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>
dropped <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> to 1,585,577, and <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> plummeted <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> to
1,027,974.;    <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s population, released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, was 2,783,726, down
7.4 percent.;    Several other cities in the <LOCATION>East</LOCATION> also were big losers.;   
The biggest drop was <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, which fell more than <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT> to 275,221
people. <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, named <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s most livable city in the mid-1980s, lost
nearly <PERCENT>13 percent</PERCENT> of its population, to 369,879. Cleveland slipped nearly <PERCENT>12
percent</PERCENT> to 505,616.;    Several small cities made big percentage gains --
<LOCATION>Boise</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, grew <PERCENT>23 percent</PERCENT>, to 125,738. Salem, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, picked up <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT>
to 107,786, and <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, gained nearly <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> to 159,789.;    <ORGANIZATION>The
Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> has received heavy criticism from municipal officials who say
many of the poor weren't counted. They've sued in an attempt to force the
bureau to correct its numbers. The bureau will decide by midsummer whether to
do so.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Washington  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910125  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  12A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  401  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday January 25, 1991
00025100,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890804-0144 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-89 0742EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Census-Metros     08-04 1004</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-Metros,0691</SECOND>
<HEAD>Half of All Americans Live in 37 Metro Areas</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: also on general news wires.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Two centuries after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> was
founded as a largely agricultural nation, nearly nine-tenths of the
population growth is occurring in metropolitan areas, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports.
   Almost half of all Americans reside in just 37 major urban
areas, the bureau said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in a new analysis of the patterns
of growth. And the metropolitan share of the population is growing
faster than that in rural areas.
   The ``rural renaissance'' reported in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> when small towns
and rural areas were growing seems to have ended, with increases in
cities and suburbs now well in the lead.
   The census study found that about <PERCENT>86 percent</PERCENT> of the nation's
population growth since <DATE>1980</DATE> has occurred in the 282 officially
designated metropolitan areas across the country. That pattern
represents a return to the metropolitan area dominance that has
been common since the era of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Depression</ORGANIZATION>, the bureau
reported.
   The analysis of <DATE>1987</DATE> figures found that nearly half of all
Americans, <PERCENT>48.9 percent</PERCENT>, reside in the 37 metro areas with
populations of a million or more.
   Led by <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, these metro areas had 119
million residents in <DATE>1987</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said.
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> leads the way as the only state entirely included
within metropolitan areas, the bureau noted. The northern portion
of the state is included in the greater <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metro area while
the southern portion is part of the <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> region.
   Seven other states have more than <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of their
populations in metropolitan areas _ <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Idaho is the least metropolitan state with only about <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>
of its residents in urban areas, the report added.
   Reflecting the nation's overall population trend, metropolitan
area growth has tended to flow to the South and <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> in recent
years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> observed in its study of growth patterns
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The population loss experienced in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>1970s</DATE> has halted in this decade, the agency found, while the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> has continued to have net losses in recent years.
   ``A slowdown in population growth has taken place since <DATE>1980</DATE> in
much of the interior of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, especially in
nonmetropolitan areas,'' noted the report prepared by <PERSON>Donald E.
Starsinic</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard L. Forstall</PERSON>.
   During this decade the nonmetropolitan population declined in 10
contiguous states _ <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
bureau pointed out.
   The nation's metro areas with 1 million or more residents, as of
<DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>, were <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 18.0 million; <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, 13.5
million; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, 8.1 million; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, 5.9 million;
<LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 5.9 million; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>, 4.6 million; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, 4.1
million; <LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>, 3.7 million;
   Also <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, 3.6 million; <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, 2.9
million; <LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION>, 2.7 million; <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, 2.6 million; <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>,
2.4 million; <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
<LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, 2.3 million;
   And <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, 2.3 million; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, 1.9 million; <LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION>, 1.9
million; <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, 1.8 million; <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION>, 1.7 million; <LOCATION>Milwaukee</LOCATION>,
1.5 million; <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, 1.5 million; <LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, 1.4 million;
<LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
   Plus <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, 1.3 million; <LOCATION>San Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, 1.3 million;
<LOCATION>Indianapolis</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, 1.2 million; <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>, 1.1 million; <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>,
1.1 million and Salt <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>, 1.1 million.
   Here is a state-by-state rundown of the percentage of the
population living in metropolitan areas as of <DATE>July 1, 1987</DATE>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881230-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-30-88 0332EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-PopulationGrowth     12-30 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Population Growth,580</SECOND>
<HEAD>Midwest Population Rebounds, But South and West Still Biggest Lures</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More Americans are once again calling the
Midwest their home, but Sunbelt states like <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
remain the favored places to settle down, government figures show.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE> released its <DATE>1988</DATE> population
estimates, showing that the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and parts of the South continued
strong population growth, while smaller growth rates were reflected
in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>.
   The Midwest appeared to be rebounding after a dropoff in
population during the early part of the decade.
   The total <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population stood at 245.8 million as of <DATE>July 1</DATE>,
the date of the <DATE>1988</DATE> Census statistics, reflecting a <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT>
increase in population from <DATE>July 1, 1985</DATE>.
   Over the three-year period, the biggest growth rate and
population loss were seen in small population states: <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> was up
<PERCENT>12.8 percent</PERCENT>, topping the 1 million mark for the first time; and the
energy-producing state of <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> had a <PERCENT>7.6 percent</PERCENT> decline, a loss
of 39,000 people, leaving its population at 471,000.
   The 12 Midwestern states _ where the depressed farm economy
caused a population downturn between <DATE>1981</DATE> and <DATE>1983</DATE> _ had an overall
<PERCENT>1.2 percent</PERCENT> population increase in the 1985-88 period, the Census
estimates showed.
   Some Midwestern states continued to lose residents, but the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> as a region picked up slightly.
   Losses were estimated in <DATE>1985-1988</DATE> for <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North
Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said in a statement,
but added, ``The <DATE>1988</DATE> data indicate that the declines may be
slowing, and several of these states may have grown in the past
year.''
   The largest state, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, had the greatest increase in
population, 1.8 million people, or <PERCENT>6.9 percent</PERCENT>, boosting its total
to 28.2 million.
   Other states that showed strong growth rates over the three years
were: <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>9.6 percent</PERCENT>, bringing its total to 3.5 million
people; <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>9.9 percent</PERCENT>, to 1.1 million residents;
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>8.9 percent</PERCENT>, to 12.4 million people; <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>7.1 percent</PERCENT>,
to 6.4 million; <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>5.7 percent</PERCENT>, to 4.6 million; and <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>,
<PERCENT>5.4 percent</PERCENT>, to 660,000 people.
   Eleven states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> lost population during
the three years: <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>.
   In the regions outside the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>, the government found that
population increased by <PERCENT>1.5 percent</PERCENT> in the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION>, including the
<LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> and Mid-Atlantic states; by <PERCENT>3.7 percent</PERCENT> in the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>;
and by <PERCENT>5.5 percent</PERCENT> in the West, including the Mountain and <LOCATION>Pacific
Coast</LOCATION> states.
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sunshine State</ORGANIZATION>, continued to attract residents, with
a population growth rate of <PERCENT>8.9 percent</PERCENT>. That boosted its population
to 12.4 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890503-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-89 1255EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-AgingAmerica     05-03 0573</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Aging America,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>For Release at 6:30 p.m. EDT</HEAD>
<HEAD>American Are Just a Shade Older than Ever _ Median Age Reaches 32.3
Years</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   America's people, statistically speaking, are
a just shade older than they've ever been before, with the median
age in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> reaching a record 32.3 years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   That means half of all the people living in the country were
older than 32.3 years, and half younger, as of last <DATE>July 1</DATE>. This is
up from the median age of 32.1 a year earlier.
   By states, in terms of the median age, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> are in the middle while the oldest Americans are in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and the youngest in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   The maturing of the massive Baby Boom generation, born in the
years following World War II, is raising the nation's median age,
census officials and other analysts have noted.
   This group forms the largest segment of the population and as it
ages the median age is pulled along, Census demographer <PERSON>Ed Byerly</PERSON>
said in a telephone interview.
   After years of climbing gradually as life spans increased, the
median age reached 30 for the first time in the <DATE>1950</DATE> census, when
it was 30.2 years.
   But then the full force of the Baby Boom began to occur and the
large number of children in the population pulled the median down
for two decades.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the median edged back up to 30 again and has continued
climbing since then, as the <ORGANIZATION>Baby Boomers</ORGANIZATION> pursued careers and
education and postponed having families, creating what some
statisticians call a Baby Bust.
   In the last few years, total births have begun rising as aging
Baby Boomers began having children, but those numbers remain too
small to have a major impact on the national median, <PERSON>Byerly</PERSON> said.
   Retirement-haven <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> remains the state with the oldest
population, with a median age of 36.4 years, up from 36.3 years in
<DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Following <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, the highest median ages were reported for the
large industrial states in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>, with <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> second at
34.5 years followed by <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> at 34.4.
   Indeed, the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> has the highest median age of the four
regions at 33.9 years. Next is the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> at 32.3 _ same as the
national figure _ followed by the South, 32; and the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, 31.6.
   The state with the youngest residents remains <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, where half
of the population is under 25.7 years, and half over. A year
earlier, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s median age was 25.5.
   Next lowest is <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, with a median figure of 28.7 years.
   Two states, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, match the national
median age, while the populations of 20 states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION> are older than the nation as a whole. The remaining 28
states have median ages younger than that of the country.
   Here is a look at the nation's median age through the years:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   America's people, statistically speaking, are
a just shade older than they've ever been before, with the median
age in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> reaching a record 32.3 years, the <ORGANIZATION>Census
Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   That means half of all the people living in the country were
older than 32.3 years, and half younger, as of last <DATE>July 1</DATE>. This is
up from the median age of 32.1 a year earlier.
   By states, in terms of the median age, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North
Carolina</LOCATION> are in the middle while the oldest Americans are in
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and the youngest in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   The maturing of the massive Baby Boom generation, born in the
years following World War II, is raising the nation's median age,
census officials and other analysts have noted.
   This group forms the largest segment of the population and as it
ages the median age is pulled along, Census demographer <PERSON>Ed Byerly</PERSON>
said in a telephone interview.
   After years of climbing gradually as life spans increased, the
median age reached 30 for the first time in the <DATE>1950</DATE> census, when
it was 30.2 years.
   But then the full force of the Baby Boom began to occur and the
large number of children in the population pulled the median down
for two decades.
   In <DATE>1980</DATE>, the median edged back up to 30 again and has continued
climbing since then, as the <ORGANIZATION>Baby Boomers</ORGANIZATION> pursued careers and
education and postponed having families, creating what some
statisticians call a Baby Bust.
   In the last few years, total births have begun rising as aging
Baby Boomers began having children, but those numbers remain too
small to have a major impact on the national median, <PERSON>Byerly</PERSON> said.
   Retirement-haven <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> remains the state with the oldest
population, with a median age of 36.4 years, up from 36.3 years in
<DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Following <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, the highest median ages were reported for the
large industrial states in the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION>, with <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> second at
34.5 years followed by <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> at 34.4.
   Indeed, the <ORGANIZATION>Northeast</ORGANIZATION> has the highest median age of the four
regions at 33.9 years. Next is the <LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> at 32.3 _ same as the
national figure _ followed by the South, 32; and the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>, 31.6.
   The state with the youngest residents remains <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>, where half
of the population is under 25.7 years, and half over. A year
earlier, <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>'s median age was 25.5.
   Next lowest is <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, with a median figure of 28.7 years.
   Two states, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, match the national
median age, while the populations of 20 states and the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION> are older than the nation as a whole. The remaining 28
states have median ages younger than that of the country.
   Here is a look at the nation's median age through the years:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901227-0001
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901227-0001.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Census Bureau Adds 3.8 Million to Count
   But Critics Say Millions Remain Missing
   ----
   By David Wessel
</HL>
<DATE>
12/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A3
</SO>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
CONGRESS (CNG)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- The Census Bureau added 3.8 million more
people to its 1990 headcount, but critics continue to
complain that the bureau is missing millions more.
   The bureau said yesterday that its almost-final tally from
the 1990 census is 249,632,692 people, 10.2% more than the
1980 census found.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The addition of 3.8 million people to the preliminary
total released this <DATE>summer</DATE> reflects 2.9 million residents the
bureau missed the first time as well as the anticipated
922,819 military and other federal employees and dependents
overseas.
   Under the Constitution, the new headcount will result in a
shift of 19 seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> is the big winner, adding seven seats to give
it 52 representatives, or nearly <PERCENT>12%</PERCENT> of all the seats in the
435-member <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> is the big loser. It will lose
three seats and end up with 31 seats after the <DATE>1992</DATE> election.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> tally includes military and other federal workers
and dependents living overseas. The <DATE>1980</DATE> tally didn't.
Excluding those people, the resident population of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
grew by <PERCENT>9.8%</PERCENT> during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> Director <PERSON>Barbara
Bryant</PERSON> said.
   The bureau may yet make additional adjustments to the
tally. Under terms of an out-of-court settlement of a lawsuit
brought by <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> and others who argued that the
census disproportionately misses minorities, the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce
Department</ORGANIZATION> must decide by <DATE>July 15</DATE> whether to adjust the
tallies statistically to compensate for the undercount.
Commerce Undersecretary <PERSON>Michael Darby</PERSON> yesterday called the
<DATE>1990</DATE> census "full, fair and efficient."
   But congressional skepticism persists. "It's not a
question of whether we have counted everyone. The census
never does," said Rep. <PERSON>Thomas Sawyer</PERSON> (D., <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>), chairman of
the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> census subcommittee. "The question is how close
they've come to the truth."
   <ORGANIZATION>New York State Attorney</ORGANIZATION> General <PERSON>Robert Abrams</PERSON>, among those
suing the bureau, was quick to complain that the <DATE>1990</DATE> census
still undercounted his state. "When large segments of our
residents are left out of the political process, democracy is
devalued for all of us," he said.
   Additions to the preliminary tally reflect, among other
things, recanvassing of a substantial number of housing units
by census enumerators. With aid from state and local
governments, the bureau also identified about 125,000 housing
units it had missed. It also turned up an extra 400,000
people from parole records, <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said recently.
   <PERSON>Mr. Darby</PERSON> noted that the new tally is "surprisingly close"
to earlier projections that the census would find a
population of 250 million. But Rep. <PERSON>Sawyer</PERSON> noted that the
249.6 million total is still substantially shy of the
bureau's recent projections, based on demographic data, of
253.4 million.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> census confirms trends identified in earlier
reports, such as the rapid growth of the western states. "The
West is the big population gainer," <PERSON>Mrs. Bryant</PERSON> said. In the
past decade, the population of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> has grown by <PERCENT>22%</PERCENT>,
while the South grew by <PERCENT>13.5%</PERCENT>, the Northeast by <PERCENT>3.4%</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION> by <PERCENT>1.3%</PERCENT>.
   The reassignment of seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> reflects these
trends, with the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION> and Sunbelt states gaining at the
expense of the big industrial states of the <LOCATION>Northeast</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Midwest</LOCATION>. In addition to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, states adding seats
include <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, which gains four seats; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, which gains
three seats; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, which each gain one seat.
   Besides <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, states losing seats include <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, which each lose two seats;
and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, which each lose one
seat.
   None of these shifts comes as a surprise, however. Earlier
bureau reports on the <DATE>1990</DATE> count pointed to all of them.
   The figures may provide new ammunition for the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s perennially unsuccessful campaign for statehood.
Although the census found that the district lost population
during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, it still is larger than either <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. Yet the district hasn't any seats in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, and its one representative in the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> can't vote.
   The bureau also noted yesterday that four states lost
population in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>. They are <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>.
   ---
                       Population Power
                                                                                                       

   State-by-state tally of population and seats in the <ORGANIZATION>House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION> based on <DATE>1990</DATE> census
                                                                                                       

                               <DATE>1990</DATE>        TOTAL    CHANGE
                            POPULATION     HOUSE     FROM
                          (In millions)    SEATS    PRESENT
                                                                                                       

   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>                 29.84         52          7
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>                   18.04         31         -3
   <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>                      17.06         30          3

   <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>               11.92         21         -2
   Illinois                   11.47         20         -2
   <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>                       10.89         19         -2
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>                    9.33         16         -2
   <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>                  7.75         13         -1
   <ORGANIZATION>N. Carolina</ORGANIZATION>                 6.66         12         -1
   <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>                     6.51         11         -1
   <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>                    6.22         11          1
   <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>               6.03         10         -1
   <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>                     5.56         10       None
   <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>                    5.14          9       None
   <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>                   4.91          9       None
   <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>                  4.89          9          1
   Tennessee                   4.90          9       None
   <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>                    4.80          8       None
   <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>                   4.39          8       None
   <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>                   4.24          7         -1
   <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION>                     4.06          7       None
   Kentucky                    3.70          6         -1
   <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>                     3.68          6          1
   <LOCATION>South Carolina</LOCATION>              3.51          6       None
   <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>                    3.31          6       None
   Connecticut                 3.30          6       None
   Oklahoma                    3.16          6       None
   <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION>                      2.85          5       None
   <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>                        2.79          5         -1
   <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>                 2.59          5       None
   Kansas                      2.49          4         -1
   Arkansas                    2.36          4       None
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>               1.80          3         -1
   <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>                        1.73          3       None
   <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>                    1.58          3       None
   <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>                  1.52          3       None
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>                       1.23          2       None
   <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>                      1.21          2       None
   <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>                      1.12          2       None
   New Hampshire               1.11          2       None
   <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>                       1.01          2       None
   <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>                1.01          2       None
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>                     0.80          1         -1
   <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>                0.70          1       None
   Delaware                    0.67          1       None
   <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>                0.64          1       None
   <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION>                     0.56          1       None
   <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>                      0.55          1       None
   Wyoming                     0.46          1       None
   Dist. of <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>           0.61         --         --
   TOTAL                     249.6         435
                                                                                                       

   Source: <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Census Bureau
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901226-0133 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-26-90 2324EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-CensusCount 3rdLd-Writethru a0629 12-26 0785</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census Count, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0629,860</SECOND>
<BYLINE>249.6 Million People Counted in 1990 Census</BYLINE>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf to CORRECT California increase from 26.3 percent
to 26.1 percent; SUBS grafs 13-15 bgng: ``The sharpest,'' to
CORRECT Arizona from 36 percent to 35.3 percent; South Atlantic
from 18.4 percent to 18.8 percent and ``West South Central'' to
``East South Central''</NOTE>
<HEAD>With BC-Census Count-States</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TIM BOVEE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population stood at 249,632,692 as of
the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, the government said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a numerical
portrait of a nation growing far more rapidly in the Sun Belt than
in the industrial north and agricultural heartland.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the nation's largest state, added more than 6
million people in the decade, a <PERCENT>26.1 percent</PERCENT> increase to 29,839,250
people.
   Wyoming remained the smallest state, with 455,975 people, down
<PERCENT>2.9 percent</PERCENT> from <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> was the biggest population gainer in percentage terms,
and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> each grew by more than one-third as
millions of Americans flocked to the sunshine.
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> was the largest loser in percentage terms.
   In all, the population increased by <PERCENT>10.2 percent</PERCENT> from the
226,504,825 people counted in the <DATE>1980</DATE> census, below the <PERCENT>11.4
percent</PERCENT> population growth recorded from <DATE>1970 to 1980</DATE>, and the <PERCENT>13.4
percent</PERCENT> rate from <DATE>1960</DATE> to <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   The information was contained in the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s first
release of ``final figures'' - really tentative final figures -
from the <DATE>1990</DATE> count. The information will be used for everything
from readjusting the size of each state's congressional delegation
to parcelling out federal aid.
   In political terms, the population shifts will give <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>
seven new <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, and add lawmakers to seven other states.
Thirteen states will lose representation.
   Because of the importance of the population estimates, some
states and cities are likely to challenge the tallies, and a final
count isn't expected until next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The cost of the <DATE>1990</DATE> census, from planning begun in <DATE>1984</DATE> to a
final release of data in <DATE>1993</DATE>, is estimated at <MONEY>$2.6 billion</MONEY> by the
bureau.
   Still locked in <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> computers - to be doled out over
the next several years - is a wealth of information about age,
race, living conditions and other details of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> near the turn
of the century.
   Besides <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, four other states lost population. The biggest
percentage loser was <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, whose population dropped by <PERCENT>7.6
percent</PERCENT> to 1,801,625. Other states losing population were <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>,
down <PERCENT>4.3 percent</PERCENT>, and and <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, down <PERCENT>1.7 percent</PERCENT>. The
<ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> also lost population, <PERCENT>4.5 percent</PERCENT>.
   The sharpest gainer in percentage terms was <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>. That state's
population grew by <PERCENT>50.7 percent</PERCENT> to 1,206,152. Besides <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
other states with gains of more than <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> were <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, up
<PERCENT>33.4 percent</PERCENT>; <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>35.3 percent</PERCENT>; and <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, up <PERCENT>37.4
percent</PERCENT>.
   The Pacific states were the fastest growing region, <PERCENT>23.4
percent</PERCENT>, followed by the Mountain states, <PERCENT>20.6 percent</PERCENT>, and the
<LOCATION>South Atlantic</LOCATION> states, <PERCENT>18.8 percent</PERCENT>. By contrast, the <ORGANIZATION>East North
Central</ORGANIZATION> states grew a bare <PERCENT>1.1 percent</PERCENT>, and the <LOCATION>West North Central</LOCATION>
states, <PERCENT>3.1 percent</PERCENT>.
   Some regions went against the broader trend. <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, which
had a boom in high-tech industry during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, grew by <PERCENT>7.2
percent</PERCENT>. The East South Central states grew only <PERCENT>3.9 percent</PERCENT>.
   Because of the high financial and political stakes, the census
numbers and the way they were obtained are certain to draw
continued sharp scrutiny.
   More than 6,000 local governments challenged the accuracy of a
preliminary count based mainly on the <DATE>April 1</DATE> census taken by mail.
The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> responded with a series of recounts and an ad
campaign urging people who thought they had been missed to come
forward.
   The final national population total was nearly 4 million people
more than the preliminary number released by the bureau earlier
this year.
   <ORGANIZATION>Commerce</ORGANIZATION> Secretary <PERSON>Robert Mosbacher</PERSON> has until <DATE>July 1991</DATE>, to
decide whether to adjust the census numbers to account for a
statistically determined undercount of minorities. An adjustment
would increase political representation of areas with a high
percentage of minorities, and lower that of other areas.
   <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will gain seven seats, giving it 52 in the 435-member
<ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> will gain four; <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, three; and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, one seat each.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will lose three seats; <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, two seats each; and <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>,
one seat each.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> census for the first time counted some Americans living
abroad. The total included 922,819 members of the armed forces,
civilian employees of the federal government and their dependents.
   The comparable numbers from 10 years earlier counted only people
living within the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The Census Bureau on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> released two sets of <DATE>1980</DATE>
numbers. The 226,504,825 figure used by the bureau for comparison
with the <DATE>1990</DATE> national total was released in <DATE>December 1980</DATE> but was
later adjusted slightly to get rid of minor problems. The adjusted
figure was 226,545,805.
   The <DATE>1990</DATE> population count was nearly 64 times the 3,929,214
counted in <DATE>1790</DATE>, the first census in the nation's history. By <DATE>1900</DATE>,
the population had reached 76,212,168.
   In <DATE>1950</DATE>, the first census after World War II, the population was
151,325,798.
   In <DATE>January</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> will begin sending information on
small areas, in some cases the size of a city block, to state
legislatures so they can begin drawing new congressional and
legislative boundaries.
   That process will be completed by <DATE>April 1</DATE>.
   The bureau will put off releasing detailed demographic data
until after the decision on adjusting the figures.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890728-0217 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-89 1605EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Rural-Stats Adv06   07-28 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Rural-Stats, Adv 06,0535</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Aug. 6, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Facts, Figures About Rural America</HEAD>
<HEAD>With BC-Rural Crossroads</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphic</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>POPULATION:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>FARMING:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>UNEMPLOYMENT:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>POVERTY:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>SERVICES:</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts about rural <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, provided by the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Agriculture</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>American Hospital
Association</ORGANIZATION>, and the <ORGANIZATION>Center on Budget and Policy Priorities</ORGANIZATION>, a
research organization.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Aug. 6</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871013-0105 </DOCNO>
<HL> REGIONS:
Alaska Learns What It's Like
To Register a Population Loss
---
By Eugene Carlson
<DD> 10/13/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> LABOR
ECONOMIC NEWS (ECO) </IN>
<TEXT>
   ADD <LOCATION>ALASKA</LOCATION> to the short list of states losing population. 
The reason: a sharp increase in the number of residents moving out. 
In the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, a healthy influx of newcomers, plus the highest natural population increase of any state (about six babies are born in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> for every person that dies), kept population moving up briskly. 
Between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1986</DATE>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s population rose <PERCENT>32%</PERCENT>, by far the fastest rate of increase of any state. 

   But as the state's oil-based economy softened, the traditional migration pattern reversed. 
<PERSON>Gregory Williams</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s state demographer, estimates that in the 12 months ended in <DATE>July 1987</DATE>, up to 15,000 more people left <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> than moved into the state. 
That was more than enough to offset the natural population increase of about 10,000 for the same period. 

   With <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s unemployment rate close to <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT>, a lot of out-migrants have headed for <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, where the job market is healthier. 
There is a plus side to this outflow: Sluicing out excess workers should bring the local labor supply into better balance and help stanch the state's population loss. 
"We're seeing signs that this (population drain) has begun to bottom out," says <PERSON>Mr. Williams</PERSON>. 

   Ten states either lost population or had no population gain in the 12 months ended in <DATE>July 1986</DATE>, the most recent estimates published by the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>. 
They are: <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. 

   ---
   <LOCATION>PHILLY</LOCATION> MEETS THE JOB SQUEEZE: <ORGANIZATION>First Pennsylvania Bank</ORGANIZATION>'s quarterly survey of executives in Philadelphia-area companies picks up some of the same labor shortage complaints that <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION> executives have been making the past couple of years. 

   Nearly <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of the metro <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> companies questioned said they planned to add employees next year, from managers to production workers, and all but a few said finding these workers would be tough. 
Higher pay doesn't seem to help much. 
The companies are already paying an average <MONEY>$6.58</MONEY> an hour for entry-level workers. 
Only <PERCENT>11%</PERCENT> said they had anyone on the payroll making the <MONEY>$3.35</MONEY> an hour minimum wage. 

   Despite the labor crunch, only <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> of the companies said they'd consider moving operations to an area with more abundant labor. 

   ---
   LITTLE PHNOM PENH: <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, is now reputed to have the largest concentration of ethnic Cambodians outside <LOCATION>Southeast Asia</LOCATION>. 
No one has yet done a full-fledged head count, but <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s education department says there are 3,325 "English impaired" students in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> schools whose first language is Khmer (the Cambodian national language), double the number of the next-highest school district. 

   Add to this figure Cambodian students fluent in English, factor in parents, toddlers and in-laws at home, plus other adults, and the Cambodian population in <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION> could fall in the 25,000 to 40,000 range. 

   ---
   NORTH DAKOTANS TRADITIONALLY VOTE in large numbers, but in the <DATE>November 1986</DATE> congressional elections, they beat every state in both registration (an amazing <PERCENT>95%</PERCENT> of the voting age population) and turnout at the polls (<PERCENT>73%</PERCENT>). 
A fiercely contested <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> race, in which Democrat Kent Conrad nosed out Republican incumbent <PERSON>Mark Andrews</PERSON>, helped fire the voters enthusiasm. 

   <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oregon</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION> all had turnouts of more than <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the voting-age populace in <DATE>1986</DATE>, according to a new voting behavior analysis from the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>. 
The worst performer: <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, where only one-third of potentially eligible voters cast ballots. 

   ---
   <LOCATION>ARIZONA</LOCATION> PURCHASING MANAGERS see signs of prosperity mixed with looming inflation. 
Average delivery time on incoming shipments is now the longest since mid-1984. 
Inventory levels continue to grow, and new orders in <DATE>August</DATE> and <DATE>September</DATE> were unusually strong. 
Meanwhile, price increases in the last two months were at the fastest rate in more than three years. 

   ---
   EMPLOYEE TRANSFERS to high-cost areas aren't going down well, says relocation consultant <ORGANIZATION>Runzheimer International</ORGANIZATION>, of <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis</LOCATION>. 
Three-fourths of 143 corporate relocation administrators questioned said employees reassigned to the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> metropolitan area either resisted the move or refused to go. 
Other areas where <ORGANIZATION>Runzheimer</ORGANIZATION> says above-average cost-of-living is a significant barrier to relocation: <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. 

   ---
   BRIEFS: Ornamental plants and flowers passed citrus products last year as <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s No. 1 cash crop, says the <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION>. . . . 
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>'s legislature makes the fiddle the official state musical instrument. . . . 
For upscale vacationers, <ORGANIZATION>Countryman Press</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Woodstock</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vt.</LOCATION>, publishes "<LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> on <MONEY>$500</MONEY> a Day." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910909-0175
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910909-0175.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   PEOPLE PATTERNS
   ----
   By Alan L. Otten
</HL>
<DATE>
09/09/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
MEDICAL AND BIOTECHNOLOGY, GENETIC RESEARCH, PROSTHETICS (MTC)
REAL ESTATE INVESTMENTS (REA)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY, SPORTS (REC)
</IN>
<GV>
COMMERCE DEPARTMENT (COM)
HEALTH AND HUMAN SERVICES (HHS)
</GV>
<RE>
FLORIDA (FL)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
MARYLAND (MD)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PENNSYLVANIA (PA)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Racial Groups Diverge
   In Timing of First Births
                                                                                                       

</LP>
<TEXT>
   RACIAL differences in the timing of first births are
widening, two <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> demographers find.
   Drawing on birth and other records published since <DATE>1979</DATE>,
<PERSON>Renbao Chen</PERSON> and <PERSON>S. Philip Morgan</PERSON> determine that from <DATE>1980</DATE> to
<DATE>1987</DATE> white women under 30 years old continued an earlier
trend toward postponing their first birth, while white women
over 30 began showing slightly higher rates of first births
than over-30 women of earlier decades, clearly seeking to
catch up on postponed fertility. Nonwhite women -- blacks,
Asians and others -- also tended to have their first children
at somewhat later ages than nonwhite women in earlier years.
   But at every age from the teens on, blacks and other
nonwhites were far more likely to be having their first birth
than were white women of the same age. For example, in <DATE>1987</DATE> a
20-year-old nonwhite woman was almost twice as likely to have
her first child in the following year as was a 20-year-old
white woman, while a 25-year-old nonwhite woman was about 1
1/2 times more likely to be having her first child than her
white counterpart.
   The research also showed that nonwhite women now have far
lower rates of childlessness than white women. Historically,
blacks had far higher rates, due largely to health and other
involuntary factors. This situation started reversing in the
<DATE>1950s</DATE>, and the difference has grown greater as more white
women have forgone having children altogether. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, for
instance, a white woman born in <DATE>1954</DATE> was better than three
times more likely to be childless than a 33-year-old
nonwhite.
                                                                                                       

   Farm Belt Holds Onto
   Its Oldest Americans
                                                                                                       

   THE OLDEST old, those 85 or more, bulk largest in the Farm
Belt, <DATE>1990</DATE> census figures show.
   Not surprisingly, the largest numbers of 85-plus men and
women are found in the most populous states: <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>. In each of these, people 85 and over total well
into six figures.
   Looked at as a percentage of a state's population,
however, a much different picture emerges. In 14 states, the
85-and-older group accounts for <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT> or more of the total
population. Iowa leads with <PERCENT>2.0%</PERCENT>, closely followed by <LOCATION>South
Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.9%</PERCENT>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.8%</PERCENT> and
<LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION> with <PERCENT>1.7%</PERCENT>.
   In nine other states, including <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, the oldest old account for
<PERCENT>1.6%</PERCENT> or <PERCENT>1.5%</PERCENT> of the total. The other states in this category
are <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>: <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, by contrast, is at the bottom of the ranking,
with only <PERCENT>0.2%</PERCENT> of its population 85 or older.
   Much the same states rank at or near the top in the
percentage of total state population living in nursing homes.
The <LOCATION>Dakotas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wisconsin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION> are the only states with
at least <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT> of their populations living in nursing homes.
Census Bureau specialist <PERSON>Cynthia Taeuber</PERSON> says most nursing
home residents are 85 or older.
   So why do the oldest old figure so heavily in these
states? <PERSON>Ms. Taeuber</PERSON> hypothesizes that in most of these states
younger adults move out to seek better job opportunities,
while the older natives stay and age in place, inevitably
constituting a larger share of the total. And with their
children moved away, many end up in nursing homes.
   Another census report says that the number of
centenarians, men and women 100 or older, more than doubled
between <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1990</DATE>, increasing to 35,808 from an estimated
14,000 to 16,000. (There was no precise count in <DATE>1980</DATE>.) More
than 28,000 of the 35,808 were women, and well over 29,000 of
the total were white.
                                                                                                       

   Golf Has More Players,
   Who Play More Often
                                                                                                       

   MORE PEOPLE are playing golf, and most are playing more
often, a recreation specialist reports.
   <PERSON>Rod Warnick</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Massachusetts</ORGANIZATION> professor who
tracks leisure trends, calculates that the number of adult
golfers increased about <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> a year in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> to 22.2
million, while the number of days played grew about <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>
annually to 393.7 million. Moreover, he notes, the number of
"heavy" golfers, those playing 20 or more times a year, grew
even faster, more than doubling to 6.8 million, while the
number of days these avid golfers played increased about <PERCENT>8%</PERCENT>
annually to almost 300 million days.
   <PERSON>Mr. Warnick</PERSON> says the growth of leisure time, the
increasing numbers of retirees and the aging of the baby
boomers all contributed. He also finds that more women and
minorities have taken up the game -- a trend he sees as apt
to lead to further anti-discrimination suits against golf
clubs and courses that aren't fully integrated or given to
equal treatment.
                                                                                                       

   Odds and Ends
                                                                                                       

   MOBILE HOMES make up <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> of the nation's housing inventory,
the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> reports. This is the fastest-growing type
of housing, up <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> since <DATE>1980</DATE>. . . . Athletes who play hard
to win are more apt to get hurt than those who just play for
fun, <ORGANIZATION>University of Florida</ORGANIZATION> researchers find. They say those
who take a game too much to heart are more likely to put
themselves in a risky situation in an effort to come out
ahead. . . . Diseases and other causes of disability in women
65 and older will be the subject of a seven-year study by the
<ORGANIZATION>Johns Hopkins School of Medicine</ORGANIZATION> under a contract with the
government's <ORGANIZATION>National Institute on Aging</ORGANIZATION>. About two-thirds of
all disabled older people are female.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900818-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-18-90 0251EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census-States     08-18 0237</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-States,230</SECOND>
<HEAD>Census Figures for Eighteen States Issued</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   At least four states may have lost population
since <DATE>1980</DATE>, according to preliminary Census figures.
   <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> registered
population declines, data released <DATE>Friday</DATE> showed.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said 14 other states reported increases.
   Reports for the 18 states were sent to state and local officials
as part of the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s local review program.
   Census officials emphasized that the figures are preliminary and
were provided to allow local governments to question the results in
the event people were missed or overcounted.
   Final official state population figures are scheduled to be
issued <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>.
   Here is a list of the figures made public <DATE>Friday</DATE>, compared with
the results of the <DATE>1980</DATE> census. Reports for other states are
expected to become public over the next few weeks.
   Connecticut: 3,226,929, up from 3,108,000.
   Delaware: 658,031, up from 594,000.
   Idaho: 1,003,558, up from 944,000.
   Kentucky: 3,665,220, up from 3,661,000.
   <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>: 4,180,831, down from 4,206,000.
   <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>: 1,218,053, up from 1,125,000.
   <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>: 9,179,661, down from 9,262,000.
   <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>: 2,534,814, up from 2,521,000.
   <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>: 794,329, up from 787,000.
   <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>: 1,572,503, up from 1,570,000.
   New Hampshire: 1,103,163, up from 921,000.
   <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>: 634,223, down from 653,000.
   Oregon: 2,828,214, up from 2,633,000.
   <LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>: 988,609, up from 947,000.
   <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, 693,294, up from 691,000.
   Tennessee: 4,822,134, up from 4,591,000.
   Vermont: 560,029, up from 511,000.
   <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>: 1,782,958, down from 1,950,000.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881117-0111 </DOCNO>
<HL> PEOPLE PATTERNS -- Population Projections ---- Compiled by the staff of American Demographics magazine </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
      Census Bureau Sees
   Slow <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Growth Ahead
   ACCORDING TO projections published today by the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, there will be nearly 250 million people in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> by <DATE>1990</DATE>, up 23.3 million from <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
If the <DATE>1990</DATE> census proves these figures correct, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> population will have grown by only <PERCENT>10.3%</PERCENT> this decade, the lowest rate in <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history except for the Depression years of the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, when it was <PERCENT>7.2%</PERCENT>. 
The projections also indicate record low growth in the near future: <PERCENT>7.2%</PERCENT> in the <DATE>1990s</DATE> and <PERCENT>5.3%</PERCENT> between <DATE>2000</DATE> and <DATE>2010</DATE>. 

   But the bureau foresees wide variation from state to state. 
For example, it expects that during the <DATE>1980s</DATE>, four states (<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>) will together have lost nearly 300,000 people. 
At the other extreme, the four fastest-growing states (<LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>) are expected each to have grown more than <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT>, adding a total of 4.6 million people. 

   Fastest growth doesn't mean most growth, however. 
About half of total <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> growth for the rest of the century will occur in just three states -- <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> -- which are expected to gain 12 million people in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> and 9.5 million in the <DATE>1990s</DATE>. 

   ---

                     Winners and Losers
             (Percentage change in population)
    Fastest-growing states
          1980-1990                      1990-2000
    <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>            <PERCENT>43%</PERCENT>          Arizona          <PERCENT>23%</PERCENT>
    Arizona           38           <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>           21
    <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>            35           <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>       21
    <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>           32           <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>          20
    <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION>        25           <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>          19
    Biggest-losing/slowest-growing states
          1980-1990                      1990-2000
    <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>              <PERCENT>-5.4%</PERCENT>        Iowa             <PERCENT>-7.6%</PERCENT>
    W.<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>        -4.8         W.<LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>       -7.3
    <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>      -0.3         <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>     -4.7
    <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>              -0.1         <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>     -2.7
    <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>          +0.3         Wyoming          -2.6
   Source: Census Bureau
   ---
   Interstate Migration
   Plays a Key Role
   THE CENSUS <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s projections assume that past trends in birth, death and migration rates will continue. Natural increase (births minus deaths) varies little from state to state, so interstate migration is often the key in determining future populations. For example, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> is projected to gain 435,000 people from natural increase during the <DATE>1990s</DATE> -- but lose 498,000 to out-migration.
   While all 50 states are expected to show positive natural increase this decade, 24 will see that growth partially or completely offset by people leaving. Positive natural increase is seen for most states during the next decade as well, but <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> could be an unusual case. It is projected to have 20,000 more deaths than births between <DATE>1990</DATE> and <DATE>2000</DATE>. A net in-migration of 2.6 million, though, will overwhelm this negative natural increase.
   Many factors can influence migration, perhaps even government intervention. <LOCATION>New York state</LOCATION>, which lost population in the <DATE>1970s</DATE>, has lowered personal income tax rates and some business taxes. Coincidentally or not, it is expected to gain 215,000 people this decade.
   Workers Seen Carrying
   Fewer Dependents
   PROMISING A lighter burden of support, the overall dependency ratio in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is expected to decline to 57 by <DATE>2010</DATE> from 62 in <DATE>1987</DATE>. The ratio measures the number of dependents (children under 18 and people 65 and older) for every 100 nondependents (those 18 to 64).
   The number of nondependents will rise <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> between <DATE>1990</DATE> and <DATE>2010</DATE>, while that of dependents will grow only <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>, according to the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>'s forecast. However, these figures mask differences between the young and the elderly, as well as among geographic regions.
   The number of people 65 and older is projected to grow <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> between <DATE>1990</DATE> and <DATE>2010</DATE>, raising the elderly dependency ratio to 21.9 from 20.5. The ratio for those under 18 will drop to 34.8 from 41.5, as fewer children are born.
   The dependency ratio is based strictly on age groups and makes no assumptions about true dependence. In fact, more than <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> of the elderly were employed in <DATE>1987</DATE>, and only <PERCENT>72%</PERCENT> of working-age people were actually working.
   Study Profiles Network
   Of Family Support
   MORE THAN FOUR million Americans provide financial support to seven million young children living outside their households, according to another new Census Bureau report; two million provide support to three million adults outside their homes, mostly elderly parents. Of these providers, <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT> are helping both children and adults who don't live with them. The bureau estimates that payments total <MONEY>$19 billion</MONEY> a year.
   The typical provider is a divorced father 25 to 44 years old. On average, providers have an annual family income of <MONEY>$37,800</MONEY> and pay <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> a year in support; those supporting both kids and adults average <MONEY>$43,500</MONEY> in income and <MONEY>$8,400</MONEY> in support annually. The largest amount of support -- an average of <MONEY>$7,800</MONEY> -- goes to spouses who are separated or temporarily living apart. Ex-spouses get the next-largest chunk, averaging <MONEY>$4,700</MONEY> each. Children 21 and older receive an average of <MONEY>$3,800</MONEY> a year; those under 21 get <MONEY>$1,600</MONEY> on average. Parents receiving support get an average of <MONEY>$1,500</MONEY>.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900829-0145 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-29-90 2120EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Census-States 1stLd-Writethru a0659 08-29 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Census-States, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0659,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Population Gains to Give Sunbelt States More Seats in Congress</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Inserts new 6th graf with 1980 population</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By RANDOLPH E. SCHMID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The flow of Americans to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> has pushed
the <ORGANIZATION>Golden State</ORGANIZATION> far ahead of all rivals in population and will
census figures indicate.
   Preliminary <DATE>1990</DATE> population figures show <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> picking up
seven <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> with four, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> three and a
handful of other warm-weather states with one each.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> hung on to its No. 2 ranking in population behind
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> in the new figures _ with <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> closing fast
in third and fourth places _ but will lose three seats in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
because its population rose only slightly in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   Four Northern industrial states _ <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> _ lost population during the decade and will have two
fewer seats each.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated a national count of just under 246
million, including 29.3 million in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, 17.6 million in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>, 16.8 million in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and 12.8 million in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Wyoming
was last, at just under 450,000, passed by <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, which had the
smallest population in <DATE>1980</DATE> but grew to almost 546,000 in <DATE>1990</DATE>.
   The total population count in <DATE>1980</DATE> was 226,545,805.
   House seats are redistributed among the states after each
Census. Because the number is limited to 435 seats, when a growing
state gains a seat some other state must lose one.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s slight population gain was quickly disputed by state
officials, who had predicted repeatedly that the state would be
undercounted.
   ``I don't believe it,'' Gov. <PERSON>Mario Cuomo</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>. ``Do
you really, honestly believe that everybody who should be counted
has been counted? The answer is of course not. My mother had
trouble; she didn't want to answer.''
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>David N. Dinkins</PERSON> called the city's estimated
slight decline ``unadulterated nonsense'' and promised to pinpoint
where he said the government had made errors.
   Overall 19 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats will change states according to the
figures, which could change significantly before the final report
is issued <DATE>Dec. 31</DATE>.
   The widely noted movement of Americans to the Sun Belt was
documented anew in the Census Bureau figures. Besides <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, states gaining a <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seat each were <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   Besides the two-seat losers _ <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> _ there will be one less seat each for <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION>.
   Overall, the preliminary Census figures show the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
with a population of 245,837,683 residents. That's somewhat below
the 250 million that the bureau had estimated earlier this year.
   However, 4 million or more may be added as the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION>
conducts follow up counts and completes tabulations before the
final reports are made public. If those are added in only a few
states, some of the seats allocated in the preliminary tally could
shift again.
   For example, a study by the private firm <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services</ORGANIZATION>
showed <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> neck and neck for the last seat
allocated. <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> got the seat, but a shift of 3,000 people
could shift it to <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Kimball Brace</PERSON>, head of EDS, stressed that the figures are
subject to change.
   In addition to changes made after local officials assess the
preliminary figures, there is a chance that the final report could
be adjusted next <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   The bureau has been criticized for undercounting minorities in
the past and is conducting a post-census check on its count this
time. If officials determine that some group has been missed a
decision could be made to statistically adjust the final numbers.
   That ruling will be made by the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Commerce</ORGANIZATION> in
<DATE>mid-July 1991</DATE>.
   The national total was completed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> with the reports for
the final four states _ <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
   Census officials emphasize that the figures are provided to
allow local governments to question the results in the event people
were missed or overcounted.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891229-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-29-89 0234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Census-States     12-29 0355</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Census-States,340</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Census Figures Could Affect Reapportionment</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Census Bureau figures released today indicate
that seven states are likely to gain seats in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION> in reapportionment, while as many as a dozen states
will lose at least one seat, forecasters say.
   The next reapportionment will be based on the final <DATE>1990</DATE> Census
figures, which will be collected in the 10-year census next year.
The state population figures released <DATE>today</DATE> go up to mid-1989 and
represent one last checkpoint before the final, official count.
   The non-profit <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said that if the
trends in this latest report hold true through the final <DATE>1990</DATE>
figures, <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> will gain seven seats, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> each
will gain three, and <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>
will gain one apiece.
   At the same time, 11 states are likely to lose one or more
seats, the <ORGANIZATION>Population Reference Bureau</ORGANIZATION> said. It said <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> will
lose three seats, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> each
will lose two, and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kansas</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West
Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> each will lose one.
   Comparable predictions by <ORGANIZATION>Election Data Services Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a
Washington-based political consulting firm, differed little. The
firm, however, added <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION> to the list of losers, dropping one
congressional seat, and predicted that <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> will gain four
seats, rather than three.
   However, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> figures on which the predictions are
based do not include members of the military and their dependents
living overseas. They will be counted in the <DATE>1990</DATE> reapportionment,
the government recently announced, and that change could mean the
difference in whether some states gain or lose a seat.
   The Census figures show that the populations of five states grew
at rates faster than <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> <DATE>from 1985</DATE> to mid-1989.
   The state that experienced the largest percentage increase in
population between <DATE>1985</DATE> and mid-1989, <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION>, grew by <PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT>.
Second was <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>, followed by <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New
Hampshire</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> and <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> at <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   At the same time, seven states lost population, the bureau said:
<LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ861231-0154 </DOCNO>
<HL> Florida Population Grows
To Fifth-Largest in the U.S.</HL>
<DD> 12/31/86</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> eclipsed <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION> to become the nation's fifth-most-populous state during the year ended <DATE>July 1</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Census Bureau</ORGANIZATION> estimated. 

   <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s steady population gains have moved it from 10th place since <DATE>1960</DATE>. 
Texas is the only other state among the 10 biggest to move up significantly in the past 26 years; it rose to third from sixth place in <DATE>1960</DATE>, the census agency said. 
But three states -- <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nevada</LOCATION> -- have added residents at a faster clip than <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> since <DATE>1980</DATE>. 

   In 10 Farm and Energy Belt states, population losses occurred for the first time during the <DATE>1980s</DATE> or persisted from <DATE>1985</DATE> to <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
They are: <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>North Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>South Dakota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kentucky</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Oklahoma</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>. 

   The industrial Midwestern states, however, experienced increases in population from <DATE>1985 to 1986</DATE> as their economies continued rebounding, according to the report. 
