<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900331-0093 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-31-90 1547EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-IndianaTime 2ndLd-Writethru a0537 03-31 0627</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Indiana Time, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0537,0636</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indiana Deals With Patchwork of Time Zones</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 9th graf, `Seventy-six of...', to CORRECT that reference
is to Union City, Ind., sted Ohio.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BOB SEAVEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>INDIANAPOLIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>, where time zones can divide a
town, many people keep two reckonings of the hour to cope with
living in a ``time warp.''
   Hoosiers say the state's three time zones wreak havoc on
business and family life. At no time does the entire state follow
the same clock, creating timekeeping headaches from urban centers
to country hamlets.
   People live in one zone and work in another, children cross time
lines to and from school, prime time programming for televison is
complicated and meetings can be disrupted by delays, latecomers and
no-shows.
   One of three states exempted from the national time change _ the
others are <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION> _ <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> is the only one with
fragmented zones. A large portion is permanently on <ORGANIZATION>Eastern
Standard Time</ORGANIZATION>, while the rest observes either Central time or
<ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> time and changes twice a year like the other 47 states.
   ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> has the most complex time observance of any place in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' said <PERSON>Joanne Petrie</PERSON>, an attorney for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION>, the agency in charge of setting time
zones.
   Mayor <ORGANIZATION>John Ford of Union City</ORGANIZATION>, which is divided down the middle
by the Indiana-Ohio line, calls <DATE>Sunday</DATE>'s change to daylight-saving
time a ``time warp.''
   He said most residents of the portion of <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>
will experience the anxiety of being an hour late for something as
those on the <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> side of the line spring ahead. ``But they'll make
it up by being an hour early for something else,'' he said.
   ``The majority of people live the way it suits them, and in a
lot of places that involves keeping two different times in the same
househould,'' he said.
   Seventy-six of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>'s 92 counties _ including <LOCATION>Randolph
County</LOCATION>, in which <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, is located _ remain on <ORGANIZATION>Eastern
Standard Time</ORGANIZATION> as everyone else resets their clocks on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Eleven other counties observe Central time and, on schedule,
switch from CST to CDT as of <DATE>Sunday</DATE> _ meaning that for the next
five months, their clocks will look just like the <ORGANIZATION>EST</ORGANIZATION> counties'
clocks. Five other counties that are close to <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION> or
<LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> traditionally observe <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> time to remain in step
with those cities, switching as of <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to <ORGANIZATION>EDT</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>'s time zones are a compromise following years of local
and national debate. Officials say it's probably the best that can
be expected, though far from perfect.
   Prior to <DATE>1961</DATE>, the Indiana-Ohio line also divided the Central
and <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> time zones. The line was later shifted to bisect the
state and then re-shifted to create current time boundaries.
   ``There's some sort of truce right now,'' said <PERSON>Chuck Coffee</PERSON>, a
speechwriter for Lt. Gov. <PERSON>Frank O'Bannon</PERSON>. ``It was much different
when the population was dependent on rail service and waited as
trains came to town,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> balks at joining with the rest of the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> time zone
in observing daylight saving time, officials say, because it lies
on the western edge of the zone and already has a relatively late
sunrise. Daylight saving time would exacerbate that, much to the
displeasure of farmers who relish the early daylight hours for
field work.
   Simply going on Central time is opposed by many others who feel
<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> is more attuned to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and eastern cities and changing
would put it out of step the entire year.
   ``Why would someone think that they are traveling within the
same state and the time's going to change?'' said <PERSON>Carolyn
McClintock</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Vanderburgh County</LOCATION> commissioner.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890402-0009 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-02-89 2146EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-WhatTime?     04-02 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-What Time?,0603</SECOND>
<UNK>Does Anybody Really Know What Time It Is?</UNK>
<DATELINE>UNION CITY, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It will be another <DATE>summer</DATE> of confusion
in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, where the time of day is strictly a matter of
opinion.
   Residents of this city divided by the Indiana-Ohio state line
are victims of the time change that annually splits <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION> into
what residents call ``slow and fast time.''
   When daylight-saving time went into effect nationwide at <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>, most citizens of <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, went along. They are on
fast time.
   But those who live in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, stay on <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Standard
Time year-round</ORGANIZATION>, as do Hoosiers in 76 of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>'s 92 counties.
They are on slow time _ most of them.
   ``Most people have adjusted to it, but there's still
confusion,'' said <PERSON>Scott Stahl</PERSON>, mayor of <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Leroy Stentzil</PERSON>, a native of <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, has lived in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>,
since <DATE>1930</DATE> but still sets his clocks on <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> time. ``It's a
nuisance until you get used to it,'' <PERSON>Stentzil</PERSON> said.
   A few years ago, <PERSON>Stentzil</PERSON> had clocks in his house labeled
``Indiana Time'' or ``Ohio Time.''
   ``I don't do that anymore,'' he said. ``But it does cause
confusion. I've been late lots of times. Now if I'm invited to
something in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> and I don't think about it, I'm there an hour
early. I keep reading material in my side pocket all the time.''
   In fact, most <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, residents will experience the
anxiety of being an hour late for something during the coming
months, said <PERSON>John Ford</PERSON>, mayor of the <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> side of <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>.
``But they'll make up for it by being early for something else.''
   The time change affects families who work on one side of the
state line but live on the other and merchants who must cater to
customers on both times, <PERSON>Stahl</PERSON> said.
   ``In some instances there are stores that stay on slow time no
matter what,'' <PERSON>Stahl</PERSON> said. ``The <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> stores go on fast time. There
are some stores that might split it down the middle. It just gets
confusing.
   ``If they're normally open until 5 o'clock fast time, that would
be 4 o'clock slow time. So maybe they'll move it a half hour and
close at <TIME>5:30</TIME>. That way it would be 4:30 slow time.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> said most of the larger industries in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, run
on fast time despite being in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>. Those include <ORGANIZATION>Union City
Body Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which produces step vans, and <ORGANIZATION>Sheller-Globe Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which
makes auto trim.
   ``Most of the businesses in cities such as <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>
expect them to be following those hours,'' <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> said.
   However, <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ind.</LOCATION>, schools and government stay on slow
time. As a result, some parents are leaving for work while their
children are just beginning to prepare for school.
   ``Part of the people in <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> go on the <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION> time, just like I
do,'' <PERSON>Stentzil</PERSON> said. ``And part of them don't. I used to laughingly
say: `I don't care if they put ABCs on the clock. I'll get along.'
But I'm an old man now, and it just isn't so easy to adjust.''
   Stentzil said if <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> legislators lived in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>, they'd
think again about the wisdom of exempting <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> from
daylight-saving time.
   Exemptions from daylight-saving time are <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Puerto
Rico</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Virgin Islands</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>American Samoa</ORGANIZATION> and part of <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>,
according to The World Almanac. Daylight-saving time starts the
<DATE>first Sunday</DATE> in <DATE>April</DATE> and ends the <DATE>last Sunday</DATE> in <DATE>October</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900212-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-12-90 0917EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Kashmir 1stLd-Writethru a0484 02-12 0661</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Kashmir, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0484,0680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precede ISLAMABAD</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pakistani Troops Said To Fire On Indian Security Forces</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruout to UPDATE with Indian claim that Pakistanis
fired on Indian troops, details. Changes byline. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By VIJAY JOSHI</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pakistani troops fired on Indian
security forces who stopped a mob of Pakistani protesters from
storming across the border into disputed <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, officials said
<DATE>today</DATE>.
   At least three demonstrators were killed <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, a <ORGANIZATION>Defense
Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s state-run TV said
the Indian guards killed as many as six.
   The trouble started after Indian border guards opened fire on
hundreds of Pakistanis who tried to cross a cease-fire line
separating Pakistan-controlled <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> from the Indian-held region.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Indian Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> said Pakistani
troops then fired about 200 rounds from light and medium weapons at
Indian border posts in the <LOCATION>Uri</LOCATION> sector.
   Indian forces returned fire and the exchange continued for about
half an hour, the spokesman said. No one was hurt.
   A Pakistani official in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> denied the accusations.
   ``Pakistani military authorities and the Foreign Secretary are
in touch with Indian authorities to remove the misunderstanding,''
said Additional Foreign Secretary <PERSON>Khalid Mahmood</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s top diplomat in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bashir Babar</PERSON>, was summoned
to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Foreign Ministry</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and today and apprised of
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s concern over the events, an Indian government spokesman
said.
   A fluid 840-mile cease-fire line separates the Indian and
Pakistani Kashmirs. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and Indian twice have gone to war over
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1948</DATE> and again in <DATE>1965</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Feb. 5</DATE>, at least one person was killed and 12 wounded when
Pakistani mobs tried to cross the cease-fire line near <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION>, 95
miles to the south.
   The two demonstrations at the cease-fire line were to express
support for Moslem militants who are fighting for independence for
the Moslem-dominated state from the predominantly <LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, the Pakistani mob retreated when soldiers of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
paramilitary border security force opened fire, said the Indian
spokesman who refused to be identified.
   ``The mob returned a second time by which time it had become
slightly dark,'' he said. ``That is when the Pakistani troops
opened fire.''
   A Pakistani spokesman, who also refused to be identified, said
Pakistani army patrols repulsed a mob of some 1,200 demonstrators.
Small groups broke away from the crowd and slipped into the
Indian-held territory, he said.
   An official of the Indian border security force, which normally
patrols the border, said the Indian army <DATE>today</DATE> took control of the
cease-fire line.
   Some men in the intruding crowd were armed with guns which they
fired occasionally, he said.
   ``It was becoming very difficult, our troops had to open fire,''
he said.
   <PERSON>Farouk Haider</PERSON>, vice-president of the militant Jammu-Kashmir
Liberation Front that is leading the uprising, said in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>
after the Indian firing that ``the situation is very confusing.''
   Thirty-one people were wounded in the shooting, <PERSON>Haider</PERSON> said.
Five were in critical condition in a hospital in <LOCATION>Muzzafarabad</LOCATION>, the
capital of Pakistan-controlled <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, he said, adding he knew of
only one death.
   The 40-year-old conflict over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> flared <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> after a
government crackdown and the arrest of 250 suspected militants.
Most of them were subsequently released, but the arrests sparked
widespread violence.
   At least 85 people have been killed since the crackdown began.
Most of the victims have been curfew-breaking protesters shot by
security forces in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>.
   Srinagar, the <DATE>summer</DATE> capital of <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, has been the
center of the secessionist movement that has turned violent in
recent years.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION> had earlier campaigned for
union with <LOCATION>Islamic Pakistan</LOCATION> but has in recent years demanded
independence and the status of a neutral country.
   About <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>'s 6 million people are
Moslems, making it the only Moslem majority state in predominantly
<LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION>'s 25 states.
   Nationwide, Moslems make up <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million
population. Hindus comprise <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-13468 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drnes050_r_94004" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-NES-94-050 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  12 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> SOUTH ASIA </F>
<F P=101> India </F>
<H3> <TI>   `Top' Kashmiri Muslim Militant Arrested </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  BK1203150794 Hong Kong AFP in English 1357 GMT 12 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> BK1203150794 </F>
<F P=104>  Hong Kong AFP </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> [Report by Surinder Oberoi] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 12</DATE> (AFP) -- <PERSON>Javed Mir</PERSON>, the 
president of the <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION> and 
most-wanted Kashmiri Moslem militant, was arrested here <DATE>Saturday</DATE> 
[12 <DATE>March</DATE>], witnesses and <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> sources said. 
  Mir, 30, the former commander-in-chief of the guerrilla wing 
of the Moslem separatist group, was arrested along with another 
man when the car in which they were travelling was stopped by 
border guards, the witnesses said. 
  The pair were pulled out of the car and whisked away by the 
Indian paramilitary troops, they said. The other man, whose 
identity was not immediately known, was later released. 
  JKLF sources here confirmed the arrest of the <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> president 
but there was no immediate word from the Indian authorities. 
  The stocky and bearded Mir was one of the four founders of 
the Moslem separatist rebellion which began in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s only 
Moslem-majority state in <DATE>1989</DATE> and his arrest is seen as a major 
setback to the movement. 
  Of the other three architects of the armed struggle against 
Indian rule, two are dead and the third is in prison. Mir, who 
worked for the state waterworks department before picking up a 
gun, carried a reward of 50,000 rupees (<MONEY>1,666 dollars</MONEY>) on his 
head and topped the list of Kashmiri Moslem militants wanted by 
the Indian authorities. 
  A native of <LOCATION>Sringar</LOCATION>, Mir has been accused by the Indian 
authorities of singlehandedly carrying out several deadly 
attacks against Indian troops deployed in the northern state. 
  The outlawed <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> is the second most powerful Moslem 
separatist organization in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> after the <ORGANIZATION>Hizbul Mujahedeen</ORGANIZATION>, 
which favors a merger of the state with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. 
  Unlike the Hizbul and most other groups, the <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> seeks 
independence for the Himalayan territory. 
  Mir is the third top leader of the <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> to be arrested in 
the 
past fortnight and his arrest comes just a day after he made a 
surprise appearance at the main mosque in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> to deliver a 
speech from the pulpit. 
  Last week, Mir was among a group of Kashmiri Moslem leaders 
who met here with a team of 10 New Delhi-based diplomats who 
toured the strife-torn state. 
  More than 8,000 people have died in Moslem-separatist 
related 
violence in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> since <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
  <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, which holds the southern two-thirds of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, 
accuses <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, which controls the northern third, of arming 
and training the militants waging the fight against <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> rule. 
  Pakistan denies the charge but provides diplomatic support 
to 
a campaign which it describes as a legitimate struggle for 
self-determination. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900124-0162 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-24-90 1914EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     01-24 0554</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0575</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Officers Strike, Governor Urges Militants to Lay Down Arms</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> policemen went on
strike for five hours <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to support Moslem separatists's
demands that army troops called in to quell violence leave
Jammu-Kashmir state.
   Gov. <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON>, who uses only one name, appealed to the
separatists to lay down their arms on the fourth day of a crackdown
on the violent pro-Pakistani secessionist movement in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   At least 57 people, most of them protesters, have been killed
since an around-the-clock curfew was imposed <DATE>Saturday</DATE> on <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>
and surrounding towns.
   One Moslem militant was killed <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when paramilitary
forces, fearing an attack, fired on a mob, a senior police official
said on condition of anonymity.
   Jagmohan, who has a reputation as a tough administrator, was
appointed governor of Jammu-Kashmir state by Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P.
Singh</PERSON> two weeks ago in an effort to curb the rebellion, the most
serious crisis <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> has faced since he took office <DATE>Dec. 2</DATE>.
   The Islamic militants, led by the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu Kashmir Liberation
Front</ORGANIZATION>, demand either independence for the state or union with
neighboring Islamic <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   About <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>'s 5 million people are
Moslems. Nationwide, Moslems account for <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880
million people and Hindus make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT>.
   Singh, a <ORGANIZATION>Hindu</ORGANIZATION> like <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON>, has sent hundreds of troops from
the nation's predominantly <PERSON>Hindu</PERSON> army and paramilitary forces to
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   Ethnic tensions flared <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when a Moslem policeman was shot
to death by soldiers enforcing the curfew. Government officials
said the killing was an accident.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, hundreds of state policemen refused to
work. About 300 striking officers gathered on a downtown street,
waving rifles and shouting, ``Death to the Indian army!'' and
``Indians go back!''
   The strike was called off in the afternoon after <PERSON>Jitendra Narain
Saxena</PERSON>, the state's top police officer, and <PERSON>Mohammad A. Nomani</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>'s police inspector general, spoke to the protesting
policemen.
   Saxena later said: ``It appears that over the years, some
terrorist elements have infiltrated the state police force.''
   There are 40,000 men in the police force.
   Moslem residents of Srinager were jubilant over the strike and
many embraced officers when the curfew was lifted for an hour in
the morning.
   ``Policemen were resentful of certain things. The incident took
place due to lack of leadership and mismanagement,'' <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON> said
without elaborating.
   ``The issue has been sorted out. I do not think there is any
serious problem,'' he said.
   But one of the strike leaders, constable <PERSON>Mohammad Afzal</PERSON>, said
another walkout was planned for <DATE>Saturday</DATE> unless the soldiers leave
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and the government reinstates a police union banned in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   During the news conference, <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON> rejected suggestions by
some reporters that most Kashmiris wanted to secede and join
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   ``I have come here to help, to sort out the problems. Give me
some time. There is no magic in human affairs,'' he said.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has often accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of aiding separatists. Pakistan
denies the charge.
   Claimed by both <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> was divided into
Indian and Pakistani sectors by a cease-fire line that is monitored
by <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> military observers.
   The dispute over the territory, which has led to two wars, began
after <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> were partitioned upon gaining independence
from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900122-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-22-90 1000EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-India-Kashmir 2ndLd-Writethru a0508 01-22 0747</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India-Kashmir, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0508,0772</SECOND>
<HEAD>Indian Troops Police City After Clash With Moslems</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS thruoughout to UPDATE with 300 injured when soldiers
open fire on crowd, state police mutiny, comment from leader of
Kashmir state in Pakistan; no pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>BY DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem snipers fired at Indian troops
from rooftops today and at least two people were killed and 300
injured in clashes between soldiers and Islamic militants,
officials said.
   About 500 armed state policemen holed up in a police complex
after a confrontation with the army and refused to continue the
crackdown against the militants.
   ``The whole city is up in revolt,'' said <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> police
inspector general <PERSON>Mohammad Nomani</PERSON>.
   The Islamic militants, who want <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> state to become
independent or merge with neighboring <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, marched out of
homes and mosques in defiance of a curfew.
   Nomani said at least 40 people, most of them militants, had died
since the violence began <DATE>late Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, a
predominantly Moslem city.
   He said a paramilitary policeman was killed today by a Moslem
sniper, and one Moslem protester was shot to death by the army.
   At least 300 protesters were injured today when troops fired on
a crowd of about 5,000 in a suburb of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, doctors at the
<ORGANIZATION>Soora Hospital</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The doctors, speaking on condition of anonymity, said all beds
in the hospital were occupied and the cafeteria had been converted
into a makeshift hospital.
   <PERSON>Mohammad Aslam</PERSON>, a policeman in the state constabulary, said a
fellow officer was killed by army fire.
   When soldiers refused to hand over his body to the state police,
about 500 armed officers took up positions in residential quarters
of the police complex and refused to report for duty, <PERSON>Aslam</PERSON> said.
   State police said they could not confirm the officer's death and
refused further comment.
   <PERSON>Aslam</PERSON> said the army and the paramilitary <ORGANIZATION>Central Reserve Police
Force</ORGANIZATION> wanted to disarm the state police, most of whom are Moslems.
The army and the paramilitary forces are mostly Hindu.
   ``We are not slaves,'' he said as his colleagues chanted in the
background: ``Army go back.''
   Thousands of Moslems took to the streets starting shortly before
<TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE> after government security forces rounded up
suspected militants. The government said it acted to control
escalating violence.
   Nomani said 251 people had been detained in raids but that all
except four had been released in an attempt to stop the violence.
   He estimated the militants' strength at 1,500 and said they had
at least 1,000 weapons, mostly automatic rifles.
   The city of 1 million was placed under around-the-clock curfew,
with only military vehicles and troops permitted on the streets.
   But bands of 50 to 100 men ignored the curfew today; at least 50
streamed out of one mosque in downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. Some hurled stones
at the troops, while outhers beat their breasts and shouted: ``You
Indians go back.''
   Teen-age boys hauled out an Indian flag and shredded it in front
of the soldiers. As the stones continued to fly, the army opened
fire. One demonstrator fell to the street dead.
   Before the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, 26 people had been killed this year in
confrontations involving Moslem militants and security forces.
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> today, Foreign Minister <PERSON>Shabzada Yaqub Khan</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> conferred with Indian officials during a visit scheduled
before the latest violence.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has long accused Islamic Pakistan of supporting the
Kashmiri separatists, a charge routinely denied by <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   The old princely state of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> was divided between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> when the two countries were partitioned and became
independent from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> have gone to war three times since, the last
time in <DATE>1971</DATE>, but the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> frontier is still under dispute.
   <PERSON>Abdul Qayyum</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>Azad Kashmir</PERSON> state, told a
news conference in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, today that more violence
could spark thousands to cross the 840-mile border into <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   ``People are becoming deaf to reason and logic,'' he said.
   He said an alliance of nine political parties in
Pakistani-controlled <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> would lead a ``peaceful movement
across the cease-fire line'' if Indian troops continued what he
called a campaign to destroy militant secessionists.
   Jammu-Kashmir is the only Indian state with a Moslem majority.
Moslem militants, led by the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>, have
demanded independence for <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> or union with <LOCATION>Moslem Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   Sixty-four percent of <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>'s 5 million people are
Moslems, but nationwide Moslems make up only <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
880 million people.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900203-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-03-90 1517EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India-Kashmir     02-03 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0522</SECOND>
<HEAD>Strike Called by Militants Paralyzes Kashmir</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto KAP1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> lifted curfew
restrictions for 12 hours, but shops remained closed and few people
ventured out because of a strike called by Moslem separatists,
witnesses said.
   A bomb went off in the city during the relaxation, but a senior
were no casualties.
   No other violence was reported.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION> spread a strike call by word
of mouth on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and <DATE>early Saturday</DATE>, local journalists
said, quoting shopkeepers in downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> and its suburbs.
   The front is spearheading a four-decade-old campaign for
secession of Jammu-Kashmir state's predominantly Moslem Kashmir
valley from Hindu-majority <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Srinagar, the state's summer
capital, is the largest city in the valley.
   At least 76 people have been killed since the government
launched a crackdown on the secessionist movement on <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> and
imposed around-the-clock curfews. Most of those killed were
curfew-violating Moslems shot by the security forces.
   The government reported no deaths between <DATE>Jan. 25</DATE> and <DATE>Friday</DATE>,
when at least four people were killed. Three of them died when
paramilitary police opened fire on a mob defying curfew in the
nearby city of <LOCATION>Sopore</LOCATION>, police officials said. The fourth was a
Hindu shopkeeper who was shot by militants in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>.
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s strike in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> was to protest the <LOCATION>Sopore</LOCATION> deaths,
<PERSON>Kaiser Mirza</PERSON>, a local journalist, quoted shopkeepers as saying. The
curfew relaxation began at <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME> and ended at <TIME>5 p.m.</TIME>
   <LOCATION>Mirza</LOCATION> said most shops did not open in the <TIME>morning</TIME> when curfew
was lifted, and a few shops that did open soon put down their
shutters when owners learned of the strike call.
   It was not immediately clear if the shops were closed fearing
attacks by the militants or to sympathize with the separatist cause.
   During earlier curfew relaxations, which began one week ago,
vegetable shops and groceries were crowded and streets were filled
with people and traffic. On <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, small groups of men
stood at street corners but there was little traffic, <PERSON>Mirza</PERSON> said.
   The Moslem militancy dates to <DATE>1947</DATE> when <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> were
partitioned on religious lines after gaining independence from
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. The king of mostly <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> chose union with
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> instead of Islamic <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   Moslem militants initially began agitating for union with
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> but in recent months have been demanding independence
instead.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of fomenting the trouble in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>,
a charge <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> denies.
   The two countries have fought three wars, two of them over
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   The wars have left a slice of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> under <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s control
and a U.N.-supervised cease-fire line divides the valley into
Indian and Pakistani sectors.
   The Indian state of <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, which comprises the valley
and the plains of <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> to the south, is the country's only
Moslem-majority state. At least <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of its 5 million people
follow Islam.
   Nationwide, Moslems account for <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the 880 million
population.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900126-0168 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-26-90 2013EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir 1stLd-Writethru a0641 01-26 0758</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0641,0777</SECOND>
<HEAD>Troops Search House-to-House for Separatist Moslems</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 5 grafs to include new details; picks up 5th `In
Muzaffarabad,' SUBBING 11th `Indian state' to UPDATE casualties</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Troops searched from house to house
<DATE>Friday</DATE> for pro-Pakistan Moslems waging a violent separatist
campaign in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, and the government imposed a virtual news
blackout.
   At least 70 people, most of them Moslem militants, have been
killed since the government began a crackdown <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to try to
halt separatist violence.
   Witnesses in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, <DATE>summer</DATE> capital of Jammu-Kashmir state,
said soldiers and paramilitary commandos of the elite <ORGANIZATION>National
Security Guard</ORGANIZATION> were searching the city. Similar searches were
reported in the nearby towns of <LOCATION>Anantnag</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Baramulla</LOCATION>.
   Many residents of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> refused to switch on lights after
dusk in protest of the crackdown.
   Journalists were confined to a hotel and told they would be
arrested, or even shot, if they stepped outside. They were denied
access to telex and telephone lines after the warning.
   In <LOCATION>Muzaffarabad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, Premier <PERSON>Sikander Hyat Khan</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Pakistani Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> said he would launch a Moslem ``holy war'' unless
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> schedules a special session to address the
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue.
   Muzaffarabad is the capital of <LOCATION>Pakistani Kashmir</LOCATION> and near the
cease-fire that has divided the region between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>
since <DATE>1947</DATE>, when the subcontinent became independent of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and
the two nations were created. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> have fought four
wars, three of them specifically over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   Most of the 5 million people in the <ORGANIZATION>Indian State of
Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> are Moslems. It is the only state with a Moslem
majority in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, a predominantly Hindu nation.
   ``If the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> is not ready to play its role ... I will
tell them to go and fight,'' <PERSON>Khan</PERSON> warned of the people in <LOCATION>Pakistani
Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   He gave the world organization until <DATE>Feb. 17</DATE> to schedule a
special session. He said the deadline coincided with a scheduled
meeting all Pakistani political and religious parties in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Tariq Mahmood Butt</PERSON>, head of the student wing of the militant
<ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>, said thousands of its members would
cross the frontier <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE> if the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> did not promise
action.
   Indian state television described the situation in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>
as ``by and large peaceful,'' but said paramilitary troops fired on
rioters <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Handwara</LOCATION>, 40 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. A
government spokesman, speaking on condition of anonymity, said 11
people were killed and 14 wounded.
   Troops in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> tightened restrictions under the 24-hour
curfew and prevented residents from opening windows, said witnesses
reached by telephone.
   From various vantage points in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, a city of 1 million,
only heavily armed troopers and an occasional government official
could be seen on the streets. Several people reached by telephone
from inside and outside <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> said they had not heard gunfire.
   Police sources in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION>, winter capital of the state, said
militants hurled a gasoline bomb at soldiers during house searches
but no one was injured.
   The increased security coincided with the Moslem sabbath and
<ORGANIZATION>Republic Day</ORGANIZATION>, which major towns and cities in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> usually
celebrate with military parades.
   Moslem separatists in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, who want the state to be
either independent or joined to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, declared the national
holiday a ``black day.''
   Television showed <PERSON>Jameel Qureshi</PERSON>, adviser to the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>
state governor, taking the salute at a parade in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Bakshi
Stadium</LOCATION>. No civilian spectators were shown and a policeman who was
there said none attended.
   District magistrate <PERSON>Ghulam Abbas</PERSON> told about 20 journalists at
the Hotel Broadway: ``If you go out of the hotel, you can be shot,
and if we find out you have gone out, you can be imprisoned for six
months.''
   Soldiers with submachine guns were posted around the hotel,
which is about a mile from downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. The door leading to
the roof of the five-story building was locked and telephone
service was halted after the warning by <PERSON>Abbas</PERSON>.
   Seven journalists returned to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on a commercial flight
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. They said police took them to the <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>
airport by a circuitous route one officer said was designed to
skirt trouble. Police at the airport confiscated dozens of rolls of
film, they said.
   The Moslem separatist campaign is as old as the two nations, but
has escalated in recent weeks.
   Srinagar and surrounding towns were put under 24-hour curfew
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and soldiers and paramilitary troopers were deployed.
Their number has not been released, but is known to be at least in
the hundreds.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900411-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-11-90 1000EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-India-Kashmir 2ndLd-Writethru   04-11 0718</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India-Kashmir, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0498,0738</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two More Kidnap Victims Killed, Train Bombed; Troops To Srinagar</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 5th graf, `The group...' with 2 grafs to UPDATE with
five bombs found in another Bombay suburb. Pickup 6th graf `The
New...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By QAISER MIRZA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Militant Moslem separatists escalated
their campaign for an independent <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, killing two more
hostages in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> and bombing a crowded commuter train near
<LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> today, police said.
   About 1,000 troops in battle gear were trucked into <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>,
the center of the secessionist campaign in the mostly Moslem
northern state bordering <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   The bodies of the two hostages were found <TIME>late Tuesday night</TIME>,
several hours after the body of another hostage was dumped near a
<LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> fire station. Their killings brought to at least 259 the
number of people killed in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> since a government crackdown in
<DATE>January</DATE>.
   Telephone callers purporting to speak for the ``Mujahedeen
Kashmir,'' or Islamic Holy Warriors of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, claimed
responsibility for the bombing today that injured 34 people near
the <LOCATION>Malad</LOCATION> station on the outskirts of <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>United News of India</ORGANIZATION>
reported.
   Later today, police said they found five crude bombs hidden in a
water tank in another <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> suburb. It was not immediately known
whether the discoveries were connected with the train bombing.
   The <PERSON>Mujahedeen Kashmir</PERSON> was first heard of <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when it
claimed responsibility for bomb blasts that injured at least nine
policemen in two <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> police stations.
   The <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bombay</LOCATION> bombings were the first time any
Kashmiri separatists had claimed responsibility for attacks outside
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> since the government of predominantly <ORGANIZATION>Hindu India</ORGANIZATION> launched
a crackdown on the Moslem secessionists <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>.
   Police found the bodies of the vice chancellor of <ORGANIZATION>Kashmir
University</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Mushir Ul-Haq</PERSON>, and his secretary, <PERSON>Abdul Ghani</PERSON>, dumped
on a road near the city's airport late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the police official
said.
   Both men, who were Moslems, had been shot in the back.
   Earlier <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, the body of <ORGANIZATION>L.M. Khera</ORGANIZATION>, a Hindu industrialist,
was discovered with five bullet wounds.
   ``The dastardly murders ... are the grossest violations of human
rights where innocent persons are being made victims of senseless
externally inspired and motivated violence,'' Foreign Ministry
spokesman <PERSON>Aftab Seth</PERSON> told reporters in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>.
   All three were kidnapped <DATE>Friday</DATE> and threatened with execution if
three top militants were not released. They were the first
civilians not accused of being police informers to be killed by
militants.
   The government had refused to negotiate. It imposed an
around-the-clock curfew after the kidnappings and detained between
300 and 400 people it suspected of links with the secessionist
movement.
   The killings triggered an even tighter crackdown on the
secessionists.
   About 100 Indian army trucks carrying an estimated 1,000
soldiers were seen moving into <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> today. The state government
ordered local police and civilians holding curfew passes to stay
off the streets until further notice, said a senior police official
who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   In <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> dozens of members of a Hindu militant group, the
<ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Army</ORGANIZATION>, marched to the <ORGANIZATION>Pakistan Embassy</ORGANIZATION> and
held a demonstration.
   ``We will crush <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>,'' shouted the demonstrators, who were
prevented from reaching the embassy gate by police.
   The group was formed in <DATE>March</DATE> to counter the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem
Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>, which is leading the secessionist
campaign.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>V.P. Singh</PERSON>, in the most aggressive statement yet
by an Indian leader, said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> should be
``psychologically prepared'' for an armed conflict with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>
over what he called the Islamic nation's territorial ambitions in
the <LOCATION>Kashmir Valley</LOCATION>.
   Singh made the comments in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> hours after <PERSON>Khera</PERSON>'s body
was found. He accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of fomenting the insurgency in the
northern state of Jammu-Kashmir and could ``make a limited
intervention.''
   Pakistan ``will not get away with it,'' <PERSON>Singh</PERSON> said. ``You will
have to pay a very heavy price and we have the capability to
inflict this cost.''
   Moslem-dominated <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> is a former princely state whose Hindu
ruler opted for union with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE> when the subcontinent was
divided into Hindu-majority <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Islamic Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> fought wars over the region in <DATE>1948</DATE> and <DATE>1965</DATE>.
A U.N.-monitored cease-fire line separates the valley into Indian
and Pakistani sectors. The two countries also fought a war in <DATE>1971</DATE>
that led to the independence of <LOCATION>Bangladesh</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-2908</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EFQDGAB2FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940617
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  17 JUN 94 / No peace yet in troubled Kashmir: Kidnappings highlight
unrest in spite of fragile gains
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By STEFAN WAGSTYL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
The kidnapping of two British tourists by separatist militants in the
northern Indian state of <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> highlights how far this troubled
region still is from peace.
Over the <DATE>last 12 months</DATE>, the Indian authorities have tried to create the
impression that the violence which has hit <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> in the past four years is
being brought under control. They were so successful that tourists started
coming back this year: owners of hotels, houseboats and handicraft shops
thought their trade could at last see a revival.
The kidnapping has put in jeopardy this fragile gain in confidence. It is
now 11 days since <PERSON>Mr David Mackie</PERSON>, aged 36, and 16-year-old <PERSON>Kim Housego</PERSON>, son
of <PERSON>Mr David Housego</PERSON>, a former <ORGANIZATION>Financial Times</ORGANIZATION> staff correspondent, were
captured while on trekking holidays with their families.
The incident has exposed the fact that despite considerable advances in
suppressing militants in the capital city of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> and the surrounding
valley, the Indian security forces are far from crushing the separatist
fighters.
Even the government's own figures show violence remains widespread. In the
<DATE>five months to the end of May</DATE>, the death toll was broadly the same as for
the same months last year - 501 militants, 85 members of the security
forces, and 420 civilians (killed in militant attacks or in crossfire.) A
further 139 people were kidnapped. Altogether nearly 10,000 have died since
the fighting broke out in <DATE>1990</DATE>, according to official statistics. The
militants put the total at more than 20,000.
This is not to say the authorities have made no progress in the past year.
The security forces have killed or captured several top militant leaders and
disrupted lines linking militants with their sources of supply in
neighbouring <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
Delhi scored a considerable coup last <DATE>November</DATE> by bringing to a peaceful end
a month-long siege of the Hazratbal mosque, the holiest Moslem shrine in
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
'In <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> at least the improvement is palpable,' says a senior official
of the <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> state government.
But even in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, life is far from normal. The paramilitary <ORGANIZATION>Border
Security Force</ORGANIZATION> patrols the streets and maintains sand-bagged bunkers. 'If
<LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> seems quiet it is because we have adjusted to life under
occupation, not that we have accepted it,' says <PERSON>Mr Abdul Ghani</PERSON>, a
representative of the <ORGANIZATION>All Party Freedom Conference</ORGANIZATION>, an umbrella organisation
of Kashmiri political groups, some of which demand independence and others
union with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
Moreover, while violence has declined in the Moslem heartland of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>
and the surrounding valley it has increased elsewhere - notably in the
southern districts with mixed Moslem/Hindu populations, including the hilly
<LOCATION>Doda</LOCATION> area, where militants recently assassinated two local leaders of the
right-wing Hindu Bharatiya Janata party.
There is also a shift in the balance of power among the militants, with
groups linked to the <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>, the
pro-independence political organisation, losing ground to radical
pro-Pakistan Islamic groups.
They see the battle against <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> as a jihad - a holy war. Supplied with
arms from within <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and strengthened by the presence of small numbers
of Afghan and other battle-hardened Moslem fighters, these groups have
challenged the traditional dominance of the <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION>. Among these radicals
organisations is Harkat-ul-Ansar, which captured the two Britons.
The <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> seems unsure how to react. Some leaders want no compromises, others
appear to be putting out feelers to the Indian government, among them <PERSON>Mr
Yasin Malik</PERSON>, who was released from prison a month ago and promptly appealed
publicly for talks.
It is hard to see how the government can respond if the <ORGANIZATION>JKLF</ORGANIZATION> sticks to
demands for independence. But if it does nothing, it could miss a valuable
opportunity to create a point of contact with the militant movement. There
may not be much time - pro-Pakistan militants tried to shoot <PERSON>Mr Malik</PERSON>
<DATE>earlier this month</DATE> and could try again.
Delhi is aware that the longer the fighting goes on, the more the
pro-Pakistan Islamic groups are likely to gain ground, notably
Hizb-ul-Mujahideen, the biggest and most active organisation. <PERSON>Mr Rajesh
Pilot</PERSON>, the minister responsible for <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, has said repeatedly that he
wants to start a 'political process', meaning talks with Kashmiri groups,
followed by state-level elections and possibly an increase in autonomy from
<LOCATION>Delhi</LOCATION>.
'I feel there is more chance of the political process starting now than at
any time in the past two years,' he says.
But for most Kashmiri activists, hints of increased autonomy are worthless.
<PERSON>Mr Ghani</PERSON> says: 'If we don't leave <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, all this violence will have been
for nothing.'
Yesterday <PERSON>Mr Housego</PERSON> returned to <LOCATION>Pahalgam</LOCATION>, the area of the kidnapping, with
a group of journalists, in a move to encourage the kidnappers, who are
apparently nervous about the presence of Indian security forces, to release
their captives. If he succeeds it will at least remove one point of tension
in the troubled state.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>INZ  India, Asia.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9229 Public Order and Safety, NEC.
    P9721 International Affairs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 7
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900207-0106 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-07-90 1222EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     02-07 0402</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Two Reported Killed in Kashmir Violence</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Indian paramilitary troops shot and
killed two innocent bystanders <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> after Moslem militants
bombed a shopping center in this <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> city, witnesses said.
   The deaths were reported in the <LOCATION>Lal Chowk</LOCATION> area, where witnesses
said <ORGANIZATION>Border Security Force</ORGANIZATION> soldiers fired into a crowd after
militants campaigning for an independent <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> bombed the
three-story shopping complex.
   The victims, a Moslem and a Hindu, were businessmen who were
caught in the paramilitary gunfire, said witnesses and a man who
identified himself as the father of the Moslem.
   The deaths occurred in the <LOCATION>Lal Chowk</LOCATION> area of downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>.
The witnesses said Moslems campaigning for independence for the
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> region bombed a three-story shopping center and that <ORGANIZATION>Border
Security Force</ORGANIZATION> soldiers opened fire on a mob.
   ``My son was closing the shop after the trouble started when
suddenly the <ORGANIZATION>BSF</ORGANIZATION> came and opened fire,'' said <PERSON>Mohammad Yusuf</PERSON>, whose
son, <PERSON>Shabir Yousuf</PERSON>, was reported killed.
   The government refused to either confirm or deny the deaths. The
state-run local radio said the shopping complex caught fire after a
cooking-gas cylinder exploded inside the building. The radio,
monitored in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, made no mention of paramilitary gunfire or
deaths.
   Also <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, at least six policemen and two bystanders were
injured when militants attacked a police bunker with a grenade in
downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, said witnesses who spoke on condition of
anonymity.
   In another part of the city, a bomb believed planted by
militants exploded in a post office. There were no injuries,
witnesses said.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, suspected militants blew up a truck, injuring
one person who was sleeping in the vehicle, witnesses said.
   At least 79 people have been killed since <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> when Indian
authorities began a crackdown on the Moslem secessionist movement
in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, a part of Jammu-Kashmir state. Jammu-Kashmir is the
only Indian state with a majority Moslem population, and militants
support either independence or unity with neighboring <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>,
which is mainly Moslem.
   Most of those killed have been shot for defying curfews.
   Srinagar is the largest city in the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> valley and is the
<DATE>summer</DATE> capital of Jammu-Kashmir state. The city of <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> is the
winter capital.
   In <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION>, about 200 Moslem state government employees
demonstrated <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> demanding that they be taken to <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>,
witnesses said. The demonstrators chanted anti-Indian slogans and
claimed that their lives were in danger in Hindu-dominated <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900429-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-90 1121EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-Kashmir     04-29 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-Kashmir,0590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pakistan Accuses India of Sabre-Rattling</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SHARON HERBAUGH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated press writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> dismissed
allegations of interference in <LOCATION>Indian-held Kashmir</LOCATION> as false and
untenable and accused <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> of ``whipping up a war psychosis and
indulging in sabre-rattling.''
   But the No. 2-ranking defense official said a hot-line between
senior military commanders of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> remains open and
the tense situation between the uneasy neighbors ``is gradually
moving toward normalcy.''
   The remarks by a foreign ministry spokesman and the deputy
defense minister Col. <PERSON>Ghulam Sarwar Cheema</PERSON> were in response to
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s latest charges <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is arming and training Moslem
separatists in Indian-controlled <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   ``No amount of sophistry can hide the fact that the insurrection
there is totally indigenous,'' the foreign ministry spokesman said.
``The root of the insurrection is the continued denial of the right
of self-determination of the people in Indian-occupied <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.''
   The spokesman, who cannot be identified under briefing rules,
said <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> was ``deeply disappointed'' by the ``false
allegations and untenable assertions'' made <DATE>Saturday</DATE> by the Indian
government.
   <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> warned <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> it would not tolerate infringement of
its sovereignty in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, and a government spokesman refused to
rule out cross-border raids to eliminate suspected guerrilla camps.
   ``There will be no compromise on the measures necessary to
protect our integrity,'' the Indian government said in a statement.
   The foreign ministry spokesman said <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> regrets <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> ``has
persisted in its belicose statements after the foreign minister of
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> three days ago agreed with his <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>
counterpart to exercise restraint.''
   More than 300 people have been killed in <LOCATION>Indian-held Kashmir</LOCATION>
since <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> when Indian troops launched their latest and harshest
crackdown on Moslem separatists. Most were Moslem militants or
supporters shot by Indian troops during anti-India demonstrations
or while defying curfews.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> regularly accuses <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of arming, training and
financing the Kashmiri militants who want to secede from mostly
<LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION> and become an independent nation with neutral status.
Islamabad routinely denies the allegations, but says it supports
the Kashmiris right to self-determination.
   ``Instead of whipping up a war psychosis and indulging in
sabre-rattling, we hope <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> will align its position to the
position of the international community, which stands for the
peaceful settlement of the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> dispute,'' the foreign ministry
spokesman said.
   As violence by Moslem militants escalated, both countries
reinforced their troops along the border and the contested <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>
frontier. Each side has repeatedly said it does not want war but
has accused the other of fomenting a climate that could lead to
armed confrontation.
   <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> has repeatedly denied allegations of abuse and torture
by Indian troops in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> have fought two wars over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, which is
divided by a cease-fire line monitored by the united nations.
   Kashmir was a princely state when <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> were
partitioned along religious lines into separate nations. Most of
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>'s residents were Moslems, but the ruler was a Hindu who
opted for union with <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   Pakistan moved into the northern third of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>. The rest came
under Indian control as part of the state of <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, the
only Moslem state in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   ``<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> does not want another war and no saner elements _
either in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> _ will support war,'' <PERSON>Cheema</PERSON> told
reporters in <LOCATION>Rawalpindi</LOCATION>.
   ``The hot-line is still open between the senior military
commanders of the two countries and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> is taking all steps to
reduce tension.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900124-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-24-90 0701EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-India-Kashmir 1stLd-Writethru a0488 01-24 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-India-Kashmir, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0488,0732</SECOND>
<HEAD>Police Protest Army's Presence, Refuse to Work</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with strikers to return to work.
Picks up 3rd pvs, `At least...' SUBS grafs 9-10, `Hitendra
Narain...' with 2 grafs of details. Pick up 11th pvs, `Simmering
tension...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hundreds of policemen waving rifles and
shouting ``Death to the Indian army'' refused to work <DATE>today</DATE>,
hampering government efforts to halt a violent Moslem separatist
movement in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   By mid-afternoon the strikers agreed to go back to work, a
police official and a strike leader said.
   At least 57 people, mostly Moslem militants, have been killed
since the government on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> launched a crackdown on militant
secessionists who want to become independent or merge with <LOCATION>Moslem
Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   Jammu-Kashmir is the only Moslem-dominated state in
predominantly <LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION>. About <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of the mountainous
northern state's 5 million people are Moslems.
   One death was reported today. A Moslem militant was killed when
paramilitary forces, fearing imminent attack, opened fire on a mob,
   The striking policemen, many in the brown uniforms of the state
constabulary, stopped police vehicles in the streets and urged
their colleagues to join the protest.
   Head Constable <PERSON>Mohammad Iqbal</PERSON>, one of the striking policemen,
said at least a third of the 40,000-man force had refused to report
for duty to protest the deployment of the Indian army to control
the agitation.
   ``This is the beginning of a new chapter in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>,'' he said.
``We have been driven to the wall so we are reacting.''
   A total of about 1,000 policemen were seen in three separate
groups stopping cars driven by other policemen. One group of about
300 shouted: ``Death to the Indian army'' and ``Indians go back.''
   Hitendra <PERSON>Narain Saxena</PERSON>, the top police official in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>
state, said at mid-afternoon that the strikers had agreed to return
to work.
   One of the strike leaders, constable <PERSON>Mohammad Afzal</PERSON>, said the
strike had been postponed until <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Simmering tension between <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> police and federal troops
flared <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after a policeman was shot and killed by soldiers
enforcing an around-the-clock curfew in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. Officers in
<LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> and a senior government spokesman in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> said the
killing was an accident.
   The striking policemen did not openly express support for the
escalating Moslem secessionist movement but one said: ``The
government calls us terrorists. If that is the case, why should we
fire at our own people ?''
   He spoke on condition of anonymity.
   About 300 protesting policeman marched to police headquarters.
   ``They (the government) call us Pakistani dogs. We are not ...
Let the Indian army and others know we will smash them if they
confront us,'' constable <PERSON>Mohammad Afzal</PERSON> told the crowd.
   Srinagar's police inspector general, <PERSON>Mohammad Azhar Nomani</PERSON>,
appealed to the men to return to duty and to come to him with any
grievances.
   Climbing atop his jeep, <PERSON>Nomani</PERSON> told the crowd: ``Don't get
agitated. Don't get provoked.''
   Afzal said the strikers had two demands: that the army and other
federal troops leave <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and the government re-instate a police
union dissolved in <DATE>1979</DATE>.
   Authorities said federal troops were patrolling the city but, to
avoid confrontation, had been ordered not to leave their vehicles.
   An around-the-clock curfew confining people to their homes was
lifted temporarily <TIME>this morning</TIME>. It had been scheduled to be lifted
for four hours but was restored after just one hour because of the
police situation, a government official said, speaking on condition
of anonymity.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> repeated charges that <LOCATION>Islamic Pakistan</LOCATION> was
fomenting trouble in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, but <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> again denied the charge.
   The two countries have a history of animosity and have fought
three wars, two of them over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, since they gained
independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>. The last war was in <DATE>1971</DATE>.
   A cease-fire line dividing <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> into Indian and Pakistani
sectors is monitored by <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> military observers.
   Nationwide, Moslems form <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s 880 million
peoeple and Hindus make up <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT>.
   Srinagar, the largest city in the <LOCATION>Kashmir Valley</LOCATION>, is the <DATE>summer</DATE>
capital of Jammu-Kashmir state. The <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> region is mostly
Moslem, while the southern <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> region is predominantly Hindu.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900130-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-30-90 1219EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     01-30 0467</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0483</SECOND>
<HEAD>Curfew Lifted for 8 Hours; One Violent Incident Reported</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The government lifted curfew in this
violence-torn <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> city for eight hours <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, giving
residents their longest taste of freedom in 10 days.
   At least one incident of violence was reported. Witnesses said
Moslem militants agitating for independence shot another Moslem,
claiming he was helping the Indian government in its crackdown on
the secessionist movement.
   The 23-year-old man, identified only as <PERSON>Kauser</PERSON>, was taken to a
hospital, said the witnesses, who spoke on condition of anonymity.
His condition was not known.
   Other witnesses said about 5,000 people demonstrated during the
curfew relaxation to protest the alleged entry by paramilitary
policemen into a mosque. There was no violence, said the witnesses
who also spoke on condition of anonymity.
   Meanwhile, municipal workers removed hundreds of garbage cans
piled on streets and grocers sold fresh fruit for the first time
since the curfew was imposed in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> after clashes
between security forces and Moslem separatists.
   The Moslem militants demand either independence for <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> or
unity with <LOCATION>Moslem Pakistan</LOCATION>. Kashmir is a part of the state of
<LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, the only Indian state with a majority Moslem
population. Most Indians are Hindus.
   Srinagar, the state's summer capital and once a popular holiday
retreat, is the flashpoint of the Kashmiri movement.
   At least 72 people, mostly Moslem males, have been killed in
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> since <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>. The state government said <DATE>Monday</DATE> there had
been no violence for the previous four days.
   The curfew was lifted for seven hours <DATE>Monday</DATE>, and that was
extended to eight hours <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> have fought two wars over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> since they
were partitioned in <DATE>1947</DATE> upon gaining independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
The state is divided into Pakistani and Indian sectors by a
U.N.-monitored line of control.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> accuses neighboring <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of aiding the Kashmiri
militants, a charge that has been routinely denied. But <PERSON>Paskistan</PERSON>
says it supports the separatism, describing it as a movement for
self-determination.
   Pakistani Foreign Minister <PERSON>Sahabzada Yaqub Khan</PERSON> called <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
for <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to allow the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> dispute to be decided in a popular
vote.
   ``It is an outstanding issue which is to be resolved through a
plebiscite under the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> supervision,'' he said in a
nationally televised speech.
   ``The Indian government is trying to suppress the freedom
movement in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> through atrocities, resulting in deaths of
hundreds of Kashmiris and injuries to many more,'' <PERSON>Yaqub Khan</PERSON> said.
   The Indian crackdown began after Moslem militants stepped up
attacks on the government, burning state-owned buildings,
assassinating at least three intelligence agents and kidnapping the
daughter of a Cabinet minister in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   She was released after the government freed five jailed members
of the pro-independence <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900413-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-13-90 1958EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     04-13 0350</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0363</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Militants Kidnap Former Deputy, 2 Killed</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem militants on <DATE>Friday</DATE> kidnapped a
former member of the state legislature and Indian security forces
killed two Moslem demonstrators in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, news reports said.
   At least 269 people have been killed since a government
crackdown of Moslem separatists began in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>. Most
of the victims were Moslem militants and their supporters who died
in clashes with the security forces or while defying curfew.
   Government troops intensified patrols after the former <ORGANIZATION>Congress
Party</ORGANIZATION> lawmaker, <PERSON>Amirullah Khan</PERSON>, was kidnapped by militants from his
home in <LOCATION>Shopian</LOCATION>, 37 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, a senior police
official said.
   Earlier this week, Moslem secessionists in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> abducted and
killed three hostages, including a prominent educator.
   The kidnappers were demanding the freedom of three of their
jailed comrades.
   Indian troops shot and killed two Moslem demonstrators at
<LOCATION>Bhaderwah</LOCATION>, 120 miles north of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, after they attempted to
lead a procession following Moslem <DATE>Friday</DATE> prayers, officials said.
   On <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, gunfire broke out along the tense frontier of
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and one Indian soldier and five Pakistani troops were
killed, the New Delhi-based <ORGANIZATION>United News of India</ORGANIZATION> reported.
   In <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>, a spokesman for <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s defense ministry said
he had no information of the shootout or any Pakistani casualties.
   ``There were no casualties on our side,'' said the spokesman,
who spoke on condition of anonymity.
   But he added: ``Firing along the cease-fire line is a normal
phenomena. It happens almost every day.''
   The unresolved fate of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> dates back to <DATE>1947</DATE> when Indian
and <LOCATION>Moslem Pakistan</LOCATION> were partitioned along religious lines. The old
princely state of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> was predominantly Moslem, but its Hindu
ruler opted to join <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Today the <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> region is divided
between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> along a disputed frontier and has twice
been the cause of war between them.
   The Indian part of <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION> is the only state in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> with
a Moslem majority. Nationwide, Hindus form <PERCENT>82 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
880 million people, while Moslems comprise <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of fomenting the secessionist
violence in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900211-0044 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-11-90 1630EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Pakistan-India     02-11 0504</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pakistan-India,0519</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pakistan Reports Shooting Along Indian Border</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KATHY GANNON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ISLAMABAD, Pakistan (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   About 1,000 demonstrators tried to
surge across a cease-fire line into Indian-held <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
and state-run television said Indian forces opened fire, killing
six people.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> army patrols turned
back most of the protesters but that small groups slipped into
Indian-held territory. He said only three people were killed and
four wounded.
   The incident occurred near a small village of <LOCATION>Chaukoti</LOCATION>, about
100 miles north of <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>. It came as <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is cracking down on
Moslem militants conducting a violent secessionist campaign in
<LOCATION>Indian-held Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> have fought two wars over the region. A
portion of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> valley is under Pakistani control, and an
840-mile cease-fire line monitored by the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> separates
Pakistani and Indian troops.
   The <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> region is predominantly Moslem, while <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> is
mostly Hindu.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> again accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> of aiding the Moslem
secessionist campaign centered in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, where a curfew
remained in effect <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> has accused <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> of ``ruthlessness'' in suppressing
the secessionists and of trying to divert international attention
by blaming <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> for what it has called an ``indiginous freedom
movement.''
   Pakistan television reported <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that Indian border guards
killed six people and arrested four. The television quoted the
prime minister of Pakistan-held <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Sikander Hayat Khan</PERSON> in its
report.
   Press Trust of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> said Indian border guards fired in the air
first, then into the crowd when it continued to surge forward. The
Indian report, which quoted an unidentified Indian government
spokesman, did not mention casualties.
   The Pakistani ministry spokesman, who requested anonymity, said
his nation's soldiers repulsed all but a few small groups of the
demonstrators.
   ``We and the Indians are very clear that this is a local
trouble. It's very difficult to blame anyone, whether they fired in
self-defense or not,'' he said of the Indian border guards.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s High Commissioner to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, <PERSON>J.N. Dixit</PERSON>, told <ORGANIZATION>The
Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> he had not heard of any disturbance along the
cease-fire line.
   ``This is news to me. I have no information,'' he said. ``I
would have heard at least one or two hours after it happened.''
   <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s state-run news agency said <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> asked <PERSON>Dixit</PERSON> ``to
convey a sense of shock to the Indian authorities in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> and
also impress upon them the need to exercise utmost restraint in
dealing with armed civilians.''
   The demonstration at the border was one of many in <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> marking the sixth anniversary of the death of <PERSON>Maqbool Butt</PERSON>,
a militant <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> leader. Butt was hanged for the <DATE>1965</DATE> murder of
an Indian intelligent agent in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   Scores of people have been killed in a 2-month-old secessionist
uprising in <LOCATION>Indian-held Kashmir</LOCATION>. It has been led by Moslem
militants demanding separation from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and either independence
or union with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Feb. 5</DATE>, Indian border guards killed a 12-year-old boy when
Pakistanis stormed the border near <LOCATION>Sialkot</LOCATION>, 125 miles southeast of
<LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900122-0114 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-22-90 1510EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-India-Kashmir     01-22 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Kashmir,0634</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslems Defy Curfew, Fight Troops</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Moslem militants defied curfews <DATE>Monday</DATE>
and fought soldiers for a second day in an outburst of secessionist
violence police say has killed 48 people and injured 400.
   Trouble began late <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when Moslems protested a police
crackdown. Moslem militants want to secede from predominantly <LOCATION>Hindu
India</LOCATION> and either make <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> independent or unite the northwestern
state with adjacent <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, an Islamic nation.
   Only a brief lull during heavy rain <DATE>Sunday</DATE> has interrupted the
violence. Police said militants and two policemen were killed
<DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> and four protesters were shot to death in
neighboring <LOCATION>Anantnag</LOCATION>.
   ``The whole city is up in revolt,'' said <PERSON>Mohammad Nomani</PERSON>,
inspector-general of police in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. He estimated the number of
protesters at 1,500 and said they had at least 1,000 automatic
rifles and other weapons.
   A senior official in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> said privately the local
authorities had asked for more troops ``to back up the security
forces.'' Hundreds of soldiers have been sent to <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, a city
of 1 million that is the <DATE>summer</DATE> capital of Jammu-Kashmir state on
the <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> border.
   At least 38 people, most of them protesters, were killed late
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Police said troopers opened fire on
curfew violators in at least six places <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Doctors at the <ORGANIZATION>Soora Medical Institute</ORGANIZATION> said at least 300 people
were wounded <DATE>Monday</DATE> when soldiers fired on a group of about 5,000.
``Most of them had injuries in the upper part of the body,'' one
doctor said, asking that his name not be used.
   Other doctors said all beds in the hospital were occupied and
the cafeteria was converted to provide more space. Thousands of
Moslems, defying the curfew, camped inside the hospital to donate
blood.
   Troops with shoot-on-sight orders patrolled streets in <LOCATION>Srinigar</LOCATION>.
The roa of army trucks and wailing of ambulance sirens could be
heard through the city.
   A near-mutiny of part of the state police force, which Moslems
dominate, occurred after a member was killed by gunfire from other
security forces.
   About 500 armed policemen stayed inside a police complex <DATE>Monday</DATE>,
refusing to join the crackdown, but an officer said they were
``pacified some hours later.''
   <PERSON>Mohammad Aslam</PERSON>, a state policeman, said the dead comrade was hit
by army fire and soldiers refused to deliver his body.
   The officer of state police, who spoke on condition of
anonymity, confirmed the death and said the matter ``has apparently
been sorted out.''
   An around-the-clock curfew applies in <LOCATION>Srinigar</LOCATION>. Only soldiers
and military vehicles are permitted on the streets.
   Bands of 50 to 100 men formed throughout the day, however.
Teen-age boys shredded an Indian flag in front of soldiers while
people in a crowd screamed: ``You Indians go back!''
   Heavily armed soldiers guarded government buildings and bridges
over streams feeding <PERSON>Dal Lake</PERSON>, once a major tourist attraction.
   Jammu-Kashmir is the only Indian state with a Moslem majority.
Moslem followers of the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION> have
attacked government buildings and patrols in their quest for
independence or union with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   Attacks increased after five jailed militants were freed last
month in exchange for the the kidnapped daughter of a Cabinet
minister.
   The old princely state of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> was divided between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> when the subcontinent was partitioned in <DATE>1947</DATE> and became
independent of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>. They do not agree on the border and have
fought three wars, the last in <DATE>1971</DATE>.
   Pakistan controls the western part of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and the eastern
section was incorporated into <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   About <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> of the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>'s 5 million people are
Moslems, who make up only <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> of the Indian population of
880 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900126-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-26-90 1412EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-People     01-26 0996</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-People,1032</SECOND>
<HEAD>People in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY44</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A judge has ordered <ORGANIZATION>Washington Redskins</ORGANIZATION> owner
<PERSON>Jack Kent Cooke</PERSON> to pay his ex-wife <MONEY>$29,000</MONEY> a year to support the
couple's 2-year-old daughter, far less than the <MONEY>$110,000</MONEY> she had
requested. a hotel and told they
would be arrested, or even shot, if they stepped outside.
   In <LOCATION>Muzaffarabad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, Premier <PERSON>Sikander Hyat Khan</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Pakistani Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> said he would launch a Moslem ``holy war'' unless
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> schedules a special session to address the
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> issue.
   Muzaffarabad is the capital of <LOCATION>Pakistani Kashmir</LOCATION> and near the
cease-fire that has divided the region between <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>
since <DATE>1947</DATE>, when the subcontinent became independent of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and
the two nations were created. <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> have fought four
wars, three of them specifically over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   Most of the 5 million people in the <ORGANIZATION>Indian State of
Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> are Moslems. It is the only state with a Moslem
majority in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, a predominantly Hindu nation.
   ``If the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> is not ready to play its role ... I will
tell them to go and fight,'' <PERSON>Khan</PERSON> warned of the people in <LOCATION>Pakistani
Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   He gave the world organization until <DATE>Feb. 17</DATE> to schedule a
special session. He said the deadline coincided with a scheduled
meeting all Pakistani political and religious parties in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Tariq Mahmood Butt</PERSON>, head of the student wing of the militant
<ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>, said thousands of its members would
cross the frontier <DATE>Feb. 11</DATE> if the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> did not promise
action.
   Indian state television described the situation in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>
as ``by and large peaceful,'' but said at least nine people were
killed <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when paramilitary troops fired on rioters in
<LOCATION>Handwara</LOCATION>, 40 miles northwest of <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>.
   Troops in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> tightened restrictions under the 24-hour
curfew and prevented residents from opening windows, said witnesses
reached by telephone.
   From various vantage points in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, a city of 1 million,
only heavily armed troopers and an occasional government official
could be seen on the streets. Several people reached by telephone
from inside and outside <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> said they had not heard gunfire.
   Police sources in <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION>, winter capital of the state, said
militants hurled a gasoline bomb at soldiers during house searches
but no one was injured.
   The increased security coincided with the Moslem sabbath and
<ORGANIZATION>Republic Day</ORGANIZATION>, which major towns and cities in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> usually
celebrate with military parades.
   Moslem separatists in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, who want the state to be
either independent or joined to <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, declared the national
holiday a ``black day.''
   Television showed <PERSON>Jameel Qureshi</PERSON>, adviser to the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION>
state governor, taking the salute at a parade in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Bakshi
Stadium</LOCATION>. No civilian spectators were shown and a policeman who was
there said none attended.
   District magistrate <PERSON>Ghulam Abbas</PERSON> told about 20 journalists at
the Hotel Broadway: ``If you go out of the hotel, you can be shot,
and if we find out you have gone out, you can be imprisoned for six
months.''
   Soldiers with submachine guns were posted around the hotel,
which is about a mile from downtown <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>. The door leading to
the roof of the five-story building was locked and telephone
service was halted after the warning by <PERSON>Abbas</PERSON>.
   Seven journalists returned to <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> on a commercial flight
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. They said police took them to the <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>
airport by a circuitous route one officer said was designed to
skirt trouble. Police at the airport confiscated dozens of rolls of
film, they said.
   The Moslem separatist campaign is as old as the two nations, but
has escalated in recent weeks.
   Srinagar and surrounding towns were put under 24-hour curfew
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> and soldiers and paramilitary troopers were deployed.
Their number has not been released, but is known to be at least in
the hundreds.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900820-0098 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-20-90 1800EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-India-Pakistan     08-20 0644</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-India-Pakistan,0671</SECOND>
<HEAD>India Places Troops on Alert After Reported Border Clashes</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW DELHI, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> placed its troops on alert across
its northern border with <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> after clashes were
reported with Pakistani troops in a remote area of the disputed
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> territory.
   Describing the clashes as ``a major border incident,'' <ORGANIZATION>United
News of India</ORGANIZATION> said that according to unconfirmed reports at least
10 Pakistani soldiers were killed and five wounded in the clashes.
   There was no official confirmation on casualties.
   ``It is very difficult to say if there were casualties. We are,
however, checking,'' said an Indian government spokesman, <ORGANIZATION>Ram Mohan
Rao</ORGANIZATION>.
   The clashes reportedly occurred in the <LOCATION>Kupwara</LOCATION> sector of the
disputed frontier, about 60 miles northeast of the <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, the
capital of <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Jammu-Kashmir state.
   Earlier, Pakistani troops fired heavy artillery with explosive
and incendiary shells at Indian border posts in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir
state</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Rao</PERSON> said.
   ``Exchange of small arms fire is a frequent occurrence on the
border, but use of heavy artillery and incendiary ammunition is
something new,'' <PERSON>Rao</PERSON> said.
   In <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Pakistani defense ministry</ORGANIZATION> spokesman denied the
reported incident.
   ``There is absolutely no truth in the report of Pakistanis
firing (at) Indian troops,'' said the spokesman, speaking on
condition of anonymity.
   But in <LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION>, an Indian defense ministry official,
requesting anonymity, said all troops were put on alert along the
border after the incident.
   Indian defense officials in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> called the incident
``serious.'' The officials, who also asked not to be identified,
said some of the Pakistani shells landed a half-mile inside Indian
territory.
   Rao said the Indian government was waiting to receive more
details about the border incident.
   ``Probably <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> wants to make a little more noise, but we
have taken appropriate defensive measures,'' <PERSON>Rao</PERSON> said. He refused
to elaborate on the measures.
   A week ago, <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> accused Indian troops of using heavy
artillery, anti-tank guns and mortars in an attempt to capture a
border outpost in Pakistan-controlled <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>. At the time, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>
denied the claim.
independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1947</DATE>. Two of the wars were fought over
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>, a former principality claimed by both countries.
   The present border is a cease-fire line drawn in <DATE>1972</DATE> that
separates <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s only Moslem-majority state, from
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>'s Azad (Free) <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> region.
   In another sign of escalating tension, the prime minister of
Pakistan-held <PERSON>Azad Kashmir</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> ordered mandatory military
training for all males.
   ``<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> wants to attack. ... Responsibility for the whole of the
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> nation is on my shoulders,'' the prime minister, <PERSON>Mumtaz
Rathore</PERSON>, told about 3,000 cheering supporters in the <LOCATION>Azad Kashmir</LOCATION>
capital of Muzzaffarabad.
   ``From this day onward my mission will be the liberation of
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   A senior aide to <PERSON>Rathore</PERSON>, requesting anonymity, said military
training would also be given to Moslem militants spearheading the
secessionist uprising in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s Jammu-Kashmir state.
   The aide said <PERSON>Rathore</PERSON> sought no prior approval from the national
governmet in <LOCATION>Islamabad</LOCATION> before announcing the compulsory military
training.
   Pakistan-held <PERSON>Azad Kashmir</PERSON> is relatively autonomous, but the
federal government is responsible for the region's defense,
diplomacy and finances.
   Analysts say <PERSON>Rathore</PERSON>'s plans to provide military training for
Kashmiris could cause a confrontation with the new right-wing
government that succeeded ousted Prime Minister <PERSON>Benazir Bhutto</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has accused <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION> of providing arms and training to
Moslem militants in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, an Islamic state, has
denied the allegation, but says it supports the Kashmiri people's
   At least 1,034 people have been killed in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION> since
<LOCATION>New Delhi</LOCATION> launched a crackdown on the Moslem secessionist movement
on <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>.
   In <DATE>May</DATE>, both countries massed their armies along the cease-fire
line in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> as war fears escalated.
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900130-0010 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-30-90 0051EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Kashmir     01-30 0789</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Kashmir,0818</SECOND>
<HEAD>Kashmir: A Tourist Paradise Becomes a War Zone</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Tuesday AMs report; In 10th graf, ``We are ...''
Jagmohan uses only one name.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DILIP GANGULY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Exotic Kashmir, a tourist paradise of
houseboat hotels and Mogul gardens from whose name the English made
``cashmere,'' has become a war zone of separatism and religious
enmity.
   Military jeeps carry senior government officials and civil
servants around <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION> in these dangerous days, as soldiers and
paramilitary troopers try to stop a campaign of violence by Moslem
separatists in the <LOCATION>Kashmir Valley</LOCATION>.
   Intelligence officer <PERSON>M.K. Kaul</PERSON> commands one of the jeeps. At the
beginning of a trip through the city of 1 million people, he turned
to the four soldiers in the jeep's rear seats and ordered: ``Check
your weapons. Be ready to fire.''
   Kaul settled into the front seat, a 9mm pistol in his right
hand. ``These are bad days,'' he murmured. ``These die-hard
terrorists can attack from anywhere.
   To his men, he said: ``Shoot them if you see them.''
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, an around-the-clock curfew was lifted from <TIME>5 a.m.</TIME>
until noon and stores opened to crowds of customers. Soldiers in
sandbagged bunkers, armed with light machine guns, guarded main
intersections.
   A spokesman for the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir</ORGANIZATION> state government said the
situation was peaceful and ``absolutely normal'' in <LOCATION>Srinagar</LOCATION>, the
state's largest city.
   At least 72 people have been killed since the crackdown began
<DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> in an effort to curb attacks on government officials and
buildings. Most of the dead have been Moslem militants shot by
Indian troops.
   ``We are neither fighting a war nor trying to suppress any
popular movement,'' said <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON>, governor of <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION>, the
only state in predominantly <LOCATION>Hindu India</LOCATION> with a Moslem majority.
   ``We are fighting a handful of terrorists who are determined to
create a law and order problem,'' said <PERSON>Jagmohan</PERSON>, a Hindu with a
reputation for toughness.
   Other officials in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> say privately the situation is
critical, perhaps the most serious threat <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> has faced in 42
years of independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>.
   ``It looks like everyone here has turned into a fundamentalist
with firm belief that the day is not far off when they will become
independent,'' a state police officer said.
   Kashmir was a separate kingdom, ruled by a Hindu maharajah, when
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> relinquished colonial rule on <DATE>Aug. 15, 1947</DATE>, and the
subcontinent was partitioned on religious lines into <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>.
   The Hindu king opted to join <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, not <LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>, and the
dispute over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> has exacerbated relations since.
   Pakistan took the western part of <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> the eastern.
Each accused the other of forcible occupation.
   They have fought wars over <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> and the border question
remains unresolved. U.N. observers are stationed on the truce line
and the two sides occasionally trade gunfire.
   Officials will not say how many reinforcements have been sent to
the <LOCATION>Kashmir Valley</LOCATION> since <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE>, but reports from various sources
indicate 30,000-and 40,000 soldiers and paramilitary troops have
been deployed.
   It is the valley's heavily Moslem population that tilts the
sectarian scale in <LOCATION>Jammu-Kashmir</LOCATION> state.
   Of the state's nearly 6 million people, <PERCENT>64 percent</PERCENT> are Moslems
and <PERCENT>32 percent</PERCENT> Hindus. Most Hindus live in the southern <LOCATION>Jammu</LOCATION> area.
   Srinagar has 150 mosques. ``This is the best breeding ground for
Moslem fundamentalism,'' said a federal official who helps
coordinate the new security measures.
   Nearly every mosque has a loudspeaker to summon the faithful to
prayer _ and, more recently, to exhort listeners to defend their
faith and <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>.
   ``The residents are constantly bombarded with Islamic sermons
and are reminded that fighting a `jihad' (Islamic holy war) is the
most sacred duty of every Moslem,'' the federal official said, on
condition of anonymity.
   Electricity was cut off in the city <DATE>Friday</DATE>, which was both the
Moslem sabbath and <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s national <ORGANIZATION>Republic Day</ORGANIZATION> on <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>'s
Republic Day, but many mosque loudspeakers continued operating
because militants connected them to car batteries.
   Intelligence reports suggest the government has an advantage
because the separatists are not united.
   The most powerful group is the <ORGANIZATION>Jammu-Kashmir Liberation Front</ORGANIZATION>,
but there are several others, including the <ORGANIZATION>Allah Tigers</ORGANIZATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Hezb-e-Mujahed Hezb-e-Islami</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> claims the fundamentalists get money and weapons from
<LOCATION>Pakistan</LOCATION>. The Pakistanis deny it.
   Jagmohan, the governor, insists the main issue in <LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION> is
economic development, not separatism.
   ``The people do not want violence or the so-called independent
<LOCATION>Kashmir</LOCATION>,'' he said. ``The need of the hour is development. Let more
tourists come. Let new schools be built. Let new hospitals come
up.''
   As he spoke, military officers waited in the next room to
discuss a new strategy to crush rebellion in what the tourist
brochures call <ORGANIZATION>Paradise</ORGANIZATION>.
   Right now, <ORGANIZATION>Paradise</ORGANIZATION> looks lost, at least temporarily.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900224-0094 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-24-90 1452EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Kashmir     02-24 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Kashmir,0579</SECOND>
<HEAD>Tens of Thousands March to Moslem Shrine Demanding Freedom</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SRINAGAR, India (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Tens of thousands of people chanting
