<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0178 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 1024EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   08-14 0546</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0565</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv24</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thursday, Aug. 24</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>236th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 129
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Aug. 24, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
signed a 10-year non-aggression pact, each country pledging not to
``associate itself with any other grouping of powers which directly
or indirectly is aimed at the other party.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>A.D. 79</DATE>, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted, burying the
Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic ash. An
estimated 20,000 people died.
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and proceeded
to set fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a
non-stop flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, three days after Hawaiian statehood, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was
sworn in as the first Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K.
Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
House of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20
years to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John
Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: A 73-hour stand-off began at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kennedy
International Airport</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials prevented the takeoff of an
<ORGANIZATION>Aeroflot</ORGANIZATION> jetliner until they could determine whether Soviet
ballerina <PERSON>Lyudmila Vlasova</PERSON> was returning home voluntarily after the
defection to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of her husband, dancer <PERSON>Alexander
Godunov</PERSON>. (<PERSON>Vlasova</PERSON> was ultimately allowed to leave.)
   Five years ago: On the heels of the Republican convention,
Democrat <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON> said the proceedings had demonstrated
that President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> represented the party of the rich,
while <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> questioned <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s commitment to a strong defense.
   One year ago: Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
picked up the endorsement of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> while Republican nominee
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> campaigned in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 77. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 72. Former secretary of education <PERSON>Shirley
Hufstedler</PERSON> is 64. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 33. Actor <PERSON>Steve Guttenberg</PERSON>
is 31. All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 29.
   Thought for today: ``Posterity is as likely to be wrong as
anybody else.'' _<PERSON>Heywood Broun</PERSON>, American journalist and author
(1888-1939).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890824-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-24-89 0046EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-History 1stLd-Writethru b0245 08-24 0574</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, 1st Ld-Writethru, b0245, Adv24,0567</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 3rd graf, `Fifty years ... other party,'' to clarify that
Aug. 24 was date of announcement. Original moved in advance as b0245.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the <DATE>236th day of 1989</DATE>. There are 129
   Today's highlight in history:
   <DATE>Fifty years ago</DATE>, on <DATE>Aug. 24, 1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>
announced they had, during the night, signed a 10-year
non-aggression pact, each country pledging not to ``associate itself
with any other grouping of powers which directly or indirectly is
aimed at the other party.''
   On this date:
   In <DATE>A.D. 79</DATE>, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted, burying the
Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic ash. An
estimated 20,000 people died.
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and proceeded
to set fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a non-stop
flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, three days after Hawaiian statehood, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was
sworn in as the first Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K.
Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House
of Representatives</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20 years
to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: A 73-hour stand-off began at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Kennedy
International Airport</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials prevented the takeoff of an
<ORGANIZATION>Aeroflot</ORGANIZATION> jetliner until they could determine whether Soviet
ballerina <PERSON>Lyudmila Vlasova</PERSON> was returning home voluntarily after the
defection to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of her husband, dancer <PERSON>Alexander
Godunov</PERSON>. (<PERSON>Vlasova</PERSON> was ultimately allowed to leave.)
   Five years ago: On the heels of the Republican convention,
Democrat <PERSON>Walter F. Mondale</PERSON> said the proceedings had demonstrated
that President <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> represented the party of the rich,
while <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> questioned <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>'s commitment to a strong defense.
   One year ago: Democratic presidential nominee <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>
picked up the endorsement of the <ORGANIZATION>AFL-CIO</ORGANIZATION> while Republican nominee
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> campaigned in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 77. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 72. Former secretary of education <PERSON>Shirley Hufstedler</PERSON>
is 64. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 33. Actor <PERSON>Steve Guttenberg</PERSON> is 31.
All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 29.
   Thought for today: ``Posterity is as likely to be wrong as
anybody else.'' _ <PERSON>Heywood Broun</PERSON>, American journalist and author
(1888-1939).
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880515-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-15-88 1508EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Poll-Details     05-15 0695</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Poll-Details,0723</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Poll-US-Soviet, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This <ORGANIZATION>Media General-Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll is
based on telephone interviews <DATE>April 29-May 8</DATE> with 1,204 adults in
the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The phone numbers were selected
randomly by computer and interviews were conducted with the adult
resident of each home who had the most recent birthday.
   The results were weighted to adjust for variations in the
sample. The poll has a three-point margin of error, meaning that
theoretically the results would be within <PERCENT>3 percentage points</PERCENT> of
the same 19 times out of 20 if every adult American were asked the
same questions. The error margin is larger for subgroups _ five
points for Republicans, for example, and nine points for
respondents who have done postgraduate work.
   There are other sources of potential error in polls, including
the wording and order of questions. These are the questions and
responses in this poll:
   1. Do you think the president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the
leader of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> should meet at regular intervals even
without any major items on the agenda, or should they meet only to
complete major treaties?
   Regular intervals: <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT>. Major treaties: <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT>. Don't
know or no answer: <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.
   2. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the Soviets recently agreed on a treaty
to abolish each country's medium-range nuclear weapons in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Do you think that will increase the chance of non-nuclear war in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, decrease the chance of non-nuclear war in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, or won't
it make much of a difference?
   Increase: <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT>. Decrease: <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT>. Not much difference:
<PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer: <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>.
   3. Do you support or oppose the U.S.-Soviet treaty to eliminate
each country's medium-range nuclear weapons?
   Support: <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT>. Oppose: <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know, no answer:
<PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   4. Would you support or oppose a U.S.-Soviet treaty to abolish
<PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of each country's long-range nuclear weapons?
   Support: <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT>. Oppose: <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer: <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   5. If the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> abolished all their
nuclear weapons, do you think that would increase the chance of
non-nuclear war, decrease it, or wouldn't it make much of a
difference?
   Increase, <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>. Decrease, <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT>. Not much difference,
<PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer: <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>.
   6. <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> has proposed the <ORGANIZATION>Strategic Defense Initiative</ORGANIZATION>,
known as <ORGANIZATION>Star Wars</ORGANIZATION>, as a missile defense system. Do you think the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> should drop SDI in exchange for a Soviet agreement to
a big cut in nuclear weapons?
   Yes, <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. No, <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>18
percent</PERCENT>.
   7. Without an arms agreement with the Soviets, do you think work
on SDI should proceed as it is now, or should it be increased, or
reduced, or dropped?
   Proceed as now, <PERCENT>37 percent</PERCENT>. Increase, <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT>. Reduce, <PERCENT>13
percent</PERCENT>. Drop, <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>.
   8. Which country do you think has more political influence in
the world right now _ the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, or the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, or
are they about equal?
   <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>. About
equal, <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT>.
   9. Which country do you think is stronger militarily right now _
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, or the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, or are they about equal?
   <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. About equal
<PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   10. Overall, do you have a favorable or unfavorable opinion of
Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON>?
   Favorable, <PERCENT>54 percent</PERCENT>. Unfavorable, <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT>.
   11. Overall, do you have a favorable or unfavorable opinion of
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>?
   Favorable, <PERCENT>59 percent</PERCENT>. Unfavorable, <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   12. Do you approve or disapprove of the way President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> is
handling relations with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>?
   Approve, <PERCENT>71 percent</PERCENT>. Disapprove, <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   13. Do you think the Soviets can be trusted to live up to their
arms control agreements?
   Yes, <PERCENT>24 percent</PERCENT>. No, <PERCENT>61 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>15
percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880516-0041 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-88 0311EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Poll-Questions     05-16 0695</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poll-Questions,0723</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Poll-US-Soviet, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This <ORGANIZATION>Media General-Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll is
based on telephone interviews <DATE>April 29-May 8</DATE> with 1,204 adults in
the continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The phone numbers were selected
randomly by computer and interviews were conducted with the adult
resident of each home who had the most recent birthday.
   The results were weighted to adjust for variations in the
sample. The poll has a three-point margin of error, meaning that
theoretically the results would be within <PERCENT>3 percentage points</PERCENT> of
the same 19 times out of 20 if every adult American were asked the
same questions. The error margin is larger for subgroups _ five
points for Republicans, for example, and nine points for
respondents who have done postgraduate work.
   There are other sources of potential error in polls, including
the wording and order of questions. These are the questions and
responses in this poll:
   1. Do you think the president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the
leader of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> should meet at regular intervals even
without any major items on the agenda, or should they meet only to
complete major treaties?
   Regular intervals: <PERCENT>78 percent</PERCENT>. Major treaties: <PERCENT>16 percent</PERCENT>. Don't
know or no answer: <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>.
   2. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the Soviets recently agreed on a treaty
to abolish each country's medium-range nuclear weapons in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>.
Do you think that will increase the chance of non-nuclear war in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, decrease the chance of non-nuclear war in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, or won't
it make much of a difference?
   Increase: <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT>. Decrease: <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT>. Not much difference:
<PERCENT>55 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer: <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>.
   3. Do you support or oppose the U.S.-Soviet treaty to eliminate
each country's medium-range nuclear weapons?
   Support: <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT>. Oppose: <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know, no answer:
<PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   4. Would you support or oppose a U.S.-Soviet treaty to abolish
<PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of each country's long-range nuclear weapons?
   Support: <PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT>. Oppose: <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer: <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   5. If the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> abolished all their
nuclear weapons, do you think that would increase the chance of
non-nuclear war, decrease it, or wouldn't it make much of a
difference?
   Increase, <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>. Decrease, <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT>. Not much difference,
<PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer: <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>.
   6. <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> has proposed the <ORGANIZATION>Strategic Defense Initiative</ORGANIZATION>,
known as <ORGANIZATION>Star Wars</ORGANIZATION>, as a missile defense system. Do you think the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> should drop SDI in exchange for a Soviet agreement to
a big cut in nuclear weapons?
   Yes, <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. No, <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>18
percent</PERCENT>.
   7. Without an arms agreement with the Soviets, do you think work
on SDI should proceed as it is now, or should it be increased, or
reduced, or dropped?
   Proceed as now, <PERCENT>37 percent</PERCENT>. Increase, <PERCENT>19 percent</PERCENT>. Reduce, <PERCENT>13
percent</PERCENT>. Drop, <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>.
   8. Which country do you think has more political influence in
the world right now _ the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, or the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, or
are they about equal?
   <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>. About
equal, <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT>.
   9. Which country do you think is stronger militarily right now _
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, or the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, or are they about equal?
   <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT>. <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT>. About equal
<PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   10. Overall, do you have a favorable or unfavorable opinion of
Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON>?
   Favorable, <PERCENT>54 percent</PERCENT>. Unfavorable, <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT>.
   11. Overall, do you have a favorable or unfavorable opinion of
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>?
   Favorable, <PERCENT>59 percent</PERCENT>. Unfavorable, <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>.
   12. Do you approve or disapprove of the way President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> is
handling relations with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>?
   Approve, <PERCENT>71 percent</PERCENT>. Disapprove, <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no
answer, <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT>.
   13. Do you think the Soviets can be trusted to live up to their
arms control agreements?
   Yes, <PERCENT>24 percent</PERCENT>. No, <PERCENT>61 percent</PERCENT>. Don't know or no answer, <PERCENT>15
percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880815-0236 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-15-88 0750EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv24   08-15 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv24,0517</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv24</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Wednesday, Aug. 24</NOTE>
<HEAD>Today in History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, the 237th day of <DATE>1988</DATE>. There are
   Today's highlight in history:
   On <DATE>Aug. 24</DATE>, <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> 79, long-dormant Mount Vesuvius erupted,
burying the Roman cities of <LOCATION>Pompeii</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Herculaneum</LOCATION> in volcanic
ash. An estimated 20,000 people died.
   On this date:
   In A.D. 410, <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> was overrun by the Visigoths, an event that
symbolized the fall of the <ORGANIZATION>Western Roman Empire</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1572</DATE>, the slaughter of French Protestants at the hands of
Catholics began in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>St. Bartholomew</LOCATION>'s Day. The killings
lasted until <DATE>October</DATE>, and claimed some 13,000 victims.
   In <DATE>1814</DATE>, British forces invaded <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> and proceeded to set
fire to the Capitol and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1932</DATE>, <PERSON>Amelia Earhart</PERSON> became the first woman to make a
non-stop flight across the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, traveling from <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Newark</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, in just over 19 hours.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> signed a non-aggression
pact.
   In <DATE>1949</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty</ORGANIZATION> went into effect, with the
parties agreeing that an armed attack against one would be
considered ``an attack against them all.''
   In <DATE>1954</DATE>, the Communist Control Act went into effect, virtually
outlawing the <ORGANIZATION>Communist Party</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1959</DATE>, <PERSON>Hiram L. Fong</PERSON> was sworn in as the first
Chinese-American <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> senator while <PERSON>Daniel K. Inouye</PERSON> was sworn in
as the first Japanese-American in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. House of
Representatives</ORGANIZATION>. Both were from <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1968</DATE>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> became the world's fifth thermonuclear power as
it exploded a hydrogen bomb in the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1970</DATE>, a bomb planted by anti-war extremists exploded at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Wisconsin</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Army Math Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Madison</LOCATION>,
killing 33-year-old researcher <PERSON>Robert Fassnacht</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1981</DATE>, <PERSON>Mark David Chapman</PERSON> was sentenced in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> to 20
years to life in prison for the shooting death of rock star <PERSON>John
Lennon</PERSON>.
   In <DATE>1982</DATE>, <PERSON>Archbishop Joseph L. Bernardin</PERSON> was installed as head of
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Roman Catholic Archdiocese.
   Ten years ago: Leftist guerrillas who had seized the <ORGANIZATION>National
Palace</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Managua</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>, released the last of their hostages
after the government freed 59 political prisoners and paid a
ransom. The guerrillas and the former prisoners were flown to
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   Five years ago: <PERSON>Corazon Aquino</PERSON>, widow of Philippine opposition
leader <PERSON>Benigno S. Aquino Jr.</PERSON>, returned to her homeland for her
husband's funeral, rejecting President <PERSON>Ferdinand E. Marcos</PERSON>' denial
that his government had any part in <LOCATION>Aquino</LOCATION>'s assassination.
   One year ago: A military jury in <LOCATION>Quantico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, sentenced Marine
Sgt. <PERSON>Clayton Lonetree</PERSON> to 30 years in prison for disclosing <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
secrets to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Today's birthdays: TV personality <PERSON>Durward Kirby</PERSON> is 76. TV host
<PERSON>Dennis James</PERSON> is 71. Boxer <PERSON>Gerry Cooney</PERSON> is 32. Actor <PERSON>Steve
Guttenberg</PERSON> is 30. All-star shortstop <PERSON>Cal Ripken Jr.</PERSON> is 28.
   Thought for today: ``Nothing has really happened until it has
been recorded.'' _ <LOCATION>Virginia Woolf</LOCATION>, English author and critic
(1882-1941).
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881227-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-27-88 0019EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Poll-Method     12-27 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poll-Method,0716</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Reagan-Poll, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   This <ORGANIZATION>Media General-Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll is based
on telephone interviews <DATE>Nov. 10-20</DATE> with 1,084 adults in the
continental <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The phone numbers were selected randomly
by computer and interviews were conducted with the adult who had the
most recent birthday.
   The results were weighted to adjust for variations in the sample.
The poll has a 3-point margin of error, meaning that if every adult
American were asked the same questions, the results theoretically
would be within 3 points of the poll's results, 19 times out of 20.
The error margin is larger for subgroups _ 5 points, for example,
for Republicans.
   There are other sources of potential error in polls, including
the wording and order of questions. These are the questions and
responses in this poll; because of rounding, sums may not total 100:
   1. Overall, do you approve or disapprove of the way <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>
has handled his job as president? Approve: <PERCENT>66 percent</PERCENT>. Disapprove:
27. Don't Know or No Answer: 7.
   2. Do you think <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> has accomplished most of what he
set out do to as president? Yes: 62. No: 30. DK-NA: 8.
   3. If President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> could have run again, would you have voted
for him for a third term as president? Yes: 43. No: 52. DK-NA: 5.
   4. In general, do you think <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s economic policies
over the last eight years have been good for the country or bad for
the country? Good: 63. Bad: 28. DK-NA: 10.
   5. Do you think you and your family are better off, or worse off,
or about the same economically as a result of <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s
policies? Better: 35. Worse: 18. Same: 45. DK-NA: 3.
   6. How about these groups? Please tell me if you think they are
better off, or worse off, or about the same economically as a result
of <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s policies.
   a. Wealthy Americans. Better: 72. Worse: 3. Same: 18. DK-NA: 8.
   c. The middle class. Better: 26. Worse: 33. Same: 38. DK-NA: 4.
   d. The poor. Better: 15. Worse: 54. Same: 24. DK-NA: 7.
   7. Please rate <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> one each of the following qualities.
Rate each as excellent, good, only fair or poor.
   a. Accomplishments as president. E: 15. G: 45. F: 30. P: 9.
DK-NA: 1.
   b. Leadership as president. E: 25. G: 41. F: 23. P: 10. DK-NA: 2.
   c. Judgment as president. E: 9. G: 36. F: 35. P: 18. DK-NA: 2.
   d. Charisma. E: 42. G: 33. F: 16. P: 7. DK-NA: 3.
   e. Ability to communicate. E: 36. G: 38. F: 15. P: 9. DK-NA: 2.
   8. Please rate <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s handling of each of these issues,
also as excellent, good, only fair or poor.
   a. The economy. E: 8. G: 41. F: 30. P: 19. DK-NA: 2.
   b. The federal deficit. E: 1. G: 15. F: 34. P: 46. DK-NA: 4.
   c. Ethics in government. E: 5. G: 32. F: 34. P: 25. DK-NA: 4.
   d. Education. E: 5. G: 37. F: 34. P: 20. DK-NA: 5.
   e. Housing. E: 3. G: 26. F: 38. P: 27. DK-NA: 6.
   f. Welfare, or public assistance for poor people. E: 3. G: 26. F:
35. P: 32. DK-NA: 5.
   g. Civil rights. E: 4. G: 40. F: 34. P: 17. DK-NA: 5.
   h. <ORGANIZATION>Defense</ORGANIZATION>. E: 27. G: 45. F: 18. P 8. DK-NA: 4.
   i. Relations with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. E: 36. G: 46. F: 13. P: 3.
DK-NA: 3.
   j. Other foreign policy. E: 13. G: 45. F: 29. P: 7. DK-NA: 5.
   k. Appointments of federal judges. E: 7. G: 36. F: 32. P: 16.
DK-NA: 10.
   9. Do you think that as president, <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> made the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> a better place, or a worse place, or didn't he make it much
different? Better: 55. Worse: 12. No different: 31. DK-NA: 3.
   10. Overall, how do you think <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> will go down in
history _ as an excellent president, good, only fair or a poor
president? E: 20. G: 47. F: 24. P: 7. DK-NA: 2.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890922-0097 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890922 </DD>
<AN> 890922-0097. </AN>
<HL> REVIEW &amp; OUTLOOK (Editorial):
@  A Clear Choice </HL>
<DD> 09/22/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> TAXES </CO>
<IN> ECONOMIC NEWS (ECO) </IN>
<GV> CONGRESS (CNG) </GV>
<TEXT>

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900406-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-06-90 0227EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-CDC-DeathRates Bjt   04-06 0452</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-CDC-Death Rates, Bjt,0463</SECOND>
<HEAD>USA in Middle of Developed Nations in Life Expectancy, Death Rates</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT BYRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> lands in the middle of the pack
in rankings of life expectancy and death rates in 33 developed
nations, according to new figures from <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> health officials.
   Atop the list: <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   In the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the average life expectancy is 75 years,
trailing <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> by 4.1 years, but beating the lowest of the 33,
<LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, by more than five years, the national <ORGANIZATION>Centers for Disease
Control</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The average Hungarian lives 69.7 years, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> also ranked near the middle of the 33 nations
in death rates from all causes: 828.4 deaths are reported for each
100,000 people each year. <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> was best at 628.8; <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> worst at
1,242.
hits harder here than in other countries. The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mortality rate
from heart disease was 382 per 100,000 per year for men and 214 for
women, compared with 339 and 206 in the other 32 developed
countries.
   Throughout the 33 countries, heart disease accounted for <PERCENT>30
percent</PERCENT> of deaths, with cancer causing <PERCENT>21 percent</PERCENT> and stroke
causing <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>.
   Fourteen percent of deaths in the 33 countries _ about 1.5
million a year _ are attributed to smoking, the <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   Fewer Americans smoke, compared with the other countries; <PERCENT>31
percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> males and <PERCENT>26 percent</PERCENT> of American females smoke,
compared with <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT> of men and <PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT> of women in the
other countries.
   ``The large number of deaths attributable to cigarette smoking
indicates that reduction of this risk factor would substantially
increase life expectancy in the developed world,'' the
Atlanta-based <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study included countries defined as developed according
to a <DATE>1963</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> standard pegged to reproductive rates: countries
where the average woman has fewer than two daughters who,
themselves, survive their childbearing years.
   Such areas include the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>, most of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, some Latin American nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>CDC</ORGANIZATION> study cited life expectancies and death rates in the
latest available statistics for each country, from <DATE>1984</DATE> to <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   Life expectancies for the 33 countries: <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> 76.3 years,
<LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> 75.1, <LOCATION>Belgium</LOCATION> 74.3, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION> 71.5, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> 76.5,
<LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION> 71.0, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> 74.9, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> 73.2, <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION> 74.8,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> 75.9, <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION> 76.5, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION> 69.7, <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> 77.4, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> 73.5,
<LOCATION>Israel</LOCATION> 75.2, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> 75.5, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> 79.1, <LOCATION>Luxembourg</LOCATION> 74.1, <LOCATION>Malta</LOCATION> 74.8,
<LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION> 76.5, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION> 74.2, <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> 76.3, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION> 71.0,
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> 74.1, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION> 69.9, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> 76.6, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> 77.1, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>
77.6, <LOCATION>United Kingdom</LOCATION> 75.3, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> 75.0, <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> 69.8, <LOCATION>West
Germany</LOCATION> 75.8, <LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION> 71.0.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880516-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-88 0321EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Poll-US-Soviet Bjt   05-16 0712</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Poll-US-Soviet, Bjt,0727</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll Says Americans Favor Arms Treaty But Don't Trust Soviets</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARY LANGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans overwhelmingly favor the U.S.-Soviet
medium-range nuclear missile treaty but share fears in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
that <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> cannot be trusted to comply, according to a <ORGANIZATION>Media
General-Associated Press</ORGANIZATION> poll.
   The poll also found that Americans view Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail
Gorbachev</PERSON> nearly as favorably as they do President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, and
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> out-polls <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> among college-educated Americans.
   Seventy-three percent of those polled in the national survey
supported the accord to eliminate medium-range missiles, and as
many said they would back a treaty to cut each nation's long-range
arsenal in half.
   But <PERCENT>61 percent</PERCENT> said the Soviets can't be trusted to live up to
their arms control agreements. That reflected sentiment in the
<ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>, which last week demanded clarification of the anti-cheating
rules in the pact.
   The poll was conducted among a random sample of 1,204 adults
interviewed by telephone from <DATE>April 29-May 8</DATE>, ending less than a
month before <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> meet in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>.
   As strongly pro-treaty as they were, a near-majority of
Americans were not willing to drop <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s proposed missile
defense system known as ``Star Wars'' in exchange for a Soviet
agreement to a big cut in nuclear arms. Forty-nine percent opposed
such a trade while just one-third supported it.
   The public was split on the issue along political and
ideological lines: Republicans and conservatives strongly opposed
dropping Star Wars for a big missile cut, while Democrats and
liberals favored such an agreement.
   Without an agreement, <PERCENT>56 percent</PERCENT> said work on <ORGANIZATION>Star Wars</ORGANIZATION> should
proceed as it is now or be increased, while <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> said it
should be reduced or dropped. There again was a political division:
<PERCENT>73 percent</PERCENT> of Republicans wanted work on Star Wars kept up,
compared with <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT> of Democrats.
   Similarly, there was an ideological division in support for the
medium-range treaty and for a treaty, if one can be reached, to
halve the long-range arsenals. The pacts fared worst among
conservatives _ <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> were opposed _ and best with liberals,
whose opposition was in single digits. About <PERCENT>67 percent</PERCENT> of
conservatives and <PERCENT>83 percent</PERCENT> of liberals were in favor.
   The survey found broad support for <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s handling of
U.S.-Soviet relations, with <PERCENT>71 percent</PERCENT> approving, and a high
positive view of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> generally, with <PERCENT>59 percent</PERCENT> rating him
favorably.
   Nearly as many _ <PERCENT>54 percent</PERCENT> _ expressed a positive view of
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, the poll found. Among college graduates, <PERCENT>71 percent</PERCENT>
rated <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> favorably while <PERCENT>62 percent</PERCENT> viewed <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> favorably;
among those who have done postgraduate work, <PERCENT>76 percent</PERCENT> saw
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> favorably, compared with <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> favorable for <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> had the approval of the poll's respondents for his May
29-June 2 summit with <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. Seventy-eight percent
said the president and the Soviet leader should meet at regular
intervals even without any major items on the agenda.
   The survey gave a mixed report on U.S.-Soviet competition.
Forty-one percent said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> had more political
influence in the world and just <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT> said the Soviets had
more political influence. Thirty-eight percent said the countries
were about equally influential.
   The rating was closer on military strength: <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> said the
Soviets were stronger militarily, <PERCENT>28 percent</PERCENT> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
was stronger and <PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT> said the countries were about equally
strong.
   Poll respondents largely rejected the opinion of critics that
nuclear arms treaties may increase the chance of non-nuclear war. A
majority said the medium-range missile treaty would not make much
difference in the chance of conventional war in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, and <PERCENT>26
percent</PERCENT> said it would decrease the chance.
   Just <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> said the treaty would increase the chance of
conventional war in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. That figure doubled, though, when
respondents were asked if abolition of all <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet nuclear
weapons would increase the chance of non-nuclear war; <PERCENT>22 percent</PERCENT>,
still a minority, said it would.
   The poll had a margin of sampling error of three points. <ORGANIZATION>Media
General Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a communications company based in <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>,
publishes the <ORGANIZATION>Richmond Times-Dispatch</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Richmond</LOCATION> News Leader,
the <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>). Tribune and the <LOCATION>Winston-Salem</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION>) Journal, and
operates TV stations WXFL in <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>, WCBD in <LOCATION>Charlestown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, and
WJKS in <LOCATION>Jacksonville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880929-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-29-88 0502EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Reagan-Hotel     09-29 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Reagan-Hotel,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reporters' Notebook: With Reagan at the Waldorf</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By W. DALE NELSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   For President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, his trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> meant a dramatic farewell
appearance. For fellow guests at his hotel, it meant something of a
nuisance.
   For reporters and photographers, it meant scrambling up and down
stairwells, waiting in line in a hotel kitchen and getting stuck in
an elevator.
   Reagan spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, making his seventh
appearance there and his last before he leaves office in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   After his speech, he went to the <LOCATION>United States Mission</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for lunch. It's just across the street, so most
people would walk. Presidential security, however, required that he
make the crossing by motorcade.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, his trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> meant a dramatic farewell
appearance. For fellow guests at his hotel, it meant something of a
nuisance.
   For reporters and photographers, it meant scrambling up and down
stairwells, waiting in line in a hotel kitchen and getting stuck in
an elevator.
   Reagan spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, making his seventh
appearance there and his last before he leaves office in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   After his speech, he went to the <LOCATION>United States Mission</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for lunch. It's just across the street, so most
people would walk. Presidential security, however, required that he
make the crossing by motorcade.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, his trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> meant a dramatic farewell
appearance. For fellow guests at his hotel, it meant something of a
nuisance.
   For reporters and photographers, it meant scrambling up and down
stairwells, waiting in line in a hotel kitchen and getting stuck in
an elevator.
   Reagan spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, making his seventh
appearance there and his last before he leaves office in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   After his speech, he went to the <LOCATION>United States Mission</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for lunch. It's just across the street, so most
people would walk. Presidential security, however, required that he
make the crossing by motorcade.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, his trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> meant a dramatic farewell
appearance. For fellow guests at his hotel, it meant something of a
nuisance.
   For reporters and photographers, it meant scrambling up and down
stairwells, waiting in line in a hotel kitchen and getting stuck in
an elevator.
   Reagan spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, making his seventh
appearance there and his last before he leaves office in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   After his speech, he went to the <LOCATION>United States Mission</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for lunch. It's just across the street, so most
people would walk. Presidential security, however, required that he
make the crossing by motorcade.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   For President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, his trip to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for
the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> meant a dramatic farewell
appearance. For fellow guests at his hotel, it meant something of a
nuisance.
   For reporters and photographers, it meant scrambling up and down
stairwells, waiting in line in a hotel kitchen and getting stuck in
an elevator.
   Reagan spoke at the <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, making his seventh
appearance there and his last before he leaves office in <DATE>January</DATE>.
   After his speech, he went to the <LOCATION>United States Mission</LOCATION> to the
<ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> for lunch. It's just across the street, so most
people would walk. Presidential security, however, required that he
make the crossing by motorcade.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880322-0155 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-88 1440EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Panama Bjt   03-22 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Panama, Bjt,0797</SECOND>
<HEAD>Opposition Scorns Noriega Offer; Strike Continues</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By REID G. MILLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PANAMA CITY, Panama (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON>'s
opponents scorned what they called a cynical offer to negotiate his
resignation and kept <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> shut down <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with a general strike
intended to force him out.
   An estimated <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of offices and industries were shut by
the strike, which appeared to be gaining support on its second day.
Most shops and stores were closed, public transportation was halted
and many government employees did not go to work.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> is out of cash because of pressure from the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
to force the ouster of <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, who is the real power in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> as
commander of its 15,000 soldiers and police. The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollar is the
national currency and the supply has been cut off.
   Most government workers were paid only <MONEY>$75</MONEY> of their midmonth
wages last week and the <MONEY>$33 million</MONEY> end-of-the-month payroll for
the 130,000 public employees problably won't be met. Pension checks
due <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> have been delayed, at least until <DATE>March 28</DATE>.
   Hunger is spreading among workers as well as the poor,
unemployed and elderly. Many washerwomen, cleaning women, maids and
cooks have lost their jobs because there is no money with which to
pay them.
   <PERSON>Manuel Solis Palma</PERSON>, the civilian <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> chose to run the
government, said on television <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> the general would
resign in exchange for ``a national dialogue'' to reconcile
differences with opponents of the regime. He prefaced the offer
with a diatribe against the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The implication was that <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>, under federal court indictment
in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> on narcotics and money laundering charges, would stay in
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> and might retain power behind the scenes.
   Calling the offer a ``noble gesture,'' <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON> said <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>
pledged ``as an officer and a gentleman'' to resign before
presidential elections scheduled for <DATE>May 1989</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON>, who has the title ``minister in charge of the
presidency,'' said he would not accept <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>'s resignation unless
``all of the political forces in the country'' join ``a national
dialogue.''
   Noriega put <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON> in office <DATE>Feb. 26</DATE>, after President <PERSON>Eric
Arturo Delvalle</PERSON> tried to fire the general and the legislature
dismissed <PERSON>Delvalle</PERSON> instead.
   Delvalle, still recognized by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, is hiding in
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>. His dismissal began a run on <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>'s banks and they were
closed the next week.
   Pressure from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> has included freezing virtually all
Panamanian funds in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, including revenue from the
<LOCATION>Panama Canal</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration spokesmen rejected the <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> proposal.
Last week, <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> turned down a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> plan for him to leave <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>
and live in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
   The general said his plan was a ``Panamanian solution'' to the
crisis.
   ``I have no reason to talk to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,'' he told
reporters after <PERSON>Solis Palma</PERSON>'s speech. ``I talk to Panamanians.''
   <PERSON>Guillermo Cochez</PERSON>, vice president of the <ORGANIZATION>Christian Democratic
Party</ORGANIZATION>, said the proposed discussion would occur in a panel of 33
members, 22 of them supporting <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   ``This is not a dialogue,'' he said ``It's just cynicism.''
   <PERSON>Aurelio Barria</PERSON> said: ``The general has to go _ immediately, not
eventually.
   Barria is a leader of the <ORGANIZATION>National Civic Crusade</ORGANIZATION>, a coalition of
200 business, professional, labor and political groups that called
the general strike. It was organized <DATE>last June</DATE> to lead the campaign
against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
   Solis Palma spoke on television for 30 minutes, devoting all but
the last five minutes to castigating the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. He accused
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> of ``economic aggression'' in ``an undeclared state of
war.''
   He claimed the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> wants to renege on the <DATE>1977</DATE>
treaties under which the <ORGANIZATION>Panama Canal</ORGANIZATION> will be turned over to this
country at <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Dec. 31, 1999</DATE>.
   The canal, guarded by about 10,000 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops, has been
operating normally despite the crisis. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> sent 300
more soldiers <DATE>Monday</DATE>, most of them security personnel.
   Because of increasing hunger, the Rev. <PERSON>Francisco Verar</PERSON> said his
Roman Catholic church in the poor <LOCATION>San Miguelito</LOCATION> suburb is feeding
more families every day.
   ``If we had not done this there would have been chaos, even
cases of death,'' he said. ``We have people who have gone five, six
days without food.''
   Longshoremen, on strike for more than a week, voted
overwhelmingly <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to stay out but accepted part payment of
back wages despite fears of compromising their position.
   ``There are mothers and fathers who have to feed their
children,'' said <PERSON>Luis Asprilla</PERSON>, a union leader.
   In some parts of <LOCATION>Panama City</LOCATION>, workers formed vigilante groups to
guard stores and other places of employment. Looting occurred
during street protests against <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON> last week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890814-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-14-89 1013EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-History Adv20   08-14 0492</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-History, Adv20,0508</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Aug. 20</HEAD>
<HEAD>Today In History</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 20</DATE>, the <DATE>232nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 133
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Today is <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <DATE>Aug. 20</DATE>, the <DATE>232nd day of 1989</DATE>. There are 133
days left in the year.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06244016 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06244016 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WORLD; TRACK; CONTEST; TOKYO; RESULT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  World Championships; In Tokyo  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TRACK AND FIELD  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 1F of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  Long Jump;   Final -- 1, <PERSON>Mike Powell</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 29-4 1/2, world record;
previous record, 29-2 1/2, <PERSON>Bob Beamon</PERSON>, <DATE>1968</DATE>. 2, <PERSON>Carl Lewis</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>,
29-2 3/4 (wind added). 3, <PERSON>Larry Myricks</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 27-7 1/2. 4, <PERSON>Dietmar
Haaf</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 26-11 3/4. 5, <PERSON>Bogdan Tudor</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, 26-5 1/2. 6, <PERSON>David
Culbert</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 26-3 3/4. 7, <PERSON>Giovanni Evangelisti</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, 26-3 1/2. 8,
<PERSON>Vladimir Ochkan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 26-2 3/4. 9, <PERSON>Jaime Jefferson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, 26-0 3/4.
10, <PERSON>Andre Muller</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 26-0 3/4. 11, <PERSON>Chen Zunrong</PERSON>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, 26-0. 12,
<PERSON>Konstandinos Koukodimos</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Greece</LOCATION>, 26-0. 13, <PERSON>George Ogbeide</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Nigeria</LOCATION>, 25-6 1/4.;
<LOCATION>Decathlon</LOCATION>;   Final standings -- 1, <PERSON>Dan O'Brien</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 8,812 points.
2, <PERSON>Michael Smith</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, 8,549. 3, <PERSON>Christian Schenk</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 8,394. 4,
<PERSON>Robert Zmelik</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>, 8,379. 5, <PERSON>Petri Keskitalo</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION>, 8,318. 6,
<PERSON>Simon Poelman</PERSON>, <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, 8,267. 7, <PERSON>Eduard Hamalainen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 8,233.
8, <PERSON>Antonio Penalver</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, 8,200.;   9, <PERSON>Christian Plaziat</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 8,122. 10,
<PERSON>Thorsten Dauth</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 8,069. 11, <PERSON>Beat Gahwiler</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, 8,011. 12,
<PERSON>Michael Kohnle</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 8,000. 13, <PERSON>Alain Blondel</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 7,848. 14, <PERSON>Munehiro
Kaneko</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, 7672. 15, <PERSON>Paul Scott</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, 7,663. 16, <LOCATION>Jan Trefny</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, 7,610. 17, <PERSON>Lars Warming</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION>, 7,529. 18, <PERSON>Sasa Karan</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Yugoslavia</LOCATION>, 7,468.;   19, <PERSON>Alper Kasapoglu</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Turkey</LOCATION>, 7,211. 20, <PERSON>Rob Muzzio</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 7,133. 21, <PERSON>Dave Johnson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 6,378. 22, <PERSON>Marco Baffi</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, 6,209. 23, <PERSON>Mikhail Medved</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 5,869. 24, <PERSON>Henrik Dagard</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, 5,663. 25, <PERSON>Pedro da Silva</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, 3,929. 26, <PERSON>Homelo Vi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Tonga</LOCATION>, 2,049.
27, <PERSON>Dezso Szabo</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, 847.;   Women; 200;   Final -- 1, <PERSON>Katrin Krabbe</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 22.09. 2, <PERSON>Gwen Torrence</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 22.16. 3, <PERSON>Merlene Ottey</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, 22.21. 4, <PERSON>Irina Privalova</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 22.28. 5, <PERSON>Galina Malchugina</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 22.66. 6, <PERSON>Dannette Young</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 22.87. 7, <PERSON>Pauline
Davis</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, 22.90. 8, <PERSON>Yelena Vinogradova</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 23.10.; 10,000;  
Final -- 1, <PERSON>Liz Mccolgan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, 31:14.31. 2, <PERSON>Zhong Huandi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, 31:35.08.
3, <PERSON>Wang Xiuting</PERSON>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, 31:35.99. 4, <PERSON>Kathrin Ullrich</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 31:38.96. 5,
<PERSON>Lynn Jennings</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, 31:54.44. 6, <PERSON>Uta Pippig</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 31:55.68. 7,
<PERSON>Ingrid Kristiansen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>, 32:10.75. 8, <ORGANIZATION>Derartu Tulu</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>, 32:16.55. 9,
<PERSON>Jill Hunter</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, 32:24.55. 10, <PERSON>Luchia Yesak</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ethiopia</LOCATION>, 32:27.61. 11,
<PERSON>Conceicao Ferreira</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, 32:29.12. 12, <LOCATION>Delilah Asiago</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, 32:33.71.
13, <PERSON>Tatyana Pozdnyakova</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 32:35.17. 14, <PERSON>Wang Yongmei</PERSON>, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>,
32:40.22. 15, <PERSON>Rosanna Munerotto</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, 32:44.43. 16, <PERSON>Miki Igarashi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
32:44.62. 17, <LOCATION>Iulia Negura</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Romania</LOCATION>, 32:53.57. 18, <PERSON>Carole Rouillard</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>,
32:58.77. 19, <PERSON>Annette Sergent-Palluy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 33:01.92. 20, <PERSON>Izumi Maki</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
33:27.84. 21, <PERSON>Jane Ngotho</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Kenya</LOCATION>, 33:36.91.; 100 hurdles;   Final -- 1,
<PERSON>Lyudmila Narozhilenko</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 12.59. 2, <PERSON>Gail Devers-Roberts</PERSON>, <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION>, 12.63. 3, <PERSON>Natalya Grigoryeva</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, 12.69. 4, <PERSON>Monique
Ewanje-Epee</PERSON>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 12.84. 5, <PERSON>Julie Baumann</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, 12.88. 6, <LOCATION>Florence
Colle</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 13.01. 7, <PERSON>Aliuska Lopez</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, 13.06. 8, <PERSON>Kristin Patzwahl</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, 13.07.  </TEXT>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910831  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  7F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  474  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, August 31, 1991
00244016,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880615-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-15-88 1338EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p AM-Bush-Negatives     06-15 0792</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Negatives,780</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush's Unfavorables: Troublesome but Not Historic</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Political Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GARY LANGER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   As <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> seeks to overcome his negative
ratings in presidential campaign polls, he might draw hope from
recent history: <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> suffered equally low ratings in his
races and overcame them to win.
   But this year there is an important difference, poll analysts
say. While <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> won by beating opponents who were viewed even
less favorably than he was, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> faces a far more popular opponent
in Gov. <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>.
   Dukakis has scored high favorable ratings in polls this <DATE>spring</DATE>,
though not as high as <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> at his pinnacle of popularity in
<DATE>June</DATE> of the <DATE>1976</DATE> election year. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has scored poorly, though not
nearly as poorly as <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> at his nadir in <DATE>1980</DATE>.
   Such measures, taken by asking if poll respondents have a
favorable or unfavorable view of candidates, provide an important
guide to vote-getting ability. A poor score ``means that there's a
chunk of people who don't like you,'' said <ORGANIZATION>CBS News</ORGANIZATION> pollster
<PERSON>Kathleen A. Frankovic</PERSON>. ``They probably won't vote for you _ unless,
of course, they can't stand the other guy more.''
   Strategists on both sides have focused lately on favorability
ratings, with <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> campaign spokesman <PERSON>Leslie Dach</PERSON> contending
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was ``sitting on some of the highest unfavorable ratings of a
presidential candidate in recent memory.''
   <PERSON>Dach</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> he based that claim on Gallup Poll figures,
but the <ORGANIZATION>Gallup Organization</ORGANIZATION> said its past figures are not
comparable to its current ones because it changed its questions and
procedures. In other, comparable polls, other candidates have rated
considerably worse than <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> rates now.
   Still, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s negative rating is high _ <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> favorable to
<PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> unfavorable in a <ORGANIZATION>CBS News-New York Times</ORGANIZATION> poll in <DATE>May</DATE>, <PERCENT>51
percent</PERCENT> favorable to <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> unfavorable in a <DATE>May</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>ABC
News-Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> poll, 53-40 favorable to unfavorable in a
Gallup poll this week.
   Contrast the ratings for Dukakis: 38-14 favorable to unfavorable
in the CBS-Times poll, 64-11 in the ABC-Post's, 70-20 in <LOCATION>Gallup</LOCATION>'s.
   The general election campaign, though, hardly has begun. ``We're
looking at where these people are starting out,'' <PERSON>Frankovic</PERSON> said.
``<PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> is starting out very nicely. <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> is
starting out with as many people disliking him as liking him. So
he's got some work to do.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s negatives are by no means historic. All three candidates
in the <DATE>1980</DATE> and <DATE>1984</DATE> elections _ <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Walter Mondale</PERSON>
_ had as bad or worse favorability ratings during their campaigns.
In <DATE>June 1980</DATE>, <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>'s CBS-Times rating was a dismal 33 favorable
to 60 unfavorable.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s 33-35 score in the CBS-Times poll was comparable to
<PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s 38-38 favorability rating in <DATE>September 1980</DATE>. But <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
had the advantage of facing <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, the unpopular incumbent.
   While <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> does not have an unpopular opponent, there has been
some movement in <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' rating: He went from <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT>
unfavorable in a Gallup Poll in <DATE>May</DATE> to <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> unfavorable the
new Gallup Poll.
   The key issue is not where a candidate stands when considered
alone, but where he stands in relationship to his opponent. ``In
<DATE>1976</DATE> people liked both of them,'' said <PERSON>Frankovic</PERSON>. ``In <DATE>1980</DATE> they
really didn't like either of them. And in <DATE>1984</DATE> you had a popular
incumbent.''
   Even <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s advantage was not apparent from the start. In
<DATE>January 1984</DATE>, an <ORGANIZATION>ABC News-Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> poll gave <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> a 54-38
favorable rating and <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON> a 48-30 rating. But <PERCENT>23 percent</PERCENT> didn't
know about <PERSON>Mondale</PERSON>; many went against him, and he lost in a
landslide.
   As many, <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT>, didn't know about <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> in the ABC-Post
poll in <DATE>May</DATE>, and pollsters noted that his high favorable rating
came amid positive publicity as he chalked up a string of primary
victories over <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON>.
   ``<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> has a quarter of the people who have to get to know
him,'' said <PERSON>Kelly Hanley</PERSON>, an <ORGANIZATION>ABC News</ORGANIZATION> poll analyst. ``<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is going
to start talking about <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' record, and we'll see how people
react to that.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, with the Republican nomination wrapped up, was out of the
news in <DATE>May</DATE>. With voters not yet focused on the race, his rating
may have been more a reflection of <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s lagging popularity than
of his own standing.
   ``Those negatives don't represent some personal shortcoming with
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> as much as some dissatisfaction with the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
administration,'' said <PERSON>Larry Hugick</PERSON>, of the <ORGANIZATION>Gallup Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
``I don't think people have much of a sense of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> yet
to give a response to these questions.''
   The issue for the campaigns, the analysts said, is whether <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
can establish his own, positive identity separate from <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, and
whether he can capitalize on the public's unfamiliarity with
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890514-0031 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-14-89 1201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-NoCoattails Bjt   05-14 0876</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-No Coattails, Bjt,830</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Doesn't Have Them, But How Much Does It Matter?</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DONALD M. ROTHBERG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   When President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> looks for votes on Capitol
Hill to sustain a minimum wage bill veto or win passage of his
savings and loan bailout plan, his clout is limited by the fact
most congressmen ran far ahead of him in their districts last
<DATE>November</DATE>.
   House members and political analysts differ among themselves on
the impact of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s lack of coattails.
   But there is no argument that while <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was carrying 40 of the
50 states, voters by the millions were opting for divided
government by choosing a Republican president and a <ORGANIZATION>Democratic
Congress</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``There was a big message in this election and <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>
picked it up,'' said Rep. <PERSON>Tony Coelho</PERSON> of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
Democratic whip.
   Coelho praised <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> for ``trying to establish a level of trust
that hasn't existed for 12 years.''
   ``You run independent of everyone,'' said Republican Rep. <PERSON>Lynn
Martin</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>.
   But she insisted that a president's persuasive ability is not
tied to the results of the last election.
   ``If the president calls you and asks you to vote for something,
any living member of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> who says it is easy to say no, is
absolutely saying that for a press statement,'' she said. ``After
the election it isn't Democrat or Republican, it's the president.''
   An analysis of the <DATE>1988</DATE> election results, published in the
<ORGANIZATION>National Journal</ORGANIZATION>, found that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> ran ahead of the successful <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
candidate in only 56 of the 435 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> districts.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> out polled only 26 Republicans and 30 Democrats. Half of
the Democrats were from the <LOCATION>South</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s strongest region in the
presidential vote.
   While those numbers might be viewed as a sign of the president's
electoral weakness, they might more accurately reflect the strength
of <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> members. Of the 435 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> winners in <DATE>1988</DATE>, only 63
received under <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the vote.
   By contrast, when <PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON> was elected in <DATE>1980</DATE>, he ran
ahead of 59 Republican winners. In addition his coattails were
credited with giving Republicans control of the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> for the
first time in a quarter century and with a <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> pickup of 33 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION>
seats.
   Did that make a difference?
   ``It was very easy to deal with reluctant Republicans or
persuadable Democrats'' during <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s first two years in office,
said Rich Bond, a Republican consultant who was involved in trying
to generate support for <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s agenda.
   Reagan's clout on Capitol Hill diminished sharply after the <DATE>1982</DATE>
midterm election when the Democrats won back 26 <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> seats.
   ``It was back to business as usual,'' said Bond.
   ``I've always been the Republican in whose district our
presidential candidates did least well,'' said Rep. Bill Green of
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> whose district runs along the East Side of <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>.
Green was re-elected with <PERCENT>61 percent</PERCENT> of the vote, while <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was
receiving only <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> against Democrat <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON>.
   ``I was the only Republican elected in a district <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> didn't
carry in <DATE>'84</DATE>,'' said <ORGANIZATION>Green</ORGANIZATION>.
   Green describes himself as a progressive Republican and his
support for <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> in <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> votes declined from a high of <PERCENT>55
percent</PERCENT> of the time in <DATE>1981</DATE> to <PERCENT>38 percent</PERCENT> in <DATE>1986</DATE>, according to
Congressional Quarterly.
   The <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> congressman said, ``Plainly in <DATE>1981</DATE> one of the
things <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> had going for him in winning votes in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> was
the ability to persuade marginal Democrats in certain parts of the
country that if they didn't come along they'd be very vulnerable in
<DATE>1982</DATE>.
   ``Obviously, that kind of capacity is lacking (for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>) at this
point.''
Institution, said, ``We're getting to the point where there will be
zero correlation between presidential and congressional returns.
   ``It reinforces the view on Capitol Hill that their electoral
fates are not shared with the president and therefore there are no
electoral ties that bind. Whatever incentives they have for working
with the president, elections are not one of them.''
   ``Not many members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> are going to quake in their boots
when presidents try to force them to do things,'' said <PERSON>Norman
Ornstein</PERSON>, a political scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>American Enterprise
Institute</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Presidents win by big margins; presidents win by small
margins; members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> go marching on,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Stephen Hess</PERSON>, who served on the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> staffs of presidents
<PERSON>Eisenhower</PERSON> and <PERSON>Nixon</PERSON>, said members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> get a sense of a
president's clout in their districts from polls and letters and
from their trips back home.
   ``They don't need to look at last <DATE>November</DATE>'s election returns to
know how well <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> stands in their district and, of course,
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> probably stands in their district better than he did on
<DATE>November 8</DATE>.''
   ``A president is not a hapless giant,'' said <PERSON>Hess</PERSON>. ``There are
appointments members want, there are grants that they want, there
are an awful lot of symbolic things that they want.''
   <PERSON>Lynn Martin</PERSON> echoed that view.
   ``What the president has to offer members is not really
electability,'' she said. ``It's coming in for fund-raisers, it is
the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, it is members feeling they are working with the
president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to accomplish something.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881029-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-88 0514EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Nicaragua-Joan 1stLd-Writethru   10-29 0683</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Nicaragua-Joan, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0440,0702</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ortega Says U.S. Ordered Rebels Back Into Nicaragua</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads 11 grafs to UPDATE with report Reagan administration
trying to block charity shipments. Picks up graf 8 pvs, `The
Soviet-backed ...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRYNA BRENNAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MANAGUA, Nicaragua (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Daniel Ortega</PERSON> has accused the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> of ordering thousands of rebels to re-enter <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>
and sabotage reconstruction efforts in the aftermath of Hurricane
Joan.
   Meanwhile, it was reported today that some <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> charities trying
provide humanitarian relief to Nicaraguans hurt by the hurricane
claim they are being hampering in their efforts by the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
administration.
   ``Taking advantage of the damage, the trauma, the <ORGANIZATION>Yankees</ORGANIZATION> have
already ordered the infiltration of 3,000 mercenaries into
Nicaraguan territory,'' <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said <DATE>Friday</DATE> in a nationwide radio and
television address.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> press officer <PERSON>Anita Stockman</PERSON>
denied the allegations. ``No <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military aid is being provided to
the Contras at this time,'' she said, referring to the rebels.
   Rebel spokesman <PERSON>Bosco Matamoros</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> that the
Contras were receiving only <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> humanitarian aid.
   ``The fact is <PERSON>Mr. Ortega</PERSON> is trying to conceal the continuous
buildup they have carried out with the help of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Matamoros</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration had re-armed the rebels,
known as Contras, and instructed them to ``sabotage and slow
reconstruction work and delay the coffee harvest,'' economically
vital to <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION>'s already staggering economy.
   ``Facing a threat such as this when we are facing the
consequences of this hurricane, Nicaraguans are obliged to mobilize,
organize, to fulfill the job of defending the country,'' <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said.
   Some private <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> organizations complained the <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
administration has refused to assist their efforts to deliver
donated goods to <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> and has even threatened to declare
shipments of construction supplies illegal under the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> economic
embargo of the country.
   ``It's kind of appalling that the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION> are interfering in the process of disaster aid,'' <PERSON>Richard
M. Walden</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Operation California</LOCATION>, a Los Angeles-based
relief group organizing an airlift to <LOCATION>Nicaragua</LOCATION> next week, was
quoted as saying today in the <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> Times.
   <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> officials denied any deliberate
effort to block private aid, but they acknowledged the
administration has taken few steps to assist the charities, the
<ORGANIZATION>Times</ORGANIZATION> said.
   The Soviet-backed Sandinista government and the U.S.-supported
Contras agreed in <DATE>March</DATE> to halt offensive operations in their 7-year
civil war. The government unilaterally has extended the truce on a
month-to-month basis. The current extension ends <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Ortega offered no proof of his allegations and did not say that
mobilization meant the government was allowing the cease-fire to
lapse.
   Most of the Contras retreated to base camps in <LOCATION>Honduras</LOCATION> after the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Congress</ORGANIZATION> refused to renew arms aid. Legislation approved by
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> does allow delivery of food, shelter, clothing and medical
services to the rebels.
   The leftist government frequently has compared the effort to
survive last week's killer hurricane to its struggle against the
Contras. On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> repeated his assertion that an end to
<ORGANIZATION>Contra</ORGANIZATION> aid would be the best hurricane assistance the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
could offer.
   Citing the latest government data, <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said Hurricane Joan
left 103 dead and 186,950 homeless. Previous government figures
estimated the number of dead at more than 60, with about 300,000
homeless.
   <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said 110 people were missing, an additional 178 were
seriously hurt and 324,861 were evacuated from their homes; 29,152
homes were destroyed; 33 bridges were destroyed and 33 others
damaged, and 400 miles of roads suffered direct damage.
   The cattle and fishing industries, and rice, cotton, grain,
sugar, cacao and African palm crops suffered serious damage and
``unmeasurable'' ecological damage was done, <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON> said.
   The storm ripped across 200 miles of Nicaraguan territory from
the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   ``The data indicate we met our main goal, to save lives,'' <PERSON>Ortega</PERSON>
said.
   He thanked <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>European
Economic Community</ORGANIZATION> for their aid and said <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> also promised help.
   The president called the aid ``necessary and urgent.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880309-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-09-88 0254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-SUP--Polls-Snapshot     03-09 0875</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-SUP--Polls-Snapshot,850</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-SUP--Polls</HEAD>
<HEAD>Sorting Out Who Voted For Which Candidate</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> primaries produced a
blizzard of numbers. Here are some figures from exit polls
conducted by <ORGANIZATION>ABC News</ORGANIZATION> in a dozen Southern states that help provide
a snapshot of who voted how:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>DEMOCRATS:</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> primaries produced a
blizzard of numbers. Here are some figures from exit polls
conducted by <ORGANIZATION>ABC News</ORGANIZATION> in a dozen Southern states that help provide
a snapshot of who voted how:
</TEXT>
<HEAD>REPUBLICANS;</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   The Super <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> primaries produced a
blizzard of numbers. Here are some figures from exit polls
conducted by <ORGANIZATION>ABC News</ORGANIZATION> in a dozen Southern states that help provide
a snapshot of who voted how:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881114-0163 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-14-88 1941EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Gorbachev 1stLd-Writethru a0731 11-14 0370</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gorbachev, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0731,360</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Leader To Make Visit To United States Next Month</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Adds 3 grafs background, official State Department no comment;
combines previous, a0731-33</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BARRY SCHWEID</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Diplomatic Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail S. Gorbachev</PERSON> will make
another visit to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> next month to address the <ORGANIZATION>United
Nations</ORGANIZATION> and will meet with President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> also is expected to meet with President-elect <PERSON>George
Bush</PERSON> while he is in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
a report by <ORGANIZATION>CBS</ORGANIZATION>.
   Earlier, British Prime Minister <PERSON>Margaret Thatcher</PERSON> announced
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> and his wife <PERSON>Raisa</PERSON> would visit <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <DATE>Dec. 12-14</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> met with <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> last <DATE>December</DATE>, the third
of their four summit meetings. They signed a treaty to abolish <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
and Soviet intermediate-range nuclear missiles.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said last week he was interested in a meeting with <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>
if it could produce progress on arms control, human rights or
regional disputes.
   But first, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said, he would have <PERSON>James A. Baker III</PERSON>, who he
has named his choice for secretary of state, meet with Soviet
Foreign Minister <PERSON>Eduard A. Shevardnadze</PERSON> and with foreign ministers
of the <ORGANIZATION>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> ruled out a mere get-acquainted session. ``I am acquainted
with him,'' the president-elect said. ``What I want to see is
progress. I`ve never supported meetings just for the sake of having
meetings.''
   Reagan first met with <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Geneva</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, in
<DATE>November 1985</DATE>. They held their second summit in <DATE>1986</DATE> in <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION>,
then met in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> last <DATE>December</DATE> and in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> May 29-June 2.
   The two superpowers are close to an agreement to sharply reduce
their strategic nuclear weapons, but are wrestling with problems
over how to verify some of the cutbacks.
   On the regional front, the Soviets have suspended the withdrawal
of their troops from <LOCATION>Afghanistan</LOCATION>. But the pullout is not supposed to
completed until <DATE>Feb. 15</DATE>, and <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> administration officials have
expressed confidence the Soviets would meet the deadline.
   <PERSON>Phyllis Oakley</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman, said of a
<PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON> visit: ``There has been no official announcement from the
<LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> on this question. Therefore it is inappropriate for us to
comment now.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890503-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-03-89 2107EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Poll     05-03 0480</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Poll,0493</SECOND>
<HEAD>Poll Finds Americans Want U.N. Leadership in Disarmament, Peacekeeping</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PETER JAMES SPIELMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Americans want the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION>, not
national governments, to control nuclear and chemical weapons and
to take the lead in keeping peace in the world, according to a poll
released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Roper Organization</ORGANIZATION> survey also found strong support for
increased American financing of <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> programs for peace, food
production, population control and health.
   In conflicts among countries where the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has an
interest, <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> forces should be used in an effort to accommodate
all parties, said <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT> of the nearly 2,000 adults surveyed.
   Only <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> should use force to
impose its own solution; <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> said ``it depends,'' and <PERCENT>14
percent</PERCENT> had no opinion.
   ``That is, in effect, a tough policy choice, and we were
surprised to see a 3-to-1 margin of support for <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> intervention
rather than unilateral <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> intervention,'' said <PERSON>Jeffrey Laurenti</PERSON>
of the <ORGANIZATION>U.N. Association of the U.S.A.</ORGANIZATION>, a private non-profit group
that commissioned the poll.
   Of the respondents, <PERCENT>46 percent</PERCENT> wanted <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> and other <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION>
members to spend more money settling regional conflicts peacefully,
<PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> favored less spending, <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT> said the right amount
is spent now, and <PERCENT>11 percent</PERCENT> had no opinion.
   The <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> should have the power to control the
manufacture and spread of chemical weapons in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
other countries, said <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT>, but <PERCENT>33 percent</PERCENT> opposed that and
<PERCENT>18 percent</PERCENT> were unsure.
   <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> control over nuclear weapons manufacture and proliferation
was favored by <PERCENT>36 percent</PERCENT>. The same percentage opposed it and <PERCENT>18
percent</PERCENT> were unsure.
   <PERCENT>Sixty percent</PERCENT> said all <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> members should pay their full dues
regularly rather than withholding funds to force changes. Fourteen
percent said funds could be withheld, the same number said ``it
depends'' and <PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> had no opinion.
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> withheld more than a <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY>
from the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> in recent years to force fiscal reforms and
because they perceived an anti-Western bias in the organization.
   Reagan finally said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would pay all back dues if
current reforms continued, and President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has reaffirmed the
pledge.
   When asked how much money the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and other <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION>
member countries should spend on <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> projects, the respondents
favored more funds for most social programs, including eradicating
disease and improving health care; slowing population growth
through birth control; increasing world food production, and
protecting the environment.
   <PERSON>Burns Roper</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Roper Organization</ORGANIZATION>, said the poll
indicated for the first time in more than a decade that more
Americans thought the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations</ORGANIZATION> was doing a good job than felt
it was doing poorly.
   It was conducted <DATE>March 11-18</DATE> through personal interviews with
nearly 2,000 adults chosen at random. <PERSON>Roper</PERSON> said the margin of
error was about <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880324-0247 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-88 1951EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Reagan-Panama 2ndLd-Writethru a0865 03-24 0388</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan-Panama, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0865,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Rules Out US Military Force to Oust Noriega</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Subs grafs 7-9 bgng: Meanwhile, the ... with 2 grafs to add
confirmation from AID.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> is not going to play ``big colossus of the North'' and use
military force to get Panamanian strongman Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON> out of power.
   In a question-and-answer session with high school students in
this <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> suburb, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was asked if he thought it would be
necessary to resume <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military control in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> to protect the
safety of the canal zone.
   ``No, we're going to abide by the canal treaty (relinquishing
the canal to the Panamanians by the turn of the century),'' he
replied. ``And we're not going to be the big colossus of the <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>
once again, coming in to ... our smaller neighbors' places of
living and business and trying to guide and direct them.''
   The president said the Panamanians ``have a very difficult
problem there. We think that they're moving toward solving it with
the reaction of the people to the man that has caused so much of
this problem.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> wants ``to be of help in any way
we can, and so we've helped them in that regard in the economic
restraints that we've put down there so that there can be pressure
focused on this particular individual.''
   ``But there's no danger of us coming in with our power and
muscle and saying, `This is the way it has to be.'''
agreed to release <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> in emergency funds to buy food for the
poor in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>.
   The food will be purchased in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> if it is available and
distributed through <ORGANIZATION>Caritas</ORGANIZATION>, a Catholic relief agency said AID
spokesman <PERSON>Jim Kunder</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> is out of cash because <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> cut off the supply of
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars, the Panamanian national currency, in a bid to drive
Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio Noriega</PERSON> into exile. The general was indicted in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> <DATE>last month</DATE> on federal cocaine trafficking charges.
   The Panamanian government was unable to fully meet a <MONEY>$33 million</MONEY>
payroll for 130,000 public employees earlier this month, touching
off a series of strikes and massive demonstrations by workers once
considered loyal to <PERSON>Noriega</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880324-0241 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-24-88 1909EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Reagan-Panama 1stLd-Writethru a0811 03-24 0451</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Reagan-Panama, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0811,400</SECOND>
<HEAD>Reagan Rules Out US Military Force to Oust Noriega</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Adds 5 grafs to UPDATE with senator saying AID to provide
emergency food relief to Panama.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>VIENNA, Va. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> is not going to play ``big colossus of the North'' and use
military force to get Panamanian strongman Gen. <PERSON>Manuel Antonio
Noriega</PERSON> out of power.
   In a question-and-answer session with high school students in
this <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> suburb, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> was asked if he thought it would be
necessary to resume <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military control in <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> to protect the
safety of the canal zone.
   ``No, we're going to abide by the canal treaty (relinquishing
the canal to the Panamanians by the turn of the century),'' he
replied. ``And we're not going to be the big colossus of the <ORGANIZATION>North</ORGANIZATION>
once again, coming in to ... our smaller neighbors' places of
living and business and trying to guide and direct them.''
   The president said the Panamanians ``have a very difficult
problem there. We think that they're moving toward solving it with
the reaction of the people to the man that has caused so much of
this problem.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> wants ``to be of help in any way
we can, and so we've helped them in that regard in the economic
restraints that we've put down there so that there can be pressure
focused on this particular individual.''
   ``But there's no danger of us coming in with our power and
muscle and saying, `This is the way it has to be.'''
   Meanwhile, the office of <PERSON>Sen. Alfonse D'Amato</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-N.Y.</LOCATION>, said that
emergency food to the people of <LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION>, at least <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> worth of
food per day to be distributed through <ORGANIZATION>Caritas</ORGANIZATION>, a Catholic relief
agency.
   The money for the food would come from the federal disaster
relief fund, said <PERSON>Ed Martin</PERSON>, a D'Amato spokesman. He said he did
