<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880805-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-05-88 0057EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Soviets-Mars 2ndLd-Writethru a0767 08-05 0588</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviets-Mars, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0767,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets May Develop Atomic Rocket For Mars Mission, Official Says</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 5th graf, ``Included in,'' to CORRECT spelling of rocket
to Energia sted Ergenia</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Soviets hope to develop an atomic-powered
rocket engine to provide the propulsion for a manned mission to
Mars early in the <DATE>21th century</DATE>, a Russian scientist said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Vasiliy I. Moroz</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION> said
experts in his nation believe that ``a new type of rocket'' will
have to be developed to make a planned 1{-year voyage to and from
Mars.
   <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said Soviet engineers are working on an
``atomic-electric'' rocket engine that would be used to accelerate
a Mars explorer craft once it has been boosted into <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit.
   The Soviet scientist, speaking at a news conference at the 20th
general assembly of the <ORGANIZATION>International Astronomical Union</ORGANIZATION>, declined
to give any details on the atomic-electric rocket, but he said none
of the current chemical rockets used by the Soviets is large enough
for a Mars mission.
   Included in the Soviet fleet of launch rockets is the <LOCATION>Energia</LOCATION>,
the world's largest, but <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said even it is not powerful enough.
   American space scientists long have recognized the need to
develop propulsion systems that did not depend upon the chemical
reaction of fuel and oxidizer. The <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION> has conducted some research on electric and ion
drive rockets, but the project has never been received money for
development.
   <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said the Soviets are giving the exploration of Mars a high
priority. Two Soviets probes to <LOCATION>Phobos</LOCATION>, a moon of <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, were
launched last month.
   In <DATE>1994</DATE>, he said, the Soviets will send an unmanned craft to
Mars carrying a robot rover that would explore hundreds of miles on
the planet's surface. The rover also would take drill samples and
measurements of the atmosphere.
   The next stage of the program, <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said, is testing in space
new technical elements needed for a manned mission, including the
atomic-electric rocket and a rocket to return to orbit from the
Mars surface. The Soviets also plan a robot craft that would land
on Mars, collect soil samples and then return them to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   A manned Martian mission could be mounted by the year <DATE>2005</DATE> or
<DATE>2010</DATE>, <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said. Preliminary plans call for a six-member crew to
make the voyage in a two-stage craft that would be assembled in
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit, he said.
   Although the Soviets have gathered a great amount of information
about the de-conditioning effects on the human body of longterm
space flight, <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said the Mars mission may use artificial
gravity to keep the crew members healthy.
   Both American and Soviet studies have shown that long exposure
to the weightlessness of space causes the heart to weaken and the
body to lose bone mass.
   <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said the Soviets hope that American scientists and
astronauts will take part in the Mars mission, but even without
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> participation, the Soviets are determined to explore the red
planet.
   Mars has been only partially explored by the American Viking
spacecraft, he said, adding: ``It is our impression that it is time
to return to Mars.''
   Soviet scientists want to search for traces of liquid water on
the Martian surface and still hold out hope that there may be life,
even though Viking found no traces, <PERSON>Moroz</PERSON> said.
   ``You can't give guarantees that life in some form doesn't exist
there now, despite the negative findings of Viking,'' he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870818-0040 </DOCNO>
<HL> Ride Urges NASA
To Examine Earth
And Explore Mars
---
By Laurie McGinley
<DD> 08/18/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> GOVMT
AEROSPACE (ARO) </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Astronaut <PERSON>Sally Ride</PERSON>, warning that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> has relinquished its leadership in space in crucial areas, urged a detailed examination of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> from orbit and the human exploration of Mars early in the next century. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON>'s long-awaited report represents the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s latest effort to get the beleaguered <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space program back on track following last year's Challenger accident. 
The space shuttle catastrophe made <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s "shortcomings starkly apparent," said <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON>, who will leave the space agency next month to take a post at a <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> think tank. 

   The report to <PERSON>James Fletcher</PERSON>, administrator of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>, said that while the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> pioneered exploration of Mars using unmanned spacecraft, no American spacecraft has visited the planet since <DATE>1976</DATE>. 
By contrast, the Soviets have announced an extensive exploration program using robots. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> also is far behind the Soviets in inhabiting "low-earth orbit" space stations; while the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> hasn't had a space station since <ORGANIZATION>Skylab</ORGANIZATION> was vacated in <DATE>1974</DATE>, the Soviets have had eight space stations in orbit since the mid-1970s, the report said. 

   In mapping a blueprint for the revitalization of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space effort, <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON> studied four options: 

   --"Mission to Planet Earth," which would use satellites in low-earth orbit, an orbit as far as 350 miles from the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, to examine the earth's atmosphere, ocean topography and vegetation. 

   --Exploration of the solar system, which would send unmanned spacecraft to a comet, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> and Mars for detailed study. 

   --"Moon Output," which would call for a return to the moon by the year <DATE>2000</DATE>, leading eventually to a permanent lunar base for research and observation. 

   --"Humans to Mars," which would aim at landing Americans on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> early in the <DATE>21st century</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON>, in evaluating the options, didn't give the space agency explicit advice on how to proceed. 
But she did suggest that the most constructive strategy would be to focus initially on the Earth-observation program, while making plans to return to the moon and eventually to visit Mars. 
At the same time, she urged the agency to "solidly support" unmanned planetary exploration through the next decade. 

   <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON> didn't provide cost estimates, but said such programs will have to stay within the fiscal constraints that <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> will face in coming years. 

   While acknowledging that exploring and settling Mars "should be the ultimate objectives of human exploration," <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON> warned against a "rush headlong toward Mars." 
She added, "We should adopt a strategy to continue an orderly expansion outward from the earth." 

   <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON>'s report may displease those who have urged <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> to adopt, with great fanfare, the human inhabitation of Mars as the space agency's next big goal. 
Some believe that only such a glamorous, high-profile project can recapture the public's interest in the space program. 

   But others have argued that the space agency should follow a more gradual approach to future exploration. 
In her report, <PERSON>Ms. Ride</PERSON> seemed to endorse the latter by calling for "a strategy of evolution and natural progression." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06189040 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06189040 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Jason M. Grow -- Mercury News; Lewis Hitchner, seated, and
Michael McGreevy research virtual reality; PHOTO: A 'virtual reality' look at
Mars' Valles Marineris. The monitors provide basic images but the goggles,
connected to a computer, allow a three-dimensional picture that changes as the
wearer's head turns, simulating the panorama he or she would see if really
visiting the planet.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPACE; RESEARCH; PROGRAM; US; FACILITY; MOUNTAIN-VIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The next stop on our tour of Mars National Park is a vista point overlooking
the red-rock canyons of Valles Marineris, an awesome fissure that makes Planet
Earth's Grand Canyon look like a golf divot.;    Looking down from the Martian
ridge where we're standing, Valles Marineris is as deep as Mount Everest is
high. To the left, the 3,000-mile-long canyon stretches to the horizon. Behind
us are rocky side canyons.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NASA BRINGS MARTIAN LANDSCAPE TO LIFE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Our guides to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>' rugged terrain are a pair of visionary engineers at the
<ORGANIZATION>NASA/Ames Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in Mountain View with a "virtual reality" system
that takes users to the red planet.;    At least, almost. Virtual reality is,
as the engineers say, a metaphor.;    "You can put on goggles and feel what
it's like to be there," said <PERSON>Michael McGreevy</PERSON>, 41, the principal engineer in
the <ORGANIZATION>Human Interface Research Branch</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Ames facility. "Is it as good as really going there? Hell,
no. But it's better than not going at all.";    Unlike flat computer screens,
virtual reality presents information in the way humans are used to getting it
-- interactively and all around them. As a sensor tracks head and hand
movements, a computer adjusts the scene on miniature computer screens mounted
in goggles that resemble scuba masks.;    "When you put on the head-mounted
display, you get the impression the panorama is wrapped around in space, just
as if you were really there in a three-dimensional world," said <PERSON>Lewis
Hitchner</PERSON>, <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>'s partner.;    American researchers are developing
applications ranging from virtual walk-throughs of architectural plans to the
design of new planes to video games and simulated sex. In <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, where virtual
reality is known as "tele-existence," a government-industry partnership is
exploring the technology for super-teleconferencing.;    <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hitchner</PERSON>
want to use virtual reality to democratize planetary exploration. If they get
their way, the half-dozen adventurous astronauts chosen to blast off for <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>
will be accompanied by hundreds of geologists able to wander around Mars in a
"virtual environment.";    <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>, who has led the research team with a
shoestring budget since <DATE>1984</DATE>, hopes his project will be included in next
year's Mars Observer mission. The orbiting spacecraft, which will take about
nine months to get to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, will use lasers to map every meter of the surface
of the planet. Feeding the data into a virtual reality system could give
researchers their first chance to "explore" the whole planet in detail.;   
Robots as camera carriers;  Ultimately, <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> dreams of a room-size virtual
reality facility in which scientists at <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> or at a manned Mars
base could personally interact with the terrain through robotic rovers
equipped with cameras, mechanical arms and other devices.;    Wearing goggles
and wired with sensors, geologists would wander around the virtual environment
looking under virtual outcroppings and picking up virtual rock samples in the
same way they would conduct field research on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Their activities would
send signals to the rover, which would carry out the tasks on Mars.;    That
would be a huge advance over <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>'s first virtual environment. As a
16-year-old on vacation in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, he snapped photographs of the <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower</ORGANIZATION>.
At home, he pasted the pictures to the inside of a sphere and put his head
inside.;    Wraparound photos;  "Suddenly, I had this overwhelming feeling
that I was there," he said.;    Now, <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hitchner</PERSON> can pick any
coordinate on Mars and load it up for exploration in less than 20 minutes. Of
course their simulation is only as accurate as the available data, which at
present are plot-points spaced one kilometer apart, gathered by the <DATE>1972</DATE>
Mariner 9 expedition.;    That's enough for breathtaking stationary views from
vista points such as the one overlooking <PERSON>Valles Marineris</PERSON>, named after the
expedition that discovered it, and for less-detailed views while "flying.";   
"Would I like to get out and hike?" <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> said. "Sure. We're working on it."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAVID BANK, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910707  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  723  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 7, 1991
00189040,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06190113 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06190113 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Jason M. Grow -- Mercury News; Lewis Hitchner, seated, and
Michael McGreevy research virtual reality; PHOTO: FRESH LOOK -- A 'virtual
reality' look at Mars' Valles Marineris. The monitors provide basic images,
but the goggles, connected to a computer, allow a three-dimensional picture
that changes as the wearer's head turns, simulating the panorama one would see
if really visiting the planet.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; ORGANIZATION; PROFESSIONAL; COMPUTER; DESIGN  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The next stop on our tour of Mars National Park is a vista point overlooking
the red-rock canyons of Valles Marineris, an awesome fissure that makes Planet
Earth's Grand Canyon look like a golf divot.;    Looking down from the Martian
ridge where we're standing, Valles Marineris is as deep as Mount Everest is
high. To the left, the 3,000-mile-long canyon stretches to the horizon. Behind
us are rocky side canyons.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NASA BRINGS MARS LANDSCAPE VIRTUALLY ALIVE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Our guides to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>' rugged terrain are a pair of visionary engineers at the
<ORGANIZATION>NASA/Ames Research Center</ORGANIZATION> in Mountain View with a "virtual reality" system
that takes users to the red planet.;    At least, almost. Virtual reality is,
as the engineers say, a metaphor.;    "You can put on goggles and feel what
it's like to be there," said <PERSON>Michael McGreevy</PERSON>, 41, the principal engineer in
the <ORGANIZATION>Human Interface Research Branch</ORGANIZATION> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s Ames facility. "Is it as good as really going there? Hell,
no. But it's better than not going at all.";    Unlike flat computer screens,
virtual reality presents information in the way humans are used to getting it
-- interactively and all around them. As a sensor tracks head and hand
movements, a computer adjusts the scene on miniature computer screens mounted
in goggles that resemble scuba masks.;    Wraparound display;  "When you put
on the head-mounted display, you get the impression the panorama is wrapped
around in space, just as if you were really there in a three-dimensional
world," said <PERSON>Lewis Hitchner</PERSON>, <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>'s partner.;    American researchers are
developing applications ranging from virtual walk-throughs of architectural
plans to the design of new planes to video games and simulated sex. In <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>,
a government-industry partnership is exploring the technology for
super-teleconferencing.;    <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hitchner</PERSON> want to use virtual reality
to democratize planetary exploration. If they get their way, the half-dozen
adventurous astronauts chosen to blast off for <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> will be accompanied by
hundreds of geologists able to wander around Mars in a "virtual environment.";
   <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>, who has led the research team with a shoestring budget since
<DATE>1984</DATE>, hopes his project will be included in next year's Mars Observer mission.
The orbiting spacecraft, which will take about nine months to get to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>,
will use lasers to map every meter of the surface of the planet. Feeding the
data into a virtual reality system could give researchers their first chance
to "explore" the whole planet in detail.;    Robots as camera carriers; 
Ultimately, <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON> dreams of a room-size virtual reality facility in which
scientists at <ORGANIZATION>Mission Control</ORGANIZATION> or at a manned Mars base could personally
interact with the terrain through robotic rovers equipped with cameras,
mechanical arms and other devices.;    Wearing goggles and wired with sensors,
geologists would wander around the virtual environment looking under virtual
outcroppings and picking up virtual rock samples in the same way they would
conduct field research on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. Their activities would send signals to the
rover, which would carry out the tasks on Mars.;    That would be a huge
advance over <PERSON>McGreevy</PERSON>'s first virtual environment. As a 16-year-old on
vacation in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, he snapped photographs of the <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower</ORGANIZATION>. At home, he
pasted the pictures to the inside of a sphere and put his head inside.;   
"Suddenly, I had this overwhelming feeling that I was there," he said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DAVID BANK, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910708  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  620  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday July 8, 1991
00190113,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881130-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-30-88 0309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Soviets-Mars     11-30 0593</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviets-Mars,590</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets May Delay Mars Exploration For Better Rover</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A Soviet space official says <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> may push
back the planned launch date of an unmanned mission to Mars to
incorporate improved technology in both the spacecraft and the
robotic rover that will retrieve samples of the red planet.
   <PERSON>Genrich A. Avanesov</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Space Research Institute of the Soviet
Academy of Sciences</ORGANIZATION>, told a space conference <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> that it may be
in the Soviets' interest to put off the planned <DATE>1994</DATE> mission for
about two years.
   ``Technically we do have the possibility to send a mission by
<DATE>1994</DATE> with a Martian rover, but we're not sure it's worth doing,''
<PERSON>Avanesov</PERSON> said after a presentation to the conference on space
automation and robotics. ``It may be worth doing a more intellectual
mission later.''
   Asked whether funding for the mission was a problem, he said:
``Money is a problem today for us, too.''
   Avanesov emphasized that no official decision has been made on
the timing of the mission.
   Rescheduling the mission would enable the Soviets to use findings
of a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mission to Mars that is planned for <DATE>1993</DATE>. On that mission,
an unmanned probe called the Mars Observer is to take photographs of
Mars' surface while orbiting the planet for about two years.
   The Soviet mission will send a robotic rover to explore the red
planet's surface and return samples of its soil and atmosphere to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Experts in both countries have agreed that unmanned missions to
probe the surface of Mars will be necessary before a manned mission
can be launched, but it will take several years to develop the
necessary automation and robotics.
   ``No research breakthroughs seem to be required, but a great deal
will be needed,'' <PERSON>Lew Allen</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory, said in a paper presented to the conference.
   A Martian rover will need to be able to avoid hazards on the
planet's surface when it lands, negotiate the terrain, preserve soil
and atmospheric samples, and rendezvous with its launcher, he said.
   ``We see that the rover should be an intellectual one,'' with
sophisticated automation, <PERSON>Avanesov</PERSON> said. ``The question of the
autonomy is a very serious one ... and should be specially
a second unmanned mission to the planet to follow the Mars Observer,
<PERSON>Aaron Cohen</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, told the
conference.
   He said a mission could be launched in <DATE>1998</DATE> to land a robotic
rover on the surface of Mars, gather samples of soil, rock and
atmosphere, and return the samples to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> in <DATE>2001</DATE>.
   ``The delivery and return phases ... offer many technical and
engineering challenges,'' he said. ``It taxes our automation
capabilities.''
   Soviet plans to explore Mars, culminating with a manned mission
around <DATE>2010</DATE> to <DATE>2015</DATE>, are the top priority of <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>'s space program,
<PERSON>Avanesov</PERSON> said, adding: ``We think this Mars project will give us
broad opportunity for international cooperation.''
   His paper to the conference said the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Soviet
Union</LOCATION> could work together on certain aspects of a Mars program,
including organization of a joint ground-based network of data
reception, joint data interpretation, creation of a joint data bank
on the Martian atmosphere and other exchanges of information.
   Soviet and <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials have met twice this year in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
to exchange information. They also are making plans to fly American
instruments on future Soviet missions and Soviet instruments on
future <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> flights.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901004-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-04-90 1047EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MarsRover     10-04 0408</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Mars Rover,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robby the Robot Negotiates Canyon in Mars Rover Test</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Robby, a <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> robot rover vehicle
designed to explore Mars, successfully picked its way along a rocky
dry river bed without human help, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said.
   ``This is the first time that an autonomous vehicle has ever
navigated rugged terrain using video cameras,'' said <PERSON>Roger Bedard</PERSON>,
planetary rover program manager at the space agency's Jet
Propulsion Laboratory. ``Robby himself wouldn't go to Mars. He's a
test vehicle.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> called the <DATE>Sept. 13</DATE> test ``a significant milestone'' in
developing a planet-roving, computer-guided vehicle that would
explore Mars to find suitable landing sites for a manned mission to
the red planet.
   It will be about <DATE>1995</DATE> before engineers fully develop rover
technology, and about <DATE>2000</DATE> before one can be built to go to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   During the test, <PERSON>Robby</PERSON> took four hours, 20 minutes to crawl
along a 109-yard course in the rugged <PERSON>Arroyo Seco</PERSON>, a dry river bed
in a canyon next to the laboratory. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> wants a real Mars rover to
travel about 13 miles daily.
   <PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said engineers told <PERSON>Robby</PERSON> where it was and where it was
supposed to go, but the six-wheeled vehicle used its twin
television cameras and computer to navigate a safe course around
boulders and other obstacles. Other tests were conducted last week.
   Robby is about 15 feet long, 6 feet wide and 6 feet tall. It was
named after <PERSON>Robby</PERSON> the Robot in ``Forbidden Planet,'' a <DATE>1956</DATE> science
fiction film.
   The robot's television cameras give it stereoscopic vision,
allowing it a three-dimensional look at objects about 6{ feet in
front of it. Robby moves about 6{ feet at a time, then stops to
survey another 6{-foot stretch of terrain before proceeding.
   Robby runs on a battery recharged by an onboard gasoline
generator. A Mars rover would be powered by the radioactive decay
of plutonium, <PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said.
   The only unmanned rovers to explore another planet were two
Soviet Lunakod vehicles that explored the moon in the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>,
<PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> astronauts used a manned vehicle on the moon.
have specific plans to put rovers on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said. The Soviets
are considering using rovers and terrain-hopping balloons during a
<DATE>1994</DATE> mission to Mars.
   During the past week, 30-foot-tall balloons that would
repeatedly rise and settle on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>' surface were tested in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s desert by engineers from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and
the <ORGANIZATION>Planetary Society</ORGANIZATION>, a group that advocates space exploration.
   Balloons have the advantage of not needing to navigate rough
terrain, rising during the heat of day and settling to the Martian
surface at night to take measurements.
   <PERSON>Bedard</PERSON> said rovers can be directed to explore areas of
scientific interest, rather than taking a route that depends on
prevailing winds.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900417-0003
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900417-0003.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Politics &amp; Policy:
   U.S., Soviets Urged
   To Begin Exploring
   Mars With Robots
   ---
   National Academy of Sciences
   Envisions Separate Trips
   Beginning as Early as 2000
   ----
   By Bob Davis
</HL>
<DATE>
04/17/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A24
</SO>
<CO>
   FREST
</CO>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
INDUSTRIAL EQUIPMENT, MACHINE TOOLS (IND)
</IN>
<GV>
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT (FDL)
</GV>
<LP>
   WASHINGTON -- A National Academy of Sciences report
proposed that the U.S. and the Soviet Union work closely
together to explore Mars with robots.
   Eugene Levy, who headed the academy report, said he
envisioned a $10 billion project in which the U.S. launched
three "excursions" that would land robotic rovers on Mars as
early as the year 2000, dig for soil samples and return them
to Earth. The U.S. would also set up a series of robotic
weather and seismic stations on Mars. The Soviet Union, he
said, would be expected to launch three similar missions of
its own.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Exploring Mars has long been the dream of planetary
scientists and government space officials world-wide. But
there is a sharp difference of opinion over whether
astronauts must be part of this exploration. Astronauts have
abilities to explore that machines can't begin to match, but
astronauts drive the costs to mind-numbing levels. For
estimates the cost of setting up a manned base on the <PERSON>Moon</PERSON>
and sending astronauts to Mars early next century at about
<MONEY>$500 billion</MONEY> in <DATE>1991</DATE> dollars.
   Any manned exploration of Mars would be preceded by
robots. But <PERSON>Mr. Levy</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Arizona</ORGANIZATION>'s
planetary science department, said that robotic missions
should be judged independently. "The overall social and
technological benefits of a robotic Mars exploration are so
large it would be a mistake to forgo them," he said.
   Robotic missions would require exceptionally sophisticated
machinery, computers and communications. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now is
experimenting with vehicles that use wheels or legs to cross
rough terrain, and have sufficient intelligence to avoid
areas they can't traverse. Mars is so distant that
controllers wouldn't be able to steer the vehicles from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The academy report said that robotic exploration could
best be accomplished by closely planning separate missions
with the Soviets. That way each country's robots could
explore different areas and the findings would be shared,
reducing the overall cost and expanding the scientific return
for both sides. <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> also would probably
participate, the report said, but on teams controlled by the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   The report recommended against a joint project with the
Soviets, however, in which the Soviets probably would develop
rockets and the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> would make the robots. A cooling of
political relations between the countries could doom the
project before it was completed, the report warned. A joint
mission would also deny each participant the ability to fully
develop new technologies, the report said, and lead to
worries about transferring valuable technology to a potential
   The <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> administration has said it would begin talks with
the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and other countries about cooperating in the
exploration of the <LOCATION>Moon</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, but hasn't said what
structure it prefers.
   <PERSON>Mark Craig</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s director of exploration, said he
favored closely related, but separate missions with the
Soviets. "You date before you get married," he said.
   Returning samples from Mars could help settle questions of
whether life ever existed on Mars, and why Mars and Earth
evolved so differently. Scientists have long pondered what's
known as the "Goldilocks paradox" of planetary evolution:
Mars turned out too cold, <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> too hot and Earth just right
for life to develop.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now is debating which of several unmanned planetary
missions to ask <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to approve for the year beginning
<DATE>Oct. 1, 1996</DATE>, including possible missions to <ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and
<LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881220-0015 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-20-88 0117EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SpacePlans Bjt   12-20 0808</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Plans, Bjt,810</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Blueprint Envisions Mars Missions, Martian Moon Station</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEBORAH MESCE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is laying the groundwork to send the next
generation of astronauts beyond the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s orbit early in the <DATE>21st
century</DATE>, with missions to Mars and a space station on a Martian moon
among the possibilities.
   In a report released <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION> said the nation must make a ``modest investment of
resources'' during the <DATE>1990s</DATE> to prepare the nation for a range of
opportunities in space.
   ``This ability is critical to <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> leadership in
space,'' said the report titled, ``Beyond Earth's Boundaries: Human
Exploration of the Solar System in the 21st Century.''
   The report examined several strategies for exploring the inner
reaches of the solar system, including establishing a manned lunar
observatory, setting up a space station on the Martian moon Phobos
or sending astronauts to the red planet itself early in the next
century.
   The ambitious blueprint addresses President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s directive on
space policy issued last <DATE>January</DATE>. The directive sets as a long-range
goal ``to expand human presence and activity beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit into
the solar system.''
   <PERSON>Frank Martin</PERSON>, assistant administrator of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Office of
Exploration</ORGANIZATION>, said ``there's every indication'' the <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
administration will support that policy.
   The underpinnings of any strategy to send space explorers to the
moon and beyond in the next two decades will be increased <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
funding for development of new technology, life sciences research,
unmanned robotic missions, development of a new fleet of launch
vehicles able to lift heavier loads, and continued commitment to
Space Station Freedom, which is planned for Earth orbit in the
mid-1990s.
   If those conditions are met, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> could send
astronauts to Phobos in <DATE>2003</DATE> or to Mars in <DATE>2007</DATE> or establish by <DATE>2005</DATE>
a lunar base from which astronauts could build a Mars outpost in
<DATE>2015</DATE>, said <PERSON>John Aaron</PERSON>, who headed the <ORGANIZATION>Office of Exploration</ORGANIZATION> during
production of the report.
   <PERSON>Aaron</PERSON> said the agency has not developed reliable cost estimates
for the missions studied in the report. ``We are not talking about
missions that are cheap,'' he said, but ``we think these are
affordable.''
   <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said such missions probably could be accomplished at less
real cost than the Apollo program, which put <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> astronauts on the
moon in <DATE>1969</DATE>. At its height, the Apollo program cost about <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT>
of the federal budget annually, which in today's dollars would be
about <MONEY>$25 billion</MONEY>, he said.
   ``You can't do the civil space program on the cheap,'' he said,
noting the nation now spends about <MONEY>$11 billion</MONEY> annually on <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
programs. The fiscal <DATE>1989</DATE> federal budget is about <MONEY>$1.1 trillion</MONEY>.
   ``We're not a poor nation. We can figure out how to do these
things if they're important to us,'' he said, adding that
international cooperation could help support these missions.
   <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> must leap many technological hurdles before it
can accomplish the goal of establishing a permanent human presence
in space, but ``I don't see any show stoppers there.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Project Pathfinder, under whose umbrella much of the
research will be done, gets <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> this year and the same
amount next year, despite <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s request for <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>. <PERSON>Martin</PERSON>
said annual funding for the program must increase to <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>
soon.
   The report focused on four case studies for sending astronauts to
the moon, Phobos and Mars. One scenario would send astronauts to
Phobos and then on to Mars; another would launch astronauts directly
to Mars; a third would establish a manned observatory on the far
side of the moon; and a fourth would use an outpost on the moon as a
stepping stone to Mars.
   Aaron, who is now special assistant to the director at <ORGANIZATION>Johnson
Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, emphasized that the four case studies are not proposed
missions, but rather vehicles for assessing exploration techniques
and validating assumptions.
   A key finding, <PERSON>Aaron</PERSON> said, is that a mission to Phobos could
significantly offset the scale and uncertainties of a direct mission
to Mars.
   An Earth-to-Mars mission would require many new technologies,
including advanced propulsion and braking systems, and would require
advanced operations such as in-orbit assembly, long-term storage and
in-orbit transfer of propellant. Much work in the life sciences also
would be needed, and because the mission would last more than 14
months artificial gravity might be needed to maintain the health of
the crew, the report said.
   Phobos is believed to be an asteroid ``captured'' by <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>'
gravity and is thought to contain a substantial amount of water and
carbon-based materials, which could offer potential sources of
rocket fuel that could be tapped for exploratory missions to Mars.
   ``Phobos is an attractive way to go to Mars,'' <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said. ``I
would be surprised if Phobos isn't a part of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> going to
Mars.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890419-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-89 1330EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-ReturntothePlanets Adv23-2Takes   04-19 0902</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Return to the Planets, Adv 23 - 2 Takes,0917</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv23</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, April 23, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Back to the Planets _ Shuttle Carrying Venus-Bound Craft</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Story is complete in one take; optional 1st Add is for editors
desiring more detail and background</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The shuttle Atlantis is set to soar
into space <DATE>Friday</DATE> to rekindle an American planetary exploration
program that has languished for a decade because of budget cuts and
the Challenger accident.
   The cargo is the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft which has a radar system
powerful enough to pierce the dense sulfuric acid clouds of Venus
and map its surface. The mission costs <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> and the radar
images could reveal much about the history of <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and the
evolution of our own <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Liftoff is scheduled for <TIME>2:24 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and six hours later,
<PERSON>Atlantis</PERSON>' five astronauts are to release <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> on the start of a
466-day outward journey to the mysterious planet.
   No American planetary spacecraft has been launched since the
Pioneer-Venus probe in <DATE>1978</DATE>, and <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will be the first
planet-bound vehicle to be dispatched from the space shuttle.
   When the 7,000-pound payload reaches <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> in <DATE>August 1990</DATE>, it is
to fire into orbit and start its 243-day mapping assignment.
   ``The goal is to obtain radar images of at least <PERCENT>70 percent</PERCENT> of
the planet,'' said <PERSON>Stephen Saunders</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> project scientist at
   He said the images could help scientists understand how Venus
was formed and might provide an answer to the puzzling question of
how Earth and <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, evolved so differently even though at the
beginning of the solar system they were almost identical. At the
Venusian surface, the temperature is 900 degrees Fahrenheit and the
atmospheric pressure is 90 times greater than that on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> pictures might answer questions about
the extent of volcanic activity and settle disputes over whether
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON> once had oceans of water and whether it has shifting crustal
plates similar to those on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The radar is designed to produce images showing features as
small as 150 yards across. In comparison, the <DATE>1978</DATE> Pioneer-Venus
probe could not distinguish features smaller than 60 miles across.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is the first of two planetary craft scheduled for
launching from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION> this year. The <ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> probe to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> is
to set forth in <DATE>October</DATE>.
   The two spacecraft have been in development for more than a
decade. They initially were delayed by budget cuts resulting from a
slowdown in the space program after the completion of the Apollo
man-to-the-moon program.
   They finally were assigned to shuttle missions set for liftoff
in <DATE>1986</DATE>. But those flights were derailed after Challenger exploded
in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>, grounding the shuttle fleet for nearly three years.
   ``It's been a long time coming,'' <PERSON>Saunders</PERSON> said.
   The first manmade spacecraft to probe another planet was
<LOCATION>Russia</LOCATION>'s Venera 1, which scouted Venus in <DATE>1961</DATE>. In the years that
followed, a parade of these vehicles, each more sophisticated than
the last, pushed deep into the solar system to take the pulse of
our planetary neighbors.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has successfully sent five probes to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
six to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, four to <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, three to <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, and one each to
<ORGANIZATION>Mercury</ORGANIZATION> and Uranus. And in <DATE>August</DATE>, the long-traveling Voyager 2 is
to take the first closeup look at <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has sent 19 successful spacecraft to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and
nine to Mars. Its most recent and most ambitious probes both failed
_ Phobos 1 <DATE>last September</DATE> while en route to Mars and Phobos 2 as it
was starting its exploration from Martian orbit last month.
   Soviet engineers have not perfected the long-term
nuclear-powered batteries needed to travel to the outer planets.
The Soviet craft employ solar panels which draw electrical power
from the sun. But at distant <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> and Uranus,
these panels would be too far from the sun to be effective.
   At their destinations, some of these robot marvels skim close,
snapping pictures and gathering a few days of data before soaring
on to another planet or into interstellar space; some orbit their
targets to examine them at length, and some descend to the surface.
   What they collect is flashed as binary bits to Earth-bound
computers, which translate the unknown into recognizable places
filled with surprises and secrets. Vague speculations of the past
have been replaced by solid scientific findings.
   Humans have caught their first views and hints of the great
storm systems and rings of <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>; the active volcanoes on its
salt-covered moon, Io; the parched and cratered wasteland of
Mercury; ancient river bottoms, raging winds and an inactive
volcanoe almost 80,000 feet high on Mars; sulfuric acid clouds,
lightning and the hellish temperatures on Venus; the thousand rings
and tantalizing moons of <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>; a scalding 6,000-mile deep ocean
beneath the cloudtops of Uranus.
   From these flights, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is assembling a vast mosaic about the
solar system and its intricate workings. A basic goal is to learn
more about planet <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, fitting it into the cosmic puzzle that is
the origin, the evolution and the structure of the universe.
   Some astronomers believe, for example, that Mars may today
represent an earlier evolutionary state of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> when its
atmosphere was being formed, and that <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> may represent what
might happen to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> if its surface temperature were to rise
significantly.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881110-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-10-88 1321EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-US-SovietSpace     11-10 0424</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Soviet Space,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. To Help Soviets Pick Mars Landing Site For Robot Craft</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to help pick a landing site on
Mars for a robot craft that the Soviets will launch in <DATE>1994</DATE>,
American and Soviet scientists announced <DATE>Thursday</DATE> at a joint news
conference.
   <PERSON>Samuel W. Keller</PERSON>, the head of the <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> delegation that has been
negotiating with Soviet scientists, said that the Soviets have
picked four candidate landing sites after the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> provided
detailed maps of the Martian surface.
   <PERSON>Keller</PERSON> said the Soviets have now asked for more data and details
on the candidate sites.
   He made the comment at a news conference marking the end of a
week of negotiations between representatives of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> and a delegation representing
the Soviet solar system exploration program. The two groups met to
work out areas of cooperation.
   Academician <PERSON>Valeriy L. Barsukov</PERSON>, head of the Soviet delegation,
said that the four candidate Mars landing sites are all located
within 30 degrees of the equator, but he declined to be more
specific.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> accumulated a vast amount of detailed images and maps of
Mars during Viking spacecraft missions between <DATE>1975</DATE> and <DATE>1980</DATE>. The
Viking program put two craft in orbit of Mars and two on the surface.
   The Soviets plan to launch a spacecraft in <DATE>1994</DATE> that will orbit
Mars and drop a lander that will scoop up soil and return it to
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Barsukov</PERSON> said that in picking a landing site the Soviets are
considering such issues as a search for water and life, getting
comprehensive samples of the geology, and gaining insights into the
Martian evolution.
   <PERSON>Keller</PERSON> said other agreements reached during negotiations this
week included:
   _Using the <ORGANIZATION>American Deep Space Network</ORGANIZATION> to help track and
communicate with Soviet Mars probes.
   _An exchange of scientific personnel for work on specific
missions.
   _An exchange of data on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, a planet extensively explored by
both countries. <PERSON>Keller</PERSON> said the U.S.-Soviet studies are being
combined to produce four detailed maps.
   _An exchange of lunar material gathered by the Apollo program for
meteorite material collected by the Soviets.
   _An exchange of scientific instruments for use on planetary
probes.
   <PERSON>Barsukov</PERSON> said that the Soviets feel that a manned Mars landing is
``inevitable'' and that it probably will take place in the middle of
the next century.
   But before a manned mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> is attempted, <PERSON>Barsukov</PERSON> said
there probably will be new manned flights to the moon. He declined
to elaborate.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072189-0108 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 85044 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 21, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 26; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
927 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BUSH'S CALL FOR MISSION TO MARS RECEIVES BROAD SUPPORT FROM SPACE COMMUNITY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By LEE DYE, Times Science Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Without spending a nickel, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> won widespread support from dissident 
elements of the space community <DATE>Thursday</DATE> when he committed the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to 
embarking on a megabillion-dollar mission that will test human engineering and 
endurance to the limits. 
</P>
<P>
The manned expedition to Mars that the President endorsed is not simply a 
longer journey than a trip to the moon, which takes only about a day and a 
half. It could cost <MONEY>hundreds of billions of dollars</MONEY> over the next three decades 
and the crew aboard the spacecraft would have to endure enormous risks during a 
voyage that would last between two and three years. 
</P>
<P>
Despite those obstacles, leaders within the nation's space community hailed the 
President's proclamation because for the first time in more than a decade the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has a goal in space exploration mandated from the top. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Blueprint Remained Dormant 
</P>
<P>
"He has set our sights very clearly," said <PERSON>Thomas O. Paine</PERSON>, head of the 
and the chief architect of a congressionally mandated blueprint for the future 
of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space program -- a blueprint that has remained dormant since it was 
submitted to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> several years ago. 
</P>
<P>
"I think it's great," said <PERSON>John M. Logsdon</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Space Policy 
Institute</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>George Washington University</ORGANIZATION> and a leading space analyst. "The 
President did exactly the right thing. He gave the kind of overall direction to 
why we are putting humans in space that so many have thought has been lacking." 
</P>
<P>
Within hours of the President's speech, the nation's space community began 
healing some deep, self-inflicted wounds. Various factions have fought bitterly 
over which projects should get the highest priority, and that lack of unity has 
threatened to undermine congressional support for space exploration. 
</P>
<P>
"Actually, I have not been a chronic admirer of Republican presidents," said 
Caltech planetary scientist <PERSON>Bruce Murray</PERSON>, who directed the <ORGANIZATION>Jet Propulsion 
Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> during one of its most productive periods. "But <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said this is 
where we ought to go and that (sense of direction) has been the central problem 
since the end of Apollo." 
</P>
<P>
Like a number of other scientists across the country, <PERSON>Murray</PERSON> has been pushing 
for years for a manned expedition to Mars. He has consistently criticized plans 
to build a manned, orbiting space station, claiming that the <MONEY>$30-billion</MONEY> 
project -- which faces stiff opposition in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> -- is just another piece of 
equipment, not a goal. 
</P>
<P>
That criticism softened considerably <DATE>Thursday</DATE> on the heels of the President's 
speech because the space station, like so many other projects in the space 
program, could play a role in any effort to send astronauts to Mars. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Louis Friedman</PERSON>, executive director of the Pasadena-based Planetary Society and 
another outspoken critic of the space station, also eased his position after 
hearing <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s speech. 
</P>
<P>
The strongest criticism of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s statement stemmed from the fact that he did 
not outline the role that other nations would have in a manned expedition to 
Mars, and many believe that only an international program is likely to succeed. 
</P>
<P>
"International really means the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>," noted <PERSON>Murray</PERSON>, because the 
Soviets have the best information about the effects of long-term exposure to 
space. The record -- one year -- is held by a Soviet cosmonaut. 
</P>
<P>
A manned expedition to Mars would be costly, "probably <MONEY>hundreds of billions of 
dollars</MONEY> over a long period of time," but it's "not going to cost much extra 
over the next five years," <PERSON>Logsdon</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
What is needed now, <PERSON>Friedman</PERSON> said, is to work out the details on how such a 
mission should be approached. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the projects that would be precursors to a Mars mission are already on 
the drawing boards. The Jet Propulsion Laboratory is already developing plans 
for robotic, unmanned missions to Mars that would collect the information 
needed long before a manned expedition could be launched. 
</P>
<P>
The Freedom Space Station would serve as the beginning step toward a permanent 
manned presence in space. It would be followed by an "international spaceport" 
where large vehicles could be assembled in space so that they could be launched 
toward Mars without having to burn the fuel necessary to overcome <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s 
gravity. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Knowledge of Mining 
</P>
<P>
A manned laboratory on the moon would allow astronauts to learn how to mine 
materials for permanent facilities, and possibly even extract oxygen and 
hydrogen from the lunar surface to fuel their rocket ships. 
</P>
<P>
Even if all of that could be carried out successfully over the next couple of 
decades, the actual trip to Mars would be filled with such profound challenges 
that it may be beyond human endurance. 
</P>
<P>
Throughout the years-long trip, the astronauts would be faced with the 
possibility of a meteoroid ripping through their spacecraft, causing rapid 
decompression that would kill them within seconds. 
</P>
<P>
A violent storm on the surface of the sun could blast the spacecraft with 
deadly radiation. So the craft would require some sort of storm shelter. 
</P>
<P>
Throughout much of the trip, the craft would be so far from Earth that the 
astronauts would be pretty much on their own. It would take about 30 minutes 
for messages to travel back and forth between the craft and Earth by the time 
the astronauts reached the vicinity of Mars. 
</P>
<P>
The astronauts would probably have to spend a year there, waiting for Mars to 
reach the right point in its orbit for them to launch themselves back toward 
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
And it would take about a year to get back. 
</P></TEXT>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SPACE PROGRAMS -- UNITED STATES; SPACE EXPLORATION; MARS (PLANET); SPACE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881111-0149 </DOCNO>
<HL> NASA Will Help Soviets in Picking Mars Landing Site </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> GOVMT FREST </CO>
<IN> ARO </IN>
<DATELINE> WASHINGTON (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to help pick a landing site on Mars for a robot craft that the Soviets will launch in <DATE>1994</DATE>, American and Soviet scientists announced at a joint news conference. 

   <PERSON>Samuel W. Keller</PERSON>, the head of the <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> delegation that has been negotiating with Soviet scientists, said the Soviets have picked four possible landing sites after the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> provided detailed maps of the Martian surface. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Keller</PERSON> said the Soviets have now asked for more data and details on the candidate sites. 

   He made the comment at a news conference marking the end of a week of negotiations between representatives of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> and a delegation representing the Soviet solar system exploration program. 
The two groups met to work out areas of cooperation. 

   Academician <PERSON>Valeriy L. Barsukov</PERSON>, head of the Soviet delegation, said that the four candidate Mars landing sites are all within 30 degrees of the equator, but he declined to be more specific. 

   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> accumulated a vast amount of detailed images and maps of Mars during Viking spacecraft missions between <DATE>1975</DATE> and <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
The Viking program put two craft in orbit of Mars and two on the surface. 

   The Soviets plan to launch a spacecraft in <DATE>1994</DATE> that will orbit Mars and drop a lander that will scoop up soil and return it to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Barsukov</PERSON> said that in picking a landing site the Soviets are considering such issues as a search for water and life, getting comprehensive samples of the geology and gaining insights into the Martian evolution. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Keller</PERSON> said other agreements reached during negotiations this week included:
   --Using the <ORGANIZATION>American Deep Space Network</ORGANIZATION> to help track and communicate with Soviet Mars probes. 

   --An exchange of scientific personnel for work on specific missions. 

   --An exchange of data on <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>, a planet extensively explored by both countries. 
<PERSON>Mr. Keller</PERSON> said the U.S.-Soviet studies are being combined to produce four detailed maps. 

   --An exchange of lunar material gathered by the Apollo program for meteorite material collected by the Soviets. 

   --An exchange of scientific instruments for use on planetary probes. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Barsukov</PERSON> said that the Soviets feel that a manned Mars landing is "inevitable" and that it probably will take place in the middle of the next century. 

   But before a manned mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> is attempted, <PERSON>Mr. Barsukov</PERSON> said there probably will be new manned flights to the moon. 
He declined to elaborate. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901027-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-27-90 1908EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MarsLife     10-27 0346</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mars Life,0414</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientists Agree to be Patient in Search for Life on Mars</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JACKIE HALLIFAX</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists searching for life on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>
agreed <DATE>Saturday</DATE> that they must be patient and focus on learning
more about the environment of the cold, dry planet.
   ``If we're going to find life on Mars, it's not going to be just
sitting around in the dust someplace,'' said <PERSON>John D. Rummel</PERSON>, who
directs life biology research for the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and
Space Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We're going to have to find places on Mars that are more
likely to contain life forms than you would find at random,'' he
said.
   <PERSON>Rummel</PERSON> was among two dozen scientists from <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> who attended the International
Symposium on the <ORGANIZATION>Biological Exploration of Mars</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Florida State
University</ORGANIZATION>.
   Three speakers cautioned that it was too soon to conduct direct
life experiments on Mars, but <PERSON>Rummel</PERSON> said most of the scientists
agreed the planet should be studied for insights that could lead to
a discovery of life on the planet.
   ``Mars is not considered by many people to be a lifeless
planet,'' <PERSON>Rummel</PERSON> said.
   Ten years ago, the landings on Mars during the Viking missions
detected no signs of life on <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, the most Earth-like planet in
the solar system.
   Scientists believe the planet was once more hospitable for the
evolution of life than it is now. Conditions grew harsher,
primarily drier and colder.
   <PERSON>Rummel</PERSON> said some scientists believe that signs of life, either
past or present, might be discovered deeper under the surface, near
heat sources where water might be found.
   The latest data from Mars came from unmanned Soviet missions in
<DATE>1988</DATE>. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> plans to send a spacecraft to orbit Mars in
<DATE>1992</DATE> and the Soviets plan a <DATE>1994</DATE> mission that would land an
unmanned robotic rover vehicle and balloons to explore the planet's
surface.
   On Earth, scientists are studying volcanoes, ocean bottoms,
lakes and rocks in <LOCATION>Antarctica</LOCATION> and Siberian permafrost to see what
kinds of life can survive under Martian-like conditions.
   E. <PERSON>Imre Friedmann</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Florida State</ORGANIZATION> researcher who organized the
meeting, said there's a good likelihood that life once existed on
Mars.
   ``You cannot really express it numerically, you cannot quantify
it, but it is certainly good enough to justify serious effort to
verify whether or not this is really the case,'' <PERSON>Friedmann</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06178237 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06178237 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  STANFORD; PLANNING; SPACE; RESEARCH; TRIP  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The United States could land people on Mars 10 years sooner for about
one-tenth of the estimated cost by teaming up with the Soviet Union and
scuttling the space station that NASA has planned, says a group of Stanford
University professors.;    They said their proposal could save up to $480
$540 billion price tag over the next few decades.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  STANFORD TEAM SETS SIGHTS ON MARS
URGES U.S.-SOVIET EFFORT TO CUT COSTS, HASTEN
FLIGHT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Additional information attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     The <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> plan was scheduled to be presented today to the <ORGANIZATION>National Space
Council</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, which advises the president on space policy.;   
Although the idea of a joint U.S.-Soviet mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> was proposed several
years ago by President <PERSON>Gorbachev</PERSON>, planning for the effort never got under way
and each country has been pursuing its own scheme.;    The American version,
endorsed by President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> two years ago, includes building a space station
and a lunar base before going to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, at a total cost of up to <MONEY>$540 billion.</MONEY>;
   The cost of the space station plan has been the focus of intense debate in
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>House</ORGANIZATION> voted earlier this month to keep funding alive for another
year, rejecting an earlier vote by the appropriations committee to scuttle the
project.;    Thousands of jobs in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and elsewhere hinge on the <MONEY>$30
billion</MONEY> space station plan. <ORGANIZATION>Lockheed Missiles &amp; Space Co.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION>'s largest employer, has estimated it would lose <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> in
space-station-related contracts over the next decade if the plan is scuttled.;
   Critics of the space station plan, however, contend it would rob funds from
other space programs and from social programs for the poor.;    The <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>
plan bypasses both the space station and the moon base in favor of going to
Mars directly.;    Sometime around the year <DATE>2012</DATE>, a series of spacecraft
carrying cargo and crew would be boosted into low Earth orbit aboard the
Soviet Energia rocket, which can carry much heavier loads than anything <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
now has to offer.;    They then would be flung out of orbit like rocks from a
sling for the nine-month journey to Mars.;    When the crew of three men and
three women arrived, they would find apartments and a garage with tracked
exploration vehicles waiting for them, sent up in advance by an unmanned
rocket. They would stay about a year before embarking for the nine-month
journey back.;    The total cost: <MONEY>$60 billion</MONEY>, including several preliminary
unmanned missions to map the Martian surface and explore it with robots.;   
Scrapping the space station -- now estimated to cost up to <MONEY>$120 billion</MONEY> over
its lifetime -- and a <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY> heavy-lift rocket would save money and more
than 10 years.;    The no-frills mission would also take two steps to protect
the health of the astronauts during their long flight. It would incorporate 22
tons of water and other shielding into the spacecraft to insulate them from
cosmic radiation, which could reach a lethal peak during solar storms.;    And
the craft would rotate four times per minute to provide some artificial
gravity in the hope of avoiding deterioration of the astronauts' hearts, bones
and blood vessels.;    The plan was drafted by graduate students in a <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION>
space systems engineering class taught by <PERSON>Bruce Lusignan</PERSON>, professor of
electrical engineering. The <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> team also included a former vice
president of <ORGANIZATION>TRW</ORGANIZATION>'s spacecraft engineering division, <PERSON>Emery Reeves</PERSON>; an expert in
robotics, <PERSON>Thomas Binford</PERSON>; and <PERSON>Larry Colin</PERSON>, former chief of the space science
division at NASA/Ames.;    Although it was done as an educational exercise,
<PERSON>Lusignan</PERSON> is scheduled to present it to the <ORGANIZATION>Space Council</ORGANIZATION> at the urging of
scientists who reviewed it.;    <PERSON>Roy Merrill</PERSON>, a <PERSON>Lawrence Livermore</PERSON> software
engineer specializing in robotics who reviewed parts of the plan, said it was
based on conservative, tested technology. "It's definitely a viable way to
tackle the problem," he said.;    <PERSON>Colin</PERSON> said some people are hoping the
<ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> plan could push <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> into taking a mission to Mars more seriously. He
added, "You don't need a space station. You don't need a lunar program. You
can just go to Mars.";    The study was partly funded by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ames Research
Center.</ORGANIZATION>;  <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> team; The Mars exploration plan was drafted by graduate
students in a <ORGANIZATION>Stanford</ORGANIZATION> space systems engineering class, assisted by:;
(box)<PERSON>Bruce Lusignan</PERSON>, professor of electrical engineering; (box)<PERSON>Emery Reeves</PERSON>, a
former vice president of <ORGANIZATION>TRW</ORGANIZATION>'s spacecraft engineering division; (box)<PERSON>Thomas
Binford</PERSON>, an expert in robotics; (box)<PERSON>Larry Colin</PERSON>, former chief of the space
science division at NASA/Ames  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  GLENNDA CHUI, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910626  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  751  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday June 26, 1991
00178237,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG
FRONT  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890701-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-89 1057EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Apollo-NASAatCrossroads     07-01 1217</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Apollo-NASA at Crossroads,1249</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hopes for New Space Ventures Tempered by High Cost</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July. Also moved in advance June 28 as b0730.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY314-315, LaserGraphics, Logo</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> laments that ``the
promise of Apollo was never fulfilled,'' that the American space
program languished after he and <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> left the first human
footprints on the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>.
   He says he hopes the 20th anniversary of Apollo 11 will ``become
a catalyst for the country to chart a bold course for human
expansion outward.''
   But given today's political and tight budgetary climate, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
is not too hopeful.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is expected to voice continuing support for a
permanent manned space station and say other nice things about
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s program when he meets with <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and their
command module pilot, <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, on <DATE>July 20</DATE>, the anniversary
of the moon landing.
   But no matter how many nice things the president says about
space, the political truth is that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> must approve the money.
And with the space station already facing a sharp funding cut,
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is not expected to give much support to new projects.
is at a crossroads, as it was when the glory days of Apollo ended.
   President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> had committed this nation to landing a
man on the moon in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. The goal was to gain space superiority
over the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, whose early feats had earned the Russians
worldwide respect and shocked Americans.
   When the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> won the race to the moon, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> laid out
bold plans for the future.
   To a presidential panel, agency head <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON> in <DATE>1969</DATE>
proposed a 12-man space station and a reusable space shuttle in
operation as early as <DATE>1976</DATE>, followed by a station in moon orbit, a
base on the moon, a 50-man space station in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit and a manned
mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   But in a period of unrest due to domestic racial problems and
involvement in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, costly plans to explore space were given low
priority.
   Only the reuseable space shuttle survived, and its proposed
funding was cut deeply.
   ``Those were tough times,'' said <PERSON>Paine</PERSON>, who resigned in
frustration a year after Apollo 11.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administrations were lukewarm toward the
space program, but the shuttle was built. It performed capably as a
space truck for 24 missions until <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, when the Challenger
exploded, killing its seven crew members and grounding the program
for 32 months.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> had gained some hope from President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s endorsement of
a strong space program and from his <DATE>1984</DATE> State of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> message,
in which he backed building the space station Freedom.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> created a commission to define long-term space
goals. Its chief was <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator.
   Six months after Challenger, <PERSON>Paine</PERSON> stood in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and
gave <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> a slick leather-bound volume that recommended the space
station, a lunar base and manned trips to Mars _ essentially an
update of <ORGANIZATION>Paine</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1969</DATE> plan.
   Reagan <DATE>two years later</DATE> signed a Presidential Directive on
<ORGANIZATION>National Space Policy</ORGANIZATION> that stated space leadership was a fundamental
objective. It endorsed the space station and, without being
specific, set a long-range goal ``to expand human presence and
activity beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit into the solar system.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s policy set in motion a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> program named Pathfinder
whose goal is to test technologies for manned and robotic
exploration of the moon and planets, advanced missions in orbit and
on planetary surfaces, extended human presence in space, and space
transportation to the moon and planets.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has not disclosed his thinking beyond saying he supports a
space station. He established the <ORGANIZATION>National Space Council</ORGANIZATION>, headed by
Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, to recommend a comprehensive space policy.
   Quayle is expected to have a preliminary outline ready for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
anniversary meeting with the Apollo 11 astronauts.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs a decision from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> soon on how much money it can
spend next year on space station Freedom. A permanent orbiting space
station is essential to those ambitious Pathfinder dreams and would
serve as a training base and launch pad for flights deeper into
space.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has requested <MONEY>$2.05 billion</MONEY> in the budget for fiscal <DATE>1990</DATE> to
continue work on the station. Predictions are that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will
trim that by <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>, amounts that space
officials say could further delay or even kill the project.
   The space station project has gone through five tumultuous years.
Reagan wanted it built in cooperation with <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s major allies,
but there were stormy sessions over access to the station before 10
European nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> agreed to invest nearly <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> to build sections of it.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said in <DATE>1984</DATE> it could begin launching segments of the
orbiting laboratory in <DATE>1992</DATE> and estimated the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cost at <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, agency officials revised the pricetag to <MONEY>$14.6
billion</MONEY>. The new figure covered a suddenly scaled-down Phase One,
which left off two of the external struts to which experiment
modules would be attached. The struts would be added in orbit under
Phase Two.
   Shortly after that, a <ORGANIZATION>National Research Council</ORGANIZATION> panel reviewing
station costs and technical issues for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> said the
total cost to develop and deploy the first phase would be <MONEY>$25.02
billion</MONEY>, with Phase Two raising the cost to <MONEY>$32.8 billion</MONEY>.
   The schedule began slipping. And <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now says if it receives the
proper funding, it could begin assembling the station in <DATE>1995</DATE>.
   Some in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> believe <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> should alter its plans and build a
less complex station and, instead of relying totally on the space
shuttle, develop a large unmanned rocket to do much of the lifting
job.
   Orbiting at 250 miles, Freedom would be home to a crew of eight,
with astronauts rotating back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> after four to six months.
   The station would allow humans to study the stars and planets
from the pollution-free environment of space. The weightless
interior would permit manufacture of new, contamination-free
medicines and other products impossible to create on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
Astronauts would assemble, service and repair satellites and send
them out into space. And the station could eventually be the staging
point for man's return to the moon or a journey to Mars.
   No one can predict whether these grand plans will come about, but
the three astronauts who made that extraordinary Apollo 11 flight to
the <DATE>moon 20 years ago</DATE> think they should.
   ``A permanent presence in space is a worthy objective, and I hope
that space station Freedom becomes a reality,'' <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> said
recently.
   ``I strongly endorse the station, a scientific base on the moon
and eventually manned flights to Mars,'' said <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who orbited the moon while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
walked its surface, envisioned setting up a colony on Mars.
   ``We're a nation of explorers,'' he said. ``We started on the
<LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, we went to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, and then vertically. Starting
with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers, <PERSON>Chuck Yeager</PERSON> through the sound barrier,
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and Aldrin on the moon.
   ``It's in our tradition, it's in our culture.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890628-0215 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-89 1418EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Apollo-NASAatCrossroads Adv02   06-28 1224</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Apollo-NASA at Crossroads, Adv 02,1256</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv02</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, July 2, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Hopes for New Space Ventures Tempered by High Cost</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserGraphics, Logo</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Part of an eight-story package for use at will or on successful
Sundays in July.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON> laments that ``the
promise of Apollo was never fulfilled,'' that the American space
program languished after he and <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> left the first human
footprints on the <DATE>moon two decades ago</DATE>.
   He says he hopes the 20th anniversary of Apollo 11 will ``become
a catalyst for the country to chart a bold course for human
expansion outward.''
   But given today's political and tight budgetary climate, <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
is not too hopeful.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is expected to voice continuing support for a
permanent manned space station and say other nice things about
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s program when he meets with <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and their
command module pilot, <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, on <DATE>July 20</DATE>, the anniversary
of the moon landing.
   But no matter how many nice things the president says about
space, the political truth is that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> must approve the money.
And with the space station already facing a sharp funding cut,
<ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> is not expected to give much support to new projects.
is at a crossroads, as it was when the glory days of Apollo ended.
   President <PERSON>John F. Kennedy</PERSON> had committed this nation to landing a
man on the moon in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. The goal was to gain space superiority
over the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, whose early feats had earned the Russians
worldwide respect and shocked Americans.
   When the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> won the race to the moon, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> laid out
bold plans for the future.
   To a presidential panel, agency head <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON> in <DATE>1969</DATE>
proposed a 12-man space station and a reusable space shuttle in
operation as early as <DATE>1976</DATE>, followed by a station in moon orbit, a
base on the moon, a 50-man space station in <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit and a manned
mission to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION> in the <DATE>1980s</DATE>.
   But in a period of unrest due to domestic racial problems and
involvement in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION>, costly plans to explore space were given low
priority.
   Only the reuseable space shuttle survived, and its proposed
funding was cut deeply.
   ``Those were tough times,'' said <PERSON>Paine</PERSON>, who resigned in
frustration a year after Apollo 11.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Ford</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> administrations were lukewarm toward the
space program, but the shuttle was built. It performed capably as a
space truck for 24 missions until <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, when the Challenger
exploded, killing its seven crew members and grounding the program
for 32 months.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> had gained some hope from President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s endorsement of
a strong space program and from his <DATE>1984</DATE> State of the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> message,
in which he backed building the space station Freedom.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> created a commission to define long-term space
goals. Its chief was <PERSON>Thomas Paine</PERSON>, the former <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> administrator.
   Six months after Challenger, <PERSON>Paine</PERSON> stood in the <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION> and
gave <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> a slick leather-bound volume that recommended the space
station, a lunar base and manned trips to Mars _ essentially an
update of <ORGANIZATION>Paine</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1969</DATE> plan.
   Reagan <DATE>two years later</DATE> signed a Presidential Directive on
<ORGANIZATION>National Space Policy</ORGANIZATION> that stated space leadership was a fundamental
objective. It endorsed the space station and, without being
specific, set a long-range goal ``to expand human presence and
activity beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit into the solar system.''
   <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>'s policy set in motion a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> program named Pathfinder
whose goal is to test technologies for manned and robotic
exploration of the moon and planets, advanced missions in orbit and
on planetary surfaces, extended human presence in space, and space
transportation to the moon and planets.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has not disclosed his thinking beyond saying he supports a
space station. He established the <ORGANIZATION>National Space Council</ORGANIZATION>, headed by
Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>, to recommend a comprehensive space policy.
   Quayle is expected to have a preliminary outline ready for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
anniversary meeting with the Apollo 11 astronauts.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs a decision from <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> soon on how much money it can
spend next year on space station Freedom. A permanent orbiting space
station is essential to those ambitious Pathfinder dreams and would
serve as a training base and launch pad for flights deeper into
space.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has requested <MONEY>$2.05 billion</MONEY> in the budget for fiscal <DATE>1990</DATE> to
continue work on the station. Predictions are that <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> will
trim that by <MONEY>$400 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$700 million</MONEY>, amounts that space
officials say could further delay or even kill the project.
   The space station project has gone through five tumultuous years.
Reagan wanted it built in cooperation with <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s major allies,
but there were stormy sessions over access to the station before 10
European nations, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> agreed to invest nearly <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY> to build sections of it.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said in <DATE>1984</DATE> it could begin launching segments of the
orbiting laboratory in <DATE>1992</DATE> and estimated the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> cost at <MONEY>$8
billion</MONEY>. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, agency officials revised the pricetag to <MONEY>$14.6
billion</MONEY>. The new figure covered a suddenly scaled-down Phase One,
which left off two of the external struts to which experiment
modules would be attached. The struts would be added in orbit under
Phase Two.
   Shortly after that, a <ORGANIZATION>National Research Council</ORGANIZATION> panel reviewing
station costs and technical issues for the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> said the
total cost to develop and deploy the first phase would be <MONEY>$25.02
billion</MONEY>, with Phase Two raising the cost to <MONEY>$32.8 billion</MONEY>.
   The schedule began slipping. And <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> now says if it receives the
proper funding, it could begin assembling the station in <DATE>1995</DATE>.
   Some in <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> believe <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> should alter its plans and build a
less complex station and, instead of relying totally on the space
shuttle, develop a large unmanned rocket to do much of the lifting
job.
   Orbiting at 250 miles, Freedom would be home to a crew of eight,
with astronauts rotating back to <ORGANIZATION>Earh</ORGANIZATION> after four to six months.
   The station would allow humans to study the stars and planets
from the pollution-free environment of space. The weightless
interior would permit manufacture of new, contamination-free
medicines and other products impossible to create on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
Astronauts would assemble, service and repair satellites and send
them out into space. And the station could eventually be the staging
point for man's return to the moon or a journey to Mars.
   No one can predict whether these grand plans will come about, but
the three astronauts who made that extraordinary Apollo 11 flight to
the <DATE>moon 20 years ago</DATE> think they should.
   ``A permanent presence in space is a worthy objective, and I hope
that space station Freedom becomes a reality,'' <PERSON>Neil Armstrong</PERSON> said
recently.
   ``I strongly endorse the station, a scientific base on the moon
and eventually manned flights to Mars,'' said <PERSON>Buzz Aldrin</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Michael Collins</PERSON>, who orbited the moon while <ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Aldrin</PERSON>
walked its surface, envisioned setting up a colony on Mars.
   ``We're a nation of explorers,'' he said. ``We started on the
<LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION>, we went to the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>, and then vertically. Starting
with the <PERSON>Wright</PERSON> brothers, <PERSON>Chuck Yeager</PERSON> through the sound barrier,
<ORGANIZATION>Armstrong</ORGANIZATION> and Aldrin on the moon.
   ``It's in our tradition, it's in our culture.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, July 2</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880707-0082 </DOCNO>
<HL> Mars Moon Probe To Lift Off Today From Russian Site --- More Than a Dozen Nations Participating in Project; Remote Study of Planet </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> FREST </CO>
<IN> ARO </IN>
<DATELINE> MOSCOW (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space officials from more than a dozen countries converged on a Central Asian steppe yesterday for the launching of the first of two probes to <LOCATION>Phobos</LOCATION>, the potato-shaped moon of Mars. 

   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> says the mission will help prepare for manned flight to the planet. 

   Soviet media said final preparations were being made at the Baikonur launch site in <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION> for the liftoff today of Phobos I, a joint East-West project to study Phobos and Mars itself. 
Phobos II, the second satellite, is scheduled to be launched <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. 

   Soviet television this week showed the silver-white Phobos I and its 60-yard-tall Soviet-made <ORGANIZATION>Proton</ORGANIZATION> rocket being moved into place. 

   The satellites will enter Mars's gravity in <DATE>January</DATE> and begin a three-month remote study of the surface and atmosphere of the planet. 
After that, scientists said, they will draw closer to Phobos and drop descent vehicles carrying laser, ionic and radar equipment to help determine the internal structure and composition of the moon. 
The probes are expected to be sent to Phobos in about <DATE>April</DATE> of next year, according to <PERSON>Roald Sagdeyev</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Soviet Academy of Sciences' Space Research Institute</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Soviet space scientists said <PERSON>Phobos</PERSON> is an important step toward a manned flight to <ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, which they hope can take place in the <DATE>early 21st century</DATE>. 
Officials including Soviet leader <PERSON>Mikhail Gorbachev</PERSON> have proposed that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> take part in the mission. 

   "First, it is necessary to draw up a more accurate map of the Mars surface in order to choose a place for the future landing," said <PERSON>Vyacheslav Balebanov</PERSON>, a deputy to <PERSON>Mr. Sagdeyev</PERSON>. 

   "Then, it is necessary to study the climate and soil characteristics and find out whether oxygen should be taken from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, or whether it can be gotten directly on the planet. 
The study of Mars renewed under the Phobos program should provide answers to those questions," he said in an interview with the newspaper <ORGANIZATION>Sovietskaya Rossiya</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said that the Phobos television system will provide color photographs and that a memory unit will permit transmission of up to 1,100 pictures to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 

   Soviet space officials said the launching itself will cost about <MONEY>$65 million</MONEY> and that the total cost of the project was about <MONEY>$480 million</MONEY>. 

   Also participating in the project are <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Bulgaria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Hungary</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>East Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Finland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>. 
Many of those countries have provided equipment for experiments to be conducted by Phobos. 

   The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, a late entry into the Martian mission as relations have warmed with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>, will be represented at the launching by a group headed by Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Donald Cromer</PERSON>, head of the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> space division, said <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Marguerite Squire</PERSON>. 

   The Deep Space Network of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Aeronautics and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> will provide tracking data to permit two 100-pound landers to reach Phobos, and then will begin to track the Martian moon precisely using antennas in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION>, and a Soviet radio telescope in the <LOCATION>Crimea</LOCATION>. 

   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> scientists say the Deep Space Network can determine distance within yards, and the velocity of spacecraft billons of miles from <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Balebanov</PERSON> said scientists also suspect that Phobos is gradually drawing closer to Mars. 
The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> tracking may help to determine if that is true. 

   The Phobos craft will carry a plaque commemorating <ORGANIZATION>Phobos</ORGANIZATION>'s discovery by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> astronomer. 

   The probe is launched while the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> is still trying to recover from the loss of the space shuttle Challenger in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
Since then, the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has had several space achievements, including the 326-day mission of cosmonaut <PERSON>Yuri Romanenko</PERSON> aboard the Mir orbiting space station. 

   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> first sent a satellite toward Mars in <DATE>1962</DATE>. 
The Mars-1 craft was the first of about 15 Soviet and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> probes that gathered a large amount of data from the planet, but not enough to determine the feasibility of a manned mission, Soviet scientists say. 

   Phobos "is a logical development of the Soviet program of Mars exploration that was started about a quarter of a century ago," cosmonaut <PERSON>Alexei Leonov</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION>. 
