<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890309-0063 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-09-89 0843EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iditarod     03-09 0268</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod,0275</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dog Sled Racers Near Halfway Mark</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TAKOTNA, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Frontrunners in the 1,168-mile
Anchorage-to-Nome sled dog race edged closer to the halfway point
today after a musher who placed ninth last year took the lead.
   <PERSON>Dee Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> was the first to reach the checkpoint at <LOCATION>Takotna</LOCATION>,
arriving at <TIME>6:53 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, less than 2{ hours after she left
<PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>. Defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> held the No. 2 spot,
leaving <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON> at <TIME>5:16 p.m.</TIME>, 48 minutes after <PERSON>Jonrowe</PERSON>.
   Standings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race
showed <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON> in the lineup
immediately behind <PERSON>Jonrowe</PERSON> and Butcher. The rest of the top 10
consisted of <PERSON>Joe Garnie</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jerry Riley</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jacques Philip</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON>
and <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON>. Nine of the 10 are Alaskans. Philip is from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Takotna</LOCATION> is 128 miles from <LOCATION>Iditarod</LOCATION>, the halfway point. The first
musher at Iditarod is to receive a silver trophy and <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> in
silver ingots. The race carries a <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse, with the winner at
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> qualifying for <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>.
   Jonrowe is running in her seventh Iditarod and Butcher is
shooting for a fourth consecutive win. The two women are friends,
and <PERSON>Jonrowe</PERSON> has purchased dogs from <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION>'s kennel in <LOCATION>Manley</LOCATION>.
   Standings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> showed 15 of the Iditarod's 45 mushers
either were in <ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION> or just beyond the <LOCATION>Kuskokwim River</LOCATION> town. Most
of the others had reported in at <LOCATION>Nikolai</LOCATION>, the checkpoint 48 miles
east of <ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION>.
   Iditarod founder <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> held 12th place in the evening
standings.
   Forty-nine mushers left the starting line <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
Four have dropped out.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900312-0175 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-90 0033EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0711 03-12 0361</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0711,0367</SECOND>
<HEAD>PRECEDE Nulato.</HEAD>
<HEAD>Butcher Loses Lead in Sled Race</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs with Butcher losing lead. Pick up 9th graf
pvs, `Named for...' A version moving on sports wires.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KALTAG, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> was first out of this <LOCATION>Yukon
River</LOCATION> checkpoint <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, taking the lead in the Iditarod Trail Sled
Dog Race away from three-time winner <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> and heading
overland to <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>.
   Barve of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> left <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> at <TIME>2:28 p.m.</TIME> even though Butcher
had beaten him to the checkpoint by almost an hour in the latest
stage of the 1,158-mile marathon race from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   The two leaders were followed into <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> by four-time Iditarod
winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> at <TIME>1:26 p.m.</TIME> and <DATE>1989</DATE> champion <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> at
<TIME>1:33 p.m.</TIME> Dee <PERSON>Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON> of were next in just before
<TIME>2:30</TIME> p.m.
   <PERSON>Robin Jaconson</PERSON> of arrived at <TIME>4:15 p.m.</TIME>.
   By <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>, <PERSON>Barve</PERSON> was the only musher to have left
<LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said he would take an eight hour rest here.
   Butcher, who started the race with 17 dogs, had 12 <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Race
officials said some were dropped at checkpoints along the trail due
to illness.
   When she became the first musher to reach Ruby <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>
was rewarded with a luxurious meal of shrimp, veal, chocolate
cheesecake and other delights, as well as <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY>. She said then
that she intended to maintain the lead all the way to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Kaltag is 42 miles along the Yukon, the biggest river in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>,
from the last checkpoint at <LOCATION>Nulato</LOCATION>, which <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION> left earlier
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> as leader. From <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, where it heads overland to Unakleet
on <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>. With 850 people, Unakleet is the bigest community
on the trail outside of <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   Named for an abandoned gold-mining town along one branch of the
trail, the Iditarod race was started in <DATE>1973</DATE> to commemorate the
<DATE>1925</DATE> emergency delivery of life-saving diphtheria serum from
<LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> by relay dog sled teams.
   <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON>, the 73-year-old man considered the father of the
Iditarod, was last reported in 32nd place after pulling out of
Cripple, 510 miles from the starting line.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890313-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0477 03-13 0309</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0477,0314</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iditarod Leaders Head For Coast</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf, `The leaders...', with 5 grafs to UPDATE with
more mushers leaving Kaltag checkpoint; quotes from two leaders, background
on race. PICKS UP 4th graf pvs, `The mushers...'.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KALTAG, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three-time champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> led the
mushers as the leaders of the 1,168-mile Iditarod Trail Sled Dog
Race began the sprint to <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s west coast.
   Butcher left this <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION> village at <TIME>6:55 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, with
<ORGANIZATION>Martin Buser of Big Lake</ORGANIZATION> one minute behind her.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> was third, departing at <TIME>7:45 p.m</TIME>. Then came
<PERSON>Dee Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION>, logging out at <TIME>9:13 p.m.</TIME>, four-time
champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Manley</LOCATION>, <TIME>9:14 p.m.</TIME>, and <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION>, <TIME>10:19 p.m.</TIME>
   Butcher, <ORGANIZATION>Buser</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, Jonroe and <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> have generally been
out front of the pack, trading the lead among themselves, since they
left the gold mining ghost town of <LOCATION>Iditarod</LOCATION>, 558 miles into the race.
   ``We've seen some head games, some traveling together and some
moving alone, but the competition is definitely very intense,'' said
<PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>, who won the nation's leading sled dog race in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1987</DATE>
and <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, a four-time winner, said the top five ``have
accomplished one of our goals by separating ourselves from the rest
of the pack.''
   The race, inspired by a sled dog relay that brought serum from
<LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during a diptheria outbreak in <DATE>1925</DATE>, was begun in
<DATE>1973</DATE>.
   The mushers raced toward the coastal village of <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, 93
miles away and the longest stretch between checkpoints in the race.
When they left <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, they were 357 miles from the finish line in
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   The winner receives <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>; the next 19 finishers share <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY>.
   Forty-one mushers remain in the contest. Eight have dropped out
since the race started <DATE>March 3</DATE> in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880317-0029 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-17-88 0151EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Iditarod 2ndLd-Writethru a0450 03-17 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0450,0700</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Susan Butcher Wins Iditarod Sled Dog Race For Third Straight Time</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf with three grafs to UPDATE with Butcher quotes,
CORRECT finishing time to 8:42 p.m. sted 8:43; picks up 3rd graf
pvs; SUBS 11th graf pvs, `Butcher's lead ...' to CORRECT that only
one of the dogs mentioned led her across finish line last year.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> left the competition behind on
the icy <LOCATION>Bering Sea Coast</LOCATION> and mushed through bone-chilling winds
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> to claim her third straight victory in the 1,150-mile
Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race.
   Butcher, 33, collected a <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> first prize by urging her
nine-dog team into the finish chute at <TIME>8:42 p.m.</TIME>, hours ahead of
her closest rival in the 16th annual Anchorage-to-Nome trek. She
had been on the trail for more than 11 days.
   ``I'm just amazed at what my dogs are doing, and what they've
done all year,'' said <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>.
   Butcher said she would try next year for a fourth straight win.
``I very much want four, I guess I want five,'' she said.
   Hundreds of cheering fans braved the blustery 15-degree weather
to watch as Butcher became the first musher to win three
consecutive <LOCATION>Iditarods</LOCATION>. Butcher started the race with 17 dogs, but
dropped eight at checkpoints along the trail.
   ``I'm really happy,'' said <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>'s husband, <PERSON>Dave Monson</PERSON>, who
earlier this month won another long-distance <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> sled dog race,
the 1,000-mile Yukon Quest. The couple run a kennel in the interior
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> village of <ORGANIZATION>Manley</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We've had a tremendous year,'' <PERSON>Monson</PERSON> said. ``It shows that
hard work pays off sometimes.''
   Butcher's closest competitor, <ORGANIZATION>Martin Buser of Big Lake</ORGANIZATION>, was
trailing by at least 14 hours <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Butcher's longtime rival,
four-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of Two <PERSON>Rivers</PERSON>, was minutes
behind Buser for third place.
   <PERSON>Joe Garnie</PERSON> of Teller was running fourth, and 70-year-old <PERSON>Joe
Redington</PERSON> of Knik, who organized the first Iditarod in <DATE>1973</DATE> but has
never won the race, was fifth.
   Butcher had slept little since <DATE>Monday</DATE>, when she reached the
<LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> coast in <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, 229 miles from <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>. She said a
training run last month along the windy coast accustomed her team
to the punishing conditions.
   <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, Butcher guided her team through subzero
temperatures and winds that brought the wind chill factor down to
minus 70 degrees. Peeking out from a fur-ruffed parka, Butcher
suffered only a frost-nipped wrist.
   ``The wind was going right into my big mitt and up my arm. It's
still pretty sore,'' she said <DATE>earlier Wednesday</DATE>.
   One of Butcher's lead dogs this year was Granite, a husky that
led her to victory last year.
   Butcher, competing in her 11th Iditarod, long dreamed of being
the first woman musher to win, but that honor went to <ORGANIZATION>Libby Riddles
of Teller</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>. Butcher won in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE>, setting course
records each time.
   Last year, when the race followed its shorter southern route,
Butcher finished in 11 days, 2 hours.
   The Iditarod, named after an old supply route to the gold mining
districts of interior <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, draws its inspiration from a <DATE>1925</DATE>
relay of diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, which was hit hard by an
outbreak of the disease.
   The race started <DATE>March 5</DATE> on trucked-in snow. The temperature in
downtown <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> hovered around 32 degrees and climbed even
higher during the next few days, which strained the cold-loving
huskies.
   Fresh snow slowed the leaders as they climbed into the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska
Range</ORGANIZATION>. That gave an advantage to <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>, who had taken his
mandatory 24-hour layover early in the race and sailed past the
leaders on the trail they had packed down.
   Redington, known as the Father of the Iditarod, has entered all
but two of the race's 16 runnings and has placed as high as fifth.
For 400 miles, it seemed as if he might finally win, but he lost
the lead to <PERSON>Buser</PERSON> on the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>.
   Butcher quickly caught up, passing Buser on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> near <LOCATION>Koyuk</LOCATION>,
171 miles from the finish.
   Five of the 52 teams that started the race have dropped out.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900314-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-90 1525EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 3rdLd-Writethru a0624 03-14 0590</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0624,0605</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Musher Susan Butcher Makes It Four Wins In Iditarod Race</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede WHITE MOUNTAIN, Alaska</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: UPDATES throughout with Butcher crossing finish line in
record time. No pickup.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Musher <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> crossed the finish line
today to claim her fourth victory in the last five years in the
1,158-mile Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race.
   Her victory, in record time, turned the tables on defending
champion <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON>, who edged her last year at the finish of the
Anchorage-to-Nome race. Runyan trailed Butcher on the trail by more
than an hour.
   ``She just had a better plan,'' said <PERSON>Libby Riddles</PERSON>, the first
woman to win the race in <DATE>1985</DATE>, watching the finish on the sunny
streets of this Gold Rush-era town. ``She outraced these guys. She
maintained her dog team better.
   ``It's an incredible unbelievable high,'' <PERSON>Riddles</PERSON> said. ``You go
thorugh all those ups and downs on the way to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>. You can't
believe you've done it till you get there.''
   Smiling as she ran beside her dogs in her bright red snowsuit,
the 33-year-old Butcher finished the race shortly before <TIME>11 a.m.</TIME>
Her official time was 11 days, 1 hour, 53 minutes, 23 seconds,
beating both her record for the route taken this year and her
overall record for all Iditarod races.
   Earlier, following a mandatory six-hour rest, Butcher left the
<LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION> checkpoint 77 miles from the finish one hour 20
minutes ahead of <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>.
   She stopped for only three minutes at Safety to move a few dogs
to different positiions in the harness before striking out on the
last 22-mile leg of the race at <TIME>8:36 a.m. AST</TIME>.
   ``It's <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> who I have to worry about,'' <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON> said while
still on the trail. ``He has a hot team, but he's got to get ahead
of me.''
   Butcher had dropped another dog at <LOCATION>Elim</LOCATION>, leaving her with 11
dogs to <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>'s 15 over the last 123 miles of the race.
   Butcher's time handily broke the speed record for the identical
route in <DATE>1986</DATE> _ 11 days, 15 hours and six minutes. Her <DATE>1987</DATE>
Iditarod record of 11 days 2 hours 5 minutes was set on an
alternate route.
   Anticipating today's finish, Iditarod organizers spent <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
hanging traditional trail's end banners and setting up the racers'
chute on Front Street in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Lavon Barve reached <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION> in third place.
   Four-time winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> was reported out of the checkpoint
at <ORGANIZATION>Elim</ORGANIZATION>, while <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robin Jacobson</PERSON> and <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON> were at
the checkpoint 123 miles from the finish.
   The leaders have switched to lightweight sprint sleds, instead
of the heavier long-distance sleds they began the race with at
<LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 3</DATE>.
   First prize is <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>, with the rest of the <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> purse
divided among the next 19 finishers.
   Teams bucked a stiff sidewind across the ice pack <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>
and drove through near whiteout conditions that are common on the
Sound.
   Butcher had expressed hopes of finishing in under 11 days.
   ``I'll have to see how this team responds going over <LOCATION>White
Mountain</LOCATION> before I go for the all-time record,'' she had said
earlier.
   Named for an abandoned gold-mining town along the trail, the
Iditarod was started in <DATE>1973</DATE> to commemorate the <DATE>1925</DATE> emergency
delivery of life-saving diphtheria serum from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> by
sled dog teams running in relays.
   Of the 70 teams that began the race, seven mushers have
scratched and another was disqualified because of sick dogs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900312-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-90 1508EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0458 03-12 0447</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0458,0457</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iditarod Racers Reach Strike Out for Norton Sound</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 11 grafs to UPDATE with today's events; picks up
7th graf pvs: `Named for ...; a version also moving on sports wires</NOTE>
<DATELINE>UNALAKLEET, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three-time winner <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> and
defending champion <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON>, their dog teams well rested, gained
on Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race leader <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> today as they
pulled into this checkpoint on <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>.
   Resting his dogs only 3{ hours, <PERSON>Barve</PERSON> was about four hours ahead
of Butcher and <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> when they left <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, the last checkpoint on
the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>, for the 90-mile run to <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, the gateway to
the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>.
   Butcher, with eight hours rest, and <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> with five, were both
<DATE>less than two hours behind Barve</DATE> when they hit <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, where
racers were expected to rest about six hours before heading up the
coast for the last 170 miles to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Leaving <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> behind <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> were <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON>, four-time champion
<PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>, <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robin Jackobson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Squaw Lake</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Minn</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said any one of the first five racers could win the race
in the last 170-mile sprint to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   ``If you want to make a good bet, never bet on a dog race,'' he
said. ``It's really shaken out which team is healthy and really
fit. Looks to me like it's anybody's bet what's going on here.''
   Before leaving <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said the leaders in the 18th
running of the 1,158-mile race had come under the spell of what he
called the ``crazy syndrome.''
   ``Everybody's pushing pushing pushing,'' <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said.
   Runyan called his dogs ``little bio-mechanisms'' that have to be
understood, cared for and appreciated. ``The trick is to be
predictable for the dogs,'' said <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>.
   Because of his habit of running behind his sled rather than
riding its rails when it heads up hills, <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> area residents have
begun calling him ``Runnin' <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>.''
   Butcher said it was wrong to assume she was leading the race
from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> just because she had been first to reach
<LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>. She said everybody was running their own race with
different strategies.
   Named for an abandoned gold-mining town along the trail, the
Iditarod race was started in <DATE>1973</DATE> to commemorate the <DATE>1925</DATE> emergency
delivery of life-saving diphtheria serum from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> by
sled dog teams.
   Retired Col. <PERSON>Norman Vaughan</PERSON>, at 84 the oldest musher, was
reported in 63rd place in <LOCATION>McGrath</LOCATION>, 389 miles into the race. <PERSON>Vaughan</PERSON>
was a member of Admiral <PERSON>Byrd</PERSON>'s Antarctic expedition and competed at
the <LOCATION>Lake Placid</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> Olympics in <DATE>1932</DATE>.
   Six mushers have scratched out of the 70 who began the race
<DATE>March 3</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900312-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-12-90 2325EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-12 0473</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Barve Clings to Narrow Lead as Teams Begin Run Along Bering Sea
Coast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SHAKTOOLIK, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> clung to the lead <DATE>Monday</DATE>
as front-runners in the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race began their
run up the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> coast to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Barve of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> arrived at <TIME>4:02 p.m.</TIME> in this windswept coastal
community, the final checkpoint before mushers head across the
treacherous ice of <LOCATION>Norton Bay</LOCATION>.
   ``Once they get onto the ice, they can expect sudden storms and
an ample supply of wind,'' said <PERSON>Gail Somerville</PERSON>, an Iditarod
spokeswoman in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   Three-time winner <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of <PERSON>Manley</PERSON> and defending champion
<PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> were trailing Barve by just a couple of hours,
<LOCATION>Somerville</LOCATION> said.
   ``They haven't checked in yet, but they're not too far behind,''
she said.
   <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Clam Gulch</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dee Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Rick
Swenson</PERSON> of Two <PERSON>Rivers</PERSON>, the Iditarod's only four-time champion, had
reached <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, the largest community on the trail between
<LOCATION>Eagle River</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Barve, driving 14 dogs, was first out of Unakleet at <TIME>10:05 a.m.</TIME>
But 50 miles earlier, at <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, he rested his team only 3{ hours,
compared with eight hours for Butcher and five hours for <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>.
   He didn't seem to think that was much of a handicap, however.
   ``My dogs are getting stronger with less rest,'' <PERSON>Barve</PERSON> said. ``I
think that's my advantage. My dogs always seem to recover fast.''
   Butcher, whose team had dropped to 12 dogs, said she would like
to be in front by the time the leaders reach White Mountain, just
77 miles from the finish of the 1,158-mile race.
   ``Unfortunately, that's not up to me as much as the other
guys,'' <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON> said. ``I'd like to shed them early but I don't
know if that's possible.
   ``And probably from what I know of <LOCATION>Lavon</LOCATION>'s competitive spirit
and how he can do what he wants to do with that team, I may not
shed them at all.''
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said any one of the first five mushers could win the race
in the last 170-mile sprint to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   ``If you want to make a good bet, never bet on a dog race,'' he
said. ``It's really shaken out to which team is healthy and really
fit. Looks to me like it's anybody's bet what's going on here.''
   Before leaving <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said the leaders in the 18th
running of Iditarod had come under the spell of what he called the
``crazy syndrome.''
   ``Everybody's pushing, pushing, pushing,'' he said.
   Since 70 teams left <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 3</DATE>, seven mushers have
scratched and another has been disqualified because of sick dogs.
   The Iditarod, named for an abandoned gold-mining town along the
trail, was started in <DATE>1973</DATE> to commemorate the <DATE>1925</DATE> emergency
delivery of life-saving diphtheria serum from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> by
sled dog teams.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890308-0107 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-89 1309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0557 03-08 0335</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0557,0341</SECOND>
<HEAD>Three-Time Winner Presses For Dog Sled Lead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 8 grafs to UPDATE with today's racing conditions;
Picks up 7th graf, `Runyan said...'</HEAD>
<DATELINE>McGRATH, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three-time <ORGANIZATION>Iditarod Trail</ORGANIZATION> Sled Dog Race
champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> pressed for the lead in the Anchorage-to-Nome
race <DATE>early today</DATE> as a mob of rested mushers sprinted for this
<LOCATION>Kuskokwim River</LOCATION> community.
   Butcher pulled out of <LOCATION>Nikolai</LOCATION> <DATE>early today</DATE> and was expected in
<ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION>, 407 miles into the 1,168-mile race, at midmorning. She was
followed by <ORGANIZATION>Martin Buser</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> was the first musher to reach McGrath <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME>, but he hadn't taken his mandatory 24-hour rest.
   To complete the layover requirement, he could not leave town
until <TIME>4:43 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE>. Butcher took her 24-hour layover in <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON> and
could leave <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> behind. The next 18 mushers behind Butcher also
have completed their layover.
   Butcher said she believed the frantic pace <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> set had sapped
his dogs. ``It took him 15 hours to cross the (Farewell) Burn,'' she
said. ``It took me only 10.''
   Butcher blitzed into <PERSON>Nikolai</PERSON>, 359 miles into the race, just
before <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. Buser, four-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Rick
Swenson</PERSON>, <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrow</PERSON>, <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joe Garnie</PERSON> pulled in
behind her within minutes.
   From <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>, 761 miles remain in the race.
   Most of the 46 mushers remaining in the race were into or beyond
<PERSON>Rohn</PERSON>, 266 miles into the race.
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said he was running his own race and was trying not to
dwell on the progress of his competitors.
   ``I scratched last year,'' he said. ``Big psychological blow.''
   ``This year I looked at it, laid out a plan that I figured was
feasible. If that puts me in the money, great. If it doesn't, well
I'm gonna have a good trip.''
   Mushers are vying for a <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse, with <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> going to the
winner. Forty-nine mushers left the Iditarod starting line <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Norman Vaughan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Roger Roberts</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Masek</PERSON>, all
Alaskans, have dropped out.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900303-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-03-90 0109EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-03 0359</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0369</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dogs and Mushers Set to Start Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seventy dog teams and mushers were set
to start the ``Last Great Race on Earth'' on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the grueling
1,100-mile-long Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Teams were expected to encounter some of the harshest weather in
the race's 18-year history, said Race Manager <PERSON>Jack Niggemyer</PERSON>.
   Sub-zero temperatures accompanied by strong winds, the heaviest
snowfall in a quarter-century, ash from Redoubt Volcano and
starving, aggressive moose have combined to make it a tough year to
race and a tough year to train, he said.
   ``Awful weather,'' <PERSON>Niggemyer</PERSON> said. ``It's probably snowed 40
inches in the <DATE>last two days</DATE>.''
   The race usually lasts from 11 to 18 days. The record time, set
by <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Manley</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1987</DATE>, is 11 days, two hours
and five minutes. Butcher won the race in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Some participants and race observers said they expect this
year's race to be slow going because of the deep snow and
poorly-packed trail.
   ``We might run out of trail,'' said <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON>, a musher from
<LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. ``It's up to the mushers to snowshoe or
whatever,'' he said. It will be Barve's ninth race; he finished
fifth last year.
   The Iditarod began in <DATE>1973</DATE>. It commemorates the <DATE>1925</DATE> emergency
delivery of diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>. The serum,
taken overland by sled dog because airplanes couldn't get through,
was credited with saving hundreds of lives in the remote coastal
town.
   The trail begins in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> and heads northwest across the
giant <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> and onto the treeless tundra. Eventually it
winds along the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>.
   Since <DATE>1973</DATE>, the Iditarod has grown in fame and stature. This
year, mushers have come from as far as <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>.
Companies spend <MONEY>tens of thousands of dollars</MONEY> to sponsor top
competitors.
   <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Two Rivers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, the only person to win the
Iditarod four times, will be trying for a fifth win. Butcher will
attempt to equal <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>'s four-time win record.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890306-0091 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-06-89 1254EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 2ndLd-Writethru a0552 03-06 0470</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0552,0480</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lead Iditarod Mushers Reach Rainy Pass</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 9 grafs to UPDATE with some mushers arriving at third
and highest checkpoint; new leaders, other detail. Picks up 8th graf pvs,
`The trail...'.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>
was the first sled-dog racer to reach the highest checkpoint in the
grueling race as leading mushers made their way through the rugged
<ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> early today.
   <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, driving 18 dogs through the darkness, arrived at <ORGANIZATION>Rainy
Pass</ORGANIZATION> checkpoint at <TIME>5 a.m</TIME>. He was followed four minutes later by <PERSON>Joe
Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION>. Three-time champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> arrived at <TIME>5:22</TIME>,
and <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrow</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Bethel</LOCATION> arrived four minutes later.
   The weather plagued mushers early today. In some spots, wind had
blown the trail clean of snow and the ice underneath was wearing the
dogs' feet.
   None of the four leaders has taken the 24-hour layover required
during the race.
   Three other mushers were on the trail from Finger Lake to Rainy
Pass, which is 226 miles into the race and at 3,400 feet elevation.
   <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON>, who was out front when the first mushers pulled
into Finger Lake late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, declared his 24-hour layover and had
not moved by early today.
   Under the rules of the race, mushers are required to make a
24-hour stop at one of the race's 24 checkpoints; at the others,
they take whatever length of rest they believe they and the dogs
need. However, mushers are allowed to use the strategy of declaring
a 24-hour layover, then leaving after a couple of hours, in hopes of
getting a jump on their competitors.
   The 1,168-mile race began <DATE>Saturday</DATE> when 49 mushers left <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>
amid 46 mph gusts and a wind-chill reading of 22 degrees below zero.
Two mushers, <PERSON>Roger Roberts</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jan Masek</PERSON>, dropped out 151 miles into
the race.
   From Rainy Pass, the mushers have 942 miles to go before reaching
the finish on <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>'s historic Front Street.
   The trail out of <ORGANIZATION>Rainy Pass</ORGANIZATION> contains dangerous dogleg descents on
icy trails clinging to steep embankments.
   Several mushers complained that parts of trail were difficult to
navigate. <PERSON>Reddington</PERSON> said getting over a bluff past the <LOCATION>Yentna River</LOCATION>
was virtually impossible.
   ``You need an elevator to get over that one,'' said <PERSON>Reddington</PERSON>,
who injured his two rear dogs <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when his sled crashed into them
and opted to take a 24-hour layover at <ORGANIZATION>Finger Lake</ORGANIZATION>.
   Inspired by a sled-dog relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> for a diphtheria
outbreak in <DATE>1925</DATE>, the Iditarod was founded in <DATE>1973</DATE>. The winner this
year is to get <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> of the <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse. The remainder is
shared by the next 19 finishers.
   Most of the Iditarod mushers are from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. Others are from
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890308-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-89 2309EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0740 03-08 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0740,0475</SECOND>
<HEAD>Champion Dog Sledder Presses for Lead</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: New throughout to UPDATE with afternoon developments; no pickup.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>McGRATH, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Declaring that she must ``do everything
right from here on in,'' <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> prepared to leave here late
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME> in her quest for a fourth consecutive victory in
the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race.
   Butcher reached <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>, 407 miles into the race, at <TIME>8:17 a.m.</TIME>
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, about 15{ hours after <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> became the
first musher to arrive in the <LOCATION>Kuskokwim River</LOCATION> community.
   Butcher was followed by four-time Iditarod winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> in
the No.3 position at <TIME>10:05 a.m.</TIME> Dee <PERSON>Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON>
completed the top five, arriving in <ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION> at <TIME>10:11 a.m. and 11:03
a.m.</TIME>, respectively. Another 10 mushers in the field of 45 pulled
into <ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION> by <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>.
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said he would stay in the village for the 24-hour layover
required in the course of the 1,168-mile race from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>. Completing the layover meant <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> was unable to leave
<PERSON>McGrath</PERSON> before <TIME>4:43 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Twelve of the mushers still in the race <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> had not taken
their layovers. Many, including Butcher, completed them at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION>.
   Butcher said the number of teams leading among the 45 still in
the race hadn't thinned as much as she expected. She also said she
believed the frantic pace <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> set had sapped his dogs.
   ``It took him 15 hours to cross the (Farewell) Burn,'' she said.
``It took me only 10.''
   Forty-nine mushers left the Iditarod starting line <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>. Three dropped out relatively early in the race and a
fourth, <PERSON>David Aisenbrey</PERSON>, added his name to the scratch list
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Officials at the Iditarod headquarters in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> said
they did not know the reason for <ORGANIZATION>Aisenbrey</ORGANIZATION>'s withdrawal.
   The annual Iditarod began 17 years ago and was inspired by a <DATE>1925</DATE>
relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during a diphtheria outbreak. The race, which
carries a <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse, is put on largely by volunteers.
   Gov. <PERSON>Steve Cowper</PERSON> has been among them, but he said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that
he no longer has the time to offer his services. Nonetheless, he
made it to <PERSON>Nikolai</PERSON>, the checkpoint before <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>, to see some of
the activity.
   ``A lot of the mushers are pretty good friends of mine from way
back,'' <PERSON>Cowper</PERSON> said. ``I love this race and I'd do anything I can to
promote it.''
   The governor said musher and Iditarod founder <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON>, No.
14 in the rankings <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, has offered to provide him
with a dog team if he wants to compete some year.
   ``That may be a little ways down the trail, as they say,'' said
<PERSON>Cowper</PERSON>, who is serving his first term. ``It probably won't work
until I leave my present employment.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880308-0250 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-88 2230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-08 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0361</SECOND>
<HEAD>Redington Leads In Iditarod Dog Sled Race</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROHN, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> stole the lead of the
1,150-mile Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as he and <PERSON>Herbie
Nayokpuk</PERSON> sailed past other mushers who had packed down a smooth,
fast trail for them.
   Redington, a <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> resident who is a founder of the
16-year-old race, and <ORGANIZATION>Nayokpuk</ORGANIZATION>, of <LOCATION>Shishmaref</LOCATION>, took their mandatory
24-hour layovers on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. The race leaders passed them by, only
to get bogged down in freshly fallen snow as they crossed the
<ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION>.
   The leading mushers then took their mandatory layovers at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION>,
271 miles from the race's start in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>. They watched
helplessly as <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION> and Nayokpuk _ and <TIME>less than two hours
later</TIME>, <PERSON>Joe Garnie</PERSON> of Teller _ powered past them.
   ``I kind of have this feeling in the back of my mind that we're
going to see two Eskimos _ Garnie and Nayokpuk _ blazing across
this state,'' said <PERSON>Jerry Austin</PERSON>, one of the mushers taking a
layover at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> was the first musher to leave <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON>, at
<TIME>10:30 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>. But he has not declared his 24-hour layover, and
so is behind <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>, who left Rohn at <TIME>7:20 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
Nayokpuk left <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON> two minutes behind <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>. Garnie left at <TIME>9
a.m.</TIME>
   Still at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION>, in the order in which they arrived, were: <PERSON>Jan
Masek</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION>; defending champion
<PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Manley</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Jacques Philip of Thomery</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION>,
of <LOCATION>St. Michael</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Tim Moerlein</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kasilof</LOCATION>; and, in 11th place,
two-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>.
   From <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON>, the teams descend from the heights of the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska
Range</ORGANIZATION> into the timbered interior of the state for the longest
stretch between checkpoints in the race. Mushers must contend with
a bleak and treacherous area known as Farewell Burn before reaching
the next checkpoint, 93 miles away at <LOCATION>Nikolai</LOCATION>.
   The race is inspired by a <DATE>1925</DATE> dog sled relay that rushed
diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during an outbreak of the disease. The top
20 mushers will split a purse of <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>. The winner will get
<MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890315-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-89 1237EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0479 03-15 0689</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0479,0706</SECOND>
<HEAD>Crowds Gathering As Mushers Move Toward Finish Line</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 6 grafs to UPDATE with latest standings; PICKS UP
6th graf pvs, `Forty-one ...'. First finisher expected to cross about 4
p.m. EST. Version also moving on sports wires.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN GALLAGHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Mushers in the 1,168-mile Iditarod Trail Sled
Dog Race charged along <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s frozen west coast <DATE>today</DATE> in a tight
race to the finish line in this historic Gold Rush town.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON>, 40, of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION>, led a pack of five front-runners in
the Anchorage-to-Nome trek today when he left <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION>, 77
miles from the finish, with a five-minute lead over defending
champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>, 33, of <ORGANIZATION>Manley</ORGANIZATION>.
   Butcher, who has won the last three races, was down to 11 dogs _
several with diarrhea _ while <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> was running 14.
   Race officials expected the winner to claim the <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>
first-prize sometime around noon <ORGANIZATION>AST</ORGANIZATION> (4 p.m. EST).
   <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>, the only musher ever to win the race four times,
arrived in <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION> an hour before <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> left and said he had
given up hope of catching him. ``My goal now is to get it over
with,'' <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Dee Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> were fourth
and fifth respectively.
   Forty-one of the 49 mushers who left <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 4</DATE>
remained in the race <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. They use up to 18 dogs.
   The annual race began 17 years ago and was inspired by a sled-dog
relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during a <DATE>1925</DATE> diphtheria outbreak. Butcher
finished the <DATE>1988</DATE> race in just under 11 days and 12 hours to set a
record.
   As they awaited the finishers, workers in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> moved snow onto
historic Front Street, normally swept clean for traffic. The first
musher to cross the finish line wins <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> and <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> is divided
among the next 19 finishers.
   The race, whose trail is named for the gold mining ghost town of
Iditarod at the halfway point, attracts dozens of volunteers from
around the world.
   ``I think (author) <PERSON>Jack London</PERSON> put it best _ `It's the call of
the wild,''' Iditarod volunteer <PERSON>Peter Elstub</PERSON> said. ``It's a true
sporting event.''
   Elstub, a <ORGANIZATION>British Army</ORGANIZATION> soldier, has used his annual leave for
eight years to work for the Iditarod, performing tasks ranging from
telephone duty to dropping dog food along the trail. When military
duty kept him away in <DATE>1987</DATE>, he telephoned Iditarod headquarters for
race updates.
   ``It don't matter where I am in the world,'' he said. ``I still
want me dog information.''
   Unlike some years in which weather was a major factor in the
outcome, this year's Iditarod has been blessed with almost ideal
conditions.
   Racers stop at 25 checkpoints along the route and are required to
make two extended rest stops, one for 24 hours, the other for six
hours.
   Commercial jets flying into <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> operated near capacity <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>
as mushers' families and other race watchers headed toward this town
of 4,300 people on <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s west coast. Pilots pointed out stretches
of the trail and encouraged passengers to keep their eyes open for
sled teams.
   Nome, which looks onto the frozen <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>, took on a party
atmosphere helped by sunny skies and temperatures in the 20s. Singer
<PERSON>Hobo Jim</PERSON>, known for a song with the refrain ``I did, I did, I did
the <ORGANIZATION>Iditarod Trail</ORGANIZATION>,'' entertained customers at a Front Street saloon.
   For the locals, the Iditarod days ``give people a reason to be
outside and just walk around town and see what happened all <DATE>winter</DATE>
long while they were holed up in their houses,'' said <PERSON>Mary Knodel</PERSON>, a
shopkeeper whose store overlooks the finish line.
   <PERSON>Knodel</PERSON> said she doesn't root for individual mushers.
   ``After watching the race for all these years, you get to know
most of them,'' she said. ``It's like family. You don't like picking
one over another.''
   But <PERSON>Marylou Haggren</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Kodiak</LOCATION>, was rooting for <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``We just got back from the Lower 48, and down there everyone's
talking basketball,'' she said. ``Different lifestyles, I guess.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06063022 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06063022 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; MUSH -- Four-time winner Susan Butcher and her
dogs pull away from the starting line of the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ALASKA; ANIMAL; HUMAN; RACING; WEATHER; DEVELOPMENT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A record 75 mushers and more than 1,400 dogs began their trek Saturday from
downtown Anchorage to Nome under sunny skies in the 19th Iditarod Trail Sled
Dog Race.;    Temperatures were in the teens and 20s, cooler than the
40-degree-plus temperatures during the week that had participants worrying
about their dogs' comfort and soggy trail conditions along the 1,163-mile
route across Alaska.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  75 MUSHERS, 1,400 DOGS START 19TH IDITAROD
RACE  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "The trail doesn't matter much to the dogs. Warm weather is more conducive
to the type of race I want to run, to fast races," four-time champion <PERSON>Rick
Swenson</PERSON> said.;    <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> is trying to win a record fifth Iditarod victory
before defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> does.;    The race began at <TIME>9:02 a.m.</TIME>
(<TIME>10:02 a.m. PST</TIME>) when <PERSON>Brian O'Donoghue</PERSON>, a newspaper reporter and rookie musher
from <LOCATION>Fairbanks</LOCATION>, sent his dogs sprinting down Fourth Street. The former wire
service photographer and <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> cab driver won his starting spot by
lottery and wore bib No. 2.;    Other competitors came from other parts of the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> as well as from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and, for the first time,
the Soviet Union.;    The race, which commemorates the historic <DATE>1925</DATE> relay of
diphtheria serum to ailing gold miners in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, follows the southern route
this year, winding across tundra, mountain passes, frozen rivers and <LOCATION>Bering
Sea</LOCATION> coast.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Anchorage, Alaska  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910303  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  4A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  246  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday March 3, 1991
00063022,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900307-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-90 2247EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-07 0273</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0281</SECOND>
<HEAD>Swenson Takes the Lead, Buffalo Block Trail</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NIKOLAI, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Four-time winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> regained
the lead <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race, while a
musher miles behind him was trying to scare off curious buffaloes.
   <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> and three-time champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> were minutes
behind <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> about a third of the way through the 1,158-mile race
from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   ``There's a lot of strong teams this year,'' said <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>,
warning that there's still plenty of time for surprises. ``We've
got a long way to go yet.''
   <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> led the race <DATE>Monday</DATE> topping the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> at
3,500-foot Rainy Pass, but was overtaken by defending champion <PERSON>Joe
Runyan</PERSON> at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   He had a cut on his face and a cracked plastic runner on his
sled as he mushed away from this Athabascan Indian village of 110
people at Iditarod milepost 367.
   <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said the damage wouldn't stop him from reaching <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON>,
the next checkpoint 48 miles from here, where he either would
repair the runner or change sleds.
   Behind <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> on the trail through Farewell Burn, eighth-place
racer <PERSON>Tim Osmar</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Clam Gulch</LOCATION> fired shots into the air to clear the
trail of several buffaloes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Iditarod Trail</ORGANIZATION> is named for a tiny ghost town it passes
through. The race commemorates the <DATE>1925</DATE> emergency delivery by relay
dog teams of life-saving diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Butcher won the race in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE> and took second
place last year. Swenson won in <DATE>1977</DATE>, <DATE>1979</DATE>, <DATE>1981</DATE> and <DATE>1982</DATE>. He has
finished in the top 10 every year since <DATE>1973</DATE>, when the Iditarod was
started.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880308-0038 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-08-88 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iditarod     03-08 0297</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod,0305</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iditarod Pace Slows With New Snow On Trail</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ROHN, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Fresh snow on the trail continued to slow
the pace of the 1,150-mile Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race as mushers
slogged their way down from the frosted peaks of the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION>.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <PERSON>Jan Masek</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> led a tightly grouped caravan
of more than 20 mushers to <PERSON>Rohn Roadhouse</PERSON>, a remote log-cabin
checkpoint 271 miles from the start in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   Masek arrived at <TIME>3:10 p.m.</TIME>, followed eight minutes later by
<PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION>. Defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> arrived at
<TIME>3:20 p.m.</TIME>, followed closely by <PERSON>Jerry Austin</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>St. Michael</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Jacques Philip of Thomery</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Tim Moerlein</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Kasilof</LOCATION> pulled in at <TIME>3:31 p.m.</TIME>, trailed four
minutes later by four-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>, in
seventh position.
   By <TIME>8:30 p.m.</TIME>, half the 52 mushers in the race had made it to
<PERSON>Rohn</PERSON>. The rest were spread the 78 miles back to Finger Lake.
   Racers were slowed by up to 6 inches of new snow as they mushed
down to <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON> from Rainy Pass, at 3,400 feet the highest point along
the trail.
   Rohn is a favorite point for mushers to take the 24-hour layover
required of all mushers sometime during the Anchorage-to-Nome race.
The isolated cabin provides a refuge from spectators and reporters,
and the dogs often are tired from crossing the rugged mountains.
   The race, which started at <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, has been slower than
last year's record-setting pace, when <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION> reached <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> after 11
days, 2 hours on the trail.
   The race is inspired by a <DATE>1925</DATE> dog sled relay that rushed
diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during an outbreak of the disease. The top
20 mushers will split a purse of <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY>. The winner will get
<MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06062053 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06062053 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  ALASKA; ANIMAL; RACING; NEWSPAPER; WRITING; PROFESSIONAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A newspaper reporter will be first out of the chute today when competitors in
the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race start their 1,163-mile run from Anchorage to
Nome.;    Rookie musher Brian O'Donoghue, on leave as a staff writer for the
Fairbanks Daily News-Miner, won the starting position in a lottery at the
Iditarod banquet Thursday.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MUSH! PRESS GOES TO THE DOGS
REPORTER DISCARDS NOTEBOOK TO DIRECT IDITAROD'S
LEAD SLED  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     O'Donoghue, 35, has worked for <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> newspapers for about six years, and
has covered sled-dog races as a reporter. But this is the first long-distance
race in which he has participated.;    "My dog-driving experience was limited
to a single three-mile (beginner's) race," he wrote last month. "Still I
thought I was better prepared than most rookies because of my firsthand
observations as an <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> newspaper reporter.";    Seventy-three dog teams
were set to compete in sled-dog racing's premier long-distance race, which
traverses mountains, tundra and windswept stretches of frozen ocean.;    After
a week of springlike weather, mushers preparing for the 19th Iditarod worried
about warm conditions.;    "At first I thought it was going to be a bit dicey,
and it will be leaving <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>," said <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION>, the <DATE>1989</DATE>
Iditarod champion. "But I think once we get out on the trail, it'll be all
right. There's a lot of winter left.";    Veterinarians were busy <DATE>Friday</DATE>
checking the 1,600 dogs brought to <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> for the race. If the trail
remains slushy and icy, it will be tough on the dogs, they said.;    <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>
began to cool off <DATE>Friday</DATE> after breaking records with 40-degree-plus
temperatures for three straight days this week. Anchorage also was
unseasonably warm with record temperatures in the high 40s.;    Some stretches
of trail had about half the usual snow, trail crews said.;    Participants
were thinking positive.;    "I'm certainly looking forward to getting out on
the trail -- away from this warm weather," defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>
said.;    Butcher drew No. 38 in the lottery, which begins with No. 2.
Competitors follow an honorary first sled.;    Last year, she was 69th out of
the chute and still managed to win in a record 11 days, 1 hour, 53 minutes and
23 seconds.;    <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> each are seeking a record fifth
victory.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Anchorage, Alaska  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910302  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  370  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday March 2, 1991
00062053,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900306-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-06-90 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0468 03-06 0383</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0468,0389</SECOND>
<HEAD>Musher Kills Attacking Moose</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 8 grafs to update with racer killing moose,
picking up at the 8th graf previous, ``Swenson is.''</NOTE>
<DATELINE>ROHN, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One musher in the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog
Race and his dogs were safe today after he had to kill an attacking
moose with five pistol shots.
   Defending champion <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> held the lead today after passing
four-time winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> in the 1,160-mile race.
   <PERSON>Lorren Weaver</PERSON>, holding 44th place among the 68 racers still in
the race and 78 miles behind <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, killed a moose that attacked
his dogs on the trail between <LOCATION>Skwentna</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Finger Lake</ORGANIZATION>, race
officials said.
   Searchers had set out on snowmobiles <DATE>Monday</DATE> after two bush
pilots reported seeing the moose attack a team of dogs.
   One dog was gashed across the head, but <PERSON>Weaver</PERSON>, 50, a physician
fron Knik, and his team were otherwise unhurt. They continued into
<ORGANIZATION>Finger Lake</ORGANIZATION>, checkpoint No. 7 and 193 miles from the start of the
race from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> that started <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Race spokeswoman <PERSON>Debbie Croutch</PERSON> said the moose was without
antlers, but there was no report on whether it was a bull or a cow.
Bulls often have dropped their racks this by time of year.
   Attacks by hungry moose plagued racers during training this
year, and some mushers carried rifles for protection. The animals,
which weigh up to 1,800 pounds, have become aggressive because deep
snow has made it hard to graze.
   Runyan and five other veteran racers overtook <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> during the
sprint <DATE>Monday</DATE> from Rainy Pass to <PERSON>Rohn</PERSON>, 271 miles into the race. The
group passing <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> included his archrival, <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>.
   Swenson is the only person to have won the race four times.
Butcher won in <DATE>1986</DATE>, <DATE>1987</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>, and took second place last year.
   The Iditarod race runs from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, on the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>
coast, and crosses frozen rivers, treeless tundra and huge mountain
passes. Usually the race lasts 11 to 18 days or longer, depending
on weather and other conditions.
   Seventy mushers and dog teams left <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The Iditarod, named after a ghost town along the trail,
commemorates the delivery by sled dog teams of a life-saving
diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> in <DATE>1925</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900406-0111 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-06-90 1537EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Iditarod     04-06 0357</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Iditarod,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iditarod Winner Susan Butcher Meets with Bush</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX21</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RITA BEAMISH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Champion dog-sledder <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> told
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> that she has plans for her own brand of
U.S.-Soviet detent.
   If all goes well, <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON> said, there will be a 1,000-mile dog
sled race between <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> welcomed Butcher and her prize sled dog, <LOCATION>Granite</LOCATION>, to the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> to congratulate her on her fourth win of the annual
Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race across <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>.
   Butcher and her team of dogs made the 1,158-mile <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> run in a record 11 days, 1 hour and 53 minutes last month. She
broke her <DATE>1987</DATE> record by more than 10 minutes after braving
temperatures that dropped to 40 below zero and 100 mph winds that
ripped across the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>.
   Arriving at the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> in a shortsleeve spring dress while
others were bundled up in winter garb against a cold rain, Butcher
professed not to be cold, even when waiting outside while <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
meeting with Soviet Foreign Minister <PERSON>Eduard Shevardnadze</PERSON> ran long.
   ``I just finished a 440-mile race the day before yesterday in
the Arctic. It was 20 below,'' she laughingly told <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> as they
posed for photos with Granite in the Rose Garden.
   She gave <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> a photograph of the Iditarod race signed by the
top 20 finishers after the president emerged from his <ORGANIZATION>Oval Office</ORGANIZATION>
meetings to make superpower summit preparations.
   She also told him about plans for the Alaska-to-Siberia race.
The Soviets already have agreed, and the race will go 800 miles
into the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   Butcher, 35, who is generally recognized as the greatest sled
dog racer in the world, told <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> she started her mushing career in
<LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, the president's vacation home since his boyhood. She is a
native of <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   Butcher and her husband live in a wilderness cabin, 140 miles
northwest of <ORGANIZATION>Fairbanks</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, with a brood of dogs that numbers
as many of 150. She breeds the dogs for other dog sled racers.
   Only one other musher, <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>, has won the Iditarod four
times.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890307-0161 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-07-89 2055EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-07 0405</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0418</SECOND>
<HEAD>Top Mushers Battle for Lead in Dog Sled Race</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>, who won the last two
Iditarod dog-sled races with <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> on her heels, chased
<PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as the two winningest mushers in race history
fought for the early lead in the 1,100-mile trek.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> actually was farthest along the trail early
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. But he had not yet taken his mandatory 24-hour rest stop,
while <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, Butcher and five others declared theirs at <ORGANIZATION>Rohn</ORGANIZATION>,
which is 266 miles from the start in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> and 902 miles from
the finish line in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Swenson, Butcher and <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION> were expected to
start racing about noon <ORGANIZATION>AST</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Historically, Iditarod front-runners have faded badly by the time
they reached <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, more than 1,100 miles from the start.
   In past years, <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>, who has won the last three races, and
<PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, the only four-time winner, have been content to bide their
time, making their moves much later in the race.
   But this year <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> and Butcher went straight to the front. He
led Butcher into Rohn by 13 minutes.
   ``It just worked out that way,'' <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said of their quick
start. ``The thing is there was no one else that was going to go.''
   The two intense, outspoken competitors used to be neighbors in
<LOCATION>Manley</LOCATION>, but <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> has moved to <ORGANIZATION>Two Rivers</ORGANIZATION>. Their rivalry has grown
to epic proportions throughout the state.
   ``I think I can beat her ... but she's got a good team, and she
might beat us all,'' <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said. He said his team this year is
better than the one that was runner-up to Butcher last year.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, three people escaped serious injury when a
single-engine airplane chartered by an <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> TV station crashed
while covering the race.
   The field of mushers dwindled to 46 <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> when 83-year-old
<PERSON>Norman Vaughan</PERSON> called it quits at <LOCATION>Skwentna</LOCATION>, just 151 miles into the
race. Two other mushers dropped out earlier at <LOCATION>Big Lake</LOCATION>, only 71
miles along the way.
   Inpired by a dog-sled relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> for a diphtheria
outbreak in <DATE>1925</DATE>, the Iditarod was founded in <DATE>1973</DATE>. The winner this
year is to get <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> of the <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse. The remainder will be
shared by the next 19 finishers.
   Most of the Iditarod mushers are from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. Others are from
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890305-0066 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-05-89 2034EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0719 03-05 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0719,0494</SECOND>
<HEAD>Lead Iditarod Mushers Head For Alaska Range</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: RETRANSMITTING a0781 to fix order of cities in editor's note.
LEADS with 6 grafs to CORRECT that race to Nome, sted Fairbanks, UPDATE
with other mushers leaving Skwentna checkpoint; pickup 7th graf pvs, ``The
race ...;'' SUBS 10th graf, ``From Skwetna ...,'' to reflect that other
mushers have left checkpoint.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Big Lake musher <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON> was first
in line and on his way to the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as the leaders
in the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race sorted themselves out in the
early stages of the contest.
   Forty-nine mushers streaked out of <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> on the
first leg of the 1,168-mile race from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   Buser, 30, reached the <LOCATION>Skwentna</LOCATION> checkpoint some 150 miles into
the race at <TIME>3:53 a.m. AST</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. He and his 20-dog team were out
and on his way to Finger Lake, 45 miles farther down the trail, at
<TIME>7:44 a.m.
   Buser</TIME>, who finished third last year and paced the leaders for
much of that race, was followed out by <PERSON>Jerry Austin</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>St. Michael</ORGANIZATION>
at <TIME>9:13 a.m.</TIME> <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> dropped two dogs at the checkpoint, leaving with
16.
   Four-time champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of Two <PERSON>Rivers</PERSON> raced out of
<LOCATION>Skwentna</LOCATION> <TIME>21 minutes later</TIME>.
   The leaders were followed by about a dozen other mushers,
including Iditarod winners <PERSON>Rick Mackey</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Trapper Creek</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Susan
Butcher</PERSON> of <PERSON>Manley</PERSON> and Libby Riddles of <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   The race, inspired by a sled-dog relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> for a
diptheria outbreak in <DATE>1925</DATE>, began in <DATE>1973</DATE>. It has become the
nation's most famous sled-dog and commands a first prize this year
of <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> and total prize money of <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY>.
   Wind up to 46 mph that raked mushers in the first hours of the
race abated <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and it was clear and cold.
   But race volunteer <PERSON>Bob Nobmann</PERSON> said the leaders were taking
longer that normal to reach the first checkpoint. ``We think it was
slow going between the wind and the ice, tough going,'' he said.
   From <LOCATION>Skwentna</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Buser</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> and the others headed to Finger
Lake, a wide spot in the trail with a population of two residents.
From Finger Lake, the trail climbs into the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Rainy
Pass</ORGANIZATION>, the highest spot on the race route at 3,400 feet.
   The 17th annual race began with <LOCATION>Austin</LOCATION> first out of the chute.
Before the contest is over, mushers will trek over the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION>,
across desolate expanses and along a storm-raked coastline.
   Riddles, <DATE>1985</DATE> champion and the first woman to win the marathon
race, said she thought the cold and wind <DATE>Saturday</DATE> might have been
good for dog teams, cooling them off in the early stretches where
they tend to overheat in the excitement.
   Most of the Iditarod mushers are from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. Others are from
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Georgia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880313-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-88 1928EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0769 03-13 0410</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0769,0416</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sled Dog Race Founder Widens Lead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: NEW throughout to UPDATE with Redington widens lead, four
mushers leave Kaltag; add that finishers must arrive in Nome with
at least five dogs, status of non-Alaskan Americans in race. No
pickup.</NOTE>
<DATELINE>KALTAG, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The 70-year-old founder of the Iditarod
Trail Sled Dog Race streteched his lead <DATE>Sunday</DATE> as front-runners and
their dog teams passed the last checkpoint on the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>
section of the race.
   <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> pulled out of <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, on the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>, at <TIME>4:22
a.m.</TIME> and turned toward <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, 90 miles away on the wind-swept
<ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION> coast.
   Redington had left only nine of the 15 dogs with which he began.
Race rules require mushers to arrive in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> with at least five
dogs in harness.
   Leaving Kaltag 2{ hours after <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION> was <ORGANIZATION>Martin Buser of Big
Lake</ORGANIZATION>, who had passed <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION> early <DATE>Saturday</DATE> before falling back
into second place again <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Buser still had 13 dogs in harness,
one fewer than <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Buser had arrived in <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> only 23 minutes behind <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>.
The town is 798 miles from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>, where the 1,100-mile race
began <DATE>March 5</DATE>.
   Defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>, who won the last two races in
record times, left at the tiny village at <TIME>8:18 a.m.</TIME>, and four-time
champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> at <TIME>9:58 a.m.</TIME>, both with 12 dogs.
   The next checkpoint is <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, about 90 miles away on the
coast of <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>. From <LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, the teams run north along
the coast, open to the region's sudden storms and raking winds.
   The first musher to reach <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> will collect <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> of a
<MONEY>$150,000</MONEY> purse; the next 19 finishers will split the rest. Three of
the 52 teams that started the race have dropped out, including one
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Redington, who founded the race in <DATE>1973</DATE>, has never won, although
he has competed in all but two <LOCATION>Iditarods</LOCATION>.
   Redington had paced the race for more than 400 miles, before
<PERSON>Buser</PERSON> pulled out of <LOCATION>Galena</LOCATION> an hour ahead of him <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Buser
also arrived first at the Nulato checkpoint, but then warm weather
forced both men to wait until dark before setting out for <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>.
   American mushers from outside <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> were paced by <PERSON>Robin
Jacobson</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Minnetonka</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, in 13th place. <PERSON>John Patten</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Grand
Marais</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Minn.</LOCATION>, was 24th; <PERSON>Frank Teasley</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION>, 27th; <PERSON>Terry
Adkins</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Mikado</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mich.</LOCATION>, 31st; <PERSON>Dan McEachen</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Snowmass Village</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>,
34th; and <PERSON>Stan Ferguson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, 45th.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890315-0246 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-15-89 2145EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Iditarod 3rdLd-Writethru a0835 03-15 0744</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0835,0762</SECOND>
<HEAD>Runyan Wins Iditarod</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 8th graf, `Runyan dropped ..., with 3 grafs to UPDATE with
Butcher finishing, quotes; pickup 9th graf pvs, `Runyan arrived ...</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto AGX5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSAN GALLAGHER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Wrter</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NOME, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Cheering crowds and a blaring siren greeted
<PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when he and 11 dogs pulled into this
historic gold mining town to claim the 17th annual Iditarod Trail
Sled Dog Race.
   It took the <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION> musher slightly more than 11 days to cover the
1,168 miles from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>. His wife and baby watched as he won
<MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> of the <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse to be shared by the first 20 finishers.
   The victory gave <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, 40, the ``triple crown'' in
long-distance dog mushing. Last year, he won the Alpirod, the more
sedate European version of the Iditarod, and in <DATE>1985</DATE>, he won the
1,000-mile Yukon Quest from <LOCATION>Whitehorse</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Yukon Territory</ORGANIZATION>, to
<ORGANIZATION>Fairbanks</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said his dogs were in good shape after the grueling trek.
   ``We've gone over 200 miles in 24 hours,'' he said. ``The <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>
husky is unlike any animal on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. They can go 100 miles a day on
rough terrain and they can take it.''
   Runyan snapped a three-year winning streak by <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Manley</ORGANIZATION>, but failed by about three hours to break her <DATE>1987</DATE> record
time. When he crossed the finish line, Butcher was about five miles
behind. The only other musher to win more than one Iditarod is
four-time champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of <PERSON>Two Rivers</PERSON>, who was running
fourth when <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> finished.
   <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, who runs a kennel about 50 miles from <LOCATION>Fairbanks</LOCATION>, said his
main goal simply was to reach the finish first. ``I didn't care
about the record,'' he said. ``There's always room for fine-honing
(next year).''
   Butcher, who came in second an hour and four minutes behind
<PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, had struggled to keep up after beating him by two minutes at
the race half-way point of Iditarod, for which she won <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> in
silver ingots. Only once in race history has the halfway winner gone
on to victory.
   Illnesses among her dogs made it difficult to run a stronger
race, <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON> said at the finish line. The problems included
diarrhea and leg disorders that required her to bandage some of the
animals.
   She gave each of her 11 dogs a congratulatory pat after pulling
into the finish chute. ``I'm really proud of them,'' <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON> said.
   Runyan arrived in <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION>, about 77 miles from the finish
early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Swenson arrived in <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION> an hour before
<PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> left, but said <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>'s team was just too strong for him to
catch.
   ``My goal now is to get it over with,'' said <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, who trailed
Butcher. <PERSON>Dee Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> were
fourth and fifth, respectively.
   ``I'm kind of feeling sorry for how we have to run the dogs at
the end,'' <PERSON>Jonrowe</PERSON> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. ``I had to drop my leader. His foot
was sore.''
   Forty-nine mushers left the starting line in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> on <DATE>March
4</DATE>. Eight scratched along the way.
   <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, the last town of any size before the <ORGANIZATION>International Date
Line</ORGANIZATION>, took on a party atmosphere <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, helped by sunny skies and
temperatures that rose to the 20s.
   Workers in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, which has 4,300 people and looks out over the
frozen <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION>, moved snow onto Front Sreet, normally swept
clean for traffic, in anticipation of the mushers' arrival.
   Volunteers at the Iditarod office a block away updated race
standings from reports submitted by ham radio operators along the
trail.
   ``I think (author) <PERSON>Jack London</PERSON> put it best _ `It's the call of
the wild.''' volunteer <PERSON>Peter Elstub</PERSON> said.
   Elstub, a British soldier, said he had come to <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> for eight
of the last 17 races. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, when he was on duty in the <LOCATION>Falkland
Islands</LOCATION>, he telephoned Iditarod headquarters for race updates, he
said.
   For locals, the Iditarod days ``give people a reason to be
outside and just walk around town and see what happened all <DATE>winter</DATE>
long while they were holed up in their houses,'' said <PERSON>Mary Knodel</PERSON>, a
shopkeeper whose store overlooks the finish line.
   <PERSON>Marylou Haggren</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Kodiak</LOCATION> resident, said she and her husband made
hotel reservations a year ago for Iditarod week in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>.
   ``We just got back from the Lower 48, and down there everyone's
talking basketball,'' <PERSON>Mrs. Haggren</PERSON> said as she lingered in the
Iditarod office. ``Different lifestyles, I guess.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880310-0129 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-10-88 1333EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-Iditarod 2ndLd-Writethru a0561 03-10 0366</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0561,0373</SECOND>
<HEAD>Redington Into Cripple At Front Of Pack
^Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to UPDATE standings, picking up 6th graf
pvs, `Several racers ....'</HEAD>
<HEAD>Precede McGRATH, Alaska</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CRIPPLE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A 70-year-old man known as the ``Father
of the Iditarod' pocketed <MONEY>$2,500</MONEY> in silver ingots today for being
the first to reach the half-way point of the 1,100-mile Iditarod
Trail Sled Dog Race.
   <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> of Knik reached the Cripple checkpoint at <TIME>5:40
a.m.</TIME> His nearest competitor, <PERSON>Herbie Nayokpuk</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Shishmaref</LOCATION>, checked
into <PERSON>Ophir</PERSON>, 55 miles behind <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>, at <TIME>11:10 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Redington, a founder of the mushing marathon from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>, now heads for the <ORGANIZATION>Sulatna Crossing</ORGANIZATION> and then to <LOCATION>Ruby</LOCATION> on the
<LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>. He has raced in all but two of the 16 <LOCATION>Iditarods</LOCATION>,
finishing three times in fifth place.
   Four-time champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Two Rivers</ORGANIZATION> was running third.
He checked out of <LOCATION>Takotna</LOCATION> at <TIME>8:37 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. He was followed
by <PERSON>Joe Garnie</PERSON> of Teller, <PERSON>Jan Masek</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION> and <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON>
of <LOCATION>Bethel</LOCATION>.
   Defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of <PERSON>Manley</PERSON> was seventh.
   Several racers said that despite <LOCATION>Redington</LOCATION>'s lead, <PERSON>Nayokpuk</PERSON> is
now the musher to beat because of his strong dog team.
   ``I think it's going to take us quite a while to gain that kind
of time back, unless he runs into some kind of situation up
ahead,'' <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> said.
   A blizzard pounding <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s southwestern coast threatened to
turn into complicate things on the Iditarod trail for the racers.
If the gale-driven snow reaches inland to the <ORGANIZATION>Iditarod Trail</ORGANIZATION>, the
going could turn slow.
   At the back of the pack, 290 miles behind the leaders, the
oldest Iditarod musher announced that he was dropping out of the
race. <PERSON>Norman Vaughan</PERSON>, 82, said three of his dogs were in heat and
he had whiteout conditions ahead.
   Another musher, <PERSON>Ray Dronenburg</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Trapper Creek</ORGANIZATION>, also scratched
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, saying several of his dogs were weak with a virus. That
leaves 50 mushers in the race, which started <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   A <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> first prize awaits the winner, who is expected to
reach <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> sometime next week. The next 19 finishers will split the
rest of the <MONEY>$150,000</MONEY> purse.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900303-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-03-90 0524EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Iditarod     03-03 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Iditarod,0506</SECOND>
<HEAD>Dogs and Mushers Face Brutal Trail Conditions</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Race to start 2 p.m. EST</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JOHN ENDERS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Among the perils threatening the 70
racers and dog teams who mush today in the 18th annual Iditarod
Trail Sled Dog Race are hunger-crazed moose and ash from the
Redoubt Volcano.
   Not to mention the weather.
   Temperatures hit the 40s and turned snow into slush on the
streets of downtown <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>, where the race begins. But
conditions are some of the harshest in the history of the race
along the 1,100-mile trail to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> on the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>.
   ``Awful weather,'' said Race Manager <PERSON>Jack Niggemyer</PERSON>. ``It's
probably snowed 40 inches in the <DATE>last two days</DATE>.''
   The heavy snow has kept moose from grazing, setting the stage
for violent encounters between the huge animals and sled dog teams
on the remote trail, and prudent mushers are packing rifles.
   Redoubt has been erupting intermittently since <DATE>December</DATE>, spewing
ash as far north as the area around <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   The race usually lasts from 11 to 18 days. The record time, set
by <PERSON>Susan Butcher of Manley</PERSON> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, was 11 days, two hours and five
minutes. Butcher also won in <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Since <PERSON>Libby Riddles</PERSON> became the first woman to win in <DATE>1985</DATE>, women
have won the race four of the last five years, inspiring a popular
T-shirt saying, ``<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>: Where men are men and women win the
Iditarod.''
   Some participants and race observers said they expect the pace
to be slowed this year because of the deep snow and poorly-packed
trail.
   ``We might run out of trail,'' said <PERSON>Lavon Barve</PERSON>, a musher from
<LOCATION>Wasilla</LOCATION> who finished fifth last year. ``It's up to the mushers to
snowshoe or whatever.''
   The Iditarod was begun in <DATE>1973</DATE> to commemorate the emergency
delivery of diphtheria serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> by mail carriers driving dog
teams in <DATE>1925</DATE>.
   Taken overland after bad weather grounded airplanes, the serum
was credited with saving hundreds of lives in the remote town.
   From downtown <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>, the course goes northwest across the
<ORGANIZATION>Alaska Range</ORGANIZATION> and over the tundra before dropping down along the
<LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION>.
   Mushers must lay over for 24 hours of rest at some point along
the trail.
   The mystique of the Iditarod has grown steadily, with mushers
this year arriving from <LOCATION>France</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>. Companies spend
<MONEY>tens of thousands of dollars</MONEY> to sponsor top competitors.
   <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> of <PERSON>Two Rivers</PERSON>, the only person to win the Iditarod
four times, will be trying for a fifth win.
   Last year's winner, <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Nenana</LOCATION>, expects the teams to
start out slow because of bad weather.
   ``The big strategy this year in terms of snow is to reduce
injury,'' <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> said.
   But the teams can't afford to be too slow, he said.
   ``Even if you're conservative, it's better to be in the front of
the pack.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890309-0154 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-09-89 2234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-09 0225</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Runyan Leads Iditarod</HEAD>
<DATELINE>OPHIR, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> clung to his narrow lead in the
Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race as he approached the halfway point
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the 1,168-mile Anchorage-to-Nome trek.
   Runyan led the field into <PERSON>McGrath</PERSON> late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> but surrendered
his lead when he decided to take the 24-hour rest stop required of
all mushers somwehere along the trail.
   Most of the other top teams had stopped earlier, accounting in
part for <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>'s early lead. But storming out of <ORGANIZATION>McGrath</ORGANIZATION> on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, the rested <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> quickly regained the lead.
   He left Ophir at <TIME>4:45 a.m.</TIME> with a nine-minute edge on four-time
winner <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>.
   Five minutes behind <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON> was <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON>, who held the lead
briefly <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Defending champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> moved out 12
minutes later, and <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON> was about 20 minutes behind her.
   Behind the leaders was a pack of 14 mushers, including race
founder <PERSON>Joe Redington</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jacques Philip</PERSON> of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. Forty-nine
mushers left the Iditarod starting line <DATE>Saturday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>. Four
have dropped out.
   The next checkpoint is Iditarod, the ghost town for which the
trail and race are named. The first musher to reach Iditarod will
get <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> in silver ingots. The race carries a <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY> purse, with
the winner getting <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>.
   Iditarod is 610 miles from <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> and 558 miles from <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890314-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-14-89 2338EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-Iditarod 1stLd-Writethru a0776 03-14 0344</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0776,0350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Precedes KOYUK, Alaska</HEAD>
<HEAD>Mushers Neck-and-Neck Going Into Home Stretch</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs with Runyan taking lead, Butcher quotes;
picks up 8th graf, `As of...' A version also moving on the sports wire.</HEAD>
<DATELINE>ELIM, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Musher <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON> pulled ahead of three-time
winner <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to take the lead in the final dash
across the frozen <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> in the 1,168-mile Iditarod
Trail Sled Dog Race.
   The Nevana man finished the 48-mile first leg of the final 171
miles 41 minutes ahead of Butcher, who started the day at <LOCATION>Koyuk</LOCATION> with
a nine-minute lead. <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON> and his 15-dog team reached a checkpoint
at this <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> village at <TIME>2:03 p.m.
   Butcher</TIME>, from <PERSON>Manley</PERSON>, logged in at <TIME>2:44 p.m.</TIME> with 11 dogs. Third
was <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON>, a four-time Iditarod winner from <PERSON>Two Rivers</PERSON>, who
arrived at <TIME>4:05 p.m.</TIME>
   Dee <PERSON>Dee Jonrowe</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Willow</ORGANIZATION> hit the trail <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>morning two hours</TIME>
and three minutes after <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>.
   The winner is expected to reach <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> after
brief stops at three remaining checkpoints.
   The first musher to cross the finish line on <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>'s historic
Front Street wins <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>. The remaining <MONEY>$200,000</MONEY> is divided among
the next 19 finishers.
   With continued good weather expected, the final 171 miles of the
race across the ice of <ORGANIZATION>Norton Sound</ORGANIZATION> and along the hilly coastline to
<LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> will boil down to speed and endurance.
   All four leaders took their final mandatory rest stops <DATE>Monday</DATE> in
<LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>.
   Although Butcher has fewer dogs remaining in her team than
<PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, she said they appeared to be getting stronger.
   ``They're doing the Butcher tricks for me,'' she said early
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>. ``They know where they are (in the race).''
   As of <TIME>midday</TIME> <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, 41 mushers remained in the race; eight have
scratched since the race began <DATE>March 4</DATE> in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
   The annual race began 17 years ago and was inspired by a <DATE>1925</DATE>
relay of serum to <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> during a diphtheria outbreak. The race is put
on largely by volunteers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890929-0121 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-29-89 1328EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Soviets-Dogs     09-29 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviets-Dogs,0592</SECOND>
<HEAD>Glasnost's Effects Spreading From People to Sled Dogs</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEAN FOSDICK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ANCHORAGE, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The goodwill resulting from a thaw in
relations between <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> is spreading from
people to dogs.
   <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON>, a three-time winner of the 1,100-mile Iditarod
Trail Sled Dog Race, was to leave <DATE>Friday</DATE> for the <LOCATION>Soviet Far East</LOCATION>
along with a veterinarian and two <ORGANIZATION>Iditarod Trail Committee</ORGANIZATION>
officials.
   The group has three goals:
   _ Find two Soviet mushers who would live in <LOCATION>Manley</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>
and her husband, <PERSON>Dave Monson</PERSON>, another winning musher, and learn the
ropes about sled dog racing, Alaska-style.
   _ Examine sled dogs used in the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for size and
stamina comparisons with their <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> counterparts.
   _ Organize a committee on the Soviet side of the <LOCATION>Bering Strait</LOCATION>
that would help lay out a route for a new, international sled dog
race which would start in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> and end in the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION>, after
contestants had been flown across the strait.
   <PERSON>Ginna Brelsford</PERSON>, with the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Office of International Trade</ORGANIZATION>
and a member of the <LOCATION>Bering</LOCATION> Bridge Expedition which traveled 1,000
miles last <DATE>spring</DATE> by sled dog and kayak from the <LOCATION>Soviet Far East</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, helped arrange this week-long trip.
   ``All that sounds easy, but it's amazing how much time it takes
to get things done over there,'' <PERSON>Brelsford</PERSON> said of the goals for
<ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION>'s trip.
   The Soviets are no strangers to using dogs in the Arctic, but
they lag far behind the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> in developing racing equipment and
techniques, she said.
   ``When we introduced our sleds, they were excited about how
light and how flexible they were and how easily they could be taken
apart,'' <PERSON>Brelsford</PERSON> said of her trek last <DATE>spring</DATE>.
   ``They still operate with heavy leather harnesses and use ivory
hooks to connect things. Their technology is old when it comes to
using dogs and sleds.''
   ``Generally, they use freight animals _ dogs bigger than what
you see running the Iditarod but not necessarily better,''
<PERSON>Brelsford</PERSON> said.
   Monson and <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION> have 120 dogs in their <PERSON>Manley</PERSON> kennel, but
<PERSON>Monson</PERSON> said they always are looking for new bloodlines.
   ``Anything that will improve the general makeup of a sled dog so
it would perform better would be of interest,'' <PERSON>Monson</PERSON> said.
   The new race would be operated separately from the Iditarod,
said <PERSON>Rosemary Phillips</PERSON>, executive director of the race established
in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``We will not be taking anything from the Iditarod Sled Dog Race
to put this on, excepting experience,'' <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said. ``We've had
very positive responses from mushers _ lots and lots of calls
wondering how they could enter.''
   The race would be run about the end of <DATE>March</DATE>, at least two weeks
after the winner of the Iditarod crosses the finish line in <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>,
she said.
   ``Mushers are a sturdy bunch. You might see much the same teams
in there from the Iditarod.''
   The route would be from <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. From there,
mushers and dogs would be flown across the <LOCATION>Bering Strait</LOCATION> for a
restart in <LOCATION>Uelen</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S.S.R.</LOCATION> and the eventual finish at <LOCATION>Anadyr</LOCATION>,
she said.
   ``We would love to do it in <DATE>1990</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said.
``Realistically speaking, it probably will be <DATE>1991</DATE>.''
   The group also will be recruiting Soviet mushers and teams for
the Iditarod.
   ``Things like this just serve to break down the barriers,''
<PERSON>Phillips</PERSON> said. ``It's making the world smaller.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890313-0005 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-13-89 0009EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Iditarod     03-13 0232</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Iditarod,0239</SECOND>
<HEAD>Iditarod Leaders Turn Toward Coast</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KALTAG, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   With only 357 miles left, the leaders in
the Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race turned toward <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s windblown
coast <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   Three-time Iditarod champion <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> left this <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>
village at <TIME>6:55 p.m. AST</TIME>, with veteran musher <PERSON>Martin Buser</PERSON> one
minute behind her.
   <PERSON>Joe Runyan</PERSON>, driving 17 dogs, had led the pack of five leaders
into <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION> earlier in the day. Buser arrived about an hour later,
crouching on the back of his sled, brushing his teeth.
   He was followed into the village seven minutes later by <PERSON>Butcher</PERSON>,
who drove her team up the <LOCATION>Yukon River</LOCATION>, loudly singing a pop tune.
   From <LOCATION>Kaltag</LOCATION>, the mushers race toward the coastal village of
<LOCATION>Unalakleet</LOCATION>, 93 miles away and the longest stretch between
checkpoints in the race. From there, they sprint toward the <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY>
jackpoint waiting at the finish line on <LOCATION>Nome</LOCATION>'s historic Front Street.
   The musher who finishes first wins <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY>; the rest is shared
among the next 19 finishers.
   The leaders _ Butcher, <ORGANIZATION>Buser</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Runyan</PERSON>, <PERSON>DeeDee Jonrowe</PERSON> and
four-time champion <PERSON>Rick Swenson</PERSON> _ have been out front of the pack
since they left the gold mining ghost town of Iditarod, the half-way
point 558 miles into the race.
   Forty-one mushers remain in the 1,168-mile contest, the lowest
number since <DATE>1985</DATE>. Eight have scratched since the race started <DATE>March
3</DATE> in <LOCATION>Anchorage</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06076027 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06076027 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; NO. 1 -- Rick Swenson finishes first in the
Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race on Friday to win $50,000 and a new truck.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  ALASKA; ANIMAL; PET; RACING  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  On a day when the wind and snow blowing off the Bering Sea coast were so
severe that he thought he might be risking his life, Rick Swenson of Two
Rivers covered the final 77 miles to this historic gold-rush town and won the
19th annual Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race early Friday.;    By mushing his team
through temperatures of 20 degrees below zero and winds of 40 mph when most of
the chief competitors turned back to shelter, Swenson, 40, became the first
five-time winner of the 1,163-mile race from Anchorage to Nome.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  IDITAROD MUSHER FINISHES IN 12 DAYS, WINS
FOR 5TH TIME  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>, who last won the event in <DATE>1982</DATE>, finished in 12 days, 16 hours, 34
minutes, 39 seconds to win <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> and a new truck. In 16 Iditarod
competitions, he has never finished out of the top 10.;    The victory
rewarded <PERSON>Swenson</PERSON>'s boldness in mushing his dog team into a bitter winter storm
from <LOCATION>White Mountain</LOCATION>, the next-to-last checkpoint, and deflecting the challenge
of his chief rival, <PERSON>Susan Butcher</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Eureka</LOCATION>, who was seeking to become the
top-winning Iditarod competitor.;    <ORGANIZATION>Butcher</ORGANIZATION>, winner of four of the last five
<LOCATION>Iditarods</LOCATION>, and the event record-holder with a time of 11 days, 1 hour, 53
minutes was one of three front-runners who headed into the bad weather, but
