<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900804-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-90 1103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-ColumbusShips     08-04 0254</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Columbus Ships,0261</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nina, Pinta, Santa Maria Back In Port After Storm</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUELVA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> could have told them
it wouldn't be easy.
   Ninety Spaniards sailing in exact replicas of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' three
ships, the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, departed from this
southwestern <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> port <DATE>Friday</DATE> on a six-month <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> sea
trial.
   But by <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the explorers, who are preparing for a planned
<DATE>1992</DATE> re-creation of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' voyage to the New World, found
themselves back in port after they were blown to land by a
windstorm.
   Undaunted, <ORGANIZATION>Spanish navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Santiago Bolivar</PERSON>, the leader of
the mission, told reporters <DATE>Saturday</DATE>: ``We're going to wait out the
winds before starting out again for our first destination.'' That
destination is <LOCATION>Almeria</LOCATION>, a southwestern Spanish port roughly 310
miles east of <LOCATION>Huelva</LOCATION>.
   The ships' joyful sendoff <DATE>Friday</DATE> coincided with the 498th
anniversary of the day <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> began his first voyage to what
would become known as <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, which bankrolled <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, spent <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to build the
three ships from Galician pine and oak from the <LOCATION>Pyrenees</LOCATION>.
   The ships were built to help promote the Expo '92 World's Fair
in the southern city of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> and to commemorate the 500th
anniversary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' legendary voyage.
   Expo '92 is expected to attract 20 million visitors to <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>
from <DATE>April</DATE> to <DATE>October 1992</DATE>.
   While the sailors will attempt to follow the exact sailing
methods of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> and his intrepid men, the ships are equipped
with sophisticated equipment to navigate via satellite and carry
modern-day lighting.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900804-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-90 0704EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-ColumbusShips     08-04 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Columbus Ships,0474</SECOND>
<HEAD>Replicas Begin Spanish Tour Before Retracing Columbus' Route</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCISCO CONDE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>HUELVA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Replicas of the ships that accompanied
<PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> on his <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> crossing have set sail, but
this time in search of tourist dollars instead of precious metals
and spices.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> began their six-month
voyage to a dozen Spanish ports to prepare for a <DATE>1992</DATE> re-enactment
of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' trip to the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>.
   The ships have a total of 90 crew members and all but the
commander, a Spanish navy captain, will sleep outdoors, as
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' crew did on the voyage to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>.
   Like <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Capt. Santiago Bolivar</ORGANIZATION> will lead from the deck of
the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, the flagship.
   ``The objective of the <DATE>1992</DATE> voyage will be to study in action
the navigation methods of the <DATE>15th century</DATE> and the effectiveness of
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' sailing methods,'' <PERSON>Bolivar</PERSON>, 40, told reporters.
   The 15th century Spanish royalty bankrolled <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>.
   Today's government spent <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> to build the three replica
ships from Galician pine and oak from the <LOCATION>Pyrenees</LOCATION>. They sailed
from this southern port _ 310 miles southwest of <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> _ 498 years
to the day of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' first voyage to the New World.
   The head of the government company planning the <DATE>1992</DATE>
celebrations, <PERSON>Luis Yanez</PERSON>, saw them off and laid a wreath at a
monument to <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Yanez</PERSON> said the ships were built to help promote the Expo '92
World's Fair in the southern city of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>. Expo '92 is expected
to attract 20 million visitors to <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> from <DATE>April</DATE> to <DATE>October
1992</DATE>.
   ``An Expo such as this one is a unique occasion to launch a
country's image around the world,'' the exposition's commissioner,
<PERSON>Manuel Olivencia</PERSON>, has said.
signed commitments to build pavilions in <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> to display their
newest technologies and designs.
   The ships aren't the only promotion for Expo <DATE>'92</DATE>. A promotional
quiz game that cost <MONEY>$707,000</MONEY> to develop is to begin running soon in
Spanish newspapers to familiarize Spaniards with the discoveries of
the past 500 years.
   The government is also pumping an estimated <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> into Expo
'92 to modernize <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>'s public works communications systems and
<MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY> into the rest of the southern region of <LOCATION>Andalusia</LOCATION>.
   The ships are a particular point of pride. Last year, <LOCATION>Queen
Sofia</LOCATION> christened the single-decked 117-foot-long <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>. Her
daughter, <PERSON>Princess Elena</PERSON>, christened the <LOCATION>Nina</LOCATION> and Princess Cristina
the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION>.
   The two smaller caravelles are 50 feet long.
   While the sailors will attempt to follow the exact sailing
methods of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, the ships are equipped with sophisticated
equipment to navigate via satellite and carry modern-day lighting.
   For protection, a <ORGANIZATION>navy</ORGANIZATION> frigate will escort them.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06196250 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06196250 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2), map; PHOTO: Vicente Yanez Pinzon (color); PHOTO: Zeke Wigglesworth
-- Mercury News; Near Palos de la Frontera is this ship memorial -- and you
know it's not the Santa Maria (color).; MAP: Mercury News; Spain  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  TRAVEL; SERIES; WORLD; US; HISTORY; MAN; DATE; CEREMONY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  COLUMBUS? Columbus who?;    This is the wrong town to mention that name in.
Palos de la Frontera, you see, got the royal shaft from Ferdinand and
Isabella, Columbus -- and history.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  WRONG GUY GOT GLORY, SPANISH VILLAGERS INSIST  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  The Great Columbus Chase
Second in a four-part series  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Up on a wall next to the <ORGANIZATION>Church of St. George</ORGANIZATION> in this small, sunny town in
southwestern <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is this bold proclamation, set in blue tile:;    "Oh,
Palos! Your glory cannot be equaled. Not even <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>. Not even <LOCATION>Thebes</LOCATION>. Not
even immortal <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>. Not even <LOCATION>Athens</LOCATION>. Not even <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. No city can dispute your
historical fame!";    After all that puffy back-patting, it was natural the
citizenry would throw up a statue or two to commemorate their self-designated
place in history, and indeed, they did.;    So, there is a statue here of the
man who discovered <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, but it ain't that Italian upstart, Cristobol
Colon. Nope, it's a statue of  <PERSON>Martin Alonso Pinzon</PERSON>, captain of the Pinta
(yeah, that Pinta) and a hometown boy who, they tell you in these parts, made
good but never got the credit.;    And on a brilliant whitewashed house next
to the old church is a colorful portrait, also in tile, of <PERSON>Vicente Yanez
Pinzon</PERSON>, <PERSON>Martin Alonso</PERSON>'s kid brother and the captain of the <PERSON>Nina</PERSON> (yeah, that
Nina). The folks in Palos say that <PERSON>Vicente</PERSON>, who was made captain-general and
corregidor (head of state) of <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, also discovered <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> and the
mouth of the <LOCATION>Amazon River.</LOCATION>;    Palos and the <ORGANIZATION>Church of St. George</ORGANIZATION> were central
in the saga of the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> voyage.;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, after years of hanging
around the court of Isabella and Ferdinand, finally got the two sovereigns to
back his trip. But, never a couple to spend a peseta unnecessarily, the royal
pair decided on a little end-around run.;    The sailors of Palos -- including
the Pinzons -- had long experience at sea, trading in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Azores</LOCATION>.
Right after they promised <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> three ships, the king and queen dug up an
old case involving some African goods imported to Palos without royal duty
being paid.;    The fine for this forgotten infraction was -- guess what --
two ships, ready to sail and loaded with enough stuff to last a year. (Why pay
for three ships, they figured, when we can stiff the good people of Palos for
two of them? Were these two good, or what?);    The taxpayers of Palos were
thus forced to pay for their part in history. The two ships in question were,
of course, the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION> and the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION>. You can guess how popular <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was when
he arrived in town with that news. The royal order was issued in <DATE>May</DATE> -- and
somehow, the ships were provisioned and ready for sea by August.;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
and the elder <PERSON>Pinzon</PERSON> had known each other off and on for years. Near Palos is
the monastery of La Rabida, where <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> spent several years plotting how to
get Ferdinand and Isabella to give him an ear, and some historians say <PERSON>Martin
Alonso</PERSON> was in on the planning.;    And it seems unlikely that without <PERSON>Pinzon</PERSON>
going to bat for him, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> would ever have convinced the neighborhood
sailors to wander off toward the edge of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> -- especially with a
foreigner.;    And it's pretty obvious, looking back, that <PERSON>Palos</PERSON> and other
nearby villages were part of the scheme from the start. The Pinzons and dozens
of other experienced sailors were on tap, the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Nina</LOCATION> were already
there and the town was well placed on a little backwater on the <ORGANIZATION>Rio Tinto</ORGANIZATION>, a
wide river that opens into the sea a few miles from town.;    Relationship
turns icy;    On the night of <DATE>Aug. 2, 1492</DATE>, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, the Pinzons and the rest
of the crews went to the <ORGANIZATION>Church of St. George</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Palos</LOCATION> for Mass, then filed
down a set of stairs next to the church to where the three ships were
anchored, and boarded. They sailed the next morning.;    There's little left
today of the anchorage. The small arm of water that connected Palos to the <LOCATION>Rio
Tinto</LOCATION> is long-since silted up, and the only evidence that a wharf ever existed
is a memorial marker and a bit of stone wall.;    It was after the three ships
arrived in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> that things apparently got fairly icy between
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Martin Alonso</PERSON>. One historian says <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was constantly afraid
that <PERSON>Pinzon</PERSON> would discover gold before he did (the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION> sailed a good deal
faster than the tubby <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>). And toward the middle of their exploration
of <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION> -- and <PERSON>Pinzon</PERSON> -- disappeared for two months. Desertion?
Miscalculation? Gold fever? Who knows?;    Reneging on a deal;    The <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
fleet, minus the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, which hit a reef on <ORGANIZATION>Christmas Day</ORGANIZATION>, returned to
Palos in triumph in <DATE>March 1493</DATE>. There were, by all reports, huge parties.
<PERSON>Martin Alonso Pinzon</PERSON> did not attend. Five days after he returned to <LOCATION>Palos</LOCATION>, he
died.;    In later years, <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON> and Ferdinand tried to renege on pre-voyage
payment deals they had made with <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>. One of the strategies they used was
trying to prove that the whole idea -- sailing west to the Indies -- was the
brainchild of <PERSON>Martin Alonso Pinzon</PERSON> and his family. This started suits and
counter-suits that went on for centuries.;    It also created the stubborn
pride of the people of Palos, who for five centuries have said the wrong man
got the credit. Italian author <PERSON>Gianni Granzotto</PERSON>, in his rather biased <DATE>1984</DATE>
biography of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, suggests that the statue of <PERSON>Martin Alonso</PERSON> is
chauvinistic and "clouds the issue.";    "Fame does not make mistakes," he
writes. "Five centuries after the fact, the name of <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> still
resounds throughout the world. . . . How many people have heard of Pinzon?
Time has buried him, swallowed him up. . . . There (is) a great distance
between him and <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, the distance between obscurity and glory.";    So in
the end <PERSON>Martin Alonso</PERSON> lost. Not only did he die before the full impact of the
voyage was realized, but he also disappeared into history, just a footnote to
the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> myth. Except, of course, in Palos de la Frontera, whose "glory
cannot be equaled.";    The best thing now that can be said for Palos is that
it's close to the Portuguese border and the attractions of the Algarve. If
you're passing by this way, say howdy to <PERSON>Martin Alonso</PERSON> and his kid brother,
look at the church, then drive like a bat for the border.;    <DATE>Today</DATE>, <PERSON>Palos</PERSON>
sits in a bowl of pollution from refineries and factories on both sides of the
<ORGANIZATION>Rio Tinto</ORGANIZATION>. There is another refinery on the coast near La Rabida, and <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
would have trouble steering his small ships out to sea because of the haze.
The monastery (which now has a bar and restaurant on the grounds) is, like
almost every other <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> site in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, closed for repairs, but will be
open again in time for the grand celebration next year.;    And if you're
smart, and happen to be in Palos along about <DATE>August of 1992</DATE>, you'll forget all
about <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> and the ocean blue and <DATE>1492</DATE> and all that pastafazool -- and
remember who really discovered the <LOCATION>New World.</LOCATION>; NEXT WEEK: <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> returned in
glory to <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> after his epic first voyage. He wouldn't recognize the
place now -- and probably couldn't even get out of town. Good luck, <DATE>1992</DATE>
Olympics.; If you go. . .; FOR general information about southwestern
<LOCATION>Andalusia</LOCATION> and the Palos de la Frontera region, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Spanish National
Tourist Office</ORGANIZATION>, 8383 <LOCATION>Wilshire Blvd.</LOCATION>, No. 960, <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> 90211; (213)
658-7188.;    For more information about the <DATE>1492</DATE> voyage in general and the
Columbus/Pinzon saga in specific, try these books:;    (check) "The Conquest
of Paradise" by <ORGANIZATION>Kirkpatrick Sale</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Knopf</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$24.95</MONEY>).;    (check) "Christopher
Columbus" by <PERSON>Gianni Granzotto</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>University of Oklahoma Press</ORGANIZATION>, <DATE>1984</DATE>).;   
(check) "Columbus: His Enterprise" by <PERSON>Hans Konig</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Monthly Review Press</ORGANIZATION>),
<MONEY>$8.95</MONEY>.;    (check) "Admiral of the Open Sea," <PERSON>Samuel Eliot Morison</PERSON> (Little
<PERSON>Brown</PERSON> and Company, <DATE>1949</DATE>).  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ZEKE WIGGLESWORTH, Mercury News Travel Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  PALOS DE LA FRONTERA, Spain  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910714  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO; MAP  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,370  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 14, 1991
00196250,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06189123 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06189123 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, drawings (2); DRAWING: King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella bid Columbus
goodbye in an engraving by Theodore de Bry, published in 1594.; PHOTO: Zeke
Wigglesworth -- Mercury News; A must stop in Genoa for Columbophiles is the
house where Cristoforo Colombo was born.; (color); DRAWING: (The three ships)
(color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HISTORY; FOUND; NORTH-AMERICA; FESTIVAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IN FOURTEEN-HUNDRED and Ninety-two,;    Columbus sailed the ocean blue.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THE GREAT COLUMBUS CHASE
DESPITE DIARIES, MUCH ABOUT MAN REMAINS A
MYSTERY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Cover Story
See also related stories on P. 1T, 7T, 8T, 9T and 10T of this section
The Great Columbus Chase  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     That much, we know, is true. Somebody named <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>, or
<PERSON>Cristoforo Colombo</PERSON> (the Italian version) or Cristobal Colon (the Spanish
spelling), did sail from a tiny port in southern <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Aug. 3, 1492</DATE>, cross
the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, land somewhere in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, then return to spread the word
that a new world awaited those who embraced God, glory and gold.;    His
diaries exist. The logs of his journeys to the Americas exist. We know where
he died and have some idea where he might be buried. We also have some
indication that he was no saint or selfless explorer, as generations of
American school kids have been taught. Indeed, there is evidence to suggest he
was greedy, malicious, conniving and a cheat. (See accompanying article by
<PERSON>Nora Villagran</PERSON>.);    Whatever, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is getting very excited about <DATE>1992</DATE> and
the quincentennial of the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> voyage. <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> is holding the <DATE>summer</DATE>
Olympic Games and <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> is holding the <DATE>1992</DATE> Expo. Both events will be
heavily laced with <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> celebrations. <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> is also gearing up for a fete
or two to honor its native son, especially in his home town of Genoa.;    But
the celebrations are not confined to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. From <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>;
from <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, there are events planned all next year to honor the man
who officially (if not factually) discovered <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, though he's several
parts enigma.;    His legacy is uncertain, his contributions unclear. But he
has left footprints all over Europe.;    Following those footprints adds
little to the truth about the man -- but the footprints do take you to some
interesting spots.;    Over the next several weeks, from <LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>,
from <LOCATION>Granada</LOCATION> to a tiny monastery in the pollution-clouded <LOCATION>Rio Tinto</LOCATION> valley,
we'll chase <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> around his old haunts, 499 years after he stepped aboard
the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> and sailed off to immortality.;    One of the big mysteries
about <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> has always been where he was born. The Italians insist he was
born in <LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> about <DATE>1451</DATE>, the son of <LOCATION>Domenico Colombo</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Susanna
Fontanarossa</PERSON>. His father, so one version goes, was a wool merchant and weaver
who caught the eye of the doge of <LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> and was made gatekeeper of the
Olivella Gate.;    Another version has him being a Jew born in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>; another,
that he was non-Jewish, born in <LOCATION>Spain.</LOCATION>;    Or, even, would you believe,
Norwegian? Tor <PERSON>Borch Sannes</PERSON>, a Norwegian researcher of maritime history, says
in a new book that <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was born in the small community of Hyen in
<LOCATION>Nordsfjord</LOCATION> in western <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION>. He was named <PERSON>Christopher Bonde</PERSON>, a Norwegian name
meaning "farmer," but called himself <PERSON>Christopher Colon</PERSON> -- after "colonus," the
Latin word for farmer.;    The <PERSON>Bonde</PERSON> family, so this version goes, was
involved with the royal families of <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> and left <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> for
<LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> in the <DATE>15th century</DATE> because of conflicts between the two royal
families.;    The Scandinavians have always been miffed that <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> gets all
the publicity for discovering the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>, citing fairly convincing
evidence that Viking sailors explored the New World around the year 1000,
almost 500 years before <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> sailed. (<PERSON>Stephen Birnbaum</PERSON> discusses this
issue, Page 2T.);    Italian historian <PERSON>Gianni Granzotto</PERSON>, in a <DATE>1984</DATE> biography,
says <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> began his sailing career as a boy, perhaps as young as 13,
accompanying wool shipments belonging to his father.;    Off to sea;    In
<DATE>1476</DATE>, according to American historian <PERSON>Samuel Eliot Morison</PERSON>, a Genoese convoy
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was with was attacked by a Franco-Portuguese war fleet of about a
dozen vessels, and <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was wounded in the battle. He escaped his sinking
ship and managed to swim and cling to an oar until he reached the shore of
<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Lagos.</LOCATION>;    He apparently was not taken prisoner, because the
next year he sailed to <LOCATION>Iceland</LOCATION> and then moved back to <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> to take up work
as a chart maker and sailor.;    <PERSON>Granzotto</PERSON> opines that it was a move of
fateful consequence, because <LOCATION>Genoa</LOCATION> offered little incentive for
world-exploring voyages. <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>, on the other hand, was by this time a
center for maritime studies, and its explorers were at the forefront of the
epic voyages of discovery.;    After about eight years in <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>, plus a
marriage and a number of wide-ranging voyages, the saga now has <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
starting his round of visits to the royal courts of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, trying to get
monetary backing for a voyage to discover a western route to <LOCATION>India.</LOCATION>;    Myth
has it that he stood alone in the belief that the world was round, and was
turned down again and again by ignorant nobles unwilling to fight against
traditional geographers.;    In fact, most anybody with an ounce of education
believed by this time that the world was round. What <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> had to sell was
a new route, one that would be cheaper and more efficient than the overland
routes that had been used for centuries, or the new southern ocean route
around the tip of Africa.;    He first went to the king of <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> in <DATE>1483</DATE>.
The king, <PERSON>John II</PERSON>, was one of the many Portuguese monarchs who were ardent and
educated supporters of exploration, but he felt the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> route was too
uncertain.;    Rejected, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> tried next door, in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. In <DATE>1485</DATE>, he
arrived at <ORGANIZATION>Palos de la Frontera</ORGANIZATION>, a tiny port just across the <ORGANIZATION>Rio Tinto</ORGANIZATION> from
the Portuguese border. Near Palos was the monastery of La Rabida.;    A
devious schemer?;  Those who think <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was a devious schemer believe his
arrival in the area was no quirk. At La Rabida were two prelates, Father
Antonio de <PERSON>Marchena</PERSON> and Father Juan Perez.;    De <PERSON>Marchena</PERSON> was a cosmographer,
a man popular at court and a man not ill at ease with the vision of a round
world. And <PERSON>Perez</PERSON> (the plot thickens) was Queen Isabella's personal confessor.;
   By <DATE>1486</DATE>, thanks to the two clergymen, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> had been presented at court,
but not to the king and queen. Ferdinand and <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON> were busy kicking the
Moors out of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, and the siege of the last major Moorish stronghold,
<LOCATION>Granada</LOCATION>, was under way. Columbus had to wait until the expulsion was complete
-- a wait that lasted six years.;    In <DATE>April 1492</DATE>, the victorious <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON>
met <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> at the small village of <LOCATION>Santa Fe</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Granada</LOCATION>, one of a series of
meetings the two had over the years. This time, she was ready to support the
scheme.;    But according to <LOCATION>Granzotto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> made outrageous demands. In
exchange for royal backing, for example, he wanted <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of all profits
from the new world. He also wanted the title of Admiral of the <ORGANIZATION>Open Ocean</ORGANIZATION>. The
sovereigns eventually agreed, then later reneged on the deal, starting a
series of lawsuits between the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> family and the crown of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> still
not resolved.;    <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON> did not hock her jewels to pay for the trip, by the
way; her husband, <LOCATION>Ferdinand</LOCATION>, had to approve all bills, and in this case, the
money came from the royal treasury, and according to historian <PERSON>Morison</PERSON>, from
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> himself. The cost to obtain and outfit three ships? Morison says
<MONEY>$14,000</MONEY>.;    Because of crowded conditions in other ports, it was decided that
the voyage would commence from <ORGANIZATION>Palos de la Frontera</ORGANIZATION>. Isabella, one of
history's darker figures, was a violent anti-Semite who is given credit for
beginning the Spanish Inquisition and for formulating the <DATE>March 14, 1492</DATE>,
order for the expulsion of all Jews from Spain.;    ecause of that order, many
southern Spanish ports were filled with refugees; the two sovereigns finally
ordered all ships carrying Jewish exiles to leave port by <DATE>Aug. 2</DATE> -- the day
before <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> sailed.;    Land Ho!;  It took the three ships -- the immortal
<ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Nina</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> -- more than 40 days to reach the Bahamas
(including a forced layover in the <LOCATION>Azores</LOCATION>). Ferdinand and <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON> had offered
a lifetime annuity to the first man to spy land in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>. Granzotto
tells us it was Rodrigo de Triana aboard the <ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION>. At <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME>, <DATE>Oct. 12, 1492</DATE>,
he yelled "Tierra, tierra!" And never got a dime.;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> later claimed
that he was the first to spot land. He said the previous evening, <DATE>Oct. 11</DATE>, he
had spotted a candle light on shore. Granzotto, noting that the ships were at
that point about 30 miles offshore, says it would have been impossible to see
the light. "A cruel abuse of power," he calls the action. Columbus kept the
prize.;    <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE> -- <LOCATION>Columbus Day</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> -- he went ashore at
<LOCATION>San Salvador Island</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> and claimed it for <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. He and his crew
made the first recorded contact between Europeans and the natives of the <LOCATION>New
World</LOCATION> -- in this case, apparently, the Arawak Indians.;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> took
several Indians back to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> with him and presented them at the royal court
in <LOCATION>Barcelona.</LOCATION>;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> made four more voyages to the new lands but
significantly never really recognized that two major land masses were nearby.;
   He explored many of the islands of the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> (and did step ashore in
what is now <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>) but found little gold and no proof at all that he had
discovered a new route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. His health worsened (he caught malaria, had
gout and arthritis), and worse, the coral and sand islands of his new realm
yielded little that increased his fortunes.;    Royal displeasure;  Ferdinand
and Isabella were less than pleased by these voyages. On one, he lost a whole
fleet. On another, he was forced to deal with a mutiny that eventually saw him
returned to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> in chains.;    The sovereigns had little to show for their
backing and were more and more reluctant to abide by their contract with
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, especially the part that gave him <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> of all the goodies
(such as they were) coming back from the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. Then his chief ally,
<LOCATION>Isabella</LOCATION>, died in <DATE>November 1504</DATE>, less than a month after his return from the
last voyage.;    He and <PERSON>Ferdinand</PERSON> fought a prolonged battle over what was owed
to whom, a battle that apparently worsened <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' already frail health (he
was 53 at the time).;    In the <DATE>spring of 1505</DATE>, he moved to <LOCATION>Valladolid</LOCATION> in
northern <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, where he died a year later. He died too soon to realize that
his dream of gold and glory was real, and that the new world was more than
sandy, barren islands in the middle of the ocean. Within 15 years, <PERSON>Hernan
Cortes</PERSON> had defeated the Aztecs and by <DATE>1532</DATE>, <PERSON>Juan Pizarro</PERSON> had taken control of
the Inca empire.;    Whether he was a gold-hungry, greedy con artist who sold
a bill of goods to a couple of naive monarchs, or a great mariner and
courageous explorer, continues to be a historic debate even today, almost five
centuries later.;    If Columbus/Colombo/Colon were around today, he might be
pleased to know his name is still widely known. Or he might just fly off to
<LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> to see <PERSON>King Juan Carlos</PERSON> and check on that <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> he has coming.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  ZEKE WIGGLESWORTH, Mercury News Travel Editor  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910707  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  July  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING; PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,912  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday July 7, 1991
00189123,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06288008 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06288008 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  IMAGE; BOAT; TRIP; NORTH-AMERICA; PAST; HISTORY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  For the second time in history, Spain on Sunday sent the Nina, the Pinta and
the Santa Maria westward from the mouth of the Rio Tinto. This time, however,
the seafarers knew where they were headed.;   Crown Prince Felipe watched as
replicas of the three ships -- with 80 crew members aboard -- embarked on a
state-funded re-enactment of Christopher Columbus' 1492 voyage across the
Atlantic.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  THIS TIME, CREW MEMBERS KNOW WHERE THEY'RE GOING.
3 REPLICAS TO RE-ENACT COLUMBUS JOURNEY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The replicas are the flagships for <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s 500th anniversary commemoration
of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' journey, which changed both <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> forever. The
Italian navigator was looking for a new route to the Far East.;   The
"Discovery Ships" left a day after the 499th anniversary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' landfall
on <LOCATION>San Salvador Island</LOCATION> in the <LOCATION>Bahamas.</LOCATION>;   They are to lead a procession of
tall ships into <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> harbor as part of next year's Fourth of <DATE>July
celebration.</DATE>;   Like the first flotilla, the modern expedition is to stop over
in the <LOCATION>Canary Islands</LOCATION> off the African coast before heading for the Bahamas.;  
After landing on <LOCATION>San Salvador Island</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> and its smaller
expedition aims to dock in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> in <DATE>January</DATE>, then head for <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Tampa</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>St. Augustine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Newport</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>New York.</LOCATION>;   The three Spanish-built replicas first left <LOCATION>Huelva</LOCATION> last
year -- heading eastward -- on a test voyage that took them to ports in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Huelva, Spain  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Peninsula/Am  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911014  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  244  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 14, 1991
00288008,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06099136 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06099136 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Drawing; DRAWING: On his last trip to the New World in 1502, Christopher
Columbus abandoned two leaking caravels in Jamaica. Marine archaeologists
think they have found the spot, and they hope to dig up the ships.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  HISTORY; BOAT; FOUND; JAMAICA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  When he set sail with four small caravels on his final trip to the New World
in 1502, Christopher Columbus expected to find his long-sought shortcut to
Asia and emerge from the disgrace that less than two years before had seen him
stripped of honors and clapped in chains.;    Instead, with two leaking
caravels already abandoned in Panama after a year of perilous wandering, and
the remaining two no longer seaworthy, the ailing 52-year-old admiral and his
mutinous crew barely made it to the beach in this placid bay on the north
coast of Jamaica.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COLUMBUS SHIPS REPORTEDLY FOUND
TWO VESSELS BELIEVED TO BE IN JAMAICAN BAY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     But <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' misfortune -- shipwrecked here for a year and five days only
"a crossbow shot," as his son phrased it, from a band of hostile Arawak
Indians -- may be a boon to <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> and a team of Texas-based marine
archaeologists. They believe they have found the spot where <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> ran the
two caravels aground 488 years ago.;    "We are <PERCENT>98 percent</PERCENT> sure they are
here," said <PERSON>Dr. James M. Parrent</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Institute of Nautical Archaeology</ORGANIZATION> at
<ORGANIZATION>Texas A&amp;M University</ORGANIZATION>, who, in cooperation with the government of <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>,
first began looking for the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> caravels in <DATE>1982.</DATE>;    After starting work
in earnest <DATE>last summer</DATE>, <PERSON>Parrent</PERSON> said he hopes soon to unearth the keels and
some of the lower hull planking of the caravels "Capitana" and "<LOCATION>Santiago</LOCATION> de
Palos" -- all that could be expected to remain after almost five centuries
under the bay's bottom -- for expert study and eventual display in a <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>
museum.;    "We are charged with locating perhaps the most important historic
archaeological site in the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Parrent</PERSON> said, noting that as the
quincentennial of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' first voyage in <DATE>1492</DATE> approaches, no other trace
has been found of the ships he sailed.;    They not only will be the oldest
European vessels discovered in the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION> and the only ones
actually commanded by <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, he said, they also will help solve a simple
question that has plagued naval architects and historians for centuries,
namely: What did a caravel look like?;    <LOCATION>The Nina</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION> -- mainstays of
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' first voyage, the Spanish-underwritten expedition that launched him
into Western lore as the finder of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> -- were fast-sailing caravels that
he preferred over the larger, more lumbering <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>. Yet no reliable
drawing, painting or naval architect's plan of any of the vessels ever has
been found.;    Although divers have uncovered remains of other 16th-century
vessels thought to be similar to those sailed by <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, there remains so
much uncertainty that every attempt to construct replicas, including several
now under way for quincentennial celebrations, has involved guesswork, <PERSON>Parrent</PERSON>
said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  DON A. SCHANCHE, Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  St. Ann's Bay, Jamaica  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910408  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DRAWING  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  476  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday April 8, 1991
00099136,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06274017 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06274017 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Koski-Karell  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROBE; BOAT; HISTORY; US  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  While the rest of the world is toasting Christopher Columbus next year, Daniel
Koski-Karell hopes to uncork an archaeological spectacular by confirming
discovery of the long-lost wreckage of Columbus' flagship, the Santa Maria.;  
Koski-Karell, 44, a professional archaeologist and underwater explorer,
believes he spotted the Santa Maria's coral-encrusted timbers while snorkeling
in 15 feet of water off the northern coast of Haiti in 1987.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  EXPLORER HOPES TO FIND COLUMBUS' LOST SHIP  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     This week, a private salvage vessel is steaming from <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> toward the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> to begin a systematic search of more than 100 sunken shipwrecks
along the Haitian coast to determine whether Koski-Karell's hunch is correct.;
  Next year marks the 500th anniversary of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' first visit to the New
World. The explorer landed in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION> on <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>, 1492.;   Later on that
epochal first voyage, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> visited what became <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> and planted a cross
claiming the island of <LOCATION>Hispaniola</LOCATION> for Spain.;   Cruising eastward north of the
island, which today embraces <LOCATION>Haiti</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Dominican Republic</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> set
sail from <LOCATION>Cap-Haitien</LOCATION> on Christmas Eve of 1492.;   About an hour after
<TIME>midnight</TIME>, strong tidal currents shoved the square-rigged wooden vessel onto a
barrier reef. As the tide receded, the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>'s seams split. The crew was
forced to abandon ship.;   <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> transferred to the smaller <PERSON>Nina</PERSON> and
returned to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, leaving most of the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>'s crew ashore to build a
fortified settlement he called "Navidad" (Christmas), using timbers from the
shipwreck.;   When <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> returned the next year, he found that Indians
resentful over their mistreatment by the Spaniards had killed all the settlers
and burned <LOCATION>Fort Navidad</LOCATION> to the ground.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Arlington, Va.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910930  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  274  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, September 30, 1991
00274017,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911007-0146
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911007-0146.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Television:
   Columbus and His Controversial Legacy
   ----
   By Dorothy Rabinowitz
</HL>
<DATE>
10/07/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   Toward the very end of this documentary, a beaming Edward
I. Koch appears -- one of a group of people invited to give
their views on Columbus's legacy. Always a man to get down to
the real significance of events, Mr. Koch, who was then still
mayor of New York, observes, "If Christopher Columbus had not
crossed the seas in 1492, I would never have been the mayor.
Isn't that true?"
   It is a nice moment, the mayor in his old form. Besides,
by this time in the proceedings -- the end of a grandly
conceived, extraordinarily detailed seven-part PBS series --
we are about ready for a laugh. However, neither the National
Council of Churches, nor other Columbus bashers, will find
much to be amused at or to like in "Columbus and the Age of
Discovery," whose first two episodes aired last night.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Try though the film makers did to accommodate all views,
including the current politically correct one, the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
that emerges from this work is unmistakably a heroic figure,
whose achievement and historic legacy are eminently worthy of
celebration. This is not, of course, the view of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, which recently took occasion to express
its horror at the prospect of the quincentenary celebrations.
In keeping with the advanced political views for which it is
justly famed, the <ORGANIZATION>NCC</ORGANIZATION> declared that <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s arrival in the
<LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> was an occasion for "repentance" not celebration,
since <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s disovery had led to "genocide" as well as
"ecocide" and a host of other crimes against humanity too
numerous to mention here. The European discovery and
settlement of the New World was, in the view of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION>, "a historic tragedy."
   In this posture, the <ORGANIZATION>National Council of Churches</ORGANIZATION> is,
needless to say, not alone. The <ORGANIZATION>National Endowment</ORGANIZATION> for the
Humanities, the second largest financial supporter (after
<ORGANIZATION>Xerox</ORGANIZATION>) of "<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> and the Age of Discovery," not long ago
refused to fund another film project because of its treatment
of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>. In the opinion of that film maker too, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
was guilty of genocide -- a view, it need hardly be said, now
all the rage among the politically enlightened.
   The current PBS series doesn't neglect the ravages that
the age of discovery brought to the native peoples of the new
land. But neither, to its credit, does it neglect to note the
benefits the Europeans brought to the New World, and also
those they took from it. The most engrossing installment is
"The Columbian Exchange" (named after the <DATE>1972</DATE> book of the
same name, by <PERSON>Alfred W. Crosby</PERSON>, on which it is based). This
segment, which airs tomorrow night as part six, follows the
journey of the potato, of which Europeans were ignorant till
it was brought to their shores from the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION>. The
potato, discovered in the <LOCATION>Andes</LOCATION>, became the subsistence crop
that fed and enlarged the population of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. This
impressive episode (the script was written by <PERSON>Graham Chedd</PERSON>)
also delivers a shattering history of the Irish potato
famine. It connects events and consequences, something that
this documentary does, on the whole, very well.
   The potato famine brought the migration from <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION> to
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>. African slaves worked and died on the sugar
plantations of the New World. But -- as this production makes
clear -- the <LOCATION>New World</LOCATION> also introduced the corn and cassava
that would become the mainstays of the African food supply.
The series (produced by <PERSON>Zvi Dor-Ner</PERSON>) often feels like a
return visit -- a fascinating one to be sure -- to the
gradeschool classroom, where teachers once taught geography
and history and where -- so we are assured -- it is still
taught.
   The series is at its best in this factual mode. On the
other hand, nothing in the script equals the power of the
readings from <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s diary of his voyage: "<DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
<DATE>September 16, 1492</DATE>. Today there were some clouds and it was a
great delight to enjoy the morning. Nothing was lacking but
to hear the nightingales."
   At its worst, the script can get to be like a good part of
tonight's first hour, titled "The Crossing." Here we are
dragged aground, through the Spanish navy's commemoration of
the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> quincentenary. Captains and crews man replicas
of the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> and attempt to retrace
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s first voyage. If there were any justice in the
world, a special place in hell would be reserved for the
person who invented dramatic re-enactments. Granted,
television requires pictures, which this sort of re-creation
can provide, but such pictures come at a high cost to
authenticity. Parts of the re-enactment of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s voyage,
in fact, seem positively unhinged. At one point, a sonorous
voice declares that "many things have changed in 500 years,
but not the pattern of life on a sailing vessel" -- a message
accompanied by footage of a sailor in yuppie athletic togs
doing his situps. Also helping to put us in the historical
mood is the pop vocal blaring from the <LOCATION>Nina</LOCATION> or maybe it's the
<LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION>. In one corner of the deck on which <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s men are
supposed to be sailing, a sailor sits playing "As Time Goes
By" on his trumpet. Yes, we can feel the 15th century all
around us. At another point, we are privileged to see a power
boat draw near one of the <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> replicas -- and to learn
that it carries one sailor's girlfriend and his parents, on
an outing.
   In short, this production has its flaws. Some are simply
annoyances, such as the repetition of cautious formulations
designed to avoid offending any political side. Columbus is
forever being described as a man who changed the course of
history "for better or for worse" or its equivalents -- of
which there are many. And -- not to be stuffy -- but is it
asking too much of a PBS film into which millions were poured
that its writers have enough of a grasp of English usage to
keep them from producing lines such as the one that informs
us that <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> was so rushed, he had no time "to
contemplate the enormity of his journey?"
   Flaws and annoyances aside, this exploration of <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
and the New World is a major achievement, a fact that becomes
increasingly evident in the final three hours, which air
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> nights. At the end, the film's effort
to maintain an even keel in all political directions finally
yields, as the narrator, with some passion, utters the last
line: "So let us commemorate -- and yes, celebrate
<PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>." If this portrait is the worst thing to
happen to <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> and his legacy in the months to come, we
will have reason to be grateful.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051390-0137 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 218341 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 13, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 4; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
802 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SEARCH FOR THE NEW WORLD LAUNCHES MODERN TURF WAR; 
</P>
<P>
PROTOCOL: THE CITY AND COUNTY ARE FIGHTING OVER WHO GETS THE SPOILS FROM 
CELEBRATION OF 500TH ANNIVERSARY OF COLUMBUS' VOYAGE. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RICHARD SIMON, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Although the 500th anniversary of <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>' discovery of the <LOCATION>New 
World</LOCATION> is still two years away, the city and county are engaged in what one 
official calls a "protocol war" over control of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' celebration. 
</P>
<P>
Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON> said it was insulting that a federal commission selected the 
<ORGANIZATION>County Board of Supervisors</ORGANIZATION> as the local coordinator for the <DATE>1992</DATE> celebration. 
</P>
<P>
Unless the commission reconsiders, the mayor's office said, the city will drop 
out of the celebration, whose main event will be a parade of tall ships, led by 
replicas of the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Pinta</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, which will sail into <LOCATION>Long Beach 
Harbor</LOCATION> and other ports around the country, but not <LOCATION>Los Angeles Harbor</LOCATION>, 
according to the mayor's office. 
</P>
<P>
City pride and tourist dollars are at stake, according to <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON>'s chief of 
protocol, <PERSON>Beatrice Canterbury Lavery</PERSON>. "This is not a silly fight between the 
offices of protocol," she said. 
</P>
<P>
But Supervisor <PERSON>Ed Edelman</PERSON> said, "Egos are involved." 
</P>
<P>
"These protocol wars should cease," <PERSON>Edelman</PERSON> added. "Every time I talk to 
diplomats here, they tell me they're always in the middle between the city and 
county." 
</P>
<P>
The supervisors established their own office of protocol in <DATE>1983</DATE> after 
receiving what they considered casual treatment during a visit to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
by <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s Queen Elizabeth. 
</P>
<P>
While <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> played host to the queen and repeatedly was photographed at her 
side, the supervisors had to remind city officials to include them on the 
invitation list for a small luncheon planned for her at the <ORGANIZATION>Music Center</ORGANIZATION>, a 
county-run facility. 
</P>
<P>
Since then, the city and county offices of protocol have clashed over such 
things as who should be first to greet visiting dignitaries and seating 
arrangements at dinners, according to officials who were present. 
</P>
<P>
In the latest dispute, <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> said he was shocked by the selection of the 
county to coordinate <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' celebration -- especially after he traveled 
to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> last year to discuss the city's plans for the event with <PERSON>King Juan 
Carlos I.</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
The designation was awarded in <DATE>April</DATE> by the federal <ORGANIZATION>Christopher Columbus 
Quincentenary Jubilee Commission</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The county's volunteer chief of protocol, <PERSON>Sandra J. Ausman</PERSON>, said: "The 
commission wanted a governmental body that had the ability to bring together 
all the cities of the county. 
</P>
<P>
"This (celebration) belongs to everyone," she said. "It doesn't belong to one 
city." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON>, in a strongly worded letter to the commission, pointed out that 
the city spent three years planning for the celebration. 
</P>
<P>
"It was even more insulting that this decision was made without our knowledge 
or consultation," he wrote. 
</P>
<P>
The city should run the celebration because it was founded by the King of 
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Lavery</PERSON>, who is paid <MONEY>$56,104</MONEY> a year. 
</P>
<P>
"We are the Spanish city," she said. "The county is not a Spanish county." 
</P>
<P>
Lavery complained that the county "never informed us they were going to compete 
with us. . . . The county keeps trying to come into our territory. I don't 
interfere in their territory." 
</P>
<P>
County protocol chief <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said the county offered to coordinate the event 
after being approached by a commission official and a Spanish diplomat who 
complained that the city was not making enough progress. Supervisor <PERSON>Mike 
Antonovich</PERSON> added that members of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' Italian community also complained 
to him about the city's efforts to honor the Genovese sailor <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jana Joustra</PERSON>, the commission's public relations director, said: "We felt the 
ball had been dropped by the city. I don't know what they have been doing for 
three years, but they haven't been doing it with us." 
</P>
<P>
Last month's choice of the <ORGANIZATION>Republican-dominated Board of Supervisors</ORGANIZATION> over the 
Democrat <PERSON>Bradley</PERSON> had nothing to do with politics, <PERSON>Joustra</PERSON> said. The commission, 
although appointed by Republican President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, is bipartisan, she said. 
</P>
<P>
The county has established a local committee to plan events and raise private 
funds for the celebration. At least <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> is needed to pay for the ships' 
visit, <PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The replicas will duplicate <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' voyage across the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. 
They will sail into <LOCATION>New York Harbor</LOCATION> on <DATE>July 4, 1992</DATE>, then travel through the 
<LOCATION>Panama</LOCATION> Canal to arrive in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> on <LOCATION>Columbus Day</LOCATION>, <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>. On <DATE>Sept. 27, 
1992</DATE>, they will berth at <LOCATION>Long Beach</LOCATION>, where visitors will be allowed to board. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Ausman</PERSON> said she is working on a way to include <LOCATION>Los Angeles Harbor</LOCATION> in the 
celebration and plans to invite city officials to serve on the organizing 
committee for the celebration. "I am hoping that all of this will be put behind 
us," she said. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Lavery</PERSON> said the chairman of the federal commission recently suggested that "we 
might peel off one of the caravels" and let the ship visit <LOCATION>Los Angeles Harbor</LOCATION>. 
However, she said, city officials responded: "No way." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, (Bulldog Edition) A statue of Christopher Columbus stands at Los Angeles 
County Mall. KEN LUBAS / Los Angeles Times; Photo, Replicas of Christopher 
Columbus' ships will sail into the Southland in 1992. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COLUMBUS, CHRISTOPHER; BRADLEY, TOM; LOS ANGELES COUNTY BOARD OF SUPERVISORS; 
LOS ANGELES -- CELEBRATIONS; EXPLORERS; PROTOCOL; ANNIVERSARIES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880714-0128 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-14-88 1407EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-BRF--Japan-Columbus     07-14 0144</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Japan-Columbus,0146</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan To Build Replica Of Santa Maria</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> will build a replica of <PERSON>Christopher
Columbus</PERSON>'s ship, the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, and sail it from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>
in <DATE>1992</DATE> to mark the 500th anniversary of the explorer's discovery
of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, an official said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Akihiko Osugi</PERSON>, an official at <ORGANIZATION>Kadokawa Publishing Co.</ORGANIZATION>, said the
plan was announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> by company president <PERSON>Haruki Kadokawa</PERSON>,
who is chairman of the organizing committee.
   Osugi said that at the suggestion of Eikichi Hayashiya, a former
Japanese ambassador to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Kadokawa</PERSON> and other businessmen,
politicians and scholars decided to fulfill <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' dream of
sailing from <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
   He said Japanese technicians will build a replica of the
three-mast <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>, used by <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> when he discovered
American in <DATE>1492</DATE>. The replica, to be built in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>,
will cost <MONEY>$9.85 million</MONEY>, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890909-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-09-89 0307EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Names     09-09 0723</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Names,0753</SECOND>
<HEAD>Names in the News</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY14</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WEST PALM BEACH, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>GUAYAQUIL, Ecuador (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>HUELVA, Spain (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>VANCOUVER, British Columbia (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Actor <PERSON>Burt Reynolds</PERSON>' idea to expand
business at his ranch is causing some disagreement.
   Reynolds wants a zoning change for the <ORGANIZATION>B.R. Ranch</ORGANIZATION>, where he lives
and has a feed store, souvenir shop and petting farm.
   His plan to add a gas station and car wash, double the size of
the souvenir shop and build shops and offices was approved by a <LOCATION>Palm
Beach County</LOCATION> advisory panel <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   County site planner <PERSON>James Youngblood</PERSON> said the zoning change is
appropriate for the site in rural <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>. Earlier, a county staff
report called the planned development ``too intense'' and said it
would ``create a lone commercial pocket'' in a rural area.
   County commissioners will consider the plan at a public hearing
<DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900604-0055
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900604-0055.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   This Time, the Ships
   Really Will Fall Off
   The End of the Earth
   ---
   To Honor Columbus, Teams
   Design Sailboats to Mars,
   But the Obstacle Is Money
   ----
   By Jerry E. Bishop
</HL>
<DATE>
06/04/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   I.AER
</CO>
<IN>
AEROSPACE (ARO)
</IN>
<LP>
   About this time of year in 1490, Columbus was chewing his
fingernails in Salamanca, Spain, waiting for a royal
commission to advise Ferdinand and Isabella on whether they
should finance his proposed voyage west to reach the East.
   Half a millennium later, dozens of amateur and
professional space enthusiasts await word of who, if anyone,
will finance a voyage that seems almost as far-fetched: a
race to Mars by solar-sailing spaceships.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Early last year, these space fans' imaginations were
grabbed by a proposal from the <ORGANIZATION>Christopher Columbus
Quincentenary Jubilee Commission</ORGANIZATION>. To mark the Italian's
discovery, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> group suggested, teams from around the
world would build and launch in <DATE>October 1992</DATE> a fleet of three
small spaceships unlike any ever seen.
   Once in space, each of these unmanned ships would unfurl
thousands of square yards of gossamer sails that would billow
out under the almost infinitesimal pressure of sunlight.
Driven only by light bouncing off the sails' surfaces and
steered from Earth by electronic tillers and mainsheets, the
ships would tack past the moon and head for the red planet.
   The team whose sailing ship made the quickest transit from
<LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> to Mars would claim the first Columbus 500 Space Sail
Cup, a trophy that would be put up for grabs every 10 years.
   At least that was the plan the <ORGANIZATION>Jubilee Commission</ORGANIZATION> put
forth in late <DATE>1988</DATE>. Fascinated by the idea, space cadets of
all ages and disciplines rushed to their computers and
drawing boards. Last <DATE>November</DATE>, a committee of experts picked
the preliminary designs of eight teams -- three from the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
and one each from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> and the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> -- that seemed to have a chance of actually
making it to Mars.
   But alas, history repeats itself. Many of the would-be
space sailors say they feel the kind of letdown <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> must
have felt in <DATE>1486</DATE> when a rich Spaniard, the <ORGANIZATION>Conde de Medina
Celi</ORGANIZATION>, backed out on a promise to lend him some caravels.
   When the <ORGANIZATION>Quincentenary Commission</ORGANIZATION> called for design
proposals last year, "it indicated it was going to raise
funds," says <PERSON>Harold Fox</PERSON>, director of the solar sail project
University</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>. Scientists and engineers at the
laboratory rounded up government, industrial and university
space enthusiasts in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> and designed a <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY>
solar sail.
   But "they busted the bubble" a month ago, <PERSON>Mr. Fox</PERSON> says of
the commission's <ORGANIZATION>Columbus 500 Space Sail Project</ORGANIZATION>. Not only
did the project's director reveal that no money had been
raised, <PERSON>Mr. Fox</PERSON> says, but "the teams were encouraged to seek
funding on their own." The disappointed <PERSON>Johns Hopkins/APL</PERSON>
team is talking to some potential donors, he says. "We'll
give it a couple more months," but if funds aren't in sight
by then, the project will be shelved, he says.
   "I'm enthusiastic and I'd love to see it happen, but I'm
not into fund raising," says <PERSON>Andreas von Flotow</PERSON>, professor of
<LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. von Flotow</PERSON> and a graduate student will
spend the <DATE>summer</DATE> working on their concept of a <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY>
"heliogyro" with eight 250-foot bladelike sails. But that's
the most he can do without funding, he says.
   A Canadian team has obtained about <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> worth of
hardware and services promised from corporations and this
month will test the waters of Canadian nationalism by
launching a public fund-raising drive. "If we can get nominal
cash donations from 100,000 individuals," then <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> can
launch its own <MONEY>$9.6 million</MONEY> (Canadian) entry in the race,
says <PERSON>Steve Horvath</PERSON>, a computer expert who heads the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian
Solar Sail Project</ORGANIZATION> organized by the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian Space Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   Fittingly, it's the Italians who seem really committed.
"We accepted with enthusiasm to do this space sailing to
Mars," says <PERSON>Joseph Viriglio</PERSON>, managing director of the space
systems group at <ORGANIZATION>Aeritalia</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Turin</LOCATION> aerospace company.
<ORGANIZATION>Aeritalia</ORGANIZATION> is leading an industrial consortium to build and
launch a <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> space sailer to be named the <ORGANIZATION>Capitana
Italica</ORGANIZATION>, the other name for the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>. "We are quite
confident of raising the money," <PERSON>Mr. Viriglio</PERSON> says.
   The man who dreamed up the race and heads the <ORGANIZATION>Columbus 500
Space Sail Project</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Klaus P. Heiss</PERSON>, remains optimistic. <PERSON>Mr.
Heiss</PERSON> is a mathematical economist who has worked on the
economics of a number of space projects, including the space
shuttle. He concedes the project doesn't yet have any money,
but says "funding is being strongly pursued" and a
fund-raising consortium will be organized by early <DATE>July</DATE>. The
project, he says, is still planning to get three ships,
including at least one from <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, ready to launch in
<DATE>October 1992</DATE>. "It can be done if we have <MONEY>$25 million</MONEY> in
cash," he says.
   The idea of sailing through interplanetary space on puffs
of light is far from new, but it's never been tried.
Scientists have known since the <DATE>turn of the century</DATE> that when
light reflects off an object it exerts pressure on that
object. In the <DATE>1920s</DATE>, the details of sun sailing in space
were worked out by two Russians, <PERSON>Konstantin Tsiolkovsky</PERSON> (a
schoolteacher who earlier had devised a remarkably prescient
way to rocket men to the moon) and <PERSON>Fridrikh Tsander</PERSON>, a
mathematician.
   Enthusiasts, however, say a <DATE>1951</DATE> article in Astounding
magazine by scientist and science-fiction writer <PERSON>Carl A.
Wiley</PERSON> gave birth to present concepts of solar sails. And they
trace the idea of a race to a <DATE>1963</DATE> <PERSON>Arthur C. Clarke</PERSON>
science-fiction story about an <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Cup-type race to the
moon among seven space sailors.
   In "The Wind From the Sun," <PERSON>Mr. Clarke</PERSON> noted that the
pressure of sunlight on one's hand was about a millionth of
an ounce. With this minuscule pressure applied to two square
miles of a sail in space, the sail would move about an inch
in the first second and about 60 feet in the first minute,
<PERSON>Mr. Clarke</PERSON> calculated. In an hour it would accelerate to 80
miles per hour, and by the end of the day the ship would be
traveling 2,000 mph -- and the speed would continue to build
day after day.
   The sails could be maneuvered by changing their angle to
the sun's rays, just as a sailing ship maneuvers in the wind.
Power to change the angles of the sail, "trimming" it, as
well as power for communications, could come from
solar-electric cells. Thus, the sail could flit through space
without a drop of fuel.
   All this prompted <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE> to commission Jet
Propulsion Laboratories in <LOCATION>Pasadena</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, to design a
solar sailship to rendezvous with <PERSON>Halley</PERSON>'s Comet when it came
by in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Unlike rocket-launched probes that could only fly
by, a sail ship could maneuver about the comet for several
days.
   The <PERSON>Halley</PERSON>'s project foundered on a budget reef. But the
idea fascinated a group of space enthusiasts in <LOCATION>Southern
California</LOCATION>, who organized the <ORGANIZATION>World Space Foundation</ORGANIZATION> and
built what is still the world's only space-sail manufacturing
machine. In <DATE>1981</DATE> they actually built a 50-foot-square
prototype solar sail of aluminized Mylar plastic, which was
unfurled once, in a gymnasium.
   Designing "sunjammers," as they were dubbed in a <DATE>1964</DATE>
science-fiction story by <PERSON>Poul Anderson</PERSON>, is far from simple.
To get the most sail area per pound of spacecraft weight, the
sail must be tissue-thin. Proposed sails are huge, with
diameters and diagonals three to seven times the length of
the 117-foot <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION>. The Canadians' hexagonal sail would
cover 12,000 square yards, while the disk-shaped one designed
by <ORGANIZATION>Cambridge Consultants Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> would cover 15
acres, or 11 football fields.
   Yet the sails are so light they must be unfurled at least
1,000 miles above the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s surface, where there's not the
slightest wisp of atmosphere to drag them down. This altitude
is beyond the reach of the space shuttle, so ships must be
launched by rocket.
   The trickiest part of the whole race is unfurling the
giant sails after they've been packed into a nose cone.
<ORGANIZATION>Cambridge Consultants</ORGANIZATION> designed its sail, dubbed the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>,
with 36 elastic ribs wound around a central hub, with the
sail folded up between the ribs. In space the ribs would
<DATE>spring</DATE> out radially from the hub.
   The Johns Hopkins/APL team figures its sail will have to
spend 60 to 90 days in a steadily elongating elliptical orbit
before it has enough speed to break free of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s gravity.
If it breaks loose at just the right moment, it will be
grabbed by the moon's gravity and whipped out on a course to
<ORGANIZATION>Mars</ORGANIZATION>, getting there in maybe 400 to 500 days.
   If past is prologue, the would-be space sailors are in for
at least one more disappointment. The finalists are to be
picked this <DATE>October</DATE>, by which time <PERSON>Mr. Heiss</PERSON>'s promised
consortium should know its prospects for funds. This is 500
years almost to the month from the report of the <ORGANIZATION>Talavera
Committee on Columbus</ORGANIZATION>' request. The committee told <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand</ORGANIZATION>
and <PERSON>Isabella</PERSON> that it wasn't proper for them "to favor an
affair that rested on such weak foundations and which
appeared uncertain and impossible to any educated person,
however little learning he might have."
   And President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> doesn't have any jewels to hock.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-12851</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CDOBJADPFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920415
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  15 APR 92 / Survey of Seville and World Expo '92 (1): The fair of the
century - About 18m visitors are expected at Seville's Universal Exposition.
The fair, commemorating the 500th anniversary of Columbus's voyage to
America, also heralds the return of Spain to Europe's mainstream after
centuries of seclusion
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PETER BRUCE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
THE WORLD'S most sophisticated railway lines run up to it. <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s newest
airport was built for it. <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s best roads have just reached it. What if
no one comes to it?
Of course they will] Welcome to the <DATE>1992</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Universal Exposition</ORGANIZATION>, or Expo <DATE>'92</DATE>,
in <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>, the biggest, certainly the most expensive, and easily the most
rapidly assembled celebration of any single event, probably, in human
history.
The cost? About Dollars 9bn, but who's counting? It is too easy to knock
Expo - it is a big, brash, fabulous waste of money  - and much harder to
appreciate what its success means to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
This is a country gripped by one dominating and rampaging anxiety - what do
other people think of it? Hardly a week goes by in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> without a symposium
somewhere devoted to this very serious matter. Its newspapers write articles
about what foreign newspapers write about <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
Now, in these few days before Expo opens and the country's <DATE>1992</DATE> celebrations
(including the Olympics in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>) really get underway, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is
fluffing its skirts and patting its hair like a young lady preparing for her
first date, hoping to get a glimpse of herself in a nice big mirror before
the night is over.
Expo and the foreigners that go to it are that mirror. By Expo's success and
by the smiles on the faces of its visitors, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, or a large part of it,
will judge itself. Spaniards know that many northern Europeans think they
are a lazy, good for nothing and untrustworthy lot.
It is nonsense, of course, but there have been some horrible moments along
the way to Expo: when a terrible fire, caused by careless working practices,
destroyed one of the Expo's most important pavilions in <DATE>February</DATE>, the press
was vicious.
'<ORGANIZATION>Chapuza Nacional</ORGANIZATION>' screamed one - national cock-up  - as if to say it before
some foreigner did. Earlier a replica of the first ship to sail round the
world toppled over moments after being launched and some crew in replicas of
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s three ships tried to run away when they reached the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>.
About 18m people, the organisers say, will go to <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> to meander about
the town and the Expo site between its opening on <DATE>April 20</DATE> and its closure
176 days later on <DATE>October 12</DATE>, 500 years to the day that <PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON>
first set foot in the new World.
The site is <LOCATION>Cartuja Island</LOCATION>, once home to a monastery where <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> often
rested after his great voyages. The 450 hectare island sits in the middle of
the <LOCATION>Guadalquivir River</LOCATION> that skirts <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> and up which eventually sailed
gold-laden galleons for the century or so in which <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> was able to reap
maximum benefit from the colonisation of <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> that <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> had
begun.
The monastery still stands, but dwarfed by the incredible Expo city that has
been built around it. It is impossible to stand in the middle of it - even
while frantic last-minute preparations continued  - and not be thrilled by
the sheer scale of what has been put down on Cartuja and the speed with
which it has been done.
Just <DATE>18 months ago Cartuja</DATE> was little more than a swampy bulldozed mess. In
four days time the Expo will open its 95 pavilions, 70 bars, 150 shops,
40,000-place car park, 16 banks to the public. Somehow, the organisers have
managed to squeeze in 55,000 different pieces of entertainment at 21 stages
dotted around the site. The <ORGANIZATION>New York Metropolitan Opera</ORGANIZATION> will be coming, and
so will opera from <LOCATION>Vienna</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Dresden</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Milan</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> are
sending a steel band.
The whole point is that everyone is coming and Expo '92 is probably going to
be the last truly great cultural statement of this century. It is not, or it
should not be, a trade fair. It is a celebration of knowledge and,
specifically, discovery. The country, theme and corporate pavilions may not
push the barriers of architectural knowledge beyond what we already know,
but nowhere on earth are the eccentric and conventional forms and structures
of the late 20th century so brilliantly scrambled together. At the risk of
sounding like a publicist, Expo promises to be terrific fun.
This is, after all, <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION>. The incredible noise on the streets and in
the bars of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> could just as easily be the sound of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s beating
heart. These people taught the rest of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> the meaning of fiesta.
Visitors might find <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> a little cramped - not any more so than during
its Easter fiesta - but it is the smallest city ever to host a <ORGANIZATION>Universal
Exposition</ORGANIZATION> and it has managed to attract the greatest number of countries to
take part. One result will be a great shortage of accommodation and what is
available will be very expensive.
For most of the time the fair is opened, it will also be unspeakably hot.
That partly explains why the Expo site will be open until four in the
morning every day and also why the organisers felt it necessary to plant
350,000 trees and shrubs around the site. Shade will be Expo's most valuable
commodity.
Just how valuable the Expo is to <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> is already easy to measure. It was
<PERSON>King Juan Carlos</PERSON> who first suggested (naturally, when one is the <PERSON>King</PERSON>, one's
ideas are always one's very own ideas) holding an Expo at <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
That was in the late <DATE>1970s</DATE>. But it was the election of the socialist
government, led by Prime Minister <PERSON>Felipe Gonzalez</PERSON>, in <DATE>1982</DATE> that really set
things moving.
<PERSON>Mr Gonzalez</PERSON> and his most senior advisers were all Andalucians in the early
years and they have bent over backwards to make sure that, along with the
Expo, <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE> would be used to mark the return of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> to
prominence as a major economic and democratic power. Their <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION> was
(and still is) a largely poor, dry and illiterate place. It has bred some
wonderful people but given them precious little to live off.
So <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION> has been showered with gifts for this year. Easily the most
exotic is the world's newest high-speed train line, between <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>, with a branch to the Expo entrance.
Just outside <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>, where the airport was once little more than a
blockhouse, stands a spanking new terminal capable of taking 8m passengers a
year.
After the Expo, it could take <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> 20 years to use that airport to
capacity. Around the city are nearly 70km of new roads and eight new bridges
cross the Guadalquivir, while five new highways connect <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> with
<LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION>'s other great centres and with <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION>.
This is <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION>'s big chance. It has become fashionable to speak of
<LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION> as <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s next, or first, <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION>. But it may just find
the imagination needed to turn the infrastructure it has been showered with
in the past few years to its advantage once all the visitors have gone.
The Expo organisers have already established a project - <DATE>Cartuja 93</DATE>  - which
is designed to preserve the Expo site more or less intact for use as a base
for research and study. <LOCATION>Andalucia</LOCATION> has never shown much interest in the
future, but <LOCATION>Cartuja</LOCATION> may change that.
Just as it may change the way Spaniards think about their past. What is
being celebrated here is <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>'s discovery of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, or what he thought
was the East, and the firm establishment, for arguably the first time, of
true democracy in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>. Both are important, for the Expo has neatly
coincided with an intense effort by <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> to reconnect itself with its
former colonies in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION>, which now account for just 3 per cent of
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s trade.
<LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> holds up a rather different mirror to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> than do its
admiring European partners. It is an older mirror, perhaps darker too. The
devastation wrought by the Conquistadores on the native populations of the
countries they invaded still provokes quick and fiery argument in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>.
Should <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> feel shame at that memory? Surely not now, just as it has been
able to welcome back and legalise the Jews 500 years after their expulsion
by <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Isabella</LOCATION>.
This is not a very contemplative society, but Spaniards who think about
themselves might want to extract as much as they can from the Latin
Americans who come to <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>. That continent's chaos, its struggle for
democracy, has a frighteningly clear reflection in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> as well. Some
people think they know why - that by the time the Conquistadores sallied
forth democracy in <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> had already been lost as a trade off for land and
title.
That notion is suspect simply for being so neat and tidy and the lessons to
be drawn from what <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> began 500 years ago in <LOCATION>Latin America</LOCATION> are not
easily defined. The Spanish started planning for <DATE>1992</DATE> calling it the year of
Discovery until South Americans reminded Spaniards that people were living
in the new world long before <DATE>1492</DATE>. <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> changed the theme of <DATE>1992</DATE>, then, to
the Re-encounter. That seems more apt and, even if it says nothing much, it
is at least a mark of a new humility.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page I
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891231-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-31-89 1119EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Portugal-Discoveries Bjt   12-31 0830</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Portugal-Discoveries, Bjt,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>Is Small Beautiful For Portugal's 500-Year Discoveries Celebrations?</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By TONY SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LISBON, Portugal (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s plans to stage a
headline-grabbing 500th birthday party for <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1992</DATE> have
stirred up a storm of controversy over how <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is celebrating
its own discoverers, who were charting the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> before
<PERSON>Christopher Columbus</PERSON> was born.
   <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> were archrivals in the push in the 15th and
16th centuries to sail off the end of known maps and find new
worlds. Both succeeded.
   But now, many Portuguese fear their neighbors are stealing the
limelight for the <DATE>1992</DATE> fiesta.
   At the center of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s celebrations is <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>'s Expo <DATE>'92</DATE>, a
530-acre international fair that is set to end a six-month run <DATE>Oct.
12, 1992</DATE>, 500 years to the day after <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> reached the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
island of <LOCATION>San Salvador</LOCATION>.
   Also making <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> hot property in <DATE>1992</DATE> will be the excitement of
the Summer Olympic games in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>. And the <ORGANIZATION>European Economic
Community</ORGANIZATION> has chosen <LOCATION>Madrid</LOCATION> as its cultural capital on the eve of
the trading bloc's deadline to create a single European market.
   Compared with all that, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s <DATE>1992</DATE> celebrations seem
lackluster.
   <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s government-appointed <ORGANIZATION>National Discoveries Commission</ORGANIZATION> is
promoting research, exhibitions and the publishing of more history
books about the era.
   It has commissioned American composer <PERSON>Philip Glass</PERSON> to write an
opera for <DATE>1992</DATE> release, based probably on the Lusiads _ an epic
poem about <PERSON>Vasco da Gama</PERSON>'s voyages that was written by <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s
16th century roving bard, <PERSON>Luis de Camoes</PERSON>.
   But the Spaniards got there first by casting Catalan soprano
<ORGANIZATION>Montserrat Caballe</ORGANIZATION> and tenor <PERSON>Jose Carreras</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Cristobal Colon</LOCATION>, an
opera based on trials and tribulations of the Genoese captain. It
sold out when it premiered in <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   News media, executives and even historians here have called for
more glamour to promote <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION>'s past glories and to show that it
is a rapidly modernizing European country.
   ``I'm ashamed at how my country is celebrating the
discoveries,'' said <PERSON>Waldemar de Abreu</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> publisher and
editor of ``The Portuguese Christopher Columbus _ Secret Agent of
<PERSON>King Dom Joao II</PERSON>,'' a 600-page book that claims proof the explorer
was Portuguese.
   ``<LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> could easily have pooled resources with <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> and
staged an Iberian discoveries exhibition in <DATE>1992</DATE>,'' de <PERSON>Abreu</PERSON> said.
   While admitting <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> ``is pegging all the force of its
modernization on <DATE>1992</DATE>,'' <PERSON>Vasco Graca Moura</PERSON>, head of the
<ORGANIZATION>Commission</ORGANIZATION>'s executive board, makes no apologies for not going
overboard in that year.
   ``The main difference is that <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> is only commemorating one
date and a short journey _ <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' voyage in <DATE>1492</DATE> to the <LOCATION>West
Indies</LOCATION>,'' he said.
   ``Our celebrations began last year with <ORGANIZATION>Bartolomeu Dias</ORGANIZATION> and will
only end in <DATE>2000</DATE>, with <PERSON>Pedro Alvares Cabral</PERSON>.''
   Spurred by their pioneering Prince <PERSON>Henry</PERSON> the Navigator's studies
of astronomy and cartography, Portuguese seafarers had claimed the
island of <LOCATION>Madeira</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>mid-Atlantic Azores</LOCATION> archipelago by <DATE>1430</DATE>.
   Dias took his ship around the <LOCATION>Cape</LOCATION> of Good Hope in <DATE>1488</DATE>, leaving
da <LOCATION>Gama</LOCATION> to open up the sea route to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> <DATE>10 years later</DATE>.
   Cabral discovered <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION> in <DATE>1500</DATE>, the Portuguese went east of
<LOCATION>India</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Fernao de Magalhaes</PERSON> _ better known as <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
_ closed the Discoveries circle in <DATE>1520</DATE> by commanding the first
expedition to sail around the world.
   ``Our commemorations match our dimension _ we're smaller than
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, so honestly we can't be as elaborate,'' said the
commission's <PERSON>Antonio Mega Ferreira</PERSON>, though adding <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> still
has a few tricks up its sleeve.
   <LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION> <DATE>last week</DATE> submitted its candidacy to the Paris-based
<ORGANIZATION>International Exhibitions Bureau</ORGANIZATION>, to hold Expo '98 _ a three-month,
international fair, only about a tenth the size of <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>.
   Instead of trying for the Olympics, <LOCATION>Portugal</LOCATION> is expected to bid
in <DATE>January</DATE> to hold soccer's World Cup in <DATE>1998</DATE>.
   Expo <DATE>'98</DATE>'s theme will be East meets West, its hero _ Vasco da
Gama. Graca Moura argues da <PERSON>Gama</PERSON>'s trips to the Orient were as
important as <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' discovery in the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>.
   Mega <PERSON>Ferreira</PERSON>'s plans for Expo '98 include a subway train
connecting the undeveloped left bank of the Tagus estuary with
<LOCATION>Lisbon</LOCATION>'s historic <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> district.
   <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> is already the site of three ornate monuments to the
discoveries _ <LOCATION>Belem</LOCATION> tower and Jeronimos monastery, and former
dictator <PERSON>Antonio Oliveira Salazar</PERSON>'s colossal, caravel-shaped
``Padrao'' _ a pillar that navigators used to leave behind them on
land to mark the spread of the Portuguese empire.
   Salazar in <DATE>1940</DATE> organized an exhibition called ``O Mundo
Portugues'' _ the Portuguese world, that glorified the country's
discoveries and African empire to distract attention from its
isolation in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and World War II that was going on around it.
   ``The (center-right) government has a complex of being linked to
<PERSON>Salazar</PERSON>. They're frightened they'd be accused of nationalism, if
they did more to glorify our history,'' de <PERSON>Abreu</PERSON> said. ``But
nobody's accusing <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s socialist government of anything, and
what is <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION> if not a glorification of <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>'s colonial past?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06126096 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06126096 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo, diagram; PHOTO: Knight-Ridder; News Service; John Goudie, with a bust
of Columbus, is under investigation for alleged financial improprieties
connected with the presidential commission overseeing the Columbus Day
quincentennial.; DIAGRAM: Mercury News. Columbus' route; Columbus first
crossed the Atlantic in 1111492, reaching an island in the Behamas that he
named San Salvador on Oct. 12. The 500th anniversary trip is far more
ambitious--it probably will included sailing up the continenet by truck and
them sailing in the Pacific Ocean.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; ANNIVERSARY; BOAT; FESTIVAL; SAN-FRANCISCO  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  On Oct. 12, 1992, replicas of Christopher Columbus' ships, the Nina, the Pinta
and the Santa Maria, will sail into San Francisco harbor while millions of
tourists and television viewers look on. Festivities and memorabilia sales
will generate tens of millions of dollars for the tourist industry and win the
city flattering publicity of incalculable worth.;    At least that's what San
Francisco city officials hope for the 500th anniversary of Columbus' voyage.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  COLUMBUS DAY 1992 JUBILEE IN DIRE STRAITS
AMID SCANDAL, S.F. TRIES TO SAVE ITS ROLE
IN EVENT  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related article on page 8A of this section.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     But now, in what many see as a classic morality tale of greed and
overreaching ambition, the presidential commission in charge of the
celebration is in shambles, its only big sponsor is refusing to shell out any
more money and its former chairman, <PERSON>John Goudie</PERSON>, is under federal
investigation for alleged financial improprieties.;    <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> officials
have  been left scrambling to save their mega-buck event, even as they try to
distance themselves from the scandal surrounding deals made under <PERSON>Goudie</PERSON>. They
must, by their own estimate, raise <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY> for the local celebration,
which few people have even heard of.;    "We aren't tainted by them," said
<PERSON>Michael Housh</PERSON>, an assistant to Mayor Art Agnos who handled <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s
<DATE>1988</DATE> bid to the national commission.;    But at the same time individuals and
groups around the country were refusing to do business with <PERSON>Goudie</PERSON> because of
what they allege were unethical requests from him, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> alone among
the cities vying for <ORGANIZATION>Columbus Day</ORGANIZATION> was willing -- even eager -- to entertain
unusual demands by the chairman to pay the commission cash up front.;    The
world's most; dazzling event ever;    The quincentenary celebration of
<LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>' voyage to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> had been promoted -- initially by <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, later by
other countries including the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> -- as the most dazzling event of
its kind the world had ever seen. Bigger than the Bicentennial. Bigger than
the Statue of Liberty party.;    By one account, <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> commissions had been
organized in 30 countries, 39 states and 100 cities. Exhibits, movies, tours,
medallions, mugs, T-shirts, sporting events, operas, conferences, books,
scholarships, contests, parties -- the multibillion-dollar <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>
celebration would have it all.;    And everyone wanted a piece of it.;    The
centerpiece of the pageant was to be the re-creation of the historical voyage
itself: Replicas of the <ORGANIZATION>Nina</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>Pinta</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Santa Maria</LOCATION> would sail from
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION>, host of the <DATE>1992</DATE> World's Fair and Summer Olympics, and make their way
to the <LOCATION>Western Hemisphere</LOCATION>, visiting 50 <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> port cities on an extended tour.; 
  But the prize, which <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> won, was who got the show on <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> <DATE>Day
1992</DATE>, the anniversary of the day <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> landed on an island in the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>
that he named <LOCATION>San Salvador.</LOCATION>;    City officials, mesmerized by their vision of
hosting the event, have not let a few inconvenient historical facts get in the
way of a lucrative commercial opportunity.;    <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION> never landed anywhere
near <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. The telegenic caravels, supposedly a symbol of 16th
century discovery, will be flying <ORGANIZATION>Texaco Inc.</ORGANIZATION> flags, and their crew members
will be sporting <ORGANIZATION>Texaco</ORGANIZATION> emblems. And the ships won't really sail in from
anywhere; they will be carted overland from the <LOCATION>East Coast</LOCATION> by a subsidiary of
the <ORGANIZATION>Ringling Brothers</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus.;    Commission</ORGANIZATION> head;
resigned suddenly;    The person heading this massive jubilee in the <LOCATION>United
