<DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900927-0136
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900927-0136.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Sun Microsystems
   Introduces a Printer,
   Companion Software
</HL>
<DATE>
09/27/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   SUNW
</CO>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
SOFTWARE (SOF)
</IN>
<LP>
   MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif. -- Sun Microsystems Inc. unveiled a
printer and printer software, the latest weapons in its
battle to crack markets traditionally served by personal
computers.
   Sun's new software, a $495 program called NeWSprint,
breaks ground for Sun, because it allows the company's
workstations to use a much broader range of printers than
before, including inexpensive dot-matrix machines and
Hewlett-Packard Co.'s popular ink-jet printers. Until now,
Sun workstations could "talk" only to printers with
sophisticated processing abilities built in.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The software is part of Sun's two-year strategy of
increasing its share of markets, such as corporate offices,
that mainly use personal computers tied into networks. Sun
has cut prices of some of its machines to less than <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>,
bringing them to PC price ranges, and has persuaded software
houses, such as <ORGANIZATION>Lotus Development Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, to adapt their PC
software to <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s workstations.
   But without a printer-software package such as NeWSprint,
which includes fonts, or print typefaces, that are compatible
with <ORGANIZATION>Adobe Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s PostScript, Sun's machines couldn't
easily be integrated into many personal-computer networks.
"As far as driving revenue and profit, it's not meaningful,"
<PERSON>Cliff Friedman</PERSON>, an analyst at Bear, <ORGANIZATION>Stearns &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, said. "But
as far as their two-year goal, it's critical."
   The new software is unique, because it places the
"intelligence" necessary for printing -- the processing of
typefaces and graphics, for example -- in the computer,
rather than in the printer. In a conventional scheme, the
laser printer contains the intelligence, which tends to slow
down the printing process.
   Sun's new Sparcprinter, priced at <MONEY>$2,695</MONEY>, prints twice as
fast as <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s older, <MONEY>$6,400</MONEY> LaserWriter. Analysts said that
the printer isn't a threat to more entrenched laser printer
makers, such as <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>, but that it will help Sun
dealers offer more attractively priced computer packages.
closed at <MONEY>$27.75</MONEY>, up <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY>, on volume of more than 1.4
million shares.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900516-0033
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900516-0033.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology &amp; Health:
   Sun Introduces
   Its PC-Priced
   Workstation
   ----
   By G. Pascal Zachary
</HL>
<DATE>
05/16/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), NO PAGE CITATION
</SO>
<CO>
   SUNW
</CO>
<IN>
</IN>
<LP>
   MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif. -- Sun Microsystems Inc. introduced
a computer workstation priced at $4,995, setting a new
standard for high-powered desktop computing at relatively low
prices.
   Sun's new computer, called the Sparcstation SLC, is likely
to cement Sun's lead in the workstation market, one of the
fastest-growing segments of the computer industry. While
Sun's chief competitors in workstations, Hewlett-Packard Inc.
and Digital Equipment Corp., vow to introduce similarly
priced but more powerful workstations, some analysts think
Sun's new machine will confound competitors for many months.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   "This makes it difficult for <ORGANIZATION>DEC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>HP</ORGANIZATION> to keep up with
Sun in the workstation business," said <PERSON>Vicki Brown</PERSON>, an
analysts at <ORGANIZATION>International Data Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Sun declined to estimate future sales of the machine,
though it said it had already received orders for 5,000
units.
   However, <PERSON>Ms. Brown</PERSON> said Sun's newest computer is expected
to lift sales of its year-old Sparcstation family
significantly. She said sales of all three models, including
the SLC, will probably total 95,000 units this year, roughly
three times last year's sales.
   Besides helping Sun satisfy its traditional engineering
and scientific customers, the new machine will add momentum
to the company's assault on the market for personal
computers, generally used by white collar workers.
   "The battle today is on the desktop," said <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>,
Sun's chief executive officer, referring to the company's
plans to butt heads with such PC makers as <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer
Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
   While Sun may steal some PC sales, the new <ORGANIZATION>SLC</ORGANIZATION> lacks a
hard-disk drive, the basic storage device for PCs, and it
can't be upgraded with accessories that improve performance.
   But the machine operates at blazing speeds -- 12.5 million
operations a second -- because it has at its heart Sun's own
Sparc microprocessor. The extra speed is useful in, for
instance, financial modeling or electronic publishing, where
PCs often lack the horsepower to carry out complex tasks.
   Sun is expected to introduce an even faster Sparcstation
before the end of the year, putting further pressure on
competitors. That machine might even share the same packaging
as the SLC, which is designed so that its circuitry shares
the same housing as its 17-inch monitor.
   The packaging is crucial to Sun's profit margins on the
computer, which may sell for as little as <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY> when
purchased in large quantities. <PERSON>Ms. Brown</PERSON> said Sun spent <MONEY>$1
million</MONEY> on tooling for the computer and managed to design the
machine without a fan, which reduces the computer's noise and
manufacturing costs.
closed at <MONEY>$29.25</MONEY> apiece, down <MONEY>$1.25</MONEY> on heavy volume of about
1.9 million shares.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910930-0055
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910930-0055.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology &amp; Health:
   Sun Microsystems
   To Unveil Faster
   Computer `Server'
   ----
   By Stephen Kreider Yoder
</HL>
<DATE>
09/30/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B5
</SO>
<CO>
   SUNW
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<NS>
NEW PRODUCTS &amp; SERVICES (PDT)
</NS>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif. -- Sun Microsystems Inc., attempting
to fill a gaping hole in its product line, said it plans to
unveil today a new line of high-speed "multiprocessing"
servers, computers that use more than one processor.
   Sun is aiming its new line, the Sparcserver 600MP, at
users in big corporations, where servers are often used to
connect desktop computers into networks and central data
bases. The 600MP, with list prices ranging from $45,000 to
just over $105,000, will go up against machines from
formidable incumbents such as International Business Machines
Corp. and Digital Equipment Corp.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Sun has the world's biggest market share in the
workstation computers that are often used by engineers, but
it has lagged in the market for high-end servers that
businesses are increasingly using to replace old-line
mainframe and mini-computers. Sun's servers were seen as too
slow and lacked the sophisticated software needed to direct
the complex tasks that such machines are asked to do.
   "On the server side we've been pretty primitive," said
<PERSON>Lawrence Hambly</PERSON>, vice president of marketing of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s
computer unit. "This is the first really major announcement
of servers that really are worth calling servers."
   The new servers come in versions with two and four central
processors, the "brains" of the machines, and run typical
business software at around 140 transactions per second, a
common measure of computing speed. That's nearly three times
as fast as <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s previous, similarly priced, server models,
<PERSON>Mr. Hambly</PERSON> said.
   Analysts said Sun's new servers are likely to be a hit
with existing Sun users, but they are more skeptical of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s
ability to succeed outside its own camp. The machines "will
be a home run for Sun in its own native market but they're 18
months late," said <PERSON>Douglas Crook</PERSON>, an analyst at <ORGANIZATION>Dataquest
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a market-research firm.
   Companies such as <ORGANIZATION>Solbourne Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Longmont</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Colo.</LOCATION>, have sold multiprocessing machines since <DATE>1989</DATE>. And
Sun, facing an increasingly crowded market for servers in
corporate computer rooms, isn't likely to make big headway in
business applications such as data base servers and online
transaction processing, <PERSON>Mr. Crook</PERSON> said. "They've got
competitors with faster boxes and better technology who've
been there longer," he said.
   Sun also will announce a multiprocessing version of its
Unix operating system, Sun's <PERSON>Mr. Hambly</PERSON> said. Sun will offer
devices allowing users of existing Sun server models to
convert their machines to multiprocessing machines while
keeping the older computers outer package and disk drives, he
said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910722-0153
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910722-0153.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Sun Microsystems Inc. to Introduce Line
   To Bolster Lead in Low-Cost Work Units
   ----
   By Stephen Kreider Yoder
</HL>
<DATE>
07/22/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B3
</SO>
<CO>
   DEC HWP IBM SGI SUNW
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
NEW YORK (NY)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   Sun Microsystems Inc. plans to unveil today a range of
speedier new computers that defend Sun's position as the
leader in low-cost workstations.
   Separately, Hewlett-Packard Co. says it has sped up its
own workstations. And Silicon Graphics Inc. plans to announce
today a low-cost "multimedia" computer that processes
high-quality music and video along with fast
three-dimensional graphics now available only in expensive
workstations.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   While Sun's new workstations are vital to maintain its
position as the highest-volume workstation vendor, analysts
said, the machines don't provide the high-performance machine
they feel Sun needs to compete with offerings from
<ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION>.
   "It's a ho-hum announcement," said <PERSON>Nancy Battey</PERSON>, a
research director at <ORGANIZATION>International Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a
market-research firm. "It continues Sun's leadership in
low-cost. But what they're still lacking is leading-edge
computer performance."
   Sun officials said its new machines are "enhanced"
versions of existing products. One of the machines, the
<ORGANIZATION>Sparcstation ELC</ORGANIZATION>, listing for <MONEY>$4,995</MONEY>, is <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> faster and has
four times the memory of its predecessor, the <MONEY>$6,995</MONEY>
Sparcstation IPC. Another, the <ORGANIZATION>Sparcstation IPX</ORGANIZATION>, will be
similar to the Sun's existing Sparcstation 2 but will list at
<MONEY>$11,995</MONEY>, or <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> less than the older machine.
   With its low-cost workstations, Sun has aggressively gone
after the large pool of users who typically buy personal
computers for business and technical computing tasks. The
Mountain View, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, company's inexpensive machines have
helped it build its No. 1 share of the workstation market.
Sun plans to entice more low-end computer users through a
trade-in program, whereby users can get a <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> discount on
its IPC color workstation by trading in competitors'
workstations or highend PCs.
   Sun is also a leader in introducing workstations that
employ reduced-instruction-set computing, or Risc, a set of
technologies that computer makers are using increasingly to
squeeze more speed out of their computers. But Sun has lagged
in pushing its Risc machines to run faster, allowing <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION> to surpass it in the performance race.
   Sun's new IPX, for example, runs at 24.2 "SPECmarks," a
widely used measure of a computer's speed in doing typical
tasks. H-P last <DATE>March</DATE> began selling a Risc machine that, at
about the same base price as <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s, runs at a faster 55.5
SPECmarks; <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s similarly priced RS/6000 Risc workstation
clocks in <MONEY>32.5 SPECmarks</MONEY>.
   Moreover, <ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> are juicing up their machines. <ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION>
said it will announce today it has begun shipping new
software that increases by about <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> the speed of its Series
700 Risc workstations. <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Armonk</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>, said it will begin
shipping software in <DATE>September</DATE> that will speed up its Risc
machines <PERCENT>27%</PERCENT>.
   Sun's "announcement does absolutely nothing to close the
performance gap," said <PERSON>Robert Weinberger</PERSON>,
workstation-marketing manager for <ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Palo Alto</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Sun also will face assaults on its own stronghold this
<DATE>fall</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>H-P</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Maynard</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, are expected to begin selling Risc machines for around
<MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>. On one hand, Sun's new workstations will help it sell
<PERCENT>47%</PERCENT> more machines in <DATE>1991</DATE> than in <DATE>1990</DATE>, estimates <PERSON>Ms. Battey</PERSON>
of <ORGANIZATION>International Data</ORGANIZATION>. But rivals' low-cost machines this
<DATE>fall</DATE> will be Sun's "first true competition," she says. "That
could stall the growth."
   Separately, <ORGANIZATION>Silicon Graphics</ORGANIZATION> said it will unveil a machine
it calls a "Risc personal computer," essentially a low-cost
version of the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, company's workstations
with multimedia technology added. The machine, dubbed <PERSON>IRIS
Indigo</PERSON>, lists from <MONEY>$7,995</MONEY> and can provide fancy, fast-moving
3-D images that, until now, only came from machines costing
several times that much.
   The machine can process and play music matching the
quality coming from digital-audio-tape players used by audio
buffs today, the company said. Along with other computer
makers, <ORGANIZATION>Silicon Graphics</ORGANIZATION> is aiming at what many expect to
become a booming market among business, schools and
laboratories for multimedia computers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870708-0076 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sun Microsystems to Unveil Computers;
Stock Plummets Prior to Announcement
---
By Brenton R. Schlender
<DD> 07/08/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SUNW
COMPUTERS (EDP) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> is slated to introduce today a new line of high-performance workstations that provide the horsepower of conventional minicomputers costing 10 times as much. 

   But despite the wide anticipation of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement, the company's share price plunged <MONEY>$5.25</MONEY>, to <MONEY>$35.125</MONEY> in national over-the-counter trading yesterday. 
Other technology stocks declined as well, though not as sharply as Sun shares. 
A Sun official said the company didn't have any explanation for the drop in the share price. 

   The new Sun-4 workstations, priced starting at <MONEY>$40,000</MONEY>, are tailored for computer-aided engineering and design uses, as well as for scientific modeling and calculation-intensive tasks. 
They are built around a new microprocessor Sun developed with the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> semiconductor unit of <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. 
The new chip uses so-called RISC -- or reduced instruction set computer -- technology similar to that used in the new generation of computers made by <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION> and workstations made by <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Moreover, in an unusual move, Sun said it will license <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu Microelectronics Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and other chipmakers to sell the special RISC chip to other computer manufacturers. 
The plan is aimed at establishing an industry standard around Sun's workstation and software designs, much like personal computers follow design standards set by <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Some analysts speculated that <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s share price fell because of the apparent riskiness of licensing its microprocessor designs to other chip makers, thus inviting companies to quickly replicate Sun's new machines. 
Others said that <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> is expected to introduce a souped up version of its Micro VAX workstation later this year that will compete directly with Sun's new machine. 

   "This is an unprecedented move on <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s part that changes the rules of the game," said <PERSON>Richard Shaffer</PERSON>, publisher of <ORGANIZATION>Technologic Computer Letter</ORGANIZATION>. 
"Here you have a computer box company getting into the microprocessor design business that chip makers like <ORGANIZATION>Intel Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Motorola Corp.</ORGANIZATION> have long dominated. 
It shows just how ambitious Sun is." 

   Indeed, the Sun-4 announcement is the latest in a flurry of new products and aggressive price-cutting actions taken by the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, Calif.-based company in recent months. 
In <DATE>April</DATE>, Sun chopped the price on its low-end workstation <PERCENT>37%</PERCENT> to less than <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>, a move that has since been matched by its main competitors, <ORGANIZATION>Apollo Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment</ORGANIZATION>. 
The company also recently announced a line of communications products that can connect a full array of personal computers, workstations, minicomputers, mainframes and supercomputers. 
Later this year, the company is expected to introduce some new low-end machines. 

   The new workstation, which can cost almost <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY>, is 2 1/2 times more powerful than its predecessor, the Sun-3, though it costs only about <PERCENT>30%</PERCENT> more. 
It can handle 10 million instructions per second, or <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>, which is faster than most superminicomputers. 

   Archrival Apollo, based in <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, generally has had more powerful workstations than Sun but doesn't have any products as fast as the Sun-4. 
However, rumors of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s new workstation have been widely circulated. 
Last week, <PERSON>Edward Zander</PERSON>, vice president, marketing, at Apollo predicted his company would be back in the race soon. 
"By <DATE>early 1988</DATE>, we think you'll need 25 <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>," he said. 

   The key to the speed of the Sun workstation is the RISC chip, which <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu</ORGANIZATION> helped design in this country, but makes in its Japanese plants. 
It marks the first time that a major <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> computer relied on a Japanese-made microprocessor. 

   "It's a sad state that Sun would have to turn to a Japanese chip maker," said <PERSON>Mr. Shaffer</PERSON>, "but the fact is, <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu</ORGANIZATION> makes crucial parts for a lot of this country's high performance computers." 

   According to <PERSON>Kenichi Katashiba</PERSON>, senior vice president of <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu Microelectronics</ORGANIZATION>, the RISC chip is the product of <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu</ORGANIZATION>'s advanced products division, which was established in <LOCATION>Santa Clara</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> to develop semiconductors custom designed for American customers. 

   The RISC chip works faster because it has fewer basic functions to perform. 
Sun said its design will enable <ORGANIZATION>Fujitsu Microelectronics</ORGANIZATION> and other licensees, including <ORGANIZATION>Cypress Semiconductor Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Bipolar Integrated Technology Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, to further enhance the chip to make it even faster and more powerful while remaining compatible with all the software for existing machines. 
Likewise, the new Sun-4 machines can run the same software that Sun's previous Sun-3 and Sun-2 families use. 

   Sun is supplying special programs that convert programs from some 90 software companies into a form the new machines can understand. 
All of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s computers use a version of <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s Unix operating system as the internal traffic cop routing data and instructions between the microprocessor and the workstation's screen, keyboard, printer and data storage devices. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890412-0248 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-89 0843EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-Sun-Workstations     04-12 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sun-Workstations,0513</SECOND>
<HEAD>Company That Helped Start Workstation Trend To Unveil Revamped Products</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the upstart company
that helped launch the desktop computer industry trend toward
high-powered workstations, was unveiling an entire overhaul of its
product line today.
   Some of the new machines, priced from <MONEY>$5,995</MONEY> to <MONEY>$73,900</MONEY>, boast
sophisticated new graphics and digital sound technologies, higher
speeds and a circuit board that allows full-motion video on a
computer screen.
   <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, Sun's president, said in a prepared statement the
revamped line is another step toward bringing more powerful desktop
computers into everyday business and personal use.
   ``Tomorrow, people will be talking to, gesturing at, and even
arguing with these machines,'' he predicted, saying his new
products reflect ``ease-of-use features found, before now, only in
personal computers.''
   Workstations outperform personal computers by offering greater
speed, more memory and better monitors for enhanced graphics
capabilities.
   The star of Sun's new product line is the SPARCstation 1, ``the
most powerful, full-function computer for under <MONEY>$9,000</MONEY>,'' <PERSON>McNealy</PERSON>
claimed. The price does not include disk drives.
   The machine's speed of 12.5 million instructions per second,
<ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>, is about four times the speed of similarly priced high-end
Macintosh from <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer</ORGANIZATION>, and more than twice as fast as the
most powerful IBM-compatible personal computers. Previously, the
Sun's fastest RISC machine had a speed of 7 <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$22,000</MONEY>.
   The new machine and the revamped older models are designed to
capture markets other than the traditional technical ones that for
years have relied on machines from Sun and rival <ORGANIZATION>Apollo Computer</ORGANIZATION>.
The companies control about <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the workstation market.
   ``This machine is the beginning of Sun getting into the volume
market,'' said <PERSON>Richard Shaffer</PERSON>, editor of <ORGANIZATION>Techologic Computer
Letter</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Anil Gadre</PERSON>, Sun's director of marketing for graphics, predicted
the new products will help the company for the first time sell more
than 100,000 workstations in a single year.
   But <PERSON>Kathleen Hurley</PERSON>, an analyst at the research firm of
<ORGANIZATION>Dataquest Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, said the power and prices of some of the new
products are comparable to others available on the commercial
market.
   Sun is using the SPARC technology, its version of so-called RISC
_ reduced instruction set computing _ in an effort to capture a
significant share of the burgeoning <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> workstation market.
By the mid <DATE>1990s</DATE>, the market for the machines is expected to be
about <MONEY>$20 billion</MONEY> annually.
   Sun also plans to unveil during a two-day conference at the <ORGANIZATION>San
Francisco Civil Auditorium</ORGANIZATION> a library of 500 software packages than
can be run on the new systems.
   Other new products to be announced today include a revamp of the
original Sun-3 workstation line, with the addition of <ORGANIZATION>Motorola</ORGANIZATION>'s
fast 68030 microprocessor chip, three-MIPS machines that will start
at <MONEY>$5,995</MONEY>; a 16-MIPS workstation based on RISC chips starting at
<MONEY>$29,900</MONEY>; and an equally fast SPARC system starting at <MONEY>$40,900</MONEY> that
is designed to operate as a ``server'' to interact with many
computers on a network.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890412-0288 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-89 2141EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-SunWorkstations     04-12 0688</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sun Workstations,0709</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Generation of Workstations Unveiled By Industry Pioneer</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Apollo-Hewlitt Workstations</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By RICH CARTIERE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN FRANCISCO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The upstart company that sparked the
desktop computer industry's trend toward higher-powered and
speedier machines on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> unveiled a new generation of
products _ faster and mightier than before.
   <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of Mountain
View, hailed the line for ``ease-of-use features found, before now,
only in personal computers.''
   Surrounded by dazzling displays of multicolored canvas artwork
at <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>'s Civic Auditorium, analysts and industry members
generally reacted favorably to Sun's machines.
   But not all are convinced the company can beat similar products
already released or planned by major competitors, including Apollo
Computer, <PERSON>Steve Jobs</PERSON>' Next Computer System and <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment
Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``These are beautiful machines, clearly intended to push the
company into a bigger market,'' said software designer <PERSON>Ken Burton</PERSON>.
   ``But are these machines the right price, the right design with
the right capabilities for the business, school and personal-use
market?'' he asked. ``Or do the `other guys' have a more suitable
product for the business desktop? Only time will tell.''
   Workstations outperform personal computers by offering greater
speed, more memory and better monitors for enhanced graphics
capabilities, sometimes including 3-D.
   Some models of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s new line, priced from <MONEY>$5,995</MONEY> to <MONEY>$73,900</MONEY>,
include or can add sophisticated new graphics and digital sound
capabilities, higher speeds and a <MONEY>$12,900</MONEY> circuit board that allows
full-motion video on a computer screen, which can be used for
teleconferencing.
   The new and revamped products from the company, which <DATE>last year</DATE>
had a <PERCENT>28.3 percent</PERCENT> share of the <MONEY>$4 billion</MONEY> annual workstation
market, are intended to capture a major share of the burgeoning
commercial market for workstations. By the mid <DATE>1990s</DATE>, the total
annual workstation market is expected to be <MONEY>$20 billion</MONEY>. For most
of the <DATE>last decade</DATE>, workstations were used primarily by scientists
and engineers.
   The company's success for its new line is pinned on its
comparatively vast library of software available for it.
Competitors so far have fewer few software packages for their
machines.
   The company's SPARCstation 1, the so-called ``star'' of the new
line, will have the ability, for an additional <MONEY>$500</MONEY>, to emulate the
MS-DOS operating system of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp</ORGANIZATION>. That will allow the
SPARCstation to run popular programs written for <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> personal
computers, although at a lower speed.
   SPARCstation 1's <MONEY>$8,995</MONEY> pricetag does not include a disk drive.
   Its speed of 12.5 million instructions per second, or <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>, is
about four times the speed of the similarly priced high-end
Macintosh from <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer</ORGANIZATION> and more than twice as fast as the
most powerful IBM-compatible personal computers.
   Previously, Sun's fastest machine using so-called reduced
instruction computing set technology, or RISC, had a speed of 7
mips and was priced at <MONEY>$22,000</MONEY>. Sun's version of RISC is called
SPARC.
   The SPARCstation 1 offers built-in digital audio capability,
eight megabytes of internal memory, three expansion slots, a
black-and-white screen and a size that is less than half the height
of a traditional PC console. A color-monitor version is available
for <MONEY>$15,500</MONEY>.
   Other new products announced included a revamp of the original
Sun-3 workstation line, with the addition of <ORGANIZATION>Motorola</ORGANIZATION>'s fast 68030
microprocessor chip, three-MIPS machines that will start at <MONEY>$5,995</MONEY>;
a 16-MIPS workstation based on RISC chips starting at <MONEY>$29,900</MONEY>; and
an equally-fast SPARC system starting at <MONEY>$40,900</MONEY> that is designed
to operate as a ``server'' to interact with many computers on a
network.
   <ORGANIZATION>Prime Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that it plans to
incorporate SPARC technology in future engineering workstations.
With this strategy, Sun hopes to turn its SPARC-based systems into
an industry standard.
   Other manufacturers offer machines that compare with Sun's new
models: DEC offers an eight megabyte internal memory workstation,
without disks, with a speed of 14 MIPS for <MONEY>$11,900</MONEY>, but no
expansion slots; <ORGANIZATION>Data General</ORGANIZATION> offers one with 17 MIPS for <MONEY>$7,450</MONEY>,
but with only four megabytes of internal memory and no expansion
slots.
   <ORGANIZATION>Next Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s machine at <MONEY>$9995</MONEY> will offer five MIPS with three
expanson slots and 256-megabytes of optical disk storage capacity
and eight megabytes of internal memory.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900509-0005
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900509-0005.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Workstation
   Options
   Expanding
   ----
   By Stephen Kreider Yoder and Jacob M. Schlesinger
</HL>
<DATE>
05/09/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   SUNW J.TOS DEC HWP
</CO>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<LP>
   The workstation is about to become cheaper and portable as
well, continuing its penetration of the personal-computer
market.
   Sun Microsystems Inc., of Mountain View, Calif., is
expected to unveil on Tuesday a new low-cost version of its
popular Sparcstation that puts it in the price range of many
personal computers. And Tokyo's Toshiba Corp., in a bid to
expand its share of the rapidly growing market for
workstations, said it would begin selling the world's first
portable workstation.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Sun's machine, expected to cost just under <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>, is just
the latest in a technological leapfrogging game by computer
makers; rivals say they will soon best Sun's machine with
still faster, cheaper workstations.
   <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement comes a month after Japanese rival
<ORGANIZATION>Sony Corp.</ORGANIZATION> announced it would sell a portable workstation by
late <DATE>July</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> said it hopes to begin production of its
new machine, based on <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s Sparc chip, in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> by the
end of the year, officials said at a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> news conference.
It is scheduled to go on sale in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> in mid-July.
   Called the <ORGANIZATION>Sparc LT</ORGANIZATION> model, it is the latest demonstration
of <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION>'s ability to pack more and more computing power
into smaller and smaller machines. The company, long a minor
player in computer sales, has become a world leader in laptop
personal computers in the past three years. The new
workstation "is going to extend the market because you're
going to be able to do more things with it," said <PERSON>Peter G.
Wolff</PERSON>, a technology analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Kidder Peabody</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>
office. "It's an innovative step."
   But many computer makers say the market for laptop
workstations is limited. Since the main users of workstations
are scientists and engineers, who typically work with
equipment that isn't readily movable, the advantages of
portability aren't as clear-cut as they are for
personal-computer users.
   In addition, workstations usually gain much of their
usefulness from being hooked up to one another and to other
computers. As a result, users aren't very likely to use them
at home or on the road, as many business executives do with
portable personal computers.
   Workstations, which combine high speed with flashy
graphics and usually run the Unix operating system, until
recently have been high-priced desktop machines selling for
<MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> and up. But prices have fallen steeply since last
year as makers worked toward the high end of the
personal-computer market.
   "The technology wars are really heating up and the
technology price curve is getting steeper," said <PERSON>John Hime</PERSON>,
vice president of systems products marketing at <ORGANIZATION>MIPS Computer
Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> "Sun's got a great machine, but other companies
like <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION> are introducing technology just as fast, if not
faster."
   The new Sun machine, called the <ORGANIZATION>Sparcstation SLC</ORGANIZATION>, will run
at 12.5 million operations per second, analysts familiar with
the machine say. The <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> price tag brings the computer
well into the price range of high-end personal computers,
which don't run as fast and have poorer graphics. Sun's
cheapest machine now is the <MONEY>$8,995</MONEY> Sparcstation 1-Plus.
   Still, the Sun machine may lack important components. The
SLC will be a stripped-down version of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s Sparcstation
built into a 17-inch monochrome monitor with no disk drive
and no ability to be expanded with add-in cards. So it will
have to be tied into a network of other computers to be
useful.
   What's more, any low-priced workstation faces a basic
hurdle: Most of the software programs that businesses use are
written to run on <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s MSDOS operating system,
not on the Unix operating system used by <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>.
   Sun's rivals are critical of the new product. "I don't
think they'll have the performance in the box to make up for
all the things the box doesn't have," said <PERSON>Donald Gaubatz</PERSON>,
group manager for workstations at <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
Digital began selling last year a <MONEY>$5,950</MONEY> workstation that is
only slightly slower than the Sparcstation, he said, adding
that the company plans to keep the price competitively low.
   <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>, likewise, said it plans price cuts and performance
improvements that will bring its machines in line with Sun's
by this <DATE>summer</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION> plans to sell later this
year a low-end workstation based on <ORGANIZATION>Motorola Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s new 68040
microprocessor chip. Hewlett now has the cheapest
workstation, the <MONEY>$3,990</MONEY> DN 2500, running at about <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> the
speed of the new Sun machine, said <PERSON>Mark Tolliver</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett</ORGANIZATION>'s
workstation-marketing manager. "We have no intention of
surrendering that position," he said.
   The new <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> machine, which weighs 17.7 pounds, has a
fold-up screen. Company officials said it weighs a third as
much as the basic Sun model sold in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, and takes up half
the space. It has a processing speed of 13.2 mips and will
sell in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> for about <MONEY>two million yen</MONEY> (about <MONEY>$12,600</MONEY>).
<ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> expects to sell about 3,000 of the machines in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>
this year and about 14,000 next year.
   But, in addition to concerns about the practicality of a
laptop workstation, the <ORGANIZATION>Sparc LT</ORGANIZATION> has some technological
constraints that may limit its use. It currently has only a
built-in black and white screen. Color, often a crucial
feature for the scientists and engineers who are the main
workstation users, won't be available for more than two
years. Unlike battery-operable laptop computers, the machine
has to be plugged in.
   <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION>'s market projections for laptops are "rubbish,"
said <PERSON>Vicky Brown</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>International Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Framington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> "Can you see someone carrying 18 pounds on the bullet
train? We're far away from the point where we're going to
have a big market for laptop workstations."
   Digital's <PERSON>Mr. Gaubatz</PERSON> agrees. Users of Unix workstations
depend heavily on networks that tie them together with other
machines, he said. "There will be some people who would find
a reason to buy it," he said. But most users "are just too
intimately connected to their network. You don't have that if
you have the thing on your lap."
   But <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> officials say that, with desk space more
cramped in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> than in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>, such smaller machines may
have greater appeal in their home market. And they say they
are simplifying the software to try and broaden the base of
traditional workstation users.
   <ORGANIZATION>Toshiba</ORGANIZATION> has been selling Sun workstations in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> since
<DATE>1986</DATE>, and a year ago signed an agreement with Sun allowing it
to develop and manufacture machines based on the Sun system.
"Sun welcomes the Sparc LT," said <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, Sun's
chairman, in a statement videotaped for yesterday's press
conference. "This complementary product will expand the
market for Sparc workstations and servers, just as the PC
market was enhanced by the arrival of laptops."
   The Japanese, who still have only a tiny share of the
world computer market, have been jumping into the <MONEY>$6 billion</MONEY>
workstation market. <ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION> is <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s leader with its News
workstation, which it started selling in <DATE>1987</DATE>, and exporting
the following year.
   ---
   <PERSON>Laurence Hooper</PERSON> contributed to this story.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910610-0019
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910610-0019.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   For Chip Makers, Much Is at Stake
</HL>
<DATE>
06/07/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B1
</SO>
<CO>
   CPQ DEC DGN HIT HWP INTC J.TOS MIPS SUNW
</CO>
<MS>
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
</MS>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
ELECTRICAL COMPONENTS AND EQUIPMENT (ELQ)
SEMICONDUCTORS, INTEGRATED CHIPS (SEM)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
FAR EAST (FE)
JAPAN (JA)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
PACIFIC RIM (PRM)
TEXAS (TX)
UNITED STATES (US)
</RE>
<LP>
   These are tumultuous times for makers of microprocessors,
the tiny chips that play central commander in desktop
computers.
   For a decade, Intel Corp. has dominated the market for
these brainy chips and has profited handsomely as demand
boomed for personal computers using Intel-designed chips.
Motorola Inc.'s chips have been a distant second, the chips
of choice for engineers' computers and for Apple's Macintosh.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   But now a new breed of fast chips is threatening to bring
a change of guard, and to create a new set of winners and
losers in the computer market. The new chips use a technology
called reduced-instruction-set computing, or Risc, a term
used to describe a set of techniques for laying out circuitry
so that chips can perform calculations faster than with older
methods. Risc chips are rapidly winning favor with computer
makers because the chips offer far more speed at lower prices
than older chips offer.
   The power of Risc chips is showing up in the market. <ORGANIZATION>Sun
Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, an early leader in Risc chips, has quickly
gained No. 1 share of the workstation market using its Risc
chip. And Sun is making inroads into PC turf with low-cost
Risc workstations. <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION> unveiled a machine
using its own Risc chip in <DATE>March</DATE> that runs as much as 10
times faster than similarly priced systems using <ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION>'s
latest chip.
   Intel-designed chips still go into <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the PCs sold
world-wide, and the PC market is still 10 times bigger than
the workstation market. But computer makers see in Risc chips
an opportunity to recarve the computer-market pie.
   The big gamble: which of a half-dozen Risc chips to
choose. <ORGANIZATION>Compaq Computer Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has formed a loose alliance
with <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and others that sided with a
Risc chip designed by start-up <ORGANIZATION>Mips Computer Systems Inc</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Toshiba Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and several Taiwanese clone makers have chosen
Sun's chip. <ORGANIZATION>Hitachi Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> sides with <ORGANIZATION>HP</ORGANIZATION>'s chip; <ORGANIZATION>Data General
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> has chosen <ORGANIZATION>Motorola</ORGANIZATION>'s, while <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> uses its own.
   The name of the game for the Risc-chip makers is to woo a
critical mass of computer makers; those who fail to win
allies will become also-rans, locked out of big-volume
markets. The game for computer makers is to bet which chip
will garner the most other computer makers, the most software
and the most users; those that bet on the wrong chip will be
left with warehouses full of machines that no one wants.
   (See related story: "Apple, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> Discuss Swap of
Technology" -- WSJ <DATE>June 7, 1991</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880406-0065 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sun Microsystems to Unveil Computers For General Use Based on 80386 Chip </HL>
<AUTHOR> Brenton R. Schlender (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> SUNW </CO>
<IN> EDP </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a maker of technical workstations, will announce today a new family of general-purpose computer workstations built around <ORGANIZATION>Intel Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s popular 80386 microprocessor. 

   The new computers, with suggested prices starting at about <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY>, represent Sun's first foray into the crowded personal computer market and will give users the ability to run programs written for either of two popular computer operating systems -- <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s MS-DOS, which is widely used in most personal computers, and <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s Unix, which is the system of choice for engineering and scientific computers. 

   "Sun's new computers are a bridge between the commercial world of <ORGANIZATION>DOS</ORGANIZATION> and the technical world of Unix in a single box," said <PERSON>David Korus</PERSON>, a securities analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Kidder, Peabody &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION> who follows the small computer systems industry. 

   Workstations in the past have been used for sophisticated financial modeling and computer-aided engineering and design. 
Recently, price performance improvements have made them comparable in price to powerful personal computers. 

   Sun's introduction of the 386i family of computers had been widely rumored for months. 
"The timing just kind of happened," said <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, president and chief executive officer of the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, company, who said the delay was due in part to "trying to understand the shortage of memory chips," which has been a nagging problem for Sun. 
Earlier this year, Sun had to raise prices on workstations as memory chip prices have climbed. 
Meanwhile chip shortages have caused Sun's backlog for its most popular computers to balloon to 120 days. 

   The new machines will come equipped with a monitor, a floppy disk-drive data storage device, a mouse pointing device, copies of both Unix and MS-DOS operating systems, circuitry necessary to plug the machine into a network and four megabytes of memory -- twice the amount provided by most competing personal computers using the <ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION> 80386. 

   "We think our machine compares favorably with the <ORGANIZATION>Compaq</ORGANIZATION> (<ORGANIZATION>Computer Corp.</ORGANIZATION>) 
Deskpro 386," said <PERSON>Mr. McNealy</PERSON>, referring to the first personal computer to incorporate the powerful <ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION> chip. 
The <ORGANIZATION>Compaq</ORGANIZATION> machine, priced from about <MONEY>$6,000</MONEY> and up, not including Unix, has been popular among power-hungry technical users and has far outsold competing machines. 

   Sun's new 386i family expands the company's family tree to include computers based on three different microprocessors, all using Unix. 
Sun started out building machines around <ORGANIZATION>Motorola Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s 68000 family of microprocessors. 
Last year, Sun unveiled a high-performance chip called SPARC, for Scalable Processor architecture, that it uses in its most expensive and powerful workstations. 

   While Unix is the common thread among all three, analysts worry that three different hardware "architectures" might be too much for Sun to support. 
"The problem many computer companies run into is trying to do too many things to do any of them well," said <PERSON>Richard Shaffer</PERSON>, a computer industry analyst and consultant who publishes <ORGANIZATION>Technologic Computer Letter</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The 386i family presents other potential problems for Sun. 
If it catches on in a big way, it could exacerbate Sun's chip supply problems and perhaps cannibalize sales of its big-selling 3/60 workstation, which faces lengthy production delays. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ901228-0115
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
901228-0115.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   PC Makers Gain
   As Mainframe
   Firms Struggle
   ---
   Compaq, Sun Microsystems
   To Post Jump in Net;
   DEC, Unisys Faltering
   ----
   By G. Pascal Zachary and Stephen Kreider Yoder
</HL>
<DATE>
12/28/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE 10
</SO>
<CO>
   CPQ SUNW DEC UIS AAPL TDM AMH IBM
</CO>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<LP>
   Recession talk has cast a pall on the computer industry,
but some desktop-computer makers are still shining.
   Analysts say results for the December quarter will
illustrate a continued split of the industry, in which many
makers of mainframes and minicomputers post smaller gains
while makers of personal computers and workstations prosper.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Maynard</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION> -- once a
highflier that used its minicomputers to tweak the noses of
oldline makers of more expensive mainframes -- is getting
some nose-tweaking of its own by the likes of <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>,
Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> with less expensive, fast
workstations. Thus analysts say <ORGANIZATION>DEC</ORGANIZATION> profit will drop as much
as <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> in its <DATE>fiscal second quarter ending Monday</DATE>.
   A big part of the problem for <ORGANIZATION>DEC</ORGANIZATION> and other companies such
as <ORGANIZATION>Blue Bell</ORGANIZATION>, Pa.-based <ORGANIZATION>Unisys Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which analysts expect
to post a <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> net loss, is the rapidly growing
trend toward open systems -- computers that use standard
software such as programs written for Unix operating systems.
That hurts makers of proprietary systems -- those that run
software written only for them.
   But it's a boon for Sun and large PC makers such as
Houston-based <ORGANIZATION>Compaq Computer Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, which, despite recession
signs, continue to post strong gains. Analyst <PERSON>Bruce Lupatkin</PERSON>
of <ORGANIZATION>Hambrecht &amp; Quist Inc.</ORGANIZATION> expects <ORGANIZATION>Compaq</ORGANIZATION> to post a <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> rise
in <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> earnings to <MONEY>$133 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.55</MONEY> a share,
<PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> revenue gain to <MONEY>$1.1 billion</MONEY> from <MONEY>$788 million</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Compaq</ORGANIZATION>'s growth is outpacing other leading
desktop-computer makers mainly because of its huge presence
in the booming market for laptop and notebook computers, said
<PERSON>Mr. Lupatkin</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION> is expected to post strong gains in
profit and revenue for its <DATE>fiscal second quarter ending
Monday</DATE>. <PERSON>Peter Rogers</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Robertson Stephens &amp;
Co.</ORGANIZATION>, expects Sun's profit to increase <PERCENT>73%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY>, or
year earlier.
   Not all desktop makers are in the pink. <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>,
Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, is expected
to post roughly flat results for its fiscal first quarter
ending <DATE>Monday</DATE>. <PERSON>Mr. Lupatkin</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Hambrecht &amp; Quist</ORGANIZATION>, expects
slightly lower profit of <MONEY>$115 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1</MONEY> a share, vs.
<MONEY>$125 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>96 cents</MONEY> a share, a year earlier. Sales are
expected to exceed <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> vs. <MONEY>$1.49 billion</MONEY>. For Apple
to see stronger sales, it needs to enter the laptop and
notebook market, <PERSON>Mr. Lupatkin</PERSON> says.
   Some old-line makers -- including DEC -- have bigger
problems as recession fears slow capital spending. <ORGANIZATION>Robert
Herwick of Hambrecht &amp; Quist</ORGANIZATION>, who admits he is "a rip-roaring
bear" on <ORGANIZATION>Digital</ORGANIZATION>, expects the company to post lower net
income of about <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>50 cents</MONEY> a share, for the
year earlier. He expects sales of <MONEY>$3.1 billion</MONEY> vs. <MONEY>$3.18
billion</MONEY>.
   Also, <PERSON>Mr. Herwick</PERSON> says, "the shift away from proprietary
systems to Unix systems in the workstation market is costing
DEC market share." That has hurt <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION>, too, says analyst
<PERSON>Stephen Cohen</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>SoundView Financial Group</ORGANIZATION>. He expects <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION>
to post a net loss of <MONEY>$46 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>29 cents</MONEY> a share, for
the quarter on lower revenue of <MONEY>$2.8 billion</MONEY>. A year earlier,
<ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION> earned <MONEY>$34 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>five cents</MONEY> a share, on revenue
of <MONEY>$2.97 billion</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION> is struggling because of a heavy debt load and
users defecting to open systems, <PERSON>Mr. Cohen</PERSON> says. "The old
core business is declining in profitability and the new
open-systems business they're growing to replace that with
has inherently lower margins," says <PERSON>Mr. Cohen</PERSON>.
   Spending slowdowns in the security and banking industries
have hurt <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>, Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Tandem Computers Inc.</ORGANIZATION> more
than expected, says analyst <PERSON>John Jones</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Montgomery
Securities</ORGANIZATION>. He recently lowered his earnings estimates for
the company and now expects net income in its fiscal first
quarter ending <DATE>Monday</DATE> to fall <PERCENT>74%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$8 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>seven
year earlier. He sees sales rising <PERCENT>4.7%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$457 million</MONEY> from
<MONEY>$436.5 million</MONEY>.
   A general slowdown in capital spending could be helping
<LOCATION>Sunnyvale</LOCATION>, Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Amdahl Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, because its
IBM-compatible mainframes are less expensive than
<ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s own machines, <PERSON>Mr.
Jones</PERSON> says. He expects <ORGANIZATION>Amdahl</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>fourth-quarter</DATE> net income to
million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>38 cents</MONEY> a share, a year earlier. He expects
revenue to decline to <MONEY>$615 million</MONEY> from <MONEY>$625.8 million</MONEY>,
partly because of a product transition.
   <LOCATION>Armonk</LOCATION>, N.Y.-based <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>, meanwhile, is expected to have a
respectable <DATE>fourth quarter</DATE>, in part because of the success of
its new air-cooled mainframes, says <PERSON>Mr. Cohen</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>SoundView</ORGANIZATION>.
He expects higher net income of <MONEY>$2.3 billion</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$4</MONEY> a share,
vs. the year-earlier <MONEY>$591 million</MONEY>, or <MONEY>$1.04</MONEY> a share,
including a <MONEY>$2.42 billion</MONEY> pretax charge. <PERSON>Mr. Cohen</PERSON> expects
sales of <MONEY>$22 billion</MONEY> vs. <MONEY>$20.4 billion</MONEY> last year. He says
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s introduction of ES/9000 computers last fall spurred
sales.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880204-0031 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sun Microsystems Unveils Low-Cost Sun-4 Workstation </HL>
<AUTHOR> Ken Wells (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> SUNW </CO>
<IN> EDP </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> introduced a low-cost version of its Sun-4 workstation that analysts say represents a price-for-performance breakthrough in the high-speed workstation field. 

   Known as the Sun-4/110, the machine is capable of handling seven million instructions per second and sells for <MONEY>$19,000</MONEY>, about <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> less than a speedier version unveiled in <DATE>July</DATE>. 

   "That kind of performance for twenty grand" currently is unrivaled among workstation makers, said <PERSON>Richard Shaffer</PERSON>, editor of <ORGANIZATION>Technologic Computer Letter</ORGANIZATION>, a New York-based newsletter. 

   "This is a powerful machine for the price," added <PERSON>Lisa Thorell</PERSON>, an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Dataquest</ORGANIZATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>Silicon Valley</ORGANIZATION> high technology market research firm. 
<PERSON>Ms. Thorell</PERSON> said a <ORGANIZATION>Dataquest</ORGANIZATION> analysis, assuming the Sun-4/110 performs as advertised, indicates that buyers seeking comparable performance would have to spend about double the cost of the machine. 

   Despite the bullishness of analysts, Sun's stock was battered in a general decline of high-technology issues. 
Sun closed yesterday at <MONEY>$29.75</MONEY> a share, down <MONEY>$2.50</MONEY> in national over-the-counter trading. 

   Sun said the new workstations are available immediately and would be shipped within 30 days of receipt of orders. 
It declined to estimate sales but said it has already sold about 1,000 units of its previously introduced Sun-4/200 series, which has a base price of about <MONEY>$39,000</MONEY>. 

   Sun said the low-cost workstations would be marketed to users in the financial analysis, artificial intelligence, medical imaging and computer-aided design fields. 
The basic Sun-4/110 is equipped with eight megabytes of memory and a monochrome monitor. 
Sun also said it would begin offering an optional 327-megabyte, 5 1/4-inch disk drive to add capacity to all of its Sun-4 workstations. 

   The Sun-4/110 represents the latest in a flurry of new products and aggressive price-cutting by the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain View</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, computer maker, whose machines are developed around superfast microchips known as RISC, or reduced instruction set computer. 
Sun, in its announcement, called the Sun-4/110 "the first supercomputing desktop computer," though not everyone buys that claim. 

   Though the definition of supercomputers is somewhat hazy, <PERSON>Mr. Shaffer</PERSON> said Sun's claims for the Sun-4/110 are "something of a stretch" since supercomputers currently are generally considered to have much faster processing speeds than the <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION> unit. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900404-0154
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900404-0154.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Digital Unveils
   New Workstations,
   Cuts Some Prices
   ----
   By William M. Bulkeley
</HL>
<DATE>
04/04/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B4
</SO>
<CO>
   DEC SUNW
</CO>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<LP>
   MAYNARD, Mass. -- Digital Equipment Corp. slashed prices
25% to 40% on older products in one line of workstations and
introduced some new models.
   The price cuts affected its DECstation and DECsystem
computers based on the Mips Computer Systems Inc. RISC
design. For example, the entry level DECstation 2100 was cut
to $5,950 from $7,950 and the DECsystem 5400 computer was cut
to $30,000 from $49,900.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Price cuts on older models frequently accompany
new-product introductions in the computer industry. However,
<PERSON>Russ Crabs</PERSON>, an analyst with <ORGANIZATION>Soundview Financial Group</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Stamford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, said the sharp cuts were "a surprise
component" of <ORGANIZATION>Digital</ORGANIZATION>'s new-product announcement. He said
<ORGANIZATION>Digital</ORGANIZATION> may be "making a pre-emptive move" to counter a
low-priced RISC computer expected from workstation leader <ORGANIZATION>Sun
Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> later this year.
   <PERSON>Vicki Brown</PERSON>, who follows the workstation market for
<ORGANIZATION>International Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Framingham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, said that while
<ORGANIZATION>Digital</ORGANIZATION> has had lower-priced RISC workstations than Sun since
the DECstation's introduction in early <DATE>1989</DATE>, they have been
slow sellers. With new models and an increasing amount of
software available, she predicted <ORGANIZATION>Digital</ORGANIZATION> will sell about
25,000 of the RISC systems this year compared with just 6,000
last year. She expects Sun to sell 100,000 of its
Sparcstation RISC systems this year.
   Digital's new workstation line, the DECstation 5000, will
have a base price of <MONEY>$14,995</MONEY>. The workstation runs at 24
million instructions per second, almost as fast as the speed
entry-level RS/6000 workstation. Digital's 5000 comes in four
models, depending on graphics capabilities, with the top
color model priced at <MONEY>$51,100</MONEY>.
   Digital also said that in <DATE>June</DATE> it will introduce more
powerful members of the RISC-based multiuser 5800 family. The
two additional models will include three or four
microprocessors and run at speeds up to 62 million
instructions per second. With price cuts on the two existing
models, pricing for the <DATE>5800</DATE> series now runs from <MONEY>$75,000</MONEY> to
<MONEY>$160,000</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870407-0026 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sun Microsystems Slashes Price 36%
On Workstation to Thwart IBM, Apple
---
By Brenton R. Schlender
<DD> 04/07/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SUNW XLGX
COMPUTERS (EDP) </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> slashed the price of its least expensive computer workstations <PERCENT>36%</PERCENT> in an attempt to preempt encroachment into its markets by powerful new personal computers from <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 

   "We've basically declared war on the low-end workstation market," said <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, Sun's president and chief executive officer, who contends that the new prices for Sun's 3/50M workstations make them less costly than comparably equipped personal computers. 
The 3/50M, now priced at <MONEY>$4,995</MONEY>, is used by professional printers for typesetting and page layout, and by engineers designing everything from computer software to automobiles and jet engines. 

   Mountain View, Calif.-based Sun announced the price cuts within a month of announcements by both <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and Apple of their intent to enter the market for technical workstations with souped up personal computers. 

   Last week, for example, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> announced a series of new personal computers, including its Personal System/2 Model 80, which is built around an <ORGANIZATION>Intel Corp.</ORGANIZATION> 80386 microprocessor. 
The machine, priced from <MONEY>$6,995</MONEY>, will be capable of many of the sophisticated engineering tasks that Sun's workstations can perform, but software for those functions won't be available until late next year. 
In <DATE>March</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> unveiled its Macintosh II, priced from <MONEY>$4,800</MONEY> and aimed squarely at the engineering, publishing and technical workstation markets. 

   Both the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> machines, however, require the purchase of software and accessories to match the performance of the Sun workstation. 

   "The difference between us and them is that they're announcing products that will become available in the next 12 to 18 months, while we're shipping ours in volume," said <PERSON>Mr. McNealy</PERSON> in an interview. 
"Plus, we have over 850 software applications that will work right now, not next year," he added. 

   Historically, markets for technical workstations have been rather small. 
Analysts estimate that since its founding in <DATE>1981</DATE>, Sun has sold about 38,000 workstations, most of which are 3/50M models. 
Its main competitor, <LOCATION>Chelmsford</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Mass.-based Apollo Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, has sold about 30,000 workstations, and analysts estimate that other manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION> have sold about 35,000 workstations. 
By contrast, about nine million personal computers have been sold. 

   But as the distinction begins to blur between personal computers and more sophisticated workstations, both in terms of price and performance, market opportunities broaden for both industries. 
Indeed, <PERSON>Mr. McNealy</PERSON> said he would like to see Sun expand its markets down into areas traditionally served by personal computer manufacturers -- such as more conventional office automation -- even as personal computer makers are attempting to move into more sophisticated markets. 

   "We think there's the opportunity to sell in the tens of thousands of workstations easily, if not more than that" each year, <PERSON>Mr. McNealy</PERSON> said. 
"Our factory is primed so we can pump these out like cookies." 

   Analysts say Sun's aim is defensive as much as anything. 
"Sun is certainly mindful of competition from three areas: <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> and folks in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION> like <ORGANIZATION>NEC Corp.</ORGANIZATION>," said <PERSON>Robert Herwick</PERSON>, an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Hambrecht &amp; Quist</ORGANIZATION>, a San Francisco-based investment banking firm. 
"They have to be looking over their shoulder all the time," <PERSON>Mr. Herwick</PERSON> added. 

   That's because Sun's workstations run software that uses an industry standard operating system called Unix. 
While that means the Sun machines have access to a greater library of software, it also leaves their hardware vulnerable to being cloned, much like <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s personal computers, especially as manufacturing costs decline. 

   In response to <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement, <LOCATION>Cupertino</LOCATION>, Calif.-based <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>'s manager of business marketing, <PERSON>John Zeisler</PERSON>, said he didn't think Sun's pricing strategy would necessarily pit the two companies against each other. 
"Sun workstations typically are sold in a configuration of five or eight workstations, while a Macintosh II will be more of a stand-alone workstation," he said. 

   A spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Apollo Computer</ORGANIZATION> said that the company doesn't have any workstations directly competing with the low end of <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s line, and that its units remain priced competitively against <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s more powerful models. 
He said Apollo doesn't have any plans for price cuts at the current time. 
<LOCATION>Armonk</LOCATION>, N.Y.-based <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> said it doesn't comment on announcements by competitors. 


   Separately, <LOCATION>Burlington</LOCATION>, Mass.-based <ORGANIZATION>Xylogics Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it received a <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY> contract to supply disk controllers to Sun for two years. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900215-0253 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-15-90 1445EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u f AM-IBMWorkstations Bjt   02-15 0763</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-IBM Workstations, Bjt,0794</SECOND>
<HEAD>IBM's New Workstations Enter Fast-Growing Market It's Never
Mastered</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY30</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BART ZIEGLER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Business Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> unveiled a line of computer workstations
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the company says outperform and underprice the
competition and should help it snare a major stake in a
fast-growing market where it never had success.
   ``The opportunity is big _ it's growing at over <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> a
year, and it's mostly a new opportunity for <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>,'' said President
<PERSON>Jack D. Kuehler</PERSON>.
   The machines, called the RISC System-6000, also mark the first
time that the world's largest computer maker has wholeheartedly
embraced the Unix computer operating system that is fast becoming
   <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION> also announced its
intention to provide ways to link the new machines with <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>
computers that run on its proprietary operating system.
   An operating system is software that controls basic computer
functions, such as executing commands from the keyboard and opening
computer files.
   <PERSON>Kuehler</PERSON> told a news conference that the new machines, designed
for use by engineers, ``outperform the newest and best that our
competitors offer.''
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> announced four high-performance workstations and five
file-servers, which are used to link computers in a network. The
machines range in price from about <MONEY>$13,000</MONEY> to more than <MONEY>$74,000</MONEY>.
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> said the lowest-price model is the most powerful desktop
workstation on the market, beating the offering of <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, considered the workstation leader. The <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> model performs
27.5 million instructions per second, or mips, compared with 12.5
mips for the Sun model. It also is slightly cheaper than Sun's.
   Industry analysts say the workstations are impressive for their
performance, pricing and features.
   ``From the customer standpoint, I think it's going to get <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>
into the door in ways it didn't before,'' said <PERSON>Peter Burris</PERSON>, an
analyst for <ORGANIZATION>International Data Corp.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Framingham</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   Workstations are desktop or side-of-desk machines that are much
more powerful than personal computers. Some even match the power of
mainframes. They are used for such processing-intensive tasks as
three-dimensional computer modeling of new products.
   The workstation market is small, but is among the
fastest-growing computer segments, and uses for the machines are
expanding.
   ``A lot of things start in the scientific market and gravitate
out toward other markets,'' said <PERSON>Barry Bosak</PERSON>, an analyst for <ORGANIZATION>Smith
Barney, Harris Upham &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> introduced a workstation line several years ago, the RT
line, but it captured less than <PERCENT>3 percent</PERCENT> of market. Experts
consider the machines underpowered and overpriced.
   ``We made a mistake,'' <PERSON>Kuehler</PERSON> said in an interview.
   The workstation field is dominated by <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co</ORGANIZATION>.
machines from different manufacturers to work together. Until now,
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> had promoted its own operating systems. Basing the workstations
on Unix shows <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> is serious about this market, <PERSON>Kuehler</PERSON> said in the
interview.
   It also is recognition of the huge library of Unix-based
software available for workstations, he said.
   The machines are based on <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s own version of Unix, called <LOCATION>AIX</LOCATION>,
but are a new generation of the operating system. Analysts said the
new <LOCATION>AIX</LOCATION> is even more compatible with industry standards.
   Unix-based applications programs _ the software that provides
the actual uses of computers, such as word processing _ must be
rewritten for <LOCATION>AIX</LOCATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> has been working with software companies for some time to
develop programs for the new machines. By the end of the year,
about 1,500 application programs worldwide will be available, it
said.
   <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s embrace of Unix has broad implications for the operating
standard, said <PERSON>Louise Rehling</PERSON>, a senior vice president at <ORGANIZATION>SPSS
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> software company that was among those recruited.
   ``We think <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> is going to bring a lot of credibility to the
Unix markeplace,'' she said. ``The size of the pie will grow as
well as the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> share.''
   Like the older <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> workstations, the new models are based on
reduced-instruction-set computing technology, or RISC, which
simplifies the circuitry of a computer's central processor to
increase speed and offer cost savings. But <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> said the RISC system
in the new machines is greatly improved.
   Shipments of the workstations will begin within 90 days, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>
said.
   <PERSON>Bosak</PERSON> said the workstations would have little short-term impact
on <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s earnings. But they represent an important signal that the
company is working to improve its fortunes.
   Last month, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> reported its <DATE>1989</DATE> profit slipped <PERCENT>35 percent</PERCENT> from
the year before. The company also has embarked on a cost-cutting
program that involves the elimination of thousands of jobs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ881014-0020 </DOCNO>
<HL> Technology Brief -- Sun Microsystems Inc.: Workstation Prices Increased To Reflect Component Costs </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> SUNW </CO>
<IN> EDP </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> said it raised prices on its workstations by an average of <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT>, passing on to customers the higher cost for computer components such as <ORGANIZATION>DRAM</ORGANIZATION> memory chips. 

   Sun's move follows the trend of recent price increases by such companies as <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The increase, for example, raises the price of Sun's entry level workstation, the Sun-3/50, to <MONEY>$5495</MONEY> from <MONEY>$4995</MONEY>. 
Also raised <PERCENT>7%</PERCENT> were prices for Sun's file server products. 
System prices for newer products were raised an average of <PERCENT>6%</PERCENT>, while prices for older product lines were hiked by <PERCENT>10%</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>15%</PERCENT>. 

   Sun, based in <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, said the increased prices will help the company purchase larger quantities of memory components, thereby increasing manufacturing and driving down "unacceptably long lead times" for its products. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT911-3919</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-BDWB7AATFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>910423
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  23 APR 91 / Survey of The Computer Industry (20): Makers plan more
powerful machines - Workstations, market continues to grow
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LOUIS KEHOE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SAN FRANCISCO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
COMPUTER workstations are 'not just for 'techies' anymore', <ORGANIZATION>Sun
Microsystems</ORGANIZATION>, market leader, has declared.
These high performance desktop computers have until recently been aimed
primarily at engineering and scientific applications. Sun and others see a
new market opportunity for workstations as high-powered business computers.
'The mass penetration of workstations into markets dominated by personal
computers, minicomputers and mainframes isn't a future event - it has
already happened,' Sun claims.
The marriage of computer workstation performance with the vast software base
of the PC is luring dozens of computer makers and software developers into
this emerging market. PC companies such as <ORGANIZATION>Compaq Computer</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Apple
Computer</ORGANIZATION> are planning to build more powerful desktop machines based upon
Reduced Instruction Set Computing (RISC) microprocessors borrowed from the
engineering workstation world.
Workstation manufacturers such as <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>
are targeting business users as well as their traditional engineering and
scientific markets. The technical features and market characteristics that
divide the PC and workstation markets are fast disappearing.
Business applications are increasingly being ported to varieties of the Unix
operating system which is widely used on engineering workstations. The raw
data processing power of the PC vies with that of low end workstations.
Distribution patterns are also overlapping.
Traditionally, workstations have been sold primarily by direct sales forces
or through value-added resellers who add specialised software. Increasingly,
however, workstations are being offered by the computer dealers and retail
outlets that dominate the PC market. However, as workstations enter the
business market a conflict between PC and workstation software standards has
arisen.
While <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s DOS operating system dominates the PC world, Unix - in
various forms - is the operating system of choice for workstations. Backers
of the <ORGANIZATION>Advanced Computindustry</ORGANIZATION> consortium of 21 companies, have declared
their support for both a future unified version of Unix and a future version
of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s OS/2 operating system.
Members of the group acknowledge that they are hedging their bets, until it
becomes clearer which way the business workstation market will move. The
emergence of workstations as business computers has added to the fierce
competition in all sectors of the Dollars 7.5bn workstation market.
Sales of workstations are expected to total Dollars 9.2bn this year and
reach over <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 12bn in <DATE>1992</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Dataquest</ORGANIZATION>, the market research
company. Sun Microsystems is the clear winner in workstations, with a
dominant 32 per cent market share.
Sun's combination of the Sparc Reduced Instruction Set Computing (RISC)
microprocessor and SunOS version of Unix has attracted several licensed
cloners who offer Sun-compatible computers.
Sun's strategy has been to establish Sparc as an industry standard and
mostly through the success of its own products it is succeeding. Industry
analysts predict that Sun will continue to lead the workstation market
throughout the early <DATE>1990s</DATE> although <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines</ORGANIZATION> may
aggressively challenge Sun.
'By 1992-93 Sun and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> may tie for first place among workstation vendors,'
predicts Ms <PERSON>Vicki Brown</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>International Data</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> has made a remarkable resurgence in the workstation market since its
introduction, a year ago, of a range of products based upon its own RISC
design.
The company sold <ORGANIZATION>Dollars</ORGANIZATION> 1bn-worth of its RS/6000 workstations in <DATE>1990</DATE> and
gained a 6.6 per cent share in the market. Sales are expected to rise to
Dollars 1.7bn-Dollars 2bn this year.
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>, the number two workstation vendor, lost market share in
<DATE>1990</DATE> but is expected to make a strong recovery this year with the recent
introduction of a new product range.
Using an enhanced version of the Reduced Instruction Set Computing (RISC)
architecture upon which its minicomputers are based, <ORGANIZATION>HP</ORGANIZATION> has taken a
technological leapfrog to produce machines that greatly outperform
comparably priced workstations from its main competitors.
<ORGANIZATION>HP</ORGANIZATION>'s new top of the range Series 700 Model 730 workstation is twice as fast
as <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s fastest workstation, and 3.5 times the performance of Sun
Microsystems Sparcstation 3, <ORGANIZATION>HP</ORGANIZATION> claims.
<ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment</ORGANIZATION> saw its share of the workstation market reduced in <DATE>1990</DATE> to
17 per cent from 23 per cent in the previous year, according to <ORGANIZATION>IDC</ORGANIZATION>.
Digital is aggressively supporting Ace, the Advanced Computing Environment
initiative, and plans to upgrade its DEC station product line with new
workstations based upon the powerful R4000 <ORGANIZATION>Mips</ORGANIZATION> computer RISC chip, when
that device becomes available.
'Marketing prowess and execution - not pure technology - will ultimately
determine the winners in the workstation market,' predicts <PERSON>Ms Brown</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>IDC</ORGANIZATION>.
A challenge for all workstation participants will be to maintain profit
margins as average workstation prices fall and to adjust to new distribution
channels as the market for workstations expands.
 -------------------------------------------------
Market share of workstation shipments worldwide
 -------------------------------------------------
                              %
 -------------------------------------------------
Sun Microsystems            32.4
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>             21.2
<ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment</ORGANIZATION>           16.2
<ORGANIZATION>Intergraph</ORGANIZATION>                   7.0
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>                          6.7
Silicon Graphics             5.9
<ORGANIZATION>Sony</ORGANIZATION>                         2.8
Next                         1.0
Others                       7.2
 -------------------------------------------------
Source: <ORGANIZATION>International Data</ORGANIZATION>
 -------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
Survey COM Page 10 Photograph Olivetti Laptop S20/D33 (Omitted).
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870601-0001 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sun Microsystems to Announce Products
For Linking to Other Computer Systems
---
By Brenton R. Schlender
<DD> 06/01/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SUNW
COMPUTERS (EDP) </IN>
<DATELINE> MOUNTAIN VIEW, Calif.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
    <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> will
announce today products that will allow its workstations to
be used as intermediary systems between mainframes,
minicomputers and personal computers.
   The new products include SunLink, a package of hardware and software that enables a Sun workstation to connect directly into an <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION> mainframe computer, providing high-speed communications capable of transmitting three million characters a second, the equivalent of 1,500 double-spaced, typewritten pages. 
This means SunLink, which will be available in <DATE>August</DATE> and will cost about <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY>, can support a network of as many as 128 workstations entering simultaneous transactions. 

   The other major product is an enhanced version of TOPS, a software that enables <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> personal computers and <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s Macintosh personal computers to share data. 
The new version, produced by Sun's recently acquired <ORGANIZATION>Centram Systems West Inc.</ORGANIZATION> unit, will translate data from <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> computers into a form usable by Sun workstations, mainframes and even supercomputers. 
Sun hasn't set a price for the new version, which will be available in the third calendar quarter. 

   The new products are "designed so that a user can get to all of his company's computer resources from his desktop system, without having to know the idiosyncrasies of every machine on the network," said <PERSON>Scott McNealy</PERSON>, Sun's president and chief executive officer. 

   According to <PERSON>Eric Schmidt</PERSON>, Sun's vice president and general manager of software products, the products also "allow Sun's workstations to be used in many more situations than previously accessible," namely conventional business settings. 
Up to now, Sun's workstations have been used mainly as computer-aided design tools, or for professional photo-typesetting. 
In its five-year history, Sun has sold about 36,000 workstations. 

   To make its workstations more attractive to conventional businesses, Sun recently lowered the price of its least-expensive workstation by <PERCENT>37%</PERCENT> to <MONEY>$4,995</MONEY>, in an attempt to begin competing directly in some markets now dominated by personal computers. 
Sun's workstations, which usually are sold in networks of five or more, provide larger screens, fancier graphics and number-crunching abilities than most personal computers. 
Common business applications software, such as spreadsheets, accounting, database systems must be written for Unix, a standard operating system developed by <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph Co.</ORGANIZATION> that <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION> uses in its workstations, before Sun can hope to sell many workstations as general business machines. 

   Meanwhile, with easier access to personal computers and mainframes that the new products provide, Sun hopes its workstations will come to be used as "gateways for high-performance interplay with other systems," said <PERSON>Mr. Schmidt</PERSON>. 

OF  AQUARIUS  PRINT  REQUEST         DATE: 8 8 / 0 1/ 1 4
 DOCUMENTS =    10,706
SED =    17,689
RUN
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910520-0133
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910520-0133.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Technology:
   Hewlett to Unveil
   Office Workstation
   Priced at Low End
   ----
   By Stephen Kreider Yoder
</HL>
<DATE>
05/20/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B5
</SO>
<CO>
   GTE HWP
</CO>
<MS>
TECHNOLOGY (TEC)
UTILITIES (UTI)
</MS>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
TELEPHONE SYSTEMS, INCLUDING CELLULAR (TLS)
</IN>
<RE>
CALIFORNIA (CA)
CONNECTICUT (CT)
</RE>
<LP>
   PALO ALTO, Calif. -- Hewlett-Packard Co. said it will
unveil today a low-priced workstation aimed at business
users, the latest in a recent volley of inexpensive yet
powerful new workstations from makers who are battling for
new markets.
   The new machine, the Model 425e, will rival in price the
lowest-priced workstations on the market. The 425e will list
for $5,490 but runs as much as 76% faster, for example, than
Sun Microsystems Inc.'s bottom-end machine, the $4,995
Sparcstation SLC, Hewlett-Packard said.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>, Sun and other workstation makers are
trying to expand the market for their workstations into the
office -- usually the turf of personal computers and
mainframes. "That's the real sweet spot of the market," said
<PERSON>Karl Freund</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>'s workstation-marketing manager.
   <PERSON>Mr. Freund</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> engineers tailored the
425e to the business user by stripping out features such as
fast graphics and special printer sockets that, while vital
to workstations' usual engineering users, aren't needed for
most business tasks but add cost to a machine.
   The new <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> machine, on the other hand,
includes amenities that makers have until now kept out of
their low-priced workstations to hold down to around <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY>.
Sun's bare-bones <ORGANIZATION>SLC</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>'s older <MONEY>$4,990</MONEY> 400DL
workstation are monochrome-only machines that are limited to
16 megabytes of internal memory and can't accept internal
hard-disk drives.
   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> said its new 425e, which uses <ORGANIZATION>Motorola
Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s 68040 microprocessor chip, can plug into color
monitors, can contain as many as 48 megabytes of internal
memory and can hold as much as an 840 megabyte hard-disk
drive. The machine has circuitry to process audio
information, such as music from compact disks or speech from
a microphone, and store it in digital form on hard-disk
drives.
   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> said it has received orders for 10,000 of
the new machines, including an order valued at <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>
from <ORGANIZATION>GTE Corp.</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>GTE Telephone Operations</ORGANIZATION> unit.
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> said it also will announce today two new
higher-end 425 models -- the Model 425t for <MONEY>$8,990</MONEY> and the
425s for <MONEY>$21,490</MONEY> -- which will include additional features
such as more memory.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890808-0012 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890808 </DD>
<AN> 890808-0012. </AN>
<HL> Technology:
@  HP Joins Forces
@  With Samsung
@  In Workstations
@  ----
@  By G. Christian Hill
<DD> 08/08/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<CO> HWP C.SEL SUNW PHG </CO>
<IN> COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR) </IN>
<TEXT>
   The competition among makers of low-end workstations and high-end personal computers may be about to get much fiercer. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION> plans to announce today an alliance with <LOCATION>South Korea</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Samsung Group</ORGANIZATION>. 
Under the agreement, <ORGANIZATION>Samsung Electronics Co.</ORGANIZATION> will manufacture both microprocessor chips and workstations using <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>'s reduced-instruction-set-computing (RISC) technology and UNIX software. 
RISC chips are very fast, powerful microprocessors; <ORGANIZATION>UNIX</ORGANIZATION> is an operating system offering multi-tasking and advanced graphic capabilities. 

   The centerpiece of their plan, the companies said, is to produce a <MONEY>$5,000</MONEY> workstation within two years. 
Such a machine, with several times the processing power of today's entry-level machines that cost about <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>, would compete not only with low-end workstations made by <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Digital Equipment Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, but also with high-performance personal computers made by <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc</ORGANIZATION>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> said it will buy some of the <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> workstations and resell them under its own name. 
<ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> can also sell the machines on its own. 

   An industry consultant, <PERSON>Andrew Allison</PERSON>, said the two companies will have to ship the machine, or at least a version with performance comparable to <ORGANIZATION>Sun</ORGANIZATION>'s least expensive machine, the SparcStation 1, by late next year for it to be competitive. 
He said they are capable of meeting such a deadline. 
<ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION> has forged an alliance with two Taiwanese companies, to clone and ship low-cost versions of its workstations next year. 

   The strategic aim of the alliance with <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> is to enlist <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION>'s renowned ability to manufacture products, including a clone of <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s personal computers, at very low costs, with low margins. 
<ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> is known as a producer of high-performance machines, at high margins, and wants to stay in that market. 

   But just as clearly, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>'s direct competitors weren't impressed. 
"Very simply, it's too little, too late," said <PERSON>Chester Silvestri</PERSON>, vice president for technology products for <ORGANIZATION>MIPS Computer Systems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which licences RISC chips to manufacturers, including Digital. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION> said the <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> alliance confers no special competitive advantage on <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>, since Sun could buy and resell machines made by low-cost producers in the <LOCATION>Far East</LOCATION>, if it so chose. 
Its SparcStation 1 is already priced at about <MONEY>$10,000</MONEY>. 

   Nonetheless, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> is a huge company with much greater resources than Sun and <ORGANIZATION>MIPS</ORGANIZATION>. 
It dominates the RISC market with its line of high-end workstations, and is the leading maker of all kinds of workstations with its recent acquisition of <ORGANIZATION>Apollo Computer</ORGANIZATION>. 
Although late to the low-end of the RISC computer market, it could be a formidable competitor. 

   The <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> alliance "is a major announcement," asserted <PERSON>Mr. Allison</PERSON>. 
"It puts another gorilla into the low-end UNIX systems cage." 

   In the past, RISC/UNIX machines have been very expensive, and limited mostly to scientific and engineering applications. 
But <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION> has led a movement to offer less expensive workstations that are beginning to compete with <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s PS/2 line and with <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer</ORGANIZATION>'s Macintosh. 

   The market for RISC/UNIX machines, while relatively small, is growing much faster than the market for computers using MS/DOS -- the operating system for personal computers made by <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and its clones -- or for <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>'s proprietary operating system. 
In many cases, the RISC/ UNIX machines offer more speed for less money, and already offer graphics and multi-tasking capabilities that MS/DOS users can get only by upgrading to <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s expensive new OS/2 operating system. 

   The major constraint on their invasion of the personal-computer market is the lack of commercial applications. 
<PERSON>Mr. Allison</PERSON> predicted that these machines will run MS/DOS as well as <ORGANIZATION>UNIX</ORGANIZATION> within two years. 
"It is just a prerequisite to penetrate the PC market," <PERSON>Mr. Allison</PERSON> said. 
"They will all do it." 

   After that, the main problem facing makers of both powerful personal computers and powerful RISC/UNIX machines will be the lack of software applications that fully tap their power. 
"Why do I need a <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> OS/2 computer to run an application that can run as fast on a <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> PC?" asked <PERSON>Mr. Allison</PERSON>. 

   <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> said it will also help <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> develop less expensive sets of RISC chips that <ORGANIZATION>Samsung</ORGANIZATION> will be licensed to manufacture and sell to <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> and to other manufacturers. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Kay</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> isn't trying to encourage clones of its machines -- a course being taken by <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION>. 
Rather, it is seeking partnerships that will give it a competitive advantage in some particular niche, such as the extreme low end or extreme high end of the workstation market. 
Last week, <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION> announced an agreement with <ORGANIZATION>Hitachi Ltd.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> to develop jointly a very high-performance RISC chip set. 
The two companies' goal is to develop in about two years a machine with a speed of "considerably more" than 100 million instructions per second, more than five times faster than any desktop computer available today. 

   But <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard</ORGANIZATION>'s RISC competitors are also forging alliances and planning far faster chips. 
Tomorrow, <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems</ORGANIZATION> will announce an agreement with <ORGANIZATION>N.V. Philips</ORGANIZATION> of the <LOCATION>Netherlands</LOCATION>, under which <ORGANIZATION>Philips Components</ORGANIZATION>, a unit that is the largest semiconductor supplier in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, will develop RISC chips. 
Sun said the agreement "will have a formidable impact on the world-wide RISC market." 

   ---

   <PERSON>G. Pascal Zachary</PERSON> contributed to this article. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ871103-0057 </DOCNO>
<HL> Business Brief:
Sun Microsystems Inc.</HL>
<DD> 11/03/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> SUNW </IN>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sun Microsystems Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which previously sold its line of technical workstations through its own direct sales force, said it is signing up outside resellers to help it broaden distribution. 

   The fast-growing computer company said it is recruiting so-called value added resellers with established experience selling computer equipment to customers engaged in computer-aided design, manufacturing, software engineering and publishing fields. 
Sun, which is based in <LOCATION>Mountain View</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, will require the resellers to package Sun systems with third-party software or other enhancements before selling them to customers. 
The resellers also will be restricted to prescribed geographical areas. 

   Sun said it hopes the broader distribution will help the company sell its machines to commercial customers not currently served, such as more conventional businesses. 
Since being founded in <DATE>1982</DATE>, Sun has sold nearly 50,000 technical workstations. 
