<DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-6974</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EK0AOAEJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941126
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  26 NOV 94 / Thinking the unsinkable: The modern parallels exposed by an
exhibition about the Titanic, which sank in 1912
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By CHARLES BATCHELOR
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It was a grim coincidence that the first comprehensive exhibition of
artefacts recovered from the Titanic opened at the <ORGANIZATION>National Maritime Museum</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Greenwich</LOCATION> a few days after the sinking of the ferry <LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION>.
The fascination surrounding the loss of the supposedly unsinkable Titanic,
on its maiden voyage, was overshadowed by the shock of the sinking of a
modern ferry at a cost of more than 900 lives. The Titanic went down after
it struck an iceberg off <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 14, 1912</DATE>. Only 705 of the
2,228 passengers and crew survived.
Timing apart, historians and naval experts see other parallels between the
two doomed vessels. Both were designed and built to prevailing standards but
both were found wanting.
The Titanic was launched when the number of lifeboats carried reflected the
cubic footage of the vessel devoted to passenger accommodation rather than
the number of passengers and crew. Its designers added a 12 per cent safety
margin to the minimum required by the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Trade</ORGANIZATION> but there were still
only enough lifeboats for half those on board.
A more comprehensive sub-division of the Titanic by internal bulkheads - a
design issue which is again being hotly debated after the <LOCATION>Estonia</LOCATION> sinking in
<DATE>October</DATE> - might have saved the liner, some experts think.
For 73 years the Titanic lay undisturbed, up to two miles down on the floor
of the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. The prospect of ever finding the vessel and answering
the unsolved mysteries of its sinking appeared remote.
But in <DATE>1985</DATE> the wreck was discovered by a joint French-US expedition.
RMS <ORGANIZATION>Titanic Inc</ORGANIZATION>, a New York-based company, was declared 'salvor in
possession', meaning that it had unique rights to explore the vessel and
raise material.
The company has since carried out three expeditions, the most recent in
<DATE>July</DATE>, using a submersible provided by the <ORGANIZATION>French Oceanographic Research
Institute</ORGANIZATION>. It has raised a total of 3,600 artefacts.
RMS Titanic is committed to raising material from the Titanic and putting it
on general display. It is pledged not to sell any of its finds.
Some 150 objects are on display at the maritime museum, include a ship's
porthole, metal deck bench ends and a letter from a manufacturer lamenting
the demise of the feather boa as a fashion accessory.
Video footage taken from the submersible shows the ship's rail, chandeliers
hanging in a long-abandoned state room and racks of plates.
The chance to stage the exhibition was offered to the maritime museum 'out
of the blue' by <ORGANIZATION>RMS</ORGANIZATION>, says Dr <PERSON>Eric Kentley</PERSON>, a curator.
There are no plans to take the exhibition to any other museums around the
world though the maritime museum and <ORGANIZATION>RMS</ORGANIZATION> are working on designs to establish
a permanent museum to display the material.
The Japanese meanwhile, have announced plans to build a full-scale replica
of the Titanic to act as a floating hotel and conference centre. All the
details of its interior would be replicated although there would be no
engines or steering gear.
As the Titanic sank into the darkness of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> it broke its back and
landed in two separate sections. When it hit the ocean floor the bow section
ploughed into the mud, obscuring to this day the details of how large a gash
was caused by the iceberg.
'The technology exists to remove the silt from the bow section but the
problem is to find the capital to get the equipment down there,' says <PERSON>John
Eaton</PERSON>, a historian with an interest in the Titanic going back more than 45
years.
Recovery of material has been limited to the sea around the vessel. A
decision to treat its interior as a grave site has meant that no attempt has
been made to raise artefacts from inside the hull. Although very few
survivors of the sinking are still alive 'people are very sensitive about
anyone going into the hull', comments Dr Kentley. Eaton confesses to finding
this ban 'very frustrating'.
Although the intense cold, the absence of light and low oxygen levels on the
ocean bed have slowed the deterioration of the Titanic, chemical attack and
sea-bed bacteria have eaten into the metal, staining many objects black.
A comparison of the photographs taken in <DATE>1986</DATE>, and those from a descent in
<DATE>1993</DATE>, show a marked deterioration of the wreck, says <PERSON>Eaton</PERSON>. Dr Kentley
thinks there may be as little as 10 years left to continue work on the hull
before it disintegrates.
RMS and its backers are keen to raise more material from the wreck. However,
even if a sudden deterioration was to halt work, enough has been raised to
create a powerful reminder of the fate of the Titanic, and any other vessel
and its crew which underestimate the power of the sea. The exhibition, says
Dr Kentley: 'Is a timely reminder that the sea signs no treaties.'
The Wreck of the Titanic. Until <DATE>April 2, 1995</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page III
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880416-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-16-88 0246EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Titanic     04-16 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Titanic,0193</SECOND>
<HEAD>Titanic Memorabilia Auctioned On 76th Anniversary Of Sinking</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A postcard mailed from the Titanic fetched <MONEY>$2,068</MONEY>
during an auction <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the 76th anniversary of the ocean liner's
sinking, but a water-stained letter found on the body of a dead
passenger went unsold.
   The auction of 200 items of Titanic memorabilia raised <MONEY>$56,400</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Onslow</ORGANIZATION>'s Auctioneers reported.
   A spokesman said the water-stained letter didn't sell because it
may have been considered too ghoulish.
   One collector paid <MONEY>$2,068</MONEY> for the postcard stamped on the ship
and posted when it stopped in <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>.
   Northern <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ulster Folk</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Transport Museum</ORGANIZATION> paid the
auction's top price of <MONEY>$14,100</MONEY> for a <DATE>1912</DATE> watercolor painting
entitled ``Fitting Out The Titanic, <LOCATION>Belfast</LOCATION>.''
   The Titanic, built in <LOCATION>Belfast</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Northern Ireland</LOCATION>, and declared
unsinkable, went down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 15, 1912</DATE>, after
hitting an iceberg while on its maiden voyage from <LOCATION>Southampton</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. A total of 1,513 people perished.
   The wreck of the liner about 2.5 miles below the surface and 350
miles south of <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION> was first located by a U.S.-French
expedition in <DATE>September 1985</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880121-0150 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Bookshelf: The Great Maritime Mystery </HL>
<AUTHOR> Rich Jaroslovsky </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   It was news that the world had waited seven decades to hear. 
On <DATE>Sept. 1, 1985</DATE>, <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON> announced that he had found and photographed the wreck of the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Mail Steamship Titanic</ORGANIZATION>, the largest and most luxurious liner that had ever plied the seas. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON> had triumphed -- where many before him had failed -- through a combination of determination, detective work and a firm commitment to advanced technology. 
In that first expedition and in a follow-up a year later, he and his scientific crew shot thousands of still photos and made hours of videotape of the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s final resting place. 

   Now comes "The Discovery of the Titanic" (<ORGANIZATION>Madison Press/Warner Books</ORGANIZATION>, 230 pages, <MONEY>$29.95</MONEY>), <PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON>'s lavishly illustrated account of how the ship was located and what was found when it was. 
One needn't be a Titanic buff to be bowled over by the result. 

   The loss of the Titanic was one of those events that defined an era. 
Hailed as "unsinkable" (though not by either its builders or owners), it was speeding through the <TIME>night</TIME> on its maiden voyage when it struck an iceberg on <DATE>April 14, 1912</DATE>. 
It carried lifeboats for only a fraction of the 2,227 on board, and when it plunged 2 1/2 miles to the bottom of the frigid <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> it took more than 1,500 people with it. 

   For 73 years, the wreck had eluded all searchers. 
Enter <PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON>, a geologist and self-described "submarine cowboy" working out of the <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>. 
His previous deep ocean work in the <LOCATION>Galapagos Rift</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Pacific Rise</ORGANIZATION> had already gained him a measure of renown. 
Throughout those explorations, however, the lure of finding the Titanic remained, and each advance in oceanographic technology brought the dream tantalizingly closer. 

   Finally, in <DATE>1985</DATE>, a joint U.S.-French team set out using some of the highest of high-technology equipment, including an underwater television camera capable of scanning the ocean's bottom. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON> hoped to prove that video exploration of the oceans was both feasible and preferable to using manned submersibles. 
Yet the task was formidable -- far more difficult than finding the proverbial needle in the haystack. 
The explorers found the wreck on almost the very edge of the expanse of water they had identified as their primary search area. 

   The discovery, when it came, was a tremendous scientific achievement, but it also was a human one. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON> writes of his emotions while standing on the deck of his ship at the exact hour and over the exact spot of the Titanic's demise: "It was one thing to have won -- to have found the ship. 
It was another thing to be there. 
That was the spooky part. 
I could see the Titanic as she slipped nose first into the glassy water. 
Around me were the ghostly shapes of the lifeboats and the piercing shouts and screams of people freezing to death in the water." 

   "The Discovery of the Titanic" is no idealized version of events. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON> documents tensions within the crew over the approach to the search, as well as the rupture between the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and French scientific teams after the discovery, when the French felt they were being deprived of their share of the glory of discovery. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON>'s own conceits -- some even bordering on arrogance -- come through as well. 
His insistence that electronic rather than human exploration is the wave of the future brought him into conflict with the group manning <PERSON>Alvin</PERSON>, the famous miniature submarine. 
Yet even this champion of new technology could not resist the desire to see the wreck through his own eyes: When he returned to the <LOCATION>Titanic</LOCATION> <DATE>a year later</DATE>, it was with <PERSON>Alvin</PERSON> -- allowing him physically to land on the deck of the Titanic and, using a swimming robot camera, explore the interior reaches of the wreck. 

   In any event, the book itself is splendid visual testament to <PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON>'s approach. 
The underwater photographs are stunning in both their clarity and their poignance: the empty davits that launched the too-few lifeboats; a doll's head lying incongruously on the ocean floor; a pair of shoes perfectly preserved long after the disappearance of any trace of the body that once wore them. 
Hundreds of color pictures of the rusting hulk -- often matched with vintage photos of how the ship looked in its heyday -- give eloquent testimony to its fate. 
Equally absorbing are paintings of what the entire hulk must look like now, by artist <PERSON>Ken Marschall</PERSON>. 

   The location and visual inspection of the wreck also cast new light on some of the mysteries surrounding the ship. 
It indeed broke in two before its final descent, as a few of the survivors claimed. 
The explorers found no evidence of the continuous gash many thought had been ripped in the hull; the evidence instead supports the notion that the collision caused the ship's steel plating to rupture intermittently. 
And the ship's location indicates it was not traveling quite as fast as was long believed -- though it was still moving much too quickly. 

   Many people might have thought that the Titanic should remain undiscovered. 
As with watching a magic trick, some of the wreck's fascination has always been rooted in mystery; know too much and the thrill is spoiled. 
It is a tribute to <PERSON>Mr. Ballard</PERSON>, and to this absorbing book, that he manages to preserve the fascination with the Titanic even while stripping away a significant amount of the mystery around its fate. 

   ---
   <PERSON>Mr. Jaroslovsky</PERSON> is a features editor in the Journal's <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> bureau. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890613-0049 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-13-89 0526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-BismarckFound     06-13 0541</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bismarck Found,0555</SECOND>
<HEAD>Expedition Discovers Mighty German Battleship</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY7</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LESLIE DREYFOUS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a fruitless search last year, the German
battleship <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> has been found on the ocean floor 600 miles off
the coast of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, 48 years after it was sunk by the <ORGANIZATION>British Navy</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was located <DATE>Monday</DATE> under 15,000 feet of water by a
remote-controlled robot named Argo that scuttles across the ocean
floor. Argo and his master, expedition leader <PERSON>Dr. Robert Ballard</PERSON>,
also discovered the sunken <DATE>Titanic four years ago</DATE>.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was sitting upright on the sea floor ``intact in an
excellent state of preservation'' about 600 miles west of <LOCATION>Brest</LOCATION> on
the Brittany coast, said <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>, who is based at <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole
Oceanographic Institution on Cape Cod</ORGANIZATION>.
   The discovery is likely to trigger great curiosity among naval
historians, said Maj. <PERSON>Charles Neimeyer</PERSON>, a history professor at the
<ORGANIZATION>U.S. Naval Academy</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``They'll be looking for the sort of technology the Germans had
at the time, because this ship was considered state-of-the-art,'' he
said. The find could answer questions about the way the ship went
down and ``how the crew lived and survived at sea on a German
warship,'' he added.
   No human remains were found near the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, on which all but
about 100 of the 2,200 crew members perished. A memorial service for
those who perished was held aboard one of the expedition's ships.
   The ship will be left undisturbed as a grave site, like the
Titanic, according to <PERSON>David Gallo</PERSON>, assistant director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center
for Marine Exploration</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole</ORGANIZATION>. The battleship might be
explored by the sophisticated robot, though, <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON> said.
   Ballard and a research team searched several days for the
Bismarck last year. Instead of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, the explorers found a
<DATE>19th century</DATE> sailing ship that has yet to be identified, <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON> said.
   ``There were quite a few reports about its position when it
sank,'' <PERSON>Gallo</PERSON> said. ``But the problem is, those reports can be off
by a mile or more, and a mile at sea, when you're looking at the sea
floor, represents a very large area to be covered in a search.''
   The demise of the dreaded <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, which was equipped with eight
15-inch guns, began on <DATE>May 24, 1941</DATE>, when it encountered the <ORGANIZATION>Royal
Navy</ORGANIZATION> off the coast of <LOCATION>Greenland</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION> sank <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s battle cruiser Hood but was hit by
the Prince of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION>. The Germans then fled south for occupied <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>
with the British in pursuit.
   Two days later, British warships and aircraft located the
crippled vessel and launched a furious attack. The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> finally
went down the next day.
   The successful campaign was a significant victory for the Allies,
who thwarted <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON>'s plan to use the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> to raid <LOCATION>Atlantic
Ocean</LOCATION> shipping lanes.
   <PERSON>Neimeyer</PERSON> said the victory also gave a big psychological boost to
the <ORGANIZATION>Royal Navy</ORGANIZATION>, which was stunned by the loss of the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Tis gave confidence to the carrier-aviation community that they
could indeed sink a battleship,'' he said.
   The expedition was jointly funded by <ORGANIZATION>Turner Broadcasting System
Inc.</ORGANIZATION> and a group of private investors. The <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic
Society</ORGANIZATION> plans to produce a documentary on the discovery that will be
televised next <DATE>fall</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891006-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-89 1537EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-WeekendTV-Bismarck Adv20-22   10-06 0805</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Weekend TV-Bismarck, Adv 20-22,0824</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv20</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv21</HEAD>
<HEAD>$adv22</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Weekend Editions, Oct. 20-22, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>`National Geographic Explorer' Traces Hunt for Sunken German Warship</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOHN HORN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Riding the waves, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> plowed across
the seas as the fiercest fighting ship in World War II. Collapsed
on the ocean floor, the German battleship looks cowed, a beaten
Nazi relic.
   The <DATE>1941</DATE> sinking of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> _ and this year's discovery of
its eerily well-preserved wreckage _ is the subject of ``National
Geographic Explorer,'' airing on cable's TBS on <DATE>Oct. 29</DATE> at <TIME>9 p.m.
EST</TIME>.
   The host of the one-hour special is <PERSON>Robert Ballard</PERSON>, the
oceanographer who previously discovered the remains of the Titanic.
The <DATE>1987</DATE> television account of the Titanic find still stands as
basic cable's most popular show.
   ``The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> initially was just another hunt, just another
ship,'' <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. ``But when I saw the faded remains of the
swastika on the ship's bow and stern, and a solitary seaman's boot
lying on the ocean floor, that symbolized to me the great tragedy
of World War II.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Ballard</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION> show will repeat <DATE>Oct. 30</DATE> at <TIME>midnight EST</TIME> and
<DATE>Nov. 4</DATE> at <TIME>8 a.m. EST</TIME>. A videocassette of the program will be
released in <DATE>December</DATE> by <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic</ORGANIZATION>, whose <DATE>November</DATE>
magazine also details the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> exploration.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was the most formidable battleship of its era. In
its first tour of duty, the 820-foot floating fortress literally
blew <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s prize battle cruiser Hood out of the water, killing
all but three of the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION>'s 1,419-person crew.
   ``At the time, it was the most powerful ship on the sea,'' <PERSON>Peter
Schnall</PERSON>, co-producer of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> documentary, said of the
German warship. ``It threatened to stop basically all of the supply
ships that were coming in through the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>.''
   A terrorized <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> put every available warship into the
1,750-mile chase after the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>. Prime Minister <PERSON>Winston
Churchill</PERSON> made his orders to his navy perfectly clear: ``Sink the
Bismarck!''
   Two days after destroying the Hood and racing for protection,
the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was crippled by a British torpedo-equipped biplane and
the country's carrier Ark Royal. The combined assault ruined the
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s steering gear and rudders.
   Functionally immobile, the warship was bombarded all night and
finally scuttled by the Germans. Only 115 of the <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION>'s 2,200
hands survived.
   ``The Germans put everything into'' the battleship, <PERSON>Schnall</PERSON>
said. ``But like everything, it had an Achilles heel. Knock out the
rudder and it's like a big ship with nowhere to go.''
   Ballard's finding the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> required almost as much
determination and luck as did <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION>'s sinking it. With sonar and
video and still cameras whirring away, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> spent two summers
combing a 100-square mile area of the ocean's bottom 600 miles west
of <LOCATION>Brest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>'s cabin was a couple of doors down from us,'' said
<PERSON>Schnall</PERSON>, who accompanied the oceanographer on the search. ``And all
of sudden one morning, we hear this incredible scream because
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> has a video monitor in his room. He had just woken up and
he saw it: just as (the underwater camera) was crossing the
midsection of the ship, right across the gun turrets.
   ``And he let out a whoop. That woke me up, we ran down and
grabbed our camera just as he was running out the door. ... It was
one of those rare moments in film when you catch something exactly
as it happens.''
   What <ORGANIZATION>Ballard</ORGANIZATION>'s cameras found more than 15,000 feet below the
surface of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> startled the team.
   ``It looked like the ship had just been launched from its
original berth,'' <PERSON>Schnall</PERSON> said. ``It sat straight up on its
bottom.''
   There were no skeletons or human bones in sight.
   ``The exciting thing (about making the documentary) is that it
is almost like a natural story,'' <PERSON>Schnall</PERSON> said. ``You have the
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> going out, you have the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> eluding the British, and
then eventually being sunk.
   ``And we have an explorer (<ORGANIZATION>Ballard</ORGANIZATION>) who goes to find the
<LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, can't find it, has to regroup himself, and then go back
out again the next year and find it.''
   After the filmmakers collected footage of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s
wreckage, they met with some of the men who once served on her
decks and showed them the underwater footage.
   ``Very slowly, they started to say, `Yes. Isn't that the gun
where I was standing?' Or, `Wasn't that the deck where so-and-so
was standing before it went down?'
   ``And on and on it went. Eventually, they saw the swastika on
the stern of the ship. ... One of the survivors, <PERSON>Heinrich Kuhnt</PERSON>,
was asked what it felt like to have survived this horrible sea
battle. And he hesitated. And slowly tears filled his eyes and he
couldn't stop crying.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Oct. 20-22</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900430-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-30-90 1904EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-WrecksExplored     04-30 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Wrecks Explored,0584</SECOND>
<HEAD>Robot Driven By Students Explores 1812-Era Wrecks</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. CATHARINES, Ontario (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The crew that discovered the
wreck of the Titanic used a robot diver <DATE>Monday</DATE> to explore a War of
1812-era wreck in <LOCATION>Lake Ontario</LOCATION> _ and shared the expedition with
children across <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
   The camera-equipped robot examined the <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, a merchant
schooner that the British pressed into service as a warship.
   Students at 14 spots in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> watched
satellite TV transmissions. A few students even got to try steering
the robot through a satellite link, using joysticks like those used
with computer games. It transmitted pictures to students watching
through satellite hookups at 14 locations in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   Cannons, railings and the ship's elegantly carved figurehead
could be seen in the television transmission.
   <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON>, the expedition's leader, said the ship's
state of preservation was remarkable.
   ``We can see the caulking in the planks,'' he said.
   The <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and its sister ship, the <LOCATION>Scourge</LOCATION>, sank during a
storm on <DATE>Aug. 8, 1813</DATE>, killing 53 sailors. They had taken part in
several battles for the British against <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces that invaded
southern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> during the war.
   The wrecks remained undisturbed in 300 feet of water six miles
off <LOCATION>St. Catharines</LOCATION>, about 30 miles south of <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> and less than
10 miles west of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> border at <ORGANIZATION>Niagara Falls</ORGANIZATION>, until their
   Since then, there have been several attempts to examine the
wrecks, including one by French explorer <PERSON>Jacques Cousteau</PERSON>. But none
were technologically advanced enough to reach them.
   The cold, fresh water helped keep the ships in much better
condition than most wrecks, said <PERSON>Shelley Lauzon</PERSON>, a project
spokeswoman.
   ``The wood on the Titanic is all gone because there are
wood-boring animals in salt water,'' <PERSON>Lauzon</PERSON> said. ``They're not
present here.''
   Ballard, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Marine Exploration</ORGANIZATION> at the
expedition that discovered the wreck of the Titanic. The ocean
liner sank in the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> after ramming an iceberg in <DATE>1912</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s examination of the <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and the
Scourge was aimed more at teaching children about archaeology and
oceanography than at making startling new discoveries about the two
warships.
   ``We've had four students actually take control and operate the
vehicle beautifully,'' he said in an interview by ship-to-shore
telephone. ``That was the biggest technological feat.''
   The children controlled the robot with a joystick linked to the
system by satellite, <PERSON>Lauzon</PERSON> said. A computer program restricted the
robot's movements so the children could not damage it.
   Although there were no archaeological breakthroughs, the
expedition did reveal a number of details not known before, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>
said.
   The two-week expedition will prepare a comprehensive diagram of
both ships and could provide information allowing the city of
<LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, which has title to the wrecks, to decide whether they are
worth raising. <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said there appeared to be little damage that
would stand in the way of such an effort.
   ``There's no suggestion that they suffered any damage due to the
sinking itself,'' he said. ``They just got flooded and went down
very gently.''
   The museums taking part in the program were in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>; Salt
<LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Sarasota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; and <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021090-0004 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 174154 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 10, 1990, Saturday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 35; Column 3; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
74 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ANN STRAUBE; SURVIVED SINKING OF TITANIC 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Ann Straube</PERSON>, 92, who survived the sinking of the ocean liner Titanic. 
</P>
<P>
As a child she had moved from <LOCATION>Scranton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, with her parents to their homeland 
of <LOCATION>Ireland</LOCATION>. But as a teen-ager she boarded the Titanic with an aunt to return 
to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>. The British steam liner struck an iceberg and went down 
in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> on the <TIME>night</TIME> of <DATE>April 14, 1912</DATE>, with a loss of 1,500 lives, 
including <PERSON>Mrs. Straube</PERSON>'s aunt. On <DATE>Jan. 30</DATE> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Obituary 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071789-0059 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 83254 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 17, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
<P>
Correction Appended 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 2; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
2315 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
OCEANOGRAPHER BALLARD: HIS DISCOVERIES CONNECT SCIENCE WITH HISTORY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GARRY ABRAMS, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON> headed up the discovery of two fabled sunken ships, the 
Titanic in <DATE>1985</DATE> and, just <DATE>last month</DATE>, the World War II German battleship 
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>. In both cases, poignant reminders of human frailty persist on the 
dark, cold ocean floor, he says, lingering testaments to the dead, dragged far 
beyond air and light by plummeting hulks of steel and iron. 
</P>
<P>
Shoes. 
</P>
<P>
Pairs and pairs of shoes resting on the sea floor as if their owners had just 
stepped out of them. 
</P>
<P>
"People say, 'What was it like to go to the Titanic, particularly out in the 
debris area, the stern section where everyone died?' " Ballard recalls of the 
ocean liner that sank to a depth of 12,000 feet in the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE>, 
killing 1,500 of the 2,200 passengers and crew. "There are pairs of shoes all 
over there where people actually came to rest on the bottom of the ocean. Their 
shoes are still there. Shoes all over the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, boots all over the place. 
Animals won't eat processed leather. They eat the body and the clothes but they 
won't eat the leather." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Oceanographer Ballard</PERSON>, in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> to announce that he will host a 
television series about underwater explorations and other scientific ventures, 
is somewhere in the middle of a long explanation about why he pursues the 
sunken past with such avidity. Partly, he concedes, it's for the sensations 
that only discovery can provide. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
The Moment of Discovery 
</P>
<P>
"I think the thrill of exploration is to see something, to be the first to set 
eyes on something that has never been seen before," he says. "The first time I 
saw the Titanic, wow! There it was, this monstrous ship just came out of the 
gloom and there it was." 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>, the moment of discovery is intellectually kinetic -- an instant 
when he connects palpably with history. "The best experience that I can give 
that's sort of an analogy is like going to <PERSON>Custer</PERSON>'s Last Stand," he says. "To 
go and stand where <PERSON>Custer</PERSON> stood and imagine, you know, bad day to be in the 
cavalry. That's the sense, it's your hallowed grounds. You sense <ORGANIZATION>Crazy Horse</ORGANIZATION> 
there . . . and you just realize the hopelessness of the situation. Well, when 
you're out at the Titanic and all of a sudden it happened right here. It's no 
longer abstract." 
</P>
<P>
Unknown territory, scientific and historic, has been <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>'s country for more 
than two decades, perhaps even as far back as his childhood in <LOCATION>Southern 
California</LOCATION>, when he was smitten by accounts of African exploration and became 
captivated by the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. Now, four years after the discovery of the 
Titanic catapulted him from mere well-known scientist to global fame, the 
47-year-old seems to be in the throes of another transformation. This time 
around he apparently is eager to shape both the future and the past with the 
technology that he developed in more than a decade of underwater exploration. 
</P>
<P>
Furthermore, he plans to use his new tools as the new host of <ORGANIZATION>National 
Geographic Explorer</ORGANIZATION>, a weekly two-hour program produced by <ORGANIZATION>National Geographic</ORGANIZATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Turner Broadcasting System Inc</ORGANIZATION>. It is the kind of popularizing of science 
that <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> has been criticized for in the past by his peers. But <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says 
he sees his metamorphosis into TV personality as an educational mission that 
may help convince children that science is a "contact sport." 
</P>
<P>
Discussing the search for the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> obviously savors the contact 
with history and science. 
</P>
<P>
Because the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was engaged in a running battle hundreds of miles from 
land when it sank, neither the British nor the Germans were able -- or much 
interested -- in keeping precise records of their locations. So <ORGANIZATION>Ballard</ORGANIZATION>'s 
expedition had to search about 150 square miles of ocean floor, initially with 
sonar and then with remote control, computerized robot sensors and cameras 
controlled from a surface ship before locating the wreck <DATE>June 8</DATE>. (This kind of 
exploration isn't cheap, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> notes, joking that "we had 100,000 pounds of 
equipment and 10 vans and six robots and a partridge in a pear tree.") 
</P>
<P>
"You have to understand that the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> battle was waged in a Force 8 sea -- 
50-knot winds, 15-foot waves -- (with) overcast and no celestial navigation," 
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says. 
</P>
<P>
The search for the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> -- which, like the Titanic, sank on its maiden 
voyage -- was further complicated by the nature of the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>. The 
battleship was in "16,000 feet of water and it was in a mountain range," 
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says, not without enthusiasm. "It was in an awful place and it was in 
the northern latitudes, up at 48 degrees North latitude, which is not a nice 
stretch of ocean -- ever, even in the <DATE>summer</DATE>." 
</P>
<P>
Despite the difficulties, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> was drawn to the wreck because, like the 
<LOCATION>Titanic</LOCATION>, it is one of the most famous lost chunks of history to litter the 
ocean floor. "I do it because of the challenge to do it," he says. "But I'm 
also interested in the fact that this ship is well preserved. . . . There is 
probably more history preserved in the deep oceans of the world than in all the 
museums of the world." 
</P>
<P>
Although it has lost its gun turrets and was hit by numerous shells and 
torpedoes, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> still has touches of freshness, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> adds, citing 
the "huge painted swastikas" on the ship's bow and stern. 
</P>
<P>
In its day, the 50,000-ton <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, with heavy armor, eight 15-inch guns 
capable of firing one-ton shells 24 miles and high-performance diesel engines, 
was one of the most powerful warships afloat. And briefly it proved to be just 
that. Slipping out of its home port of <PERSON>Danzig</PERSON> (now <LOCATION>Gdynia</LOCATION>) on <DATE>May 18, 1941</DATE> to 
attack Allied convoys, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> soon had much of the <ORGANIZATION>British Royal Navy</ORGANIZATION> 
looking for it. At the time <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> faced a victorious <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> alone and was 
dependent on convoys from <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> for most of its food and war material. 
Discovered by two British heavy cruisers 
</P>
<P>
on <DATE>May 23</DATE>, the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> was engaged the next day by two other British warships. 
From a distance of 25,000 yards, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s huge shells hit the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION>, 
starting a fire in an ammunition locker. Within minutes the Hood exploded, 
killing all but three of the ship's 1,400 crew members. The Prince of <LOCATION>Wales</LOCATION> was 
also damaged. 
</P>
<P>
Of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, "the British were lucky to get it to the bottom," <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> 
claims. In the climactic battle, a "freak hit" by a torpedo launched from a 
vintage World War I biplane knocked out the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s steering, forcing the 
crippled battleship to "wait for the British to come and get it." Of course, 
the British came and the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was sunk in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> about 600 miles west 
of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Since the discovery of the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says there has been curiosity 
about what actually caused the ship to sink -- British firepower or scuttling 
by her own crew. But <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> believes the evidence makes the point moot. The 
British warships had orders to sink the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION>, not capture it, and the 
Germans were under orders not to let the pride of their fleet be taken as a war 
prize, he says. 
</P>
<P>
At <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME> on <DATE>May 27</DATE>, the captain of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> ordered his crew to open the 
seacocks on his disabled ship, thus flooding the hull, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> recounts. About 
<TIME>10:30 a.m.</TIME>, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was hit by three torpedoes from the British cruiser 
Dorsetshire and sank three minutes later. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Bismarck's Survivors 
</P>
<P>
"So it was on its way down and the torpedoes helped -- but it was on its way 
down," <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says. "If they hadn't opened the seacocks, I'm convinced the 
British would have sat there and plunked torpedoes into it until it sank. So 
it's sort of academic who sank it." Only about 100 of the <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION>'s crew 
survived. Nearly 2,300 perished, including several hundred who were swimming in 
the water after their ship disappeared. 
</P>
<P>
It is that moment that seems to galvanize <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"When the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> sank, approximately 800 living souls went into the water and 
were alive after the ship went under," he says, leaning forward in his chair. 
"And the Dorsetshire came in and began picking up survivors and then someone 
thought they saw a periscope and they took off and they left 700 people in the 
water alive. . . . Can you imagine the awfulness, the hopelessness, the despair 
of the sailor who's just had a ship blown out from underneath him? He's 
paddling and freezing to death in this water and salvation is right there and 
he's grabbing hold of the hull and the ship takes off." 
</P>
<P>
Ballard has said he will not reveal the exact location of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> except 
to German authorities. As a ship of war, the battleship belongs to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>, he 
says, although there might be some debate about which half of that divided 
country would have the more legitimate claim. 
</P>
<P>
As with the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says he strongly believes that such relatively 
recent wrecks should be left undisturbed, memorials to those who perished. As 
for wrecks from the dim reaches of the past, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> argues that they should be 
explored only by qualified archeologists intent on broadening historical 
knowledge. In fact, he still becomes visibly angry that private expeditions to 
the Titanic took some artifacts from the wreck. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Developed Deep-Sea Robots 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> seems to be chiefly an enthusiast, not a critic. In particular he 
is a proponent of machines, especially robots. Ballard has headed up the 
development of a system of deep-sea unmanned robots -- called the Argo-Jason 
system. Equipped with cameras and other sensing devices, the robots are now 
capable of plumbing the world's deep waters faster and more safely than the 
tiny, slow, manned submarines that previously were the cutting edge of ocean 
research and exploration, he says. 
</P>
<P>
While an unmanned robot named <PERSON>Jason Jr.</PERSON> was used in a <DATE>1986</DATE> expedition to the 
Titanic, it was only within the last few months that the leap was made "to 
fully robotic exploration," <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> says, meaning that robots can now be 
directed from a surface ship rather than from a manned submarine via a control 
cable. 
</P>
<P>
It's a relief that he and others won't have to spend five or more hours per day 
"commuting" to the ocean floor, which averages 12,000 feet in depth, he says. 
Even though he has spent a lot of time in cramped research submarines and 
probably will spend more, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> is miffed by the inefficiency of the 
"romantic little guys," referring to the small submarines. 
</P>
<P>
He explains: ". . . you're spending five hours a day freezing to death in this 
little sphere. Our average dive time on the Titanic was three hours a day. 
Three hours out of 24 and you've got 50 people and you've got one guy looking 
out of a window." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
More Interest in <LOCATION>Science 
</P>
<P>
Ballard</LOCATION> has been talking about the potential of this technology for years. But 
recent advances have made him more convinced than ever that the concept of 
"telepresence" will revolutionize not only undersea exploration but the way 
many people "travel." More important, he sees the technology as capable of 
rekindling interest in science among American schoolchildren. 
</P>
<P>
"We're now reaching a point in technology, in imaging devices both acoustic and 
visual, fiber optic transmission links, digital enhancement, computer 
manipulation, robotics etc, etc. to simulate presence," he says in a gee-whiz 
way. "In fact many of us in the technology believe it will become a pervasive 
way of people living their lives. In other words, ultimately you won't travel 
that much. You'll travel in a telepresence way. We can have this conversation 
half a world apart and you'll sense my presence, I'll sense yours. . . . The 
idea of the Argo-Jason system is to put you in a room and convince you you're 
in a submarine looking out a bunch of windows" that are in fact video monitors 
displaying scenes picked up by robot-mounted cameras. 
</P>
<P>
Ballard, whose professional base is the Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution on 
<LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>' <LOCATION>Cape Cod</LOCATION>, is such a believer in the concept of telepresence that 
he's already using it to change the way he lives. He recently built a house 
near <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Glacier National Park</ORGANIZATION> in which he is installing a satellite 
antenna so that he can bounce his image and voice into space and back to <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> 
for professional meetings and conversations with people far, far away. His goal 
is "to create a place where I don't feel professionally inconvenienced by 
living in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>." 
</P>
<P>
How much time he actually will spend in northern <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> is an open question, 
though, given the demands of the Explorer television series. 
</P>
<P>
With the series, including a program on the <LOCATION>Bismarck</LOCATION> to be broadcast in late 
<DATE>October</DATE>, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> asserts that he can do his bit to instill a respect for the 
past and take millions on magical mystery tours of the kingdoms under the sea. 
</P>
<P>
". . . <PERCENT>70%</PERCENT> of the planet's under water. We've seen less than <PERCENT>.1%</PERCENT> of <PERCENT>1%</PERCENT>. I mean 
we know more about the mountain ranges on Mars than the mountain ranges of our 
own planet," he says. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
The Vast Unknown 
</P>
<P>
It is this sense of the vast unknown here on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> that he wants to 
communicate. 
</P>
<P>
"To me the concept of an explorer has been somewhat diminished," he says. 
"People now retrace <ORGANIZATION>Hannibal</ORGANIZATION>'s route in a Winnebago or they walk backwards to 
the <LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION>. It's sort of become a <ORGANIZATION>Guinness Book of World Records</ORGANIZATION> type of 
thing." 
</P>
<P>
And he says he wants to do his part to protect good old people-friendly dry 
land too. 
</P>
<P>
"It's very important right now to realize that the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> is in jeopardy and 
we're the first generation that can kill it and we're killing it," he says, 
leaving the battles of World War II far behind. ". . . This baloney about 
living in space is baloney. You send everyone else out there and give me 
<LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. I have no desire to live underwater. I've seen the place." 
</P>
<P>
BISMARCK 
</P>
<P>
Type: German battleship 
</P>
<P>
Length: 823 feet 
</P>
<P>
Displacement: 52,000 tons 
</P>
<P>
Date Sunk: <DATE>May 27</DATE>, l941 
</P>
<P>
Lives Lost: 2,100 
</P>
<P>
Depth: 16,000 feet 
</P>
<P>
Date Found: <DATE>June 8</DATE>, l989 
</P>
<P>
Type: British super luxury liner 
</P>
<P>
Length: 882 feet 
</P>
<P>
Displacement: 45,000 
</P>
<P>
Date Sunk: <DATE>April 14</DATE>, l912 
</P>
<P>
Lives Lost: 1,500 
</P>
<P>
Depth: 12,000 
</P>
<P>
Date Found: <DATE>Sept.1</DATE>, l985 
</P></TEXT>
<CORRECTION-DATE>
<P>
July 18, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</CORRECTION-DATE>
<CORRECTION>
<P>
FOR THE RECORD 
</P>
<P>
A photograph in the Monday View section identified as that of the German 
battleship Bismarck is actually a photo of the British battleship King George 
V, one of the ships that gave chase to the Bismarck. 
</P>
</CORRECTION>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Above, the Titanic as it left England on its doomed first voyage. 
Associated Press.; Photo, Map, top left, shows location of two ships found by 
Dr. Robert Ballard. VICTOR KOTOWITZ / Los Angeles Times; Photo, Robert D. 
Ballard, top right Mike Meadows / Los Angeles Times; Photo, The Bismarck, 
Germany's most powerful warship, was attacked by British naval vessels in the 
North Atlantic in May of 1941 and scuttled by the Germans. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SHIPWRECKS; BALLARD, ROBERT D; MILITARY SHIPS; TITANIC (SHIP); OCEANOGRAPHY; 
BISMARCK (SHIP); EXPLORATION; REMOTELY PILOTED VEHICLES; TECHNOLOGY 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910402-0125
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910402-0125.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Letters to the Editor:
   Titanic Wired `Shut Up'
   In Reply to Warning
</HL>
<DATE>
04/02/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A21
</SO>
<LP>
   In regard to your Feb. 21 page-one article about the new
investigation into the Titanic disaster: I wrote a
college-term paper on the subject 37 years ago. According to
my research then, Capt. Stanley Lord ordered his wireless
operator to contact the Titanic and advise it that he had
stopped his ship, the Californian, because of the iceberg
conditions. He was told by the Titanic's operator to "shut
up" because his current was interfering with its outgoing
commercial messages.
   In 1912, Marconi wireless operators did not maintain a
24-hour watch aboard transAtlantic vessels -- so, at 11:30
p.m., the Californian's operator removed his earphones and
went to bed.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   At <TIME>11:40 p.m.</TIME>, the Titanic struck the iceberg and shortly
thereafter began to fire off its white distress flares. Capt.
<PERSON>Lord</PERSON>, when informed of this, noted that it was probably just
the Titanic's passengers celebrating the maiden voyage of the
new luxury liner. He ordered his crew to attempt to
communicate with the Titanic by <PERSON>Morse</PERSON> light and returned to
his bed. Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON>'s men continued signaling with the light
until <TIME>1:30 a.m.</TIME>, but got no response from the Titanic. It has
been suggested that the Titanic's officers and crew were far
too busy loading their passengers onto lifeboats to have seen
the <ORGANIZATION>Californian</ORGANIZATION>'s flashing signals. Several surviving
passengers later recalled seeing the lights, and some of them
said they rowed their lifeboats toward them.
   Following the investigations on both sides of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>
into the Titanic sinking, steamship companies were required
to keep a radio operator on duty round the clock.
   <PERSON>James G. Smith
   Potomac</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910221-0064
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910221-0064.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Maritime Mystery:
   What Ship Watched
   As the Titanic Sank?
   ---
   Britain Refloats the Question
   Of S.S. Californian's Role;
   A Quest for Exoneration
   ----
   By Richard L. Hudson
</HL>
<DATE>
02/21/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A1
</SO>
<CO>
   EUROP
</CO>
<IN>
MARINE TRANSPORTATION (MAR)
</IN>
<LP>
   On the cold, clear night in 1912 that the RMS Titanic
struck ice and sank into history, a heinous crime occurred.
   As the icy Atlantic gushed in through the great liner's
hull, passengers and crew spied a flicker of hope. On the
horizon, the lights of another ship appeared. They signaled
to it, firing rockets high into the sky. But the ship didn't
respond. In fact, "it seemed as if the vessel was turning
around and leaving us," a survivor recalled.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The mystery ship steamed off, abandoning about 1,500
people to drown in the chill black sea; 705 survived.
   Thus began one of maritime history's great whodunits --
and one that has suddenly inspired new investigations in
<LOCATION>Liverpool</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>. What ship was it? And why, as a <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee of the day put it, did it disregard "the
dictates of humanity, international usage, and the
requirements of law?" Armed with new evidence, the British
government has reopened its Titanic files and named a special
examiner to plumb this 79-year-old mystery. "This is a unique
investigation," says a government spokesman.
   At issue is the guilt or innocence of <ORGANIZATION>Stanley Lord</ORGANIZATION>, the
English sea captain whose cargo ship, the <ORGANIZATION>S.S. Californian</ORGANIZATION>,
was accused of being the mystery vessel. Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON> was
napping in his chartroom that fateful night, while junior
officers were said to have dithered on the bridge. He denied
it, but went to his grave in <DATE>1962</DATE> portrayed as the monster
who slept while hundreds drowned.
   "Reprehensible and un-British," was how one <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
magazine damned his conduct. His supporters, on the other
hand, view him as a scapegoat. They say he was blamed to
divert public outrage from the real reason so many died that
night: lax safety regulations that enabled the Titanic to
scrimp on lifeboats.
   Indeed, Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON>'s culpability is again being
challenged, and he may soon have his reputation restored. If
the British examiner exonerates him, a parallel campaign
could gather steam in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to correct the record there.
The grand aim, says <PERSON>Leslie Harrison</PERSON>, the captain's former
union leader and chief defender, is to correct "the grossest
miscarriage of justice" in British seafaring history.
   The prospect has the small world of Titanic scholarship in
a maelstrom. For 30 years, a tiny -- and now very aged --
crew of British and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> history buffs has debated the late
captain's case. Like a schismatic church, they are split into
Lordites and anti-Lordites. The Lordites say the Californian
wasn't the mystery vessel. Bilge, say the anti-Lordites. The
two sides trade jibes in such journals as "The Titanic
Commutator," a quarterly publication of the <ORGANIZATION>U.S.-based
Titanic Historical Society</ORGANIZATION>.
   "Passions are high. I have spent more time working on this
one issue than any other" about the Titanic, says <PERSON>Walter
Lord</PERSON>, author of the <DATE>1950s</DATE> best-seller about the sinking, "A
Night to Remember." Confusingly, <PERSON>Mr. Lord</PERSON>, now 73, is an
anti-Lordite. He is also "no relation of ours, thank
goodness," says <PERSON>Stanley T. Lord</PERSON>, who is a Lordite and the
captain's 83-year-old son.
   Steering the course for the Lordite faction is <PERSON>Mr.
Harrison</PERSON>, who has been Capt. Lord's tireless defender since
<DATE>1958</DATE>. That year, <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON> recalls, a tall, elderly
captain appeared in his Liverpool office one day and declared
with authority: "I'm Lord of the Californian." The name meant
nothing to <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>, then a clerkish young idealist who
had spent much of his own brief sea career leaning greenly
over the rail. But the captain explained: A new British
movie, "A Night to Remember," based on the book, was
dramatizing the charges against him and he wanted his union's
help to defend his name.
   Since then, muses the now-elderly union leader -- he is 78
and retired to a cottage overlooking the sea -- "my life has
been one of constant battles with people."
   In trying to prove the captain's innocence, <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>
scoured musty archives, tape-recorded hours of conversation
with the captain and took affidavits from Titanic witnesses.
He badgered British politicians for a rehearing. To publicize
the case, he spent four years writing a book on it -- and 10
years trying to get it published. When it finally appeared in
<DATE>1986</DATE>, it sold 1,720 copies. He even quarreled with his own
union colleagues, some of whom urged him to drop the case as
hopeless.
   He refused. "My approach to life is scrupulous honesty,"
<PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON> says, struggling to explain his persistence. "So
long as there's this absolutely gross slander on his name,
I've got to do what I told him I'd do: Not drop the case."
   According to <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>'s book, "A Titanic Myth: The
Californian Incident," Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON> had prudently stopped his
ship that night in mid-Atlantic upon encountering a vast ice
field -- the same field into which the Titanic was then
heedlessly steaming. On the horizon, he spied a ship that he
took to be a tramp steamer, but which a junior officer
thought resembled an ocean liner. Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON> signaled to it,
but it didn't respond. So with everything quiet, he left the
bridge after <TIME>midnight</TIME> for a four-hour nap on the chartroom
settee.
   As the mariner slumbered, the sea brought strange sights.
"I observed a flash of light in the sky," the officer on
watch said later. It was a white rocket -- possibly a
distress signal -- and it rose near the unidentified vessel.
Seven more rockets followed. After conferring by speaker-tube
with the sleepy captain, the bridge tried signaling the ship
again; still it didn't respond. Then it disappeared --
steamed away, the officer on watch said; sank, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and
British inquests said.
   The next morning, the Californian's wireless operator
learned of the Titanic's sinking from other passing ships.
"Where have you been all night?" one ship asked. "Been
asleep?"
   The questions came to torment Capt. Lord. After landing at
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>, his ship was named by a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee and by
a British inquest as being the vessel seen from the Titanic.
Cowardice was the crime: He and his officers were accused of
ignoring the distress rockets in order to avoid a risky
nighttime rescue through an ice field. Capt. Lord denied
this; but he was disgraced -- a scapegoat, Lordites say,
referring to the alleged cover-up of the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s lack of
lifeboats.
   "They wanted to find somebody to blame, and they pounced
on father," says his son.
   Even so, Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON> continued to get commands, thanks to
his reputation among shipowners as a skillfull and safe
captain.
   The chief Lordite theory is that -- far from seeing each
other that night -- the Californian and Titanic were watching
a third, unidentified vessel steaming between them. One
suspect is a seal ship called the <LOCATION>Samson</LOCATION>, said to have been
hunting illegally in the area. It supposedly mistook the
<ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s lights and rockets for a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> patrol
and fled. But anti-Lordites contend there is little evidence
to support that -- and even if there was a third ship, the
<ORGANIZATION>Californian</ORGANIZATION>'s officers were still negligent in failing to
investigate the rockets.
   This dispute percolated until <DATE>1985</DATE>, when new evidence
emerged. Deep beneath the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION>, an American team of
oceanographers discovered the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s final resting place,
several hundred miles off <LOCATION>Newfoundland</LOCATION>. The spot was close to
where Capt. Lord had always claimed it would be -- a fact,
Lordites argue, that corroborates a key claim in his defense:
That the Titanic and Californian were too far apart to have
seen each other that night.
   But anti-Lordites still dispute that reasoning. They say
locating the wreck of the Titanic says nothing about the
location of the Californian. The British government, however,
took the new theory seriously enough to reopen the case. The
fate of Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON>'s reputation is now with a special
examiner, Capt. <PERSON>Thomas Barnett</PERSON>, a retired government marine
surveyor.
   Whatever happened that night, Capt. <PERSON>Lord</PERSON> himself wasn't
without regrets. Rather than rely on the watch, he wished
that he had risen from his couch to inspect the situation on
the bridge himself. The result, he once told <PERSON>Mr. Harrison</PERSON>,
was "there's always this stigma: <LOCATION>Was Lord</LOCATION> to blame, or was he
not to blame?"
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890622-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-89 1542EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bismarck Bjt   06-22 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bismarck, Bjt,700</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nazis Scuttled the Ship, Discover Says; He Leaves Its Fate to Germans</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphotos</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A deep-sea inspection of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> suggests
that the most powerful battleship in <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON>'s navy was
scuttled by its own crew rather than sunk by the British in a
celebrated battle, underwater explorer <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON> said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   During a 90-minute news conference, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> described how he his
ocean-crawling robot located the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> ``sitting upright and
proud'' two weeks ago.
   Then the American oceanographer, whose father was of British
background and whose mother was of German heritage, addressed
himself to the German people in German.
   ``I am an underwater explorer, not a treasure hunter,'' he said,
translating himself back into English. ``We found no human remains.
We touched nothing and took nothing. ... The future of the <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION>
is in the hands of the German people.''
   He said he will disclose its exact location only to <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> so
Germans themselves can decide whether to try to raise the ship,
which sank after a battle <DATE>May 27, 1941</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>, a senior scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole Oceanographic
Institution</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>, said structural evidence satisfied him
that the Germans scuttled the battleship rather than trying to
surrender or allowing her to be sent down by British fire.
   ``Only scuttled ships tend to make it to the bottom in one
piece,'' <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. ``It appears the crew opened it up along its
entire length. It was clearly flooded, stem to stern.''
   ``Maybe the Germans didn't want it taken as a war prize,'' he
added.
   It is known that <DATE>two years earlier</DATE>, <PERSON>Hitler</PERSON> ordered the German
pocket battleship <PERSON>Graf Spee</PERSON> scuttled after it was cornered in the
neutral port of <LOCATION>Montevideo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>, and attacked by British ships.
Hitler apparently wanted to keep the British from learning the
secrets of the <ORGANIZATION>Graf Spee</ORGANIZATION>'s construction and weapons.
   In the <DATE>1941</DATE> battle, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s main guns were quickly knocked
out and the attacking British ships were out of range of her
secondary guns, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said, so its was helpless and taking
hundreds of hits _ its sinking clearly inevitable.
   Rendered unsteerable by torpedoes dropped by tiny fabric-covered
British biplanes, it was unable to escape.
   Asked if the German commander couldn't have surrendered by
ceasing fire, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said ``in the fuzz of battle'' in fierce seas
it would have been unlikely that the British would have recognized
that the Germans were giving up.
   Again, he speculated, perhaps the Germans did not want the ship's
technologically advanced equipment to fall into British hands.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was found by <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> in more than 15,000 feet of
water about 600 miles west of <LOCATION>Brest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. He said it was in
remarkably good shape, ``elegant, well preserved.''
   Before the battle, <ORGANIZATION>British Prime Minister Winston Churchill</ORGANIZATION> had
left convoys unprotected and thrown all his capital ships in pursuit
with a ringing three-word command: ``Sink the Bismarck!''
   Of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s 2,200-man crew, only about 115 survived.
British ships picked up 110 survivors but left with hundreds of
German sailors still in the icy waters after spotting what might
have been a German U-boat. German vessels later rescued only five
more survivors.
   The story has been recounted in books, songs and a movie.
   The sinking occurred only eight days after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> left
<LOCATION>Gdynia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, for her first operation. If unstopped, it could have
posed a critical threat to convoys of merchant shipping and undercut
British morale at a time when <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> stood virtually alone against
combined German sea and air power.
   The British sent the warship Hood after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> but within
five days of going to sea the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> had sunk the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> in a
three-minute engagement, with the loss of all but three of the
vessel's crew of 1,419.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> was a symbol of British sea power, and its loss stunned
the British public and the war government and made sinking the
Bismarck a mission of crucial importance.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said under laws of the sea, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> remains the
property of the German people.
   The sunken battleship was discovered and photographed by the same
remote-controlled robot that <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> used four years ago to find the
wreck of the Titanic, the British passenger liner that sank in <DATE>1912</DATE>
after striking an iceberg.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890622-0086 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-89 1017EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bismarck     06-22 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bismarck,370</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discoverer of Sunken Battleship Believes It Was Scuttled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Laserphotos WX6, WX8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Underwater explorer <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON>, whose
deep-sea robot discovered the German battleship <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> on the
bottom of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> two weeks ago, said <DATE>today</DATE> he believed the
World War II vessel had been scuttled by its own crew.
   At a news conference to disclose details of the discovery,
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the condition of the ship confirmed for him the theory
that the vessel was scuttled rather than sunk by British fire in one
of the most famous and important naval engagements of the war.
   ``Only scuttled ships tend to make it to the bottom in one
piece,'' <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. ``It appears the crew opened it up along its
entire length. It was clearly flooded, stem to stern.''
   The sunken battleship was discovered and photographed by the
robot called Argo, the same device that was used four years ago to
find the wreck of the Titanic, the British passenger liner that sank
in <DATE>1912</DATE> after striking an iceberg.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was the most powerful vessel in the <ORGANIZATION>German Navy</ORGANIZATION> when
it sank during a battle with the British on <DATE>May 27, 1941</DATE>. Of the
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s 2,200-man crew, only about 115 survived.
   The sinking occurred only eight days after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> left
<LOCATION>Gydnia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, for her first operation, intended to attack convoys
of merchant shipping and damage British morale at a time when
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> stood virtually alone against combined German sea and air
power.
   The British sent the warship Hood after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, but five
days after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> went to sea it sank the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> with the loss
of all but three of the British vessel's crew of 1,419.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> was the largest warship in the world until the start of
World War II and symbolized British sea power, so its loss stunned
the British public and the war government and made sinking the
Bismarck a mission of the most crucial nature.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was found ``in a remarkable state of
preservation. There doesn't appear to be as much damage as I had
expected.''
   Ballard is a senior scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole Oceanographic
Institution</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was found in more than 15,000 feet of water about
600 miles west of <LOCATION>Brest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890524-0088 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-24-89 1012EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-RiverDeaths 1stLd-Writethru a0476 05-24 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-River Deaths, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0476,0703</SECOND>
<HEAD>Memphis Monument Notes Mississippi River Deaths</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 4th graf pvs, `Built for ...' to CORRECT date of sinking
to April 27 sted April 7.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto MX1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WOODY BAIRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1865</DATE> explosion of the paddlewheeler
<PERSON>Sultana</PERSON> was a disaster to rival the sinking of the Titanic.
   The dead, many of them emaciated from Confederate prison camps,
totaled more than 1,500, but newspapers of the day gave scant
notice. The horror was lost in the greater gore of Civil War and
presidential assassination.
   Until now, there had been no marker here for the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> soldiers
who perished in the muddy <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>. But on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, a six-foot
granite marker is being unveiled in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>' <LOCATION>Elmwood Cemetery</LOCATION> as a
reminder that the Sultana went down in flames just seven miles
north of the city's downtown riverfront.
   Built for 300 passengers and a crew of 76, the steamship was
carrying more than 2,300 people plus 100 horses and mules when
three of its four boilers exploded at <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME> on <DATE>April 27, 1865</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Jerry Potter</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> lawyer who has researched the disaster
for a dozen years and is writing a book on it, said <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> officers
may have overloaded the paddlewheeler to inflate troop transport
payments.
   ``There were two other steamboats that were trying to get a
portion of the men. The only explanation I have been able to
uncover for why the Sultana got them all is bribery,'' <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> and <PERSON>Hugh Berryman</PERSON>, a forensic pathologist at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Tennessee</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, estimated the death toll at
1,547, 44 more than the number of people lost when the ocean liner
Titanic hit an iceberg and sank in the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE>.
   Other counts of the Sultana victims have put the total between
1,400 and 1,450, but <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> said those estimates failed to
include one of three trainloads of soldiers who boarded at
<LOCATION>Vicksburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>.
   The monument, financed by three <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> residents, will be the
second of two major markers to the disaster.
   The other, in <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>, was put up in <DATE>1916</DATE> by Sultana survivors
who raised money for the monument.
   Researching the disaster has been difficult because newspapers
of the day were still primarily concerned with the assassination of
<PERSON>Abraham Lincoln</PERSON> two weeks earlier and with the end of the war.
   ``It was just lost to history because of the other events that
were going on at the time,'' <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> said.
   The <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> has shifted its course since the Sultana went
down, and the steamboat's remains rest now under a soybean field
about a mile east of the river in <LOCATION>Arkansas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> said.
   Excavating the boat could cost hundreds of thousands of dollars,
and would produce little of commercial value since the wreck was
salvaged two months after it burned, he said.
   <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON>, who wrote a paper on the <LOCATION>Sultana</LOCATION> <DATE>last year</DATE> for the
Journal of Forensic Sciences, said survivors told of watching
dozens of victims drown en masse, hands clasped together as they
grappled for survival.
   ``Many of these victims had been through some of the roughest
battles in the war, and those experiences paled in comparison to
what they went through that night,'' he said.
   Most of the victims had recently been freed from prison camps in
<LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and were headed north to be released from the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>. Many
were crowded onto two decks directly over the paddlewheeler's four
18-foot boilers, one of which had developed a leak that was hastily
repaired.
   When one of the boilers blew, setting off two others, the upper
decks collapsed forming a funnel that dumped dozens of victims into
the fire, <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> said.
   The 263-foot boat, made of wood and covered with flammable
paint, was equipped with 76 life jackets. Many of the survivors
also escaped by clinging to debris. One survivor floated to shore
on a dead mule.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> investigated the disaster and a captain in charge of
loading the troops at <LOCATION>Vicksburg</LOCATION> was found guilty of mishandling his
duties. His conviction was overturned on appeal, however, and he
was honorably discharged.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900709-0061 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-09-90 1240EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Britain-Titanic     07-09 0436</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Britain-Titanic,0447</SECOND>
<HEAD>Titanic Inquiry after 78 Years</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An inquiry will be held into the conduct of a
steamship captain who was criticized for not coming to the aid of
the Titanic when it sank 78 years ago, the government said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The Titanic sank after striking an iceberg in the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION>
on <DATE>April 14, 1912</DATE>. More than 1,500 of the 2,200 people aboard the
ship perished.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Marine Accident Investigation Branch</ORGANIZATION> will examine testimony
at the <DATE>1912</DATE> inquiry into the loss of the great liner to throw light
on the role of the late Capt. <PERSON>Stanley Lord</PERSON>, said a <ORGANIZATION>Department of
Transport</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman.
   The inquiry comes in response to a campaign by <ORGANIZATION>Lord</ORGANIZATION>'s relatives,
who have been trying to clear his name, said the spokeswoman. She
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The inquiry was first reported in <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s editions of <ORGANIZATION>The Daily
Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, which said a crucial piece of evidence would be the
position of the wreck as determined in <DATE>1985</DATE> by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> oceanographer
<PERSON>Robert Ballard</PERSON>.
   Lord was master of the Boston-bound Californian, believed to
have been the ship nearest to the Titanic when it struck the
iceberg.
   The <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION> and other ships which were farther away than the
Californian did reach the scene in answer to the stricken liner's
distress calls.
   Lord's ship was stopped by ice at the time. The original inquiry
censured him for not responding to distress rockets from the
Titanic and ruled that as he was 8 to 10 miles from the liner he
could have gone to its aid and saved lives.
   Lord died in <DATE>1962</DATE>, claiming to the end that the Titanic was in
an icefield 20 miles or more from his ship and that he was unable
to help. A campaign to clear his name has been carried on by his
son and other supporters, and an earlier petition to reopen the
inquiry was rejected in <DATE>1965</DATE>.
   Lord insisted that a ship seen from the Californian was not the
Titanic. The ship was only identified in <DATE>1962</DATE> as the <LOCATION>Samson</LOCATION>, a
seal-hunter.
   ``Supporters of Capt. Lord claimed he was a scapegoat for the
failire of the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s owners and the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Trade</ORGANIZATION> to make sure
there were enough lifeboats,'' The <ORGANIZATION>Daily Telegraph</ORGANIZATION> said.
   It quoted Capt. <PERSON>James de Coverley</PERSON>, deputy chief of marine
accidents, as saying the <DATE>1912</DATE> inquiry would not be reopened as that
had been into the Titanic's loss, not Lord's conduct.
   ``We are not in the business of rewriting history but in this
particular case it was considered desirable to have a
re-evaluation,'' de Coverley was quoted as saying.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900501-0053 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-01-90 1102EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WrecksExplored 2ndLd-Writethru a0510 05-01 0485</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wrecks Explored, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0510,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Schoolchildren Get Inside Glimpse of 1812-Era Wrecks</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 7th graf, `The Hamilton . ..' to CORRECT that British
were NOT invading forces in Canada.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALAN FLIPPEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ST. CATHARINES, Ontario (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientists using a robot diver to
explore two War of 1812-era wrecks let schoolchildren across <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION> in on the expedition.
   The underwater look <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the merchant schooner <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and
its sister ship, the <LOCATION>Scourge</LOCATION>, was televised live to 13 museums.
Four youngsters watching got to operate the robot using a computer
joystick hooked up by satellite.
   The cold, fresh water of <LOCATION>Lake Ontario</LOCATION> and the 300-foot depth of
the wrecks helped preserve the two ships, which were pressed into
battle service by the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> during the War of <DATE>1812</DATE>.
   Cannons, railings and an elegantly carved figurehead could be
seen as the black-and-white television image panned slowly.
   <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON>, the expedition's leader, and other scientists
gave a running narration and took questions from viewers at the
museums in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and at the <ORGANIZATION>Canadian
Football Hall of Fame</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Hamilton</LOCATION>, a city 25 miles west of <ORGANIZATION>St.
Catharines</ORGANIZATION> that has title to the wrecks.
   ``The ship is in immaculate condition. We can see the caulking
in the planks,'' <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. ``There's no suggestion that they
suffered any damage due to the sinking itself. They just got
flooded and went down very gently.''
   The <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> and the <ORGANIZATION>Scourge</ORGANIZATION> sank during a storm <DATE>Aug. 8, 1813</DATE>,
killing 53 sailors. They had taken part in several battles against
British forces in southern <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   However, the wrecks narrowly escaped damage from large ships
that dragged their anchors across the lake bottom, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. He
said the furrows caused by the anchors were plainly visible near
the wrecks.
   The wrecks remained undisturbed six miles off <LOCATION>St. Catharines</LOCATION>, 30
miles south of <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> on the lake's southern shore, until their
discovery in <DATE>1975</DATE>. Since then, scientists such as French underwater
explorer <PERSON>Jacques Cousteau</PERSON> have used submarines and remote cameras
to explore them, but <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON>'s expedition was the most
technologically sophisticated yet.
   In an interview by ship-to-shore telephone, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the
children's participation was the most significant part of the
program. He said the remote control setup had never been used
before.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the two-week expedition would produce a detailed
map of the wrecks that <PERSON>Hamilton</PERSON> officials could use in deciding
whether to raise them someday.
   Ballard, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Center for Marine Exploration</ORGANIZATION> at the
expedition that discovered the wreck of the Titanic. The storied
ocean liner sank in the <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> after ramming an iceberg in
<DATE>1912</DATE>.
   The museums taking part in the program were in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Dallas</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tenn.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Rochester</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION>; Salt
<LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Sarasota</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>; <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>British Columbia</LOCATION>;
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>; and <LOCATION>Woods Hole</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890622-0115 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-22-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-Bismarck1stLd-Writethru a0547   06-22 0690</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bismarck 1st Ld-Writethru, a0547,630</SECOND>
<HEAD>Discoverer of Sunken Battleship Believes It Was Scuttled</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Inserts 8 grafs with news conference details on scuttling after
3rd graf, ``Only scuttled;'' picks up at pvs 4th graf, The sunken</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIKE FEINSILBER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Underwater explorer <PERSON>Robert D. Ballard</PERSON>, whose
deep-sea robot discovered the German battleship <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> on the
bottom of the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> two weeks ago, said <DATE>today</DATE> he believed the
World War II vessel had been scuttled by its own crew.
   At a news conference to disclose details of the discovery,
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the condition of the ship confirmed for him the theory
that the vessel was scuttled rather than sunk by British fire in one
of the most famous and important naval engagements of the war.
   ``Only scuttled ships tend to make it to the bottom in one
piece,'' <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. ``It appears the crew opened it up along its
entire length. It was clearly flooded, stem to stern.''
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said he could only speculate on why the German commander
decided to send his vessel to the bottom in <DATE>May 1941</DATE>. He said
perhaps it carried technologically advanced equipment that the
Germans did not want to fall into British hands.
   ``Maybe the Germans didn't want it taken as a war prize,'' he
said.
   In <DATE>1939</DATE>, after a battle with three smaller British ships, the
German pocket battleship <PERSON>Graf Spee</PERSON> was cornered in the neutral port
of <LOCATION>Montevideo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Uruguay</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Adolf Hitler</PERSON> ordered it scuttled, possibly
to prevent the British from learning the secrets of its construction
and weapons.
   In the <DATE>1941</DATE> battle, the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s four main guns were quickly
knocked out of action and the attacking British ships were out of
range of the <ORGANIZATION>Bismarck</ORGANIZATION>'s secondary guns, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. With the ship
helpless and taking hundreds of hits, its sinking was clearly
inevitable, he said.
   Asked if the Germans couldn't have surrendered the ship to save
lives, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said there was no mast left on which a white flag
could have been hoisted.
   Asked if the Germans couldn't have surrendered by ceasing fire,
<PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said ``in the fuzz of battle'' in fierce seas it would have
been unlikely that the British would have recognized that the German
fire had ended.
   The British ships did halt their gunfire but continued to send
torpedos, <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said. However, he said, the lack of evidence of an
implosion in the remains persuaded him that the ship had been
blasted open by its own crew rather than sunk by British torpedoes.
   He said he would keep secret the exact location of the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>
and let the German people decide its future fate.
   The sunken battleship was discovered and photographed by the
robot called Argo, the same device that was used four years ago to
find the wreck of the Titanic, the British passenger liner that sank
in <DATE>1912</DATE> after striking an iceberg.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was the most powerful vessel in the <ORGANIZATION>German Navy</ORGANIZATION> when
it sank during a battle with the British on <DATE>May 27, 1941</DATE>. Of the
<PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>'s 2,200-man crew, only about 115 survived.
   The sinking occurred only eight days after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> left
<LOCATION>Gydnia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, for her first operation, intended to attack convoys
of merchant shipping and damage British morale at a time when
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> stood virtually alone against combined German sea and air
power.
   The British sent the warship Hood after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON>, but five
days after the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> went to sea it sank the <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> with the loss
of all but three of the British vessel's crew of 1,419.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Hood</ORGANIZATION> was the largest warship in the world until the start of
World War II and symbolized British sea power, so its loss stunned
the British public and the war government and made sinking the
Bismarck a mission of the most crucial nature.
   <PERSON>Ballard</PERSON> said the <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was found ``in a remarkable state of
preservation. There doesn't appear to be as much damage as I had
expected.''
   Ballard is a senior scientist at the <ORGANIZATION>Woods Hole Oceanographic
Institution</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>.
   The <PERSON>Bismarck</PERSON> was found in more than 15,000 feet of water about
600 miles west of <LOCATION>Brest</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890627-0140 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-89 1546EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Saturn-Titan 1stLd-Writethru a0609 06-27 0245</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Saturn-Titan, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0609,0245</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saturn's Moon Titan May Have Dry Land, Not Just An Ocean</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 3rd graf to CORRECT Saturn's to Jupiter's</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A pioneering space probe suggested
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s largest moon might be covered with an ocean of liquid
natural gas, but scientists who bounced radar off its surface say it
may have some dry land or an icy surface.
   ``We interpret our results to mean that the surface of Titan is
highly variable,'' planetary scientist <PERSON>Duane O. Muhleman</PERSON> said in an
announcement issued <DATE>Monday</DATE> by the <ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   Titan, nearly twice as massive as <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s moon, is one of only
three moons in the solar system known to have atmospheres. The
others are <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION>'s moon Io and <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION>'s moon <ORGANIZATION>Triton</ORGANIZATION>.
   Data from Voyager 1 in <DATE>1980</DATE> suggested that methane and ethane,
components of natural gas, condense in <ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION>'s mostly nitrogen
atmosphere and rain on the surface, leading some scientists to
believe <ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION> might be covered by up to a mile of liquid ethane and
methane.
   <PERSON>Muhleman</PERSON> and his colleagues bounced 360,000-watt radar signals
off Titan during three 5{-hour periods on <DATE>June 3</DATE>, 4 and 5.
   An ethane-methane ocean would have low reflectivity, creating
weak radar echoes. Instead, they found strong radar echoes during
one observation period and weak echoes during the other two while
Titan rotated on its axis. That suggests <ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION> has oceans in some
places and a solid surface in others.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-14753</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CDEAFACTFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920404
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  04 APR 92 / The Titanic's tales of terror: Alexander Garrett on a famous
maritime disaster
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALEXANDER GARRETT
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
IN THE afternoon of the <DATE>April 15 1912</DATE>, <PERSON>Bruce Ismay</PERSON>, managing director of the
<ORGANIZATION>White Star Line</ORGANIZATION>, filled out a <ORGANIZATION>Marconi</ORGANIZATION> telegram form for company headquarters
in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 'Deeply regret to advise you Titanic sank <TIME>this morning</TIME> 15th
after collision iceberg resulting serious loss life,' he wrote. 'Further
particulars later.'
Ismay was aboard the rescue ship <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION>, one of 705 survivors - 1,516
perished. But his message remained unsent until 5.50 am on the 17th, nearly
two days later. The wireless telegraph was <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION>'s only contact with the
world, and as its operator worked round the clock to send out messages from
survivors, the signal from the White Star managing director - confirming
what the world already feared - was overlooked.
Today, a vessel involved in a collision would be in contact with coastguard
authorities within seconds. Then, the delay caused enormous uncertainty,
provoked accusations of censorship, and added one more mystery to the
intrigue surrounding the disaster.
On <DATE>Tuesday April 14</DATE>, <PERSON>Ismay</PERSON>'s communique is one of 448 radio signal messages
relating to the Titanic to be sold at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s in <LOCATION>South Kensington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. Together they provide a poignant chronicle of events in the world's
most famous maritime disaster, 80 years ago this week. The collection is
being sold by <PERSON>John Booth</PERSON>, who has exhibited them at the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic Signals
Archive</ORGANIZATION> for the last three years.
That these signals survived is remarkable. At the time the Titanic went
down, telegraph companies kept originals of all transmitted signals for 12
months. Messages from ships involved in the <LOCATION>Titanic</LOCATION> disaster were assembled
for the two public inquiries, one in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, the other in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. After
that, they were returned to the <LOCATION>Marconi</LOCATION> company where they were held in a
vault until the late <DATE>1940s</DATE>.
When Cable and Wireless took over the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Telegraph Company</ORGANIZATION> - as it had
by then become - the signals were earmarked for destruction, but they were
salvaged by an unnamed employee, whose son found them hidden in a suitcase
when his father died 30 years later. Booth later acquired the signals. He is
selling them now, he says, 'because my wife says they take up too much of my
time'.
Before the wireless was invented by <PERSON>Guglielmo Marconi</PERSON> in <DATE>1896</DATE>, ships
communicated with each other by flags and light signals.
But when the Titanic set sail from <LOCATION>Southampton</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday April 10 1912</DATE>,
she had the most powerful wireless yet fitted. She was one of the first
liners to have two wireless operators - <PERSON>John Phillips</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harold Bride</PERSON>, both
employed by <PERSON>Marconi</PERSON> - who could together provide a round-the-clock radio
watch.
Early in the voyage, they were busy telegraphing arrangements for passengers
to meet relatives in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. It was a lucrative business for <ORGANIZATION>Marconi</ORGANIZATION>: each
message cost 30 shillings, at a time when the second wireless operator
earned 50 shillings a month.
It is the tone of optimism that is striking. One starts: 'Fine voyage fine
ship feeling fine'. Another: 'Hardly wait to get back. Cable made me awfully
happy. Love Mutzie'
One, however, was more ominous. 'Westbound steamers report bergs growlers
and field ice in 42 N from 49 to 51 <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>. <DATE>April 12th</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Compts Barr</ORGANIZATION>'
On <DATE>April 12</DATE>, the Touraine radioed to report 'dense fog and thick icefields'.
Further danger signals followed from the Californian and the <LOCATION>Caronia</LOCATION>. One of
the great unresolved questions of the disaster is why the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s captain
continued to sail towards the danger zone at 22 knots, especially as <PERSON>Harold
Bride</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Titanic</ORGANIZATION>'s surviving wireless operator, told the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> inquiry that
he had passed on the message from the <LOCATION>Californian</LOCATION>, and it had been
'personally acknowledged' by Captain <PERSON>Smith</PERSON>.
Later that day a fateful message was sent: 'Sinking wants immediate
assistance'.
The shortcomings of the wireless - as then operated - become evident
immediately following the collision with the iceberg. Unlike the Titanic,
most of the ships that night had only one radio man, if any.
<PERSON>Thomas Cottam</PERSON>, sole operator on the <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION>, should have finished duty at
<TIME>midnight</TIME>. At 12.30 he was about to retire when the first distress signal
came through. The <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION> sailed to the Titanic's aid at full speed, but
it was 60 miles away, three and a half hours sailing. Another ship, the
Californian, was (by its own controversial account) only 19 miles away, but
its wireless operator, <PERSON>Cyril Evans</PERSON>, had gone to bed. A third vessel, the
Norwegian trawler <PERSON>Samson</PERSON>, may have been even closer, but had no radio.
Marconi was later asked why his apparatus did not have a bell to wake the
operator. He replied: 'On the old equipment used by ships there was a bell
arrangement, which did not work well because it alarmed the operators of all
ships, as well as the one called.'
'Titanic struck iceberg sunk <DATE>Monday 3</DATE> am. Carpathia picked up many
passengers am proceeding <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. Captain <PERSON>Rostron</PERSON>.'
The signals flying through the airwaves created total confusion for the
press. In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, The Evening Sun trumpeted 'All saved from Titanic after
collision.' The following morning in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the account in The Times was
riddled with contradiction. After reporting that the Titanic had sunk with
'great loss of life,' it cited later that she was being towed by The
Virginian to <LOCATION>Halifax</LOCATION>, or was heading under her own steam to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
By the following day, <DATE>April 17</DATE>, the full extent of the tragedy had become
clear and the recriminations began. The Times scolded the <ORGANIZATION>Central News
Agency</ORGANIZATION> over a phantom wireless message which had reported everybody safe;
while questions were asked about signals being 'interfered' with by 'amateur
operators'.
An explanation for one of the 'phantom' signals later materialised. A radio
ham unwittingly merged two signals, one asking 'Are all Titanic passengers
safe?' and another from the Asian announcing she was towing the German
tanker Deutschland to <LOCATION>Halifax</LOCATION>. The result: 'Titanic passengers safe being
towed to <LOCATION>Halifax</LOCATION>.'
Before the Titanic went down, its two radio operators were given permission
to leave their posts. Bride was washed overboard, but was picked up by the
<LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION>. As the <LOCATION>Carpathia</LOCATION> headed back to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, he assisted <LOCATION>Cottam</LOCATION> in
sending messages from survivors. A few remained cheerful, as: 'Meet me dock
with two hundred dollars underwear cap big coat. Am well but feet slightly
frozen answer <PERSON>George</PERSON>.' Others were tragic: 'Mother girls safe father Charlie
missing'. 'Father not seen no hope arrive <LOCATION>Carpathia Wednesday New York</LOCATION>.
Richard.'
The <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> inquiry made a number of recommendations about the use of
radiotelegraphy on ships. But although the Titanic sinking had highlighted
its shortcomings, the momentous significance of radio communication for
sea-going vessels was elegiacally summed up in a Times editorial on <DATE>April
16</DATE>:
'But for wireless telegraphy, the disaster might have assumed proportions
which at present we cannot measure; and we should have known nothing of its
occurence for an indefinite period . . . The advantages conferred by this
abridgment of space are enormous. No vessel need be alone, none need vanish
without a sign from human ken; and in none but crushing and instant
disasters need any despair of help.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page VII
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890528-0078 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-28-89 2147EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RiverDeaths     05-28 0501</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-River Deaths,0514</SECOND>
<HEAD>Memphis Monument Marks River Deaths of Union Soldiers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By WOODY BAIRD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MEMPHIS, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <DATE>1865</DATE> explosion of the paddlewheeler
<PERSON>Sultana</PERSON> was a disaster to rival the sinking of the Titanic, and the
muddy <LOCATION>Mississippi River</LOCATION> coughed up burned and bloated bodies for
weeks afterward.
   But until <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, no memorial had been created in this onetime
Confederate stronghold for the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> soldiers who perished aboard
the steamship, many of them emaciated survivors of Confederate
prison camps during the Civil War.
   Before a small crowd of about 50 people, a 6-foot granite marker
was unveiled in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>' <LOCATION>Elmwood Cemetery</LOCATION> as a reminder that the
Sultana went down in flames just seven miles north of the city's
downtown riverfront.
   Built for 300 passengers and a crew of 76, the paddlewheeler was
carrying more than 2,300 people, in addition to 100 horses and
mules, when three of its four boilers exploded at <TIME>2 a.m.</TIME> on <DATE>April
27, 1865</DATE>, less than three weeks after the end of the war.
   Most of the more than 1,500 people who died had recently been
freed from prison camps in <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> and were headed north to be
released from the <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION>. Many were crowded onto two decks directly
over the paddlewheeler's 18-foot boilers, one of which had
developed a leak and been hastily repaired.
   When one of the boilers blew, setting off two others, the upper
decks collapsed, forming a funnel that dumped dozens of the victims
into the fire, said <PERSON>Hugh Berryman</PERSON>, a forensic pathologist at the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Tennessee</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Jerry Potter</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Memphis</LOCATION> lawyer who has researched the disaster
for a dozen years and is writing a book on it, said <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> officers
may have overloaded the paddlewheeler to inflate troop transport
payments.
   ``There were two other steamboats that were trying to get a
portion of the men. The only explanation I have been able to
uncover for why the Sultana got them all is bribery,'' <PERSON>Potter</PERSON> said.
   Potter and <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> estimated the Sultana death toll at 1,547.
By comparison, 1,503 lives were lost when the ocean liner Titanic
hit an iceberg and sank in the remote <LOCATION>North Atlantic</LOCATION> in <DATE>1912</DATE>.
   Other counts of the Sultana victims have put the total between
1,400 and 1,450, but <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> said those estimates failed to
include one of three trainloads of soldiers who boarded the boat at
<LOCATION>Vicksburg</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>.
   ``Our figure is probably a conservative one,'' <PERSON>Berryman</PERSON> said.
