<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900730-0059 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-30-90 1413EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w PM-US-Trinidad 1stLd-Writethru a0435 07-30 0390</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-US-Trinidad, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0435,420</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Trinidad Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>US Has No Plans to Send Forces to Trinidad</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: New material, editing throughout.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TOM RAUM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has no plans to send
military forces to <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, where Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON>
and more than 30 others are being held hostage by Moslem rebels,
the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE>.
   At the same time, deputy spokesman <PERSON>Richard Boucher</PERSON> criticized
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>'s involvement with the rebels, saying it has provided some
training for the insurgents. But he said there was no apparent
direct link between <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and the hostage-taking, which occurred
last <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Boucher refused comment on reports that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military assets
were being deployed in the vicinity of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> but said ``there
are no plans for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military intervention.''
   The USS Roosevelt paid a scheduled visit to <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> <DATE>July
20-23</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> said. The carrier is now in port in <LOCATION>Norfolk</LOCATION>. The
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> has 10 ships in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> on what the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> calls ``routine
exercises.''
   <PERSON>Boucher</PERSON> said there have been no reports of injury to the
estimated 6,000 Americans living in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was keeping up to date on developments after
returning to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> late <DATE>Sunday</DATE> after a weekend at his vacation
home in <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>.
   ``We fully support the government of Prime Minister (<PERSON>Arthur</PERSON>)
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and hope for a peaceful solution to the situation there,''
said <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman <PERSON>Alixe Glen</PERSON>.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> officials said any direct <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> role had been all but ruled
out. Even sending <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> experts on hostage negotiations _ discussed
informally on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> between the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
representatives of the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> government _ had been ruled out,
sources said.
   ``The Trinidadians would like to find a solution on their own
without any outside assistance. They'd just rather settle it
themselves,'' the official said.
   The administration has hailed <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s government as a model
of democracy, and the attempted coup was viewed with distress in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, the leader of a Moslem sect, launched the coup attempt
late <DATE>Friday</DATE> by seizing the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> and
capturing <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and about 40 other hostages.
   <PERSON>Angus Khan</PERSON>, the ambassador from <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> to the
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, said the negotiations between his government and the
``terrorists over the release of the hostages are very delicate.''
He refused to say more.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 0557EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-TrinidadUprising Bjt   07-28 0834</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trinidad Uprising, Bjt,0863</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Moslems Take Prime Minister and Cabinet Hostage</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ALISTER HUGHES</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ A black Moslem leader said his
rebels captured Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON> and his Cabinet in
the Parliament building <DATE>Friday</DATE>, and claimed to have toppled the
government of this southern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation.
   But government radio early today broadcast a condemnation of the
uprising and said police had moved into the streets of the capital
to bring order in this mainly Catholic and Hindu country. There
were no immediate reports of casualties.
   The attack on Parliament came <DATE>Friday</DATE> as the capital's police
headquarters was blown up and explosions and gunfire were heard in
the direction of the government's television station, which the
rebels seized.
   ``The government has been overthrown,'' leader <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON> of
<ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, Arabic for the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION>, said on
government television.
   He promised ``free and fair'' elections within 90 days in
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, a former British colony of 1.3 million people
on two islands that lie off the Venezuelan coast.
   ``We will stop the incest, robbery, and drugs which there was no
hope for the present regime to stop,'' he said.
   Bakr's group has an estimated 250 followers. The country has a
1,500-member army and a 5,000-member police force.
   British West <ORGANIZATION>Indies Airways</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines</ORGANIZATION> canceled
commercial flights into <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>, but the <LOCATION>Piarco
International Airport</LOCATION> remained under control of government security
forces.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION>'s Radio 610, the government
radio station, said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and his Cabinet were being held in the
<ORGANIZATION>Red House</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building across the street from the
central police station.
   Radio 610 said the police station was blown up and burned out of
control for hours. Announcer <PERSON>Dennis McComie</PERSON> said no one attempted
to put out the fire and there were several explosions of what he
assumed was ammunition in the station.
   Bakr first appeared on television at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> to announce the
uprising by <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>.
would deplore any attempt to overthrow the democratic government of
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.''
   Denny said the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> had reported gunfire and explosions
in the vicinity of the TV station, which is several miles northwest
of the parliamentary building, but only a few blocks below the
hillside <ORGANIZATION>Hilton Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   Denny said he had no word about the situation of Americans in
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>. The smaller island of <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> is a popular
vacation site.
   <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said there was no plan for violence, looting or retribution
against civilians.
   Acting President <PERSON>Emmanuel Carter</PERSON> told Radio 610 that people
should pray for a solution to the situation.
   ``Stay at home and let the protected (police) forces do their
jobs,'' he said.
   McComie said at <TIME>3 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>today</DATE> that there had been some looting
and police had moved into the streets for the first time since the
country's leading officials were seized.
   Radio 610 broadcast a statement from <PERSON>David Coore</PERSON>, Jamaican
foreign affairs minister, deploring the uprising. His comments were
heard on Radio 610 on a relay from <LOCATION>Radio Jamaica</LOCATION>.
   ``We call urgently and directly on those responsible for this
totally unacceptable situation to release the hostages
unconditionally and pursue whatever complaints they have by the
regular processes of constitutional democracy which are the
hallmark of our <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Community</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Coore</PERSON> said.
   Caribbean heads of state and their ministers were to meet this
<DATE>weekend</DATE> in the Jamaican capital of <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION> for the annual meeting
the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> common market. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> Foreign Affairs Minister
<PERSON>Sahadeo Basdeo</PERSON> is in <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>.
   It could not be ascertained how many ministers were taken
hostage with <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 63, a veteran political leader, lawyer and
economist.
   Bakr, in his mid-40s, is a former <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> policeman and has
been arrested several times in the past on charges of contempt of
court and illegal demonstrations.
   He lives with 200 to 250 followers, their wives and children in
a commune on the western side of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>. Members of the
sect, founded in <DATE>1980</DATE>, are widely perceived in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> as violent
outlaws, though the group's rhetoric is highly moralistic.
   Abu <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> has said he doesn't recognize ``man's law,'' only ``the
law of almighty Allah.''
   In <DATE>November of 1988</DATE>, police raided the sect's sanctuary and
seized weapons and ammunition. <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said then he was waging a war
against ``the menace of cocaine.''
   The Moslem group is known to have connections to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> that are
said to include some funding. Trinidad published reports say <PERSON>Abu
Bakr</PERSON> has visited <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> gained independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1962</DATE>. It
is an English-speaking country with a large populace from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   About a third of the people are Roman Catholic and a quarter are
Hindu. Only about <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> are Moslem, most of them <LOCATION>East Indians</LOCATION>.
There is great tension between the black and Indian Moslems.
   The rebel group in the past year has been occupying some
government land in western <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>. Recently, the government
had denied customs approval of a shipment of medical supplies
donated to Bakr by <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0020 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 0150EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-TrinidadUprising 6thLd-Writethru a0415 07-28 0910</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad Uprising, 6th Ld-Writethru, a0415,0936</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslems Said to Seize Trinidad Parliament, Hold Prime Minister</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 3 grafs to CORRECT name of group to Jamaat
al-Muslimeen, or Group of Moslems. Pickup 4th graf `An
announcer...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALISTER HUGHES</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Moslem militants said they
captured the prime minister and his Cabinet in the Parliament
building on <DATE>Friday</DATE> in this <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> capital. There were reports of
gunfire and explosions in the city.
   <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, head of the black rebel group, said in a nationwide
radio and TV broadcast late <DATE>Friday</DATE> that the government was toppled.
The claim could not be independently confirmed.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> had a station newscaster read a statement on
national television about <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> EDT in which <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> announced the
uprising by the group <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, which is Arabic for the
<ORGANIZATION>Group of Moslems</ORGANIZATION>. He claimed to be holding captive in <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>
the prime minister, <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON>.
   An announcer on Radio 610, <PERSON>Dennis McComie</PERSON>, quoted <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> as having
said on TV that ``the government has been overthrown'' and promised
elections within 90 days. Bakr did not mention what he had done
with the prime minister and his Cabinet.
   Bakr was quoted as saying his motive for moving against the
government was ``poverty and the destruction of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. ... We
will stop the incest, robbery, and drugs which there was no hope
for the present regime to stop.''
   There has been no official reaction from the government but late
``We would deplore any attempt to overthrow the democratic
government of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.''
   He also said, ``Our embassy reports gunfire in the vicinity of
the TV station. Explosions and gunfire have been heard downtown.''
   There were unconfirmed reports of casulaties in this city of
300,000 residents though <PERSON>Denny</PERSON> said he had no word about the
situation of Americans in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s smaller island of
<LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> is a popular vacation site.
   <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said there was no plan for violence, looting or retribution
against civilians, McComie told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Moslem group claims to have 200 to 250 members. They are
known as a small militant group with connections to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> that are
said to include some funding.
   The rebel statement said the Cabinet also was being held hostage
with <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 63, a veteran political leader, lawyer and
economist, but it could not be ascertained how many were inside the
Parliament building.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s ambassador to the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> told <ORGANIZATION>CBS Radio</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> that <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and the entire Cabinet, which had been
meeting at the time, were believed in the custody of the rebels.
   A radio station in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, government-owned <ORGANIZATION>National
Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION>, said that police headquarters in downtown
<LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> also had been blown up <DATE>Friday</DATE> by the rebels. The
rebels are based in <LOCATION>St. James</LOCATION>, outside the capital, and near police
headquarters.
   McComie said the central police station was on fire and there
had been several explosions that he assumed was ammunition. No one
was trying to put the fire out and it was spreading to surrounding
structures, he said, adding that it appeared headed for the
telephone company.
   Trinidadian <PERSON>James Fadelle</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> said he had spoken with a
friend in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> by telephone earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>.
   ``They're all locked up in their houses. They cannot go
outside,'' <PERSON>Fadelle</PERSON> said. He added that his friend, <PERSON>Peter Lambie</PERSON>,
had told him some civilians had been killed in the downtown area
and two police stations had been blown up.
   McComie said he was in the street by the radio station at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME>
when he heard gunshots inside <ORGANIZATION>Red House</ORGANIZATION>, which is the parliament
building. He said he returned safely to the station, but two gunmen
entered and set fire to the engineering department.
   McComie said radio employees were able to extinguish the fire.
   ``We can see people in the streets with guns,'' he said.
   The leader, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>, is a former police officer in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. Little
is known about him. Trinidad published reports say he spent some
time in <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, the larger of the two islands in the nation of
just off the northeast coast of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>
gained independence from <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1962</DATE>. It is an English-speaking
country with a large populace from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>.
   About a third of the people are Roman Catholic and a quarter are
Hindus. Only about <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> are Moslem.
   The island in recent years has suffered from a recession, with
closing of oil refineries, devaluation of the local currency and a
new, unpopular <PERCENT>15 percent</PERCENT> value-added tax, according to locals.
   The rebel group in the past year has been occupying some
government land in western <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>, creating controversy and
tensions on the island.
   The 1,500-member army has not entered into the fray yet, and is
said to be in northwestern <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.
   The broadcast statement said the rebels were in touch with the
army but it was not known what that signified.
   The police force on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> has about 5,000 members.
   McComie said he and his crew had locked themselves inside the
building and considered themselves ``in considerable danger.''
   Although station personnel felt in danger, they continued to
broadcast a live broadcast of a soccer game at the national stadium
in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>.
   A security guard at the <ORGANIZATION>Trinidad Guardian</ORGANIZATION> said the newspaper
building had been evacuated. He said that most likely there would
not be a <DATE>Saturday</DATE> edition.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0051 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 0814EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Bakr-Profile 1stLd-Writethru   07-28 0414</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bakr-Profile, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0475,0425</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Leader Has Fought With Government for Years</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs last graf, `Most East...' with 1 graf to CORRECT
description of island's population. No pickup. Abu Bakr is
pronounced AH-boo BAH-kuhr.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With PM-Trinidad-Uprising, Bjt</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, the Moslem leader whose
rebels captured the prime minister and his Cabinet in a coup
attempt, has been fighting with the government for years.
   Most recently, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> has been involved in a dispute over medical
supplies and pharmaceuticals reportedly donated by <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and
prohibited by customs agents from entering the country.
   One of the first things <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> did after taking the leaders
captive was accuse the government of refusing to let him distribute
free medicine to the poor people of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>.
   Members of his sect, <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, have long been
perceived by many Trinidadians as violent outlaws, although they
proclaim moralistic motives for their actions.
   Bakr, in his mid-40s, founded <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, Arabic for
``Group of Moslems,'' six years ago.
   He has said he does not recognize ``man's laws,'' but only ``the
law of almighty Allah.''
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, he said he understood ``the present suffering of the
people'' and that Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON> had been
overthrown by God.
   ``God has removed him,'' <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said on government television.
``No man, including me, has power. ... He gave us victory over the
prime minister.''
   Bakr, his 200 to 250 followers and their wives and children live
on a commune in western <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, police raided the commune, seizing weapons and
ammunition and arresting 34 members of the sect on charges of
larceny, robbery, illegal possession of weapons, rape and murder.
   Bakr, a former policeman, said then his vigilantes were waging a
war against ``the menace of cocaine.''
   On <DATE>Friday</DATE>, he said, ``We will stop the incest, robbery, and
drugs which there was no hope for the present regime to stop.''
   Moslems make up <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> of the population of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, a former British colony just off the northeast coast of
<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. Of the nation's 1.3 million people, about <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT> are
of African descent and the same proportion is of East Indian
descent.
   Most of the <LOCATION>East Indians</LOCATION> are Hindu. Most of the <LOCATION>Africans</LOCATION> are
Roman Catholic or Protestant. The nation's small Moslem population
is mostly East Indians with some <LOCATION>Africans</LOCATION>. But the black Moslem
population has grown since the black power movement began 20 years
ago, and <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s sect is the largest among them.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900804-0064 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-90 1110EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad-Uprising Bjt   08-04 0816</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad-Uprising, Bjt,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coup Attempt Further Damages Island's Economy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ A Moslem zealot's attempt to
overthrow the government, and the burning and looting that
accompanied it, have staggered <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> after three decades of
stable democracy.
   The rebels surrendered <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and the six-day coup attempt
ended with the safe release of the hostages, but the casualty toll
in the assault and subsequent violence was at least 38 dead and 150
wounded.
   Now Trinidadians face food and gasoline shortages, economic
disruption from a week of paralyzing curfews and the devastation
left by looters and arsonists.
   This racially and ethnically diverse nation known for sun and
calypso also must deal with tensions created by the violent effort
to destroy a democracy that has endured since independence from
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   ``As a sociologist, I know that conflict and crisis can either
splinter groups or unify them; it's never in-between,'' said
<PERSON>Anthony Maingot</PERSON>, who was born in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and is a <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> expert
   The coup attempt by <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, leader of a commune of 250 to 350
Moslems, began <DATE>July 27</DATE>.
   Bakr and his followers, most of whom are poor and black,
attacked police headquarters with explosives and seized Prime
Minister <PERSON>N.R. Robinson</PERSON> and other government officials in <ORGANIZATION>Parliament
House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Other members of Jamaat-al-Muslimeen simultaneously invaded the
state television complex a mile away and took employees hostage.
   Bakr's immediate demands were the prime minister's resignation
and elections within 90 days.
   ``I don't know that they planned beyond taking <ORGANIZATION>Red House</ORGANIZATION>,'' the
parliament building, said Col. <PERSON>Joe Theodore</PERSON>, who led the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>
and <ORGANIZATION>Tobago Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> in the crisis. ``He went in with a
half-baked plan.''
   The sports and culture minister, <PERSON>Jennifer Johnson</PERSON>, one of the
hostages, said the rebels were convinced they could improve
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> by establishing a fundamentalist Moslem state. Bakr, whose
newspaper had attacked ``satanic'' <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and International Monetary
Fund economic treatment of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, promised to help the poor.
   There were no signs of popular support for <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s attempt to
overthrow th prime minister.
   Robinson trails in public opinion polls and elections are due
next year.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> has had a boom-to-bust economy over the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>
tied to the world price of oil, its main source of wealth.
   The <DATE>1970s</DATE> oil boom brought prosperity and gave Trinidadians the
highest standard of living in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>. The bottom fell out of
the oil market in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s gross national product,
the value of all goods and services, has dropped <PERCENT>41 percent</PERCENT> in
eight years.
   Robinson led the new <ORGANIZATION>National Alliance for Reconstruction</ORGANIZATION> to a
landslide in <DATE>1986</DATE> with promises of recovery, ousting the <ORGANIZATION>People's
National Movement</ORGANIZATION>, which had been in power since colonial days.
   He has tried to diversify the economy, partly by expanding
tourism, to which the island was largely indifferent during the oil
boom. Unpopular austerity measures demanded by the <ORGANIZATION>IMF</ORGANIZATION> in return
for loans included wage freezes, new taxes, public employee layoffs
and devaluations that cut the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> dollar's value from about <MONEY>42
cents</MONEY> to 24.
   Officials say the economy has shown signs of recovery, but that
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s reserved personal style and an unraveling of his
coalition weakened the government.
   ``There is discontent in the country,'' government spokesman
<PERSON>Gregory Shaw</PERSON> said. ``Apparently, he (<PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>) took this as a sign
that the people were ready to revolt, but that is not the way
Trinidadians change government.''
   Much of downtown <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> was looted, prompting
international assistance that began with food shipments last week
from <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
   Tourism and foreign investment are expected to suffer.
   ``We will have to make an effort to win people's confidence,''
<PERSON>Shaw</PERSON> said.
   There were signs of strained ethnic relations during the
violence. Looters shouted epihets at Arab store owners and Moslems
were the targets of anger.
   Most of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s 1.3 million people are Hindu or Christian,
each representing more than <PERCENT>40 percent</PERCENT>. Moslems make up about <PERCENT>6
percent</PERCENT> and, among them, <LOCATION>East Indians</LOCATION> outnumber the blacks 20 to 1.
   Many East Indians scorn black Moslems as a sect outside the
mainstream Islamic community, an attitude resented by the <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> and
his followers.
   Confidence in <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s government could be undermined by the
fact that such a small group was able to cripple the nation.
   Abu <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s sect had been involved in court cases and with
police. It was under surveillance and police spokesman <PERSON>Winston
Cooper</PERSON> said ``the Libyan connection was established.''
   Authorities say sect members received money and training from
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, although there is no evidence <PERSON>Moammar Gadhafi</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>'s
leader, was linked to the coup attempt.
   <PERSON>Raffique Shah</PERSON>, managing editor of The Mirror, said he hoped
other would-be rescuers of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> would learn from <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s attempt
and ``see the futility of such action.''
   As the week ended, turmoil in another land offered some hope to
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. The Iraqi invasion of <LOCATION>Kuwait</LOCATION> pushed oil prices up.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0102 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 1610EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Caribbean-Moslems     07-28 0459</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Caribbean-Moslems,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>About 400,000 Moslems Scattered Across Caribbean</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Trinidad, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KERNAN TURNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SAN JUAN, Puerto Rico (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly 400,000 Moslems make the
<LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> their home, but most are East Indians who disdain the
radical politics of black Moslems like those who are holding
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s government hostage.
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, black <PERSON>Moslem Abu Bakr</PERSON> took over <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> and
threatened to kill the prime minister and much of his Cabinet.
   Bakr is a fundamentalist who has developed strong support from
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s poor black community. His <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION> sect has
an eight-acre commune in western <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>, where more than 250
men, women and children live. There is a large mosque, day care
center, school and kitchens for the homeless.
   Bakr has close ties with <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and has often stated that Islamic
principles must dominate society.
   But few East Indian Moslems support views like <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s and
tensions between Moslems of East Indian and African descent _ two
groups that rarely mix _ have been high.
   Many East Indians consider the black Moslems political
opportunists inspired more by the black power movement than by
traditional Islam. <PERSON>Stokely Carmichael</PERSON>, the black power advocate of
the <DATE>1960s</DATE> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, was born in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.
   Among the region's political leaders, prominent Moslems include
East Indian President <PERSON>Noor Hassanali</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and Prime Minister
<PERSON>Hamilton Green</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION>, a black who converted to Islam in the
<DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   The first Moslems came to the region to work in the sugar cane
fields, either as black slaves in the <DATE>1700s</DATE> or as indentured
servants from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 100 years later.
   Now domed mosques can be found on a dozen <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> islands, but
the heaviest concentrations of Moslems are on the islands of
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> and in <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Suriname</LOCATION> on the South
American mainland.
   ``One of the region's strongest religious trends today is the
movement toward Islam among blacks,'' says freelance writer <PERSON>Larry
Luxner</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>San Juan</LOCATION>. In the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE>, many blacks
have converted to Islam.
   Luxner, who has written extensively on Moslems in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>,
estimates that Trinidad-Tobago and <LOCATION>Suriname</LOCATION> each have 100,000
Moslems and <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> 120,000.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> is mostly a Hindu and Christian nation of
1.3 million people. About <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT> of the population is Moslem,
with those of East Indian and African descent each make up <PERCENT>40
percent</PERCENT> of the Moslem population.
   Writing in the Arabic magazine <LOCATION>Aramco World</LOCATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Luxner</PERSON> said
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> had 85 mosques, <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> 133 and <LOCATION>Suriname</LOCATION>, formerly Dutch
<LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION>, 150. He said <PERCENT>25 percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Suriname</LOCATION>'s 400,000 people were
Moslem, the highest percentage in any country in the <LOCATION>Western
Hemisphere</LOCATION>.
   There are also 2,500 Moslems in <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>, most of them
Palestinians who arrived between <DATE>1958</DATE> and <DATE>1962</DATE>, <PERSON>Luxner</PERSON> said.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900731-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-90 0033EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad 5thLd-Writethru a0746 07-31 0918</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0746,0947</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hostage Prime Minister Reports Trinidad Accord Reached</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 7 grafs to UPDATE with further elaboration of how
announcement made. Picks up 6th pvs, `The announcement ...'
^LaserPhotos POS4,5</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R.
Robinson</PERSON> and the chief negotiator for his Moslem extremist captors
said <DATE>Monday</DATE> that they had reached agreement to end a 4-day-old
hostage siege.
   Robinson, other Cabinet ministers and lawmakers were among 41
hostages reported held by the black Moslems, who stormed the
Parliament building and the government television station on <DATE>Friday</DATE>
in a coup attempt. Robinson suffered gunshot wounds in both feet.
   Word of the accord came in telephone call to <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> journalist
<PERSON>Tony Fraser</PERSON> from inside <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and was not immediately
announced to the nation.
   <PERSON>Selwyn Richardson</PERSON>, the justice and national security minister,
said in the call that the agreement called for <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s immediate
resignation, with elections to be held within 90 days.
   <PERSON>Richardson</PERSON> said the government granted amnesty to rebel leader
<PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON> and his followers in the revolt, which has left at least
nine people dead and led to looting on this island-nation of 1.3
million residents.
   The official said, however, that the agreement was contingent
``upon the safe return of all members of Parliament'' now held
hostage.
   It was unclear when the hostage release might occur.
   The announcement came hours after government and military
spokesmen said negotiations with the radical Moslem group had
collapsed.
   Earlier <DATE>Monday</DATE>, security forces exchanged gunfire with the
rebels at both the parliament building and the state-run television
station, the two buildings were hostages were being held.
   Speaking from inside <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> late <DATE>Monday</DATE>, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said the
agreement was reached after ``very difficult bargaining.''
   The prime minister said he instructed Col. <PERSON>Joe Theodore</PERSON>, head of
the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Tobago Defense Force</ORGANIZATION>, to ``make necessary
arrangements for the evacuation (of hostages and rebels) as soon as
possible.''
   Chief rebel negotiator <PERSON>Bilal Abdullah</PERSON>, speaking next on the
telephone, said: ``I wish to totally corroborate what Prime
Minister <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> has just said.''
   The rebels claim <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s government is corrupt and
responsible for widespread poverty in this once oil-rich country.
They claimed on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to have wired <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> with explosives and
threatened to blow him up if a rescue attempt was made.
   Government spokesman <PERSON>Gregory Shaw</PERSON> said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> was shot in both
feet and <PERSON>Richardson</PERSON> was shot in one leg when rebels stormed
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Army</ORGANIZATION> spokesman Maj. <PERSON>Dave Williams</PERSON> reported that the Moslems were
armed with AK-47 assault rifles, pistols and grenades.
   In the first official casualty count, <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said at least
nine people had died in the fighting since <DATE>Friday</DATE>. He said Anglican
negotiator <PERSON>Knolly Clarke</PERSON> told him additional bodies were inside the
parliament building, but it was not known how many.
   The two sides nearly reached agreement earlier <DATE>Monday</DATE> but a
government official said negotiations stalled over conditions for
releasing the hostages, who include eight Cabinet ministers.
   <PERSON>Shaw</PERSON> said 41 hostages were being held and about 100 rebels were
involved in the siege.
   He said 16 hostages, including the government ministers, were
being held in the parliament building. The remaining 25 hostages
are all employees of the government TV station, he said.
   Among the dead were six rebels, two police officers and one
civilian, <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said. Six rebels were known to be wounded.
<PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said three soldiers were wounded, none seriously.
   The <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> there are no
plans for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military intervention in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. Deputy spokesman
<PERSON>Richard Boucher</PERSON> refused comment on reports of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military
maneuvers in the area, but suggested a military solution was ruled
out.
   <PERSON>Boucher</PERSON> said none of the estimated 6,000 Americans living in
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and neighboring <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> were reported hurt.
   He criticized <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>'s involvement, saying the radical North
African Arab nation trained Trinidadian insurgents. But he said no
apparent direct link existed between <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and the hostage-taking
in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.
   Shaw and <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> called a news conference hours after a gun
battle between security forces and rebels at the state-run <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> Television complex.
   <PERSON>Williams</PERSON> said rebels fired on troops in an apparent attempt to
escape the TV complex. ``We were fired upon; we fired back,'' he
said. ``We won the firefight. They withdrew.''
   Three buildings in the area were set ablaze, witnesses said.
   Sporadic gunfire also broke out at the parliament building,
about a mile away, where the ministers were held. The army said no
attempt was made to storm either building.
   Army chief Col. <PERSON>Ralph Brown</PERSON> said he did not think the hostages
suffered casualties.
   <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> it sent 120 soldiers to neighboring <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION>
to assist <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> if needed.
   Bakr, a former policeman who converted to Islam in <DATE>1980</DATE>, founded
<ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, which means the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION> in Arabic, in
<DATE>1984</DATE>. The group is believed to number 250 to 300.
   <ORGANIZATION>Shaw</ORGANIZATION> said a <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> to noon curfew would remain in effect
islandwide despite a ``significant diminishing'' in looting, which
caused an estimated <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> damage to downtown stores.
   In a statement read on state radio, <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Embassy</ORGANIZATION> spokeswoman
<PERSON>Lucy Hall</PERSON> urged all American tourists in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> to obey the
curfew.
   Caribbean leaders gathering in <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, for a
conference added regional security to their agenda because of
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>. Heads of state and other government leaders
from the 13 member nations will open the <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Economic
Community</ORGANIZATION> conference on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Robinson easily won the <DATE>1986</DATE> parliamentary elections. Under the
constitution, the next elections don't have to be held until <DATE>1991</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0122 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 2028EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad-Reax     07-28 0561</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad-Reax,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Caribbean Leaders Condemn Coup Attempt, Consider Assistance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Trinidad, Bjt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>KINGSTON, Jamaica (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Caribbean leaders <DATE>Saturday</DATE> condemned
the attempted overthrow of the government of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>.
<LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> put their armies on alert in case <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s
government asks for help.
   Several Caribbean heads of state and government officials were
in <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> to attend a summit of the <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean Economic Community</ORGANIZATION>.
The meeting starts <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N. Robinson</PERSON>, who has been held
hostage since <DATE>Friday</DATE> by black Moslem rebels in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s capital, is an influential figure within the community
and had planned to attend the summit.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, with a population of 1.3 million, is the
second largest member after <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> in the 13-nation Caribbean
community, which groups 11 island nations as well as <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Belize</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Percival J. Patterson</PERSON>, acting prime minister of <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION>, said
his country's defense force was being readied in the event the
community was asked to provide military assistance.
   ``The army has been placed on full alert,'' <PERSON>Patterson</PERSON> said after
a meeting in <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION> with other <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> leaders who had arrived
early for the summit.
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Erskine Sandiford</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> said his island
nation's army had also been placed on alert.
   ``<LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> supports democratic government, and where such
governments are overthrown or threatened by illegal means, we will
not support this,'' <PERSON>Sandiford</PERSON> said. ``If any request is made we
will consider assistance.''
   In <LOCATION>Dominica</LOCATION>, Prime Minister <PERSON>Eugenia Charles</PERSON> called for an end to
the takeover attempt.
   ``We cannot allow this nonsense,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Charles</PERSON>, who asked
for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military intervention in <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> in <DATE>1983</DATE> after a bloody
coup there.
   Troops from the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> community provided token support for
the invading <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> forces, which ousted the Marxist military junta
that took power after killing Prime Minister <PERSON>Maurice Bishop</PERSON> and
several government ministers.
   <PERSON>Lynden Pindling</PERSON>, prime minister of the <LOCATION>Bahamas</LOCATION>, also pledged
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> ``to render whatever assistance'' possible if <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s
government asks for help from the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> organization.
   Pindling did not indicate, however, whether his administration
was willing to consider military assistance.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s foreign minister, <PERSON>Sahadeo Basdeo</PERSON>, who had led a
delegation to pre-summit discussions in <LOCATION>Kingston</LOCATION>, said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
<TIME>afternoon</TIME> that he would attempt to return home to assess the
situation.
   ``We are pleading with the rebels to free the prime minister and
to talk about their problems,'' <PERSON>Basdeo</PERSON> said. ``We are pleading for
common sense and rationality to prevail, and for a restoration of
democracy.''
   In <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>, Acting Foreign Minister <PERSON>Edden Shand</PERSON>, who was
released by the rebels <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, made a statement on radio opposing
any foreign military intervention.
   In <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and national security
adviser <PERSON>Brent Scowcroft</PERSON> were ``following the situation carefully,''
said deputy press secretary <PERSON>Alixe Glen</PERSON>.
   In <LOCATION>Caracas</LOCATION>, the Venezuelan government said it would not
recognize any rebel government in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, a former
British colony of two islands which lies off <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>'s coast.
   ``<LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> ... energetically rejects this attempt to overthrow
the constitutional government,'' said the statement released
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> by the government news agency <ORGANIZATION>Venpres</ORGANIZATION>.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> is one of 48 members of the <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>, an
association of <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and its former colonies. In <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION> secretary general on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> called the attempted
coup ``unwelcome and unacceptable.''
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Brian Mulroney</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, another <ORGANIZATION>Commonwealth</ORGANIZATION>
member, called for the immediate release of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and other
government hostages.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900730-0118 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-30-90 2111EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-US-Trinidad 2ndLd-Writethru   07-30 0535</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-US-Trinidad, 2nd Ld-Writethru,a0683,480</SECOND>
<HEAD>US Rules Out Military Intervention in Trinidad</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS graf 6: ``Aronson, who,'' to identify second minister;
SUBS 9th graf: ``As in,'' to delete reference to rebel curfew.
Trinidad curfew is a government measure</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Trinidad Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GEORGE GEDDA</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Monday</DATE> there are no
plans for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military intervention to bring an end to the
Moslem-led insurrection against the elected government in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.
   While refusing comment on reports of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> military maneuvers in
the area, deputy spokesman <PERSON>Richard Boucher</PERSON> suggested that a
military solution had been ruled out.
   At the same time, <PERSON>Boucher</PERSON> criticized <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>'s involvement with
the rebels, saying it has provided some training for the
insurgents. But he said there was no apparent direct link between
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and hostage-taking which occurred last <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, the leader of a Moslem sect, launched the coup attempt
by seizing the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> and capturing
Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R. Robinson</PERSON> and about 40 other hostages.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and one other goverment minister were believed to have
been shot in the leg early in the coup attempt, and both have been
getting medical attention, said <PERSON>Bernard W. Aronson</PERSON>, assistant
   Trinidad government spokesman <PERSON>Gregory Shaw</PERSON> identified the second
victim as Justice Minister <PERSON>Selwyn Richardson</PERSON>, and said both men
were in stable condition. <ORGANIZATION>Shaw</ORGANIZATION> said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> had been shot in both
feet, not the legs
   <PERSON>Aronson</PERSON>, who spoke in an interview on the ``MacNeil-Lehrer
NewsHour'' on the <ORGANIZATION>Public Broadcasting System</ORGANIZATION>, also said people were
killed in the coup attempt but said the department did not have a
figure on the casualties. He said none of them was a high-ranking
government official, but he declined to identify the victims
further.
   The <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> crisis has some of the earmarks of the situation in
<LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> <DATE>seven years ago</DATE> when a radical leftist movement took power.
In that case, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and several other <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
countries decided to oust the radicals.
   As in <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION>, the insurgents have shown a willingness to use
extremist methods to advance their cause.
   In both <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, there were signs of involvement by
anti-American elements from abroad. In <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION>, the leadership
there had close links to <LOCATION>Cuba</LOCATION> while in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> has been
allied with the rebels. Also, in both cases, a major concern of
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> has been the well being of thousands of Americans
residing in the two countries.
   But a major difference between the two situations is that
whereas virtually all of the Americans in <LOCATION>Grenada</LOCATION> were students at
a medical school, the 6,000 Americans in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> are dispersed
around the island and are less vulnerable to a mass hostage-taking.
   The international political climate also has undergone a
dramatic transformation since <DATE>1983</DATE>, a period when Cold War tensions
were at a peak.
   There is little indication that the events in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> will have
an impact beyond that country's borders. This was not the case in
asked for the dispatch of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> troops.
   Beyond that, American officials said government officials in
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> have indicated a desire to resolve the crisis without
outside help.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900802-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-90 0003EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad 7thLd-Writethru a0801 08-02 0943</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad, 7th Ld-Writethru, a0801, a0793,0977</SECOND>
<HEAD>Coup Leader, 112 Trinidad Militants Surrender, Free 46 Hostages</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS throughout to UPDATE with deputy prime minister saying
rebels had surrendered unconditionally and Robinson still prime
minister; DELETES outdated material. No pickup</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos POS100,101, LaserColor POS201</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Coup leader <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON> and 112
militant Moslem followers surrendered <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> and freed 46
hostages they seized five days earlier in a failed bid to overthrow
the government, officials said.
   State radio said a wounded hostage freed on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> died on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> in a hospital. That raised the death toll in the uprising
to at least 10.
   Deputy Prime Minister <PERSON>Winston Dookeran</PERSON> said the rebels, who
appeared not to have any significant support among the people,
``surrendered unconditionally'' and were under heavy guard at an
army base.
   He said they would face ``the appropriate charges,'' but did not
elaborate.
   Dookeran told reporters that Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R. Robinson</PERSON>
had not resigned, as he had offered to while held hostage.
   ``Prime Minister <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> is the prime minister of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Dookeran</PERSON> said. ``There is no intention to resign.''
   ``We have made no deals with this extremist group,'' said
<PERSON>Dookeran</PERSON>, who was held hostage on the first day of the coup attempt.
   Bakr released Dookeran on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, saying he wanted the deputy
prime minister to head a caretaker government that would hold new
elections in the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation.
   The attempted coup began <DATE>Friday</DATE> when armed rebels stormed the
state television station and the Parliament building, taking top
government officials and other captives.
   Bakr had demanded the resignation of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, whom he accused
of corruption.
   The 63-year-old prime minister was freed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and
hospitalized for treatment of a leg wound suffered in the takeover
as well as exhaustion and glaucoma.
   Bakr blamed <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> for widespread poverty in this former
British colony of 1.3 million people. Bakr was among the rebels who
surrendered at the television station, where the first group of
hostages was freed.
   Government spokesman <PERSON>Gregory Shaw</PERSON> said 113 rebels, including
<PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>, took part in the coup. He said 46 hostages held at <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>
and the TV building one mile away were released <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   Shaw and army spokesman Maj. <PERSON>Dave Williams</PERSON> said all hostages and
rebels had been evacuated and taken to separate army bases.
   State radio identified the former hostage who died Wednesdey as
<PERSON>Leo des Vignes</PERSON>, a junior minister. It said he died of a heart
attack in the hospital after being shot in the heel during the
takeover.
   The rebels released him on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, the broadcast said.
   The radio said heavy gunfire was reported <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> in
<LOCATION>Champs Fleurs</LOCATION>, about 10 miles east of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>. There was no
official explanation, but soldiers have been firing blank bullets
to scatter would-be looters for several days.
   The 29 captives at the TV station were all station employees.
The remaining 17 hostages at the Parliament building included seven
Cabinet ministers.
   In a live broadcast, state radio described the haggard-looking
captives filing out of the television station, one by one.
   Soldiers searched each one in the street, because the militants
had claimed at one point to have wired the captives with explosives
and threatened to blow them up.
   After the prisoner release, witnesses said about 50 rebels left
the television building, dropped their weapons and surrendered to
soldiers.
   Witnesses said <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> emerged wearing a fez, a white tunic and
white trousers. Like the other rebels, he dropped his gun and put
his hands behind his head.
   After boarding an army bus, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> shouted: ``Allahu akhbar!'' or
God is great.
   Hostages began leaving the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building at <TIME>5:10 p.m. EDT</TIME>.
The first to leave was a woman who held a white handkerchief to her
face.
   An army truck rolled up to the red, colonial-style building to
provide cover for soldiers who escorted her down the street.
   A few minutes later, the finance minister, <PERSON>Selby Wilson</PERSON>,
emerged, followed by another man who had a white handkerchief tied
across his face. The two men walked unescorted to a security van.
   The hostages walked along a sidewalk to a security area at the
end of the street, where they emptied their pockets and were
searched before getting onto an army bus. Some of the hostages
jogged down the street; others walked.
   Justice Minister <PERSON>Selwyn Richardson</PERSON>, reportedly shot in the leg
during the Parliament takeover, walked with a noticeable limp.
Applause broke out as he boarded the bus.
   State radio said the rebels were taken to army headquarters at
Chaguerames in <LOCATION>northwest Trinidad</LOCATION> and the freed hostages to <PERSON>Camp
Ogden</PERSON>, an army base about five miles west of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>.
   A local reporter who spoke with the former hostages at Camp
<PERSON>Ogden</PERSON> said they told him they had not eaten since <DATE>Friday</DATE> but were
otherwise OK. They were all undergoing medical exams in a tent.
   At <ORGANIZATION>Ogden Camp</ORGANIZATION>, freed hostage <PERSON>Grensell Kissoon</PERSON>, told a reporter,
``I'm glad to be alive.''
   TV station worker <ORGANIZATION>Raul Board</ORGANIZATION> held onto a post, saying he feared
he might faint from hunger. ``You know why I'm holding the post?
I'm afraid I might fall.''
   The capital was quiet <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. A 6 p.m.-to-noon curfew
remained in effect throughout most of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> following earlier
widespread looting.
   Bakr's <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION> group, which means the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION>
in Arabic, was founded in <DATE>1984</DATE> and is believed to have 250 to 300
members. It is also believed to have received financing from <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   Gargano had said 200 troops from neighboring Caribbean nations
were on neighboring <LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> and ``could be here in 45 minutes,''
but that <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and its sister island of <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> had not asked for
help.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0068 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 1158EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Trinidad-Uprising 5thLd-Writethru   07-28 1005</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trinidad-Uprising, 5th Ld-Writethru,a0489,1033</SECOND>
<HEAD>Black Moslems Take Prime Minister and Cabinet Hostage; Claims Coup</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 11 grafs to UPDATE with state of emergency,
buildings on fire, some ministers reported freed, comment from Bush
spox. Abu Bakr is pronounced AH-boo BAH-kuhr. Pickup 10th, `Bakr,
a...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ALISTER HUGHES</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ A group of black Moslems who
kidnapped the prime minister and some Cabinet members in a coup
attempt said <DATE>today</DATE> the captives may be harmed if the government
moves against a rebel-held TV station.
   One report said three people were killed in the first hours of
the rebel strike, which began <DATE>Friday</DATE> on the former British colony
of two islands that lie off the Venezuelan coast.
   ``The government has been overthrown,'' the coup leader, <PERSON>Abu
Bakr</PERSON>, said on government TV <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME> after the station was
seized by his followers.
   But government radio said <DATE>today</DATE> that a state of emergency had
been declared and that police were moving into the streets of the
capital of this southern <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation to restore order.
   Gunfire was heard in the direction of the television station,
located in northeastern <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> about two miles from the
Parliament building and the main police station. Buildings also
were burning in eastern <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>.
   Education Minister <PERSON>Clive Pantin</PERSON> said on government radio that he
had not been captured by the rebels and that the mutineers had
already released two unidentified ministers and four civilians they
had been holding.
   The Barbados-based <ORGANIZATION>Caribbean News Agency</ORGANIZATION>, or <LOCATION>CANA</LOCATION>, said three
people had been killed as the coup attempt began with an explosion
at the police station and rebels bursting into <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> firing
weapons.
   It said a news reporter had seen the body of a woman <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>
worker in the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building, and it quoted witnesses as
saying they saw two bodies in front of the building.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, a <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> official said it appeared
``the active elements of the insurrection are limited to the
television station and the parliament building.''
   ``We understand there has been some looting'' in the streets,
``but nothing affecting the safety of our embassy or foreign
nationals,'' said the official, who spoke on condition of
anonymity. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s island of <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> is a popular vacation site
for Americans and others.
   In <LOCATION>Kennebunkport</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>National Security</ORGANIZATION>
Adviser <PERSON>Brent Scowcroft</PERSON> were ``following the situation carefully,''
said deputy press secretary <PERSON>Alixe Glen</PERSON>. She said the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
government had not yet received a request for international aid,
but would consider it once it arrives.
   Bakr, a former policeman who heads a group called <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat
al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, Arabic for the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION>, has said he doesn't
recognize ``man's law,'' only ``the law of almighty Allah.''
   The Moslem group is known to have connections to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> that are
said to include some funding. News reports say <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON> has visited
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   Bakr's group has an estimated 250 followers. The mostly Hindu
and Roman Catholic country of 1.3 million people has a 1,500-member
army and a 5,000-member police force.
   The <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> said earlier that the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> would
``deplore any attempt to overthrow the democratic government of
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>.''
   Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Alliance</ORGANIZATION> for
next elections are due in <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   British West <ORGANIZATION>Indies Airways</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>American Airlines</ORGANIZATION> canceled
commercial flights into <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>evening</TIME>. <ORGANIZATION>Piarco
International Airport</ORGANIZATION> remained under control of government security
forces but was closed early today.
   When <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> broadcast his claim of a takeover, he did not disclose
the whereabouts of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and the other captured officials. It
was not known how many Cabinet ministers were taken hostage with
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 63, a veteran political leader, lawyer and economist.
   But the news director at the captured government television
station went on the air <TIME>this morning</TIME> and said the prime minister
and the other officials were alive and being ``well treated.''
   The news director, <LOCATION>Jones Madeira</LOCATION>, said some of the officials
were being held at the TV station and others at the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>
building, <ORGANIZATION>Red House</ORGANIZATION>.
   But he warned that the television station's signals were being
tampered with and ``this could endanger the lives of those people
being held.''
   Roman Catholic Archbishop <PERSON>Anthony Pantin</PERSON> told government radio
he had spoken to <LOCATION>Madeira</LOCATION> by telephone.
   ``He asked me to emphasize the request not to interfere with the
television channels, because if they do something may happen,'' the
prelate said.
   Several government ministers were seen on the rebel-controlled
television. Government radio, the <ORGANIZATION>National Broadcasting Service</ORGANIZATION>'s
Radio 610, said the capital's police station was blown up and
burned out of control for hours.
   It said no one attempted to put out the fire, and there were
several explosions of what was assumed to be ammunition in the
station.
   Bakr first appeared on television at <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE> to announce
the uprising. He said his followers planned no violence, looting or
retribution against civilians, and promised ``free and fair''
elections within 90 days.
   Government radio said before dawn <DATE>today</DATE> that there had been some
looting and police had moved into the streets.
   Bakr, in his mid-40s, has been arrested several times in the
past on charges of contempt of court and illegal demonstrations.
   He lives with 200 to 250 followers, their wives and children in
a commune on the western side of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>. Members of the
sect, founded in <DATE>1980</DATE>, are widely perceived in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> as violent
outlaws, though the group's rhetoric is highly moralistic.
   In <DATE>1988</DATE>, police raided the commune, seizing weapons and
ammunition and arresting 34 members of the sect on charges of
larceny, robbery, illegal possession of weapons, rape and murder.
<PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said then his vigilantes were waging a war against ``the
menace of cocaine.''
   ``We will stop the incest, robbery, and drugs which there was no
hope for the present regime to stop,'' he said in <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s
broadcast.
   The rebel group in the past year has been occupying some
government land in western <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>. Recently, the government
had denied customs approval of a shipment of medical supplies
donated to Bakr by <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900729-0050 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-90 1529EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Trinidad-Glance     07-29 0354</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad-Glance,0351</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trinidad and Tobago at a Glance</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Trinidad, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
<TEXT>
   Here are some facts and figures on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>:
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900804-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-04-90 1638EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad     08-04 0586</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad,0606</SECOND>
<HEAD>Trinidad Prime Minister Said He was Gagged, Beaten by Moslem
Rebels</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Trinidad-Uprising, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R.
Robinson</PERSON> said he was gagged, beaten and shot in the leg by Moslem
fundamentalists who held him and other Cabinet ministers hostage in
an attempt to overthrow the government.
   ``I was incensed at the manner in which we were treated,''
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said in a television interview broadcast <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>. It
was his first public appearance since he was freed <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``We were roughed up, made to lie face down on the floor, our
pants down, legs tied ... unable to turn except with excrutiating
pain,'' he said.
   Robinson, whose right cheek was badly bruised, spoke from his
hospital bed to <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> television.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> spoke briefly of his five-day captivity inside the
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> chamber and of the Moslem insurgents who held Cabinet
members inside the building until they surrendered on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   ``I really do not wish to re-live those events at this
particular moment,'' he said. ``But it is a fact I was gagged; that
the gag was being pushed down my throat by a gun.''
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said the gag thrust down his throat caused him to
vomit. He said he was shot in the right leg after shouting
``Murderers! Torturers!'' and calling on his two-way radio to the
armed forces to storm the building.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said his leg ``is still in such a state that I cannot
use it.''
   The prime minister, who is losing his eyesight because of
glaucoma, was released by the rebels <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for health reasons.
   ``Now, I could have been out before on medical grounds, but I
was convinced that my duty was to stay with my colleagues until the
fate of all of us was certain,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> did not say whether he signed an agreement with the
rebels, who had insisted on his resignation and early elections as
conditions for the release of the hostages.
   Besides <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and his Cabinet, the rebels also held 26 other
hostages inside the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> Television station.
   Officials said an estimated 38 people were killed during the
coup attempt. Maj. <PERSON>Dave Williams</PERSON> said the government is still
trying to determine the count.
   <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, the leader of the Moslem radicals, and more than 100
of his followers were being held at the <LOCATION>Chaguaramas</LOCATION> military
headquarters. Lawyers were meeting <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to draw up charges
against them that could include murder, treason and kidnapping.
   On <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, one of <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s followers was killed in a shootout
with police.
   Police Inspector <PERSON>Winston Cooper</PERSON> said <PERSON>Njassane Omuaali</PERSON>, 21, was
killed during an exchange of gunfire and was among a ``band of
Moslems'' who fired on police.
   But <PERSON>Omuaali</PERSON>'s grandmother, <PERSON>Elaine Bailey</PERSON>, said her grandson, the
son of <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s first wife, was killed after police seized him.
   ``They grabbed him, kicked him down the stairs and killed him.
They shot him,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Bailey</PERSON>, 75, in a telephone interview.
   She said <PERSON>Omuaali</PERSON> was scheduled to return <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
where he was studying finance and accounting at <ORGANIZATION>Howard University</ORGANIZATION>
on a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> fellowship.
   In another development, <LOCATION>Guyana</LOCATION> sent 40 troops to <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> to
assist authorities. More than 100 other troops from <LOCATION>Jamaica</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Barbados</LOCATION> were assisting Trinidadian troops.
   A state of emergency remained in effect with a curfew in
<LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> from <TIME>6 p.m.</TIME> to <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> Soldiers and police were still
combing the city for any explosives that could have been left
behind in the coup attempt.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901004-0142 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-04-90 1945EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-UN-Trinidad     10-04 0509</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-UN-Trinidad,0612</SECOND>
<HEAD>Prime Minister of Trinidad Blames U.S. on Arms Purchase Dispute</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By VICTORIA GRAHAM</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>UNITED NATIONS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The prime minister of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>
said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities failed to tell his government
of arms purchases in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> by Moslem coup-plotters.
   ``If we had the information possessed by <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities in
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, this coup would have been avoided,'' Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur
N.R. Robinson</PERSON> told a news conference.
   Later, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. State Department</ORGANIZATION> official, requesting anonymity,
said, ``We did not withhold information which would have enabled
Prime Minister <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> to prevent the coup d'etat.''
   On <DATE>July 27</DATE>, Moslem militants stormed <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and the
government-run TV station and took the prime minister and more than
50 others hostage.
   The ensuing six-day siege and accompanying looting left 24
people dead and 500 wounded. <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> is a <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island nation
of 1.2 million people off northeast <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. The fighting caused
an estimated <MONEY>$60 million</MONEY> damage to the main shopping district in
<LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>.
   In answer to a question, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> said his government has
evidence the rebels had ties to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   ``In fact, the leader of the terrorist organization has
confessed openly about his visits and relations with <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.''
   He declined to say, however, whether the coup was backed by
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, saying the case was in the courts.
   Rebel leader <PERSON>Yasin Abu Bakr</PERSON>, a former policeman who converted to
Islam, and 113 followers were jailed to face charges of treason and
murder after the coup was suppressed. Saying it fearing that <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s
supporters might be plotting another attack, the government
extended a state of emergency until mid-November. The proclamation
gives security forces unrestricted rights of search and arrest.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, who was shot in the leg by the rebels, said in a
speech to the <ORGANIZATION>United Nations General Assembly</ORGANIZATION> that the coup was
launched by ``a new breed of fanatics claiming divine inspiration,
but acting rather under satanic impulse.''
   Robinson walked with a cane as he went to the podium at <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION>
headquarters.
   After his speech, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> told reporters that he would raise
the issue of exchanging information about security when he meets
President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> on <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   ``We must find out why there was not a proper transfer of
information,'' he said. ``We want to ensure that in the future,
more effective arrangements are made about information exchange.''
   He said it was common knowledge that some of those later
involved in the coup were buying weapons in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> with large
amounts of <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> currency and shipping the arms to the island
nation, a former British colony.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> knew about the arms purchases, he
said.
   ``Oh, yes,'' he said, ``there was much more information that
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> authorities had'' which was not passed along to his
government.
arrested an Moslem, <PERSON>Louis Haneef</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Pompano Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, on charges
of supplying assault rifles, ammunition and other equipment to the
coup leaders.
   But <PERSON>Jack Killorin</PERSON>, a spokesman for the bureau in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
said its agents were not aware of any contact between the man
buying the guns and <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> until after the coup attempt.
   ``Had it been known that the firearms were going to go to
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> authorities would have been notified,''
<PERSON>Killorin</PERSON> said. ``It simply was not known until <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> authorities
captured the arms and we matched them to the arms shipment in
<LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>.''
   ``We couldn't agree more with the prime minister that
governments should set up avenues of communication to crack down on
this gun running,'' he added.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900729-0071 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-29-90 1919EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Trinidad-Bakr 1stLd-Writethru a0764 07-29 0695</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad-Bakr, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0764,0715</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Leader Says Lavish Monument to Woman `Broke the Camel's
Back'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with two grafs to RESTORE first reference to Robinson;
pickup graf 3 `Speaking to...'</NOTE>
<NOTE>Eds: Abu Bakr is pronounced AH-boo BAH-kuhr</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TONY FRASER</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Black Moslem rebel <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, long
at odds with authorities, says their decision to spend <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> on
a memorial to a dead woman leader was the ``straw that broke the
camel's back.''
   Shortly after his followers seized Parliament house <DATE>Friday</DATE>, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>
commandeered the government television station and announced he had
overthrown Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur Robinson</PERSON> and was holding him
hostage with his Cabinet.
   Speaking to the country on television, he accused <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s
4-year-old government of mismanagement and corruption. He singled
out <ORGANIZATION>Robinson</ORGANIZATION>'s announcement on <DATE>June 23</DATE> that a monument would be
built in honor of <PERSON>Jean Miles</PERSON>, a senior public servant who died more
than a decade ago.
   ``That was the straw that broke the camel's back: the allocation
of <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> to create a concrete statue to this woman, while poor
people all over the country are starving,'' he said.
   Bakr, a broad-shouldered, 6-foot-2-inch, charismatic leader, has
long considered himself a spokesman for the poor.
   A former mounted policeman who converted to Islam while studying
in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> in the early <DATE>1980s</DATE>, <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> founded and has been the leader
for six years of the <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION> commune. It is on eight
acres of former swamp land on the western edge of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>,
the capital.
   The rebel leader, in his late-40s, is married and has a son and
daughter believed to be attending the <ORGANIZATION>University of Toronto</ORGANIZATION>. His
wife, <PERSON>Annisa</PERSON>, is an executive for the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Tobago
Industrial Development Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   Another major source of friction with authorities is the city
council's contention that <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> built his commune without a clear
title to the land.
   In the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, the late Prime Minister <PERSON>Eric Williams</PERSON>
donated the land to East Indian Moslems to build whatever they
wanted. But they never picked up the offer.
   Abu <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> returned from <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> in <DATE>1984</DATE> and grabbed the land,
saying his black Moslems had a right to it.
   He built a mosque in the center and living quarters for his 250
to 300 followers. Four major buildings include a kitchen for the
poor and a large school.
   The dispute came to a head in the <DATE>1980s</DATE> when <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> was jailed for
several weeks for contempt of court when he failed to answer
charges of illegal occupation brought by the council.
   Over the years, the commune has been raided by police looking
for arms and ammunition. They found a few rifles and small amounts
of ammunition.
   Three months ago, police and defense force soldiers seized a
portion of the commune where <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> was constructing a new building.
Bakr sought a court order to remove the troops.
   A week ago, <ORGANIZATION>High Court Judge Ivol Blackman</ORGANIZATION> ruled against Bakr.
   Another irritant was the government's recent refusal to
distribute free medical supplies and pharmaceuticals Bakr wanted to
donate to people of the island.
   He said he had received the supplies from a <ORGANIZATION>U.N.</ORGANIZATION> agency.
However, it was widely believed in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> that they came from
<LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>.
   Bakr is thought to receive financial support from <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and has
visited that North African country several times.
   He has also been highly critical of the government's record on
fighting drugs and even formed a paramilitary squad to raid drug
dealers. This earned him the enmity of the police.
   Moslems in mostly Hindu and <ORGANIZATION>Christian Trinidad</ORGANIZATION> make up <PERCENT>6 percent</PERCENT>
of the population of 1.3 million people.
   There are only a small number of black Moslems outside <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s
group. Most are East Indians, who consider the blacks as
opportunists guided by politics more than the <LOCATION>Koran</LOCATION>.
   A Moslem leader in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> who knew <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> when he converted to
Islam, said he was ``committed to social justice.''
   Hardon Salamat, head of the <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Region Islamic
Congregation</ORGANIZATION>, said in an interview that he thinks <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s action
resulted from ``years and years of frustration and government
harassment.''
   Salamat said <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s group receives financing from Moslems around
the world, including those in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Montreal</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900913-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-09-13-90 1803EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Trinidad     09-13 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trinidad,0368</SECOND>
<HEAD>Moslem Militants Appear in Court Amid Tight Security</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT GLASS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) - A magistrate ordered a delay
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> in the start of a hearing for <ORGANIZATION>Yasin Abu Bakr</ORGANIZATION> and 112 other
Moslem militants who captured the prime minister during a coup
attempt.
   Chief Magistrate <PERSON>Melville Baird</PERSON> granted a prosecution request
for an adjournment to allow more time to prepare its case. The
magistrate set <DATE>Sept. 25</DATE> as the new date for the preliminary
hearing.
   Bakr, 48, a former policeman, and the members of his <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat
al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION> (Society of Moslems) face the death penalty for
charges that include murder and treason.
   About two dozen female <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat</ORGANIZATION> supporters shouted ``Allah
akbar!'' (God is great) as <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> and 18 other prisoners filed into
the courtroom, where they were kept in a specially built iron cage
for the 45-minute proceedings.
   For security reasons, the remaining prisoners are to appear
later in four separate groups.
   Heavily armed soldiers in camouflage uniforms ringed the
converted gym in the western town of <LOCATION>Chaguaramas</LOCATION>, 10 miles outside
<LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION>, for the Moslems' first court appearance since the
six-day coup attempt ended <DATE>Aug. 1</DATE>.
   Wearing a white tunic and black fez, the Moslem leader bowed to
reporters and said: ``Morning to the press. Morning everybody.''
   Spectators were searched and scanned with metal detectors before
entering the courtroom. An armored tank was positioned outside.
   Prosecutor <PERSON>Theodore Guerra</PERSON> said the newly appointed head of the
prosecution team, <PERSON>Karl Hudson-Phillips</PERSON>, needed more time to prepare
his case. Defense attorney <PERSON>Nathaniel King</PERSON> had no objection.
   Bakr and his followers captured the Parliament and state-run
television station and seized Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R. Robinson</PERSON>
and more than 50 others, including several Cabinet members.
   The attack and subsequent looting left 24 dead. <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, 63,
was shot in the left leg. Bakr and his men are charged in
connection with eight deaths.
   Bakr had blamed <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s administration for widespread poverty
in this once oil-wealthy <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation off <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and its sister island of <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> remain under a state of
emergency, giving police wide powers of search and arrest, and a
nighttime curfew.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900731-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-31-90 1550EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Trinidad 5thLd-Writethru a0630 07-31 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trinidad, 5th Ld-Writethru, a0630,0573</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Prime Minister Freed, Others Remain Captives in Trinidad Standoff</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with nine grafs to CORRECT prime minister's initials,
ADDS that no details of release immediately available, background.
Picks up 11th pvs, `Bakr said...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By SUSANA HAYWARD</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Prime Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R.
Robinson</PERSON> was freed by his Moslem captors <DATE>today</DATE> but other officials
held hostage were not released, the government announced.
   Attorney General <PERSON>Anthony Smart</PERSON> gave no details of how and under
what conditions the prime minister, who had been shot in both feet
during the uprising, was freed. But the release of <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> alone
indicated the 5-day-old standoff between the government and Moslem
extremists was not over.
   ``We continue to pray for the safe return of the rest of the
hostages,'' Smart told state radio.
   He said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> was the only one of the 41 hostages released.
   Smart said <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>, who was freed at <TIME>1:20 p.m. EDT</TIME>, ``is in
good spirits.''
   The siege began <DATE>Friday</DATE> when radical Moslems led by <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>
stormed <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and the government-run television station in
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s capital city. Bakr has accused the government of
mismanagement.
   The release came after a day of conflicting reports over the
progress of negotiations to end the hostage siege, which has
plunged this <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> nation of 1.3 million residents off
northeast <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> into chaos.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> had said by telephone that he had
accepted an agreement under which he would resign and <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> and his
men would be granted amnesty.
   But government officials said <DATE>today</DATE> that no such agreement
existed and that <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> had made the statement under duress.
   <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON> said <DATE>earlier today</DATE> that the rebels agreed that <PERSON>Winston
Dookeran</PERSON>, the deputy prime minister, would replace <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> when he
steps down. Dookeran was released from the <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> building
<DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The interim government would be a coalition consisting of
representatives of all major political parties, along with <PERSON>Bakr</PERSON>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION> group.
   The group, which is believed to number 250 to 300, has blamed
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> for widespread poverty in this once-oil rich <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION>
nation near <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>. It has little support among the populace.
   Bakr is a former policeman who converted to Islam in <DATE>1980</DATE> and
has long considered himself a champion of the downtrodden. He
founde <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, which means the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION> in Arabic,
in <DATE>1984</DATE>.
   Robinson easily won parliamentary elections in <DATE>1986</DATE>. Under the
constitution, the next elections don't have to be held until <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Monday</DATE>, security forces exchanged gunfire with the rebels at
<ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION> and at the government television station. Three
buildings in and around the TV complex were set ablaze but no
injuries were reported.
   At least nine people _ six rebels, two police officers and a
civilian _ have been killed since the siege began, and the
instability has spawned massive looting in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, a
two-island nation of 1.3 million people. State radio said some
looters were shot <DATE>Monday</DATE> but gave no details.
   Bakr has ties to <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> and it is believed he has received
funding from that country. In a conversation with local radio
today, he said he had no regrets over what he had done.
   ``I hope we can settle it in love,'' he said.
   Asked if the siege could end in violence, he said, ``Everyone
will die at some time in their lives.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900730-0076 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-30-90 1527EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Trinidad 4thLd-Writethru a0537 07-30 0970</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trinidad, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0537,1006</SECOND>
<HEAD>Gunfire Breaks Out Near TV Station, Parliament</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 13 grafs to UPDATE with colonel's briefing,
negotiator saying peaceful solution likely. Pickup 9th pvs, `Attiba
said...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos POS1,2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAN SEWELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   PORT-OF-SPAIN, <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> (AP) _ Gunfire and explosions broke out
today around the government television station and <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>,
where Moslem extremists held the prime minister and 30 other people
hostage for a fourth day.
   Later today, an Anglican minister negotiating between the
government and the rebels said a settlement was likely.
   The heaviest shooting was centered on the television station,
whose employees were taken hostage <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Automatic rifle and
machine-gun fire was punctuated by what sounded like artillery
booms.
   One witness said he heard four explosions that sounded like
bombs.
   ``A major firefight is going on,'' said a diplomatic source, who
spoke on condition of anonymity.
   The shooting at the station appeared to be coming from two
directions, but it was not clear whether security forces had tried
to storm the building.
   Earlier, automatic weapons fire rang out near <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION>, about
a mile from the television station, where rebels seized Prime
Minister <PERSON>Arthur N.R. Robinson</PERSON> on <DATE>Friday</DATE>. Witnesses said they heard
what sounded like heavy artillery booms.
   A ham radio operator in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> said he monitored a radio
communication indicating security forces had stormed the television
station and were moving on <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>.
   But Col. <PERSON>Ralph Brown</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Trinidad-Tobago Defense Force</ORGANIZATION> denied
the station was attacked.
   He told reporters that troops had fired on the TV station when
the rebels tried to leave the building. ``Some of his men tried to
come out and we are not letting them out.''
   An Anglican minister who was negotiating between the rebels and
the government, the Rev. <PERSON>Knolly Clarke</PERSON>, also spoke with reporters
early this afternoon.
   When asked if a peaceful solution was likely, he said, ``Yes,
today. The end is in sight.''
   One of the rebels inside <ORGANIZATION>Parliament</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Kwasi Attiba</PERSON>, said by
telephone that a tentative agreement with the government had been
reached to end the siege.
   Attiba said the accord called for <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> to resign immediately
and be replaced by Deputy Prime Minister <PERSON>Winston Dookeran</PERSON>. Attiba
gave no indication when <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and other other hostages would be
released, and no government official could be reached to confirm
his report.
   An agreement was also reported <DATE>Sunday</DATE> by a television executive,
<PERSON>Jones Madeira</PERSON>, who was held at the station. He said in a telephone
interview that under the plan, <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> would turn over power to an
interim government, which would rule until elections in three
months.
   Robinson won the <DATE>1986</DATE> parliamentary elections by a landslide,
and the next elections are not scheduled until <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   The rebels claim <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>'s government is corrupt and
responsible for widespread poverty in this once oil-rich country.
They claimed <DATE>Saturday</DATE> to have wired <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> with explosives and
threatened to blow him up if a rescue attempt was made.
   Attiba said the gunfire at <LOCATION>Parliament</LOCATION> came from police ``who
have been attempting to thwart'' negotiations.
   Attiba said the rebels were holding eight government ministers
along with the prime minister.
   Energy Minister <PERSON>Herbert Atwell</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> the two sides were
far from a settlement. But <PERSON>Attiba</PERSON> said: ``We are very hopeful for
an amicable solution.''
   Security forces patrolled the capital with orders to shoot
looters on sight.
   <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, leader of a black Moslem commune, stormed Parliament
on <DATE>Friday</DATE> and captured <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and most of his Cabinet. Bakr is
believed backed by <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> but has little general support.
   Simultaneously, the rebels seized the government television
station and its employees.
   Unconfirmed reports said more than 20 people had been killed in
the fighting. A medical officer at the state hospital said <DATE>today</DATE> he
could confirm only five deaths, including that of a police officer.
   Fires burned in the capital of <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. There
was scattered gunfire and widespread looting. Convoys of cars and
pickup trucks were loading up with everything from looted powdered
milk to refrigerators, electric stoves and television sets.
   The government sent police and military patrols to re-establish
order and continued a nationwide curfew that was imposed <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Atwell, representing the government, appeared on national
television late <DATE>Sunday</DATE> with an official statement saying: ``I am in
no position to offer any hope that the situation will be resolved
speedily and-or amicably.''
   He confirmed reports that <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and Justice Minister <PERSON>Selwyn
Richardson</PERSON> had each been shot in the leg.
   State-run radio 610 said <PERSON>Nolli Clarke</PERSON>, an Anglican priest, was
the official mediator with help from Anglican Bishop <PERSON>Clive Abdullah</PERSON>
and Roman Catholic Archbishop <PERSON>Anthony Patin</PERSON>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Red Cross</ORGANIZATION> sent mobile units to take blood donations from
people too frightened to leave their homes.
   Radio 610 estimated damage downtown at <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> as thousands
of people looted stores, shopping centers, warehouses and
industrial plants.
   A spokeswoman for President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that American
citizens and tourists on <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> did not appear to be
in danger.
   ``Obviously we support the government and are coordinating
closely with them until the situation is resolved,'' a <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION> official said in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. The official did not want
to be identified.
   Bakr is a former policeman in his mid-40s who converted to Islam
in <DATE>1980</DATE> while living in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   He founded <ORGANIZATION>Jamaat al-Muslimeen</ORGANIZATION>, which means the <ORGANIZATION>Moslem Group</ORGANIZATION> in
Arabic, in <DATE>1984</DATE> and set up a commune on land he said had been
donated to Moslems by the late prime minister, <PERSON>Eric Williams</PERSON>.
   Bakr built a mosque, a school and a kitchen to feed the
homeless. Some 250 to 300 Moslems live there.
   Bakr has visited <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION> several times and is believed to have
received assistance from that country.
   He has said the coup was intended to stop ``poverty and the
destruction'' of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, which has high unemployment
and skyrocketing food prices.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900728-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-28-90 1906EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Bush 2ndLd-Writethru a0584 07-28 0599</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0584,620</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Voices Support for Besieged Leader of Trinidad</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Inserts grafs 9-10, ``Later, the State</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER CONNELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>KENNEBUNKPORT, Maine (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> expressed ``strong
support'' <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s prime minister, a captive of
black Moslem rebels who took over the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> island's parliament.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was spending the weekend relaxing at his
oceanfront <DATE>summer</DATE> home here, but he and national security adviser
<PERSON>Brent Scowcroft</PERSON> were kept abreast of the attempted coup, a
spokeswoman said.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, who spent the morning on the tennis courts and boating,
attended the wedding of a second cousin in <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>.
   Deputy press secretary <PERSON>Alixe Glen</PERSON> said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and Scowcroft were
``following the situation carefully'' in <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>, a
former British colony off the coast of <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION> that gained
independence in <DATE>1962</DATE>.
   ``We maintain our strong support for the Democratic government
of Prime Minister (<PERSON>Arthur</PERSON>) <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>,'' <PERSON>Ms. Glen</PERSON> said.
   ``It appears that no American citizens are in any danger. The
situation seems limited to one building,'' she said.
   <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> have not yet asked for help, but the <LOCATION>United
States</LOCATION> would consider the request if they do, she said.
   <PERSON>Robinson</PERSON> and several members of his cabinet were being held
hostage in the parliament in <LOCATION>Port-of-Spain</LOCATION> by rebels led by former
policeman <PERSON>Abu Bakr</PERSON>, leader of a Moslem sect that said it recognizes
no government but ``the law of almighty Allah.''
   Later, the <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> issued this written statement:
   ``We condemn yesterday's attempt by a violent extremist group to
overthrow the democratic government of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>. We call
upon the parties in this attempted coup to release the hostages
under their control and to surrender to the legislative
constitutional authority of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION>. This violent
attack on the government has no support from the people of <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Tobago</LOCATION> who have enjoyed a long tradition of democratic
government. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> fully supports the elected government
and is consulting closely with it and other interested governments
in the region.''
   An administration official who accompanied <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION> said
the army was still loyal to the prime minister and his
four-year-old government.
   On another international hotspot, <LOCATION>Liberia</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Ms. Glen</PERSON> said, ``The
situation has not changed. We're following it closely.''
   The beleaguered government of President <PERSON>Samuel Doe</PERSON> has been
under siege for weeks in that West African nation. Rebel leader
<PERSON>Charles Taylor</PERSON> claimed <DATE>Friday</DATE> to have established his own
government, even though street fighting continued.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, getting a weekend respite from the drawn out negotiations
with Democrats over the budget deficit, brought his wife, <PERSON>Barbara</PERSON>,
daughter, <PERSON>Dorothy LeBlond</PERSON>, and several grandchildren with him
<DATE>Friday</DATE> on the flight from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Pease Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Newington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.H.</LOCATION>
   He also gave his taciturn <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> nominee, <PERSON>David H.
Souter</PERSON>, a ride home to <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>. Before heading off to visit
his mother at a <LOCATION>Concord</LOCATION> nursing home, <PERSON>Souter</PERSON> said it felt ``damn
good'' to be back in the <ORGANIZATION>Granite State</ORGANIZATION>.
   This was the Bushes' third visit to their vacation home since
Memorial Day.
   President and <PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON> attended the wedding of a second cousin,
<PERSON>Ruben Andrus Holden</PERSON> V, 37, of <LOCATION>Marshfield</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass.</LOCATION>, to <PERSON>Pamela Anne
