<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880922-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-22-88 0242EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-AtlantaSkyline     09-22 0849</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Atlanta Skyline,0873</SECOND>
<HEAD>New Buildings Changing Atlanta's Skyline, Giving City Respect</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Thursday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new generation of skyscrapers is about to alter
the skyline of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, previously dismissed as sterile and
nondescript.
   Even homegrown architect <PERSON>John Portman</PERSON>, whose glass towers and
soaring atriums for years defined <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and who in the past
criticized post-modern architecture as a step backward, has given a
nod to the style in his latest project, a 60-story office building
planned for downtown <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   Much of the excitement over the pending transformation of the
capital of the <LOCATION>New South</LOCATION> started last fall with the opening of the
50-story <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> building. Officially called <ORGANIZATION>One Atlantic Center</ORGANIZATION>, it is
a slender, post-modern tower of stone with tall arched entryways
and Gothic finials, dramatically crowned by a 100-foot-high,
eight-sided copper pyramid topped by a golden lantern.
   Rush-hour traffic on Interstate 85 slows to a cautious crawl as
drivers gaze its way. At night, the lights in its crown command
attention from all over town. Architecture writers have used words
like ``gracious,'' ``truly wonderful,'' ``serene,'' ``imposing''
and ``glamorous'' to describe the tower.
   ``It certainly projects a vibrance to the rest of the world,''
said <PERSON>Roy Cooper</PERSON>, vice president for economic development with the
<ORGANIZATION>Atlanta Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's just beautiful. Everybody's
just staggered by it.''
   The tower is a dramatic departure from the glass boxes common in
modern architecture and contrasts with the sleek look of most of
the city's tallest buildings.
   Its influence shows up in at least three other skyscrapers going
up in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, and the design of the proposed Promenade skyscraper
complex was altered to complement the rose-colored <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> tower.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> architect <PERSON>John Burgee</PERSON>, whose firm designed the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>
building with design consultant <PERSON>Philip Johnson</PERSON>, won't take credit
for transforming <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s skyline. But he said the city's image,
as defined by the way it looks, is undergoing a change.
   ``<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> has been looking for its identity,'' <PERSON>Burgee</PERSON> said in a
telephone interview from his <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office. ``It's an historical
city (but) its architecture and image is not strictly historical.
You think of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and you think of `Gone With The Wind.' Now,
there is an attempt to come up with a visual image.
   ``We all know Peachtree Street, but you don't think of its
buildings,'' he said. ``Like in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, the Empire State
Building; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> building; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>TransAmerica</ORGANIZATION> building. Atlanta doesn't have that. It's moving
toward that, very definitely.''
   Burgee and <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> also are behind One Ninety One Peachtree
Tower, a post-modern skyscraper planned for downtown <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   Another planned project grouped in the ``Son of <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'' building
spurt is the Promenade in the tree-lined, historic Midtown section,
a complex of three office buildings and a hotel being developed by
<ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> and the Atlanta-based <ORGANIZATION>Landmarks Group</ORGANIZATION>.
   When unveiled last year, it was designed with an exterior of
glittering green glass. But when Promenade officials saw the
excitement over the nearby IBM Tower, its architects, <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Ventulett &amp; Stainback</ORGANIZATION>, redrew the plans to use rose glass above
rose-toned stone and topped with a gray steel spire.
   The most recently announced skyscraper is a downtown giant by
<PERSON>Portman</PERSON>, whose imprint is already deeply felt in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, primarily
through the <ORGANIZATION>Peachtree Center</ORGANIZATION> and the towering cylindrical <ORGANIZATION>Westin
Peachtree Plaza Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   Portman's new building is slated to begin construction next year
and, at 60 stories, will eclipse One <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> as the Southeast's
tallest building. Unveiling the design in <DATE>May</DATE>, <PERSON>Portman</PERSON> said it was
``respectful of the past but, like this city, is audacious and bold
and forward-looking _ the beginning of post-post-modern
architecture.''
   <PERSON>Dale Durfee</PERSON>, a professor of architecture at <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>, said
completion of the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> tower signaled the acceleration of a change
in the look of the city that began a decade ago.
   ``<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was pretty much plain vanilla,'' he said, ``with no
development of architectural significance.''
   Burgee echoed that appraisal, saying, ``It was pretty
nondescript. It might be anyplace. If they took you (to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>)
blindfolded and took off the blindfold, you wouldn't have a clue
where you are.''
   <PERSON>Durfee</PERSON> said <DATE>that 10 years ago</DATE>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was groping to form an
identity and had no demand for the type of buildings now are going
up.
   Today, however, companies want sophistication in their office
buildings, <PERSON>Durfee</PERSON> said, and corporate sponsorship of building
projects has changed the rules of skyscraper financing.
   Some say that all the building activity simply makes good
business sense.
   ``Sure, there's competitive prestige. Good architecture is good
business,'' said <PERSON>Truman Hartshorn</PERSON>, chairman of the geography
department at <ORGANIZATION>Georgia State University</ORGANIZATION> and a specialist in urban
affairs.
   A good-looking building, he said, ``is easier to sell to the
financing people as well as the tenants.''
   <PERSON>Hartshorn</PERSON> said he expects the new projects in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> will bring
special recognition.
   ``I think it's going to open some eyes,'' he said. ``We have
prestige with our cultural buildings, but I don't know that our
office buildings are that distinctive nationally.
   ``These aren't just ultra post-modern. They're classic. They're
different.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880914-0225 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-14-88 1245EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-AtlantaSkyline ADV22   09-14 0865</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Atlanta Skyline, ADV 22,0888</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv22</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Thurs AMs, Sept. 22, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>New Buildings Changing Atlanta's Skyline, Giving City Long Desired
Respect</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MARC RICE</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A new generation of skyscrapers is about to alter
the skyline of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, previously dismissed as sterile and
nondescript.
   Even homegrown architect <PERSON>John Portman</PERSON>, whose glass towers and
soaring atriums for years defined <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and who in the past
criticized post-modern architecture as a step backward, has given a
nod to the style in his latest project, a 60-story office building
planned for downtown <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   Much of the excitement over the pending transformation of the
capital of the <LOCATION>New South</LOCATION> started last fall with the opening of the
50-story <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> building. Officially called <ORGANIZATION>One Atlantic Center</ORGANIZATION>, it is
a slender, post-modern tower of stone with tall arched entryways
and Gothic finials, dramatically crowned by a 100-foot-high,
eight-sided copper pyramid topped by a golden lantern.
   Rush-hour traffic on Interstate 85 slows to a cautious crawl as
drivers gaze its way. At night, the lights in its crown command
attention from all over town. Architecture writers have used words
like ``gracious,'' ``truly wonderful,'' ``serene,'' ``imposing''
and ``glamorous'' to describe the tower.
   ``It certainly projects a vibrance to the rest of the world,''
said <PERSON>Roy Cooper</PERSON>, vice president for economic development with the
<ORGANIZATION>Atlanta Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's just beautiful. Everybody's
just staggered by it.''
   The tower is a dramatic departure from the glass boxes common in
modern architecture and contrasts with the sleek look of most of
the city's tallest buildings.
   Its influence shows up in at least three other skyscrapers going
up in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, and the design of the proposed Promenade skyscraper
complex was altered to complement the rose-colored <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> tower.
   <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> architect <PERSON>John Burgee</PERSON>, whose firm designed the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>
building with design consultant <PERSON>Philip Johnson</PERSON>, won't take credit
for transforming <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s skyline. But he said the city's image,
as defined by the way it looks, is undergoing a change.
   ``<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> has been looking for its identity,'' <PERSON>Burgee</PERSON> said in a
telephone interview from his <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> office. ``It's an historical
city (but) its architecture and image is not strictly historical.
You think of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> and you think of `Gone With The Wind.' Now,
there is an attempt to come up with a visual image.
   ``We all know Peachtree Street, but you don't think of its
buildings,'' he said. ``Like in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, the Empire State
Building; <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> building; <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, the
<ORGANIZATION>TransAmerica</ORGANIZATION> building. Atlanta doesn't have that. It's moving
toward that, very definitely.''
   Burgee and <PERSON>Johnson</PERSON> also are behind One Ninety One Peachtree
Tower, a post-modern skyscraper planned for downtown <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   Another planned project grouped in the ``Son of <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'' building
spurt is the Promenade in the tree-lined, historic Midtown section,
a complex of three office buildings and a hotel being developed by
<ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> and the Atlanta-based <ORGANIZATION>Landmarks Group</ORGANIZATION>.
   When unveiled last year, it was designed with an exterior of
glittering green glass. But when Promenade officials saw the
excitement over the nearby IBM Tower, its architects, <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Ventulett &amp; Stainback</ORGANIZATION>, redrew the plans to use rose glass above
rose-toned stone and topped with a gray steel spire.
   The most recently announced skyscraper is a downtown giant by
<PERSON>Portman</PERSON>, whose imprint is already deeply felt in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>, primarily
through the <ORGANIZATION>Peachtree Center</ORGANIZATION> and the towering cylindrical <ORGANIZATION>Westin
Peachtree Plaza Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   Portman's new building is slated to begin construction next year
and, at 60 stories, will eclipse One <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> as the Southeast's
tallest building. Unveiling the design in <DATE>May</DATE>, <PERSON>Portman</PERSON> said it was
``respectful of the past but, like this city, is audacious and bold
and forward-looking _ the beginning of post-post-modern
architecture.''
   <PERSON>Dale Durfee</PERSON>, a professor of architecture at <ORGANIZATION>Georgia Tech</ORGANIZATION>, said
completion of the <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> tower signaled the acceleration of a change
in the look of the city that began a decade ago.
   ``<LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was pretty much plain vanilla,'' he said, ``with no
development of architectural significance.''
   Burgee echoed that appraisal, saying, ``It was pretty
nondescript. It might be anyplace. If they took you (to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>)
blindfolded and took off the blindfold, you wouldn't have a clue
where you are.''
   <PERSON>Durfee</PERSON> said <DATE>that 10 years ago</DATE>, <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> was groping to form an
identity and had no demand for the type of buildings now are going
up.
   Today, however, companies want sophistication in their office
buildings, <PERSON>Durfee</PERSON> said, and corporate sponsorship of building
projects has changed the rules of skyscraper financing.
   Some say that all the building activity simply makes good
business sense.
   ``Sure, there's competitive prestige. Good architecture is good
business,'' said <PERSON>Truman Hartshorn</PERSON>, chairman of the geography
department at <ORGANIZATION>Georgia State University</ORGANIZATION> and a specialist in urban
affairs.
   A good-looking building, he said, ``is easier to sell to the
financing people as well as the tenants.''
   <PERSON>Hartshorn</PERSON> said he expects the new projects in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> will bring
special recognition.
   ``I think it's going to open some eyes,'' he said. ``We have
prestige with our cultural buildings, but I don't know that our
office buildings are that distinctive nationally.
   ``These aren't just ultra post-modern. They're classic. They're
different.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Thurs AMs, Sept. 22</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030790-0132 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 186044 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 7, 1990, Wednesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 5; Column 2; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1298 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
STAINLESS-STEEL TOWER PLANNED FOR COSTA MESA; 
</P>
<P>
ARCHITECTURE: CESAR PELLI'S DESIGN FEATURES A CURVING FACADE AND A COPPERY 
GLOW. THE SEGERSTROM FAMILY AND IBM ARE JOINTLY DEVELOPING THE BUILDING NEAR 
SOUTH COAST PLAZA. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MICHAEL FLAGG, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
COSTA MESA 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Orange County will add an unusual new building to its skyline -- which some 
critics have called boring and mundane -- with the addition next year of a 
21-story, stainless steel office tower near <LOCATION>South Coast Plaza</LOCATION> that was designed 
by renowned architect <PERSON>Cesar Pelli</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Pelli, who recently designed what could become the world's tallest skyscraper 
in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> unveiled a model of the new <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> building, which is 
being jointly developed by the <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON> family and <ORGANIZATION>IBM Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The design has a curving facade of burnished steel facing inward toward a 
parking garage and walkway on one side. On its other side, the design presents 
a flat surface to passing motorists on Avenue of the Arts. The stainless steel, 
an unusual material for an office tower, is designed to give off a warm, 
coppery glow. 
</P>
<P>
Construction is scheduled to begin in <DATE>May</DATE> and be completed in <DATE>September, 1991</DATE>. 
While it looks thoroughly modern, the design's details allude to the look of 
older office buildings. 
</P>
<P>
Pelli, who lived in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and <DATE>1970s</DATE> and designed many 
buildings there, is one of the foremost architects in the nation. He is 
probably best known for designing graceful and daring skyscrapers in big 
cities. This will be his first building in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and <DATE>1980s</DATE>, the county's cityscape changed, from a low-slung suburb 
of single-family homes and one-story commercial buildings into a series of 
small urban areas where mid-rise office towers of 10 to 15 stories <DATE>spring</DATE> up in 
spiky clumps around malls or <PERSON>John Wayne Airport</PERSON>. One of these areas grew up 
around <LOCATION>South Coast Plaza</LOCATION>, the giant mall that became <ORGANIZATION>Costa Mesa</ORGANIZATION>'s "new 
downtown" and that will be the new building's neighbor. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the new county buildings were boxy, glass structures with few 
distinguishing features, a result of the Modernist school of architecture that 
favors sleek, stark buildings with clean lines. These buildings often had the 
advantage of being cheaper to build than more elaborate designs too. 
</P>
<P>
But in the <DATE>last 20 years</DATE> or so, such Post-Modernist architects as <PERSON>Pelli</PERSON> have 
experimented with different building materials -- more expensive stuff such as 
granite, for instance -- and more complicated designs that often incorporate 
elements of earlier buildings, such as the soaring, big-city skyscrapers of the 
<DATE>1920s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Most of these new buildings, of course, have been built in such cities as <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>. But lately they have been appearing more 
frequently in such previously undistinguished suburban markets as <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> 
and <ORGANIZATION>Tysons Corner</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, outside <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Still, the county's architecture has drawn little praise to date. For instance, 
the architecture critic of the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Paul Goldberger</PERSON>, complained in a 
<DATE>1988</DATE> article that the county's architecture "celebrates not the whimsy of 
<LOCATION>Disneyland</LOCATION>, but the conformity of glass boxes and other architectural 
banalities." 
</P>
<P>
The county's biggest developers have begun hiring architects such as <PERSON>Pelli</PERSON> to 
design their own buildings for reasons both aesthetic and economic: 
</P>
<P>
* A building with an architectural pedigree is easier to rent to the classy 
tenants that landlords like, especially in an overbuilt office market such as 
<LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>'s. 
</P>
<P>
* There are so many office buildings in the county now that a building with a 
distinctive look may be easier to market. 
</P>
<P>
And there are some less tangible benefits: A developer such as the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s 
<PERSON>Donald L. Bren</PERSON>, for instance, has a vision of how his vast landholdings should 
look and hires the best architects to make it so; there is also some 
civic-mindedness and a healthy dose of ego and one-upmanship involved in hiring 
prominent architects, local realty observers say. 
</P>
<P>
Few developers are quite so blunt as to acknowledge this, though, or to 
criticize each other's buildings. 
</P>
<P>
"This building is a little more daring, a little more creative than we've 
seen," said <PERSON>Henry T. Segerstrom</PERSON>, whose family owns <ORGANIZATION>South Coast Plaza</ORGANIZATION> and much 
of the land around it. "Orange County is at the stage where we need an 
identity, something very exceptional. 
</P>
<P>
"This is not a mediocre community, and we want to elevate our standards of 
design." 
</P>
<P>
Working in the suburbs is often a new experience for such architects as <PERSON>Pelli</PERSON>. 
He said he did not tone down his imaginative ideas for the conservative county, 
although he acknowledged that he might have settled on a different building in 
<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"Every building must be part of its environment," <PERSON>Pelli</PERSON> said. "Architecture is 
the art of intelligent and creative response to that environment. But no, we 
didn't tone it down." 
</P>
<P>
Pelli is the latest in a string of renowned architects to work in <LOCATION>Orange 
County</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Philip Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Burgee</PERSON> designed TV minister <PERSON>Robert H. 
Schuller</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Crystal Cathedral</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Garden Grove</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Helmut Jahn</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> is 
designing a small headquarters building in <LOCATION>Dana Point</LOCATION> for developers <PERSON>David 
Stein</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barry Brief</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Pelli ranks with such glittering names. Born in <LOCATION>Argentina</LOCATION> 63 years ago, he was 
worked for several firms in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> before becoming dean of the <ORGANIZATION>School of 
Architecture</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>. He left in <DATE>1984</DATE>. He now designs 
buildings through his firm, <ORGANIZATION>Cesar Pelli &amp; Associates</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New Haven</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Among the more prominent buildings <PERSON>Pelli</PERSON> has designed are: 
</P>
<P>
* A building that will be the world's tallest if built, just approved for 125 
stories by <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION>. It is to be 15 stories higher than <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION>, now the world's tallest building. 
</P>
<P>
* The big 777 Tower at <ORGANIZATION>Citicorp Plaza</ORGANIZATION> in downtown <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Design Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>West Hollywood</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
* The <ORGANIZATION>World Financial Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
* <ORGANIZATION>Norwest Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
IBM is a big enough tenant -- especially in a slow office market -- to demand a 
piece of the ownership, so <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> are partners in the building. 
</P>
<P>
Like <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> has a history of hiring prestigious architects. In this 
case, the company has a practical objective too: The computer manufacturer is 
the largest tenant in <LOCATION>Segerstrom</LOCATION> buildings around <LOCATION>South Coast Plaza</LOCATION> and wanted 
to consolidate its offices and save on rent by building a new tower. 
</P>
<P>
Originally, the building was to have been part of <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON>'s giant Home Ranch 
project a mile or so north of the mall off the <LOCATION>San Diego Freeway</LOCATION>. But that 
project was killed by <LOCATION>Costa Mesa</LOCATION> voters. 
</P>
<P>
That building was planned as considerably taller, at 32 stories. The new 
building, much closer to the mall at the northwest corner of Avenue of the Arts 
and <PERSON>Anton Boulevard</PERSON>, would be just 21 stories, because of the proximity of 
flight paths around <LOCATION>John Wayne Airport</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Pelli, who often designs much taller buildings, said he did not feel 
constrained by the relative smallness of the <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON> building. It will still 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> will occupy the first eight floors or so -- about 160,000 of the 440,000 
square feet -- and <PERSON>Segerstrom</PERSON> will lease the rest to tenants. IBM, unlike many 
big tenants in office buildings, says it does not put a big corporate sign on 
its buildings and will not on this one, saying it prefers not to distract from 
the architecture. 
</P>
<P>
While neither partner will comment, the building is expected to cost at least 
<MONEY>$90 million</MONEY>, based on current construction costs, and probably more because of 
the stainless steel's expense. 
</P>
<P>
SEGERSTROM-IBM PROJECT 
</P>
<P>
Location: <ORGANIZATION>Northwest</ORGANIZATION> corner of <PERSON>Anton Boulevard</PERSON> and Avenue of the Arts 
</P>
<P>
Height: 21 stories 
</P>
<P>
Square footage: 440,000 
</P>
<P>
Start date: <DATE>May, 1990</DATE> 
</P>
<P>
Completion: <DATE>Sept.,1991</DATE> 
</P>
<P>
Architect: <PERSON>Cesar Pelli</PERSON> 
</P>
<P>
Construction: Peck/Jones 
</P>
<P>
Cost: Not disclosed 
</P>
<P>
Financing: <ORGANIZATION>Bank of America 
</P>
<P>
Major</ORGANIZATION> tenant: <ORGANIZATION>IBM Corp.</ORGANIZATION> -- <PERCENT>33%</PERCENT> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, SEGERSTROM-IBM PROJECT ; Photo, Architect Cesar Pelli unveils a model of 
the stainless-steel Segerstrom-IBM building that will be built near South Coast 
Plaza. KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles Times; Photo, HIGHEST HIGH-RISE: Renowned 
architect Cesar Pelli unveiled his plan for a 21-story, stainless-steel office 
tower to open next year near South Coast Plaza. It will be a joint development 
by IBM and the Segerstrom family. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
COSTA MESA (CA) -- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT; OFFICE BUILDINGS; 
INTERNATIONAL BUSINESS MACHINES CORP; C J SEGERSTROM &amp; SONS; DESIGN; 
ARCHITECTS; REAL ESTATE DEVELOPERS; ARCHITECTURE; PELLI, CESAR 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA011690-0081 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 162781 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 16, 1990, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
726 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ON CALIFORNIA: A TRUMP CARD AND AN ACE UP THE SLEEVE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROBERT A. JONES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
LOS ANGELES 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Dear <PERSON>Mr. Trump</PERSON>: 
</P>
<P>
We love it that you love <LOCATION>L.A</LOCATION>. As soon as we picked up our <DATE>Sunday</DATE> paper and saw 
-- right there on Page 1! -- your plans to tear down the ratty Ambassador Hotel 
and build the World's Tallest Building in its place, our smog-choked chests 
heaved with pride. Trumpomania, here at last! 
</P>
<P>
Do you wanna know how bad it was before you got here? Here's how bad: Just <DATE>last 
summer</DATE> we topped off the Library Tower building downtown and thought it was a 
big deal. Lotsa ink in the local sheets, and it was just a measly 73 stories 
tall. Now you pop into town, and right off you're talking 125 stories! 
</P>
<P>
That's why that scamp <PERSON>John Ferraro</PERSON> (he's our <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> president) was right 
on the mark at your press conference when he quipped, "Why did it take you so 
long to get to <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>?" 
</P>
<P>
And you just smiled like a chipmunk at that one. Heh, heh, you old faker. That 
stuff in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Trump Tower</ORGANIZATION> and all, that was just in prelude, wasn't it? 
And the casinos in <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, merely a warm-up, eh? Now you're gonna strut 
your real stuff, go for the works, and where? <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>! We knew you wouldn't 
forget! 
</P>
<P>
OK, maybe it's true that not everyone loves it that you love <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> Maybe some 
grouches have claimed you showed up at your news conference without plans or 
drawings or descriptions of any of the new buildings, not even a sketch of the 
World's Tallest Building. And maybe the grumps wondered why the mayor and two 
city councilmen agreed to stand around like house plants at your news 
conference when they didn't know squat about what you intend or when. 
</P>
<P>
Well, let me give you a little advice: Those nattering negativos don't mean 
nothing. Here in <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION>, we understand a high concept when we see it. Let the 
little people deal with details like traffic and congestion and design. Just 
keep repeating the phrase, "World's Tallest Building," and the mayor will show 
up to play house plant any time you need him. 
</P>
<P>
Now there is one thing I'm curious about. I noticed that, when you bought your 
share of the Ambassador property, you changed the name of the company from 
<ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Center Partners to Trump Wilshire Associates</ORGANIZATION>. And rightly so, of 
course. People should know who's ushering <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> toward its future. 
</P>
<P>
But you didn't say what you intend to call the World's Tallest Building and its 
ensemble of Slightly Smaller Buildings. At first I thought that <ORGANIZATION>Trump City</ORGANIZATION> 
would do the trick. That way, see, your development could act as a counterpart 
to something called <ORGANIZATION>Century City</ORGANIZATION>, a little thing we built ourselves out on the 
Westside. Then I realized that was a bad idea. Compared to yours, <ORGANIZATION>Century 
City</ORGANIZATION>'s buildings aren't tall at all, they're hardly even skyscrapers, and 
there's not nearly enough of them. 
</P>
<P>
So I was reading the news stories, looking for clues, when I read where you 
intend to employ "true <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> style" in the design of your buildings. This 
inspired me. How about "La Ciudad Trump," hmmm? It has that international ring 
to it. Or "Rancho Trump Deluxe?" Or, if you wanted to pick up on a lost theme 
of <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> design, "Tail o' the Trump" might do nicely. These are just a couple of 
ideas, of course. We have a lot more if you need them. 
</P>
<P>
I have saved this last matter to the end because it's, well, sensitive to all 
of us here in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. We understand that, in truth, you have also been 
working on another proposal for the World's Tallest Building, and that other 
proposal is located right smack in the middle of you-know-where. <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. We 
also understand -- and this is where it hurts -- that <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s World's 
Tallest Building is planned for 150 stories, 25 more stories than our World's 
Tallest Building. 
</P>
<P>
Yo, <PERSON>Don</PERSON>, what goes? Do you understand the insecurities you are stirring up 
here? Are we gonna be top dog, or is this another case where we get stuck with 
the old "biggest west of the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>" monicker? We're real sick of the 
west-of-the-Mississippi business, <PERSON>Donnie</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Lucky for us, there are solutions to this problem. You could always switch 
plans and go the full 150 here while you slipped the ol' 125 to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. It 
would make their Tallest Building look like a termite mound, haw haw. This 
would be a favor we wouldn't forget, <PERSON>Donnie</PERSON>. We might even let you stick one of 
your dollar bills in wet cement at <ORGANIZATION>Grauman</ORGANIZATION>'s, right next to <PERSON>Rin Tin Tin</PERSON>'s paw 
prints. It's a high concept to think about. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
TRUMP, DONALD J; LOS ANGELES -- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT; HIGH RISE 
BUILDINGS; AMBASSADOR HOTEL; DEMOLITION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880321-0275 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-21-88 1751EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f AM-Germany-TallBuilding     03-21 0223</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Germany-Tall Building,0231</SECOND>
<HEAD>Europe's Tallest Building Planned for Frankfurt</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FRANKFURT, West Germany (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> real estate firm on
<DATE>Monday</DATE> announced plans to erect <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s tallest building _ a
53-story, 838-foot office tower _ on sprawling fairgrounds in this
West German city.
   <ORGANIZATION>Tishman Speyer Properties</ORGANIZATION> said the project, which it valued at
<MONEY>$375 million</MONEY>, will be financed by <ORGANIZATION>Citibank</ORGANIZATION>.
   The skyscraper, with its 920,000 square feet of office space,
will surpass the <PERSON>Palac Kultury</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Warsaw</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Poland</LOCATION>, as <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>'s
tallest building. The <PERSON>Palac Kultury</PERSON>, has 42 stories and is 790 feet
tall.
   <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Wolfram Brueck</PERSON> said the building is expected to
be completed by <DATE>1991</DATE>.
   Tishman Speyer President <PERSON>Jerry Speyer</PERSON>, appearing at a press
conference with the mayor, said his company already has received
rental inquiries about the building.
   <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>'s flourishing banking and finance
center, has been expanding in recent years. New office buildings
have sprouted up in the city's center, and decaying downtown
neighborhoods have been renovated.
   The fairgrounds are not far from the city's downtown shopping
area, its main train station and banking district.
   Tishman Speyer manages a portfolio of properties valued at <MONEY>$4
billion</MONEY>, the company said in a statement. The company currently has
<MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> worth of projects under development, including the
<ORGANIZATION>Beijing American Express Center</ORGANIZATION>, an office and apartment complex in
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06054037 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06054037 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BUILDING; TECHNOLOGY; PROFESSIONAL; DEATH; OBITUARY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Abraham S. Bolsky, who 30 years ago erected the city's first building to
exceed the height limit of 13 stories and built some of the tallest buildings
in the West, died of heart failure Thursday. He was 68.;    Mr. Bolsky was
president of Tishman Construction Corp. of California and executive vice
president of its parent firm, the New York-based Tishman Realty &amp; Construction
Co.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A.S. BOLSKY, 68, ERECTED SKYSCRAPERS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Obituaries  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     During his 37 years at <LOCATION>Tishman</LOCATION>, he directed construction of more than 50
major developments in the West, including three of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>' largest
buildings -- the 48-story <ORGANIZATION>Wells Fargo Bank Building</ORGANIZATION>, the Broadway Plaza
complex and the Twin Towers in <LOCATION>Century City</LOCATION>, company spokesman <PERSON>Bernie Roswig</PERSON>
said.;    More recently, he supervised construction of the <ORGANIZATION>Ronald Reagan
Building</ORGANIZATION> in downtown <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> and the Rodeo Collection in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Roswig</PERSON> said.;    <PERSON>Mr. Bolsky</PERSON> was born in <LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION> and raised in <LOCATION>New York.</LOCATION>;  
 In <DATE>1960</DATE>, he built the 21-story 615 South Flower Building, the city's first
structure to exceed 13 stories, <PERSON>Roswig</PERSON> said. Taller buildings followed with
the advent of new engineering and construction techniques that would ensure
safety during earthquakes.;    <PERSON>Mr. Bolsky</PERSON> is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Helen</PERSON>, and
two daughters, <PERSON>Debbie</PERSON> and <PERSON>Francine</PERSON>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Los Angeles  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910223  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  February  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  201  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday February 23, 1991
00054037,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-6664</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CHYBZACOFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920822
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  22 AUG 92 / Canary Wharf to share its bird's eye view
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By VANESSA HOULDER, Property Correspondent
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<LOCATION>LONDON</LOCATION> is once again to have its own panoramic viewing platform. But, unlike
the <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower or Empire State Building</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s look-out point is miles
away from its most notable monuments.
One <LOCATION>Canada Square</LOCATION>, the steel-clad, 50-storey centrepiece of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>
<ORGANIZATION>Docklands' Canary Wharf</ORGANIZATION> and the tallest building in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, is opening its
top floor to the public.
The decision to allow visitors has been taken to 'generate and maintain
interest in the Docklands', according to the administrators who were
appointed to the project in <DATE>May</DATE>.
At 800ft, the tower is 200ft higher than its nearest UK rival, the <ORGANIZATION>National
Westminster Tower</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>City</LOCATION> of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. On a clear day, the view from the
top can stretch for 30 miles.
Visitors will be charged Pounds 3 a person, but after additional security
and ticketing costs, this will do little to help the finances of the
project, which has debts estimated at Pounds 700m.
It will provide the first opportunity in nearly 20 years to visit the top of
the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s tallest building. The 580ft Post Office tower (now the BT tower),
which held the record until the <ORGANIZATION>NatWest</ORGANIZATION> tower was built in <DATE>1980</DATE>, has been
closed to the public since <DATE>1973</DATE>, when a bomb exploded in the restaurant.
The <ORGANIZATION>Canary Wharf</ORGANIZATION> tower will be the tallest office building that can be
visited in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, since <LOCATION>Frankfurt</LOCATION>'s 841ft 6in Messeturm is off limits to
visitors. However, an even loftier view is available from the the
iron-framed, 985ft 11in <ORGANIZATION>Eiffel Tower</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>.
The tallest buildings in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Sears Roebuck Building</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> and
the World Trade Center and <ORGANIZATION>Empire State Building</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, also court
visitors. The world's tallest tower remains the 1,815ft CN Tower in <LOCATION>Toronto</LOCATION>,
while the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>'s highest structure is the 1,265ft ITN mast in <LOCATION>Lincolnshire</LOCATION>.
The <ORGANIZATION>Canary Wharf</ORGANIZATION> tower will be open on <DATE>Saturdays</DATE> and <DATE>Sundays</DATE>, from 10am to
5pm, from <DATE>September 12</DATE>. On that <DATE>weekend</DATE>, the Docklands Light Railway will,
unusually, be open as it coincides with the European Oyster and Seafood
Fair, organised by the <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> <ORGANIZATION>Docklands Development Corporation</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890708-0110 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-08-89 1748EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SearsTower     07-08 0219</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sears Tower,0225</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sears Denies Reported Plans for Adding to Height of World's Tallest
Building</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Roebuck and Co.</ORGANIZATION> denied reports <DATE>Saturday</DATE>
that it plans to add stories to the <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION> because another
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> skyscraper might overshadow the world's tallest building.
   The Wall Street Journal and the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> Sun-Times reported that
<ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> is planning to outdo two <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> developers who announced
plans in <DATE>May</DATE> to erect a taller skyscraper only a few blocks from the
<ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> building.
   ``Not to be outdone,'' <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s Journal said, ``Sears quietly
began drawing up contingency plans to add at least 16 floors to its
tower _ topping the proposed unstart by at least one floor.''
   ``Absolutely not,'' <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Doug Fairweather</PERSON> said when
asked if the story was true.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Sun-Times</ORGANIZATION> reported <DATE>Saturday</DATE> that <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> is preparing plans for
an addition, but neither the Sun-Times nor the Journal quoted <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>
officials by name.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> tower is for sale, and the Journal said the company is
preparing the plans to placate potential buyers who might balk at
the thought of owning the world's second-tallest building.
   Construction would be done by the new owner, the Journal said.
   ``There are no plans, nor has there been any formal study for
such a plan. Not a nickel has been spent,'' <PERSON>Fairweather</PERSON> insisted.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900120-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-20-90 0537EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--TallestBuilding     01-20 0139</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Tallest Building,0142</SECOND>
<HEAD>Zoning OK'd for World's Tallest Building</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Chicago City Council</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Friday</DATE> unanimously
approved a zoning request to allow construction of a 125-story
building, which would be 15 stories higher than the world's tallest.
   The building, proposed by the <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> real estate development
firm <ORGANIZATION>Miglin-Beitler Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, would rise 1,950 feet, 496 feet taller
than the <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION>, currently the world's tallest building.
   The proposed Miglin-Beitler Tower would be in the city's west
<LOCATION>Loop</LOCATION> area downtown, near the 110-story <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION>.
   The council approved the zoning request 44-0, said <PERSON>Alderman
William Banks</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Committee on Zoning</ORGANIZATION>.
   Developer <PERSON>Paul Beitler</PERSON> said the tower's skinny design will cater
to the ``new market of the <DATE>1990s</DATE>'' _ consulting firms, small
corporations and other small tenants who can't afford entire floors
in fatter office buildings.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900413-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-13-90 1406EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Trump-LA     04-13 0790</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trump-LA,0815</SECOND>
<HEAD>Taj Mahal West or 125-Story Megabuilding? Trump's LA Plans Unclear</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE V. BIGELOW</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>'s new Taj Majal casino in
<LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>, with its minarets and huge stone elephants, has left
many here wondering _ or worrying _ what the mega-developer plans
for an encore.
   But details concerning <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s grand design for the site of the
historic Ambassador Hotel remain by and large the sultan's secret.
   Three months ago, the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> billionaire revealed he had
become a partner in a group that bought the boarded-up hotel with
the intention of razing it and building a new project. The
development at the 24-acre site on <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Boulevard</ORGANIZATION> would be
<ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s first in the nation's second-largest city.
   He's hinted that he may try to put up the world's tallest
building, a tower of 125 stories or more, if plans for a similarly
outsized building are thwarted in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>.
   Such talk has worried environmentalists _ <PERSON>Bob Hattoy</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club</ORGANIZATION> quipped that <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> was giving the city an ``edifice
complex'' _ but it remains just talk.
   ``We haven't formally announced anything in terms of how tall or
how wide,'' said <PERSON>Barbara Res</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Trump Organization</ORGANIZATION> vice president
who is shepherding the deal.
   Whatever its shape, the <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY> project would give <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> something it lacks _ a landmark comparable to the Eiffel
Tower or <ORGANIZATION>Rockefeller Center</ORGANIZATION>, Res said in a recent telephone
interview.
   ``We anticipate having a major shopping area, a luxury hotel _ a
very large one with a very, very large banquet and ballroom
facility, maybe on the order of 50,000 square feet _ a lot of
office space and a housing element,'' she said.
   The Ambassador was home to the <LOCATION>Cocoanut Grove</LOCATION> nightclub where
the rich and famous in <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> came to play, but is
perhaps best known as the place where <PERSON>Robert F. Kennedy</PERSON> was
assassinated in <DATE>1968</DATE>. The hotel, its glamour now faded, finally
closed in <DATE>January 1989</DATE>.
   With no specifics to react to yet, not even an artist's concept,
the potential opponents of <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION>'s development are left with little
to say.
   ``There's nothing on the table,'' said <PERSON>Jay Rounds</PERSON>, executive
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>, a non-profit historic
preservation group. ``We don't deal in critiques of press
conferences.''
   A spokesman for Mayor <PERSON>Tom Bradley</PERSON>, reflecting the views of
several local politicians, said, ``We need to wait until we see
specifics of the project before we can discuss it in detail.''
   The scarcity of details on design or financing has prompted
speculation that <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> wanted the publicity only to gain leverage
against <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> officials who have held up his plans for a
150-story tower on the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION>.
   ``Perhaps the fact that I go out to <LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> will change things in
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The New York Times</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>February</DATE>. He denied
trying to play <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> off against each other, but
added his plans for the world's tallest building ``could go to
either place, and it will only go to one.''
   Could such a building be put up in an earthquake-prone area?
   ``There's no inherent reason why you can't build a building in
the range of 125 stories to be resistant to an earthquake,'' said
<PERSON>Wilford Iwan</PERSON>, a professor of earthquake engineering at the
<ORGANIZATION>California Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION>.
   But Iwan added that really big structures ``tend to be quite
flexible,'' and the way such a building would sway in a quake or
strong wind could make people inside feel uncomfortable.
   Another concern is fire, especially since city fire officials
acknowledged that the <DATE>1988</DATE> inferno in the 62-story <ORGANIZATION>First Interstate</ORGANIZATION>
tower, then the state's tallest building, came perilously close to
exceeding the metropolitan area's firefighting resources.
   Among those who voice few doubts about <PERSON>Trump</PERSON>'s intentions is
<PERSON>Jackie Goldberg</PERSON>, president of the city's <ORGANIZATION>Board of Education</ORGANIZATION>.
Wilshire-area students at a cost of <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> a year, wants to
take over the property as the site for a desparately needed new
high school. But the board has found itself stymied repeatedly by
the Trump organization, <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> said.
   ``We're involved with somebody here who is accustomed to getting
his own way, and has the funds and the lack of public scrutiny to
do it,'' <PERSON>Goldberg</PERSON> fumed.
   When school officials asked the state <ORGANIZATION>Allocation Board</ORGANIZATION> for <MONEY>$120
million</MONEY> to pay for the land, they discovered that lobbyists hired
by <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> already had persuaded members of the obscure state agency
to withhold the funds.
   The board instead ordered district officials to work out a
compromise with the billionaire developer, whose representatives
offered to find an alternate site for the school.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06130092 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06130092 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  NEW-YORK; CITY; BUILDING; SPORT; UNUSUAL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Startled bystanders watched as a young man atop the 110-story World Trade
Center blew them a kiss, let out a whoop and jumped over the side -- then
opened a parachute and glided to a perfect landing.;    The man landed on a
patch of grass next to the twin towers, quickly packed up his chute and hopped
into a waiting car that disappeared into rush-hour traffic Wednesday afternoon.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PARACHUTIST LEAPS OFF TALLEST N.Y. SKYSCRAPER
'GERONIMO!' . . . THEN 110 STORIES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     WNYW-TV identified him as <PERSON>John Vincent</PERSON>, 23, of <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>. His whereabouts
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> were unknown.;    Port Authority police Officer <PERSON>Lloyd Schwalb</PERSON>
said he was in his offices on the 60th floor of one of the towers when he
spotted someone floating down from the other tower.;    "I was quite concerned
they might land in a path of traffic," he said. "But as it turned out, this
person seemed to skillfully maneuver the glider to land in a patch of green
lawn.";    <PERSON>Robert Bradley</PERSON>, a tourist from <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, said the jumper leaped from
the observation deck after yelling "something like 'Geronimo!' ";    He had to
get past an electrified fence before he could go over the side.;    The World
Trade Center, at 1,368 feet, is <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s tallest building. The <ORGANIZATION>Sears
Tower</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, the world's tallest building, is 86 feet higher.;    <PERSON>Schwalb</PERSON>
said police arrest building jumpers when they catch them, but authorities
early <DATE>today</DATE> said they didn't know if an effort would be made to track down the
jumper. The <ORGANIZATION>Port Authority</ORGANIZATION> owns the World Trade Center.;    "This is a deadly
sport, and we want to discourage anything like this because it's potentially
deadly to the person and to those below," <PERSON>Schwalb</PERSON> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910509  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  May  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  10C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  275  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday May 9, 1991
00130092,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890523-0065 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-23-89 0954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TallestBuilding     05-23 0167</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Tallest Building,0173</SECOND>
<HEAD>Planned Loop Skyscraper Would Eclipse Sears Tower As World's Tallest</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CHICAGO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A developer wants to turn the <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION> into
the world's second-tallest building.
   <ORGANIZATION>Miglin-Beitler Developments Inc.</ORGANIZATION> announced plans <DATE>Monday</DATE> for a
slender, 125-story skyscraper resembling a rocket emerging from the
<LOCATION>Loop</LOCATION>. The 1,914-foot structure would eclipse by 400 feet the <ORGANIZATION>Sears
Tower</ORGANIZATION>, the tallest building in the world.
   The developer did not indicate how much the concrete and
steel-reinforced skyscraper would cost.
   Plans for the building have been submitted for approval to the
<ORGANIZATION>Chicago Plan Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
   Planning Commissioner <PERSON>David Mosena</PERSON> said his first impression is
``it is a handsome building, but I can't take an official position
until we get a chance to study it.''
   Construction could begin by <DATE>December</DATE> and could be completed by
mid-1992, the developer said.
   The building, being designed by architect <PERSON>Cesar Pelli</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>New
Haven</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, would contain 1.2 million square feet of office
space, only about one-third the rentable space of the <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910620-0160
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910620-0160.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Big Towers and Dead Birds
   ----
   By Marie Winn
</HL>
<DATE>
06/20/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- At 5 a.m. one morning last month I accompanied
a small group of New York bird lovers on a gruesome
expedition. Though spring migration was at its height, we
were not heading for budding groves of Central Park's Ramble,
where warblers, thrushes, tanagers and other songbirds of
passage are known to drop in on their way to northern
breeding grounds.
   No, we were heading for the treeless canyons of downtown
and midtown Manhattan. We were looking for birds that had
collided with skyscrapers. Dead birds.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   Our pre-dawn outing had been organized by <PERSON>Sarah Elliott</PERSON>, a
former children's book editor who now leads bird walks for
the <ORGANIZATION>Central Park Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON> believes that
illuminated tall buildings, "well-lit phallic symbols," in
her words, are deathtraps for passing migratory birds. And so
in the latest issue of the Urban Audubon, a monthly
newsletter of the <ORGANIZATION>New York City Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, she has
launched the Captains for Conservation program. Its purpose:
to inspire "Captains of Industry" who own or run brightly
illuminated skyscrapers to turn off their lights during the
migration seasons. This will save birds. It will save
electricity costs as well and bring companies good publicity.
<PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON> also threatens: "Soon holdouts with flashy
floodlights will look like slobs to the public and their
peers." But she needs evidence -- hence our expedition.
   <PERSON>Richard C. Banks</PERSON>, an ornithologist for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>, does not consider skyscrapers to be a
serious threat to birds. "It's more of an emotional thing
than a scientific problem," he says, "connected with people's
concern about the individual bird. As an avian biologist I
tend to worry more about populations, and from that viewpoint
the numbers killed by crashing into tall structures are not
significant."
   An expert on bird collisions with man-made structures
disagrees. Ornithologist <PERSON>Robert Crawford</PERSON> accumulated vast
quantities of data about bird migration by picking up dead
birds daily at the base of a huge TV tower in <LOCATION>Leon County</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, as part of a 25-year research project. If the numbers
of transmitters and other tall structures throughout the
country are added up, <PERSON>Mr. Crawford</PERSON> believes, the cumulative
effect on birds is "far from trivial." He estimates that more
than one million birds die annually in collisions with TV
towers alone.
   <PERSON>Mr. Crawford</PERSON> believes that bad weather and bright
illumination can be a deadly combination for migratory birds.
Normally, they zip along at altitudes well above the highest
tower or skyscraper. But they are forced to fly lower when
the skies are overcast. Then rain, mist or fog combine with
lights to disorient and bewilder birds, causing them to
crash. Why, then aren't our city streets littered with dead
birds on rainy days in the <DATE>spring</DATE> and fall? <PERSON>Mr. Crawford</PERSON> has
an answer based on his study: Long before dawn, predators
make off with <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT> of the downed birds.
   That is why we are here at the plaza of the World Trade
Center at this mind-numbing hour. We want to beat the
sweepers who might whisk away the unsightly little corpses,
or the rats who might make a tasty meal of them before
anybody arrives.
   Our fact-finding mission sets to work. We search the bases
of all buildings, we look in crevices, nooks and crannies.
<PERSON>Starr Saphir</PERSON>, a board member of the <ORGANIZATION>New York City Audubon
Society</ORGANIZATION> who also leads bird-identifying walks during
migration seasons, suddenly stops and listens. "Over there] I
hear a white-throated sparrow." Sure enough, a small bird
with black-and-white head stripes and a yellow spot above the
bill appears. It is scratching around near a planter. It is,
however, a living bird.
   A subsequent telephone call to <PERSON>Gus Preschle</PERSON>, the general
manager of the <ORGANIZATION>World Trade Center</ORGANIZATION>, helped to explain the
absence of avian cadavers at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s tallest skyscraper
complex. "Unlike many other tall buildings," <PERSON>Mr. Preschle</PERSON>
said with a certain smugness, "we have no decorative lighting
on the towers themselves. There are no floodlights on the
building."
   The <ORGANIZATION>Empire State Building</ORGANIZATION> is a different story. Everybody
knows that this famous skyscraper is lavishly illuminated
with bright lights and colors. And indeed, birds colliding
with the building have made headlines for almost half a
century. "Fog Is Blamed as Birds Die Hitting Empire State
Building. Tiny Bodies Litter 5th Avenue," a front-page
headline proclaimed on <DATE>September 12, 1948</DATE>. At least eight
other large bird kills at the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State</ORGANIZATION> have been reported
over the years.
   Actually, the powers that be at the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State Building</ORGANIZATION>
are not unconcerned about bird welfare. "We try to avoid any
real trauma to the flock," says <PERSON>Charles Giuno</PERSON>, head of
operations. "On nights when the atmospheric conditions would
cause them confusion, we turn off the floodlights and the
vertical and horizontal fluorescent lights. The decision is
made on a day-to-day basis. If the guard at the observatory
sees any birds flying around the lights, he is instructed to
notify the engineer. The engineer then turns off the lights."
   This information does not mollify <PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON>. She happens
to live just three blocks east, and she says she has observed
the tower lights on even in bad weather. This is why our
group now makes its way to 33rd Street and Park Avenue. Since
the small migrants would likely be coming from the South, we
would find any dead birds on the south side of the great
skyscraper.
   It is almost <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME> by now. We do not find any dead birds.
But we do encounter a porter sweeping directly across the
street. Angel Roman is his name and he has worked at 10 West
33rd St. for 11 years. A couple of years ago, around <TIME>midnight</TIME>
on a foggy night, he looked up and saw an amazing sight:
"Thousands of birds. Just going round and round and round in
the lights on top of the Empire State Building," he related.
The next morning, he said, he found many dead birds on the
sidewalk, and a few that were lying there, stunned but alive.
   "Aha]" said <PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON> triumphantly.
   Our last inspection site was the Metropolitan Life
Insurance Building, a tall landmark on 23rd Street and
<PERSON>Madison</PERSON> that is "lit up like a birthday cake," as <PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON>
described it. "It is to lights what boom boxes are to music,"
she added. Across the street from our target building is
<LOCATION>Madison Square Park</LOCATION>, a small, leafy oasis. "A wave of
warblers may have arrived <TIME>last night</TIME>," said <PERSON>Ms. Saphir</PERSON>. "I
hear an oven bird and a black-throated blue."
   It was almost daybreak as we approached the entrance of
the Met Life building. And there we saw it, a soft, velvety
bird about five inches long with a rich yellow throat and a
dramatic black mask across its eyes. It was lying motionless
on the sidewalk: a male common yellowthroat, a warbler more
at home in moist thickets and low underbrush than on a city
pavement, a bird whose piercing song ("witchety, witchety,
witchety]") is one of the loudest in the warbler kingdom.
"Poor bird," said <PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON> in a low voice as she stooped
to inspect it. At that moment the bird flew off, somewhat
shakily, across the street into the park.
   Our emotion: relief. Our tally: no dead birds, one dazed
survivor. But the fact-finding committee had found a fact and
<PERSON>Ms. Elliott</PERSON> was gratified. "We do know that bright lights put
birds at risk, and that's enough. People can destroy, but
they can't replace what they destroy. If birds go, all goes."
   Note: If you are a Captain of Industry and wish to become
a Captain for Conservation, you may write <PERSON>Sarah Elliott</PERSON> at
333 East 34 St., <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 10016.
   ---
   <PERSON>Ms. Winn</PERSON> watches birds in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Riverside Park</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891109-0112 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-09-89 1225EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Skyscraper     11-09 0416</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Skyscraper,0431</SECOND>
<HEAD>Company Designs 500-Story Building, But No Plans to Build It</HEAD>
<HEAD>With LaserPhoto</HEAD>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A construction company said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> it has
designed a 500-story skyscraper for <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, although there are no
immediate plans to build it.
   The designers would need 25 years and <MONEY>$326.2 billion</MONEY> to build
the 6,669-foot-tall ``Aeropolis <DATE>2001</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Yasuyuki Kimura</PERSON>, a
spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Ohbayashi Corp</ORGANIZATION>.
   This includes the money necessary to reclaim a 56-square-mile
island in <LOCATION>Tokyo Bay</LOCATION>, he added.
   The project was made possible by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s advanced techniques to
protect buildings in earthquakes, he said.
   The tallest building in earthquake-prone <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is the 60-story
Sunshine City Building in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. The 110-story <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> is the world's tallest building.
   <PERSON>Yukihisa Tokunaga</PERSON>, a city planning official of the <ORGANIZATION>Construction
Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, said the 500-story building is one of a number of private
plans by major construction firms to meet <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s growing need for
office and apartment space.
   ``I understand that none of the plans, including what they call
`Waterfronts,' `Geofronts,' `Undergroundpolis' and `Aeropolis,' has
been submitted for any government approval,'' <PERSON>Tokunaga</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Ohbayashi</ORGANIZATION> building would be able to accommodate 300,000
people. Aside from office space and residential units, it also
would have space for hotels, hospitals, parks and convention
centers.
   The design envisions elevators that would reach the top floor in
15 minutes.
   The building is shaped like a triangle, becoming smaller at the
top to help it absorb shock waves. It would have a number of
tunnels to let typhoon winds pass through rather than hitting the
building with full force.
   The Japanese archipelago, in the world's most active seismic
zone, is hit each year by some 1,000 tremors strong enough to be
felt. Three times this century, in <DATE>1923</DATE>, <DATE>1946</DATE> and <DATE>1948</DATE>, quake
deaths have climbed into the thousands. The Great Kanto Earthquake
of <DATE>1923</DATE> leveled vast areas of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, killing 140,000
people.
   About 25 typhoons develop in the region annually.
   In the early <DATE>1960s</DATE>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> developed a technique of building
flexible structures to replace the rigid construction techniques
favored for decades.
   Under the old concept, engineers built structures of up to 11
stories, using ferroconcrete solid pillars and walls to absorb
shock and sustain the building's weight. The new concept called for
making walls of slabs of reinforced concrete with several slits on
the surface.
   Using the new method, <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s 36-story, 482-foot-tall
<LOCATION>Kasumigaseki</LOCATION> Building was completed in <DATE>1968</DATE>.
   <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> has about 200 buildings of 12 stories or more, all erected
since <DATE>1963</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111089-0075 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 132631 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 10, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 2; Column 4; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
376 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TOKYO DESIGNERS ENVISION 500-STORY TOWER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TOKYO 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A construction company said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that it has designed a 500-story 
skyscraper for <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, although there are no immediate plans to build it. 
</P>
<P>
The designers would need 25 years and <MONEY>$326.2 billion</MONEY> to build the 
6,669-foot-tall "Aeropolis <DATE>2001</DATE>," said <PERSON>Yasuyuki Kimura</PERSON>, a spokesman for 
<ORGANIZATION>Ohbayashi Corp</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
This includes the money necessary to reclaim a 56-square-mile island in <LOCATION>Tokyo 
Bay</LOCATION>, he added. 
</P>
<P>
The project was made possible by <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s advanced techniques to protect 
buildings in earthquakes, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The tallest building in earthquake-prone <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> is <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s 60-story Sunshine 
City Building. The 110-story <ORGANIZATION>Sears Tower</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> is the world's tallest 
building. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Yukihisa Tokunaga</PERSON>, a city planning official of the <ORGANIZATION>Construction Ministry</ORGANIZATION>, said 
the 500-story building is one of a number of private plans by major 
construction firms to meet <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s growing need for office and apartment space. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Ohbayashi</ORGANIZATION> building would be able to accommodate 300,000 people. Aside from 
office space and residential units, it also would have space for hotels, 
hospitals, parks and convention centers. 
</P>
<P>
The design envisions elevators that would reach the top floor in 15 minutes. 
</P>
<P>
The building is shaped like a triangle, becoming smaller at the top to help it 
absorb shock waves. It would have a number of tunnels to let typhoon winds pass 
through rather than hitting the building with full force. 
</P>
<P>
The Japanese archipelago, in the world's most active seismic zone, is hit each 
year by some 1,000 tremors strong enough to be felt. In <DATE>1923</DATE>, <DATE>1946</DATE> and <DATE>1948</DATE>, 
quake deaths climbed into the thousands. The Great Kanto Earthquake of <DATE>1923</DATE> 
leveled vast areas of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Yokohama</LOCATION>, killing 140,000 people. 
</P>
<P>
About 25 typhoons develop in the region annually. 
</P>
<P>
In the early <DATE>1960s</DATE>, <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> developed a technique of building flexible structures 
to replace the rigid construction techniques favored for decades. 
</P>
<P>
Under the old concept, engineers built structures of up to 11 stories, using 
ferroconcrete solid pillars and walls to absorb shock and sustain the 
building's weight. The new concept called for making walls of slabs of 
reinforced concrete with several slits on the surface. Using the new method, 
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s 36-story, 482-foot-tall <LOCATION>Kasumigaseki</LOCATION> Building was completed in <DATE>1968</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Artist's conception of 500-story "Aeropolis 2001." Elevator trip to top 
would take 15 minutes. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
DESIGN; TECHNOLOGY; ARCHITECTURE; EARTHQUAKE SAFETY; HURRICANES -- JAPAN; 
EARTHQUAKES -- JAPAN; TOKYO (JAPAN) -- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT; OHBAYASHI 
CORP; OFFICE BUILDINGS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112089-0076 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 137481 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 20, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Business; Part D; Page 1; Column 5; Financial Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
864 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SELIG UNDAUNTED AFTER SELLING HIS SEATTLE SKYSCRAPER 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BILL DIETRICH, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When maverick <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> skyscraper developer <PERSON>Martin Selig</PERSON> fell behind on his 
light bill <DATE>last winter</DATE>, his competitors figured that he might be in trouble. 
And when nearly <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> in mortgage checks on five of his buildings bounced 
this <DATE>summer</DATE>, they were pretty well convinced. 
</P>
<P>
But by mid-October, <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> was back in the black, although he was no longer 
literally on top of this city's hot commercial real estate market. He solved 
his cash problems by agreeing to sell <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s tallest building, the 76-story 
<ORGANIZATION>Columbia Seafirst Center</ORGANIZATION>, for <MONEY>$354 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The sale was the latest twist in the unlikely saga of a controversial 
52-year-old businessman who started with nothing and who remains, even after 
the deal, <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s biggest property holder. 
</P>
<P>
The sale of the skyscraper to tenant <ORGANIZATION>Seafirst Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, a subsidiary of 
<ORGANIZATION>BankAmerica Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, was the biggest real estate sale in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state 
history. The 986-foot building was the tallest on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION> when it was 
completed in <DATE>1985</DATE>, although the <ORGANIZATION>First Interstate Tower</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> later 
topped it by 73 feet. 
</P>
<P>
Selig's practiced positivism was in full bloom after the sale. "The sale of 
this building is not a setback, it is a phenomenal victory," he proclaimed. 
</P>
<P>
After all, he reasoned, the sale price is <MONEY>$102 million</MONEY> more than the mortgage 
he holds. Just starting construction of the 1.5-million-square foot building in 
a city <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s size was "a significant risk," <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> said, and now it must be 
viewed as a winning gamble. 
</P>
<P>
But the necessity of selling, caused by depressed rents from a temporary glut 
of new skyscrapers, has to hurt. Selig once called the 10-year process to plan, 
build and fill the tower "an Olympian feat." 
</P>
<P>
"The Space Needle told people where <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> was," he once remarked. "<ORGANIZATION>Columbia 
Center</ORGANIZATION> tells people <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> has arrived." 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think there is another building of this size in the world owned by an 
individual," <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> boasted when the tower was completed. 
</P>
<P>
A flurry of new buildings from competitors forced <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> to keep his rents down 
at <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Center</ORGANIZATION> and at his other buildings, and postpone his bills. At one 
point he owed <MONEY>$640,000</MONEY> to <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> City Light for electricity, since paid. 
</P>
<P>
Both <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> and his skyscraper remain controversial. Critics have charged that 
the black-glass, curved edifice is out of scale with <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and that several 
other <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> buildings are too derivative of Houston-style architecture. The 
tower and the swank private club that <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> installed at the top was a project 
driven by ego instead of civic need, they sniped. 
</P>
<P>
Citizen activists who preferred the days when the horizon was dominated by 
<ORGANIZATION>Mount Rainier</ORGANIZATION> launched a campaign that resulted in new city zoning that makes 
it impossible to build a skyscraper as high as <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Center</ORGANIZATION> again. This 
year, voters also approved a lid on future downtown office construction. 
</P>
<P>
Enthusiasts, however, think that the spire nicely punctuates a newly cocky 
skyline in a city trying to cash in on <LOCATION>Pacific Rim</LOCATION> trade. 
</P>
<P>
Selig, an avid collector of modern art, said of his buildings: "You have to 
look at them as sculptures." 
</P>
<P>
"It was an opportunity," <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> said of the building code in force in the late 
<DATE>1970s</DATE>. "I wanted to build the maximum building I could build at that time." 
</P>
<P>
The present cap, he said, could make existing buildings more valuable but may 
hurt future downtown growth. 
</P>
<P>
The sale of the skyscraper has also provoked controversy. It was assessed for 
tax purposes at only <MONEY>$195 million</MONEY>. The big price tag in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s hot real 
estate market has prompted county officials to propose recalculating 
assessments of all commercial and residential properties. 
</P>
<P>
Turmoil is nothing new to <PERSON>Selig</PERSON>. He and his parents emigrated to the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> in <DATE>1940</DATE> as Jewish refugees from <LOCATION>Nazi Germany</LOCATION>, when he was 3 years old. 
</P>
<P>
His drive was apparent early. Shortly before the <DATE>1962</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Seattle World</ORGANIZATION>'s Fair, he 
gave construction workers some Space Needle sweat shirts that he was hawking in 
return for a ride to the top of the new landmark. And he bought his first 
borrowed part of the down payment and sold the property a year later for a good 
profit. 
</P>
<P>
With aggressive borrowing, attention to construction details and personal 
service to tenants, he has averaged about one new building per year since the 
mid-1960s. 
</P>
<P>
The result is a local empire of big office buildings that he puts in "the high 
20s" with an assessed value of more than half <MONEY>a billion dollars</MONEY>. Observers 
believe that the true market value of his holdings is at least <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> higher. 
</P>
<P>
But while immensely successful, <PERSON>Selig</PERSON> has remained somewhat aloof from 
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s clubby establishment. He keeps a low profile on most civic issues, 
will not discuss his personal life with the media (he is married with two 
children) and is reluctant to talk about what makes him tick. 
</P>
<P>
Instead, he concentrates on making <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>'s profile higher with buildings. "I 
love <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> and am pleased to be able to play such an active role in its 
evolution," he said in a statement issued with the sale. 
</P>
<P>
Plans are under way for additional Selig buildings of 10, 19 and 36 stories. 
"We absolutely are still here," he said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Selig sold the 76-story Columbia Seafirst Center for $354 million. 
Associated Press; Photo, Martin Selig 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SELIG, MARTIN; SEAFIRST CORP; PROPERTY SALES; HIGH RISE BUILDINGS; REAL ESTATE 
INDUSTRY -- WASHINGTON (STATE); SEATTLE (WA) 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06011196 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06011196 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Good news to some; bad news for others. It depends on your point of view.;   
Those two planned 12-story towers in central Fremont billed as the future
downtown "focus" are just about ready for construction. The first tower should
rise on former ranch land at the corner of California Street and Walnut Avenue
later this year.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TOWERING PROGRESS VIEWED WITH REGRET  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Inside Our Towns  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "You should see activity there in <DATE>March</DATE> and ground-breaking in <DATE>mid-April</DATE>,"
said <PERSON>Monty Goodell</PERSON>, general partner of One Pacific Plaza.;    But this complex
with its 12-story towers -- the tallest buildings in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> -- will cut off
the view of the eastern  hills for the folks in our third floor MercNews
office across <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> Street. Some people are really steamed.;    "They'll
never build that in our lifetime," said one reporter.;    But progress marches
on.;    The four-acre <MONEY>$72</MONEY> to <MONEY>$75 million</MONEY> project was approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Fremont
City Council</ORGANIZATION> three years ago. It has taken that long to line up the finances
and attract prospective tenants.;    <PERSON>Goodell</PERSON> said that construction will be
done in two stages. The first, which will cost about <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>, will bring
<LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> one 12-story building with two levels of upscale shopping. Goodell
likened the planned development to the Embarcadero shopping center in <LOCATION>San
Francisco</LOCATION>. The second stage will be the second tower which will be either for
offices or for a hotel, depending on the market in two years. Two restaurants
are also planned.;    "We're getting a lot of calls from hotels," <PERSON>Goodell</PERSON> 
said. Interest is also high in the retail shops and view office space. He said
that <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of the tenants are lined up for phase one.;    <PERSON>Goodell</PERSON> said
that the first stage of construction will require the removal of the top 12
feet of earth to make way for the underground garage. Goodell is talking with
a highway builder who can use some dirt for fill.;    <PERSON>Partners Goodell</PERSON>, his
cousin <PERSON>Ralph Goodell</PERSON>, who is the architect, and investor <PERSON>Sam Fung</PERSON> bought out
<PERSON>Mash Khan</PERSON>, who was the original developer on the project.;    Other financing
is coming through a Los Angeles-based investment fund, <PERSON>Goodell</PERSON> said.;    It's
probably too late for us to get our money in.;    "We don't need investors
anymore," <PERSON>Goodell</PERSON> said.;    But if you want to see the great view from the
MercNews, y'all come over. But do it before mid-April.; HIGH IN <LOCATION>FREMONT</LOCATION>: Tall
buildings make some people nervous. Others complain that because they are so
tall they are out of place. So-o-o-o, while the <DATE>1986</DATE> architects' drawing for
One Pacific Plaza is viewed from eye level showing very tall buildings, the
<DATE>1991</DATE> updated drawings give you the view a passing hawk might have. The result:
12 stories looks less imposing.; NAMES, NAMES, NAMES: <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>M.C. Hammer</ORGANIZATION> is
a Grammy nominee for his "U Can't Touch This." The 33rd annual award show will
be telecast from <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Radio City Music Hall</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>Feb. 20</DATE> on CBS . . .
They are bragging about 4th grader Ria <PERSON>Denise Quiazon</PERSON> over at <ORGANIZATION>Pioneer
Elementary</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Union City</LOCATION>. Ria was among the 100 finalists chosen from 250,000
students across the country who entered books in the <DATE>1990</DATE> contest sponsored by
the <ORGANIZATION>Landmark Editions, Inc.</ORGANIZATION> publishing house of <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mo</LOCATION>. She received
an Award for Achievement certificate for her effort. Ria's book in entitled
"The Impossible Dream."  Helping her with it were her 3rd grade teacher <PERSON>Cathy
Schoon</PERSON> and <PERSON>Janice Gill</PERSON>, a librarian at Pioneer. Ria said she plans to do
another book this year.; DEADLINE TODAY: Today is the deadline for
reservations for the <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> third annual Human Services Awards Program
sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>Fremont Human Relations Commission</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>United Way</ORGANIZATION>. The
program is from noon to <TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> at Choices, <DATE>5399</DATE> <ORGANIZATION>Farwell Place</ORGANIZATION>. Awards are
given to people or groups who have contributed in the categories of community
action, human services, Intercultural affairs and humanitarian endeavors.
Tickets are <MONEY>$25</MONEY>. To make reservations or to get more information, call <PERSON>Fern
Lane</PERSON> at (415) 745-2807.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Dennis Rockstroh column  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910111  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  674  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, January 11, 1991
00011196,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890821-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-21-89 1012EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r f PM-ManhattanDevelopment 1stLd-Writethru   08-21 0832</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Manhattan Development, 1st Ld-Writethru,0851</SECOND>
<HEAD>Developers Look Under Ground, Under Water, Anywhere to Build Up</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 5th graf, `Developers have...', with 2 grafs to clarify
how air rights work. Picks up 6th graf, `On street...'. SUBS 15th graf,
`On the...'. to recast.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA ROSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION>, where even the air is for sale,
developers are wheeling and dealing to keep building higher and
denser on an island that isn't getting any bigger.
   <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON> wants to use the rights he owns to land under the
<LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> to create the world's tallest building. Across town,
the owner of the air space above <LOCATION>Grand Central Terminal</LOCATION> has been
battling for more than 11 years to convert it to glass, steel, and
cash on the ground.
   ``It's a logical extension of the cleverness of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>
developers' lawyers,'' says <PERSON>Steve Robinson</PERSON>, co-chairman of
<LOCATION>Westpride</LOCATION>, a community organization fighting excessive development.
``They push the limits, they invent new mechanisms, they try
anything that may have a shot at working, because there are so many
dollars at stake.''
   Dozens of office and apartment buildings are going up in <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION>'s midtown area alone, especially around Times Square.
   Under the city's complex zoning laws, the sale of air rights has
become commonplace. It works this way: An investor owns, say, a
five-story building in an area where 10-story buildings are allowed.
He or she ``sells'' the unused air space to a neighbor, who then
gets the right to build a 15-story building. With air rights
purchases and other maneuvers, such as offering to build public
plazas or low-cost housing in exchange for waiver of size
restrictions, developers have managed to put up bigger buildings
than the zoning law would otherwise allow. But such actions have
raised cries of foul.
   ``On street corners all over <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> ... you have
disproportionately large buildings going up,'' said <PERSON>Sandor E. Katz</PERSON>
of the <ORGANIZATION>Women's City Club</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, a civic organization. ``There
needs to be some absolute limit on the amount of additional floor
area that can be imposed on any one lot.''
   Civic groups are focusing on <LOCATION>Trump City</LOCATION>, the billionaire
developer's massive West Side project. <PERSON>Katz</PERSON> calls it ``the most
dramatic single example of the kind of monstrous result you can get
by the accumulation of development rights.''
   Westpride targeted it from early on.
   ``If we are able to have an impact on what <ORGANIZATION>Trump</ORGANIZATION> proposes, then
other developers in the city would begin to get the signal,'' says
<PERSON>Robinson</PERSON>.
   On 76 acres of old railroad yards along the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> between
59th and 72nd streets, the largest undeveloped land parcel in the
city, <LOCATION>Trump City</LOCATION> would include a 150-story structure and 13 other
buildings ranging from 13 to 60 floors. Besides offices, hotel space
and apartments, there would be an 800,000-square-foot shopping mall.
   Westpride says the 7,600 housing units would heavily overburden
the neighborhood's schools and sewers, and that the tower, the
world's tallest, would cast a shadow across the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Central Park</ORGANIZATION>. Trump's people say there are plenty of sewers and
schools, and that the shadow would not be that obtrusive in a city
full of skyscrapers.
   Trump wants to transfer to his shoreline property the development
rights he owns to 19 acres under the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION>, a holdover from
the days when waterfront industry extended onto the piers.
   <PERSON>William Valletta</PERSON>, counsel to the <ORGANIZATION>Department of City Planning</ORGANIZATION>,
said that the city's zoning law allows a lot's overall size _
including underwater rights _ to be the basis for determining the
size limits of a building. Zoning reformers want to get rid of that
provision.
   Trump hopes to start building in mid-1990.
   On the <LOCATION>East Side</LOCATION>, developers are hoping to use the air rights
created by the space above the <ORGANIZATION>Grand Central</ORGANIZATION> commuter train terminal
to build the city's fourth-largest skyscraper nearby.
   In <DATE>1978</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> backed the city in blocking <ORGANIZATION>Grand
Central</ORGANIZATION>'s owner, the <ORGANIZATION>Penn Central Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, from building a 53-story
office tower atop the landmark train station.
   But the court said it might reconsider if <ORGANIZATION>Penn Central</ORGANIZATION> found it
couldn't use the leftover development rights on the station site or
get compensation by transferring them, according to a <ORGANIZATION>Penn Central</ORGANIZATION>
attorney.
   In <DATE>1983</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Penn Central</ORGANIZATION> contracted to sell up to 1.5 million square
feet of air rights to 383 <ORGANIZATION>Madison Associates</ORGANIZATION>, which wants to use
about half of the rights for a 74-story building at its address
several blocks away.
   The zoning law allows such transfers from a landmark to an
adjacent lot. <ORGANIZATION>Penn Central</ORGANIZATION> owns the underground land, used for train
tracks, between the terminal and <PERSON>383 Madison</PERSON>, and it and the
developers hope the rights to this land will qualify the properties
as adjacent, thus facilitating the transfer.
   The local community board rejected the 383 Madison Ave. proposal
in <DATE>June</DATE>, but it could be overturned by the city <ORGANIZATION>Planning Commission</ORGANIZATION>,
which is voting on the plan this week.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA041789-0047 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 45143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
April 17, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1929 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TOWERING AMBITIONS; 
</P>
<P>
CITY'S SEARCH FOR AN IMAGE IS LOOKING UP 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By FRANK CLIFFORD, Times Urban Affairs Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A downtown in search of a more fashionable face can look out at the world with 
a new hauteur today, as the sleek, pale contours of a new and conspicuously 
different skyscraper rise in cool contrast to the city's bulky skyline. 
</P>
<P>
This horizontal city, where buildings over 13 stories were prohibited until 
<DATE>1957</DATE>, has become home to the tallest building on the <LOCATION>West Coast</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The 73-story tower is the work of <ORGANIZATION>I.M. Pei &amp; Partners</ORGANIZATION> and is one of a score 
of giant office buildings being shaped for <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> by well-known 
architects, including <PERSON>Michael Graves</PERSON>, <PERSON>Cesar Pelli</PERSON>, <PERSON>Arthur Erickson</PERSON>, <PERSON>Helmut Jahn</PERSON> 
and others. 
</P>
<P>
The new crop of designer skyscrapers is part of a bid for visual distinction 
that has long eluded downtown <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. Flush with foreign money and eager 
for the world's approval, the city is anxious to shed any traces of 
provincialism. At the same time, the city is hoping to create a landscape in 
which a lot more people will want to live. With less than <PERCENT>2%</PERCENT> of the people who 
work downtown living there, habitability has become a major issue. 
</P>
<P>
Take care of the problem, and local leaders believe they can realize their goal 
of a downtown with nearly twice its current working population of 276,000 and 
twice the commercial space of downtown <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>. (<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> now has 
slightly less than <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>.) With office growth averaging about 1 million 
square feet a year and the occupancy rate running about <PERCENT>80%</PERCENT>, the boosters' 
dream of a skyline that stretches from Union Station to <ORGANIZATION>USC</ORGANIZATION> may not be all that 
fanciful. 
</P>
<P>
In the works for nearly 10 years, the tower points to the city's growing 
preoccupation with its image and its confusion over what the image ought to be. 
</P>
<P>
On one side are those who say the city needs a majestic skyline, like <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
or <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, if it is going to be recognized as a world capital. <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> 
historian <PERSON>Kevin Starr</PERSON> said recently that one reason <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> has not been 
taken as seriously as other cities its size is because its large buildings are 
not especially impressive. Starr suggested that a city better known for zany 
architecture -- the original <PERSON>Brown Derby</PERSON> restaurant shaped like a hat, 
<ORGANIZATION>Grauman</ORGANIZATION>'s Chinese Theater, the Tail of the Pup hot dog stand -- could do with a 
make-over. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Some Dubiousness 
</P>
<P>
But there are also people who say that the rush to build modish skyscrapers, 
like <PERSON>Pei</PERSON>'s tower, will superimpose an anonymous big-city look on a town famous 
for the personality of its smaller buildings. Critics wonder why a Western city 
with a long legacy of original architecture should look eastward for its 
inspiration. 
</P>
<P>
Pei's architects said that as they worked on plans for the new tower, they 
looked east and west, at buildings rich in classical ornamentation and at those 
with very little detailing. The architects said they hung up pictures of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Chrysler Building</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Empire State Building</ORGANIZATION>. But they said they also paid 
close attention to the Central Library -- "a strong, spare building, very 
authoritative and very Western," in the words of <PERSON>Henry N. Cobb</PERSON>, the architect 
in <LOCATION>Pei</LOCATION>'s firm most responsible for designing the tower. 
</P>
<P>
Cobb and his colleagues said they wanted to put up a building that was both 
showy and self-effacing. 
</P>
<P>
"We wanted to make a building that was more spirited than many big buildings 
downtown, but one that did not threaten the primacy of the library," <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In other words, <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON> set out to build the tallest building west of <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>, a 
<MONEY>$350-million</MONEY> skyscraper standing a fifth of a mile high, that would not 
overshadow the three-story structure across the street. 
</P>
<P>
Cobb has reason to be sensitive about the library. Few buildings in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> 
have so endeared themselves to the public. The preservation of the library has 
been a cause celebre for at least 25 years. Moreover, its fate and that of the 
tower are closely linked. Approval of the tower was contingent on a commitment 
by the developer, <PERSON>Maguire Thomas Partners</PERSON>, to underwrite <MONEY>$110 million</MONEY> of the 
cost of preserving and expanding the library. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Focus on the Ground 
</P>
<P>
As the tower has risen to its full height, it has become clear that its success 
will be gauged as much by the way it meets the ground around it as how it 
greets the sky. 
</P>
<P>
"The building is going to be judged on how it enhances the environment around 
it as opposed to how it shows off at the top. The top 60 feet belongs to a few 
people. The bottom 60 feet belongs to everyone," said <PERSON>Richard Weinstein</PERSON>, dean 
of the <ORGANIZATION>UCLA School of Architecture and Urban Design</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's at the bottom that the building will achieve its uniqueness, if it is 
going to, in its response to the weather, to the street-scape, to the library . 
. . to those things that are distinctly <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>," <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
When completed, the tower and a 54-story neighbor that also is a <PERSON>Maguire Thomas</PERSON> 
project will bring 8,000 to 10,000 people, about 2,000 cars, and more than 3 
million square feet of development to the three-block neighborhood now known as 
<ORGANIZATION>Library Square</ORGANIZATION>. Most of the people who will work there are part of the city's 
expanding financial service sector. 
</P>
<P>
There will be no public viewing deck at the top of the tower. The bottom is 
where the developers will try to please the public. There, they have taken on 
the daunting challenge of trying to provide downtown <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> with a popular 
outdoor gathering place. 
</P>
<P>
Creating a colorful street-scape where people of all walks of life mix easily 
and often, where there is a little fun in the air, has proved to be one of the 
more elusive goals for planners and developers who want to make the downtown an 
enjoyable place to work and live. 
</P>
<P>
In <PERSON>Weinstein</PERSON>'s words, the downtown badly needs "an extraordinary public place." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Picking a Location 
</P>
<P>
If one can be created, Library Square would be an appropriate spot. 
</P>
<P>
Fronting on 5th Street between Flower and Grand, the new tower perches on a 
50-foot rise that symbolizes a cultural divide between the granite and glass 
canyons of the <ORGANIZATION>Bunker Hill Financial District</ORGANIZATION> and the lower downtown, a seedier 
if livelier place, that stretches north from the apparel and jewelry marts to 
<LOCATION>Broadway</LOCATION>, Skid Row and <ORGANIZATION>City Hall</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The challenge to <PERSON>Maguire Thomas</PERSON> and their architects is to create a link 
between the two sectors. 
</P>
<P>
The developers have responded with the kind of exotic gesture one might have 
expected of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in an earlier time, when the city dreamed of itself as 
a <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> oasis, created its own <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> and built houses to look like 
Moorish palaces. 
</P>
<P>
Library Square looks to <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> for its inspiration. A lavish outdoor stairway 
meant to recall <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>'s Spanish Steps will wend its way 50 feet down from the 
top of the hill, around the curved base of the tower to 5th Street and a 
walkway leading to the library's west lawn. According to designer <PERSON>Lawrence 
Halprin</PERSON>, cafes and kiosks will border one side of the stairway, which will be 
broken into a series of terraces with places to sit and eat. 
</P>
<P>
The steps, which won't be finished for several months, are based on one of the 
most striking architectural elements in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> and one of that city's most 
romantic settings. In <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>, unlike <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION>, the steps will be notched 
between two giant buildings, the new tower and an existing high-rise office 
building next door. This being a modern city, the steps will be flanked by 
escalators. And, here, the steps will end rather abruptly against a busy 
thoroughfare, something that the Spanish Steps, descending into a long piazza, 
don't have to contend with. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Halprin</PERSON>'s plan has generated excitement downtown and a bit of grumbling. 
</P>
<P>
"Too baroque, too grandiose, too voluptuous, entirely too much going on," said 
<PERSON>Merry Norris</PERSON>, who chairs the city's <ORGANIZATION>Cultural Affairs Commission</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Topping It Off 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>Pei</PERSON>'s staff prepares to complete the new tower with its illuminated crown, 
they too say the bottom of the building is the most important part of the 
project. 
</P>
<P>
"The base will be considered the most notable aspect of the building when the 
whole thing is done," <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
He was referring not just to the steps but to his own efforts at the foot of 
the tower. Cobb said he wanted to get away from the fortress facades typical of 
many big buildings downtown and to avoid "a confrontational stance" toward the 
library. 
</P>
<P>
"We wanted a building that came to the street facing several directions, and 
not staring stiffly in a flat-faced way that would challenge the primacy of the 
library," <PERSON>Cobb</PERSON> said. At the same time, he said, he did not want a round 
building. "Round buildings are self-centered. We were not interested in being 
the center of everything. We were trying to make a welcoming gesture." 
</P>
<P>
The shape that evolved is an interlocking series of planes and curves. From its 
glass crown, the building steps down, its competing geometries facing off at 
corners, terraces and ledges. At the base, the tower's granite finish gives way 
to colonnades of glass that <ORGANIZATION>Cobb</ORGANIZATION> hopes will create a feeling of transparency 
and openness. 
</P>
<P>
As critics and other architects watch the tower take shape, they say the 
business community is getting what it wanted, a thoughtfully conceived, sleekly 
tailored contemporary skyscraper with an aura of the past about it. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a late-modern office tower that recalls the romantic era of American 
skyscraper building," said <PERSON>John Kaliski</PERSON>, principal architect for the city's 
<ORGANIZATION>Community Redevelopment Agency</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Fulfilling Hopes 
</P>
<P>
The building may also turn out to be the pacesetter that people hoped it would 
be. 
</P>
<P>
The sculpted facades and classical allusions evident in the plans of a dozen or 
more office buildings, now in the works, suggest that the skyline will be more 
varied than ever before. 
</P>
<P>
"There is no doubt at all that the design stakes have been raised," <PERSON>Kaliski</PERSON> 
said. "<LOCATION>L.A.</LOCATION> is going to have a skyline as up to date as anywhere in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>" 
</P>
<P>
