<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0082 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 1048EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-VanGoghRecord-List 2ndLd-Writethru a0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Van Gogh Record-List, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0558,0322</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Van Gogh Record, Bjt</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: CORRECTS transposed figures in 8th item.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a list of the top 17 prices paid for paintings at
the world's major auction houses:
   1. ``Portrait of Dr. Gachet'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$82.5
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 15, 1990</DATE>.
   2. ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>.
   3. ``Les Noches de Pierrette'' (<ORGANIZATION>Pierrette</ORGANIZATION>'s Wedding) by <PERSON>Pablo
Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY>, sold by Drouot-Montaigne, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> (bid from
the Bunkamura Shibuya auction house in <LOCATION>Toyko</LOCATION> in a televised
satellite hook-up), <DATE>Nov. 30, 1989</DATE>.
   4. ``Yo Picasso'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   5. ``Au Lapin Agile'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   6. ``Sunflowers'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>.
   7. ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>November 28, 1988</DATE>.
   8. ``Portrait of Duke Cosimo D'Medici'' by <ORGANIZATION>Pontormo</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$35.2
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 31, 1989</DATE>.
   9. ``The Mirror'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   10. ``Maternity'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>.
   11. ``Dans La Prairie'' (``In the Meadow'') by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>;
<MONEY>$24.59 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>.
   12. ``Mata <ORGANIZATION>Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times)'' by <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.2
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   13. ``Interchange'' by <ORGANIZATION>Willem de Kooning</ORGANIZATION>; <MONEY>$20.6 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 8, 1989</DATE>.
   14. ``The Trinquetaille Bridge'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>.
   15. ``Mere et Enfant'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$18.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900515-0193 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-15-90 2043EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a BC-Paintings-TopPrices     05-15 0312</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Paintings-Top Prices,0328</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Auction Record</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a list of the top 15 prices paid for paintings at
the world's major auction houses:
   1. ``Portrait of Dr. Gachet'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$82.5
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 15, 1990</DATE>.
   2. ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>.
   3. ``Les Noches de Pierrette'' (<ORGANIZATION>Pierrette</ORGANIZATION>'s Wedding) by <PERSON>Pablo
Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY>, sold by Drouot-Montaigne, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> (bid from
the Bunkamura Shibuya auction house in <LOCATION>Toyko</LOCATION> in a televised
satellite hook-up), <DATE>Nov. 30, 1989</DATE>.
   4. ``Yo Picasso'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   5. ``Au Lapin Agile'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   6. ``Sunflowers'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>.
   7. ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>November 28, 1988</DATE>.
   8. ``The Mirror'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   9. ``Maternity'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>.
   10. ``Dans La Prairie'' (``In the Meadow'') by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>;
<MONEY>$24.59 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>.
   10. ``Mata <ORGANIZATION>Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times)'' by <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.2
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   11. ``Interchange'' by <ORGANIZATION>Willem de Kooning</ORGANIZATION>; <MONEY>$20.6 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 8, 1989</DATE>.
   12. ``The Trinquetaille Bridge'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>.
   13. ``Mere et Enfant'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$18.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   14. ``La Promenade'' by <ORGANIZATION>Pierre-Auguste Renoir</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$17.6 million</MONEY>,
sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 3, 1989</DATE>.
   15. ``False Start'' by <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON>; <MONEY>$17.05 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900517-0199 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-90 2151EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ArtAuction-List 1stLd-Writethru a0646 05-17 0336</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Art Auction-List, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0646,0349</SECOND>
<HEAD>Highest Prices for Paintings</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Updates with sale of Renoir painting for second-highest
price.</NOTE>
<HEAD>With AM-Art Auction, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a list of the top prices paid for paintings at the
world's major auction houses.
   1. ``Portrait of Dr. Gachet'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$82.5
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 15, 1990</DATE>.
   2. ``Au Moulin de la Galette'' by <PERSON>Pierre Auguste Renoir</PERSON>; <MONEY>$78.1
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 17, 1990</DATE>.
   3. ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>.
   4. ``Les Noches de Pierrette'' (<ORGANIZATION>Pierrette</ORGANIZATION>'s Wedding) by <PERSON>Pablo
Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY>, sold by Drouot-Montaigne, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> (bid from
the Bunkamura Shibuya auction house in <LOCATION>Toyko</LOCATION> in a televised
satellite hook-up), <DATE>Nov. 30, 1989</DATE>.
   5. ``Yo Picasso'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   6. ``Au Lapin Agile'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   7. ``Sunflowers'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>.
   8. ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>November 28, 1988</DATE>.
   9. ``Portrait of Duke Cosimo D'Medici'' by <ORGANIZATION>Pontormo</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$35.2
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 31, 1989</DATE>.
   10. ``The Mirror'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
   11. ``Maternity'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>.
   12. ``Dans La Prairie'' (``In the Meadow'') by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>;
<MONEY>$24.59 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>.
   13. ``Mata <ORGANIZATION>Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times)'' by <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.2
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   14. ``Interchange'' by <ORGANIZATION>Willem de Kooning</ORGANIZATION>; <MONEY>$20.6 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 8, 1989</DATE>.
   15. ``The Trinquetaille Bridge'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>.
   16. ``Mere et Enfant'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$18.7 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891116-0043 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-16-89 0538EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ArtSale     11-16 0558</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Art Sale,0583</SECOND>
<HEAD>Picasso Sells for $40.7 Million</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA ROSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In <DATE>1905</DATE>, <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON> painted ``Au Lapin
Agile,'' a Parisian tavern scene, for his suppers. In <DATE>1989</DATE>,
philanthropist <PERSON>Walter Annenberg</PERSON> bought it for <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>.
   The painting, in which <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> depicts himself as a harlequin,
had been described by <PERSON>John L. Marion</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>North
America</LOCATION>, as the most important 20th-century picture to come up for
auction.
   <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>'s price fell within the presale estimate, but left it
behind another famous self-portrait painted four years earlier.
``Yo Picasso'' sold for <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY> at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in <DATE>May</DATE>, a
record for the artist and more than double its presale estimate.
   The record for any work of art _ <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> _ was set in <DATE>1987</DATE>
for <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Irises.''
   ``We were a little disappointed it didn't pass `Yo Picasso,'''
said <PERSON>John Payson</PERSON>, whose sister, <PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, consigned ``Au
Lapin Agile.''
   Payson's and <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON>'s mother, art collector and former
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets owner <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, acquired the painting in
<DATE>1952</DATE> for <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY>.
   She displayed it in her <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION> home and bequeathed it to
her daughter. ``Irises'' also came from the collection.
   <PERSON>John Payson</PERSON> had said his sister offered the Picasso because the
prices commanded by ``Irises'' and ``Yo Picasso'' made her ``a bit
nervous having the painting in her house.''
   <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON> said she would establish a foundation for medical
research and education with part of the proceeds.
   Annenberg, of <LOCATION>Rancho Mirage</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, the former <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador
to <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and friend of former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, was in the auction
house but bid by phone, said <PERSON>Diana Brooks</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's
North America</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> said <PERSON>Annenberg</PERSON>'s collection had ``just about everything
but a great Picasso.''
   While subdued in comparison with other recent auctions,
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s sale drew an estimated 1,500 people, totaled
<MONEY>$269.5 million</MONEY> and set records for 12 artists.
   Among other highlights:
   _<PERSON>Picasso</PERSON>'s ``The Mirror,'' one of a series of portraits of
sleeping women done in <DATE>1932</DATE>, sold for <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY> to Japanese
dealer <PERSON>Shigeki Kameyama</PERSON>.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Mere et Enfant,'' which dates from <DATE>1921</DATE> when the
artist's son was born, sold for <MONEY>$18.7 million</MONEY> to a private Japanese
collector.
   _<PERSON>Edouard Manet</PERSON>'s ``La Promenade'' sold for <MONEY>$14.8 million</MONEY> to a
Japanese dealer.
   _<PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Quarry near Saint-Remy,'' a landscape painted in
<DATE>1889</DATE>, was sold for <MONEY>$11.5 million</MONEY> to a Japanese dealer.
   All prices include a <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> premium.
   `Young Girls at the Piano,'' a Renoir pastel produced in <DATE>1892</DATE> on
commission from the French government, failed to sell. The <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>
had been expected to bring up to <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, but the high bid was
<MONEY>$17.5 million</MONEY>.
   ``Au Lapin Agile,'' which means the agile rabbit, was the name
of the tavern frequented by <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>.
   He painted ``Au Lapin Agile'' when he was 25. It shows him and a
woman _ model <PERSON>Germaine Pichot</PERSON> _ standing at a bar, brooding and
disenchanted with one another. Picasso had blamed <PERSON>Pichot</PERSON> for
causing his best friend's suicide.
   ``The big question in the picture is whether or not at the time
it was painted <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> was actually having an affair with this
woman,'' <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON> said.
   A photograph from the period shows the painting hanging unframed
in a bar.
   ``I painted it in exchange for free meals and drinks,'' <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>
once said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891115-0210 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-15-89 2253EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-ArtSale 2ndLd-Writethru a0799 11-15 0581</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Art Sale, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0799,0596</SECOND>
<HEAD>Picasso Works Put Up For Auction</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 3rd graf with 2 grafs to CORRECT spelling of name to Annenberg,
sted Annenburg, UPDATE that painting will go to his private collection.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BARBARA ROSEN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A scene in a Parisian tavern that <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>
painted when he was 25 in exchange for free meals and drinks sold
for <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY> at auction <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   The <DATE>1905</DATE> painting ``Au Lapin Agile,'' in which <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> depicts
himself as a harlequin, is ``the most important 20th-century
picture to come up for auction,'' said <PERSON>John L. Marion</PERSON>, chairman of
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>.
   ``It goes to the <ORGANIZATION>Annenberg Collection</ORGANIZATION>,'' <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> said as he
hammered down the sale. Southeby's had predicted the work would
fetch <MONEY>$35 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>.
   The auction house said the painting will go to the private
collection of <PERSON>Walter Annenberg</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Rancho Mirage</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, the
philanthropist and former owner of TV Guide magazine, a close
friend of former President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>.
   The painting was consigned by <PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, daughter of art
collector <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, who acquired it in <DATE>1952</DATE> and hung it
in her <LOCATION>Manhasset</LOCATION> home. <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON> said in a statement she felt
``Au Lapin Agile'' has become too valuable a painting to keep.
   ``I plan to establish a foundation for medical research and
education with part of the proceeds,'' she added.
   ``Au Lapin Agile'' was painted four years after another famous
self-portrait, ``Yo Picasso,'' which sold for <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY> at
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in <DATE>May</DATE>. That was a record for the artist and more than
double its presale estimate.
   The record for any work of art _ <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> _ was set in <DATE>1987</DATE>
for <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Irises,'' also from the <LOCATION>Payson</LOCATION> collection.
   Several other paintings were on the block <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>:
   _<ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s ``The Mirror,'' one of a series of portraits of
sleeping women done in <DATE>1932</DATE>, was expected to bring up to <MONEY>$25
million</MONEY>.
   _``Mere et Enfant,'' which dates from <DATE>1921</DATE> _ the year of the
birth of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s son _ is estimated at up to <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY>.
   _A Renoir pastel, ``Young Girls at the Piano,'' produced in <DATE>1892</DATE>
on a commission from the French government, did not sell <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
It had been expected to bring up to <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>.
   _<PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Quarry near Saint-Remy,'' a landscape painted in
<DATE>1889</DATE>, was estimated to bring up to <MONEY>$15 million</MONEY>.
   _Major pieces by <PERSON>Piet Mondrian</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Paul Klee</PERSON>, <PERSON>Willem de
Kooning</PERSON>, <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON> and <PERSON>Joan Miro</PERSON> were being auctioned from the
collection of the late <PERSON>Edgar Kaufmann Jr</PERSON>. The 21 pieces were
expected to bring between <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Diane Brooks</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s president, described ``Au Lapin Agile''
as a large, powerful, serious painting, one of the most important
of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s rose period.
   In addition, she said, ``The subject has a story behind it.''
   Done when he was 25, the painting shows <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> and a woman _
model <PERSON>Germaine Pichot</PERSON> _ standing at a bar, brooding and obviously
disenchanted with one another.
   Picasso blamed <PERSON>Pichot</PERSON> as being the cause of his best friend's
suicide four years earlier.
   ``The big question in the picture is whether or not at the time
it was painted <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> was actually having an affair with this
woman himself,'' <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON> said.
   In the background is <PERSON>Frederic Gerard</PERSON>, the owner of the tavern
<ORGANIZATION>Lapin Agile</ORGANIZATION> (Sprightly Rabbit) and the painting's first owner. A
photograph from the period shows the painting hanging unframed in
the bar.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA051690-0103 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 219633 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 16, 1990, Wednesday, Southland Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 1; Column 2; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
729 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
VAN GOGH PAINTING SELLS AT RECORD $82.5 MILLION; 
</P>
<P>
ART: 'PORTRAIT OF DR. GACHET' IS AUCTIONED TO A JAPANESE BUYER. THE PREVIOUS 
HIGH PRICE WAS $53.9 MILLION. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Portrait of Dr. Gachet" stunned the art market <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> when 
it was auctioned for <MONEY>$82.5 million</MONEY>, shattering the world record price for a 
painting by more than <MONEY>$28 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The price was double the estimate by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, a spokeswoman for the auction 
house said. 
</P>
<P>
"This is by far the world's most expensive painting," surpassing the previous 
auction record of <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> bid by Australian businessman Alan Bond for Van 
Gogh's "Irises" in <DATE>November, 1987</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The money for Bond's bid was largely borrowed from <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, the house that 
handled the auction. The debt-ridden Bond was eventually forced to sell the 
painting for an undisclosed price to the <ORGANIZATION>J. Paul Getty Museum of Malibu</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The unidentified Japanese bidder was in the room during the about 10 minutes of 
bidding that opened at <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>, <PERSON>Britman</PERSON> said. Toward the end of bidding, 
just two people were vying for the painting, she said. 
</P>
<P>
"Portrait of <PERSON>Dr. Gachet</PERSON>" was painted six weeks before <PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON> committed 
suicide in <DATE>1890</DATE>. Dr. <PERSON>Paul-Ferdinand Gachet</PERSON> tended Van Gogh in the weeks before 
his death. 
</P>
<P>
The record price quashed all reports of an art market in recession after <DATE>last 
week</DATE>'s disappointing contemporary sales. More than <PERCENT>35%</PERCENT> of the works had gone 
unsold last week. 
</P>
<P>
The crowd gasped when the bidding reached <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
It had been expected to fetch between <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> and <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> at a sale of 
major works by Impressionist and Modern artists. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a great painting," said <LOCATION>Manhattan</LOCATION> art dealer <PERSON>Richard Feigen</PERSON>. "It's by a 
rare artist. It's in fine condition. There are practically no paintings like it 
in private hands." 
</P>
<P>
After the bidding, which was tensely conducted between the Japanese dealer and 
a telephone bidder, the jam-packed gallery broke into a standing ovation, 
prompting auctioneer <PERSON>Christopher Burge</PERSON> to pound his gavel to control the house. 
</P>
<P>
The painting was lent to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in <DATE>1984</DATE>. It is from the 
collection of <PERSON>Siegfried Kramarsky</PERSON>, a German-born <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> banker who died in 
<DATE>1961</DATE>. It was put on the block by a trust created under his will. 
</P>
<P>
In a letter to artist <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>, Van Gogh wrote on <DATE>June 16</DATE> that he had 
painted <PERSON>Gachet</PERSON> "with the heart-broken expression of our time" and that it was 
"not destined to be understood." 
</P>
<P>
Gachet, a practitioner of homeopathic medicine, was Van Gogh's friend and 
physician. He was also close to other Impressionist painters of the time. 
</P>
<P>
Van Gogh painted a second, slightly larger version of the portrait, which hangs 
in the <ORGANIZATION>Musee d'Orsay</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. It lacks the details of the <PERSON>Kramarsky</PERSON> painting 
and its colors are flatter. 
</P>
<P>
Another Van Gogh from the <PERSON>Kramarsky</PERSON> collection was auctioned in <DATE>1987</DATE> for <MONEY>$20.24 
million</MONEY>. It too had been lent to the Metropolitan. 
</P>
<P>
The next-highest prices paid for paintings at the world's major auction houses 
are: 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Les Noches de Pierrette" (<ORGANIZATION>Pierrette</ORGANIZATION>'s Wedding) by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$48.9 
million</MONEY>, sold by Drouot-Montaigne, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> (bid from the Bunkamura Shibuya 
auction house in <LOCATION>Toyko</LOCATION> in a televised satellite hook-up), <DATE>Nov. 30, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Yo Picasso" by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 
<DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Au Lapin Agile" by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Sunflowers" by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, 
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Acrobat and Young Harlequin" by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46 million</MONEY>, sold by 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 28, 1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "The Mirror" by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 
<DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Maternity" by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 
<DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Dans La Prairie" ("In the Meadow") by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.59 million</MONEY>, sold 
by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Mata <ORGANIZATION>Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times)" by <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.2 million</MONEY>, sold by 
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Interchange" by <PERSON>Willem</PERSON> de Kooning; <MONEY>$20.6 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 8, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "The Trinquetaille Bridge" by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24 million</MONEY>, sold by 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "Mere et Enfant" by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$18.7 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New 
York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 15, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "La Promenade" by <ORGANIZATION>Pierre-Auguste Renoir</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$17.6 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, 
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 3, 1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
 -- "False Start" by <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON>; <MONEY>$17.05 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, 
<DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Van Gogh's "Portrait of Dr. Gachet" has sold for $82.5 million. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
List; Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890510-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-10-89 0531EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Paintings-TopPrices     05-10 0199</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Paintings-Top Prices,0208</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Art Auction, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a list of the top 10 prices paid for paintings at
the world's two major auction houses, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s:
   1. ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>.
   2. ``Yo Picasso'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   3. ``Sunflowers'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>.
   4. ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>November 28, 1988</DATE>.
   5. ``Maternity'' by Pablo Picasso; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>.
   6. ``Dans La Prairie'' (``In the Meadow'') by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>;
<MONEY>$24.59 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>.
   7. ``Mata <ORGANIZATION>Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times)'' by <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.2 million</MONEY>,
sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 9, 1989</DATE>.
   8. ``The Trinquetaille Bridge'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>.
   9. ``La Promenade'' by <ORGANIZATION>Pierre-Auguste Renoir</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$17.6 million</MONEY>,
sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 3, 1989</DATE>.
   10. ``False Start'' by <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON>; <MONEY>$17.05 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA122589-0059 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 153463 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
December 25, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
746 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ART IN THE EIGHTIES; 
</P>
<P>
AN INTERNATIONAL BULL MARKET 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUZANNE MUCHNIC, TIMES ART WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The most expensive artwork on record at the end of the '70s was <PERSON>Velazquez</PERSON>'s 
<MONEY>$5.5-million</MONEY> painting, "Juan de Pareja." As the '80s draw to a close, that 
dubious honor is held by <PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises," which brought <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> in a 
<DATE>1987</DATE> auction. 
</P>
<P>
What accounts for the 10-fold rise? 
</P>
<P>
* An injection of new money from American, European and Japanese collectors. 
The Japanese, for example, have inflated the French Impressionist market by 
purchasing vast quantities of paintings at escalating auction prices. One 
Japanese buyer -- <ORGANIZATION>Aska International</ORGANIZATION>, which operates the <ORGANIZATION>Aoyama Gallery</ORGANIZATION> in 
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> -- spent more than <MONEY>$120 million</MONEY> in <DATE>November</DATE> at <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Impressionist art 
auctions. 
</P>
<P>
* An increase in private collectors who follow the art scene feather their 
nests with artworks and contribute to the image of collecting as a fashionable 
and intellectually rewarding activity. 
</P>
<P>
* A growing belief that art is a good investment, despite hard evidence to the 
contrary. 
</P>
<P>
* A change in income-tax laws in <DATE>1986</DATE> that reduced deductions of donated art to 
the purchase price instead of the appreciated value. Having lost a tax 
incentive for giving their collections to museums, private collectors began to 
cash in at auction. 
</P>
<P>
* A proliferation of high-quality -- or at least high-profile -- works on the 
resale market. <PERSON>John L. Marion</PERSON>, chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, dates this 
phenomenon to the <DATE>1983</DATE> sale of the <PERSON>Doris Havemeyer</PERSON> estate. Each big-ticket 
auction seems to beget others by encouraging collectors to sell. 
</P>
<P>
* Publicity about high auction prices that has raised public awareness and 
built large audiences. As art prices have become front-page news, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s have changed from sedate places where dealers did business to forums 
for public spectacles. These activities have filtered down from newspaper and 
television reports to ads for <ORGANIZATION>Hughes Markets</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Lincoln Town Cars</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
All these factors overlap and interact to such a degree that it is difficult to 
track the causes of the art boom. Effects of soaring art prices also can be 
elusive. The major auction houses and the sellers of multimillion-dollar 
artworks are obvious winners in this bull market, as are foundations and 
charities that have benefited richly from big art sales. The trickle-down 
effect on artists and dealers is a matter of hot debate, however. 
</P>
<P>
Among the losers during this money-happy decade are museums, most of which have 
been priced out of the art market at the very moment when reduced income-tax 
deductions have put a squeeze on donations. The <ORGANIZATION>J. Paul Getty Museum</ORGANIZATION> stands 
alone in its spending power, but even that wealthy institution's budget has 
been cramped by soaring prices. 
</P>
<P>
Nonetheless, the <PERSON>Getty</PERSON> has emerged as an important collector in the <DATE>'80s</DATE>. 
Originally feared for its presumed power to plunder the world's treasures, the 
museum later was chastised for being timid and stingy. In fact, the <ORGANIZATION>Getty</ORGANIZATION> has 
made big purchases throughout the decade. 
</P>
<P>
As prices have risen, the art market has become increasingly global. Sotheby's 
in <DATE>1988</DATE> staged a landmark auction of Russian avant-garde and Soviet 
contemporary art in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>. This year, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> launched a joint venture 
operation in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, while Sotheby's joined the Japanese department store, 
<LOCATION>Seibu</LOCATION>, in a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> auction. 
</P>
<P>
Big changes are also afoot in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> has lagged well behind <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and 
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in art sales because of protectionist policies, but reforms are already 
under way and <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> is expected to open up to foreign sales after <DATE>1992</DATE>. Both 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s are gearing up for action there. 
</P>
<P>
Whether prices rise or fall, global growth is likely to be the big art market 
story of the '90s. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
BULL MARKET 
</P>
<P>
Top-10 Auction Prices of the <DATE>1980s 
</P>
<P>
1</DATE>."Irises," <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>, <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>. Sotheby's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 1987 
</P>
<P>
2."Pierrette's Wedding," <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$51.3 million</MONEY>. Drouot <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. 1989 
</P>
<P>
3."Yo Picasso," <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>. Sotheby's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 1989 
</P>
<P>
4."Au Lapin Agile," <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>. Sotheby's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 1989 
</P>
<P>
5."Sunflowers," Van Gogh, <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>. Christie's <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 1987 
</P>
<P>
6."Acrobat and <PERSON>Young Harlequin</PERSON>," <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$38.5 million</MONEY>. Christie's <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>. 
1988 
</P>
<P>
7."Portrait of Duke Cosimo de' Medici," <PERSON>Jacopo Pontormo</PERSON>, <MONEY>$35.2 million</MONEY>. 
Christie's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 1989 
</P>
<P>
8."Rue Mosnier With Flags," <PERSON>Edouard Manet</PERSON>, <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>. Christie's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
<DATE>1989 
</P>
<P>
9</DATE>."The Mirror," <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY>. Sotheby's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. <DATE>1989</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
10."Motherhood," <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>. Christie's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. <DATE>1988</DATE> 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, The most expensive paintings of the decade were, in descending order: 
Van Gogh's "Irises," depicted on F1; "Pierrette's Wedding," above left, "Yo 
Picasso," far left, and "Au Lapin Agile," left -- all Picassos; and Van Gogh's 
"Sunflowers," at right. ; Photo, Van Gogh's "Irises" fetched $53.9 million in 
1987. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
List 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
1980S (DECADE); TRENDS; ART; AUCTIONS; ART SALES; ART COLLECTIONS AND 
COLLECTORS; MUSEUMS; PAINTINGS; PRICES 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890907-0138 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-07-89 2019EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Picasso     09-07 0489</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Picasso,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sotheby's to Auction Early Picasso Self-Portrait</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY35</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The family of <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, which sold
<PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Irises'' two years ago for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, hopes
to fetch a similar price on <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> for an early <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>
self-portrait.
   Sotheby's said <DATE>Thursday</DATE> that ``Au Lapin Agile,'' named after a
tavern frequented by the artist, has been consigned by <PERSON>Mrs. Payson</PERSON>'s
daughter, <PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, who kept the Picasso in her home in
<LOCATION>Manhasset</LOCATION>, on <LOCATION>Long Island</LOCATION>.
   She inherited it from her mother, a philanthropist, co-owner of a
racing stariod are in museums;
this one appeared briefly in <DATE>1980</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>National Museum of Western</ORGANIZATION>
Art in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>David Nash</PERSON>, senior vice president of fine arts
for <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   Picasso, then 25, painted the unsigned work in <DATE>1905</DATE> as a gift to
<PERSON>Frederic Gerard</PERSON>, the tavern owner, who appears in the background,
strumming a guitar. ``Maybe Picasso gave it in exchange for a few
drinks _ who knows?'' said <PERSON>Nash</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Payson</PERSON> acquired it in <DATE>1952</DATE>. ``This magnificent painting was
in our parents' home in <LOCATION>Manhasset</LOCATION> for 27 years and, for a time, hung
near van Gogh's `Irises,''' <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON> said in a statement.
   Her brother said in an interview that <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON> also
displayed ``Au Lapin Agile'' prominently. But she became ``a bit
nervous having the painting in her house'' because of the prices
commanded by ``Irises'' and ``<PERSON>Yo Picasso</PERSON>,'' a <DATE>1901</DATE> self-portrait,
sold for <MONEY>$47.8 million</MONEY> on <DATE>May 9</DATE>.
   The real clincher, said <PERSON>Payson</PERSON>, was in <DATE>December</DATE>, when <PERSON>Mrs. de
Roulet</PERSON> discovered her grandsons playing with a dartboard near the
<ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``That seemed to be some kind of an omen,'' said <PERSON>Payson</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Nash</PERSON> said it's difficult to set a presale estimate because of the
unpredictable art market.
   ``This is much larger than `<ORGANIZATION>Yo Picasso</ORGANIZATION>.' It is a much more
complex painting, with considerable psychological tensions,'' he
said. ``In a logical world, it should lead to a higher price.''
   Part of the sale proceeds will be used to establish a foundation
for medical research and education.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900116-0135 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-16-90 1605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Renoir     01-16 0478</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Renoir,0491</SECOND>
<HEAD>Investor's Widow Seeks up to $50 Million for Renoir</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Betsey cq in 4th graf.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The widow of investor-publisher <PERSON>John Hay Whitney</PERSON>
will offer a Renoir from the couple's collection for sale for an
estimated <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house said
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Pierre-Auguste <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>1876</DATE> artwork, acclaimed for its light,
shadow and movement, depicts the <ORGANIZATION>Moulin de la Galette</ORGANIZATION>, a French
outdoor dance hall in <LOCATION>Montmartre</LOCATION> frequented by avant-garde writers,
painters and actors.
   It shows a model named <PERSON>Estelle</PERSON> siting at a table with three of
<ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>'s friends, including biographer <PERSON>Georges Rivere</PERSON>, who later
described the painting as ``a page of history, a precious moment of
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> life depicted with rigorous examination.''
   The painting was owned for 60 years by <PERSON>Whitney</PERSON> and his wife,
<PERSON>Betsey Cushing Whitney</PERSON>.
   Whitney, who died in <DATE>1982</DATE>, founded <ORGANIZATION>J.H. Whitney &amp; Co.</ORGANIZATION>, a
venture-capitalist firm, and was an ambassador to <LOCATION>Great Britain</LOCATION> and
publisher of <ORGANIZATION>The New York Herald Tribune</ORGANIZATION>.
   He became a trustee of the Museum of Modern Art in <DATE>1930</DATE>, was
named president in <DATE>1941</DATE> and was chairman from <DATE>1946</DATE> to <DATE>1956</DATE>. He was
a trustee of the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> from <DATE>1961</DATE> to
<DATE>1979</DATE>.
   A larger version of ``Au Moulin de la Galette'' is in the <LOCATION>Musee</LOCATION>
d'Orsay in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. It is believed one was painted at the scene and
the other at <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION>'s studio _ but no one knows which is which.
   Sotheby's will take the <LOCATION>Whitney</LOCATION> version to <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> for a
comparison in <DATE>February</DATE>. Then, after exhibits in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Renoir</ORGANIZATION> will return to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> for an auction
on <DATE>May 16</DATE>.
   After <PERSON>Whitney</PERSON>'s death, his wife gave five institutions 20 works
by <PERSON>Edgar Degas</PERSON>, <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>, <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, <PERSON>Henri Rousseau</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Georges Seurat</PERSON>, <PERSON>James Abbott McNeill Whistler</PERSON> and other artists.
   Several other Whitneys also are well-known in the art world.
   Whitney's niece, <PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, sold <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>'s ``Au
Lapin Agile,'' a <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> tavern scene, on <DATE>Nov. 17</DATE> for <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>.
   <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON>'s brother, <PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON>, sold <PERSON>Vincent van
Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Irises'' in <DATE>1987</DATE> for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>, the highest price ever
obtained at an art auction.
   Payson got his money, but other parts of the deal went sour. It
turned out <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION> had lent Australian tycoon Alan Bond <MONEY>$27
million</MONEY> to help buy ``Irises,'' using the painting itself as
collateral. Bond didn't pay off the loan; the van Gogh is now in a
vault, its ownership cloudy. Last week, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION> announced it was
abandoning its loan policy _ which triggered the quandary and
which, critics charged, inflated art prices in general.
   Both the van Gogh and the <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> came from the collection of
former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets owner <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Whitney</LOCATION>'s sister
and the mother of <PERSON>Mrs. de Roulet</PERSON> and <PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA090889-0126 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 104832 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
September 8, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part 6; Page 22; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
686 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ROSE-PERIOD PICASSO HEADS FOR AUCTION BLOCK 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUZANNE MUCHNIC, Times Art Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The family that sold <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises" for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> two years 
ago will put a rose-period Picasso on the block <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. 
"Au Lapin Agile," a <DATE>1905</DATE> self-portrait expected to bring around <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> or 
<MONEY>$50 million</MONEY>, has become "too expensive to keep," said <PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, owner of 
the painting, in a prepared statement. 
</P>
<P>
De <PERSON>Roulet</PERSON>, who inherited the Picasso from her mother, <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, is 
following in the footsteps of her brother, <PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON>, who inherited 
"Irises" from the family collection. He sold "Irises" for a record price after 
another <PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>, "Sunflowers," brought <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY> at auction. 
</P>
<P>
De <PERSON>Roulet</PERSON>'s statement said she was persuaded to part with "Au Lapin Agile" 
after another early Picasso self-portrait, "Yo Picasso," sold in <DATE>May</DATE> for <MONEY>$47.85 
million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Also like her brother, who established a charitable foundation from the 
proceeds of "Irises," De <PERSON>Roulet</PERSON> will set up a foundation for medical research 
and education. AIDS research and the research unit of <ORGANIZATION>North Shore University 
Hospital</ORGANIZATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Cornell University Medical School</ORGANIZATION> will benefit from the the new 
<ORGANIZATION>Patrina Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, said <PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON>, speaking by telephone for his 
sister. Other causes will be decided on a case-by-case basis as applications 
for grants are received, he said. 
</P>
<P>
The family isn't distressed about breaking up the family collection, <PERSON>Payson</PERSON> 
said. "I'm sure <PERSON>Linda</PERSON> will feel as I did when I sold 'Irises.' I felt a kind of 
loss at first, but when I saw the grant applications come in and the potential 
of the funds, it was very exciting. It's an upbeat thing." 
</P>
<P>
"Au Lapin Agile" is considered one of the most important rose-period Picassos 
in private hands. Picasso painted it the year after he left <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION> for 
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>. Living with his mistress, <PERSON>Fernande Olivier</PERSON>, in the dilapidated building 
known as the Bateau Lavoir, the young artist frequented a local circus and 
began to paint harlequin figures. 
</P>
<P>
In the gaily colored 39 x 39 1/2-inch oil, <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> depicted himself as a 
brooding harlequin standing at a bar. A woman beside him is said to be <PERSON>Germaine 
Pichot</PERSON>, a model whom <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> blamed for the <DATE>1901</DATE> death of his friend and fellow 
artist <PERSON>Carlos Casegemas</PERSON>, who was in love with her. 
</P>
<P>
"Au Lapin Agile" ("The Lively Rabbit") is named for a <LOCATION>Montmartre</LOCATION> cafe that is 
still in operation and once featured a sign picturing a rabbit in a saucepan. 
Picasso originally gave the painting to <PERSON>Frederic Gerard</PERSON>, the proprietor of the 
bohemian cafe who hung it there. Gerard is seen in the back of the picture, 
strumming his guitar. 
</P>
<P>
The painting subsequently passed through two private collections before <PERSON>Joan 
Whitney Payson</PERSON> bought it in <DATE>1952</DATE>. She was a philanthropist for civic and 
medical institutions, a breeder of race horses and owner of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets 
baseball team, as well as a formidable art collector. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON> was known to collect Impressionist and Post-Impressionist 
works, including paintings by <PERSON>Gauguin</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rousseau</PERSON>, in addition to <LOCATION>Van Gogh</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON> was only 12 when his mother bought "Au Lapin Agile," but he 
recalls the delivery of a big crate to their home in <LOCATION>Manhasset</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.Y.</LOCATION> 
"Unfortunately I was probably more interested in the truck that delivered it 
than I was in the painting, so my memories aren't very clear," he said. 
</P>
<P>
Payson does remember that the painting hung in a hallway near the entrance to 
the library, where the family spent a great deal of time. Old family photos 
show that at one point "Au Lapin Agile" and "Irises" shared a wall. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Linda de Roulet</PERSON>, who lives in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, resided in <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> in the '50s with 
her late husband, <PERSON>Vincent de Roulet</PERSON>. She inherited the painting in <DATE>1975</DATE> at the 
death of her mother and has carried on <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>'s philanthropic 
activities, serving on hospital and museum boards. De <PERSON>Roulet</PERSON> was president of 
the <ORGANIZATION>New York Mets</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>1975</DATE> until the team was sold in <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Is "Au Lapin Agile" just the second tip of the <LOCATION>Payson</LOCATION> iceberg? Will other 
family treasures be offered for sale in the future? 
</P>
<P>
"No other paintings are under consideration right now," <PERSON>Payson</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, An early Picasso self-portrait, "Au Lapin Agile" is named for a 
Montmartre cafe still in business. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PICASSO, PABLO; PAYSON, JOAN WHITNEY; ART COLLECTIONS AND COLLECTORS; ART 
SALES; PAINTINGS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891012-0174 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-12-89 2054EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Picasso     10-12 0358</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Picasso,0369</SECOND>
<HEAD>Long-Lost Picasso Painting to Be Auctioned Next Month</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto PAR3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MARILYN AUGUST</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A masterpiece from <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>'s ``blue period''
long thought to have disappeared is expected to become the world's
most expensive painting when sold at auction on <DATE>Nov. 30</DATE>, an
auctioneer said <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   ``Les Noces de Pierrette'' (``Pierrette's Wedding''), executed
in 1904-05 in <LOCATION>Montmartre</LOCATION>, is expected to bring <MONEY>$46 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$61
million</MONEY>, said auctioneer <PERSON>Jean-Claude Binoche</PERSON>.
   ``It's going to shatter the world record not only for Picassos,
but for all paintings,'' <PERSON>Binoche</PERSON> said.
   The record paid at an auction for a <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> was <MONEY>$48.7 million</MONEY>
for a <DATE>1901</DATE> self-portrait titled ``Yo Picasso,'' sold on <DATE>May 9</DATE>.
<PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Irises'' became the most expensive painting in
the world when it sold two years ago for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>.
   Binoche said he was hopeful Culture Minister <PERSON>Jack Lang</PERSON> would
allow ``Les Noces'' to leave <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. The painting is considered
part of <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>'s national heritage and must receive an official
authorization to leave the country.
   With its hauntingly beautiful pink and blue tones, the work
straddles <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s best-loved early periods. Six figures _ their
pale pink faces illuminated by an eerie light _ sit around a table
with the newlyweds. The bride wears a Spanish-style mantilla. Her
husband sports a top hat.
   Though experts are familiar with dozens of sketches <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> drew
for ``Les Noces,'' the final work dropped from sight years ago.
Many thought it was lost in a fire.
   It surfaced in <DATE>1988</DATE> as part of a Picasso show in <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>.
<PERSON>Binoche</PERSON> said the work was long the property of a Swedish family
that does not want to be identified.
   ``The family considered the painting to be a private treasure,
and now it's for sale, that's all,'' he said.
   The sale has been hailed as the major event of the auction
season.
   Sotheby's in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> has said the family of <PERSON>Joan Whitney
Payson</PERSON>, the sellers of van Gogh's ``Irises,'' hope to fetch a
similar price on <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> for an early <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> self-portrait titled
``Au Lapin Agile,'' named after a tavern frequented by the artist.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110689-0095 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 131073 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 6, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 1; Column 2; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1150 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PRESTIGE ON THE BLOCK; 
</P>
<P>
ART: A STAR-STUDDED LIST OF SELLERS JOCKEY FOR POSITION IN THE OVERHEATED N.Y. 
AUCTION WORLD. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUZANNE MUCHNIC, TIMES ART WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Christie's and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s are gearing up for the height of <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s fall 
auction season. They have laid in plentiful supplies of multimillion-dollar 
paintings, mailed catalogues far and wide, sent star artworks on the road and 
lined up prospective buyers. Now comes the public part: a round of auctions, on 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE> through <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>, that is expected to ring up more than <MONEY>$500 million</MONEY> in 
sales of contemporary, modern and Impressionist art. 
</P>
<P>
Art isn't the only thing for sale, however. Prestigious provenance is also on 
the block, as we see from the star-studded list of sellers. Collectors who are 
concerned about who has owned the art they buy should feel secure this season. 
Even those who want or need no validation of their own judgment are likely to 
be impressed by the consignors: 
</P>
<P>
* <PERSON>Lorinda de Roulet</PERSON>, sister of <PERSON>John Whitney Payson</PERSON> -- who sold <PERSON>Vincent van 
Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises" for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> two years ago -- will sell <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>'s 
"Au Lapin Agile" at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s on <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE>. De <PERSON>Roulet</PERSON> and <PERSON>Payson</PERSON> inherited the 
paintings from their mother, <PERSON>Joan Whitney Payson</PERSON>, a noted collector, 
philanthropist and owner of the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> Mets. 
</P>
<P>
Rumors abound that "Au Lapin Agile" may replace "Irises" as the world's most 
expensive painting. Failing that, the Rose Period cabaret scene featuring 
<PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> as a harlequin may still break the artist's record of <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY> 
set in <DATE>May</DATE> for "Yo Picasso." Sotheby's has announced no firm estimate for "Au 
Lapin Agile," but a press release states that the firm anticipates "the same 
level of interest among collectors" as "Yo Picasso." 
</P>
<P>
* <PERSON>Paul Mellon</PERSON>, a major benefactor of the <ORGANIZATION>National Gallery</ORGANIZATION> of Art and son of 
museum founder <PERSON>Andrew W. Mellon</PERSON>, is pruning his personal collection to the tune 
of <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>. Christie's <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> on <DATE>Nov. 14</DATE> will offer about <MONEY>$85 million</MONEY> to 
<MONEY>$90 million</MONEY> worth of that cache -- in the form of 15 Impressionist and modern 
works. 
</P>
<P>
Prime among them are <PERSON>Edouard Manet</PERSON>'s painting "Rue Mosnier, <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION>, Decorated 
With Flags on <DATE>June 30, 1878</DATE>," valued at more than <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, and "The Tree, 
<LOCATION>Arles</LOCATION>," a vivid <DATE>1888</DATE> landscape by <PERSON>Van Gogh</PERSON>, expected to bring at least <MONEY>$25 
million</MONEY>. Picasso's "Death of a Harlequin," a Rose Period painting that <ORGANIZATION>Mellon</ORGANIZATION> 
bought from <PERSON>W. Somerset Maugham</PERSON>'s collection, is expected to sell for more than 
<MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>. Three of <PERSON>Edgar Degas</PERSON>' wax sculptures of ballet dancers, valued at 
<MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY> apiece, are also in the Mellon sale. 
</P>
<P>
* <PERSON>Billy Wilder</PERSON>, a legendary film maker and highly regarded art collector, will 
sell 94 modern and contemporary works at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s on <DATE>Nov. 13</DATE>. Expected to 
total as much as <MONEY>$30 million</MONEY>, the <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> collection is among the liveliest 
collections to come up for sale in many years. Exercising a purely personal 
taste that favors literary complexities and emotional punch, <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> purchased 
exquisitely raunchy nudes by <ORGANIZATION>Austrian Expressionist Egon Schiele</ORGANIZATION>, poetic boxes 
and collages by <PERSON>Joseph Cornell</PERSON> and delightful whimsies by <PERSON>Joan Miro</PERSON>. In the 
<PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> roster of works by 47 artists, <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s classical <DATE>1921</DATE> pastel drawing, 
"Tete de Femme," is expected to bring the sale's top price of <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$7 
million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
* The late <PERSON>Edgar Kaufmann Jr.</PERSON>, a <PERSON>Frank Lloyd Wright</PERSON> scholar and heir to a 
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> department store fortune, is known for persuading his father to 
commission <PERSON>Wright</PERSON>'s masterpiece, a house called "Fallingwater," but he was also 
a distinguished collector of art. Sotheby's <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> sale of 21 Impressionist 
and modern works from his collection is expected to total up to <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
There's a Monet waterlily painting, valued at <MONEY>$7 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$9 million</MONEY>, an 
early <ORGANIZATION>Mondrian</ORGANIZATION>, called "Facade in Tan and Grey" (<MONEY>$6 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8 million</MONEY>) and 
a sprightly <PERSON>Miro</PERSON>, "l'Oiseau au Plumage Deploye Vole Vers l'Arbre Argente "(<MONEY>$4 
million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>). Another painting from the <PERSON>Kaufmann</PERSON> collection, <PERSON>Willem 
de Kooning</PERSON>'s <DATE>1955</DATE> "Interchange" (<MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$6 million</MONEY>) is among top 
offerings in Sotheby's contemporary sale on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
* The late <PERSON>Robert B. Mayer</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> clothing retailer, founding member of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Chicago Museum of Contemporary</ORGANIZATION> Art and supporter of the <ORGANIZATION>Art Institute of 
Chicago</ORGANIZATION>, amassed one of the finest private art collections in the country. 
Twenty contemporary pieces from the <PERSON>Mayer</PERSON> collection, for sale at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s on 
<DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, include <PERSON>Roy Lichtenstein</PERSON>'s comic-strip style "Torpedo . . . Los!," 
expected to bring <MONEY>$3 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY>, and <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON>' small gray 
painting of numbers, "O Through 9," valued at <MONEY>$2.5 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$3.5 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
How does such distinguished ownership figure into the auction houses' 
estimates? Not at all, officials from <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s insist. If only 
to protect themselves from being overly optimistic in an overheated market, 
they establish estimates that they say reflect market value, based on sales of 
similar works. 
</P>
<P>
But the two houses compete vigorously for big-name collections and promote them 
to the hilt. The selling of collections includes selling the collectors as 
people of prescience and taste. 
</P>
<P>
Prestigious "single-owner" sales -- auctions that include a number of works 
from a single collection -- are fancy dress occasions with admission by ticket 
and reserved seats for favored clients. 
</P>
<P>
These sales have color-illustrated catalogues, often containing essays about 
the collectors, historical notes and photographs of how the artworks were 
installed in the collectors' homes. Really big sales get hard-cover catalogues. 
Really, really big sales of single paintings -- such as "Irises" and "Au Lapin 
Agile" -- get their own hard-cover books. 
</P>
<P>
Artworks in "single-owner" sales are also sent on carefully plotted 
international tours that include private openings and public viewings. 
</P>
<P>
Apparently the strategy works. Highly publicized "single-owner" sales often 
surpass, even double, their estimates. That success -- coupled with the fear 
that the bubble will burst -- persuades more collectors to sell. 
</P>
<P>
With art pouring out of closets, new collectors emerging in ever larger numbers 
and European buying reportedly on the rise, this year promises to bring more of 
the same. 
</P>
<P>
The strongest note of skepticism about the perpetually escalating art market 
has been voiced over what some observers call artificial prices, pumped up by 
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s practice of loaning money to their clients for the purchase of art 
from <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s sales. 
</P>
<P>
The most famous case is that of Australian businessman Alan Bond who reportedly 
borrowed about <MONEY>$27 million</MONEY> from <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s to buy "Irises" in <DATE>1987</DATE> and 
subsequently suffered financial setbacks. Although he has made regular payments 
-- after renegotiating the loan -- the painting is safely locked in a Sotheby's 
vault, according to the auction house. To help pay off his loan, Bond has 
consigned "La Promenade," an Impressionist painting by <PERSON>Edouard Manet</PERSON> valued at 
<MONEY>$10 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$14 million</MONEY>, to <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> sale -- the same auction that 
features "Au Lapin Agile." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Picasso's "Au Lapin Agile" is being auctioned by Lorinda de Roulet, 
daughter of Joan Whitney Payson. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ART COLLECTIONS AND COLLECTORS; AUCTIONS; ART SALES; PAINTINGS; ARTISTS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881128-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-28-88 2213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-WorldArt     11-28 0174</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-World Art,0182</SECOND>
<HEAD>Millions And Millions As Art Records Soar</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Britain-Picasso</HEAD>
<DATELINE>LONDON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Christie's list of the 10 most expensive works of
art sold at auction, after <DATE>Monday</DATE>'s sale of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Acrobat and
Young Harlequin'':
   1. Vincent van Gogh ``Irises,'' <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>; <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   2. <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON> ``Sunflowers,'' <DATE>March 30, 1987</DATE>; <MONEY>$41.33
million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   3. Pablo Picasso ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin,'' <DATE>Nov. 28, 1988</DATE>;
<MONEY>$38.46 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   4. <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON> ``In the Field,'' <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>; <MONEY>$24.90 million</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   5. Pablo Picasso ``Maternity,'' <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   6. <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON> ``The Bridge at Trinquetaille,'' <DATE>June 29,
1987</DATE>; <MONEY>$20.37 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   7. <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON> ``False Start,'' <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>; <MONEY>$17.05 million</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   8. Pablo Picasso ``The Bird Cage,'' <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>; <MONEY>$15.4 million</MONEY>,
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>.
   9. <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON> ``The Railroad Bridge at <LOCATION>Argenteuil</LOCATION>,'' <DATE>Nov. 28,
1988</DATE>; <MONEY>$12.55 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
   10. Henry the Lion manuscript dated <DATE>1173</DATE> A.D., <DATE>Dec. 7, 1983</DATE>,
<MONEY>$11.93 million</MONEY>, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900112-0117 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-12-90 1710EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ArtAuction     01-12 0540</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Art Auction,0552</SECOND>
<HEAD>Nation's Auction Houses Paint Rosy Picture of Record Year</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCIS HOPKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> auction houses sold more than <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY>
worth of art last year and chalked up their best-selling season
ever thanks to a broader, more educated audience, art dealers said.
   Two Pablo Picasso paintings sold for more than <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY> each
to become the third- and fourth-most expensive paintings ever, but
the not-so-wealthy art lover also contributed to the record sales
by buying works that cost thousands rather than than millions.
   When the final bang of the gavel sounded on <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> art auction
sales for the season, the total came to <MONEY>$1.53 billion</MONEY>, nearly
double last year's total, <PERSON>Leonard</PERSON>'s Annual Price Index of Art
Auctions reported this week.
   The total number of art lots sold was 33,000 in <DATE>1989</DATE>, down by
more than 5,000 from the previous year. Experts said both the
limited art supply and increased consumer interest stoked the
season's record-breaking sales.
   ``When my grandfather ran the business, his clientele was the
very top <PERCENT>5 percent</PERCENT> of the upper class,'' said <PERSON>Abbot William Vose</PERSON>,
president of <ORGANIZATION>Vose Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, which opened in <LOCATION>Providence</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>R.I.</LOCATION>, in
<DATE>1841</DATE> and relocated to <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> <DATE>40 years later</DATE>.
   ``The clientele is very broad-based now, with even the lower
middle-class buying art,'' he said. ``Art education in even grade
schools, up through high schools, has played a good part in
focusing attention on American art and other arts, and has made a
difference in attendance at museums and art shows.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's Holdings Inc.</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> last year sold the third-and
fourth-top moneymakers ever with ``<PERSON>Yo Picasso</PERSON>,'' a self-portrait of
the artist that earned <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY>, and his ``Au Lapin Agile,''
which went for <MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>, said <PERSON>Robin Riley-Ahrens</PERSON>, the house's
spokesman.
   Picasso's ``Pierrette's Wedding'' went for <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY> in
<DATE>November</DATE> to earn the title of the second-most expensive painting
ever, but it was sold at the Drouot-Montaigne auction house in
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> and thus not included in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> figures.
   The world's most expensive painting, <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s
``Irises,'' was sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in <DATE>1987</DATE> for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>. The
auction house disclosed <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, however, that it lent Australian
tycoon Alan Bond <MONEY>$27 million</MONEY> to buy the <DATE>1889</DATE> painting; that as
collateral Bond posted the picture he was going to buy, and that
Bond has not paid off the loan. Sotheby's said it was abandoning
the loan policy, which many critics say artificially inflates
artwork prices.
   ``About <PERCENT>20 percent</PERCENT> of the art sold at auction went for below
<MONEY>$1,000</MONEY>,'' said <PERSON>Susan Theran</PERSON>, publisher of Leonard's Annual Price
Index, an industry database that provides information annually on
art auction prices.
   ``Art is affordable, and people are finding that out,'' she
said. ``People are developing their tastes and buying books on how
to purchase art.''
   However, sales were still chiefly pushed to their record heights
by purchases in the <MONEY>$1 million-plus</MONEY> market, <PERSON>Theran</PERSON> said.
   Final tally for the <DATE>1989</DATE> selling season showed 240 lots of
artworks worth more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> were sold, compared with 84
similarly priced lots in the previous year, <PERSON>Theran</PERSON> said. Sales for
the 240 lots was <MONEY>$779 million</MONEY>, more than triple the <DATE>1988</DATE> figure of
<MONEY>$213.5 million</MONEY> for the 84 lots.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881129-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-29-88 0213EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Paintings-Top10     11-29 0212</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Paintings-Top 10,0222</SECOND>
<HEAD>10 Most Expensive Paintings Sold At Christie's And Sotheby's</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Picasso</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Following is a current list of the top 10 prices paid for
paintings at the world's two major auction houses, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s:
   
   1. ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent</PERSON> van Gogh; <MONEY>$53.90 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 11, 1987</DATE>.
   2. ``Sunflowers'' by van Gogh; <MONEY>$41.3 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 31, 1987</DATE>.
   3. ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>; <MONEY>$38.46
million</MONEY> (record for a 20th-century work), sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s,
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 28, 1988</DATE>.
   4. ``Maternity'' by <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>; <MONEY>$24.75 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s,
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 14, 1988</DATE>.
   5. ``In the Field'' by <PERSON>Claude Monet</PERSON>; <MONEY>$24.90 million</MONEY>, sold by
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 28, 1988</DATE>.
   6. ``The Trinquetalle Bridge'' by van Gogh; <MONEY>$20.24 million</MONEY>, sold
by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>June 29, 1987</DATE>.
   7. ``False Start'' by <PERSON>Jasper Johns</PERSON>; <MONEY>$17.05 million</MONEY> (record for a
living artist), sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>.
   8. ``Bird Cage'' by <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$15.4 million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s,
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 10, 1988</DATE>.
   9. ``Portrait of Adeline Ravoux'' by van Gogh; <MONEY>$13.75 million</MONEY>,
sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <DATE>May 11, 1988</DATE>.
   10. ``The Railroad Bridge at <LOCATION>Argenteuil</LOCATION>,'' by <ORGANIZATION>Monet</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$12.55
million</MONEY>, sold by <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <DATE>Nov. 28</DATE>. <DATE>1988</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890510-0047 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-10-89 0429EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-ArtAuction Bjt   05-10 0519</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Art Auction, Bjt,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Picasso Brings Second-Highest Price Ever Auctioned</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto NY8</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BETH J. HARPAZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Pablo Picasso would have gotten a kick out of
seeing his self-portrait sell for <MONEY>$47.85 million</MONEY> to become the
second most expensive art work ever auctioned, his daughter said.
   ``Yo Picasso,'' painted 88 years ago when the artist was 20, was
last sold in <DATE>1981</DATE> for <MONEY>$5.5 million</MONEY>.
   Its price <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION> was more than twice its
pre-sale estimate and was second only to <PERSON>Vincent Van Gogh</PERSON>'s
``Irises,'' which sold for <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The <PERSON>Picasso</PERSON> was one of 67 Impressionist, Post-Impressionist and
Modern works that sold for a record total of <MONEY>$204.82 million</MONEY>. The
previous mark for one auction was <MONEY>$117 million</MONEY> at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in <DATE>April</DATE>.
   The previous record sale for <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, who died in <DATE>1973</DATE>, was
<MONEY>$38.45 million</MONEY> paid last year for ``Acrobate et Jeune Arlequin.''
   <PERSON>Paloma Picasso</PERSON>, who attended <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s sale, said she thought
her father ``would get a kick out of it'' if he knew how much his
self-portrait had brought.
   ``It's in another stratosphere, but it's because there's a lot
of cash around,'' she said. ``It's better that these people use
their money for these paintings rather than planes and bombs.''
   Two bidders made their offers by telephone, upping one another
in increments of a <MONEY>million dollars</MONEY> once the price war got past <MONEY>$30
million</MONEY>. The standing-room-only audience oohed as each offer was
announced and applauded the winning figure.
   Neither bidder was identified. The loser also was the
underbidder when the painting was last sold.
   ``Yo Picasso'' was sold by <PERSON>Wendell Cherry</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Louisville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ky.</LOCATION>,
who heads <ORGANIZATION>Humana Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the hospital management corporation.
   Records were set <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> for 11 artists besides <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Paul Gauguin</PERSON>'s ``<ORGANIZATION>Mata Mua</ORGANIZATION> (In Olden Times),'' a colorful
Tahitian landscape, sold for <MONEY>$24.2 million</MONEY>. That broke a record set
last month when <PERSON>Gauguin</PERSON>'s ``The Fare Hymenee'' sold for <MONEY>$10.36
million</MONEY>.
   A record <MONEY>$11.55 million</MONEY> for <PERSON>Paul Cezanne</PERSON> was set by his 1893-94
still life ``Pichet et Fruits sur une Table.'' In <DATE>1988</DATE>, his ``La
Cote du Galet, A <LOCATION>Pontoise</LOCATION>'' sold for <MONEY>$9.24 million</MONEY>.
   An abstract landscape by <PERSON>Wassily Kandinsky</PERSON>,
``Herbstlandschaft,'' sold for <MONEY>$3.96 million</MONEY>, a record for the
Russian-born artist whose next highest-priced work,
``Murnau-Landschaft Mit Kirsche 1,'' brought <MONEY>$2.4 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1987</DATE>.
   The <PERSON>Gauguin</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Cezanne</ORGANIZATION> and six other Impressionist and
Post-Impressionist works sold <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> were from the collection of
<PERSON>Jaimie Ortiz-Patino</PERSON>, heir to a Bolivian tin fortune.
   All prices include the auction house's <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> commission.
   Sotheby's and <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, two of the largest auction houses in
the world, hope to ring up <MONEY>$572 million</MONEY> from 4,472 art works over
12 days of sales that began <DATE>May 2</DATE>.
   ``What do we do for an encore?'' asked <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auctioneer <PERSON>John
Marion</PERSON>.
   Then he answered his own question when he noted that the art
collection of the heir to the <ORGANIZATION>Campbell Soup Co.</ORGANIZATION> fortune, <PERSON>John
Dorrance</PERSON>, who died <DATE>April 9</DATE>, will be sold at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s in <DATE>October</DATE>.
   The multi-million dollar collection includes Impressionist and
Post-Impressionist paintings, as well as French 18th-century
furniture and porcelain.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890601-0074 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-01-89 0605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-MediciPortrait     06-01 0277</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Medici Portrait,0285</SECOND>
<HEAD>Old Master Sold for $35 Million</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <ORGANIZATION>Getty Museum</ORGANIZATION> paid a record <MONEY>$35.2 million</MONEY> for
a 16th-century Florentine portrait of <PERSON>Duke Cosimo de'Medici</PERSON> that
had been displayed in the <ORGANIZATION>Frick Collection</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   The price paid <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> was a record for an Old Master, and was
the fifth highest price paid for a painting at the world's two
major auction houses, <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby's</ORGANIZATION>.
   Scholars described the work, sometimes called the Halberdier, as
the finest Italian Renaissance painting to be offered at auction in
more than a decade.
   Christie's said many consider it to be the finest Old Master
painting in private hands in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.
   The previous auction record for an Old Master painting was <MONEY>$10.4
million</MONEY>, paid for <PERSON>Andrea Mantegna</PERSON>'s ``Adoration of the Magi'' in
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   The presale estimate for the Medici portrait was <MONEY>$20 million</MONEY>.
The price included a <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT> buyer's premium.
   The painting, circa <DATE>1537</DATE>, is by <PERSON>Jacopo da Carucci</PERSON>, who was known
as <ORGANIZATION>Pontormo</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Chauncey Devereaux Stillman</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> investor and
philanthropist who died <DATE>Jan. 24</DATE>, had lent it to the <LOCATION>Frick</LOCATION> in <DATE>1970</DATE>
for its 50th anniversary exhibition.
   Stillman's lawyers said it would be sold for the benefit of the
<ORGANIZATION>Homeland Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, his charitable organization.
   <PERSON>Charles A. Ryskamp</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Frick</ORGANIZATION>, said in <DATE>March</DATE> that
he was devastated by the painting's removal and expressed concern
that it might leave the country.
   Paintings that have sold for more are: ``Irises'' by <PERSON>Vincent van
Gogh</PERSON>, <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY>; ``Yo Picasso'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, <MONEY>$47.85
million</MONEY>; ``Sunflowers'' by van Gogh, <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, and ``Acrobat
and Young Harlequin'' by <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, <MONEY>$38.46 million</MONEY>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900516-0058 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-90 0705EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Japan-ArtMarket     05-16 0498</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Japan-Art Market,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Japan Holds Several of World's Most Expensive Paintings</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Van Gogh Record, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ELAINE KURTENBACH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TOKYO (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The tiny gallery that bought the world's most
expensive painting for an anonymous client in a <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> auction
has added another trophy to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s growing collection of
masterpieces.
   The <PERSON>Kobayashi</PERSON> Gallery of <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> bought ``Portrait of <PERSON>Dr.
Gachet</PERSON>,'' one of <PERSON>Vincent Van Gogh</PERSON>'s last paintings, for <MONEY>$82.5
million</MONEY> after a 10-minute auction battle <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> with a telephone
bidder at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house. The price includes a <PERCENT>10 percent</PERCENT>
buyer's premium.
   A staff member of <PERSON>Hideto Kobayashi</PERSON>'s one-room gallery in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>'s
fashionable <LOCATION>Ginza</LOCATION> district said the world record purchase, far
surpassing the <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> paid for van Gogh's ``Irises'' at a
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction in <DATE>November 1987</DATE>, came as a surprise.
   ``We weren't prepared for the deluge of reporters and
photographers <TIME>this morning</TIME>,'' said <PERSON>Kasunori Tanabe</PERSON>. ``The price is
amazing. It's as if we bought a dream.''
   <PERSON>Tanabe</PERSON> said the new owner of ``Portrait of <PERSON>Dr. Gachet</PERSON>'' is a
but declined to say more.
   In <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Kobayashi</PERSON> told <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Kyodo News Service</ORGANIZATION> that his
client was ``extremely pleased.''
   Kobayashi established an independent gallery in the <LOCATION>Ginza</LOCATION>, home
to hundreds of similar art dealers, 12 years ago after working for
the nearby <ORGANIZATION>Fujii Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Tanabe</PERSON> said.
   Both galleries are active collectors of Impressionist works.
   With <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s purchase, <PERSON>Kobayashi</PERSON> joined a growing list of
record-setting Japanese art buyers.
   The world's third most expensive painting, ``Les Noces de
Pierrette (<ORGANIZATION>Pierrette</ORGANIZATION>'s Wedding)'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, was sold for
<MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY> in <DATE>November</DATE> to <ORGANIZATION>Nippon Autopolis Co</ORGANIZATION>. The firm said it
planned to make the painting the centerpiece of an auto racing
theme resort.
   Another record smasher, ``Sunflowers,'' by van Gogh, sits in the
corporate headquarters of <ORGANIZATION>Yasuda Marine</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fire Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>. The <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY> purchase in <DATE>March 1987</DATE> was a world record
at the time and marked a high-profile return of Japanese buyers to
the world art market.
   Several others among the world's 10 most expensive paintings
have gone to Japanese buyers.
   <PERSON>Shigeki Kameyama</PERSON>, owner of the <ORGANIZATION>Mountain Tortoise Gallery</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION>, owns at least two prize masterpieces: ``The Mirror,'' by
<ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>, bought at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s for <MONEY>$26.4 million</MONEY> in <DATE>November</DATE>, and
``Interchange,'' by <PERSON>Willem de Kooning</PERSON>, also bought from <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s
in <DATE>November</DATE> for <MONEY>$20.6 million</MONEY>.
   An anonymous buyer, bidding through a <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> department store,
paid <MONEY>$38.46 million</MONEY> for <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Acrobat and Young Harlequin''
in a <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s auction in <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   Japanese dealers and collectors have bought 40 to <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> of
Impressionist works at <ORGANIZATION>Christies</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auctions in the past
few years.
   Lackluster bidding in the most recent auctions indicates that
the meteoric price increases of the mid- to late-1980s have
plateaued, <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auctioneer <PERSON>Julian Thompson</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> <DATE>last
month</DATE>.
   But active Japanese participation at recent auctions indicates
that demand in <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> for the world's greatest masterpieces remains
strong, he said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890620-0141 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-20-89 1742EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-VanGogh-Gift     06-20 0449</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Van Gogh-Gift,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pamela Harriman Giving Van Gogh Painting to National Gallery</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto WX31</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Pamela Harriman</PERSON>, wife of the late Ambassador <PERSON>W.
Averell Harriman</PERSON>, will give <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s ``Roses'' to the
<ORGANIZATION>National Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION>, the gallery director said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   The painting, which <PERSON>Mrs. Harriman</PERSON> valued at <MONEY>$50 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$60
million</MONEY>, will be the first van Gogh still life to join the <ORGANIZATION>National
Gallery</ORGANIZATION>'s permanent collection.
   Gallery director <PERSON>J. Carter Brown</PERSON> also announced at a <ORGANIZATION>National
Press Club</ORGANIZATION> luncheon that the gallery had received gifts of three
major <DATE>20th century</DATE> works from the late <PERSON>Rita Schreiber</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>
in memory of her husband, <PERSON>Taft B. Schreiber</PERSON>, a Republican activist
and <ORGANIZATION>MCA Inc.</ORGANIZATION> executive who died in <DATE>1976</DATE>.
   The <PERSON>Schreiber</PERSON> gifts include a <DATE>1924</DATE> painting titled ``Harlequin
Musician'' by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, ``Woman Seated in an Armchair'' painted
by <PERSON>Henri Matisse</PERSON> in <DATE>1940</DATE> and a <DATE>1927</DATE> bronze sculpture by <PERSON>Constantin
Brancusi</PERSON> titled ``Bird in Space.''
   <PERSON>Brown</PERSON> said ``Roses'' would be displayed as part of a three-month
exhibit devoted to anniversary gifts of art beginning <DATE>March 17,
1991</DATE>, the 50th anniversary of the opening of the gallery's West
Building.
   ``Our hope is that it will set an example for other patriotic
donors,'' he said.
   The gallery will receive complete title to the painting when <PERSON>Mrs.
Harriman</PERSON> dies.
   <PERSON>Mrs. Harriman</PERSON> said her husband, a former Democratic governor of
<LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and heir to a railroad fortune, bought the van Gogh in
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> in <DATE>1930</DATE> with his mother.
   A similar van Gogh still life, ``Irises,'' was sold at auction
for a record-breaking <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> in <DATE>November 1987</DATE>.
   Another van Gogh, ``Sunflowers,'' sold in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in <DATE>March 1987</DATE>
for <MONEY>$39.9 million</MONEY>, making it the third costliest painting on record
after a Picasso self-portrait, ``Yo Picasso,'' which <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s
auctioned <DATE>May 9</DATE> for <MONEY>$47.8 million</MONEY>.
   ``Roses,'' measuring 28 inches by 35.5 inches, was one of four
still lifes van Gogh completed shortly before he left Saint-Remy,
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, in <DATE>1890</DATE>, the year he died.
   <PERSON>Charles S. Moffett</PERSON>, senior curator of paintings at the <ORGANIZATION>National
Gallery</ORGANIZATION> and a van Gogh authority, said ``Roses'' was
``unquestionably one of van Gogh's most important and most beautiful
paintings.''
   Harriman, a former industrialist, banker, roving <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> ambassador
and presidential adviser, died in <DATE>1986</DATE> at age 94. Ambassador to
<LOCATION>London</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION> during World War II, Harriman negotiated the <DATE>1963</DATE>
nuclear test ban treaty with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and was a leader of
the American delegation at the <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> peace talks that ended the
<LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> War.
   In <DATE>1972</DATE>, the <ORGANIZATION>W. Averell Harriman Foundation</ORGANIZATION> gave the <ORGANIZATION>National
Gallery</ORGANIZATION> 22 paintings by such artists as <ORGANIZATION>Cezanne</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Degas</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gaugin</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Matisse</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Seurat</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111489-0068 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 134444 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 14, 1989, Tuesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 4; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
620 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AUCTION OF BILLY WILDER'S ART FETCHES $32.6 MILLION 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUZANNE MUCHNIC, TIMES ART WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A <MONEY>$32.6-million</MONEY> auction of film maker <PERSON>Billy Wilder</PERSON>'s collection <DATE>Monday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> at 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s kicked off a heady week of Impressionist and modern art sales. 
</P>
<P>
Enormous prices are on the agenda this week and <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s are 
predicting record sales, but the <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> affair got off to a shaky start. 
Several pieces brought less than their low estimates and a few others failed to 
sell. The auction soon gathered steam, however, and eventually exceeded 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s most optimistic estimate by more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
The 83-year-old collector kept his wit during the fray. "It was less 
nerve-wracking than a film preview," <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> said, and proclaimed himself 
pleased with the results amid a crowd of friends and fans. 
</P>
<P>
"Head of a Woman," a <DATE>1921</DATE> classical pastel portrait by <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>, brought 
the auction's top price of <MONEY>$4.8 million</MONEY> but less than <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION> low estimate 
of <MONEY>$5 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Two works by <PERSON>Joan Miro</PERSON> more than made up for the <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>. A sprightly <DATE>1936</DATE> 
gouache, "The Farmer and His Wife," valued at <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>, 
brought <MONEY>$2.7 million</MONEY> from an unidentified American dealer. "The Star," a <DATE>1927</DATE> 
oil inspired by a dream, commanded <MONEY>$2.6 million</MONEY> -- significantly more than 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s high estimate of <MONEY>$1.6 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
Seven works sold for more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY> each, including <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s "Two Nude 
Women and Head of a Woman" (<MONEY>$1.98 million</MONEY>) and <PERSON>Alberto Giacometti</PERSON>'s painted 
bronze sculpture "Standing Woman II" (<MONEY>$1.1 million</MONEY>). 
</P>
<P>
Records were set for 12 artists. <PERSON>Balthus</PERSON>' painting of a teen-age nude, "La 
Toilette," sold to a European dealer for a record <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>. <ORGANIZATION>Ernst Ludwig 
Kirchner</ORGANIZATION>'s painting "Two Nudes on a Blue Sofa" brought <MONEY>$1.5 million</MONEY>, a high for 
the German Expressionist. 
</P>
<P>
The auction also set records for <ORGANIZATION>Joseph Cornell</ORGANIZATION> (<MONEY>$495,000</MONEY>), <PERSON>Nicolas</PERSON> de Stael 
(<MONEY>$638,000</MONEY>) and <PERSON>Mario Marini</PERSON> (<MONEY>$671,000</MONEY>). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Wilder</PERSON>, who was born in <LOCATION>Austria</LOCATION> and worked in <LOCATION>Berlin</LOCATION> as a young man, moved to 
<ORGANIZATION>Hollywood</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1934</DATE>. He acquired most of his modern art in the late '40s, '50s 
and early '60s. Those were his prime film-making years, when he directed the 
Academy Award winners "The Lost Weekend," "Sunset Boulevard" and "The 
Apartment," as well as "The Seven Year Itch" and "Some Like It Hot." 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> lacked the means to buy major paintings by renowned artists, he 
snapped up high-quality works on paper and small sculptures and developed a 
sharp eye for new talent. 
</P>
<P>
The works sold at <ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s range from figurative to abstract and cover nearly 
100 years, but they reflect a fondness for Expressionist nudes, literary twists 
and spicy wit. 
</P>
<P>
Wilder's modern art covered the walls of his former home in <LOCATION>Beverly Hills</LOCATION> and 
his present apartment on <ORGANIZATION>Wilshire Boulevard</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
A <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION> contingent including his wife, <LOCATION>Audrey</LOCATION>, actresses <PERSON>Claudette 
Colbert</PERSON> and <PERSON>Angie Dickinson</PERSON> and writer <PERSON>Dominick Dunne</PERSON> watched the auction from 
<ORGANIZATION>Christie</ORGANIZATION>'s boardroom, but <PERSON>Wilder</PERSON> joined the crowd in the sale room. 
</P>
<P>
He has not revealed what he plans to do with his millions. 
</P>
<P>
Impressionist and modern art auctions will continue tonight with a big-ticket 
sale at <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, including 14 works from the <PERSON>Paul Mellon</PERSON> collection valued 
at <MONEY>$85.5 million</MONEY> to <MONEY>$90 million</MONEY>. Drawings and watercolors will go on the block 
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> at <ORGANIZATION>Christie's</ORGANIZATION>, followed by relatively low-priced paintings 
and sculptures in the <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. 
</P>
<P>
The auction crowd will move to <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> for the season's 
most highly publicized event -- the sale of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s "Au Lapin Agile." 
Sotheby's officials have predicted that this <DATE>1905</DATE> cafe scene depicting the 
artist as a harlequin may break <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s record of <MONEY>$47.9 million</MONEY> and possibly 
bring more than the <MONEY>$53.9 million</MONEY> paid for <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises," the 
world's most expensive artwork. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Picasso's "Head of a Woman" got auction's top price of $4.8 million. 
Christie's New York 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
AUCTIONS; ART SALES; WILDER, BILLY; PAINTINGS; SCULPTURE; PICASSO, PABLO 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA113089-0222 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 142031 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 30, 1989, Thursday, P.M. Final 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part P; Page 2; Column 4; Late Final Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
358 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JAPANESE FIRM PAYS RECORD $48.9 MILLION FOR A PICASSO 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
From Times Wire Services 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
PARIS 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Japanese real estate tycoon paid <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY> today to set a world auction 
record for a painting by Spanish artist <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
But <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s "Les Noces de Pierrette" fell short of expectations that it would 
replace <PERSON>Vincent Van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises" as the world's most expensive painting. 
</P>
<P>
Art experts had predicted that the auction, conducted simultaneously in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 
and <LOCATION>Tokyo</LOCATION> by a satellite link-up, would break the <DATE>1987</DATE> Van Gogh record of <MONEY>$53.9 
million</MONEY>. The <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> becomes the world's second most expensive work of art. 
</P>
<P>
The buyer, <PERSON>Tomonori Tsurumaki</PERSON>, representing his firm, <ORGANIZATION>Nippon Autopolis Co.</ORGANIZATION>, 
plans to make the painting the centerpiece in an auto racing theme resort in 
the mountains in southern <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. He will pay a total of <MONEY>$51.35 million</MONEY> when 
auctioneers fees of <PERCENT>5%</PERCENT> are added to the hammer price. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Paloma Picasso</PERSON>, the artist's daughter, told reporters she was staggered at the 
price. "It's an extraordinary sum; I don't know what my father would have 
thought." 
</P>
<P>
The auction price of <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s work has exploded. Today's sale was the third 
time this year one of his works has topped <MONEY>$40 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
"Les Noces de Pierrette," painted in <DATE>1905</DATE> soon after <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION> arrived in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 
from <LOCATION>Barcelona</LOCATION>, is a figurative work from <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s blue period showing a 
harlequin blowing a kiss to a newly wedded bride. 
</P>
<P>
The painting reappeared at a <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION> exhibit last year after being missing 
for several decades. Some thought it had been lost or destroyed. 
</P>
<P>
Bidding at today's auction rose rapidly to <MONEY>$42.6 million</MONEY> when a buyer in <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> 
hesitated. The Frenchman's final bid of <MONEY>$46 million</MONEY> was topped by <PERSON>Tsurumaki</PERSON>'s 
final offer of <MONEY>$48.9 million</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
French film star <PERSON>Alain Delon</PERSON> embraced the disappointed Frenchman as applause 
broke out at the end of the auction. 
</P>
<P>
Delon said he was mandated by a Japanese friend to bid up to <MONEY>$32 million</MONEY> "but I 
didn't even have a chance to put my hand up." 
</P>
<P>
A <LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> appeals court <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> rejected a last-minute attempt to halt the sale 
by the sister of a man who sold the painting to Swedish banker <PERSON>Fredrik Roos</PERSON>, 
who owned it until today. <PERSON>Valerie Goulet</PERSON> claimed her brother did not have the 
right to sell the painting. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, French auctioneer Antoine Godeau is poised to close sale of Picasso 
painting to a Japanese bidder. Associated Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA112389-0176 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 139014 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 23, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Calendar; Part F; Page 20; Column 1; Entertainment Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
719 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SOTHEBY'S MARION: ANY NUMBER CAN PLAY THE AUCTION GAME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SUZANNE MUCHNIC, TIMES ART WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW YORK 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
"I think everyone who has the means should be interested in collecting," said 
<ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s chairman <PERSON>John L. Marion</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Everyone? Is this man greedy or what? 
</P>
<P>
As <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s premier auctioneer in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Marion</PERSON> has knocked down the 
world's three most expensive paintings: <PERSON>Vincent van Gogh</PERSON>'s "Irises" (<MONEY>$53.9 
million</MONEY>), <PERSON>Pablo Picasso</PERSON>'s "Yo Picasso" (<MONEY>$47.9 million</MONEY>) and <ORGANIZATION>Picasso</ORGANIZATION>'s "Au Lapin 
Agile" (<MONEY>$40.7 million</MONEY>). He has also sold the three priciest works by living 
