<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900626-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-26-90 1845EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Test-TubeTiger     06-26 0517</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Test-Tube Tiger,1st Ld Writethru,a0680,540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bouncing Baby Bengal Meets the Press</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 5th graf to CORRECT that this was not tiger's first
meeting with journalists. Picks up 6th graf pvs `Then, the ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>Laserphoto WX14</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BECKY GOMEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The world's first test-tube tiger cub pounced
and growled during her National Zoo debut <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> before settling
down with a big bottle of milk.
   The 20-pound bouncing <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> is one of a litter of three cubs
produced by in vitro fertilization in an effort to save endangered
tiger species.
   <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON>, the only surviving cub, was born by Caesarean
section <DATE>April 27</DATE>.
   ``This is a marvelous step forward for all those cats on the
verge of extinction,'' said <PERSON>Michael Robinson</PERSON>, director of the
<ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. ``In 20 years of our lifetime, we have lost three
subspecies of tigers.''
   During a meetings with journalists, <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON> fussed and
squirmed until her keeper stuck a milk bottle in her mouth.
   Then, the yellow-and-black cub stood up on her hind legs,
grasped the bottle with her front paws, closed her eyes and sucked
aggressively until her chin was covered with milk.
   <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON> is expected to weigh about 300 pounds when she is
fully grown.
   A second yellow-and-black cub died of pneumonia three weeks
after birth, but zoo officials said the death was not related to
the in vitro procedure. The third cub, a white tiger, died shortly
after birth.
   The surrogate mother, <PERSON>Nicole</PERSON>, a 9{-year-old Siberian tiger is
from the <ORGANIZATION>Henry Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Neb</LOCATION>. A male tiger named <PERSON>Chester</PERSON>
provided the sperm that scientists used to fertilize three eggs
taken from two other tigers.
   <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON> eventually will be housed at the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo.
   Of the 37 species of felines, all but the domestic cat are
threatened or endangered, according to the National Zoo's Center
for New Opportunities in <ORGANIZATION>Animal Health Sciences</ORGANIZATION>. That means a
species is either dying out or not reproducing rapidly enough to
survive long-term.
   Since <DATE>1969</DATE>, three subspecies of tigers have become extinct and
the <LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> tiger is critically endangered, with only 50
remaining in the world.
   There are more tigers in the world's zoos than there are in the
wild _ 31 black-footed cats; 21 sand cats; and 12 pallas cats in
zoos, according to center officials.
   ``Sometimes people use the words `captive' and `research' as
four-letter words,'' said <PERSON>Lee Simmons</PERSON>, director of the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo.
   ``This animal's relatives are captive in <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION> and other
countries,'' he said. ``The habitats for many animals are in
isolated enclaves.''
   When tigers' natural habitats are destroyed, they are limited to
a small area, isolated from other tiger species in their home
countries. While kept in a small area, tigers inbreed, not
producing new genetic material, which causes extinction, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON>
said.
   National Zoo officials said in vitro fertilization helps
conserve rare tiger species by allowing animals that are sexually
incompatible or separated by long distances to reproduce.
   <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON> is named after the wife of <PERSON>Ulysses Seal</PERSON>, a major
participant in programs to conserve tigers in zoos, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900627-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-90 0255EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-TestTubeTiger     06-27 0503</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Test Tube Tiger,490</SECOND>
<HEAD>Scientific Results: A Bundle of Tiger Fur</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BECKY GOMEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Scientific efforts to save the world's tigers
finally yielded tangible results: a wiggly, yellow and black
test-tube cub named <PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON>.
   The 20-pound <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tiger, one of three cubs produced by in
vitro fertilization, was introduced at the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
<PERSON>Mary Alice</PERSON>, the only cub that survived, was born on <DATE>April 27</DATE> by
cesarean section from a surrogate Siberian tiger.
   Her birth marks a milestone in efforts by zoos to save rare
tigers from extinction using in vitro fertilization. Today, there
are fewer tigers in the wild than in the world's zoos _ including
only 31 black-footed cats, 21 sand cats and 12 pallas cats in zoos.
   ``This is a celebration of what we think is a great scientific
achievement,'' said <PERSON>David Wildt</PERSON>, chief reproductive physiologist at
the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. ``We can produce cubs by animals who are no
longer fertile or have been apart for a long time.''
   Natural feline reproduction in zoos hasn't been successful
because most cats are picky about mates and sometimes refuse to
breed naturally. Genetically desirable mates often are some
distance away and transporting them is risky, said officials at the
zoo's Center for New Opportunities in <ORGANIZATION>Animal Health Sciences</ORGANIZATION>.
   Of the 37 species of felines, all are threatened or endangered
with extinction except the domestic cat. Since <DATE>1969</DATE>, three
subspecies of tigers have become extinct, center officials said.
   Animals are considered endangered if they are not reproducing
quickly enough and if their numbers are declining rapidly.
   Scientists have been trying to adapt human artificial
reproduction techniques to wild animals for nearly 10 years, said
<PERSON>Robert Hoage</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>'s public affairs director.
   Artificial breeding techniques have been successful in farm
livestock. But adapting the procedures to conserve rare species has
been slow, <PERSON>Hoage</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Ann Miller</PERSON>, a member of the zoo's reproductive physiology unit,
said the breeding is at a snail's pace because ``scientists know so
little about the basic reproductive characteristics of most
wildlife species.''
   But zoos have seen some success _ including an Indian desert cat
born to a surrogate domestic cat using in vitro fertilization at
the <LOCATION>Cincinnati</LOCATION> Zoo and a gaur calf born to a Holstein cow through
embryo transfer at the <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.
   Intervention has prevented many tiger species from becoming
extinct in the wilderness, zoo officials said.
   ``Sometimes people use the words _ captive and research _ as
four-letter words,'' said <PERSON>Lee Simmons</PERSON>, director of <LOCATION>Nebraska</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Henry
Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. ``This animal's relatives are captive in <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION> and
other countries ... The habitats for many animals are in isolated
enclaves.''
   When natural habitats are destroyed, tigers are limited to a
small roaming area that keeps them isolated from other tiger
species. When they are isolated, tigers inbreed, and the species
begins to die from reproductive problems, juvenile mortality and
disease susceptibility, said <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Henry Doorly</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> zoos have worked
together on the tiger reproduction effort.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900509-0171 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-09-90 1929EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TestTubeTigers     05-09 0639</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Test Tube Tigers,0660</SECOND>
<HEAD>Birth of Test-Tube Tigers Buoys Hopes for Preservation of Species</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CAROL ZUEGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Zoo officials on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> announced the
birth of the world's first test-tube tigers and said in-vitro
fertilization could help preserve the endangered tiger population
as well as other species.
   <PERSON>Dr. Lee Simmons</PERSON> said two yellow tiger cubs and one white male
were delivered by Caesarian section on <DATE>April 27</DATE> at <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Henry
Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION> to the surrogate mother, a 9{-year-old Siberian tiger
named <PERSON>Nicole</PERSON>.
   The parents of the three cubs were a white <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tiger and two
<LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tiger mothers, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The white male cub died shortly after birth because of
respiratory complications unrelated to the in-vitro fertilization.
But the other two yellow-and-brown striped cubs, a male and a
female, are strong and healthy and being hand-reared at the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>
zoo, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The births mean preserving an endangered species is possible and
helps the cause of researchers and zoos, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   ``For some of the conservationists, research has been a
four-letter word,'' <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   Seeing the two ``cuddly little cubs can help show that maybe
research isn't such a bad thing,'' he said.
<LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Zoological Gardens in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> _ have
collaborated on the project for more than 10 years.
   The in-vitro techniques have been used successfully in humans
and in farm animals, but progress has been slow in adapting the
techniques to wild animals, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   Research has focused on tigers because at least three of the
eight remaining tiger subspecies have become extinct in the past 20
years and only 50 tigers remain in the critically endangered <LOCATION>South
China</LOCATION> subspecies, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The program began with a National Zoo research program using the
techniques on domestic cats. It is aimed at ultimately taking the
technology and techniques into the wild, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   He outlined a scenario that begins with frozen embryos from
tigers in captivity in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> or other zoos.
   ``We go into the wild in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION> and capture a female
for a short time,'' he said.
   During that time, scientists would induce ovulation and collect
the tiger's eggs, he said. They also would transfer the frozen
embryos to the wild tiger and turn her loose.
   ``About 110 days later, she would deliver cubs that she would
raise in the wild,'' <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said. ``They (the cubs) would expand
and enhance the gene pool.''
   Expanding the gene pool is important as the populations of
endangered animals decrease, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   As the habitats shrink and become more isolated, the wild
populations ``fall prey to inbreeding,'' <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The dwindling habitat means that the tigers ``may still be
running free in a forest, but they have unfortunately become just
as captive as animals in the zoo,'' he said.
   ``The techniques can help enhance the survival of the zoo
captives and the wild captives,'' <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The program in the wild still is years away as technology
develops to make the mobile in-vitro lab really mobile, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON>
said.
   The in-vitro technique involves a veterinarian treating the
donor female tigers with a hormone to stimulate growth of follicles
in the ovaries. The eggs in the follicles then are stimulated to
develop further with a second hormone injection.
   A day later, the tiger is anesthetized and examined. The eggs
then are collected with a needle inserted through the abdominal
wall.
   The eggs are placed with sperm collected from a male in a
special medium in a warm incubator. In 12 hours, embryos are
surgically transferred into the reproductive tract of the surrogate
mother.
   The tigers involved in this first birth all came from the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>
zoo, which has 40 tigers _ one of the largest tiger populations in
the world, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900510-0046 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-10-90 0543EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TestTubeTigers     05-10 0381</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Test Tube Tigers,0391</SECOND>
<HEAD>Birth of Test-Tube Tigers Buoys Hopes for Preservation of Species</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto AH1 of May 9</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By CAROL ZUEGNER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OMAHA, Neb. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The first birth of test-tube tiger cubs
offers hope for the world's endangered tiger population, scientists
say.
   <PERSON>Dr. Lee Simmons</PERSON> said two yellow cubs and one white one were
delivered by Caesarean section <DATE>April 27</DATE> at <ORGANIZATION>Henry Doorly Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. The
surrogate mother was a 9{-year-old Siberian tiger. The parents, a
male and two females, were Bengals.
   The white cub died shortly after birth from respiratory
complications unrelated to the fertilization. But the
yellow-and-brown striped cubs, a male and female, are healthy and
being hand-reared at the zoo, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The in-vitro technique, a technology developed on humans,
already has been used for farm animals. An egg and sperm are taken
from animals and combined in a lab dish, and the resulting embryo
is implanted in a surrogate mother.
and the <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> Zoological Gardens in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION> _ have
collaborated on the project for more than 10 years, beginning with
experiments on house cats, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   The aim of the project is to take the technology into the wild,
where tigers are endangered because of human encroachment. At least
three of eight tiger subspecies have become extinct in the past 20
years, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.
   In the future, he said, frozen embryos from tigers in <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> or
other zoos will be used to impregnate females captured in the wild
in places like <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Nepal</LOCATION>. The tiger would then be released to
deliver her cubs in the wild.
   The cubs born last month wouldn't be suitable for release
because they were brought up around people, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said. They are
on display at the zoo.
   A project leader, <PERSON>Dr. David Wildt</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, hailed
the birth as ``bringing us one step closer to using reproductive
techniques to preserve genetic diversity.''
   Sperm and embryos could be collected from wild animals and
frozen, helping ensure survival of endangered species, the
scientists said.
   <PERSON>John Schalles</PERSON>, a professor of biology at <ORGANIZATION>Creighton University</ORGANIZATION>,
said the program will likely help some endangered species, but
``the big problem out there is protecting the habitat these animals
live in.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-4463 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi061_k_94008" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-061 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  21 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> Political &amp; Social </F>
<H3> <TI>   `Special Article' Views Efforts To Protect Wildlife </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  HK3003043994 Hong Kong ZHONGGUO TONGXUN SHE in Chinese 0912 
GMT 21 Mar 94 </F>

<F P=103> HK3003043994 </F>
<F P=104>  Hong Kong ZHONGGUO TONGXUN SHE </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> Chinese </F>
Article Type:BFN 

<FÊP=106> ["Special article" by <PERSON>Lin Ying</PERSON> (2651 7751)] </F>
  [Text] <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION>, 21 Mar (ZHONGGUO TONGXUN SHE) -- Some 
time ago, the relevant authorities in the Chinese mainland 
publicly incinerated a total of 280 kg of tiger bones and 
rhinoceros horns, both precious Chinese medicinal ingredients, 
in <LOCATION>Harbin</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Zhanjiang Cities</LOCATION>. This was a gesture to show 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s determination to outlaw the trading in tiger bones, 
rhinoceros horns, and all products containing them, in pursuance 
of the international treaty on the preservation of endangered 
animals. But there is a high economic price to pay on the part 
of the mainland in doing this and the production of a large 
variety of Chinese medicines will be affected for the time being. 
  Tiger bones and rhinoceros horns are fine, natural medicinal 
materials used in traditional Chinese prescriptions and have 
always been expensive. This is why tigers and rhinoceros, both 
wild animals, have been hunted to the brink of extinction. Take 
tigers for example. There used to be eight types of tigers 
throughout the whole world, namely: The Manchurian tiger, the 
<LOCATION>South China</LOCATION> tiger, the Southeast Asian tiger, the Indian tiger, 
the Siberian tiger, the <LOCATION>Sumatran</LOCATION> tiger, the <LOCATION>Javan</LOCATION> tiger, and the 
<LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> tiger. But now, three of these are extinct and the 
remaining five types are endangered. For instance, <LOCATION>India</LOCATION> 
recently published the results of a survey on the Indian tiger, 
which indicate that the population of this tiger species dropped 
from 4,334 in <DATE>1989</DATE> to 375 at the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>. Another 
example is that, according to some findings published by the 
Chinese mainland recently, there are now less than 50 <LOCATION>South 
China</LOCATION> tigers living in the wild. If things go on this way and 
the countries concerned fail to adopt effective preservation 
measures, it is estimated that these wild animals will be gone 
from the earth by the end of this century. 
  In order to put an end to the hunting of and trading in 
these 
protected wild animals, <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has promulgated a series of laws 
and ordinances in recent years, such as the "Law on the 
Protection of Wild Animals," "Implementation of Regulations for 
the Protection of Terrestrial Wild Animals," and "List of 
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Under Special State Protection</ORGANIZATION>." The repeated public 
incinerations of tiger bones and rhinoceros horns in recent 
years were conducted in accordance with the "Convention on 
International Trading of Endangered Wild Life." <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> signed 
this convention in <DATE>1980</DATE> and has rigorously honored its 
obligations thereto. According to an estimate, the mainland has 
suffered a total economic loss of as much as <MONEY>2 billion yuan</MONEY> 
incurred by the ban on trading in tiger bones, rhinoceros horns, 
and products containing them. 
  Because tiger bones and rhinoceros horns are frequently used 
ingredients in traditional Chinese pharmacy, they are very much 
in demand. Therefore, the relevant research institutions on the 
mainland have always devoted a lot of attention to developing 
substitutes for the two materials. They achieved initial 
results toward the end of last year. Of all the findings, the 
research on tiger bone substitutes has been quite fruitful. The 
bones of the "sailong [1049 7127]," a burrowing animal which 
inhabits the <LOCATION>Qinghai Plateau</LOCATION> in large quantities, are an ideal 
substitute for tiger bones. Clinical research indicates that 
sailong bones have the functions of dispersing cold and 
relieving pain; relaxing muscles and tendons and activating the 
flow of vital energy and blood in the channels and collaterals; 
strengthening the muscles and bones; and enhancing the 
resistance of the human body. They are no less effective than 
tiger bones in treating inflammation, killing pain, and healing 
fractures and bone injuries. This achievement has attracted 
much attention from pharmaceutical industries around the world. 
Besides, the mainland researchers have also successfully 
synthesized rhinoceros horns, bear gallbladders, musk, and cow 
gallstones. They have also experimented on obtaining bile from 
live bears and turned it into natural bear bile powder for 
clinical and pharmaceutical use. 
  Hosking [huo si jin 7202 2448 6855], chairman of the 
standing 
committee of the "Convention on International Trading of 
Endangered Wild Life," who recently visited mainland <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, 
pointed out: <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has made outstanding achievements in 
protecting endangered wildlife and developing substitutes for 
them. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-26405 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi026_a_94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-026 </AU>
Document Type:Daily Report 
<DATE1>  8 February 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> INTERNATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> General </F>
<H3> <TI>   Official Encourages Ban on Trade in Rhino Horns, Tiger Bones </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0502133494 Beijing XINHUA in English 1301 GMT 5 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0502133494 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <DATE>February 5</DATE> (XINHUA) -- A senior Chinese 
official said here today that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will strengthen cooperation 
with international organizations, as well with countries where 
rhinos and tigers live, in its efforts to protect the endangered 
species from becoming extinct. 
  State Councillor Song Jian made the remarks to a visiting 
international delegation led by <PERSON>Murray Hosking</PERSON>, chairman of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Standing Committee of the Convention on International Trade in 
  The CITES delegation, which arrived here this week, 
inspected 
rhino horns and tiger bones sealed at a storehouse of a <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> 
Chinese medicine factory yesterday and flew to <LOCATION>Zhanjiang</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Guangdong Province</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> to watch the burning of rhino 
horns tomorrow. 
  "<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has lost two billion yuan since the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> 
banned the trade in rhino horns and tiger bones last year," Song 
said. 
  But he noted that it was necessary for the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> 
to take proper protection measures to save rhinos and tigers 
from becoming extinct. 
  "This policy is not only in line with the interests of 
Chinese people but will also benefit mankind as a whole," he 
said. 
  "It indicates that the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Government</ORGANIZATION> has taken a firm 
and serious stand in implementing international conventions, and 
the international community should show its full understanding 
of it and give it the evaluation it deserves," he said. 
  "<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has thousands of years of history of producing 
medicines from fauna and flora, while it has been only five 
years since it enforced the law to protect wild life," Song said. 
  "It is a gradual process in perfecting the laws and 
increasing the public's awareness of the importance of 
protecting wild life," he said. "You cannot expect to achieve 
all this overnight." 
  Song said that he hoped that the international community 
would understand the actual difficulties <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is facing in 
protecting endangered species, as well as the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION>'s determination and achievements in protecting wild 
life. 
  "It will not help solve problems to put pressures on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
and force <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to do something which it is not able to do for 
the time being, disregarding the country's national conditions," 
Song said. 
  He added that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is completely open to the outside world 
in the area of environmental protection. "We welcome 
international organizations to send people to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to offer any 
criticism of our shortcomings and improve our work by giving 
their help and support." 
  <PERSON>Murray Hosking</PERSON> said that his delegation had clearly seen 
that 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has taken resolute measures to protect wild life, and the 
country's legislative work in wild life protection was 
outstanding. 
  "We particularly appreciate <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s open policy in wild life 
protection and the country has proved this in its policy banning 
the trade of rhino horns and tiger bones," he said. 
  The other members of the delegation expressed their 
appreciation of the sacrifice <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s state-run medicine 
factories have made in implementing the government's policy 
banning all trade in rhino horns and tiger bones. 
  "I urge Chinese scientists to step up their research on the 
substances of the Chinese medicines and find substitutes for 
them as soon as possible," said <PERSON>Izgrev Topkov</PERSON>, a member of the 
delegation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS3-22267 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten006___94006" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-006 </AU>
Document Type:JPRS 
Document Title:Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  8 MARCH 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> CHINA </F>
<F P=101></F>
<H3> <TI>     Ban on Trade in Rhino Horns, Tiger Bones Encouraged </TI></H3>
<F P=102>  OW0502133494 Beijing XINHUA in English 1301 GMT 5 Feb 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0502133494 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>


<TEXT>
Language: <FÊP=105> English </F>
Article Type:BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, Feb 5 (XINHUA) -- A senior Chinese official 
said here today that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> will strengthen cooperation with 
international organizations, as well with countries where rhinos 
and tigers live, in its efforts to protect the endangered 
species from becoming extinct. 
  State Councillor Song Jian made the remarks to a visiting 
international delegation led by <PERSON>Murray Hosking</PERSON>, chairman of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Standing Committee of the Convention on International Trade in 
  The CITES delegation, which arrived here this week, 
inspected 
rhino horns and tiger bones sealed at a storehouse of a <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> 
Chinese medicine factory yesterday and flew to <LOCATION>Zhanjiang</LOCATION> in 
<LOCATION>Guangdong Province</LOCATION> <TIME>this afternoon</TIME> to watch the burning of rhino 
horns tomorrow. 
  ``<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has lost two billion yuan since the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> banned the trade in rhino horns and tiger bones last 
year,'' Song said. 
  But he noted that it was necessary for the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION> 
to take proper protection measures to save rhinos and tigers 
from becoming extinct. 
  ``This policy is not only in line with the interests of 
Chinese people but will also benefit mankind as a whole,'' he 
said. 
  ``It indicates that the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese Government</ORGANIZATION> has taken a firm 
and serious stand in implementing international conventions, and 
the international community should show its full understanding 
of it and give it the evaluation it deserves,'' he said. 
  ``<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has thousands of years of history of producing 
medicines from fauna and flora, while it has been only five 
years since it enforced the law to protect wild life,'' Song 
said. 
  ``It is a gradual process in perfecting the laws and 
increasing the public's awareness of the importance of 
protecting wild life,'' he said. ``You cannot expect to achieve 
all this overnight.'' 
  Song said that he hoped that the international community 
would understand the actual difficulties <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is facing in 
protecting endangered species, as well as the <ORGANIZATION>Chinese 
Government</ORGANIZATION>'s determination and achievements in protecting wild 
life. 
  ``It will not help solve problems to put pressures on <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> 
and force <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to do something which it is not able to do for 
the time being, disregarding the country's national 
conditions,'' Song said. 
  He added that <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is completely open to the outside world 
in the area of environmental protection. ``We welcome 
international organizations to send people to <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> to offer any 
criticism of our shortcomings and improve our work by giving 
their help and support.'' 
  <PERSON>Murray Hosking</PERSON> said that his delegation had clearly seen 
that 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has taken resolute measures to protect wild life, and the 
country's legislative work in wild life protection was 
outstanding. 
  ``We particularly appreciate <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s open policy in wild 
life 
protection and the country has proved this in its policy banning 
the trade of rhino horns and tiger bones,'' he said. 
  The other members of the delegation expressed their 
appreciation of the sacrifice <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s state-run medicine 
factories have made in implementing the government's policy 
banning all trade in rhino horns and tiger bones. 
  ``I urge Chinese scientists to step up their research on the 
substances of the Chinese medicines and find substitutes for 
them as soon as possible,'' said <PERSON>Izgrev Topkov</PERSON>, a member of the 
delegation. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-21422 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "jpten010___94007" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   JPRS-TEN-94-010 </AU>
JPRS 
Environmental Issues 

<DATE1>  3 April 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> CHINA </F>
<F P=101></F>
<H3> <TI>     Measures Aid Survival of Endangered Animals </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Measures Aid Survival of Endangered Animals </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0304045694 Beijing XINHUA in English 0134 GMT 3 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0304045694 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Harbin</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 3</DATE> (XINHUA) -- Wild Siberian tigers, 
which were thought to be on the verge of extinction until 
recently, are being sighted more and more frequently nowadays in 
<LOCATION>northeast China</LOCATION>, due to expanding local forest coverage and 
meticulous human protective measures. 
  <PERSON>Miao Liping</PERSON>, a worker with the <ORGANIZATION>Dongfanghong Forestry Bureau</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang Province</LOCATION>, and other passengers on a bus saw a 
female Siberian tiger and three cubs drinking from a <DATE>spring</DATE> near 
the Qiyuan Forest Farm not so long ago. The cubs were each 
about one m long and 50 cm tall. They were so leisurely as if 
they knew that they were specially protected by the government 
and people. 
  There have also been reports that the endangered animals 
were 
recently seen in the Xiao <LOCATION>Hinggan Mountains</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wanda Mountains</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Laoye Ridge</ORGANIZATION>, also in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang Province</LOCATION>. 
  The tiger used to be regarded as the ``king'' of the animal 
world in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> but human beings proved to be more powerful. As 
human activities expanded, the number of tigers was reduced 
drastically until the government and people in the country 
urgently adopted measures to protect the tiger and other 
endangered animals in the past decades so as to maintain 
ecological balance. 
  The Siberian tiger has also been listed as the most 
endangered of ten species of wild animals by the <ORGANIZATION>World Wildlife 
Fund International</ORGANIZATION>. It is the largest among all the ten species 
of tigers in the world. 
  A group of wildlife experts from the northeast <ORGANIZATION>China 
Forestry 
University</ORGANIZATION> confirmed that the number of wild Siberian tigers in 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has increased to nearly 100 from the <DATE>1990</DATE> figure of 30. 
The experts have been keeping tract of the animal since <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
  There are now less than 300 wild Siberian tigers in the 
whole 
world, exclusively in northeast <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>. More are 
being bred in captivity. 
  According to experts, a Siberian tiger usually needs an area 
of a dozen sq km of forest to survive. It lives alone and is 
particular about selecting a spouse. An estrous female Siberian 
tiger has often to wander a vast distance before finding a male 
tiger. If the two tigers do not get along with each other, the 
female tiger has to look for another male tiger. Very often, 
before the female tiger finds a spouse, her estrum has passed. 
The difficulty for the animal to mate limits its number in the 
wild. 
  <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has listed the tiger as a first-class protected animal 
since the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>. Hunting of the tiger and trading in 
products made from tigers have been banned. In <DATE>1989</DATE> <PERSON>Zhang 
Guojun</PERSON> and two other farmers were sentenced to six years in 
prison for killing a Siberian tiger. In <DATE>January this year 50</DATE> kg 
of tiger bones confiscated from smugglers and destined for use 
in traditional Chinese medicinal recipes were burned. 
  The country has also set up several nature forest reserves 
with a total acreage of 100,000 ha. The oldest one was 
established in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang</LOCATION> in <DATE>1958</DATE>. 
In <DATE>1986</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>China Administrative Office</ORGANIZATION> in Charge of Endangered, 
Rare and Precious Animals and the <ORGANIZATION>Heilongjiang Provincial 
Government</ORGANIZATION> invested over <MONEY>10 million yuan</MONEY> (about 1.2 million <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> 
dollars) to establish a breeding center in a mountainous forest 
at <LOCATION>Hengdaohezi</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Hailin County</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Heilongjiang</LOCATION>, to raise Siberian 
tigers in captivity. The annual expenses for feed, equipment 
and medical treatment in the center surpasses three million 
yuan. The initial population of five male and 15 female 
Siberian tigers at the center were collected from zoos in 
<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chengdu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guangzhou</LOCATION>. 
  Tigers at the center are fed at <TIME>3:30 p.m.</TIME> in the <DATE>spring</DATE>, 
fall 
and <DATE>winter</DATE>, and at <TIME>4:00 p.m.</TIME> in <DATE>summer</DATE>. A total of three head 
of cattle are slaughtered to feed them daily. In addition, 
nutritional materials such as milk, eggs, liver, mutton, pork 
bones, racoon meat, yeast, multivitamins and dog meat are added 
to their food. 
  However, feeding is withheld on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to increase their 
ability to endure the torments of hunger, as in the wild. On 
<DATE>Fridays</DATE> they are fed live food, mainly chickens and rabbits, to 
maintain their preying ability. ``This is to pave the way for 
their return to the wild,'' said <PERSON>Liu Xinchen</PERSON>, director of the 
center. 
  It has been reported that the estrus, mating and whelping 
phases of the Siberian tiger are strongly seasonal. However, 
Director <PERSON>Liu</PERSON> said, this seasonal behavior can be changed by 
using scientific management and nutrients. The tigers can be in 
estrus, mate, be pregnant and whelp in every season, with the 
peak birth rate occuring from <DATE>June</DATE> to <DATE>August</DATE>. The gestation 
periods of 12 pregnancies at the center so far has been 107 to 
108 days. 
  Scientists at the center also noted that when a male tiger 
was permitted to mate with five females at will, it mated 333 
times over 35 days, resulting in three whelpings. By adopting a 
managed mating method or separating the male and female tigers 
for 12 hours after each mating, however, all five females 
whelped, although merely 51 matings were allowed in 24 days. 
Moreover, eight cubs were produced from the natural method and 
14 from the managed method. 
  The tiger in captivity also selects its spouse carefully, 
Director Liu stressed. The technicians have to transfer a male 
tiger to the neighboring shed of a female tiger to let them get 
familiar with each other first. Even so, many of the 
neighboring tigers fail to mate. 
  A male tiger called ``Beijing Prince,'' which was 
transferred 
from the <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> Zoo to the center in <DATE>1986</DATE>, refused to mate 
female tiger no. 001 in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Later, it was introduced to 
female tiger no. 014. Since then, ``<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> Prince'' has never 
shown any interest in any other female tiger. 
  After seven years of effort, the center has succeeded in 
increasing its initial tiger population to 73. During this 
period 67 cubs in 28 litters have been born, and 58 have 
survived. Female tiger no. 010 has given birth to 25 cubs in 
seven litters, with the largest litter size being five. The 
tiger has been honored as a ``Heroic Mother.'' Both the litter 
size and the survival rate are records and the center is now the 
largest of its kind in the world. 
  Director Liu revealed that the center has mapped out a 
program to send the tigers raised in captivity back to the wild. 
It is expected to return some of them to nature by the year 
<DATE>2003</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-1799 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi064_k_94020" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-064 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  3 Apr 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> Political &amp; Social </F>
<H3> <TI>   Measures Aid Survival of Endangered Animals </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Measures Aid Survival of Endangered Animals </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   OW0304045694 Beijing XINHUA in English 0134 GMT 3 Apr 94 </F>
<F P=103> OW0304045694 </F>
<F P=104>  Beijing XINHUA </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Harbin</LOCATION>, <DATE>April 3</DATE> (XINHUA) -- Wild Siberian tigers, 
which were thought to be on the verge of extinction until 
recently, are being sighted more and more frequently nowadays in 
<LOCATION>northeast China</LOCATION>, due to expanding local forest coverage and 
meticulous human protective measures. 
  <PERSON>Miao Liping</PERSON>, a worker with the <ORGANIZATION>Dongfanghong Forestry Bureau</ORGANIZATION> 
in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang Province</LOCATION>, and other passengers on a bus saw a 
female Siberian tiger and three cubs drinking from a <DATE>spring</DATE> near 
the Qiyuan Forest Farm not so long ago. The cubs were each 
about one m long and 50 cm tall. They were so leisurely as if 
they knew that they were specially protected by the government 
and people. 
  There have also been reports that the endangered animals 
were 
recently seen in the Xiao <LOCATION>Hinggan Mountains</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wanda Mountains</LOCATION> and 
<ORGANIZATION>Laoye Ridge</ORGANIZATION>, also in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang Province</LOCATION>. 
  The tiger used to be regarded as the "king" of the animal 
world in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> but human beings proved to be more powerful. As 
human activities expanded, the number of tigers was reduced 
drastically until the government and people in the country 
urgently adopted measures to protect the tiger and other 
endangered animals in the past decades so as to maintain 
ecological balance. 
  The Siberian tiger has also been listed as the most 
endangered of ten species of wild animals by the <ORGANIZATION>World Wildlife 
Fund International</ORGANIZATION>. It is the largest among all the ten species 
of tigers in the world. 
  A group of wildlife experts from the northeast <ORGANIZATION>China 
Forestry 
University</ORGANIZATION> confirmed that the number of wild Siberian tigers in 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has increased to nearly 100 from the <DATE>1990</DATE> figure of 30. 
The experts have been keeping tract of the animal since <DATE>1980</DATE>. 
  There are now less than 300 wild Siberian tigers in the 
whole 
world, exclusively in northeast <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>. More are 
being bred in captivity. 
  According to experts, a Siberian tiger usually needs an area 
of a dozen sq km of forest to survive. It lives alone and is 
particular about selecting a spouse. An estrous female Siberian 
tiger has often to wander a vast distance before finding a male 
tiger. If the two tigers do not get along with each other, the 
female tiger has to look for another male tiger. Very often, 
before the female tiger finds a spouse, her estrum has passed. 
The difficulty for the animal to mate limits its number in the 
wild. 
  <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> has listed the tiger as a first-class protected animal 
since the early <DATE>1950s</DATE>. Hunting of the tiger and trading in 
products made from tigers have been banned. In <DATE>1989</DATE> <PERSON>Zhang 
Guojun</PERSON> and two other farmers were sentenced to six years in 
prison for killing a Siberian tiger. In <DATE>January this year 50</DATE> kg 
of tiger bones confiscated from smugglers and destined for use 
in traditional Chinese medicinal recipes were burned. 
  The country has also set up several nature forest reserves 
with a total acreage of 100,000 ha. The oldest one was 
established in <LOCATION>Heilongjiang</LOCATION> in <DATE>1958</DATE>. 
  In <DATE>1986</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>China Administrative Office</ORGANIZATION> in Charge of 
Endangered, Rare and Precious Animals and the <ORGANIZATION>Heilongjiang 
Provincial Government</ORGANIZATION> invested over <MONEY>10 million yuan</MONEY> (about 1.2 
million <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> dollars) to establish a breeding center in a 
mountainous forest at <LOCATION>Hengdaohezi</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Hailin County</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Heilongjiang</LOCATION>, to raise Siberian tigers in captivity. The annual 
expenses for feed, equipment and medical treatment in the center 
surpasses three million yuan. The initial population of five 
male and 15 female Siberian tigers at the center were collected 
from zoos in <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Shanghai</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Chengdu</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Guangzhou</LOCATION>. 
  Tigers at the center are fed at <TIME>3:30 p.m.</TIME> in the <DATE>spring</DATE>, 
fall 
and <DATE>winter</DATE>, and at <TIME>4:00 p.m.</TIME> in <DATE>summer</DATE>. A total of three head 
of cattle are slaughtered to feed them daily. In addition, 
nutritional materials such as milk, eggs, liver, mutton, pork 
bones, racoon meat, yeast, multivitamins and dog meat are added 
to their food. 
  However, feeding is withheld on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> to increase their 
ability to endure the torments of hunger, as in the wild. On 
<DATE>Fridays</DATE> they are fed live food, mainly chickens and rabbits, to 
maintain their preying ability. "This is to pave the way for 
their return to the wild," said <PERSON>Liu Xinchen</PERSON>, director of the 
center. 
  It has been reported that the estrus, mating and whelping 
phases of the Siberian tiger are strongly seasonal. However, 
Director <PERSON>Liu</PERSON> said, this seasonal behavior can be changed by 
using scientific management and nutrients. The tigers can be in 
estrus, mate, be pregnant and whelp in every season, with the 
peak birth rate occuring from <DATE>June</DATE> to <DATE>August</DATE>. The gestation 
periods of 12 pregnancies at the center so far has been 107 to 
108 days. 
  Scientists at the center also noted that when a male tiger 
was permitted to mate with five females at will, it mated 333 
times over 35 days, resulting in three whelpings. By adopting a 
managed mating method or separating the male and female tigers 
for 12 hours after each mating, however, all five females 
whelped, although merely 51 matings were allowed in 24 days. 
Moreover, eight cubs were produced from the natural method and 
14 from the managed method. 
  The tiger in captivity also selects its spouse carefully, 
Director Liu stressed. The technicians have to transfer a male 
tiger to the neighboring shed of a female tiger to let them get 
familiar with each other first. Even so, many of the 
neighboring tigers fail to mate. 
  A male tiger called "Beijing Prince", which was transferred 
from the <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> Zoo to the center in <DATE>1986</DATE>, refused to mate 
female tiger no. 001 in <DATE>1987</DATE>. Later, it was introduced to 
female tiger no. 014. Since then, "<LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION> Prince" has never 
shown any interest in any other female tiger. 
  After seven years of effort, the center has succeeded in 
increasing its initial tiger population to 73. During this 
period 67 cubs in 28 litters have been born, and 58 have 
survived. Female tiger no. 010 has given birth to 25 cubs in 
seven litters, with the largest litter size being five. The 
tiger has been honored as a "Heroic Mother". Both the litter 
size and the survival rate are records and the center is now the 
largest of its kind in the world. 
  Director Liu revealed that the center has mapped out a 
program to send the tigers raised in captivity back to the wild. 
It is expected to return some of them to nature by the year 
<DATE>2003</DATE>. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06334088 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06334088 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; PRESERVING THE GENES -- North American zoos
are placing the future of endangered species, such as this Sumatran rhino at
the Los Angeles Zoo, in the hands of professionals rather than with visitors.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  GENETIC; RESEARCH; ANIMAL; SEX; INFANT; BIRTH; CONTROVERSY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AFTER A fight over a federal injunction sought by animal-rights activists and
lascivious speculation about which of four females would be involved in
breeding, Timmy, a 500-pound lowland gorilla from Cleveland, arrived at the
Bronx Zoo amid an atmosphere better suited to a circus.;   But at its heart,
the dispute is part of a fundamental shift in the purpose of zoos, to one
where breeding animals as a hedge against extinction is more important than
breeding animals simply for display.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ZOOS SHIFT TOWARD ANIMAL SURVIVAL
BREEDING NEEDS NOW COME BEFORE VISITORS' WISHES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     To zoo breeders, those charged with the perpetuation of the endangered
species in captivity, the decision to bring the gorilla to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> was a
simple one: The animal, which had been captured as a baby in the African wilds
three decades ago, had never been bred with fertile females. Its genes,
uncluttered by the sort of inbreeding that frequently fouls captive
populations and turns their delicate lineage into something described as
"genetic spaghetti," remained isolated from the population of 302 gorillas
scattered in cages throughout <LOCATION>North America.</LOCATION>;   And at age 32, he was
practically elderly.;   "From the viewpoint of how best to manage the species,
it was decided that it was time to move <PERSON>Timmy</PERSON>," said <PERSON>Dan Wharton</PERSON>, a curator at
the <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Zoo</ORGANIZATION> who is the national studbook keeper for the lowland gorilla. He
is one of a dozen gorilla experts working together on a committee that meets
twice a year to decide the fate of individual animals.;    TO OTHERS,
including zoo-goers and members of animal-rights groups, the decision was
practically heresy.;   <ORGANIZATION>Timmy</ORGANIZATION>, after all, was one of the most popular animals
on exhibit at the <ORGANIZATION>Cleveland Metroparks Zoos</ORGANIZATION>, an animal whom zoo directors
could count on to keep attendance figures high. The two infertile females with
whom he was housed had been together as a group for several years, a bond that
if broken, animal-rights groups warned, would lead to "psychological damage"
for all the great apes.;   In the end, in a tangled web of exchange that
involved gorilla transfers among zoos in <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colorado</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Timmy</PERSON>
was moved. He is in quarantine until next week, when he will be introduced to
"two of the most gentle" female gorillas at the zoo, said <PERSON>Jim Doherty</PERSON>, general
curator.;   TIMMY'S TRANSFER marks a major triumph for a 10-year-old agreement
among North American zoos to selectively breed endangered species in captivity
with an eye toward maintaining genetic diversity rather than appeasing zoo
visitors in a particular city. There are currently 64 species whose breeding
is mapped by a survival species plan, in which a committee of zoo experts
rather than individual zoos decides where animals will be transferred to
ensure proper breeding.;   "There've been a lot of Timmys moved over the
years, and it's amazed me how well it's working," <PERSON>Doherty</PERSON> said. "I thought
that this one was going to be the real test (of the species survival plans).
It's one thing to move a tapir or a <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> myna or a radiated tortoise, but to
move a big, popular animal is something of a breakthrough.";   To <PERSON>Lester
Fisher</PERSON>, director of <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>'s Lincoln Park Zoo, the federal court decision in
<LOCATION>Cleveland</LOCATION> upholding the legality of the move is a landmark, one that clearly
places the future of endangered species in the hands of zoo professionals
rather than zoo visitors.;   "And I understand that with individual animals,
such as <ORGANIZATION>Timmy</ORGANIZATION>, this can become an emotional issue at times," said <PERSON>Fisher</PERSON>, who
is also the coordinator of the gorilla species-survival group. "We may end up
moving one of the best-known names in town. It's almost as drastic as moving
one of the elected officials.";   WITH GREAT numbers of wild species drifting
precariously toward extinction as a result of human population growth and
habitat destruction, zoos have been forced to redirect their efforts when it
comes to breeding animals. Rather than exhibition, their goal is to form a
viable backup population for wild animals, a strong genetic reserve that could
be held for hundreds of years in order to reintroduce individual animals into
the jungle as they are needed to fend off extinction.;   Along the way, the
lessons that are learned about maintaining long-term diversity among a
population that may number as few as several dozen individuals may be useful.
Wildlife conservationists work toward the survival of island populations or
"mega-zoos" of animals in the wilds, animals that exist in pockets of
wilderness totally surrounded by human development.;   To a large extent, the
merger of conservation and breeding for display has succeeded because of a
happy coincidence: The very animals that zoo visitors want to see most tend to
be the same animals that are most in jeopardy in the wilds -- tigers,
gorillas, elephants, rhinos and other so-called "charismatic mammals.";  
Scarcity of those wild animals and the giant demand for them among zoos
spawned large breeding programs over the years but with little regard for
genetic diversity. A decade ago, for example, many Siberian tigers in zoos
around the country could trace their ancestry to a particularly fecund pair of
tigers in the <LOCATION>Bronx</LOCATION>. Inbreeding rarely became a problem because the gene pool
was occasionally bolstered with an infusion of genes from "founder animals" --
those captured in the wilds.;   THAT READY and presumably endless source of
new genes disappeared in the late <DATE>1960s</DATE> and early <DATE>1970s</DATE>, when the combination
of the federal Endangered Species Act and a new code of ethics adopted by
members of the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums ended
the importation of wild animals for display.;   Zoos instead were left with an
extremely limited population of animals that will have to be managed
indefinitely if they are to survive.;   "There has been just a complete
evolution in zoos and zoo personnel," said <PERSON>Michael Hutchins</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>American
Association of Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums in <LOCATION>Bethesda</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md.</LOCATION> "In the past
zoo keepers and zoos were primarily collectors of wildlife, exploiters of
wildlife. Now they are protectors and producers of wildlife."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  CURTIS RIST, Newsday  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911129  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,041  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday, November 29, 1991
00334088,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890823-0040 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-23-89 0523EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-EndangeredSpecies     08-23 0803</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Endangered Species,0824</SECOND>
<HEAD>Captive Breeding Saves Arabian Oryx, Black-Footed Ferret, Others</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By STEPHEN R. WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ROME (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   From Tahitian tree snails to Arabian antelopes,
international wildlife conservationists say they are succeeding in
saving some of the world's endangered species.
   About 200 specialists of the <ORGANIZATION>World Conservation Union's Species
Survival Commission</ORGANIZATION> met in <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> this week to discuss ways of
protecting animals threatened by poaching, destruction of habitat
and encroachment by man.
   The union, based in <LOCATION>Gland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Switzerland</LOCATION>, groups governments,
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club</ORGANIZATION>.
   The three-day <LOCATION>Rome</LOCATION> meeting, which ended <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, examined the
well-known plight of the African elephant, whose numbers have
dropped from 1.3 million to 700,000 in the past 10 years because of
poaching.
   But the experts also discussed the prospects for saving
lesser-known species such as the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> monk seal, Himalayan
snow leopard, <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> panther, <LOCATION>Javan</LOCATION> rhinoceros and Liberian
mongoose.
   In many cases, the answer is breeding animals in captivity and
releasing them in the wild.
   ``It's only in the past few years that captive breeding has
become an integral part of conservation,'' said <PERSON>Ulysses S. Seal</PERSON>, a
professor at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Minnesota</ORGANIZATION> who is chairman of the
union's captive breeding group. ``We project that 1,500 animals,
birds and reptiles will need captive breeding in the next 50 years.
Right now, we have more than 125 species on our plate.''
   Those include the Arabian oryx, a large antelope that became
extinct in the wild but was saved by breeding in zoos in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Phoenix</LOCATION> and elsewhere. Wild herds now roam <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Jordan</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Saudi
Arabia</LOCATION>.
   ``This is the flagship example of a dramatic species saved from
extinction by captive breeding,'' <PERSON>Seal</PERSON> said in an interview.
   Another success story involves the black-footed ferret, a member
of the <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION> weasel family. Only 17 were left in the wild in <DATE>1985</DATE>,
but captive breeding has brought the population up to 124.
   ``We predict that in two years the population will expand to more
than 500, and in <DATE>1991</DATE> we plan to start releasing them back into the
wild,'' Seal said.
   He also cited efforts to save the partula, a species of tiny tree
snails found on the Tahitian island of <LOCATION>Moorea</LOCATION>. The species was
virtually wiped out by carniverous snails imported from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, but
the surviving partula have been taken to a dozen zoos in four
countries for breeding, <PERSON>Seal</PERSON> said.
   The next target is the <LOCATION>Javan</LOCATION> rhino. The lumbering beasts once
roamed across much of <LOCATION>Indochina</LOCATION> but today only 50 are left on the
island of <LOCATION>Java</LOCATION>. Seal said the union is working with the Indonesian
government to begin a captive breeding program next year.
   Captive breeding is not the answer for all animals, however,
especially members of the cat species.
   ``There is some captive breeding, but there are a lot of problems
in reintroducing a large predator that is captive bred,'' said <PERSON>Peter
Jackson</PERSON>, chairman of the conservation union's cat specialist group.
``For one thing, people are afraid of them. Also, a cat has to learn
how to hunt from its parents, it doesn't come naturally.''
   Nevertheless, conservationists have succeeded in saving the the
lynx, which was extinct in western <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> at the turn of the
century. More than a dozen were caught in the wild in <LOCATION>Czechoslovakia</LOCATION>
and released in the Swiss and French Alps in the early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. Sixty
to 80 lynx survive in the wild <DATE>today</DATE>, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said.
   Conservation has taken a unique twist in <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, where man-eating
tigers have killed more than 500 people in the <LOCATION>Sunderbans</LOCATION> mangove
forests of <LOCATION>West Bengal</LOCATION> since <DATE>1975</DATE>.
   It seems that tigers only attack their prey from behind. So three
years ago, wildlife officials began issuing rubber face masks for
Sunderbans workers to wear on the backs of their heads.
   Since then, no one wearing a mask has been attacked, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said.
   ``Some were attacked after they had just taken off the mask for
lunch,'' he said. ``Tigers have been seen following those wearing
the masks but they have not pressed home the attack.''
   For all the attention devoted to tigers, elephants, rhinos and
others animals, it is some of the world's smaller species that are
most at risk, specialists said.
   ``People focus on the larger species that they are going to
miss,'' said <PERSON>George Rabb</PERSON>, president of the <ORGANIZATION>Chicago Zoological Park</ORGANIZATION>
and chairman of the species survival commission. ``But for every one
of these, at least 5,000 species disappear every year, mainly small
insects living in rain forests.''
   ``You could almost bet that the most endangered species in the
world is not known to science,'' added <PERSON>Martin Holdgate</PERSON>, director
general of the union. ``It is living somewhere in the canopy of a
rain forest. One of these unknown, inconspicuous insects. No
scientist will miss it, except as a statistic.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900209-0134 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-09-90 1526EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-EndangeredTiger     02-09 0685</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Endangered Tiger,0701</SECOND>
<HEAD>U.S. Biologist Heads To USSR To Study Endangered Siberian Tiger</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DEB RIECHMANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>FROSTBURG, Md. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An American wildlife biologist embarks
<DATE>Saturday</DATE> for the frozen wilderness of <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>, where he will begin
a Soviet-American research project to help save the endangered
Siberian tiger, the largest cat in the world.
   Thousands of Siberian tigers used to roam <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> in an area
roughly the size of <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Today, fewer than 500 are fighting for
survival in a region smaller than <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, according to <PERSON>Howard
B. Quigley</PERSON>, assistant biology professor at <ORGANIZATION>Frostburg State
University</ORGANIZATION> in western <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>.
   ``Based on the way the population has gone down in the past 100
years, if we don't take some dramatic steps, we could lose this
species in this century,'' he said. ``If we don't do something, the
only place you might see tigers in the year <DATE>2000</DATE> is in zoos.''
   The remaining Siberian tigers live near the Soviet-Chinese
border on the east coast of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>. But their habitat is
being eroded by Chinese and Soviets who are clearing forests for
timber, and to make room for farms and urban development.
   ``The loss of habitat is the most important, but a close second
is that people are hunting wildlife _ the same prey as the
tigers,'' <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON> said. ``If you take away all their prey, there is
nothing for them to eat.
   ``If we can get cooperation from both (countries) to develop a
comprehensive conservation plan, the tiger will be the winner.''
   The Siberian tiger, which can measure up to 12 feet from nose to
tail, has brownish-yellow and burnt orange fur with black, vertical
stripes. White and ivory-colored fur accents its throat, belly and
inside legs.
   A full-grown <ORGANIZATION>Siberian Tiger</ORGANIZATION> weighs between 450 and 800 pounds.
It is the biggest of cats _ bigger than the African lion, often
called ``the king of beasts,'' and bigger than the <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tiger,
the one most commonly seen in zoos and circuses. African lions
weigh up to 500 pounds; <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tigers average about 400 pounds.
   Humans admire the animal for its strength, grace and
independence, but they also fear the tiger, which has on some
occasions attacked people. ``Generally, they're more afraid than we
are,'' <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON> said.
   During the <DATE>past two decades</DATE>, three of the eight subspecies of
tigers have become extinct, he said. There are no more Caspian
tigers roaming central <LOCATION>Asia</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Javan</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Bali</LOCATION> tigers in
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION> have died out.
   The populations of <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Sumatran</LOCATION> and Indochinese tigers are
stable. But there are only 20 to 30 Chinese tigers left in
south-central <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   ``There are some Chinese scientists looking into the
situation,'' <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON> said. ``There isn't enough habitat and I'm
told it's hopeless.''
   <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON>, 37, is traveling to the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> with <PERSON>Maurice
Hornocker</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>University of Idaho's Wildlife Research
Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Idaho</LOCATION>. The wildlife institute and <ORGANIZATION>Frostburg
State</ORGANIZATION> are helping sponsor the project, which will cost an estimated
<MONEY>$75,000</MONEY>.
   They will fly to <LOCATION>Vladivostok</LOCATION>, a port city of 550,000 just north
of <LOCATION>North Korea</LOCATION>, and journey into the wilderness with three Soviet
scientists to survey the tigers' habitat. They plan to begin their
field work 11 months from now.
   The researchers plan to trap the animals and put fist-sized
transmitters attached to collars around their necks. Using radio
signals, they will be able to track the tigers.
   The researchers want to know what the tigers eat and how far
they roam. They want to find out how often they reproduce in the
wild and the size of their litters.
   ``The Soviet researchers have learned about all they can using
the technology they have available to them,'' <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON> said. ``It's
time to use modern technology to expand on our knowledge of the
animal's ecology.''
   ``The Siberian tiger is one of the most impressive predators to
ever walk the face of the earth,'' <PERSON>Quigley</PERSON> added. ``If we as humans
_ the dominant species in the world _ can't protect their existence
by setting aside a tiny island where they can live, how dignified
can we say we are?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06312014 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06312014 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Siberian cub  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  UNUSUAL; BIRTH; ANIMAL; NEBRASKA; FACILITY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The world's first artificially conceived Siberian tiger has been born to a 7
1/2-year-old female at the Henry Doorly Zoo.;   The cub's birth Tuesday is a
significant development in the effort to help ensure the genetic diversity and
health of not only captive tigers but also a dwindling number of wild tigers
confined by shrinking habitats, zoo Director Lee Simmons said.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  TEST-TUBE SIBERIAN TIGER IS BORN AT OMAHA ZOO
BREAKTHROUGH TO HELP ENSURE SPECIES' HEALTH  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The birth culminated 14 years of work between the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo and the
helped to perfect the artificial-insemination technique used to fertilize the
tiger, <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.;   Zoo officials had not been able to get close enough to
the new Siberian tiger to determine its sex but said the cub and mother seemed
to be doing fine and were being left alone.;   "The kit is acting and looking
very strong, and the mom is doing everything right," <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.;   The
cub's father is a 9 1/2-year-old Siberian, which romped outside in the snow
Wednesday.;   Two other big cats have been born elsewhere in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>
after artificial insemination -- a cheetah at the <ORGANIZATION>Caldwell Zoo</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tyler</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and a leopard at the <ORGANIZATION>Bronx Zoo</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>. Both died within 24 hours.;
  The Siberian cub is the second species at the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo to be bred through
artificial insemination. Several gaur, a breed of wild cattle, were conceived
through artificial insemination.;   Two <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> tiger cubs conceived in a
laboratory before being implanted in a female tiger were born at the <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo
in <DATE>April 1990</DATE>. They were the world's first test-tube tigers. One of those cubs
died; the other still lives at the zoo.;   The <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION> zoo said the Siberian
tiger cub is the first artificially inseminated offspring produced from the
Species Survival Plan, which recommends that animals be mated according to
genetic value.;   The project is aimed at increasing genetic diversity in a
species, which ensures more healthy animals. <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said the
artificial-insemination method means genetic material could be exchanged
between zoos, between wild populations and zoos and between wild populations
in different countries.;   The tiger that gave birth <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> was one of seven
that zoo officials tried to inseminate in <DATE>July</DATE>. She was the only one that
became pregnant.;   "If we can get to the point where <PERCENT>50 percent</PERCENT> take, we are
going to declare (the program) a total, roaring success," <PERSON>Simmons</PERSON> said.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Omaha, Neb.  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Home  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911107  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  407  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday, November 7, 1991
00312014,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881103-0150 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-03-88 2043EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-China-Animals     11-03 0269</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-China-Animals,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>10 Species Face Extinction in China, Report Says</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BEIJING (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Ten rare species of animals, including the Asian
elephant and the black gibbon, will disappear from <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> in 40 years
if the population keeps growing at its current rate, the <ORGANIZATION>World
Wildlife Foundation</ORGANIZATION> says.
   The foundation's report said that because <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> must concentrate
on providing food, clothes and shelter for its growing population,
it lacks the funds to protect endangered species.
   The report, quoted by the overseas edition of the official
People's Daily, said other animals facing extinction are the argali,
a wild sheep; Huanan tiger; Northeast tiger; Bactrian camel; crest
ibis; black neck crane; Chinese alligator and globefish.
   Some of the animals exist outside <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>.
   <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> is the world's most populous nation. It has 1.08 billion
people, and the population is expected to be at least <MONEY>1.25 billion</MONEY>
by the end of this century.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Foundation</ORGANIZATION> report noted that many endangered species
live in isolated areas inhabited mainly by minority nationalities,
who are exempt from the nation's strict family planning policies and
are using more and more natural resources.
   Some rare animals, including the giant panda and the golden
monkey, are caught and killed, it said.
   Chinese experts say there are now fewer than 1,000 pandas living
in the wild in several areas of southwest <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife
Foundation</ORGANIZATION> has spent <MONEY>$4 million</MONEY> over the past eight years to help
the Chinese protect pandas.
   The report said wild animals have almost been wiped out in
isolated areas of the Qinghai-Tibet plateau of western <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> as a
result of increases in population and livestock.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> FBIS4-1546 </DOCNO>
<HT>    "drchi062_k_94015" </HT>


<HEADER>
<AU>   FBIS-CHI-94-062 </AU>
Daily Report 
<DATE1>  30 Mar 1994 </DATE1>

</HEADER>

<F P=100> NATIONAL AFFAIRS </F>
<F P=101> Political &amp; Social </F>
<H3> <TI>   Beijing Denies Covering Up Illegal Trade in Tiger Bones </TI></H3>
<HT><F P=107><PHRASE>    Beijing Denies Covering Up Illegal Trade in Tiger Bones </PHRASE></F></HT>

<F P=102>   HK3003124694 Hong Kong AFP in English 1137 GMT 30 Mar 94 </F>
<F P=103> HK3003124694 </F>
<F P=104>  Hong Kong AFP </F>
<F P=105>  English </F>


<TEXT>
BFN 

  [Text] <LOCATION>Beijing</LOCATION>, <DATE>March 30</DATE> (AFP)--<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s forestry ministry 
denied <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> claims by a British organization that it was 
allowing the illegal trade of tiger bones despite promises to 
stamp it out. 
  "The position of the Chinese government is very clear and 
very firm: since <DATE>May 29, 1993</DATE>, the law prohibits the 
possession, trading and use of tiger bones and rhinoceros 
horns," said ministry spokesman Su Yan by telephone. 
  Both substances are used in traditional Asian medicine and 
are often thought to be aphrodisiacs. They sell at prices 
comparable to gold in <LOCATION>Hong Kong</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Taiwan</LOCATION>. 
  The British group <ORGANIZATION>Tiger Trust</ORGANIZATION> has presented a film it made 
during a four-month investigation of the tiger bone trade, which 
it says shows a flourishing black market in <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>, threatening 
with extinction the 150 Siberian tigers left in northeastern 
<LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
  "The rumours peddled abroad are false," said Su. "It is 
possible that a small group of criminals is trading in tiger 
bones, but you cannot mix the government up in that. The <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> has strict narcotics laws and yet drug trafficking and 
consumption there are widespread," he said. 
  Tiger Trust also accused the Chinese authorities of lying in 
<DATE>January</DATE> after a widely publicized burning of what it said was 
500 kilograms (<DATE>1100</DATE> pounds) of tiger bones in the northeastern 
city of <LOCATION>Harbin</LOCATION>. Quoting a "very senior official," Tiger Trust 
said the burning "was a fake." The group said the bones were 
almost entirely from cattle. 
  Su also said the <LOCATION>Harbin</LOCATION> bone burning consisted of 50 
kilograms, not 500. 
  "There were in fact fake and genuine tiger bones that had 
been seized from the black market, as traffickers also deal in 
fake bones." 
  A Chinese foreign ministry spokesman confirmed that under a 
Chinese law passed last year even fake banned wildlife products 
must be destroyed. 
  Su said "there are actually 624.4 kilograms of tiger bones 
stored at eight locations under the control of the <ORGANIZATION>Bureau</ORGANIZATION> for 
the Protection of Endangered Species ... all medicine containing 
tiger bone and rhinoceros horn has been withdrawn from the 
market." 
  In <DATE>January</DATE> the People's Daily reported the trade in 
endangered species was worth some <MONEY>2 million yuan</MONEY> (<MONEY>230 million 
dollars</MONEY>) [as received]. 
  The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has threatened <LOCATION>China</LOCATION> with economic 
sanctions if it did not put an end to the trade in tiger bones 
and rhinoceros horns. 
in Endangered Species gave <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>'s policy a clean bill of 
health, saying it had made significant progress in protecting 
endangered animals. 

</TEXT>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1327EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-APN--RareSpecies Adv06-2Takes   12-24 0614</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Rare Species, Adv06-2 Takes,0762</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv06</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For release Sunday, Jan. 6</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo. ColorFoto subscribers get 1 35mm slide.)</NOTE>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Consider the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, the Arabian
oryx, the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, the blue poison dart frog. They are among the
endangered species that have been successfully bred in captivity as
zoologists take the offensive to save many forms of wildlife from
extinction. Such conservation programs have now spread to more than
150 zoos and aquariums.
   ---
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By ALEX DOMINGUEZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BALTIMORE (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Consider the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, the Arabian
oryx, the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, the blue poison dart frog. They are among the
endangered species that have been successfully bred in captivity as
zoologists take the offensive to save many forms of wildlife from
extinction. Such conservation programs have now spread to more than
150 zoos and aquariums.
   ---
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
<TEXT>
   Consider the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> condor, the Arabian
oryx, the <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> rail, the blue poison dart frog. They are among the
endangered species that have been successfully bred in captivity as
zoologists take the offensive to save many forms of wildlife from
extinction. Such conservation programs have now spread to more than
150 zoos and aquariums.
   ---
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030889-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 28044 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 8, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1095 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BIG CATS ARE NO PROBLEM; IT'S LAWS HE CAN'T TAME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By RONALD B. TAYLOR, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
ROSAMOND, Calif. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Joe Maynard</PERSON> is a tough-talking trucker who loves exotic big cats but has a hard 
time getting along with the state officials who try to regulate how he cages 
and cares for his rare leopards and tigers. 
</P>
<P>
"They try to tell us how to run things, but they've got no expertise 
whatsoever," said <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON>, a wiry, bearded man who spends 14 days at a time as 
a cross-country truck driver. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> and his wife <PERSON>Jeanne</PERSON> run the <ORGANIZATION>Exotic Feline Breeding Compound Inc.</ORGANIZATION> a 
private, nonprofit zoo located west of this small desert town in <LOCATION>Kern County</LOCATION>, 
about 80 miles north of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. Many of the 40 wild cats caged here are 
endangered species, some are owned by zoos that have loaned them to <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> for 
breeding. 
</P>
<P>
State regulators say the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> are operating a zoo without proper 
accreditation and have been keeping wild animals without a state permit that 
has been required since <DATE>1985</DATE>, when new animal protection laws went into effect. 
The facility does not meet new state standards, primarily because its cages are 
too small, state inspectors say. 
</P>
<P>
Prior to <DATE>1985</DATE>, the compound was exempt from state regulation because it was 
classified as a private zoo, officials said. But under the new law, such 
facilities must meet standards set by the <ORGANIZATION>American Assn.</ORGANIZATION> of Zoos, <LOCATION>Parks</LOCATION> and 
Aquariums, a national organization created to upgrade animal protection and 
public safety criteria. 
</P>
<P>
Already operating on a shoestring budget funded by donations and paid 
memberships in their zoo, the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> said, they want to upgrade their cages 
to association standards but have little money with which to do so. They have 
built one big new cage, for the snow leopards, but most of their funds must go 
for care and breeding, <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"The bureaucrats in <LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> are wrong. . . . We have a bona fide zoo," 
<PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> argued, claiming that the compound should be exempt from state 
regulations because it is a designated federal research facility and has the 
necessary federal permits to handle and transport endangered species. State 
officials agree that he has the federal permits, but say the new state rules 
must be applied. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> has little nice to say about state officials, but his whole demeanor 
changes when he walks among the big cats, talking about breeding programs and 
the need to keep the rare cats from becoming extinct. He is gentle with the 
felines. 
</P>
<P>
"All my life I've loved big cats," he explained. He bought his first leopard 20 
years ago for <MONEY>$600</MONEY>. The couple lived in <LOCATION>Northridge</LOCATION> then. "I wanted to breed . . 
. these leopards because they were being killed off and I wanted to do 
something to save them." 
</P>
<P>
The Maynards moved from <LOCATION>Northridge</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Simi Valley</LOCATION>, then to <LOCATION>Kern County</LOCATION> in <DATE>1977</DATE>, 
buying 68 acres to make room for their cats. Doing the work himself, <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> 
built the cages and fenced off the compound. In <DATE>1983</DATE> the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> formed the 
nonprofit corporation and sold 2,000 memberships to finance the operation. Last 
year they raised <MONEY>$134,000</MONEY>, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Although <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> has no college degrees, he has a good reputation among zoo 
professionals active in the work of saving exotic cats. Breeding the animals in 
captivity is essential to the effort to save them from extinction, experts say. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION>' unusual collection includes seven North Chinese leopards, a pair 
of snow leopards from the <LOCATION>Himalayas</LOCATION>, on loan from the <LOCATION>San Diego Zoo</LOCATION>, several 
big Siamese tigers and three tiny <ORGANIZATION>Temminck</ORGANIZATION>'s Golden Cats. The compound -- a 
haphazard mix of old cages, new construction and mobile homes -- is open to the 
public, without charge. 
</P>
<P>
"He's got one of the best collections (of North Chinese) leopards in the 
country . . . in terms of genetics." said veterinarian <PERSON>Allen Schoemaker</PERSON> of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Riverbank Zoo</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Charlotte</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.C.</LOCATION> <PERSON>Schoemaker</PERSON> keeps breeding records on the 90 
Chinese leopards in captivity. No one knows how many of these rare cats still 
exist in the wilds of northern <LOCATION>China</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
'Very Competent' 
</P>
<P>
"His knowledge of (big cats) . . . is very superior from what you'd expect in 
the private sector," said <PERSON>Pat Morris</PERSON>, a zoo veterinarian and assistant 
professor of wildlife medicine at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Tennessee</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Knoxville</LOCATION>. 
<PERSON>Morris</PERSON>, one of <ORGANIZATION>Maynard</ORGANIZATION>'s medical consultants, added, "He is very competent." 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>State Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game officials concede that <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> cares about 
animals but insist that his facilities must now meet state standards. 
</P>
<P>
"In the past we had no serious problems with him, but the law has changed," 
said <PERSON>Celeste Cushman</PERSON>, a department spokeswoman. The state's caging and fencing 
standards had to be upgraded to protect both the animals and the public, she 
said. 
</P>
<P>
Most of the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION>' cats are housed in cages that are about 10 by 20 feet. 
Each contains a heavy plywood shelter. The flooring is dirt and few of the 
cages have double-gated entryways to prevent escapes. As <ORGANIZATION>Maynard</ORGANIZATION> builds new 
cages, he is adding these safety features. 
</P>
<P>
When the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> failed to comply with the department's demands, the state 
Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Game Commission</ORGANIZATION> stepped into the controversy. At first the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> 
refused to participate in commission hearings, but in <DATE>February</DATE> they appeared to 
present their case. The commission gave the couple 90 days to come up with a 
plan detailing how they will meet state standards within three years. 
</P>
<P>
"No one wants to take animals away from him," said <PERSON>Harold C. Cribbs</PERSON>, the 
commission's executive secretary. <PERSON>Cribbs</PERSON> said the department has been 
cooperating with <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> on developing such a plan. If a plan cannot be worked 
out, the commission could seize the animals, <PERSON>Cribbs</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
In the meantime, state game wardens are asking the <LOCATION>Kern County</LOCATION> district 
attorney to file misdemeanor charges against the Maynards for importing a North 
Chinese leopard in <DATE>January</DATE>, in violation of a department order. The animal is 
on loan from the <LOCATION>Omaha Zoo</LOCATION>. The state had instructed the couple not to obtain 
any more animals until they are in compliance with state laws. 
</P>
<P>
Maynard denied that he violated the law, saying that he had a valid federal 
permit to transport the leopard from <LOCATION>Omaha</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"They (state wardens) came here with the cops . . . (and) said we'd brought 
that cat in illegally," <PERSON>Maynard</PERSON> said. Zoo keepers who work with the <ORGANIZATION>Maynards</ORGANIZATION> on 
a regular basis say they are not put off by the compound's physical facilities 
because the couple cares for its animals and works to preserve threatened 
species. 
</P>
<P>
"It's true their facilities . . . don't meet (public) zoo standards," said <PERSON>Dr. 
Lee Simmons</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Omaha Zoo</ORGANIZATION>. "But by all reports . . . <PERSON>Joe Maynard</PERSON> 
doesn't fall short on animal care. . . . (He) really cares about his animals." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Sign beside desert road leading to Exotic Feline Breeding Compound. ; 
Photo, Joe Maynard readies shot of antibiotics for ailing leopard, as Jeanne 
Maynard helps tend animals housed in cages that state officials object to. 
Below, a California mountain lion growls warning to visitor. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
GOVERNMENT REGULATION; CALIFORNIA -- LAWS; MAYNARD, JOE; EXOTIC FELINE BREEDING 
COMPOUND INC; ENDANGERED SPECIES; ANIMAL BREEDING; WILDLIFE MANAGEMENT; ZOOS; 
ANIMALS; CATS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-11860</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EBBDOAEDFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940202
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  02 FEB 94 / Business and the Environment: Profits from preservation - As
many US zoos are privatised, they are beginning to undergo an ecological
awakening
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By VICTORIA GRIFFITH
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
Hanging in the personnel offices of the <PERSON>Franklin Park Zoo</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> is a
poster which reads: 'Extinction is forever.' At the hot dog stand, a message
has been taped to the napkin dispenser: 'Please conserve. Save a tree.' At
the African tropical rain forest exhibit, an entire wall is devoted to
explaining the ecological dangers facing rain forests in the world.
Welcome to the modern zoo, a hotbed of environmental activism.
Zoos and aquariums have come a long way since the dark days of cramped cages
and disregard for animals in the wild. While the image emanating from
<LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION> is still negative - the popular children's film Free Willy, about
a whale, caused an international furore last year when its decrepit
real-life living conditions in <LOCATION>Mexico City</LOCATION> were discovered - most US zoos
and aquariums today are highly sensitive to environmental concerns.
Zoos in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> are now seeking to redefine their ecological role in the face
of increasing fund shortages. Since many US zoos and aquariums have been
privatised, they are more dependent on their own revenue streams, and are
under pressure to set priorities. The challenge will be to continue
environmental programmes in a cost-effective way.
'Increased co-operation between international zoos will become more
important in the face of severe fund shortages,' says <PERSON>Michael Wallace</PERSON>,
curator of conservation at the <LOCATION>Los Angeles Zoo</LOCATION>. Animal conservation will
continue to be one of the mainstays of zoos' ecological efforts.
'Zoos went through an awakening on animal conservation,' says <PERSON>John Linehan</PERSON>,
general curator for the Franklin Park Zoo. 'In the past, we'd be happy if
the animals had a few babies now and then, to attract the public, but that
was the extent of our breeding efforts. Then we started noticing that
animals were getting harder to find and more expensive. We realised this
great resource we had, and that we could become a major player in animal
conservation.'
A number of species exist only in captivity, and zoos and aquaria breed
these species to prevent extinction. Reintroduction of the animals into the
wild is the ultimate goal in many cases, and some zoos have chalked up
stunning successes in this area.
The Arabian oryx, a large antelope, for example, was extinct in the wild
until zoos began to reintroduce the animal in the <DATE>1970s</DATE> and <DATE>1980s</DATE>. Today,
several hundred roam the deserts of <LOCATION>Oman</LOCATION>. Similarly, the black-footed ferret
was successfully reintroduced in <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, and the <LOCATION>Sumatra</LOCATION> tiger in
<LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>.
There are numerous pitfalls to reintroduction, however. The programmes are
extremely expensive to administer, so the number of targeted species must be
limited. Moreover, many involved in the industry complain that zoos and
aquariums are too often the last-ditch effort.
'Reintroduction from zoo populations is usually a last resort, an
after-thought,' says <PERSON>Michael Hutchins</PERSON>, director of conservation and science
at the <ORGANIZATION>American Association of Zoological Parks</ORGANIZATION> and Aquariums. 'Releasing
animals back into the wild would be more effective - and less expensive - if
we did it before numbers dwindled to a dangerous level. It's a lot easier to
boost the numbers of existing populations than to create a population from
scratch.'
Zoos hope to correct this problem by becoming increasingly involved in 'in
situ' conservation - that is, conservation in the wild.
Involving local people is the key to an effective reintroduction programme,
say conservationists. Poverty-stricken people understandably see
conservation as a luxury, and will often not hesitate to hunt endangered
species, or log forest areas necessary for the species' survival. Along the
<LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> coast of <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>, for instance, locals have been employed as guards
and monitors for the golden-eyed tamarin. 'The people who are dependent on
this animal's survival to make a living become staunch protectionists,' says
<PERSON>Benjamin Beck</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Zoo</ORGANIZATION>.
Zoos and aquariums also see education as a priority in their preservation
efforts. According to <LOCATION>AAZPA</LOCATION>, whose members had a budget of Dollars 825m
(Pounds 557m) last year, 105m people visited a zoo or aquarium in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>
<DATE>last year</DATE>. 'That gives us a tremendous potential to reach the public,' says
<PERSON>Hutchins</PERSON>. As an added advantage, educational programmes are relatively
inexpensive to administer.
In addition, aquariums are especially good at incorporating animals into
their entertainment mix. Marine animal 'acts' often include environmental
messages. A sea lion at the <ORGANIZATION>New England Aquarium</ORGANIZATION>, for instance, makes a show
of tossing rubbish into the appropriate recycling containers.
While conservation efforts and education will continue, ecological
fund-raising at many zoos is likely to be curtailed over the next few years.
With limited resources, zoos say they cannot afford to raise money for
causes other than their own. So benefits for other wildlife organisations
are likely to be phased out. Research is also controversial, with many
institutions believing funds are too short to stretch themselves far in that
area.
Indeed, the availability of funds over the next few years will help
determine the number of environmental projects zoos and aquariums involve
themselves in. Environmentalism is important, say zoo officials and
managers, but they cannot afford to lose sight of their main function, which
is to provide entertainment.
'If people don't have fun, they will stop coming,' says <PERSON>Ronald Tilson</PERSON>,
director of conservation at the <ORGANIZATION>Minnesota Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, 'and that will be the end of
our ecological involvement. While we're worrying about environmental issues
we have to make sure that our visitors are having a good time with the
animals. In the end, that may be the most important message of all.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P8422 Botanical and Zoological Gardens.
    P9611 Administration of General Economic Programs.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>RES  Facilities.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 16
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-8277</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EKUDAACZFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941121
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  21 NOV 94 / Leading Article: Rare species
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
It is possible that, within years, tigers could become extinct. The
conference to update the Cites convention on endangered species, which
concluded this weekend in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, made that clear. Would extinction matter?
On one view, it might not: the loss would pose no immediate threat to human
health or wealth.
But on several counts, it is worth putting effort into saving rare species.
In western eyes, tigers, elephants, whales and the like are romantic beasts,
whose existence is valued even by those who never see a live specimen. For
local communities, the animals can add greatly to tourism revenues. For all
countries, the animals represent a pool of genes which has potential value.
What is the best means of saving these species? The threats they face are
poachers who want to sell tusks, hides and meat for profit, farmers who
resent the damage they do, and the steady encroachment of human societies
into wild habitats.
The essence of the task is to give people an economic incentive to keep the
animals' numbers at sustainable levels. But there are two particular
problems. One is that, as some east and central African countries have
found, the benefits of the live animals, through tourism, generally go to
the government and companies, while the value of dead animals is received by
poachers and farmers. Governments have found it hard to redistribute the
benefits of tourism at a local level.
Second, demand for products such as rhino horn, driven largely by Asian
markets, has not yet been checked by rising prices. Given the disparity
between Asian wealth and African poverty, it is possible that species would
be extinct before prices rose by enough to choke demand.
One solution is simply to improve enforcement of national rules against
killing animals. <LOCATION>South Africa</LOCATION>, which devotes considerable resources to
protecting its wildlife, has found numbers of elephant and white rhino
growing rapidly, even though it allows limited domestic trade in ivory.
But that requires funds which are beyond the resources of poorer countries.
One of the best arguments for maintaining an international ban against trade
in products of endangered species is that it makes guarding the animals
easier and cheaper even for the poorest states. The Worldwide Fund for
Nature estimates that the budgets for protecting elephants have dropped by
nearly 90 per cent in <LOCATION>Zimbabwe</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Zambia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Tanzania</LOCATION> since the worldwide ban
on ivory trade in <DATE>1989</DATE>
A third device is to reduce demand for the products. Environmental groups
argue that since the start of the ivory ban, the price of ivory has fallen -
where it can be obtained - while the price of rhino horn has increased. That
is, they say, partly because the main markets for ivory were in western
countries which have enforced tough import controls on ivory. Meanwhile,
western public opinion has turned against ivory,
There is no single solution to the problem of supporting rare species. But
the Cites conference was right to uphold the ban on elephant and white rhino
products, as one of several mechanisms. The next useful step would be to
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
    XAZ  World.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P9512 Land, Mineral, Wildlife Conservation.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 19
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102389-0013 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 124474 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 23, 1989, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
886 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SCIENCE / MEDICINE; 
</P>
<P>
ZOO PLAYS CUPID TO MOTHER NATURE 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DAN FISHER, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
TRINITY, Jersey, Channel Islands 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Some might consider it arcane that tape-recorded thunderstorms act as an 
aphrodisiac for the Majorcan toad. 
</P>
<P>
But not <PERSON>Quentin Bloxam</PERSON>. Nor, one assumes, the toads. 
</P>
<P>
Bloxam is a senior curator at the <ORGANIZATION>Jersey Wildlife Preservation Trust</ORGANIZATION>, better 
known locally as, simply, the <ORGANIZATION>Jersey Zoo</ORGANIZATION>, and he's spent 25 years learning the 
amorous secrets of some of nature's more obscure creatures. 
</P>
<P>
That's because his employer is no ordinary zoo. Instead of lions, tigers and 
giraffes, the tenants here are Round Island boas, cheetahs, pink pigeons and 
partula snails. 
</P>
<P>
Founded 30 years ago by author and naturalist <PERSON>Gerald Durrell</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Jersey Zoo</ORGANIZATION> is 
a pioneer in captive breeding programs meant to preserve rare and endangered 
species of mammals, birds and reptiles. And it claims the most extensive 
collection of such species anywhere. 
</P>
<P>
The zoo's symbol is the dodo, the flightless, turkey-like bird from the Indian 
Ocean island of <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION> that became extinct in the <ORGANIZATION>17th Century</ORGANIZATION>. There's a 
Dodo Cafe here, a Dodo Dispatch newsletter and replicas of the strange-looking 
bird everywhere one gazes on the preserve. They're reminders of what could 
happen to 50 other endangered species that call <LOCATION>Jersey</LOCATION> home if it weren't for 
the trust and a growing network of more conventional North American, European 
and other zoos that now cooperate in captive breeding programs. 
</P>
<P>
Ideally, the goal of these programs is to rebuild the supply of a rare species 
to the point where it can be reintroduced into the wild. In fact, that's not 
practical for most, because the same elements that threatened to make them 
extinct in the first place still exist in their indigenous homes. 
</P>
<P>
There are exceptions -- such as the pink pigeon, which has been bred in 
captivity and reintroduced to the Maccabbe forest area of <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION>; or the 
reddish-maned golden lion tamarin, raised in <LOCATION>Jersey</LOCATION> and several American zoos 
and returned recently to <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s Poco das Antas Biological Reserve; and 
<PERSON>Quentin Bloxam</PERSON>'s Majorcan toads, which have been prospering with the help of 
his artificial rainstorms and tape-recorded thunder. 
</P>
<P>
It's not easy being a midwife to <ORGANIZATION>Mother Nature</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Bloxam</PERSON> said. Take the case of 
the Round Island boa, indigenous to an island off <LOCATION>Mauritius</LOCATION> but now believed to 
be the world's rarest snake. The boa is threatened to the verge of extinction 
by rabbits that apparently destroy its eggs and habitat. Early explorers 
introduced the rabbits to provide for future shipwrecked mariners. 
</P>
<P>
Field workers for the trust captured 11 specimens and transported them to 
<LOCATION>Jersey</LOCATION> between <DATE>1977</DATE> and <DATE>1982</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"It took us two years to perfect the management of them," said <PERSON>Bloxam</PERSON>, who is 
in charge of the reptile collection. "Then we had to try and get them to 
breed." 
</P>
<P>
Dietary experimentation finally worked, and in <DATE>1982</DATE> the first infant <LOCATION>Round 
