<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890511-0045 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-11-89 0545EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-SpacecraftNamed     05-11 0476</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Spacecraft Named,450</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Picks ``Endeavour'' For Name Of New Space Shuttle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> will go after some historical ``colour''
by naming its newest space shuttle, built to replace the destroyed
Challenger, after a British sailing ship.
   The space agency announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> had
selected the name ``Endeavour`` after it was the most popular name
in a national name-the-shuttle competition among <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s school
children.
   The Endeavor was the flagship used by 18th century English
explorer <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>.
   Thirty-one of the 111 state-level winners in the competition
chose the name Endeavour, although many of the entries used the
American spelling of Endeavor. Second most popular among the state
winners, with 12 selections, was Resolution.
   The competition was in two divisions, kindergarten through grade
6, and grades 7 through 12. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> selected a winning entry in each
category.
   The winning entry for kindergarten through grade 6 was from the
fifth graders of <ORGANIZATION>Senatobia Middle School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Senatobia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>.
   Winning in the other division was <ORGANIZATION>Tallulah Falls School</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>Tallulah Falls</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ga</LOCATION>.
   For their winning project, the <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> fifth graders created
a space camp where younger children were taught about space.
   The Tallulah Falls entry had two parts _ a magazine called
``Math Exploration with <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>,'' and a play called ``Where on
Earth?'' which compared <ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION>'s explorations with the voyages of a
space shuttle called Endeavour.
   More than 6,100 teams, formed by 71,650 students, submitted
research projects supporting the names selected. Panels from each
of the state education agencies then sorted through the entries and
picked state winners in the two divisions. From these state
winners, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> made his selection.
   Endeavour was the name <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON> chose for the 98-foot vessel
he used to explore the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION> <DATE>from 1768</DATE> to <DATE>1772</DATE>. He sailed
southwest from <LOCATION>Plymouth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, around <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, then
explored the coasts of <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION> before
returning to <LOCATION>England</LOCATION> by way of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Cape of Good Hope</LOCATION>,
completing a circumnavigation of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Cook chose the name Resolution for a ship he used in his second
and third voyages exploring the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. During those trips,
<ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION> went as far north as the <ORGANIZATION>Arctic Ocean</ORGANIZATION> and as far south as the
<ORGANIZATION>Antarctic Circle</ORGANIZATION>. He located and named the <LOCATION>Sandwich Islands</LOCATION>, later
called <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, and was killed there in <DATE>1779</DATE>.
   The second vessel in <LOCATION>Cook</LOCATION>'s company during his final voyage was
named Discovery, the same as that given to one of the current space
shuttles.
   Challenger was destroyed <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE> in an explosion that
killed seven astronauts. When <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> authorized money for a
replacement shuttle, it directed that <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s school children
would name the new craft.
   The new shuttle craft is now being built by <ORGANIZATION>Rockwell
International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Downey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. It is scheduled for completion in
<DATE>1991</DATE> and will make its first space voyage in <DATE>March 1992</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890322-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-22-89 0217EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-ShuttleNames     03-22 0474</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle Names,460</SECOND>
<HEAD>Endeavour or Endeavor? Either Way, Most Common Shuttle Name Suggestion</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Names of the ships of 18th-century British
explorer Capt. <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON> were the most popular choices among
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s school children in <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s name-the-shuttle contest.
   The space agency said that 31 of the 111 state-level winners in a
national student competition chose the name Endeavour, though many
of the entries used the American spelling of Endeavor. Second most
popular among the state winners, with 12 selections, was Resolution.
   Both Endeavour and Resolution are names <PERSON>Cook</PERSON> used for his ships
of exploration.
   A close third in popularity, with 11 choices, was <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>, the
name of the ship used by <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the 16th century
Portuguese navigator.
   State-level winners in the shuttle-naming competition were
selected by committees in each of the states, the <ORGANIZATION>District of
Columbia</ORGANIZATION> and four <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territories, and from the schools of the
<ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Indian Affairs</ORGANIZATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>State
Department</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> announced the selections <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   More than 6,100 teams, formed by 71,650 students, submitted
research projects supporting and justifying the names selected.
Panels from each of the state education agencies then sorted through
the entries and picked state winners in two divisions, kindergarten
through grade 6, and grades 7 through 12.
   The state-level winners will be reviewed by <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> and the final
winners in each division will be named in <DATE>May</DATE>, along with the chosen
name for the shuttle.
   Under the direction of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is letting <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s school
children choose the name of the new shuttle which now is being
built. The new ship will replace Challenger, the shuttle that
exploded on <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, and killed seven astronauts including
school teacher <PERSON>Christa McAuliffe</PERSON>.
   Endeavour was the name Cook chose for the 98-foot vessel he used
to explore the <LOCATION>South Pacific</LOCATION> <DATE>from 1768</DATE> to <DATE>1772</DATE>. He sailed southwest
from <LOCATION>Plymouth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>England</LOCATION>, around <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, then explored the
coasts of <LOCATION>New Zealand</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Australia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Guinea</LOCATION>, before returning to
<LOCATION>England</LOCATION> by way of <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Cape of Good Hope</LOCATION>, completing a
circumnavigation of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Resolution was the name Cook chose for a ship he used in his
second and third voyages exploring the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. During those
trips, <ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION> explored as far north as the <ORGANIZATION>Arctic Ocean</ORGANIZATION> and as far
south as the <ORGANIZATION>Antarctic Circle</ORGANIZATION>. He located and named the <LOCATION>Sandwich
Islands</LOCATION>, later called <LOCATION>Hawaii</LOCATION>, and was killed there in <DATE>1779</DATE>.
   The second vessel in <LOCATION>Cook</LOCATION>'s company during his final voyage was
named Discovery, the same name as that given to one of the current
space shuttles.
   Ferdinand <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, a Portuguese explorer, explored the <DATE>Earth
from 1519</DATE> to <DATE>1522</DATE> on a ship he called <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>. The vessel was the
first to sail around the world, though <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was killed in the
<LOCATION>Philippines</LOCATION> before the voyage was completed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880330-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-30-88 1256EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-NewShuttleName     03-30 0310</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-New Shuttle Name,0318</SECOND>
<HEAD>Students Asked To Name Replacement For Space Shuttle Challenger</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> asked the nation's
schoolchildren to select a name for the space shuttle that will
replace Challenger, destroyed in an explosion in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   The agency, in cooperation with the <ORGANIZATION>Council of Chief State
School Officers</ORGANIZATION>, invited teachers to enter their students in a
national competition to name the orbiter, now being built and
scheduled for its maiden flight in <DATE>1992</DATE>.
   ``The orbiter-naming program responds to a basic human impulse
to name things,'' the announcement said. ``<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s first orbiters
were named after sea vessels used in research and exploration. The
tradition of naming an orbiter after an exploratory or research sea
vessel will be continued.''
   The three remaining shuttles in the fleet are Discovery,
Atlantis and <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said the name Challenger had been retired, in honor of the
seven astronauts killed in the explosion.
   The announcement said the name chosen should not only identify
an American spacecraft but also should capture the spirit of
<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s mission in space.
   Announcements of opportunity will be distributed soon to
elementary and secondary teachers and principals. Entry packets
will be available in <DATE>May</DATE>.
teams and research a name,'' <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said. ``Each team will prepare a
related classroom project to support and justify the name
selected.''
   There will be two entry divisions, covering kindergarten through
the sixth grade and seventh through 12th grades.
   Students in public and private schools in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> territories, <ORGANIZATION>Department of Defense</ORGANIZATION> overseas dependents'
schools and <ORGANIZATION>Bureau of Indian Affairs</ORGANIZATION> schools are eligible.
   Each state, territory and agency will announce one winner in
each division in <DATE>March 1989</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> will announce the final winner
for each division and the name selected for the new shuttle in <DATE>May
1989</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06117094 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06117094 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Diagram; Diagram: Space Shuttle Endeavour; NASA's newest space shuttle
incorporates many modifications, upgrades and technologies added to the
orbiter fleet over the past several years. Endeavour's unique features shown
below, will later be added to existing shuttles.; ...; Dimensions; (Same For
All Shuttle Orbiters); Length: 122.3 ft.; Height: 56.67 ft.; Wingspan: 78.06
ft.; ...; Drag Chute to aid deceleration and reduce loads on the landing gear
and brakes.; Extended duration; Endeavour is designed with future
modifications in mind that will make missions of up to 28 days possible; ...;
First flights of shuttles; Columbia 1981; Challenger 1983; Discovery 1984;
Atlantis 1985; Endeavour 1982 (x); (x) planned; ...; Drag chute deployment;
(Drawing shows deployment of the Drag Chute); Associated Press; Source: NASA,
Rockwell International  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  US; SPACE; VEHICLE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  The $1.8 billion space shuttle Endeavour officially rolled off the Rockwell
production line here Thursday, replacing the ill-fated Challenger and bringing
NASA's space fleet back up to its full complement of four vehicles.;    To the
majestic strains of "Thus Spake Zarathustra" -- which became the unofficial
anthem of the space generation when it was used as theme music in the film
"2001: A Space Odyssey" -- the 5-story tall, gleaming white craft made its
debut before a crowd of 3,000 employees and well-wishers at Air Force Plant 42.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Front  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  NEW SHUTTLE UNVEILED; ENDEAVOUR MAKES FOUR  </HEADLINE>
however, until Endeavour is flown piggyback on a 747 to the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space
Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Fla.</LOCATION>, this weekend.;    Although the orbiter
will actually not be completed until after it reaches <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials
and astronauts waxed poetic about it.;    "Endeavour, the jewel of the fleet!
Isn't it beautiful?" asked astronaut <PERSON>Daniel Brandenstein</PERSON>, who will command the
shuttle on its first voyage in <DATE>March 1992</DATE>, a mission to bolt a new rocket
motor onto a failed communications satellite. "I tell you, if that doesn't put
a lump in your throat, I don't think you're human.";    The new shuttle
incorporates all the improvements that have been made on the other three
shuttles, and some that will not appear on those shuttles until later. The
most obvious is a drag parachute that will be deployed on landing to slow the
orbiter, thereby easing pressure on the brakes and landing gear.;    The
parachute and a newly beefed-up nose wheel will also increase control of the
shuttle when it is forced to land on the concrete runway at the <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION> center
rather than on the longer and wider dry lake bed at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>
near here.;    Endeavour also contains more fuel cells, which generate
electricity, to allow it to stay in orbit for as long as 28 days, twice as
long as the existing craft.;    At the ceremony, <PERSON>Brandenstein</PERSON> was presented
with part of the sternpost recovered from the first Endeavour, a research ship
commanded by British explorer Capt. <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON> between <DATE>1768</DATE> and <DATE>1771</DATE>. The
centuries-old memento will be carried into space on Endeavour's first
mission.;    Endeavour joins Discovery, which is scheduled to lift off <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
<TIME>morning</TIME> on a military mission, and Atlantis and <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>, which were also
named after sea-going research vessels. The shuttle replaces Challenger, which
exploded 73 seconds after liftoff on <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, killing all seven aboard.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Los Angeles Times  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Palmdale  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910426  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Friday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  16A  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  DIAGRAM  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  537  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Friday April 26, 1991
00117094,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890516-0153 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-16-89 1907EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Bush-Space 1stLd-Writethru a0696 05-16 0379</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Space, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0696,350</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Honors Astronauts, School Children Who Helped Name New Shuttle</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs 5th graf bgng: The crew ..., to restore dropped word ``million''</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HARRY F. ROSENTHAL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> made a small ceremony do double
duty <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> as he honored the most recent space fliers and two
groups of school children who picked the winning name for the
newest space shuttle.
   ``We are gathered here today to celebrate the continuity of our
space program and really of our country itself, of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>
herself,'' the president said as he shared a <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> stage with
five shuttle astronauts, nine fifth-graders and nine math students
from grades 8-12.
   ``In a sense today's setting reflects the continuity,'' he said.
``You are pioneers pushing back the boundaries of our technological
future.''
   To astronauts <PERSON>David Walker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Ronald Grabe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Norman Thagard</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mark
Lee</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary Cleave</PERSON>, who returned on <DATE>May 8</DATE> from a four-day shuttle
mission, the president said, ``You've reaffirmed your nation's
genius in science and technology and yet, I think we would all
agree, this really is only just the beginning.''
   The crew on the 29th shuttle flight launched a space probe that
will orbit Venus after an 800-million-mile, 15-month journey and
map the surface of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s fog-shrouded sister planet.
   The pupils, from <ORGANIZATION>Senatobia Middle School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Senatobia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>,
and <ORGANIZATION>Tallulah Falls School</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Tallulah Falls</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>,. each submitted
the name ``Endeavour,'' for the shuttle being built to replace the
ill-fated Challenger, which exploded after its launch in <DATE>January
1986</DATE>.
   ``My friends, choosing a name can be a thankless task,'' said
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>. ``Consider the new father who was once reproached by <PERSON>Sam
Goldwyn</PERSON>. `You are going to call your son <LOCATION>William</LOCATION>,' he said. ``What
kind of a name is that? Every <PERSON>Tom</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dick</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harry</PERSON> is called
<PERSON>William</PERSON>.'''
   Endeavour will have the British spelling. It was the name of the
flagship used by <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>, the <DATE>18th century</DATE> English explorer and
it was chosn from several names by 31 of the 111 state-level
winners.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> recalled that more than 6,100 teams formed by 71,650
students submitted research projects supporting the names they
selected. Panels from state education agencies picked state winners
in the two divisions and <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> made the final selection.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890412-0188 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-12-89 1911EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Bush-Truly 1stLd-Writethru a0745 04-12 0505</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush-Truly, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0745,500</SECOND>
<HEAD>Truly Named NASA Chief</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Subs grafs 12-13, The president, to add Fletcher's first name
and correct Montgomery's state</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> announced <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> he will
nominate <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Rear Adm. <PERSON>Richard Truly</PERSON>, an astronaut who flew in two
space shuttle missions, to head the <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics and Space
Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``This marks the first time in its distinguished history that
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> will be led by a hero of its own making, an astronaut who has
been to space,'' <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told members of <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> and others at the
<ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>.
   Truly, 50, became a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> astronaut in <DATE>1969</DATE> and has been the
agency's associate administrator for space flight since <DATE>1986</DATE>. He
piloted the shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> on <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s second space shuttle flight
and was commander of the eighth flight in <DATE>1983</DATE>.
   He led the recovery team after the Challenger disaster on <DATE>Jan.
28, 1986</DATE>, and a subsequent team in charge of redesigning the
shuttle's boosters and revamping safety procedures.
   ``Because <PERSON>Dick Truly</PERSON> is an active duty naval officer, I will
need the assent and cooperation of the <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to make this
appointment,'' the president said.
   B. <PERSON>Jay Cooper</PERSON>, deputy <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> press secretary, said <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION>
had agreed to waive a requirement that the head of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> be a
civilian.
   The position is subject to confirmation by the <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION>.
   The president also announced that he plans to nominate <PERSON>James R.
Thompson Jr.</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, to succeed <PERSON>Dale D. Myers</PERSON> as deputy administrator
of the agency.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> said that immediately after the ceremony, Truly was leaving
for <LOCATION>Cape Canaveral</LOCATION> to take charge of the flight readiness team for
the next space shuttle flight, in which the shuttle Atlantis will
carry the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> radar mapping device.
   ``The launch of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> is the first in a series of
long-planned space science missions scheduled for <DATE>1989</DATE>, and I
personally place a great deal of importance in our nation's civil
space program,'' the president said.
   Truly, asked after the ceremony what his top priority would be,
said, ``To have a good flight readiness and get <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> on its way
to Venus.''
   The president thanked <PERSON>James Fletcher</PERSON>, who attended the
ceremonial announcement in the <PERSON>Roosevelt Room</PERSON>, for ``an outstanding
job'' as head of <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>. Fletcher retired from the post <DATE>last month</DATE>
after holding it for more than two years.
   Also at the ceremony were Vice President <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>; Rep. <PERSON>Norm
Mineta</PERSON>, <LOCATION>D-Calif.</LOCATION>; Rep. <PERSON>Bob Walker</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Pa.</LOCATION>; Rep. <PERSON>Sonny Montgomery</PERSON>,
<LOCATION>D-Miss.</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Sen. Phil Gramm</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Texas</LOCATION>; <PERSON>Sen. Thad Cochran</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Miss.</LOCATION>; and
<PERSON>Sen. Trent Lott</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Miss.</LOCATION>, among others.
   Before his space flights, Truly was pilot for one of the two-man
crews that conducted landing tests with the space shuttle
Enterprise when it was hauled aloft on the back of a 747 jumbo jet.
   Truly holds a bachelor of aeronautical engineering degree from
in the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Navy</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1959</DATE>. He became a naval aviator in <DATE>1960</DATE> and
made more than 300 carrier landings.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890505-0023 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-05-89 0202EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ShuttleBriefs     05-05 0686</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle Briefs,0711</SECOND>
<HEAD>With PM-Space Shuttle, Bjt</HEAD>
<HEAD>Ships Retrieving Boosters</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two reusable booster rockets
that helped Atlantis soar into space were on their way back to port
<DATE>today</DATE> from the spot where they splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>
50 miles offshore.
   Two ships were to start towing them <TIME>this morning</TIME> and they were
expected to reach port by evening, said <PERSON>Rocky Raab</PERSON>, a spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>Morton Thiokol Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the rockets.
   The rockets were redesigned after the failure of a booster
rocket part caused the explosion of Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE> and
the deaths of seven astronauts.
   As planned, the rockets separated from the winged orbiter just a
little more than two minutes after <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s launch. Five minutes
after that they fell into the ocean.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>Shuttle Launch Cheers Scientists At Planetary Science Lab</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two reusable booster rockets
that helped Atlantis soar into space were on their way back to port
<DATE>today</DATE> from the spot where they splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>
50 miles offshore.
   Two ships were to start towing them <TIME>this morning</TIME> and they were
expected to reach port by evening, said <PERSON>Rocky Raab</PERSON>, a spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>Morton Thiokol Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the rockets.
   The rockets were redesigned after the failure of a booster
rocket part caused the explosion of Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE> and
the deaths of seven astronauts.
   As planned, the rockets separated from the winged orbiter just a
little more than two minutes after <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s launch. Five minutes
after that they fell into the ocean.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>American Planetary Probe Named For 16th-Century Portuguese Explorer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two reusable booster rockets
that helped Atlantis soar into space were on their way back to port
<DATE>today</DATE> from the spot where they splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>
50 miles offshore.
   Two ships were to start towing them <TIME>this morning</TIME> and they were
expected to reach port by evening, said <PERSON>Rocky Raab</PERSON>, a spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>Morton Thiokol Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the rockets.
   The rockets were redesigned after the failure of a booster
rocket part caused the explosion of Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE> and
the deaths of seven astronauts.
   As planned, the rockets separated from the winged orbiter just a
little more than two minutes after <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s launch. Five minutes
after that they fell into the ocean.
</TEXT>
<HEAD>``Star Trek'' Crew Fill Callers in on Real Space Mission</HEAD>
<DATELINE>SPACE CENTER, Houston (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The two reusable booster rockets
that helped Atlantis soar into space were on their way back to port
<DATE>today</DATE> from the spot where they splashed down in the <LOCATION>Atlantic Ocean</LOCATION>
50 miles offshore.
   Two ships were to start towing them <TIME>this morning</TIME> and they were
expected to reach port by evening, said <PERSON>Rocky Raab</PERSON>, a spokesman for
<ORGANIZATION>Morton Thiokol Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the rockets.
   The rockets were redesigned after the failure of a booster
rocket part caused the explosion of Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE> and
the deaths of seven astronauts.
   As planned, the rockets separated from the winged orbiter just a
little more than two minutes after <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s launch. Five minutes
after that they fell into the ocean.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890227-0057 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-89 0835EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ShuttleTest     02-27 0187</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle Test,0192</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Officials Pleased With 45-Second Shuttle Engine Test</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some 250 spectators cheered as a space
shuttle main engine roared to life and sent smoke across the
<ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> during a successful 45-second test
firing.
   ``Anything that goes the full duration looks and sounds like a
good test to me,'' center director <PERSON>J.R. Thompson</PERSON> said after
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s test at the northern <LOCATION>Alabama</LOCATION> base.
   <PERSON>Thompson</PERSON> said the benefits of the test firings should be seen by
the mid-1990s when <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> plans to begin sending pieces of its space
station into orbit aboard the space shuttle.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers fired the engine as part of a series of tests to
make the main engines for the space shuttle more effective.
   <PERSON>John McCarty</PERSON>, head of the propulsion laboratory at <LOCATION>Marshall</LOCATION>, said
the tests will help reduce internal engine stress, making the
shuttle's main engines last longer.
   ``We're validating changes in the engine _ the first real ones
since it was designed in <DATE>1972</DATE>,'' <PERSON>McCarty</PERSON> said.
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s 45-second test firing will be followed in three to
four weeks by a longer 100-second firing.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880227-0127 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-27-88 1808EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShuttleMilestone     02-27 0255</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shuttle Milestone,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Engine Fired For 1,000th Time</HEAD>
<DATELINE>BILOXI, Miss. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The successful 1,000th test firing this
past week of a main space shuttle engine at <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Space
Technology Laboratories</ORGANIZATION> shows the engine's reliability, officials
say.
   ``This 1,000th test is a milestone,'' NSTL Director <PERSON>Jerry Hlass</PERSON>
said.
   The test was conducted <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> for a duration of 9
minutes, 33 seconds.
   ``Engine 0211 is being checked out ... and early indications
show the test firing was a succcess,'' <ORGANIZATION>Boyce Mix</ORGANIZATION>, the engine test
manager at <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala.</LOCATION>, said
<DATE>Friday</DATE>.
since <DATE>June 1975</DATE>.
   ``Last year at <ORGANIZATION>NSTL</ORGANIZATION>, there was a record number of engine tests
in terms of test duration _ 33,738 seconds, the equivalent time the
engines would be required to perform for 22 shuttle launches,''
<PERSON>Hlass</PERSON> said. ``Our team is working very diligently to do its part in
returning the shuttle to safe flight.''
   <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>'s test was the 11th conducted this year, said
<PERSON>Mack Herring</PERSON>, NSTL public affairs officer.
   Each shuttle orbiter is powered by three main engines, which
operate for the first 8.5 minutes of flight to propel the shuttle
to the point of near-earth orbit.
   All main engines used for shuttle missions are test-fired three
times before they are transported by truck to the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   The testing is conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>Rocketdyne Division of Rockwell
prime contractor for the shuttle engines.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881029-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-88 1039EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i PM-Soviet-Shuttle 2ndLd-Writethru a0468 10-29 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Soviet-Shuttle, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0468,0734</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviet Shuttle Launch Delayed Indefinitely By Launch System Problem</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: New thruout to UPDATE with Tass report explaining cause of
cancellation. TRIMS to tighten. No pickup.
^By MARK J. PORUBCANSKY</NOTE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A fault found at the last minute in one of the
launch systems of the Soviet space shuttle forced scientists today
to indefinitely postpone the maiden voyage of the unmanned craft.
   The official <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> news agency said a computer halted the
countdown 51 seconds before launch to prevent the booster, known as
<ORGANIZATION>Energiya</ORGANIZATION>, from hitting the launch platform during liftoff.
   ``The assembly platform for emergency evacuation of cosmonauts
... didn't move away from the Energiya body to a safe distance,''
<ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said. The platform is believed to be an arm-like structure that
stretches to the booster.
   A computer that senses 140 elements of the launch system
terminated the launch process, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said. The report quoted the test
control chief at the <ORGANIZATION>Baikonur Cosmodrome</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Soviet Central Asia</LOCATION>, air
force Maj. Gen. <PERSON>V. Gudilin</PERSON>.
   Gudilin told <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> he didn't think it would be long before the
launch would be attempted again, but he said a thorough analysis of
today's problem would have to be completed before a new blastoff
date was decided.
   Fuel was drained from the rocket, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said, and it appeared a
second launch attempt would not be made today.
   The shuttle, named Buran, or snowstorm in Russian, was originally
set to lift off late <DATE>Friday</DATE> from the Baikonur launch site on the
Central Asian steppe in <LOCATION>Kazakhstan</LOCATION>. But <ORGANIZATION>Tass and Radio Moscow</ORGANIZATION>
announced earlier today a four-hour delay, one half-hour after the
scheduled launch time expired.
   Then, seconds before liftoff a second time, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> in a terse
statement announced there was an ``indefinite'' delay.
   There was no live report from Baikonur by either radio or
television. Foreign reporters were not allowed to travel to Baikonur.
   Buran was to make two orbits and return to a concrete landing
strip eight miles from the launch site. Reports indicated the
initial flight would be devoted entirely to checking out the craft
and would not be used to deploy satellites or conduct any other
missions.
   Ships stationed in the <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> oceans, a satellite
network and a string of ground stations were poised to communicate
with the craft and monitor its flight, Soviet television said in a
brief report.
   Buran is attached to the Energiya rocket, the world's most
powerful launcher, and four liquid-fuel boosters. It looks like the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle.
   But Soviet officials say it can carry a payload of 66,000 pounds,
compared to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle's 55,000 pounds, is safer and more
flexible.
   The fully automated guidance system permits scientists to send
the craft into space for the first time without cosmonauts,
decreasing the risk to human life, Soviet officials said.
   In the past, the officials have been critical of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle
program that was stalled until this <DATE>fall</DATE> after seven astronauts were
killed in the explosion of the Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>.
   In a report late <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the television news program Vremya
revealed Soviet military involvement in the Soviet shuttle program.
   ``As always in our country, military specialists participate in
crucial, dangerous tests,'' a correspondent said in a report from
<LOCATION>Baikonur</LOCATION>.
   It identified the military official overseeing shuttle operations
as <PERSON>Alexander A. Maksimov</PERSON>. It identified him as the <ORGANIZATION>Defense
Ministry</ORGANIZATION>'s top specialist on ``multiple-use space transport systems
and the prospect of their development.''
   Soviet officials repeatedly have criticized military use of the
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle, and have called for space to be used only for
peaceful purposes.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Defense Department</ORGANIZATION>, in its <DATE>1988</DATE> publication Soviet
Military Power, says the Soviets might use a shuttle to deploy
anti-satellite and ballistic missile defense weapons.
   Reports <DATE>Friday</DATE> said the Buran can carry as many as 10 people _
four cosmonauts and six passengers _ and placed its cost of Energiya
and Buran at about that of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle, some <MONEY>$10 billion</MONEY>.
   Energiya, which can lift a payload of more than 100 tons, has
been used only once before. On a test flight in <DATE>May 1987</DATE>, its
payload failed to reach orbit, but Soviet officials said the problem
was with the guidance system of the satellite rather than with the
gigantic booster.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA032389-0096 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 34524 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 23, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 2; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
451 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
NEWSMAKERS: INDIAN HEEDS A CALL OF THE BEAR 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DEBORAH CHRISTENSEN 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
A Cree Indian has completed a 2,700-mile run from <LOCATION>Edmonton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>New York 
City</LOCATION> to lay claim to a sacred relic stored in the <ORGANIZATION>American Museum of Natural 
History</ORGANIZATION>. Carrying a curved staff draped with eagle feathers for strength and 
wearing a wolf pelt for protection, <PERSON>Jim Thunder</PERSON> said he was driven by a 
recurring dream in which Chief Big Bear of the Crees instructed him to retrieve 
the artifact -- a parcel of calico holding bear claws, a clump of sweet grass 
and a plug of tobacco. Big Bear, leader of the <PERSON>Plains Cree</PERSON>, made the sacred 
bundle about 150 years ago when he was about 13 years old and wore it into 
battle for strength and guidance. In <DATE>1934</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Big Bear</ORGANIZATION>'s son gave it to a museum 
researcher in western <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> for safekeeping. Since that time, the museum has 
kept it as part of a research collection but has never put it on display. 
Thunder and a small delegation of Indians were to meet with museum officials 
who will decide whether to give up the parcel. Thunder told about 100 Indians 
and supporters: "We are confident that we will get the bundle back because 
since the <DATE>1930s</DATE> there have been prophesies that it would return." 
</P>
<P>
 -- After 40 years, 11,000 performances and 500 stitches, legendary tiger tamer 
<PERSON>Gunther Gebel-Williams</PERSON> has decided it's time to call it quits before his skills 
start to fade. The 54-year-old performer, who is beginning his two-year 
farewell tour with <ORGANIZATION>Ringling Bros.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Barnum &amp; Bailey Circus</ORGANIZATION>, said: "I'm 
still very strong, but when you get older your eyesight begins to go and I have 
to wear glasses offstage. But I can't wear them in the ring." Williams became 
famous for his ability to control animals without the usual whip, chair or 
pistol. In his current show, he puts <LOCATION>Bengal</LOCATION> and Siberian tigers through their 
paces, stands on the back of a charging elephant and puts Lippizaner horses 
through a ballet routine. "I am very close to my cats," he said, "but I can't 
ever let down my guard because while I can succeed in training them, I can 
never tame them." 
</P>
<P>
 -- The name Endeavor, one of 18th-Century British explorer Capt. <PERSON>James Cook</PERSON>'s 
ships, tops the list of suggested names for the next space shuttle in a 
competition among the nation's schoolchildren. The second most popular choice 
is Resolution, the name of another of <ORGANIZATION>Cook</ORGANIZATION>'s vessels, followed by <PERSON>Victoria</PERSON>, the 
name of the ship used by <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, the 16th-Century Portuguese 
navigator. More than 6,100 teams, formed by 71,650 students, submitted research 
projects supporting and justifying the names selected. <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> is letting 
schoolchildren choose the name of the shuttle to replace Challenger, which 
exploded in <DATE>January, 1986</DATE>. The final choice will be announced in <DATE>May</DATE>. DEBORAH 
<PERSON>CHRISTENSEN</PERSON> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890429-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-89 0128EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Shuttle-RealMagellan     04-29 0323</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Shuttle-Real Magellan,0330</SECOND>
<HEAD>American Planetary Probe Named For 16th-Century Portuguese Explorer</HEAD>
<HEAD>With PM-Shuttle Launch</HEAD>
<HEAD>Also in Saturday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s first
interplanetary probe in 11 years, is named for a Portuguese
explorer who 467 years ago led the expedition that was the first to
sail around the world.
   After it is deployed in orbit by the space shuttle, the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
probe will travel to Venus in 15 months. The 800-million-mile
voyage will last less than half as long as it took a 16th-century
expedition led by <ORGANIZATION>Ferdinand Magellan</ORGANIZATION> to sail around the world.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, who chose to sail under the Spanish flag, was
commander of a five-ship flotilla that left <LOCATION>Seville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept.
20, 1519</DATE> to search for a route to the so-called <ORGANIZATION>Spice Islands</ORGANIZATION> in
the south <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   The fleet reached <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION> in <DATE>December</DATE> and then sailed
around the southern tip of that continent through what came to be
called the Straits of <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>.
   After following the west coast of <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
directed his fleet across the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. The ships made
landfall at <LOCATION>Guam</LOCATION> on <DATE>March 6, 1521</DATE>, and then went on to what became
the <LOCATION>Philippine Islands</LOCATION>.
   The Spanish sailors got into a fight with natives on <LOCATION>Mactan
Island</LOCATION> on <DATE>April 27, 1521</DATE>, and <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> was killed. The anniversary
of his death fell on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s fleet continued its voyage, with <PERSON>Juan Sebastian
Elcano</PERSON> in command, but one ship after another was lost until only
the <LOCATION>Victoria</LOCATION> was left. The vessel returned to <LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 8,
1522</DATE>. Only 17 men, of an original crew of 270, survived the
three-year voyage.
   Though <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> died before the trip ended, he is generally
credited with the first circumnavigation of the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   Stargazing sailors on the voyage are credited with discovery of
two star galaxies, called the <ORGANIZATION>Magellanic Clouds</ORGANIZATION>, which are visible
only from the southern hemisphere.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890508-0003 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-08-89 2359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle 5thLd-Writethru a0728 05-08 0945</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 5th Ld - Writethru, a0728,0966</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Shuttle Lands Safely In California</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: INSERTS 3 grafs after 9th graf, `Only about ...,' to UPDATE
with astronauts arriving in Houston; picks up 10th graf, `Just 12 ...'</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos HTN1, EAB4,8,9; LaserColor EAB5</HEAD>
<HEAD>By JOHN ANTCZAK</HEAD>
<HEAD>Associated Press Writer</HEAD>
<DATELINE>EDWARDS AIR FORCE BASE, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space shuttle Atlantis
landed on a gusty desert runway <DATE>Monday</DATE> after putting <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> planetary
exploration back on track with the launch of the unmanned <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
probe to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   Atlantis touched down at <TIME>12:43 p.m. PDT</TIME> on a concrete runway at
<ORGANIZATION>Rogers Dry Lake</ORGANIZATION> after a fiery, hour-long plunge from orbit 184
miles above <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   ``Congratulations and nice landing,'' said capsule communicator
<PERSON>Frank Culbertson</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>. ``You've extended the shuttle's reach
far beyond <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> orbit now. Commodore Magellan (the <DATE>16th century</DATE>
explorer for which the Venus probe was named) would approve.''
   ``It's good to be back. It's a great trip,'' shuttle commander
<PERSON>David M. Walker</PERSON> told reporters and space agency workers before the
crew flew back to <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION> four hours after landing.
   ``We had a great time on orbit. ... We hope you liked what we
did,'' said mission specialist <PERSON>Mary L. Cleave</PERSON>.
   The crew left the orbiter about an hour after landing and
inspected its underside, accompanied by senior <ORGANIZATION>National Aeronautics
and Space Administration</ORGANIZATION> officials. They found little damage to its
thermal tiles.
   ``The vehicle looks about as clean as any one that I've ever
seen,'' <PERSON>Richard Truly</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s acting associate administrator for
space flight, told a post-landing news conference.
   ``The <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft ... is floating toward the planet
Venus to open up a new era of planetary exploration,'' Truly said.
   Only about 27,500 of a predicted 100,000 spectators braved
baking heat to see Atlantis dive through the thin, high clouds and
rock the desert with the its signature twin sonic booms.
   About 200 people cheered the astronauts' return home <DATE>Monday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME> at <LOCATION>Houston</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Ellington Field</ORGANIZATION>. Even a few of the astronauts'
dogs were on hand to greet their <TIME>9:45 p.m.</TIME> CDT arrival.
   ``I can't tell you how grateful all of us are to those of you
who have supported us personally and professionally through all
these many months of training and through, in fact, our whole
careers,'' <PERSON>Walker</PERSON> told the crowd of mostly <ORGANIZATION>Johnson Space Center</ORGANIZATION>
workers.
   The astronauts left the airport with their families. They were
scheduled to report back to work <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to begin reviewing their
mission.
   Just 12 minutes before touchdown, Atlantis was ordered to land
on the concrete Runway 22 rather than the hard-packed clay of
Runway 17 as dust devils whipped up by the variable winds twirled
across the lakebed.
   Truly said the switch was apparently ordered because the
crosswind angle was better on the concrete runway for a test of
handling under such conditions _ a precursor to someday resuming
landings at <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   The crosswinds at landing were believed to have ranged from 12.6
mph to 20.7 mph, which would have yielded ``significant''
information on such landings, <PERSON>Arnold D. Aldrich</PERSON>, director of the
shuttle program.
   Re-entry began when two big engines at the rear of the
spacecraft ignited and burned for 2 minutes, 38 seconds over the
<ORGANIZATION>Indian Ocean on Atlantis</ORGANIZATION>' 64th orbit.
   The crew _ commander <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>, pilot <PERSON>Ronald J. Grabe</PERSON>, and mission
specialists <PERSON>Norman E. Thagard</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mark Lee</PERSON> and mission specialist
Cleave _ rocketed into space from <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
and launched the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> spacecraft.
   The <MONEY>$550 million</MONEY> probe will reach Venus after a 15-month, 800
million-mile journey and begin mapping the surface of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s
cloud-shrouded sister.
   ``The trajectory is about as accurate as you can get,'' said
<PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, associate administrator for space science and
applications. ``I think we demonstrated with this flight that the
shuttle is in fact very capable of putting a planetary mission up.''
   <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> marks the first new <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> planetary exploration in 11
years. The start of its mission was cheered by scientists working
on a variety of programs that were delayed by the long hiatus in
the shuttle program after the <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>, Challenger disaster.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> last explored <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> with the <DATE>1978</DATE> launch of the Pioneer
probe, which examined the planet's murky atmosphere and did some
radar mapping. <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>'s radar should map of <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the
planet and with much greater resolution than Pioneer.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> sent two Venera probes to Venus in <DATE>1983</DATE> but
only mapped about a quarter of its surface.
   Atlantis' mission, the fourth since shuttle flights resumed
<DATE>Sept. 29, 1988</DATE>, had two significant technical problems. The orbiter
was 31 seconds from launch on <DATE>April 28</DATE> when a short-circuit was
detected in a fuel pump, delaying takeoff until the pump and a
leaky fuel line were replaced. On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, one of the four redundant
computers that control the shuttle's systems failed.
   The crew was able to restart the computer but mission
controllers decided not to trust it for re-entry. The crew
abandoned other tasks and spent 4{ hours replacing the faulty
computer with a spare, the first time that had been done.
   The shuttle could land with just one computer operating,
according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>.
   Until the computer problem developed, the crew had worked on an
experiment involving crystallizing a metal sample in a furnace and
had photographed lightning and pollution on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>.
   The workload for mission STS-30 was light because <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> and
its booster weighed 45,000 pounds, cutting the number of
experiments that could be carried.
   The mission also served to boost flight experience in the
shuttle astronaut corps. It was the third shuttle flight for
<PERSON>Thagard</PERSON>, the second for <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>, <PERSON>Grabe</PERSON> and Cleave, and the first for
Lee.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881029-0113 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-88 1647EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Soviet-Space 1stLd-Writethru   10-29 0818</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Space, 1st Ld-Writethru,a0552,0837</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Launch Postponed; Soviet Space Program's Fifth Snag This
Year</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: LEADS with 11 grafs to add comparison to U.S. shuttle launch,
gives space official's full name, adds details of Soviet television
coverage. Pick up 9th pvs, `The shuttle...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ANDREW KATELL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seconds before the scheduled blastoff, the maiden
voyage of the Soviet space shuttle was delayed <DATE>Saturday</DATE> because of
trouble with ground equipment. It was the fifth setback this year
for the Soviet space program.
   Soviet officials did not immediately announce when a second
attempt would be made to launch the Buran on its unmanned test
flight.
   Tass, the official Soviet news agency, said scientists at the
<ORGANIZATION>Baikonur Cosmodrome</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Soviet Central Asia</LOCATION> traced <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s snag to
an equipment platform that failed to pull away from the booster
rocket.
   With 51 seconds to go, a computer stopped the countdown because
the booster, known as <ORGANIZATION>Energiya</ORGANIZATION>, would have hit the platform at
takeoff.
   The sudden halt was similar to the dramatic last-minute
postponement of the liftoff of the world's first shuttle. The <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION>
craft <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> was delayed for two days in <DATE>April 1981</DATE> because of
computer software problems. Some subsequent <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle flights
also were delayed.
   ``The accessory platform for emergency evacuation of cosmonauts
... didn't move away from the Energiya body to a safe distance,''
<ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said 11 hours after the scheduled <TIME>6:23 a.m.</TIME> liftoff.
   <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said a computer that senses 140 elements of the launch
system halted the countdown and that thousands of tons of liquid
fuel were being drained from <LOCATION>Energiya</LOCATION>. The report quoted <ORGANIZATION>Baikonur</ORGANIZATION>'s
test control chief, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Maj. Gen. <PERSON>Vladimir E. Gudilin</PERSON>.
   The government newspaper <PERSON>Izvestia</PERSON> said the platform contained
equipment to aim the spacecraft toward the proper trajectory. The
newspaper quoted Gudilin as saying the platform withdrew somewhat,
but not completely.
   Gudilin was quoted as saying he didn't think it would be long
before the launch would be attempted again, but he said a thorough
analysis of the problem would have to be completed.
   Soviet television, in its evening news program Vremya, said the
words ``automatic termination of preparations'' flashed on a
computer screen at Baikonur as dozens of scientists watched.
   The broadcast showed the gleaming white shuttle orbiter and
rocket booster on the launch pad after the liftoff attempt, with
what it said was liquid oxygen venting from <LOCATION>Energiya</LOCATION>.
   The shuttle, which looks like the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle, was
scheduled to orbit the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> twice and land on a runway eight miles
from the blastoff site. The flight was to be controlled entirely by
computers and was meant to test launch and landing equipment and
procedures, Soviet news reports said. There was no indication the
shuttle was to have deployed any satellites.
   Buran can carry as many as 10 people _ four cosmonauts and six
passengers. It is attached to <LOCATION>Energiya</LOCATION>, the world's most powerful
launcher, and four liquid-fuel boosters.
   <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s postponement was the latest in a series of problems
that have dogged Soviet space flights since the <DATE>spring</DATE>:
   _Ground controllers lost contact in <DATE>April</DATE> with a Soviet
nuclear-powered satellite, Cosmos-1900, and Western Europeans
expressed concern it would release radioactivity when it re-entered
the atmosphere. The satellite burned up safely upon re-entry <DATE>Oct. 2</DATE>.
   _Soviet cosmonaut <PERSON>Anatoly Levchenko</PERSON>, a 47-year-old test pilot for
the shuttle program, died <DATE>Aug. 6</DATE> of a brain tumor. Levchenko had
been among the candidates to fly the shuttle on its first manned
mission. His death leaves <PERSON>Igor Volk</PERSON> the only cosmonaut known to be
in line for a shuttle flight.
   _A ground controller sent an incorrect signal to the unmanned
Soviet space probe Phobos 1 on <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>, freezing the craft and
ending its radio contact with <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. The probe was on its way to
Mars on a <MONEY>multimillion-dollar</MONEY> mission to unlock the mysteries of the
planet.
   _On <DATE>Sept. 6</DATE>, an Afghan and Soviet cosmonaut were stranded in
orbit aboard a Soyuz TM-5 capsule with diminishing air and food
after two unsuccessful attempts to land. The cosmonauts eventually
overcame human error and equipment problems to land safely.
   In <DATE>Saturday</DATE>'s attempted launch, Tass initially announced a
four-hour delay but then said blastoff had been delayed
indefinitely. Soviet television did not cover launch preparations
live, and foreign reporters were not allowed to visit Baikonur.
   Soviet officials say the Buran orbiter can carry a payload of
66,000 pounds, compared to the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle's 55,000 pounds, and
that it is more flexible and safer.
   In the past, the officials have been critical of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle
program, suspended until this <DATE>fall</DATE> after seven astronauts were
killed in the explosion of the Challenger in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>.
   In a report late <DATE>Friday</DATE>, the evening television news program
revealed Soviet military involvement in the Soviet shuttle program.
It identified the military official overseeing shuttle operations as
<PERSON>Alexander A. Maksimov</PERSON> but did not say how the <ORGANIZATION>Defense Ministry</ORGANIZATION> would
use the craft.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880701-0212 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-01-88 1914EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-SpaceShuttle 3rdLd-Writethru a0782 07-01 0495</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0782,0503</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA To Move Space Shuttle To Launch Pad on July 4</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 5 grafs to CORRECT that only one of the astronauts
will attend ceremony; picks up 7th graf: `After Discovery...'</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space workers will hold a special
<DATE>Fourth of July</DATE> ceremony when they move Discovery to the launch pad
to be readied for the first space shuttle mission since the
Challenger tragedy.
   One of the five astronauts slated to fly the early <DATE>September</DATE>
mission and <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials will watch from a flag-bedecked
grandstand as the spaceship is rolled out of an assembly building
into the glare of spotlights at <TIME>12:01 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Discovery will be perched upright on a giant tracked transporter
for the six-to-seven-hour trip over a 4.2-mile course to Launch Pad
39B.
   The move is timed to avoid thunderstorms and lightning, which
often occur during the daytime this time of year.
   In a brief ceremony as the move begins, <PERSON>Forrest S. McCartney</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, will present the astronaut
with a book containing signatures of the 15,240 workers here who
have labored to return the shuttle fleet to space.
   Commander <PERSON>Rick Hauck</PERSON> and his crew, <PERSON>Dick Covey</PERSON>, <PERSON>George Nelson</PERSON>,
<PERSON>Mike Lounge</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dave Hilmers</PERSON>, will take the book into space with
them on a four-day mission. Hilmers planned to be here for the
rollout ceremony.
   After Discovery is on the pad, employees and their families will
be able to drive by between <TIME>8 a.m. and 11 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Monday</DATE> to get a
close look before a service structure encloses the spaceship.
   <PERSON>Jim Harrington</PERSON>, shuttle operations director here, said delays in
preparing Discovery placed the rollout date on the Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>.
   ``We didn't plan it that way,'' he said. ``We had hoped to do it
earlier.''
   Asked if a rollout on the nation's birthday might have an
emotional impact, <PERSON>Harrington</PERSON> replied, ``No doubt it will have an
effect. The biggest effect and the biggest morale booster we can
give ourselves is to move the shuttle out to the pad, because
that's where it belongs. The name of the game here is to get the
vehicle ready to fly, and that's what we're going to do.''
   He said checks of systems will begin as soon as Discovery is on
the pad, and workers will begin preparing the spaceship for
critical firing of its three main engines on <DATE>July 24</DATE>. With the
craft bolted firmly to its launch mounts, the engines will be
ignited for 19.4 seconds to test modifications and to give the
launch team countdown practice.
   The shuttle fleet has been grounded since Challenger and its
crew of seven were lost in an explosion 73 seconds after liftoff
<DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>.
   Earlier this week, the space agency announced it had officially
delayed <ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION>'s launch from late <DATE>August</DATE> until early <DATE>September</DATE>
because it was taking longer than expected to prepare the vehicle.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900120-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-20-90 0439EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-France-Shuttle     01-20 0211</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-France-Shuttle,0216</SECOND>
<HEAD>European Astronaut Named to Fly on Space Shuttle</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Space Shuttle</HEAD>
<DATELINE>PARIS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION> astronaut will be among the
international crew aboard the space shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION> on its
<DATE>December</DATE> mission, <ORGANIZATION>ESA</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Dr. <PERSON>Ulf Merold</PERSON> will serve as one of two payload specialists on
the 9-day flight that will also carry <PERSON>Dr. Roberta L. Bondar</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Canadian Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>, mission specialists <PERSON>Mary L. Cleave</PERSON>, <PERSON>Norman
E. Thagard</PERSON> and <PERSON>William F. Feaddy</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Ronald J. Grab</PERSON>,
the commander of the flight, and pilot <PERSON>Stephan S. Oswald</PERSON>.
   The microgravity mission will be the first of a series using a
European-developed spacelab module. A team of more than 200
scientists in 12 countries will conduct experiments in materials
and life sciences, including gravitational plant physiology and
space physiology.
   The materials experiments in the microgravity environment will
focus on vapor crystal growth systems and protein crystal growth
among others.
   This will be <ORGANIZATION>Merbold</ORGANIZATION>'s second space mission. In <DATE>December 1987</DATE>,
he was chosen from among 2,000 European applicants to fly aboard
the first spacelab on the 10-day mission launched <DATE>Nov. 28, 1983</DATE>.
   Born <DATE>1941</DATE> in <LOCATION>Greiz</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Merbold</PERSON> worked as a
solid-state physicist at the <ORGANIZATION>Max Planck Institute</ORGANIZATION> for metals
research before joining <ORGANIZATION>ESA</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880520-0234 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-88 2031EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-SovietSpaceShuttle     05-20 0568</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet Space Shuttle,570</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Plan August Launch Of New Shuttle, Magazine Says</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>'s new space shuttle, a
reusable craft that lands on a runway, will make its maiden voyage
at about the same time that the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle is scheduled to
return to orbit for the first time since the Challenger disaster,
an industry magazine reports.
   Aviation Week and <ORGANIZATION>Space Technology</ORGANIZATION> released a report <DATE>Friday</DATE>
saying the Soviet shuttle will be launched in <DATE>August</DATE> and ``roughly
coincide'' with the return to flight of the American space shuttle.
   Launch of the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> space shuttle is now expected in late <DATE>August</DATE>,
probably on <DATE>Aug. 29</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> sources.
   The Soviet space shuttle, which closely resembles the American
original in exterior design, is to carry two cosmonauts into orbit
in what is expected to be a short test mission.
   Earlier reports said that the Soviet shuttle's initial test
flight would be conducted unmanned, but officials disclosed last
week that the plans call for two pilots.
   Aviation Week quoted Soviet Lt. Gen. <PERSON>Vladium Shatalov</PERSON>, chief of
the Soviet space program, as saying, ``When the Americans tested
their shuttle, two men took off. I believe that this experience is
reasonable and can be used in our country.''
   The Soviet space shuttle is launched on a liquid-fueled rocket
called the <LOCATION>Energia</LOCATION>. Unlike the American craft, the launch rockets
are not a part of the orbiting craft. Instead, the Soviet shuttle
includes jet engines which can be used when the craft returns to
the atmosphere. This will give the Soviet shuttle a greater range
to manuever than the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> shuttle, which returns from space as a
glider with no engines.
   Challenger exploded shortly after launch from the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space
Center</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>. Seven crew members were killed. Since
then, the shuttle fleet has been grounded while <ORGANIZATION>National
tested flawed equipment, including the solid-fueled rocket engines
that were blamed for the accident.
   In <DATE>August</DATE>, space shuttle Discovery is scheduled to be launched
from the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> with a crew of five, all veteran
astronauts, and land four days later at <ORGANIZATION>Edwards Air Force Base</ORGANIZATION>,
<LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   Aviation <PERSON>Week</PERSON> said the Soviet shuttle flight is part of an
``unprecedented'' series of space missions over the next three
months.
   ``Never before has the <ORGANIZATION>USSR</ORGANIZATION> attempted so many major new space
missions withing the same period,'' the magazine said.
   Among the Soviet flights are:
   _Two robot craft to be launched to Mars and to the Martian moon
Phobos. The craft will lift off on <DATE>July 7</DATE> and <DATE>July 12</DATE> for the most
complex planetary missions yet attempted by the Soviets. The craft
will include instruments provided by eight countries and the
<ORGANIZATION>European Space Agency</ORGANIZATION>. The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> is not participating.
   _On <DATE>June 7</DATE>, a Soyuz spacecraft with a Soviet and a Bulgarian
cosmonaut will be launched to the space station Mir for an
eight-day mission. In <DATE>August</DATE>, a second <ORGANIZATION>Soyuz</ORGANIZATION> will be launched with
a Soviet and an Afghan on board.
   _<DATE>Last Sunday</DATE>, the Soviets launched a military intelligence craft
the size of a school bus in a 530-mile circular orbit.
   Two cosmonauts aboard the space station Mir completed their
150th day in orbit last <DATE>Monday</DATE>. The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> has now exceeded
128,000 man-hours in space, more than triple the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> total of
42,463 hours.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890627-0092 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-27-89 1230EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-SpaceShuttle     06-27 0270</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Space Shuttle,0277</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fire in Test Engine Could Delay Space Shuttle Launch</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Engineers examined a space shuttle
main engine <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> to determine if damage it suffered in a
test-firing could delay this <DATE>summer</DATE>'s launch of the shuttle <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``Engineers have to inspect the engine and look at the data
before they can make a decision about <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s launch,'' said <PERSON>Dave
Drachlis</PERSON>, a space agency spokesman at the <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ala</LOCATION>.
   The failure happened <DATE>Friday</DATE> on a test stand at the <ORGANIZATION>Stennis Space
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Bay St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, during firing of a development
engine that has been ignited 23 times over several years to test new
parts for future shuttle flights.
   <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s three main engines already are in place as technicians
here prepare it for a launch in late <DATE>July</DATE> or early <DATE>August</DATE> on a
classified <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> mission.
   <PERSON>Jerry Smelser</PERSON>, head of the engine program at the <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> center,
said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> needs to determine if the problem involves parts similar
to those in <ORGANIZATION>Columbia</ORGANIZATION>'s engines.
   <PERSON>Drachlis</PERSON> said the test engine operated normally until about 21
minutes into a planned firing of 22 minutes 17 seconds, when there
was a sudden shutdown and a fire. During a shuttle launch, the main
engines normally fire for about 8 minutes 30 seconds.
   There was significant damage to several internal parts, <PERSON>Drachlis</PERSON>
said.
   ``The engine did not blow up; it's still fundamentally intact,''
he said.
   The engine was flown to its manufacturer, the <ORGANIZATION>Rocketdyne Division
of Rockwell International</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Canoga Park</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Drachlis</PERSON> said
engineers would take the engine apart for detailed inspection.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880725-0012 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-25-88 0035EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpaceShuttle     07-25 0327</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Shuttle,0335</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Begins Test Aimed at Firing Space Shuttle Engines</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A practice space shuttle countdown
was under way here today in a test leading to a firing of
<ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION>'s three main engines on the launch pad <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The launch team started the count at <TIME>11:33 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. On
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, it planned to load more than a half million gallons of
liquid hydrogen and liquid oxygen propellant into the shuttle's
external fuel tank.
   It will be the first time a shuttle has been fueled since the
Challenger explosion, which killed seven astronauts on <DATE>Jan. 28,
1986</DATE>.
   When the countdown reaches 10 seconds before a mock lift-off on
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, a problem will be simulated to force a launch
postponement. Then launch crews will rehearse what's called a
72-hour turnaround.
   They will empty the fuel tank, start another countdown, refill
the tank and aim for a 20-second test firing of Discovery's main
engines at <TIME>7:30 a.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The firing, with the shuttle bolted firmly on the pad, will
check modifications made to the engines and is considered critical
to Discovery being certified for the first post-Challenger shuttle
flight.
   The launch, with a five-man crew, is scheduled for early
<DATE>September</DATE>, but the date is in doubt as engineers continue to puzzle
over how to fix a small gas leak in a steering engine system that
is separate from the main engines.
   They hope to make the repair on the pad and avoid rolling
Discovery back to a hangar, a move that could delay the flight as
much as two months.
   Experts are considering several ways to reach the inaccessible
leak, including cutting a hole through the shuttle's cargo bay wall
and running a snake-like tube through the gas line in an effort to
not make a decision on whether to move Discovery off the pad until
after the main engine test firing.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881017-0123 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-17-88 1441EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-RocketTest     10-17 0364</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Rocket Test,0375</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rocket Test Firing Scheduled Wednesday</HEAD>
<DATELINE>HUNTSVILLE, Ala. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A space shuttle main rocket engine will
be test-fired <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Space Flight Center</ORGANIZATION>, the
first extended firing since the roar of <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> rockets echoed
across <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION> in the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   ``It's going to be something <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION> hasn't heard for quite
awhile,'' <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> spokesman <PERSON>Dom Amatore</PERSON> said.
   The 15-second firing is part of a series of tests on the shuttle
main engines and coincides with the city's ``Space Awareness Week.''
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> engineers want to determine how long the rocket motors,
fueled by hydrogen and oxygen from the shuttle's huge external
tank, can run if needed. The engines now operate for about eight
minutes during a shuttle launch.
   Shuttle engine No. 0208, installed in the test stand in <DATE>August</DATE>,
was ``warmed up'' in a 1.5-second start test last month.
   After this week's test, a third test firing of 45 seconds will
be scheduled in <DATE>November</DATE>. Amatore said the primary goal of the
first brief tests is to verify that <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> can handle the firings
and whether a metal ``flame bucket'' on the test stand can handle
the rocket exhaust.
   The last test firing of a big rocket motor at <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> was a
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> test on <DATE>Sept. 11, 1969</DATE>, about two months after men first set
foot on the moon.
   Marshall is <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s main propulsion center. In addition to
developing the <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> rockets, it manages space shuttle propulsion
systems, including the main engines and solid fuel booster rockets,
which are test-fired in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>.
   ``Space Awareness Week'' includes a visit by the crew of the
shuttle Discovery.
   The five astronaunts who flew <DATE>last month</DATE> in the first
post-Challenger shuttle mission are to be in <LOCATION>Huntsville</LOCATION> on <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
and <DATE>Friday</DATE> to thank <PERSON>Marshall</PERSON> engineers.
   They also will lead a parade and appear at a public reception
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   On <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, singer <PERSON>John Denver</PERSON> and former <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> senator
and Apollo astronaut <PERSON>Harrison Schmitt</PERSON> will be in town to discuss
proposed new space missions.
   <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION>, who hopes to ride into orbit with a Soviet crew in <DATE>1990</DATE>,
will talk about Earth observation missions while <PERSON>Schmitt</PERSON> will
discuss proposals for manned missions to the moon and Mars.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890125-0204 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-25-89 2052EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-MIT-Space     01-25 0532</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-MIT-Space,0548</SECOND>
<HEAD>MIT Students, Faculty Try Out Simulated Space Docking Mechanisms</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BX11</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANA KENNEDY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAMBRIDGE, Mass. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   To bystanders, it looked as if the
contestants were trying to fish from the third-floor balcony of the
<ORGANIZATION>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   In fact, the students and teachers were competing in an
experiment that could alter how spacecraft dock in outer space.
   The competition's long-range goal was to devise a cheaper, more
effective method of linking the space shuttle with the space
station. Present space shuttle docking plans are expensive and
time-consuming, said <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> Professor <PERSON>Andreas H. von Flotow</PERSON>.
   The simulated design contest was sponsored by von <ORGANIZATION>Flotow and
Energy Sciences Laboratory Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>. The <MONEY>$500</MONEY> first prize
and a possible job with the company was offered to the competitor
who completed the docking maneuver in the shortest time.
   The experiment involved dropping a tether line from a third-floor
balcony in the <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> lobby, or the ``space station,'' and trying to
connect it with the ``space shuttle'' on the floor below, fashioned
from a garbage can and contestant-made nose cones.
   The trick was linking the tether to the space shuttle as rapidly
as possible without risking hard impact. But the link had to be
strong enough to lift the simulated space station off the floor.
   ``This idea has been drifting around for years,'' said von
<ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION>. ``But the aerospace business is the most conservative around.
They don't always want to try new things, even if there are
considerable benefits.''
   Von <PERSON>Flotow</PERSON> said several aerospace companies had expressed
interest in seeing the winning design.
   Currently, the plans for a shuttle-space station docking call for
what is termed metal-to-metal mating, which requires hours of
precision flying to dock a relatively small payload.
   Since the cost of docking is estimated to be about <MONEY>$100,000</MONEY> per
second, substantial savings can result from finding a faster
procedure, von <PERSON>Flotow</PERSON> said.
   Von <PERSON>Flotow</PERSON> said docking would require less fuel if a soft device
on a miles-long tether were dropped from the orbiting space station
to dock remotely with the space shuttle's payload at a sub-orbital
altitude.
   He said several of the designs attempted <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> could work in
space, where tether lines would be required to lift 6,600 pounds of
weight.
   Four teams of contestants competed in the two-hour experiment.
The winner, <ORGANIZATION>MIT</ORGANIZATION> graduate student <PERSON>Siegfried Zerweckh</PERSON>, used a fishnet
attached to the tether line to grasp a nose cone made of foam
rubber. His best time was 9.9 seconds.
   MIT Professor <PERSON>Norman Ham</PERSON>, the only faculty member to compete,
lowered two balloons and hooked them to cylindrical wires attached
to the nose cone in a 19-second docking maneuver.
   To ensure that the simulated docking mechanisms would not damage
a space shuttle, von <PERSON>Flotow</PERSON> tested each of the entries by dropping
them on an egg and making sure they did not break it.
   ``It's something you can create and develop and at the same time
it may prove really useful some day,'' said <PERSON>Gary Carr</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>U.S.
Department of Transportation</ORGANIZATION> mechanical engineer who was on the only
non-MIT participant in the contest.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890826-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-26-89 2029EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Voyager-SpaceFuture     08-26 0464</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Voyager-Space Future,0478</SECOND>
<HEAD>NASA Official Forsees `Second Golden Age' Of Space Exploration</HEAD>
<HEAD>With AM-Voyager-Neptune, Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By LEE SIEGEL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PASADENA, Calif. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Voyager 2's <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> encounter marks the
last planetary flyby by a <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacecraft, but missions to <LOCATION>Venus</LOCATION>,
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> and Mars mean <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> will keep exploring space, a <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>
official said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   ``We are embarking on the second golden age of space science,''
said <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, the agency's associate administrator for space
science and applications. ``What's coming up is an era of
unprecedented excitement and activity.''
35 space science flights in the next five years _ the highest launch
rate ever _ and <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> spacecraft will be exploring planets
continuously from next year until <DATE>2006</DATE>, <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said during a visit to
<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
   Fisk was at the lab to watch Voyager 2's brush with <LOCATION>Neptune</LOCATION> <DATE>last
Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> _ the probe's final encounter after it explored
<ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1979</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1981</DATE> and Uranus in <DATE>1986</DATE>.
   ``In many ways, this is the end of an era, the last time we will
see a planet for a first time, the end of the reconnaissance phase
of planetary explorations,'' he said. There are no plans to explore
<LOCATION>Pluto</LOCATION>, the only planet still not visited by a spacecraft
   But <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> listed several missions that will orbit planets rather
than fly past them:
   _<ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>, launched from a space shuttle last <DATE>May</DATE>, arrives at
Venus next <DATE>August</DATE> and will study that planet for several years.
   _<ORGANIZATION>Galileo</ORGANIZATION> will be launched from the shuttle Atlantis on <DATE>Oct. 12</DATE>,
arriving in orbit around <ORGANIZATION>Jupiter</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1996</DATE> and studying the planet
until the end of the century.
   _The <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space Telescope</ORGANIZATION> is due for launch from a shuttle next
<DATE>March</DATE>, and is so powerful that from its orbit around <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> it will
be able to ``observe the universe back to the beginning of time,''
<PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said.
   _Mars Observer will be launched in <DATE>1992</DATE>, reaching the red planet
in <DATE>1993</DATE> and studying it until <DATE>1996</DATE>.
   _<ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has asked <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> to approve the Comet Rendevous-Asteroid
Flyby and <ORGANIZATION>Cassini</ORGANIZATION> missions, <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. <ORGANIZATION>CRAF</ORGANIZATION> would fly past an
asteroid, then orbit a comet from <DATE>2000 through 2002</DATE>, <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said. The
similar spacecraft on the <ORGANIZATION>Cassini</ORGANIZATION> mission would drop a probe onto
<ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION>'s moon <ORGANIZATION>Titan</ORGANIZATION>, then orbit <ORGANIZATION>Saturn</ORGANIZATION> from <DATE>2002</DATE> through <DATE>2006</DATE>.
   Fisk disputed assertions that unmanned space exploration will
suffer financially because of the shuttle program, saying that <PERCENT>70
percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of non-military shuttle flights will be
dedicated to space science.
   <PERSON>Fisk</PERSON> said space science studies suffered in recent years not from
a lack of funds, but because of delays in developing the shuttle and
launches until last <DATE>fall</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880704-0054 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-04-88 0746EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-SpaceShuttle 1stLd-Writethru a0472 07-04 0667</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Shuttle, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0472,0678</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Shuttle Discovery Moved To Launch Pad</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 7 grafs, shuttle reaches launch pad; picks up 5th
graf, ``A recording...''</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CSB1,2, LaserColor CSB3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HOWARD BENEDICT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Aerospace Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Space shuttle Discovery made its
long-delayed trip to the launch pad today, cheered on by
flag-waving workers who have waited 2{ years for a rebirth of the
American space program.
   ``<LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, the dream is still alive,'' astronaut <PERSON>Dave Hilmers</PERSON>
told a Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE> crowd of several hundred engineers,
technicians and others who watched as the 85-ton spaceship edged
out of an assembly building into the glare of floodlights at <TIME>12:50
a.m.</TIME>
   ``What more fitting present can we make to our country than this
on the day of its birthday,'' said <PERSON>Hilmers</PERSON>, one of five crew
members scheduled to fly Discovery on the first post-Challenger
mission, set for early <DATE>September</DATE>.
   Discovery, attached to its external fuel tank and two solid-fuel
booster rockets, was perched on the broad back of a giant tracked
transporter that lumbered along at less than 1 mph in covering the
4.2-mile route to the pad in 6{ hours.
   The shuttle arrived at Pad 39B at <TIME>7:30 a.m.</TIME>, and technicians
began connecting its various systems to the launch tower, including
air-conditioning and electricity, and extending platforms from the
pad so workers can have access to the shuttle.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> scheduled the move in the early morning to avoid
thunderstorms and lightning that are common during the daytime in
the <DATE>summer</DATE> months.
   For three hours, starting at <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME>, space center workers and
their families were permitted to drive personal cars past the
launch pad for a good look at <ORGANIZATION>Discovery</ORGANIZATION> before a service structure
enclosed it.
   A recording of ``The Star Spangled Banner'' was played as the
shuttle began the move to Launch Pad 39B, the same pad from which
Challenger was launched on the flight that killed seven astronauts
on <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>.
   ``It's been a long 2{ years since Challenger, and I'm very
pleased with the progress we've made during that time,'' <PERSON>Forrest S.
McCartney</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION>, said at the
rollout ceremony. ``It's been a team effort. ... This is a proud
day.''
   McCartney presented <PERSON>Hilmers</PERSON> with a book containing the names of
more than 15,000 <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> workers who have labored to
return the shuttle fleet to space.
   <PERSON>Hilmers</PERSON> said the astronauts would carry the book, bearing the
inscription ``The <ORGANIZATION>KSC</ORGANIZATION> team is with you,'' into orbit aboard
Discovery, ``knowing that our journey will be safer because of
you.''
   ``It kind of brings tears to your eyes after so long a time of
struggling and looking at ourselves inwardly and outwardly, and
here it is; it's finally a reality,'' <PERSON>Hilmers</PERSON> said.
   ``This is what I call a happy Fourth of <DATE>July</DATE>,'' said astronaut
<PERSON>Bob Crippen</PERSON>, a veteran of four shuttle flights who is now deputy
director of shuttle operations.
   Workers were to spend several hours securing Discovery on the
pad and then begin preparing it for a critical test-firing of its
three main liquid fuel engines. The test, with the spaceship bolted
firmly on its launch mounts, is set for <DATE>July 24</DATE>.
   The following day, a final pre-flight test-firing of the
redesigned solid-fuel booster rocket is planned at the <ORGANIZATION>Morton
Thiokol</ORGANIZATION> plant in <LOCATION>Utah</LOCATION>. Both tests must be passed before Discovery
is certified for flight.
   The failure of a seal in a booster rocket joint doomed
Challenger 73 seconds after liftoff. Since then, the booster has
been significantly redesigned and tested, and hundreds of other
modifications have been made to the shuttle main engines and other
systems.
   <PERSON>Hilmers</PERSON> and four other veteran shuttle crew members will be at
the controls when Discovery blasts off on a four-day mission. The
others are commander <PERSON>Rick Hauck</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dick Covey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mike Lounge</PERSON> and <PERSON>George
Nelson</PERSON>.
   They will deploy a communications satellite, conduct scientific
and technical experiments and check out changes made to the orbiter
systems.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880318-0100 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-18-88 1011EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpaceShuttleCrews     03-18 0261</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Shuttle Crews,0265</SECOND>
<HEAD>Astronaut Crews Named For Three Space Shuttle Missions</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> has selected 15 astronauts, 11
of them veteran space shuttle fliers, for three <DATE>1989</DATE> shuttle
missions which will deploy a large space telescope, a
communications satellite and a probe to <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>.
   With <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s announcement, six crews have been selected for
shuttle missions, which are to resume <DATE>Aug. 4</DATE>. The shuttle fleet has
been grounded since the Challenger explosion that killed seven
astronauts in <DATE>January 1986</DATE>.
   Shuttle mission STS-29, scheduled for launch <DATE>Jan. 19, 1989</DATE>, will
be commanded by <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>Michael L. Coats</PERSON>. The others are <ORGANIZATION>Air
Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>John E. Blaha</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Marine Cols</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Robert C. Springer</PERSON> and <PERSON>James
F. Buchli</PERSON> and <PERSON>James P. Bagian</PERSON>. They will release the third in a
series of Tracking and <ORGANIZATION>Data Relay Satellites</ORGANIZATION> for communications.
   STS stands for space transportation system.
   <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt. <PERSON>David M. Walker</PERSON> will command STS-30, set for launch
<DATE>April 27, 1989</DATE>. With him will be <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Ronald J. Grabe</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Maj. <PERSON>Mark C. Lee</PERSON>, <PERSON>Norman E. Thagard</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mary L. Cleave</PERSON>.
Their mission will start planetary probe <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> on its way to map
the entire surface of Venus with radar.
   The STS-31 mission will feature deployment of the <ORGANIZATION>Hubble Space
Telescope</ORGANIZATION> and is set for <DATE>June 1, 1989</DATE>. <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Loren J.
Shriver</PERSON> will command the flight. The others are Marine Col. <PERSON>Charles
F. Bolden</PERSON>, <PERSON>Kathryn D. Sullivan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Steven A. Hawley</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Capt.
<PERSON>Bruce McCandless</PERSON>.
   Blaha, <PERSON>Springer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bagian</PERSON> and Lee will be making their first
shuttle flights.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880715-0139 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-88 1316EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShuttleCrewPatch     07-15 0191</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Shuttle Crew Patch,0194</SECOND>
<HEAD>Space Shuttle Crew Insignia Honors Challenger Astronauts</HEAD>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A drawing of a space shuttle lifting
off against a backdrop of a rainbow as a symbol of astronauts'
return to space is featured on the patch the crewmen will wear on
the second post-Challenger shuttle flight.
   A picture of the patch, sprinkled with seven stars to
commemorate the memory of the Challenger crew members, was released
<DATE>Friday</DATE> by the space agency.
   Around the border are the last names of the five astronauts who
will fly the mission: Commander <PERSON>Robert L. Gibson</PERSON>, pilot Guy <PERSON>S.
Gardner</PERSON> and mission specialists <PERSON>Jerry L. Ross</PERSON>, <PERSON>Richard M. Mullane</PERSON>
and <PERSON>William M. Shepherd</PERSON>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said each crewman contributed to the design.
   Their flight aboard shuttle Atlantis is scheduled for <DATE>November</DATE>
and will carry a classified <ORGANIZATION>Defense Department</ORGANIZATION> payload.
   The crew patch for the first post-Challenger flight _ that of
Discovery in early <DATE>September</DATE> _ shows a stylized shuttle lifting off
and includes in the background a sun and the seven-starred <ORGANIZATION>Big
Dipper</ORGANIZATION> as a tribute to the seven astronauts who died in the
Challenger explosion <DATE>Jan. 28, 1986</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881129-0166 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-11-29-88 2031EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Soviet-Space     11-29 0301</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviet-Space,0309</SECOND>
<HEAD>Soviets Say Shuttle Performed `Brilliantly,' Longer Mission Planned</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MOSCOW (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet space scientists declared a brilliant
success the unmanned maiden voyage of the space shuttle Buran, and
are planning a much longer second mission, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``The previous program was brilliantly performed; when the craft
came to a halt on the runway its time deviation from the program
reached only one second, while the deviation of the Buran's axis
from that of the runway was only 1.5 meters,'' the official news
agency reported.
   Only five of the 39,000 heat-protecting tiles broke away during
the 3-hour, 20-minute flight <DATE>Nov. 15</DATE> and the spacecraft, whose name
means Snowstorm in Russian, successfully maneuvered in bad weather,
<ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said.
   It quoted Gen. <PERSON>German Titov</PERSON> as saying: ``We deliberately refused
to postpone the launch and wait for ideal conditions. The value of
the flight is that its program included the maximum sum of real and
rather difficult tasks.''
   Tass said the landing took place in relatively high winds and
thick clouds.
   Officials have said the shuttle's second flight also will be
unmanned. No precise information on its length was available.
   Cosmonauts on another Soviet space mission, a joint project
including French cosmonaut <PERSON>Jean-Loup Chretien</PERSON>, began working aboard
the orbiting space station Mir on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, a day after docking their
Soyuz TM-7 capsule.
   Chretien will return with <PERSON>Vladimir Titov</PERSON> and <PERSON>Musa Manarov</PERSON>, who
have set an endurance record and will have been in space a full year
when they make the descent <DATE>Dec. 21</DATE>. Commander <PERSON>Alexander Volkov</PERSON> and
<PERSON>Sergei Krikalev</PERSON>, who went into space with the Frenchman, will remain
on the Mir until <DATE>April</DATE>.
   Tass said one project, designed by French scientists, is to make
a detailed study of the cardio-vascular system in space flight,
using ultra sound to evaluate blood flow.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890429-0060 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-29-89 1201EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-SpaceShuttle 4thLd-Writethru a0490 04-29 0839</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Space Shuttle, 4th Ld - Writethru, a0490,0858</SECOND>
<HEAD>Shuttle Launch Set Back By Pump, Fuel Line Leak; NASA Uncertain On
Time</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: SUBS 20th graf, `The crew...', to CORRECT spelling of astronaut's
name to Grabe sted Grave.</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CSB1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL RECER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE CANAVERAL, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> said <DATE>today</DATE> it will not try to
launch space shuttle Atlantis and the robot probe targeted for
Venus until a fuel pump problem and leaking fuel line are corrected
on the space shuttle and ``we don't know when we can go.''
   Sources close to the program reported earlier that the
postponement could be at least 10 days, but later said that was
based on a preliminary assessment. They said the delay will be
several days and possibly could stretch to a week or more if
technicians have to replace both the pump and the fuel line.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> spokesperson <PERSON>Lisa Malone</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> officials are evaluating
the problems today and have assigned committees to study each
element. She reports from those committees will be made on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   ``We don't know when we can go,'' said <PERSON>Malone</PERSON>. ``It depends on
where the troubleshooting takes us.''
   A launch countdown was stopped <DATE>Friday</DATE> with just 31 seconds left
after controllers detected an electrical power surge in a main
engine fuel pump. Later, engineers found leak in a hydrogen fuel
line.
   Atlantis is to carry into space a robot probe called <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION>
which is to fly to the planet <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> in a resumption of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
exploration of the solar system after an 11-year gap.
   Earlier, <PERSON>Robert Sieck</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Kennedy Space Center</ORGANIZATION> launch director,
said technicians would remove panels of the engine compartment to
get at the pump.
   The leaky hydrogen line, which spewed a cloud of vapor toward
the end of the countdown, also must be repaired, <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said.
Engineers believe the vapor escaped through a pinhole in a fitting.
   The technicians worked through the <TIME>night</TIME> to drain a half million
gallons of oxygen and hydrogen rocket fuel from <LOCATION>Atlantis</LOCATION>. They then
planned to install scaffolding at the base of the spacecraft and
remove panels covering the engine compartment.
   <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>George Diller</PERSON> said engineers should be able to
examine the faulty pump by tonight. Only then can it be determined
how the problem will be corrected. The experts looked at the leaky
hydrogen line <TIME>this morning</TIME>, but were still undecided on what
repairs were needed for that problem, he said.
   If either the pump or the hydrogen line have to be replaced, the
launch could be postponed until ``well into next week,'' <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said.
   Atlantis couldn't be launched before <DATE>Monday</DATE> at the earliest
because of the two problems, he said.
   ``Both of them would have to fall into a quick fix and it would
be optimistic to expect that,'' <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said.
   Among tens of thousands who had gathered for the planned rare
afternoon liftoff were prominent planetary scientists who have been
waiting to resume solar system exploration since <DATE>1978</DATE>, when
Pioneer-Venus was launched on the last <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> planetary expedition.
   ``We have waited a number of years for this flight, and a few
extra days won't matter,'' said <PERSON>Lennard Fisk</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION>'s chief
scientist. ``The window is a month long. Having the shuttle ready
on the first day is ample time to solve the problem and get us on
our way to Venus.''
   ``That's just the way it is,'' said <PERSON>James Head</PERSON>, a geologist from
<ORGANIZATION>Brown University</ORGANIZATION>.
   The space agency must send the <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> probe on its way by <DATE>May
28</DATE> to take advantage of the proper alignment between <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> and
<PERSON>Venus</PERSON>. If <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> can't meet that deadline, officials would have to
wait two years before the two planets again are in the desired
position.
   After the scrub was announced, the astronauts climbed out of the
spaceship in their bright orange launch suits and were taken back
to the crew quarters for a late lunch.
   The crew includes commander <PERSON>David Walker</PERSON>, along with pilot
<PERSON>Ronald J. Grabe</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mary L. Cleave</PERSON>, <PERSON>Norman E. Thagard</PERSON> and <PERSON>Mark C. Lee</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said the preparations seemed ``picture perfect'' until 20
minutes before launch.
   A computer malfunction was quickly fixed and the count resumed
after a six-minute delay. Then, with fewer than 50 seconds left on
the clock, an engineer in the launch control room told <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON>,
``Possible problem with an engine 1 recirculation pump ...
recommend hold at T-minus 31.''
   The countdown was stopped.
   ``It just wasn't our day,'' <PERSON>Sieck</PERSON> said. He fretted out loud that
the weather, perfect on <DATE>Friday</DATE>, would likely be less ideal next
week.
   After it is released from Atlantis' cargo bay, <ORGANIZATION>Magellan</ORGANIZATION> will
rocket itself onto a 15-month, 806 million-mile path toward <PERSON>Venus</PERSON>,
the <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>'s nearest planetary neighbor.
   The explorer craft will spend eight months orbiting <PERSON>Venus</PERSON> and
mapping about <PERCENT>90 percent</PERCENT> of the planet surface using a
sophisticated radar system.
   Venus is a cloud-shrouded world that has always intrigued
scientists because it is about the size of <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>, but lacks any of
the conditions that make life on this planet possible.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890715-0137 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-15-89 2102EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-ShuttleTest     07-15 0193</FIRST>
