<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880606-0253 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-06-88 0143EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Outdoors:Backyard     06-06 0652</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Outdoors: Backyard,0677</SECOND>
<HEAD>BC-SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>OUTDOORS: Backyard</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BILL SCHULZ</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   You don't have to go into the woods to enjoy
viewing wildlife. You can attract a wide variety of wildlife to your
yard with a little planning and planting.
   All animals need food, water and shelter. Trees are a good place
to start. Pick varieties that produce fruits, berries or nuts and
plant different varieties that produce those foods at different
times of the year.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> suggests the following varieties by
region:
   South _ live oak, black gum, American holly and flowering dogwood.
   Southwest _ pinyon pine, live oak, box elder and mesquite.
   West Coast _ dogwood, hawthorne, serviceberry, black oak, <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON>
fir and Ponderosa pine.
   Your local nursery, the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> or your county
agricultural extension agent all can help select varieties for your
yard.
   Birds are either fruit and seed eaters or meat-eaters.
   Orioles, vireos, warblers, chickadees, nuthatches and woodpeckers
like mature trees with large insect populations. The robin needs a
lawn with plenty of worms.
   To encourage robins and other ground feeders, water your lawn
regularly. Many species of birds love to bathe in the spray and a
well-watered lawn helps provide a good supply of both worms and
insects. It also provides mud for robins and eaves swallows to build
nests.
   If possible, let one corner of the yard grow wild with weeds and
bushes. You also can pile brush or old Christmas trees in a back
corner to create cover for both birds and small mammals, including
rabbits and ground squirrels.
   If you have alders, birches, pines, oaks, dogwoods or other
seed-producing trees, you can bet you will have squirrels.
   Seed-eating birds and flower-seeking birds often need help to
survive in the city.
   Princessfeather, asters, rockpurslanes, blessed thistle,
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> poppies, cosmos, marigold, sunflowers, tarweed,
forget-me-not, portucala, silene, zinnas and varieties of sorghum
grow large quantiites of seeds and won't become yard pests.
   Fruit-bearing trees and shrubs are popular with birds and
squirrels.
   More than 100 species of birds will throng to raspberry,
blackberry and elderberry bushes. Other popular species are juniper,
red cedar, bayberry, mulberry, pokeberry, strawberry, sumack,
grapevines and blueberry. They will bring woodpeckers, waxwings,
cardinals, bluebirds, orioles, warblers, robins, flickers and
finches.
   Hummingbirds are the best-known flower seekers.
   They are very fond of cultivated flowers, particularly those with
red, orange or purple petals. Varieties include daylilies, lilies,
canas, morning-glories, petunias, honeysuckles, jewelweed and
trumpetcreeper.
   In <DATE>summer</DATE>, the best way to bring birds and other animals is to
provide water. In dry weather, it can mean life or death.
   A bird bath a few inches deep with the bottom sloping gradually
upward toward the edge is one of the best bets. Make sure the bottom
and the edge are rough to provide good footing. Change the water
regularly.
   Make sure it is elevated because a bird bath on the ground can be
a happy hunting ground for the local feline population.
   In <DATE>winter</DATE>, food is a magnet.
   A feeder can be as simple as a Christmas tree, decorated with
popcorn or cranberries. It's best to offer several birdfeeders with
different delicacies in each.
   Place the feeders near trees or shrubs, particularly evergreens.
Many species will stay hungry rather than fly from cover to a bare
post in the middle of the yard.
   Different species prefer different foods. Cardinals and blue jays
like sunflower seeds. Goldfinches like thistles. Sparrows and
juncoes like cracked corn. All the insect eaters, such as
woodpeckers, nuthatches and chickadees, love suet, the waste fat
from beef.
   Avoid bagged, mixed bird seed. Many brands, particularly cheaper
ones, contain varieties songbirds don't eat. Often it is cheaper to
buy one large bag each of several varieties of seed and put each
seed in a different feeder.
   Keep an area under an eave or overhanging tree branch clear of
show and scatter seed for groundfeeders.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA101590-0072 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 292743 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 15, 1990, Monday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 5; Column 1; National Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
832 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
AMERICAN ALBUM: BATTLE BETWEEN BIRDS, LOGGERS GROWS IN FOREST; 
</P>
<P>
BOTH THE TIMBER INDUSTRY AND PROTECTORS OF A RARE WOODPECKER ARE COMPETING FOR 
THE SAME TREES. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIKE CLARY, SPECIAL TO THE TIMES 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
OLUSTEE, Fla. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Deep in the <LOCATION>northern Florida</LOCATION> woods, miles from anywhere, <PERSON>Jane Monaghan</PERSON> stands 
stock-still among the palmetto scrub, listening. "<LOCATION>Nuthatches</LOCATION>, red-bellies, 
chickadees, pine warblers, cardinals," she says, ticking off the calls she's 
not interested in. 
</P>
<P>
Then, on the breeze whispering through the pine trees, comes the familiar 
squeaky chatter she has been waiting for, and <PERSON>Monaghan</PERSON> turns just in time to 
see a pair of dark-winged birds rocket into a silver-dollar-size hole in a 
nearby tree. 
</P>
<P>
"There they are," says <PERSON>Monaghan</PERSON>, 28, a biologist with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION>. 
"The RCW, the spotted owl of the Southeast. You know, it's always kind of a 
thrill to see them." 
</P>
<P>
RCW is naturalist shorthand for red-cockaded woodpecker, the rarest of American 
woodpeckers, and the bird that has recently become the bane of the timber 
industry in the Southeast, particularly in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>. Both the woodpeckers and 
the loggers covet the same trees -- mature, long-leaf pine trees at least 60 
years old and 70 feet tall. The timber companies want the trees for high-grade 
board lumber and telephone poles. The birds want them for homes. 
</P>
<P>
Lately, in the 180,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>Osceola National Forest</ORGANIZATION>, anyway, the birds have 
been winning. Long protected as an endangered species, the woodpeckers have 
recently benefited from new federal guidelines that increase the buffer zone 
around their colonies and severely reduce the acreage open to logging. 
</P>
<P>
The issue -- for both the birds and the loggers -- is survival. "I think it's 
safe to say that if we are going to survive, we'd have to rebuild the mill to 
do something different than we do now," says <PERSON>Ron Lane</PERSON>, a timber buyer for 
<ORGANIZATION>Daniels Lumber Co.</ORGANIZATION>, which employs 60 people in <LOCATION>Lake City</LOCATION> at the western edge of 
the <LOCATION>Osceola</LOCATION>. "People say they want more protection for these animals, but when 
they find out the real cost it may be too late." 
</P>
<P>
Monaghan worries that it already may be too late for the woodpeckers. Over the 
past two years she has identified 44 red-cockaded woodpecker clans, each 
containing one breeding pair and up to seven other family members, in the 
<LOCATION>Osceola</LOCATION>. But her federal mandate is to increase the number of clans to 250, and 
the only way to do that is preserve the old-growth trees in which the birds 
bore their nesting cavities. 
</P>
<P>
Throughout the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, the struggle to save endangered plants and 
animals while balancing the economic costs becomes more acute each day. In the 
<LOCATION>Pacific Northwest</LOCATION>, it's the spotted owl versus the loggers. In <LOCATION>Arizona</LOCATION>, a red 
squirrel is threatened by a complex of observatories. In <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, a dam project 
could harm whooping cranes. Just west of <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION>, urban sprawl up to the edge of 
the <LOCATION>Everglades</LOCATION> makes life perilous for a host of rare creatures. 
</P>
<P>
The conflict here over a small, seldom-seen woodpecker is no less critical or 
emotional. In <DATE>1987</DATE>, two Ocala-area home builders were charged with cutting down 
200 nesting trees and then shotgunning two of the birds in order to avoid legal 
obligations to set aside land for the birds near a planned housing development. 
After guilty pleas, the two were fined <MONEY>$300,000</MONEY>. Some <MONEY>$50,000</MONEY> of that money is 
being used to fund <PERSON>Monaghan</PERSON>'s recovery effort. 
</P>
<P>
The woodpecker is not well-known, says <PERSON>Monaghan</PERSON>, "and it's not a cute fuzzy 
like the manatee. But if we lose him, it means we're losing the habitat too. It 
means there would be a niche not filled, and who knows what other species may 
be dependent on it? I don't think the timber interests understand." 
</P>
<P>
What the timber interests understand best are their numbers. Last year, sales 
from <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s three national forests put <MONEY>$8.5 million</MONEY> in federal coffers, a 
fourth of which is shared by local counties for schools and roads. 
</P>
<P>
In the <LOCATION>Osceola</LOCATION>, the smallest of the state's three national forests, private 
loggers in <DATE>1989</DATE> cut 17 million board feet of lumber. This year, because of 
restrictions designed to protect the woodpeckers, that figure will dip to 11 
million. By <DATE>1992</DATE>, the estimated total will be no more than 5 million board 
feet. 
</P>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service Timber Purchasers Council</ORGANIZATION>, an Atlanta-based group of 120 
private logging companies, has filed suit, charging that the government 
illegally drew the more restrictive guidelines that enlarged the buffer zone 
from 200 feet to three-quarters of a mile, a loss to loggers of 900 acres 
around each colony. 
</P>
<P>
Monaghan does not argue that all logging in national forests should be stopped. 
In fact, for the woodpeckers, removal of some trees is even desirable because 
the birds prefer to nest in tall pines with a clear understory. 
</P>
<P>
Last year, Hurricane Hugo ripped through the <ORGANIZATION>Francis Marion National Forest</ORGANIZATION> 
north of <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, and virtually wiped out what had been the largest 
population of the woodpeckers. That loss, says <PERSON>Monaghan</PERSON>, makes efforts here 
even more critical. "We should be able to stabilize this population in the next 
five years and keep it from declining," she says. "We can't assure its 
survival. But at least we know what to do to help." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Florida; Photo, Ralph Costa, a U.S. Forest Service wildlife biologist, 
holds a captured red-cockaded woodpecker during a banding operation. Associated 
Press 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
LUMBER INDUSTRY -- FLORIDA; ENDANGERED SPECIES; BIRDS; WOODPECKERS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012989-0070 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 11462 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 29, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part 7; Page 1; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1277 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
JACKSON HOLE: ACTION IN WYOMING'S GRAND TETONS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SHARON APFELBAULM, Apfelbaum is a free-lance writer living in Palm Springs. 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
JACKSON, Wyo. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Huddled on the snowy bank of the Snake River at <LOCATION>Moose</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dornan</PERSON>'s may be the 
world's most scenic bar. Before its picture window, skiers gather to sip Irish 
coffee at sunset and pay homage to the stunning mountain panorama. Peaks and 
jagged pinnacles tower over this valley like a Gothic cathedral. The Grand 
Tetons, a choir of majestic granite spires, trumpet their beauty through the 
high country basin called <ORGANIZATION>Jackson Hole</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
While <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> Hole offers an unspoiled paradise for winter recreation, the 
region resounds with a sanctity and power that enrich the spirit. Dramatic 
vistas and wildlife abound. The valley is part of the largest chunk of 
wilderness left in the world's temperate zones. 
</P>
<P>
Named for <PERSON>Davey Jackson</PERSON>, a beaver trapper who claimed this "hole," or valley, 
his territory in the <DATE>1800s</DATE>, <LOCATION>Jackson Hole</LOCATION> is hemmed in by mountains. The flat, 
mile-high valley reaches south from <LOCATION>Yellowstone National Park</LOCATION> for 50 miles, 
holding some of the <LOCATION>West</LOCATION>'s most spectacular country, terminating here in the 
town of <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Snow is powdery from Thanksgiving to <LOCATION>Easter</LOCATION>, and terrain to ski and explore 
remains virtually unlimited. Wide trails follow the course of the <LOCATION>Snake River</LOCATION>, 
a fertile habitat for wildlife. Flocks of ducks and teams of trumpeter swans 
honk their greetings as the fish-filled river winds its way along the valley 
</P>
<P>
Continued from Page 1 
</P>
<P>
floor from headwaters deep in <LOCATION>Yellowstone</LOCATION>. In this primitive environment you're 
more likely to meet a moose than another skier. 
</P>
<P>
Ski beneath the Tetons and experience nature's symphony. Wind whistles in steep 
glacier-carved canyons where streams chime with melting snow. A chain of lakes 
shimmer; chickadees carol in meadows at the foot of misty gabled peaks. The 
refulgent landscape is a balm and benediction. 
</P>
<P>
Thanks to some farsighted folks, the region remains a living paradigm of 
primordial <LOCATION>Western America</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>John D. Rockefeller</PERSON> donated much of the land now included in <LOCATION>Grand Teton 
National Park</LOCATION>. Local writer <PERSON>Margaret Murie</PERSON>, 87, energetically carries on the 
conservation cause. 
</P>
<P>
Only <PERCENT>3%</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Teton County</LOCATION> is privately owned, and the rest is protected within 
the national park, <ORGANIZATION>Bridger-Teton National Forest</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>National Elk Refuge</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Preservation efforts do not keep out modern recreation. The pleasures of high 
mountain helicopter and downhill skiing, snowmobiling, ice skating, snowshoe 
hiking and dude ranching are plentiful. You can take a moonlit sleigh ride, go 
by dog sled to dinner or drive a snowmobile to Granite Hot Springs for a soak 
in nature's own Jacuzzi. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Wide-Open Spaces 
</P>
<P>
Downhill skiers have a profusion of wide-open spaces. Three major ski areas 
include more than 5,000 acres of slopes and trails and an aerial tram. Snow 
<ORGANIZATION>King Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, imposing backdrop for the colorful town of <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, is <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>'s 
oldest ski area. 
</P>
<P>
At family-oriented <ORGANIZATION>Grand Targhee Resort</ORGANIZATION> on the west side of the Tetons, snow is 
so light and deep that few slopes even need grooming. Targhee averages more 
than 500 inches of annual snowfall and claims the best powder skiing in the 
northern Rockies. 
</P>
<P>
Jackson Hole Ski Resort at <ORGANIZATION>Teton Village</ORGANIZATION> boasts the longest vertical drop in 
the nation. Towering 10,000 feet over the village, the resort's <ORGANIZATION>Rendezvous 
Mountain</ORGANIZATION> offers a kaleidoscope of trails -- through powder bowls, gladed 
meadows and fragrant forests. 
</P>
<P>
All three resorts stage annual torchlight parades down mountain slopes as part 
of their <DATE>Christmas</DATE> and New Year's Eve festivities. 
</P>
<P>
In contrast to the area's stark, pastoral elegance, <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> has a lively Wild 
West character. Covered wooden walkways, Western storefronts and a cluster of 
cowboy saloons create a rustic atmosphere. Huge arches of elk antlers mark the 
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> town square and serve as the <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> logo. 
</P>
<P>
Restaurants such as the Silver Sage (on the south side of the square) and the 
<PERSON>Sojourner Stockman</PERSON>, at the <ORGANIZATION>Sojourner Inn</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Teton Village</LOCATION>, specialize in steaks 
and barbecue. Others pride themselves on their au courant atmosphere. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Mangy Moose Saloon 
</P>
<P>
 Off-Broadway</ORGANIZATION> (30 <ORGANIZATION>S. King St.</ORGANIZATION>, one block from the square) creates trendy fresh 
seafood and pasta dishes. The <ORGANIZATION>Cadillac Grille</ORGANIZATION> (on the west side of the square) 
fiddles with nouvelle cuisine in <LOCATION>Art Deco</LOCATION> interiors. You can sip a cappuccino 
at cozy Cafe Varnet (82 S. King St.) or nurse a beer at the popular <ORGANIZATION>Mangy Moose</ORGANIZATION> 
saloon at <LOCATION>Teton Village</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For country music, check out the bands at the <ORGANIZATION>Million Dollar Cowboy Bar</ORGANIZATION> on the 
square or the Silver Dollar Bar in the historic Wort Hotel. The bars are 
embedded with silver dollars and the dance floors are swinging night spots. 
</P>
<P>
The largest herd of elk in <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> winters on the northern edge of 
<LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, protected by the <ORGANIZATION>National Elk Refuge</ORGANIZATION>. Schedule a picturesque sleigh 
ride into their midst at the refuge visitor center for close views. You'll see 
thousands of the animals in their own habitat, stags cracking horns, then 
locked in battle. 
</P>
<P>
Elk is what brought <PERSON>Margaret E.</PERSON> (<ORGANIZATION>Mardy</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Murie</PERSON> here. Her husband, <PERSON>Olaus Murie</PERSON>, a 
field biologist for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Biological Survey</ORGANIZATION>, came to study the declining elk 
herd in the <DATE>1920s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Preservation Role 
</P>
<P>
His studies soon became world famous, and the two stayed to raise their family. 
<PERSON>Olaus Murie</PERSON> played an important role in preserving two major wilderness areas: 
Grand <ORGANIZATION>Teton National Park</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Arctic National Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Margaret Murie</PERSON> made her own mark as teacher and author. ("Two in the Far 
North," describing her Alaskan childhood, is still in print.) 
</P>
<P>
With her special warmth and humble eloquence, <PERSON>Mardy</PERSON> is known as the 
conservationists' "grand doyenne." The salons in her log house tucked beneath 
the Tetons, on a bend in the river near the park visitor center in <LOCATION>Moose</LOCATION>, 
attract well-known political figures and naturalists. 
</P>
<P>
"Our problem now is not the amount of lands that are under state, private or 
federal jurisdiction, but whether we can keep our souls receptive to the 
message of peace this unspoiled landscape offers," she says. 
</P>
<P>
Jackson Hole celebrates the grandeur of nature and the spirit of people acting 
for a noble cause. What's more, it's tops for winter recreation. 
</P>
<P>
 -- -- -- 
</P>
<P>
The <PERSON>Jackson Hole</PERSON> area offers a variety of accommodations for winter visitors, 
who can book by the night or buy a package that includes lift tickets. 
</P>
<P>
For lodging in downtown <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>, try the <ORGANIZATION>Wort Hotel</ORGANIZATION> (about <MONEY>$70</MONEY> for a double 
room) or the cozy, antique-filled <ORGANIZATION>Parkway Inn</ORGANIZATION> (about <MONEY>$40</MONEY> double), both within 
easy walking distance of shops, restaurants and night life. You can call both 
places toll-free: Wort Hotel, (800) 322-2727, and <ORGANIZATION>Parkway Inn</ORGANIZATION>, (800) 247-8390. 
</P>
<P>
At the base of the slopes in <LOCATION>Teton Village</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alpenhof Lodge</LOCATION> offers alpine living 
for <MONEY>$80</MONEY> to <MONEY>$125</MONEY> double. Call (800) 732-3244. 
</P>
<P>
<ORGANIZATION>Spring Creek Ranch</ORGANIZATION> has the most scenic setting in the area. It's on a hill 700 
feet above the valley floor, and the full-service resort offers a spectacular 
vista of the Grand Tetons. High-styled wood bungalows surround a large 
ice-skating pond, and all accommodations (inn rooms, condominiums, studios and 
suites) have fireplaces. Prices from <MONEY>$75</MONEY>. Call (800) 443-6139. 
</P>
<P>
Lodging rates are about <PERCENT>20%</PERCENT> higher during <DATE>summer</DATE>. For year-round reservations, 
contact <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> Hole Central Reservations, <LOCATION>P.O.</LOCATION> Box 510, <LOCATION>Teton Village</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo</LOCATION>. 
83025, toll-free (800) 443-6931. 
</P>
<P>
Excellent literature describing the area's winter activities, lodging, 
restaurants and sightseeing is available from the <ORGANIZATION>Jackson Hole Area Chamber of 
Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>P.O. Box E</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION> 83001, (307) 733-3316. 
</P>
<P>
For general information on travel to <LOCATION>Wyoming</LOCATION>, contact the <ORGANIZATION>Wyoming Travel 
Commission</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Frank Norris Jr</PERSON>. Travel Center, I-25 and <ORGANIZATION>College Drive</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Cheyenne</LOCATION>, 
<LOCATION>Wyo.</LOCATION> 82002, toll-free (800) 225-5990. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Cross-country skier heads out on trail toward the Grand Tetons. GEORGE 
CAREY / Los Angeles Times; Map, Grand Tetons, George Carey / Los aAngeles 
Times; Photo, COLOR, Skier flies down evergreen-lined slope at Wyoming's 
Jackson Hole Ski Resort, which boasts the longest vertical drop in the nation. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901023-0048 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-23-90 0515EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Obit-Cowan     10-23 0147</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Obit-Cowan,0153</SECOND>
<HEAD>Independent Film Producer Dies at 83</HEAD>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Lester Cowan</PERSON>, an independent producer whose
credits include the <ORGANIZATION>W.C. Fields</ORGANIZATION> comedies ``You Can't Cheat an
Honest Man'' and ``My Little Chickadee,'' died of an apparent heart
attack at 83.
   <PERSON>Cowan</PERSON>, who died at his home on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, was production supervisor
of <PERSON>John Ford</PERSON>'s <DATE>1935</DATE> film ``The Whole Town's Talking,'' starring
<PERSON>Edward G. Robinson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jean Arthur</PERSON>.
   Four years later he produced the first of his own films, ``You
Can't Cheat an Honest Man,'' and in <DATE>1940</DATE> made ``My Little
Chickadee,'' which also starred Mae West.
   In the <DATE>1940s</DATE>, he produced ``Commandos Strike at Dawn,''
``Tomorrow the World'' and ``The Story of G.I. <PERSON>Joe</PERSON>.''
   Cowan originated the first college course in film studies in
   Cowan is survived by his wife, <PERSON>Ann Ronell</PERSON>; two brothers, and a
sister.

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891016-0116 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-16-89 1857EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Brites     10-16 0539</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Brites,0560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bright &amp; Brief</HEAD>
<DATELINE>FORT WAYNE, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A diaper-clad ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan'' and his
companion, ``<PERSON>Kennebunk George Bushkin</PERSON>,'' cavort in a coloring book
that takes a cockeyed look at the president and vice president.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wears a business suit and has an elephant's nose
and ears in the 48-page book. Vice President <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> is portrayed as
a chubby baby wearing only a diaper and a golf visor.
   Creator <PERSON>James Travers</PERSON>, a printer and typesetter from <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, said his inspiration was a nagging question after the two
took office: ``Who is <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>?''
   The book is called ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan and His Search for Political
Par Excellence.'' In one part, ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan,'' uses a magical golf
putter to play doubles against senators with partner ``Kennebunk
George.'' Before tee-off, <PERSON>Dan</PERSON> must recite the senators' names,
their state capitals, state nicknames and the dates their states
joined the union.
   At the bottom of each page are political quotes from famous
people _ and golf rules and definitions.
   Travers has sold a few hundred copies, at <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY> each, since the
book was published in <DATE>July</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>AUBURN, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A diaper-clad ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan'' and his
companion, ``<PERSON>Kennebunk George Bushkin</PERSON>,'' cavort in a coloring book
that takes a cockeyed look at the president and vice president.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wears a business suit and has an elephant's nose
and ears in the 48-page book. Vice President <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> is portrayed as
a chubby baby wearing only a diaper and a golf visor.
   Creator <PERSON>James Travers</PERSON>, a printer and typesetter from <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, said his inspiration was a nagging question after the two
took office: ``Who is <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>?''
   The book is called ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan and His Search for Political
Par Excellence.'' In one part, ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan,'' uses a magical golf
putter to play doubles against senators with partner ``Kennebunk
George.'' Before tee-off, <PERSON>Dan</PERSON> must recite the senators' names,
their state capitals, state nicknames and the dates their states
joined the union.
   At the bottom of each page are political quotes from famous
people _ and golf rules and definitions.
   Travers has sold a few hundred copies, at <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY> each, since the
book was published in <DATE>July</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<DATELINE>VALPARAISO, Ind. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A diaper-clad ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan'' and his
companion, ``<PERSON>Kennebunk George Bushkin</PERSON>,'' cavort in a coloring book
that takes a cockeyed look at the president and vice president.
   President <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> wears a business suit and has an elephant's nose
and ears in the 48-page book. Vice President <PERSON>Quayle</PERSON> is portrayed as
a chubby baby wearing only a diaper and a golf visor.
   Creator <PERSON>James Travers</PERSON>, a printer and typesetter from <LOCATION>Wilmington</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Del.</LOCATION>, said his inspiration was a nagging question after the two
took office: ``Who is <PERSON>Dan Quayle</PERSON>?''
   The book is called ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan and His Search for Political
Par Excellence.'' In one part, ``<LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION> Dan,'' uses a magical golf
putter to play doubles against senators with partner ``Kennebunk
George.'' Before tee-off, <PERSON>Dan</PERSON> must recite the senators' names,
their state capitals, state nicknames and the dates their states
joined the union.
   At the bottom of each page are political quotes from famous
people _ and golf rules and definitions.
   Travers has sold a few hundred copies, at <MONEY>$8.95</MONEY> each, since the
book was published in <DATE>July</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111390-0119 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 307392 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 13, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<P>
KARLIN MARSH 
</P>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 1; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
909 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BIOLOGIST'S LIFE HAS BEEN A STUDY IN CANDOR, CONCERN; 
</P>
<P>
ENVIRONMENT: KARLIN MARSH KNOWS ABOUT THE POLITICAL REALITIES OF LAND-USE. BUT 
THAT HASN'T STIFLED HER VOICE ON SOME ISSUES. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By ROSE ELLEN O'CONNOR, TIMES STAFF WRITER 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
SILVERADO CANYON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Back when she wrote a series of textbooks for the then-new course of 
environmental studies for <ORGANIZATION>Orange County</ORGANIZATION>'s public schools, biologist <PERSON>Karlin 
Marsh</PERSON> included a few chapters on community activism. 
</P>
<P>
Fifteen years later, she says, those chapters seem a little naive. 
</P>
<P>
"I've learned a lot in the intervening years," <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON>, 52, said wryly. "I've 
learned a lot about science and I've learned a lot about politics." 
</P>
<P>
For <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON>, a self-described "farm girl," those lessons have come from more than 
a dozen years of work in the environmental trenches, working as a consultant to 
some of the county's major developers and, more recently, to public agencies. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh's down-home bluntness occasionally has thrust her into the center of 
controversy. 
</P>
<P>
Last month, for example, <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> and two other biologists warned in a report that 
a proposed 2,500-home development on the edge of <ORGANIZATION>O'Neill Regional Park</ORGANIZATION> would 
jeopardize one of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>'s richest natural habitats unless it were 
moved several hundred feet farther from the park. 
</P>
<P>
County land planners commissioned the report at a cost of <MONEY>$8,000</MONEY> but never 
formally presented it to the <ORGANIZATION>Planning Commission</ORGANIZATION>. A few weeks after the report 
became public, the commission, upon the recommendation of its staff, approved 
the proposed <ORGANIZATION>Las Flores Planned Community</ORGANIZATION> by a 5-0 vote. 
</P>
<P>
Commissioners cited the county's overriding need for more affordable housing 
and the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Margarita Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s pledge that <PERCENT>60%</PERCENT> of the homes would sell for less 
than <MONEY>$250,000</MONEY>, the average cost of a new house in the county. <ORGANIZATION>Santa Margarita 
Co.</ORGANIZATION> executives had dismissed <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON>'s report, noting that she had previously 
gone on record against the project. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh, a widely respected biologist who has worked as a consultant since the 
late <DATE>1970s</DATE>, previously declined comment on the <LOCATION>Las Flores</LOCATION> project. But she 
discussed herreport and the county's response during an interview <DATE>Monday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh, softly graying and given to folksy metaphors, said she was "disappointed 
for the critters" in O'Neill Regional Park but was not surprised by the 
commission's approval of the project. 
</P>
<P>
"It takes a whole lot more energy and time and -- sometimes -- money to make a 
difference in this county than I ever conceived of in the mid-<DATE>'70s</DATE>," <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> 
said. "It's not easy for <PERSON>Joe Blow</PERSON> on Elm Street to make a difference anymore or 
even for very well organized environmental groups to make a difference. . . . 
</P>
<P>
"I think <PERSON>Las Flores</PERSON> was a good example. Here you had some of the best field 
biologists in the area saying, 'Hey, there (are) problems here that need to be 
considered.' " 
</P>
<P>
The project still needs to be approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Board of Supervisors</ORGANIZATION>, which is 
scheduled to take up the proposal at its <DATE>Dec. 5</DATE> meeting. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh, who says she practices what she preaches, works out of her home, made of 
natural wood siding and set down into the hillside at the end of an unmarked 
dirt road in <LOCATION>Silverado Canyon</LOCATION>. Her office, at the top of her three-story home, 
rests above a canopy of oak trees. 
</P>
<P>
A creek with tiny rainbow trout gurgles about 100 feet from the house. From her 
window, she's far more likely to spot a chickadee than a fellow human. Her 
husband, <PERSON>Gordon Marsh</PERSON>, curator of <ORGANIZATION>UC Irvine's Museum of Systematic Biology</ORGANIZATION>, 
shares her love of nature and is likely to be seen roaming the grounds of their 
home in the <TIME>late afternoon</TIME>, sometimes in search of insects, which he collects. 
</P>
<P>
Her two children from a previous marriage, a son and a daughter, are grown and 
live in <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh is a transplant from <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>, the daughter of an engineer who 
raised his family on a sheep farm because his wife was uncomfortable with 
crowds. 
</P>
<P>
Marsh graduated from <ORGANIZATION>Allegheny College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Meadville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, and did some 
postgraduate work at the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pittsburgh</ORGANIZATION>. She came to <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> from 
<LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION> with her former husband, who was transferred here in the late 
<DATE>1960s</DATE>. She worked as a nature guide in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION> parks and as an 
environmental education teacher in the county's public school system until the 
mid-1970s, when the first stirring of the environmental movement began. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Nathaniel Lamm</PERSON>, the school system's administrator of environmental education, 
recalled the public's heightened interest in teaching youngsters about the 
environment, but he noted the county's dearth of reference materials. Lamm 
turned to <LOCATION>Marsh</LOCATION>, whom he had met several years earlier while she was working 
for one of the county's nature conservancies and who seemed a natural for the 
job. 
</P>
<P>
"We didn't really have a good reference point. That's where <PERSON>Karlin</PERSON> came about," 
<PERSON>Lamm</PERSON> recalled. "She is one of those rare individuals who can take something 
very technical and make it understandable. . . . She's very much in demand." 
</P>
<P>
Marsh eventually wrote three volumes, reprinted numerous times, that until a 
few years ago remained the principal reference books for environmental 
education in the county's schools at the elementary and junior high school 
levels. 
</P>
<P>
The first book provides an overview of the county's biological communities, the 
second provides a more detailed look at the county's coastal wetlands and 
mountain habitats, and the third looks at the effect of development and 
urbanization on the county's wildlife, <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
At the time <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON> was asked to write the reference, she was already bored with 
teaching and eager for a new challenge. 
</P>
<P>
"You can only give so many nature walks to little snappers," she quipped. "I 
figured there must be something more out there." 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, COLOR, Karlin Marsh strolls near her home in Silverado Canyon. KARI RENE 
HALL / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
ENVIRONMENTALISTS; ENVIRONMENT; POLITICAL ACTIVISM; HABITATS; WILDLIFE REFUGES; 
LAS FLORES PLANNED DEVELOPMENT; LAND USE 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880419-0186 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-19-88 1912EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HabitatforHumanity     04-19 0458</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Habitat for Humanity,0470</SECOND>
<HEAD>Habitat To Build 20 Atlanta Homes In Largest Project To Date</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By JOSEPH B. FRAZIER</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>ATLANTA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Habitat for <ORGANIZATION>Humanity</ORGANIZATION> announced <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> it will
build 20 homes for <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s working poor in a five-day crash
project starting <DATE>June 27</DATE>, the 12-year-old volunteer agency's most
ambitious project.
   The effort, named the <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON> Work Project '88 after
<PERSON>Habitat</PERSON>'s best-known volunteer, is intended ``to fill a void
between a market economy that does not reach down to some economic
classes and a government with other spending priorities,'' said
project director <PERSON>Bruce Gunter</PERSON>.
   <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> said Habitat ``arouses the conscience of the world to the
problem of the homeless'' and to the ``disgrace in our own rich
nation of the homeless situation.''
   The Americus-based Habitat has built more than 4,000 homes for
the working poor on a non-profit, no-interest basis since <DATE>1976</DATE> and
expects to complete 2,000 this year. It has chapters in 277
American cities and 26 other countries.
   Recipients of the homes, who have to help build them, pay back
the cost usually over 20 years with mortgages averaging <MONEY>$118</MONEY> a
month. The money goes into a revolving fund used to build more
houses. Most of the labor is volunteer.
   The houses are wood-frame structures designed to be simple but
adequate with all of the basics and few frills.
   Habitat has built 24 homes in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> since it started in the
city in <DATE>1983</DATE> and hopes to complete 75 by <DATE>1990</DATE>. City figures show <PERCENT>31
percent</PERCENT> of <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>'s housing to be substandard, compared with a
nationwide average of <PERCENT>8 percent</PERCENT>.
   ``Habitat is doing what the federal, state and local governments
should be doing,'' said Mayor <PERSON>Andrew Young</PERSON>, who also is active in
the Habitat organization. ``Habitat is showing us the way.''
   So far 10 families have been picked for the 20 homes to be built
in the <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> project.
   The first house has already been built to serve as the temporary
project office.
   After construction is over, <PERSON>Evelyn Jackson</PERSON> will move into the
three-bedroom house with her two children. The <ORGANIZATION>Oglethorpe
University</ORGANIZATION> housekeeper has lived all her life in the
down-at-the-edges southeast <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> neighborhood where the block of
homes will be built.
   ``This means I can keep my roots here,'' she said. `We helped
frame it up and insulate it.''
   ``There was a lot I didn't know and they showed me how,'' she
said. ``Now if something goes wrong maybe I can fix it myself.''
   Habitat also will build five row houses in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> starting
<DATE>June 20</DATE> and has announced a 12-week, 1,200-mile march from
<LOCATION>Portland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, to <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> starting <DATE>June 26</DATE> during which Habitat
volunteers plan to build 120 homes and collect <MONEY>$1.2 million</MONEY> in
donations to initiate more construction.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901224-0070 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-24-90 1410EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>d a AM-BRF--HabitatAnniversa     12-24 0189</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-BRF--Habitat Anniversary,0195</SECOND>
<HEAD>Habitat for Humanity Will Mark 15th Anniversary With Building
Blitz</HEAD>
<DATELINE>AMERICUS, Ga. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Habitat for <ORGANIZATION>Humanity</ORGANIZATION> will celebrate its
15th anniversary next year by building 1,500 homes for the needy in
225 communities around the nation.
   Habitat said the 16-week building blitz will begin in <LOCATION>Miami</LOCATION> on
<DATE>June 16</DATE> and end in <LOCATION>Columbus</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, with a three-day convention,
starting <DATE>Sept. 26</DATE>. Former President <PERSON>Carter</PERSON>, one of Habitat's
best-known volunteers, will be the keynote speaker at the meeting.
   During the anniversary project, 15 work teams will travel from
community to community, building new homes and renovating old ones,
Habitat officials said. Habitat will provide food, housing and
transportation.
   ``This will be the most exciting year in <LOCATION>Habitat</LOCATION> for Humanity's
history,'' said <PERSON>Millard Fuller</PERSON>, Habitat's president and co-founder.
   Fuller said the Christian housing group also plans to complete
its 10,000th home early in the year and to complete its 15,000th by
the end of the year.
   Volunteers build and renovate homes by using donated materials.
Recipients are required to work on their homes and the homes of
others. Houses are purchased on a non-profit, no-interest basis.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891016-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-16-89 0220EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Hugo-Woodpeckers     10-16 0523</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hugo-Woodpeckers,520</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hurricane Hugo Harmed Endangered Birds</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By H. JOSEF HEBERT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Hurricane Hugo took a devastating human toll,
but its victims also included rare and endangered birds such as the
<ORGANIZATION>Red Cockaded Woodpecker</ORGANIZATION>, which lost one of its few remaining
habitats in the killer storm.
   ``Some endangered species really took a heavy hit by Hugo,''
said <PERSON>Rudy Rosen</PERSON>, a biologist for the <ORGANIZATION>National Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION>,
which along with several government agencies has been trying to
catalog the loss.
   Perhaps no endangered bird fared as badly as the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cockaded
Woodpecker</ORGANIZATION>, a tiny bird that conservationists have been trying to
save from extinction for nearly two decades. In recent years its
decline had been halted with an estimated 2,000 woodpecker colonies
found mainly in three national forests.
   One sanctuary for about 500 woodpecker colonies was the
250,000-acre <ORGANIZATION>Frances Marrion National Forest</ORGANIZATION> just north of
<LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>S.C.</LOCATION>, where Hugo roared ashore last month.
   ``The forest was just wiped out. Trees on the ground, twisted
and uprooted,'' said <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON>. He said anywhere from one-fourth to
perhaps as many as three-fourths of the endangered woodpeckers in
the forest may have been killed. Those that lived through the storm
may not survive because most of the aging trees that were their
habitat no longer stand, he continued.
   ``We have lost potentially forever one of the most viable
populations of the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cockaded Woodpecker</ORGANIZATION> at a time when the
population is declining,'' said <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON>. The only other significant
habitats for the woodpeckers are national forests in <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION>
and <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>.
   The old-growth pine trees at the <PERSON>Marrion</PERSON> forest, which the
woodpeckers called home, were especially easy targets for Hugo
because many already had been weakened by the woodpecker's boring
of holes for nests.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> has been drilling artificial cavities
into remaining pine trees in hopes of accommodating the surviving
woodpeckers, but <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON> said it's unclear whether that will work
because the remaining trees are not ideal for woodpeckers' nesting.
He said other animals and birds, including squirrels and owls, may
compete for the man-made nests.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>Red Cockaded Woodpecker</ORGANIZATION> was not the only endangered bird
caught by Hugo.
   Even before Hugo raced onto the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> mainland, its victims in
the <LOCATION>Caribbean</LOCATION> included the rare <LOCATION>Puerto Rican</LOCATION> wild parrot. Before
the storm, 47 of the endangered wild parrots were known to live in
the wild on the island.
   ``To date we have been able to locate 23 of the birds,'' said
<PERSON>Rosen</PERSON>. He said about <PERCENT>80 percent</PERCENT> of the bird's habitat was
defoliated when Hugo whipped across the island.
   Conservationists for a time thought the storm also had claimed
five rare red wolves on <LOCATION>Bull Island</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Charleston</LOCATION>. The wolves
disappeared for days but later were found, said <PERSON>Rosen</PERSON>.
   Their loss would have been a major setback in efforts by the
<ORGANIZATION>Interior Department</ORGANIZATION> to reintroduce red wolves into the wild. Until
a few years ago the red wolf was considered extinct except for
those found in zoos.
   Today there are fewer than two dozen of the wolves believed to
be in the wild, says <PERSON>Bob Irvin</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Federation</ORGANIZATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT923-3563</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CIKCNACNFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920911
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  11 SEP 92 / UK Company News: Speculation rises over disposal of Habitat
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN THORNHILL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
FRESH SPECULATION that the Storehouse retailing group was considering
selling its Habitat business circulated yesterday after a French newspaper
reported that Au Printemps was interested in buying Habitat's French arm.
Storehouse has suggested in the past that it might dispose of Habitat if a
suitable buyer could be found but declined to comment on the report. Au
Printemps, the French retailer owned by the <PERSON>Pinault</PERSON> group, also refused to
comment.
Analysts expressed surprise that <ORGANIZATION>Storehouse</ORGANIZATION> should consider selling Habitat
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION> individually - given that it was the most profitable part of the
furniture business - but suggested that any sale could realise up to Pounds
100m.
Ms <PERSON>Julie Ramshaw</PERSON>, retail analyst at stockbrokers <ORGANIZATION>Morgan Stanley</ORGANIZATION>, said: 'I do
not believe that <PERSON>Habitat</PERSON> has a long term future with the group but I do not
think there is any urgency about selling it.'
See Page 25
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 21
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12498</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJTB8AF8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 92 / The Lex Column: Storehouse/Ikea
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Mr David Dworkin</PERSON>, chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Storehouse</ORGANIZATION>, must have his fingers
crossed. A deal to sell Habitat to <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> would suit Storehouse nicely even
though the company does not particularly need the cash. Selling the British
and French chains at anything like the mooted Pounds 50m would easily fund
closure of Habitat in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, which lost Pounds 8m last year. And though the
French business is profitable, the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> has long been a headache the company
could live without.
By the same token it is difficult to see what <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> sees in <LOCATION>Habitat</LOCATION>. There
are superficial similarities between the two chains, but they hide more than
they reveal. <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>'s vast furniture barns contrast with Habitat's mix of high
street and edge-of-town locations. The logistics of handling a pan-European
chain with half a dozen UK outlets are also very different to managing some
70 Habitat stores. While the worst may be over at <LOCATION>Habitat</LOCATION>, this could be a
deal which <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> lives to regret.
If a contract is signed, <PERSON>Mr Dworkin</PERSON> can concentrate on wringing profits out
of <ORGANIZATION>Mothercare</ORGANIZATION> in the no-holds-barred manner which proved so successful at
BhS. Better buying, distribution, pricing, layout, management and marketing
would transform <ORGANIZATION>Mothercare</ORGANIZATION>'s prospects. Yet with the shares on a multiple of
27 times this year's estimated earnings, plenty of recovery is already in
the price. And investors may wonder how Marks and <PERSON>Spencer</PERSON> intends to respond
to the revival of BhS.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 26
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031289-0138 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 29921 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1989, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 6; Page 11; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
537 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
LAKE MICHIGAN SERENADED BY 'SINGING SAND' 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By CHARLES HILLINGER, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
HOFFMASTER STATE PARK, Mich. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The theater is darkened, engulfed in the sound of crashing waves, as the story 
of sand dune creation unfolds on screen. First comes formation of the beach -- 
fore dune, trough, back dune and barrier dune. A fragile environment springs to 
life next, grasses at first, followed by woody plants and eventually a forest 
of hemlock and sugar maple on the back and barrier dunes. 
</P>
<P>
The theater is part of this 1,054-acre park established in <DATE>1967</DATE> to protect and 
preserve <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION>'s 2 1/2-mile stretch of towering sand dunes. The park's 
centerpiece is the 13-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Genevieve Gillette Nature Center</ORGANIZATION>, a <MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> 
complex including the Sand Dune Theater dedicated to the interpretation of sand 
piles. 
</P>
<P>
"Dunes are home to many unique plants and animals," said <PERSON>Earl Wolf</PERSON>, 37, a park 
naturalist here for the last 10 years. 
</P>
<P>
The giant sand piles along the eastern shore of <LOCATION>Lake Michigan</LOCATION> collectively 
represent the world's largest accumulation of sand dunes bordering fresh water. 
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>, with its unique Sand <ORGANIZATION>Dune Protection and Management Statute</ORGANIZATION>, has 
275,000 acres of sand dunes, <PERCENT>40%</PERCENT> in public ownership. 
</P>
<P>
Snow often covers the dunes this time of year and visitors can be seen 
navigating the park's 10-mile trail on snow shoes or skis. They are accompanied 
by a symphony of chirping birds -- including black cap chickadees, 
white-breasted nut hatches, tufted titmice, blue jays, red-bellied woodpeckers 
and meadowlarks -- and squirrels who scamper across the snow amid a maze tracks 
left by red fox and white-tail deer. 
</P>
<P>
Soon, tiny <DATE>spring</DATE> peeper frogs will be peeping robustly as colorful painted 
turtles scurry about with spotted salamanders and other wildlife. And as the 
snow melts, visitors to the ice-clogged shoreline will experience "singing 
sand," a sound heard few places on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"It's a very special tune played by the sand," said park ranger <PERSON>Elizabeth 
Brockwell</PERSON>, 23. "You scoot your feet along the beach and when the right amount 
of moisture is present, tiny sand particles scrape against each other and emit 
a peculiar musical whistle or squeaking sound." 
</P>
<P>
The center is filled with graphics describing dune formation and growth here 
and throughout the world. Exhibits portray plants and animals found in sand 
dune ecosystems and a gallery is devoted to works by <PERSON>Jeanne Rockette</PERSON> and other 
<LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> sand dune artists. 
</P>
<P>
Visitors, including thousands of schoolchildren, ascend the wooden Dune Climb 
Stairway that winds to the top of 220-foot-high Sugar Hill and overlooks 
190-foot Mt. Baldy and a breathtaking sweep one of <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s most scenic 
beaches. 
</P>
<P>
The park is named after the late P. J. (Pete) <PERSON>Hoffmaster</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s first 
superintendent of parks; the sand dune museum in honor of <PERSON>Genevieve Gillette</PERSON>, 
who died two years ago at 88. 
</P>
<P>
Known as <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s "Miss State Park," <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> was the first woman to receive 
a degree in landscape architecture at an American university (<ORGANIZATION>Michigan State</ORGANIZATION>). 
From the <DATE>1920s</DATE> until her death, she was a leader in establishing <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s 
park system. <ORGANIZATION>Gillette</ORGANIZATION> wrote <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s wilderness bill, was the first president 
of <ORGANIZATION>Michigan's Parks Assn.</ORGANIZATION> and was named to the 12-member <ORGANIZATION>Citizen's Advisory 
Committee on Recreation and Natural Beauty</ORGANIZATION> by President <PERSON>Lyndon B. Johnson</PERSON> in 
<DATE>1966</DATE>. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, A long stairway leads to the top of 220-foot-high Sugar Hill at 
Hoffmaster State Park. CHARLES HILLINGER; Photo, Snow covers trails along the 
dunes on the lake's eastern shore. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Series 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
SAND DUNES; PARKS -- MICHIGAN; CONSERVATION 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-11201</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJ0BMAD3FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921027
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 OCT 92 / The Lex Column: Storehouse
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
Hats off to <LOCATION>Storehouse</LOCATION> for some pretty impressive dealing. To get Pounds 78m
for a problem-child like Habitat, which the Storehouse management does not
have time to fix, must be satisfying. Finding someone to buy the
surplus-to-requirements <PERSON>Richards</PERSON> chain for an equally full Pounds 30m is all
the more so. Of course both <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, the proud new owners of <PERSON>Richards</PERSON>, and the
<ORGANIZATION>Stichting Ingka Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, which has bought Habitat, have reasons for their
purchases. <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION> can argue that <PERSON>Richards</PERSON> fills a gap in its coverage of the
womenswear market, while the <ORGANIZATION>SIF</ORGANIZATION> wants to develop a furniture brand to
complement its <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> stores.
Both will have to work hard to justify the price they have paid, but <ORGANIZATION>SIF</ORGANIZATION> has
the more difficult task. True, the foundation is not publicly quoted and so
perhaps can afford to take a relaxed view, but sorting out Habitat's
troubles is a rather different proposition from that of exporting the
successful <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> idea. With much apparently expected of the current Habitat
management, they will have to come up with better ideas than the failed move
into edge-of-town sheds.
Storehouse is left with some cash, and two businesses which it argues fit
logically together. Both BhS and <ORGANIZATION>Mothercare</ORGANIZATION> sell to families with young
children and aim to buy on advantageous terms because of the group's size.
Storehouse must make those backstage savings work if it is to avoid the
notion that once <ORGANIZATION>Mothercare</ORGANIZATION> has been sorted out it should go the way of
Habitat and <PERSON>Richards</PERSON>.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 24
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-11325</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJ0BMAAGFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921027
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  27 OCT 92 / UK Company News: Aiming to shake the shabby out of Habitat -
The history and future of a sixties trendsetter which lost its way in the
eighties
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LUCIA VAN DER POST
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
NOBODY WHO grew up in the post-Habitat era can possibly imagine what it was
like to try to furnish a house before the youthful <PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON> opened his
very first Habitat store in <LOCATION>Fulham Road</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>London</LOCATION> in the dazzling <DATE>spring of
1964</DATE>.
If middle-class <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> had a furnishing style in those post-war years, it
was either hand-me-down Brideshead or department store repro.
In the late eighties it became fashionable to mock it, to make jolly little
jokes about Shabitat, and to avow one never went near the place.
But its arrival marked a turning point in the tastes and life-styles of the
middle-classes. For the first time there was somewhere where they could go
where nothing jarred, where the salad bowls were perfectly turned, the
casseroles were authentic peasant ware from <LOCATION>Provence</LOCATION>, and where even the
wooden spoons seemed to evoke a simpler, better, more sun-filled way of
life.
Sir <PERSON>Terence</PERSON>'s peculiar talent was for turning his own tastes and life-style,
his nostalgia for French rustic life, into a highly commercial operation so
that middle-class urban dwellers in <LOCATION>Islington</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Chelsea</PERSON> came to fill their
homes with chicken bricks and tangines, with pale pine tables and petits
pots a la creme.
The single store blossomed into a chain, the chain prospered but, as <PERSON>Ian
Renwick</PERSON>, head of corporate communications at <LOCATION>Habitat</LOCATION>, puts it: '<DATE>Three years
ago</DATE> we fell off a precipice.' Profits plunged leading to losses of Pounds
8.8m in <DATE>1989</DATE> and Pounds 11.9m in <DATE>1990</DATE>. Somewhere along the road the dream
had gone wrong.
In recent months it has been no secret that <PERSON>Storehouse</PERSON>, the parent company,
had been looking for a buyer. Now we know that <ORGANIZATION>Stichting Ingka Foundation</ORGANIZATION>,
the trust started by <PERSON>Ingvar Kamprad</PERSON>, founder of <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>, the Swedish furnishing
chain, has bought it.
At Habitat headquarters the mood is buoyant.
'We can now get on with running the business,' says <PERSON>Vittorio Radice</PERSON>,
recently installed as managing director, after two years with the group
first as merchandise manager and then as buying director. 'Without any
politics, with no looking at short-term profit. The <ORGANIZATION>Foundation</ORGANIZATION> sees the
future of Habitat very much as we do and is prepared to invest in the
future.
'<ORGANIZATION>The Foundation</ORGANIZATION> sees Habitat and <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> as two completely separate brands and
we will be run quite separately from <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>. Whereas <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> goes in for 200,000
sq ft self-service style stores, eventually I want all our stores to revert
to being smaller, fully serviced stores with high quality sales staff.'
Out has gone the mail order (too down-market), out the polyester bedlinen
(nothing but <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> cotton bedlinen from now on), out the melamine and the
self-assembly furniture ('unless a piece of furniture is born to be
self-assembly').
'Already,' says <PERSON>Mr Radice</PERSON>, 'we have turned the corner. Sometime around <DATE>May
last year</DATE> it seemed to happen.'
He waves yesterday's figures jubilantly. 'Just look at this - yesterday we
were 26 per cent ahead of the same <DATE>Sunday</DATE> last year whilst for the whole
week we are 7.4 per cent ahead of the equivalent week last year. Habitat is
in line to return to profit.'
Quite why and how the chain lost its way, or more accurately, failed to
evolve, is a matter of some dispute.
<PERSON>Mr Radice</PERSON> is in no doubt. 'Habitat today could be the best home furnishings
chain in the world if the original concept hadn't been murdered. When
<PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON> first opened stores they were in beautiful buildings - a
restored church in <PERSON>Tunbridge Wells</PERSON>, a 1920s cinema in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>'s <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Road,
a grand hotel in <LOCATION>Bristol</LOCATION>, an old Spitfire factory in <LOCATION>Manchester</LOCATION> - all these
were wonderful, individual, special to their towns.
'Then they started opening in huge sheds in edge of town sites, next door to
<ORGANIZATION>B&amp;Q</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>MFI</ORGANIZATION>, Do-It-All. They even opened seven Habitat stores in BhS. All this
diluted the image, took it down-market. I think that was a tremendous
mistake.
'When I arrived I asked whom they saw as their competition. The Reject Shop,
<ORGANIZATION>MFI</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>John Lewis</PERSON> I was told. I knew at once I had to do something.'
What <PERSON>Vittorio Radice</PERSON> is determined to do it is to win back the market it
should never have lost in the first place.
'We aim to have 50 stores in this country, of which 20 will be new and
another 10 of the existing stores will be relocated. It will be an
evolutionary process with, I hope, no redundancies. In fact we hope to
create jobs.
'I want the stores to be no bigger than 10,000 sq ft, small enough to retain
an individual, characterful mood, with each store listening closely to the
needs of its own customers.'
Habitat is, if you like, returning to its roots, going back, after a painful
detour, to where it all began. Those who remember the original Habitat store
in the <LOCATION>Fulham Road</LOCATION>, where <PERSON>Joseph</PERSON> stands today, remember one really terrific
shop showing what it could be like if everything was all of a piece, if one
consistent, sure taste lay behind it all.
Times have moved on, tastes have changed, but the original blueprint is
still <PERSON>Mr Radice</PERSON>'s guiding light. 'I remember when I was with <ORGANIZATION>AMC Milan</ORGANIZATION> (a
large Italian furniture buying organisation where <PERSON>Mr Radice</PERSON> worked for seven
years) I used to come from <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> just to see Habitat because it was the
retailing phenomenon of its time. Then in the mid <DATE>1980s</DATE> I stopped coming.
Well, I want people like me to feel they have to come and see what Habitat
is up to again.'
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 28
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891216-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-16-89 0426EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-HollywoodAuction     12-16 0351</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Hollywood Auction,0358</SECOND>
<HEAD>Monroe Gown, Monster Mask Big Sellers at Auction</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Carrousel in 9th graf is cq.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By KILEY ARMSTRONG</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW YORK (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A siren-red, sequin-encrusted evening gown that
gentlemen preferred to see <PERSON>Marilyn Monroe</PERSON> wearing fetched <MONEY>$14,300</MONEY>
at an auction of Hollywood memorabilia.
   The dress worn in ``Gentlemen Prefer Blondes'' was sold <DATE>Friday</DATE>
to an unidentified buyer at <ORGANIZATION>Sotheby</ORGANIZATION>'s auction house. The
unidentified seller also threw in a Life magazine cover showing
<PERSON>Miss Monroe</PERSON> in the gown and <PERSON>Jane Russell</PERSON> in an identical one.
   A white lace bustier, which <PERSON>Miss Monroe</PERSON> wore under a different
gown in the <DATE>1960</DATE> movie ``Let's Make Love,'' went for <MONEY>$1,430</MONEY>. And a
black bra, of unspecified origin but inscribed with the sex
symbol's name, sold for <MONEY>$605</MONEY>.
   The beauty got some competition from a beast: a rubber monster
head from the <DATE>1954</DATE> movie, ``The Creature of the Black Lagoon.'' A
Canadian private collector got it for <MONEY>$5,610</MONEY> _ well above the
pre-sale estimate of <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$3,000</MONEY>.
   The monster mask, in fetching sea green with red lips, is
highlighted by ``many gills to the back'' and large moles, the
auction catalog notes. When not being worn, it can be displayed in
its own clear case.
   A Salvador Dali backdrop from <PERSON>Alfred Hitchcock</PERSON>'s ``Spellbound,''
valued at <MONEY>$60,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$80,000</MONEY>, was bought back when it failed to
make the undisclosed minimum. So was a navy blue and white checked,
cotton pinafore worn by <PERSON>Judy Garland</PERSON> in the ``Wizard of Oz,'' which
the auctioneers had hoped would go for <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY>.
   But an anonymous buyer paid <MONEY>$6,600</MONEY> for a leather chariot toga
worn by <PERSON>Charlton Heston</PERSON> in ``<PERSON>Ben Hur</PERSON>,'' circa <DATE>1959</DATE>. Brown leather
forearm covers and a blue, 9-foot cape complete the macho ensemble.
   And <ORGANIZATION>W.C. Fields</ORGANIZATION>'s top hat from the <DATE>1939</DATE> movie, ``My Little
Chickadee,'' went for <MONEY>$3,300</MONEY> to a private collector _ a bargain,
below the estimate of <MONEY>$4,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$6,000</MONEY>.
   The Hollywood mementos were part of Sotheby's annual Collector's
Carrousel sale that also includes toys, dolls, animated art, music
boxes and baseball memorabilia. The sale continued today.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12748</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJSB0ADCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921019
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 OCT 92 / International Company News: Storehouse in talks for sale of
Habitat
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By PHILIP RAWSTORNE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
STOREHOUSE, the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION> retailing group, is negotiating the sale of Habitat, its
home furnishing chain, to <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>, the Swedish furniture retailer.
Talks are also being held with <ORGANIZATION>Sears</ORGANIZATION>, the retail and mail order group, which
is understood to be interested in buying <PERSON>Richards</PERSON>, the <LOCATION>Storehouse</LOCATION> women's
wear business.
City analysts estimate the two deals could raise up to Pounds 70m for
Storehouse, though the negotiations have yet to resolve a number of 'issues
of substance', according to one source.
Habitat, founded by Sir <PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON>, was one of the high street successes
of the <DATE>1960s</DATE> and early <DATE>1970s</DATE>. Its cheap, well-designed furnishings
epitomised the lifestyle of young professional people.
It failed, however, to keep pace with the retail revolution it helped to
create. In the <DATE>past two years</DATE>, it has closed a quarter of its UK stores and
losses have amounted to more than Pounds 20m.
Habitat's French operations, in which Au Printemps, the French retailer, was
recently reported to be interested, are profitable; but the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> business lost
Pounds 7.7m last year.
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> has prospered in the UK since it opened its first superstore at
<LOCATION>Warrington</LOCATION> <DATE>five years ago</DATE>. It was ranked the country's sixth largest
furniture retailer last year despite having just three stores. Since then,
it has opened a fourth at <LOCATION>Gateshead</LOCATION>, and is due to open another at <LOCATION>Croydon</LOCATION>
next month. Its out-of-town stores, with facilities such as children's
playgrounds and family restaurants, represented 'what Habitat might have
been,' said one analyst.
Storehouse declined to comment on the Habitat disposal yesterday but <PERSON>Mr
David Dworkin</PERSON>, who became chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Storehouse</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>July</DATE>, has
indicated that the core of the group's future operations would be BhS and
<ORGANIZATION>Mothercare</ORGANIZATION>, each serving mass markets in clothing.
Storehouse, which showed signs of recovery with pre-tax profits of Pounds
15.8m last year, is expected to register a small loss during the first half
of the current year.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 22
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900517-0233 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-17-90 1538EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-Woodpecker-Timber Adv20   05-17 1244</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Woodpecker-Timber, Adv 20,1287</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv20</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, May 20, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Will Saving Rare Bird Cost Timber Jobs in South?</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos NY301,302 of May 16</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By CHRISTOPHER SULLIVAN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CALLAHAN, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Timber man <PERSON>Jim Coleman</PERSON>'s boot makes the
same print in the forest floor as biologist <PERSON>Ralph Costa</PERSON>'s, and both
men call themselves environmentalists.
   The similarities end when they talk about a humble little bird
called the red-cockaded woodpecker and the complex new rules to
preserve a million acres of Southern pine woods for the endangered
creature's home.
   Three logging contracts signed by <PERSON>Coleman</PERSON>'s small company were
scrapped when the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> regulations changed to give
the bird more space, and he sees layoffs looming in the region's
biggest industry.
   ``If we were out there destroying the environment, that'd be one
thing,'' says <PERSON>Coleman</PERSON>, whose <ORGANIZATION>Callahan Timber Co.</ORGANIZATION> planted more than
1 million seedlings last year. ``We're at a loss. We don't
understand.''
   Costa, who oversees a program to save the woodpecker in the
<ORGANIZATION>Appalachicola National Forest</ORGANIZATION> 200 miles away, says timber interests
alone must not drive decisions about federal woodlands.
   ``Public lands are going to be the last places that things
survive, pieces of the world _ whether it's a woodpecker or a bald
eagle,'' he said. ``They're the bastions.''
   Disagreement about the red-cockaded woodpecker has generated
legal briefs and government studies that now stack up well over the
bird's seven-inch height.
   The species, named for the tiny badges of red plumage behind the
male's eyes, has been on the endangered list since <DATE>1970</DATE>.
   Perhaps 10,000 birds remain, the rest falling prey to flying
squirrels, snakes and even other woodpeckers that take over the
cavities they painstakingly dig in living pine trees.
   Man, often unwittingly, has been the birds' adversary, too,
consuming much of their habitat _ parklike stands of old pines to
nest in and enough surrounding woods to forage for insects, find
mates and expand their clans.
   As the <LOCATION>Sun Belt</LOCATION>'s population has grown, developers have turned
woods into housing tracts. Loggers have replaced swaths of old
forest with tree crops, raised and cut in cycles.
   And the government routinely has extinguished the fires caused
by lightning that actually helped the woodpecker by burning out
hardwoods that <DATE>spring</DATE> up beneath tall pines, blocking nest cavities
and giving predators easier access.
   ``By far the largest factor has been clearcutting, destruction
of the habitat and suppression of fire,'' says <PERSON>Doug Honnold</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Sierra Club Legal Defense Fund</ORGANIZATION>.
   The group accused the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> in a lawsuit of
jeopardizing the species in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, and in <DATE>1988</DATE>, a judge agreed,
banning clearcutting and other timber industry methods within
three-quarters of a mile of woodpecker colony sites. The case is on
appeal.
   After a similar suit was threatened concerning national forests
in eight other Southern states, the agency last year applied a
three-quarter-mile protection zone to those areas, too.
   It then was the timber industry's turn to sue, citing the <ORGANIZATION>Forest
Service</ORGANIZATION>'s historic mandate ``to furnish a continuous supply of
timber.''
   It also contended the agency had failed to fully implement
earlier, less restrictive guidelines for the bird, and hadn't
followed required procedures in changing the rules.
   ``Unfortunately, we're fighting procedure versus emotion,'' says
<PERSON>Deborah Baker</PERSON> of the Atlanta-based industry group that filed suit,
the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service Timber Purchasers Council</ORGANIZATION>.
   The three-quarter-mile radius encompasses 1,100 acres. That's
1.2 million acres for all the known colonies, compared with 502,000
restricted acres under the previous rules, which set only a
half-mile zone, according to the <ORGANIZATION>American Forest Council</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Ron Escano</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> official in charge of protecting
endangered species in the Southeast, says the acreage was added to
give the birds space to expand colonies, not merely maintain
existing ones. In all but three national forests that have the
woodpeckers, the population seemed to be declining under the old
rules, he says.
   The new rules are interim measures while a two-year
environmental impact assessment is completed, he says.
   Meanwhile, Escano insists, timber cutting can occur within the
current zones _ ``it's just that it has to be designed to benefit
the woodpecker.''
   Asked about the industry's complaint that the new rules reduced
timber harvests by a total of 73 million board feet this year and
last, <PERSON>Escano</PERSON> says, ``In relation to total volume cut ... it's quite
small.''
   He acknowledges, however, ``If you look at individual forests
and individual operators, it could be a very different story.''
   According to <PERSON>Michael Sparks</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> timber sales
official, the impact will be greatest in coastal areas from <LOCATION>East
Texas</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>.
   In <DATE>fiscal 1989</DATE>, about 1.2 billion board feet of timber was cut
on Southeast national forests, a drop from the previous five years.
The value fell to <MONEY>$76.8 million</MONEY> after hovering around <MONEY>$100 million</MONEY>
annually through that period.
   Woodpecker protection is certainly not the only factor
influencing volume, but the new guidelines are being felt.
   <PERSON>Jim Coleman</PERSON> doesn't know how much it cost <ORGANIZATION>Callahan Timber</ORGANIZATION> when
three contracts for northern <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Osceola National Forest</ORGANIZATION> were
canceled and then renegotiated because of the rule change.
   ``It's really hurt the industry down here,'' he says. ``When you
pull timber off the market, then this timber has to be found
somewhere _ and if it can't be found, then these mills start
shutting down.''
   One mill he's thinking of is a utility-pole operation owned
jointly by <ORGANIZATION>Callahan Timber</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Richard Cochran</PERSON>.
   Cochran echoes a complaint often heard in timbering areas, that
the bird is really a surrogate, ``a tool ... for people who just
don't want to cut any timber.''
   ``If we could reason with each other, we should have enough
middle ground,'' he says.
   ``No, the time for compromise is over,'' says <PERSON>Gary Henry</PERSON>, who
oversees red-cockaded woodpecker preservation for the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Fish and
<ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``That's what's been occurring for years ...
hoping that this was adequate for the woodpecker. It's very obvious
today that it is not adequate.''
   Couldn't the industry simply turn to private lands for raw
material?
   There are 164 million acres of private timberland in the
Southeast, many times the total national forest acreage, according
to the <ORGANIZATION>American Forest Council</ORGANIZATION>. But much private land is less
carefully managed and quality is often lower, industry officials
say.
   <PERSON>Ralph Costa</PERSON> drives past miles of private timberlands, paper
company plantations, on his commute to work in the <ORGANIZATION>Appalachicola
National Forest</ORGANIZATION>, home to 1,000 or so of the woodpeckers, more than
anywhere else. It doesn't bother him to see trees cut on private
land.
   But, he says, ``I don't think that national forests or any
public lands, for that matter, should necessarily have an objective
of producing a cash crop.''
   Deer hunting is permitted to thin herds. ``Cutting a tree ought
to be the same way. We ought to take trees for the health of the
ecosystem,'' says <PERSON>Costa</PERSON>, who's often in the woods before dawn to
band red-cockadeds or move birds from his forest to others,
sometimes providing mates in colonies that have dwindled to a
single bird.
   ``People ask me what's the value of a woodpecker,'' <ORGANIZATION>Costa</ORGANIZATION> says,
answering with an analogy: ``You can take a nice fancy spider web
and start cutting the threads. You're going to clip one thread
eventually and the spider web is going to collapse.
   ``And we can keep throwing species off the planet, which we're
doing, and eventually something's going to go wrong.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, May 20</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880629-0059 </DOCNO>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS -- Gardening: The Art of Bird-Gardening </HL>
<AUTHOR> Patti Hagan </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<DATELINE> Brooklyn, N.Y.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Senior American birdman <PERSON>Roger Tory Peterson</PERSON> characterizes as "bird gardeners" people who sow their gardens "not only with flowers but also with cardinals, orioles, jays, bluebirds, purple finches and goldfinches." 
At this time of year I birdgarden almost as much as I flower-garden, getting permissive and allowing a lot of questionable plants -- pokeweed, smartweed, nightshade, thistles -- to continue in my garden by way of bird fodder. 
Bird gardeners also have the habit of putting up bird houses for any birds who'd care to share the address. 
Usually these are miniatures made in the image of the suburban box -- detached dwellings, no row birdhouses, no bird duplexes -- except, of course, for purple martin condos. 

   A couple of years ago I found an Aframe birdhouse out on the street with a neighbor's trash. 
Not wanting to be responsible for more homeless birds in this city, I retrieved it and relocated it in the old crab apple out back. 
Possibly because it was rather small -- an S.R.O. -- no birds ever moved in and nested there. 
However, nearby in the <PERSON>Dorothy Perkins</PERSON> rambler rose thicket that same <DATE>spring</DATE>, I caught a pair of cardinals nest-making with <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> man-made plastic fast-food detritus off <LOCATION>Flatbush Avenue</LOCATION>. 
Right then I vowed to do my best to get the birds of <LOCATION>Brooklyn</LOCATION> back to basics: wholesome, organic, all-natural nesting materials. 

   To this end I let dandelions have their powderpuff heads and certain rogue grasses thrive along the bluestone path. 
I did not dispose of old fern fronds and broken twigs if I thought they could be bird-useful. 
Even so, this <DATE>spring</DATE>, while flipping through a gardening catalog, I was delighted to find an all-natural product called <ORGANIZATION>Samson Nesting Material</ORGANIZATION>. 
Six dollars would buy "enough . . . to build 12 nests." 

   The "sterilized" nesting material arrived, late <DATE>April</DATE>, in a cardinal-red box: "feathers, moss, hair, string, cotton" packaged by a company called <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Products</ORGANIZATION> (P.O. 
Box 363, <LOCATION>Wisconsin Rapids</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wis.</LOCATION> 54494). 
There was a lot of copy to read on the box, with key phrases ("Blended to Attract Colorful Songbirds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>" and "Watch the Birds Build a Nest!") repeated on two sides. 
The stuff was, the box said, "designed to be perfect for bluebirds, robins, wrens, chickadees, finches, martins, cardinals and hummingbirds." 
Since the only species observed nesting in these parts during my tenure have been robins, mockingbirds, cardinals and mourning doves, I was eager to believe that "more than 50 species of North American birds will use this nesting material." 

   After studying "Some Ways to Present Nesting Material," I chose the "Directly on Ground" method, described as "the most natural way for birds." 
Within an hour of informal presentation, several songbirds not mentioned in the prospectus of coming bird attractions hit on the nesting goods. 
Starlings! 
Choosy starlings. 
Very quickly they made off with all the white bird feathers. 
Nothing else. 
The robins, cardinals, mockingbirds, catbirds were not interested, to say nothing of any of the 45 other songsters I could wish. (My cat, Be-bop, picked out the string to play with.) 

   Two months have passed, the first broods of robins and cardinals have fledged, and the mound of authentic, old-fashioned nesting material remains directly on the ground between a rock and a hard place, getting more unsterile by the day. 
Contemplating my backyard wildness, I was puzzled as to why so many songbirds would pass up such good mail-order fixings until I went back to the red box for further reading: "In a yard that is kept 'spick and span' the birds will not be able to find the natural materials they need to build their nests." (Clearly I have the wrong gardening style for the product.) 

   This insight set me to rummaging in the "Bird Homes" chapter of <PERSON>Margaret McKenny</PERSON>'s <DATE>1939</DATE> book "Birds in the Garden." 
There I read: "In the scrupulously tidied garden birds often have difficulty in finding materials with which to build their nests . . . 
In the modern, well-cared-for garden, every decayed branch has been removed, every cavity has been filled and all dead trees are immediately cut down." 

   Not so in this modern garden, which tends toward laissez-faire. 
No way can it be cited for spick and span. 
The two main trunks of the crab have fallen in the past three years and remain on the horizontal, where clematis and wisteria can engulf them. 
They are well-rotted and favored feeding stations for yellow-shafted flickers and downy woodpeckers. 
They also grow lovely rippled fungus borders. 
Birds have dropped wild multiflora rose seed near the house and now the multifloras have climbed the deck, raddling with the Asiatic bittersweet, and making an impenetrable nesting thicket plus producing little red rose hips. (And all along I had the habit of sharing the plush white hair of my late Samoyed, <LOCATION>Tofu</LOCATION>, with the birds during the dog's awesome spring sheddings.) 

   And then there's the moss. 
A while ago, inspired by the <ORGANIZATION>Moss Temple</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Kyoto</LOCATION>, I dedicated a small patch of my garden to moss. 
I sank a roasting pan and laid on rehydrated sphagnum sheet moss for a moss pond, which soon grew to have thickly moussed, brilliant green verges. 
Robins make bold to strip mine my moss -- it has been the stuffing of countless robins' nests these past five years -- such that by early <DATE>June</DATE> the moss pond is revealed for the dark blue, white-speckled turkey roasting pan that it is. 
Never mind. 

   However, I'm assuming that low maintenance, spick-and-span gardeners are in the majority nowadays. 
And it is for them that <ORGANIZATION>Samson Nesting Material</ORGANIZATION> was conceived. 
The spick-and-spanners can keep their tidy garden ways and still put out the messy stuff of bird domesticity. 
After all, as <PERSON>Margaret McKenny</PERSON> observed: "A garden without birds would be a semi-desert from the esthetic standpoint." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT924-12495</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CJTB8AGVFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>921020
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  20 OCT 92 / Ikea's logic furnishes a market riddle: John Thornhill
describes a curious interest in Habitat
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JOHN THORNHILL
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
As a rallying cry it is less than impressive. As a statement of intent it
has proved remarkably effective: 'We shall offer a wide range of home
furnishing items of good design and function, at prices so low, that the
majority of people can afford to buy them'.
The words are those of <PERSON>Mr Ingvar Kamprad</PERSON>, the Swedish entrepreneur,
outlining the business philosophy behind <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>.
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> is the privately owned furniture retailer, which, in four decades, has
grown from a single store in <LOCATION>Sweden</LOCATION>'s backwoods to become one of the most
successful international retailers in the world.
At the end of <DATE>last year</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> ran more than 100 outlets in 25 countries,
with annual sales of SKr22.3bn (Pounds 2.2bn).
The company's vast blue and yellow retail sheds selling about 11,000
strangely named furniture products, such as Orgryte sofas and Smedvik dining
tables, are a feature of the international retailing landscape. Yet the
company's remarkable expansion is due largely to organic growth.
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>'s reported interest in buying the UK and French arms of the struggling
Habitat chain, owned by <ORGANIZATION>Storehouse</ORGANIZATION>, has therefore inspired considerable
curiosity, and even outright puzzlement, within the furniture retailing
industry.
<PERSON>Mr Richard Hyman</PERSON>, director of Verdict, the retail consultants, says: 'The
possible acquisition has no commercial logic at all. If <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> has a spare
Pounds 50m to invest, I would have thought they would have done better to
continue expanding what is clearly an outstandingly successful format,
rather than buying a loss-making high street chain which provides very weak
competition.'
Such sentiments are expressed in slightly more muted form even within the
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea Group</ORGANIZATION>. The furniture company's headquarters in <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> yesterday
continued to deny all knowledge of the possible acquisition of Habitat. Its
UK business was similarly baffled.
A clue to the conundrum may lie in the fact that <LOCATION>Storehouse</LOCATION> is conducting
talks with the <ORGANIZATION>Ikea Foundation</ORGANIZATION> rather than with the <ORGANIZATION>Ikea Group</ORGANIZATION> itself. The
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, set up by <PERSON>Mr Kamprad</PERSON>, is the legal owner of the furniture
group and is responsible for other activities, including the disbursement of
awards every three years to improve the quality of life and the environment.
The idiosyncratic <PERSON>Mr Kamprad</PERSON> may therefore be conducting the discussions
through the foundation without telling his colleagues in the furniture
group. He has certainly expressed a personal interest in Habitat before.
Three years ago, when <PERSON>Storehouse</PERSON> came under siege from the corporate raider,
<PERSON>Mr Asher Edelman</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mr Kamprad</PERSON> contacted the company and asked if he could buy
the furniture chain.
<PERSON>Mr Michael Julien</PERSON>, then chief executive of <ORGANIZATION>Storehouse</ORGANIZATION>, visited <LOCATION>Denmark</LOCATION> to
discuss the deal with <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION>, but it faded away. So did the threat from <PERSON>Mr
Edelman</PERSON>.
Sir <PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON>, the former chief executive of Storehouse and the guiding
spirit behind Habitat, said <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> then believed it could use Habitat to
expand into a different segment of the UK furniture market. 'They saw that
Habitat could be the leading edge of <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> giving the group an up-market high
street presence,' he said yesterday, emphasising that he had no knowledge of
the current talks.
At the end of <DATE>March</DATE>, Habitat was running 40 stores in the <ORGANIZATION>UK</ORGANIZATION>, after slimming
down the chain in recent years in the face of recession. Habitat also runs
36 more successful stores in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, which contributed profits of Pounds
7.1m last year, and 17 troubled stores in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION>, which incurred a loss of
Pounds 7.7m. In total, the Habitat group incurred losses of Pounds 8.8m on
sales of Pounds 201.2m.
<ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> is certainly not the only name in the frame as a potential acquirer and
'issues of substance' are still said to be under discussion. Au Printemps,
the French retail group, has also expressed interest in acquiring the
successful French arm, at least. Several other groups are also believed to
have come forward with proposals.
City analysts suggest, nevertheless, that <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> is the likely prospective
victor, but they believe that any buyer would be most likely to acquire the
UK and French businesses as a package, leaving Storehouse to dispose of - or
close - the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> arm separately.
If <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> were to complete the acquisition, it would command a strong position
at the upper end of the hugely fragmented UK furniture market, even though
its combined percentage share of the sector would still be in low single
figures.
Furniture retailers have been badly affected by recession, but <ORGANIZATION>Ikea</ORGANIZATION> has
proved resistant. After establishing a presence in <LOCATION>Warrington</LOCATION> in <DATE>1987</DATE>, it
has opened stores in <LOCATION>Wembley</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Birmingham</LOCATION> generating sales of Pounds 91.4m
last year. It plans to open stores at a rate of about one per year for the
forseeable future, with <LOCATION>Gateshead</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Croydon</LOCATION> being added to the list this
year.
Ikea seems likely to retain Habitat's distinctive style and name. <PERSON>Mr Kamprad</PERSON>
may provide the listless retailer with the purpose <PERSON>Storehouse</PERSON> has been
singularly unable to supply during the past few years.
Lex, Page 26
 ---------------------------------------------------
                <ORGANIZATION>IKEA</ORGANIZATION>'S EXPANSION
 ---------------------------------------------------
Year    Outlets     Countries     Turnover SKr (m)
 ---------------------------------------------------
<DATE>1954</DATE>      1            1                3
<DATE>1964</DATE>      2            2               79
<DATE>1974</DATE>     10            5              616
<DATE>1984     66           17</DATE>             6770
1991     96           24            22325
 ---------------------------------------------------
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 27
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT942-9557</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EEPB4AFCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940514
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  14 MAY 94 / How To Spend It: A child of the sixties celebrates a
birthday - Lucia van der Post on Habitat, 30 years old this week
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LUCIA VAN DER POST
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
In <DATE>1964</DATE>, when Habitat was born, I was a young mother in <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, wheeling a
great high-sprung pram up and down the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Road from <LOCATION>World</LOCATION>'s End, where
we lived, to <PERSON>Peter Jones</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Sloane Square</LOCATION>, where I went in search of a carpet
or a lampshade or a chair that I liked and could afford. I was almost always
disappointed.
I had four floors of a terraced house to furnish and little money or
experience. Finding few things that I could bear to bring across the
threshold, I began to think I had very peculiar tastes. Certainly that was
how many shopkeepers of the day treated me, implying that anyone who stocked
the kind of things they imagined I wanted would soon be out of business.
My husband was completely nonplussed at how extraordinarily picky his young
wife had turned out to be. The trickiest scenes took place in the linoleum
department where the prevailing tastes of the day ran to bright renditions
of shells, stones or ancient Greek mosaics.
Then Habitat opened, on <DATE>May 11, 1964</DATE>. Oh, the relief. It was perfectly all
right not to like fringed velvet three-piece suites, to want no truck with
lampshades perched upon porcelain dolls, to prefer sturdy pale pine to
<ORGANIZATION>Formica</ORGANIZATION>, to find visual repose in a simple white Japanese paper lantern, to
prefer one's salad tossed in a hand-turned wooden bowl rather than a plastic
one.
It is almost impossible to convey to the post-Habitat generation just what
the birth of that first shop meant to the young marrieds of the <DATE>1960s</DATE>. The
clarity and simplicity of the vision was stunning.
Sir <PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON>'s avowed mission was to prove that 'functional can be
beautiful, and beautiful must be affordable'. One design journalist was so
carried away she felt 'as if she had died and gone to heaven'. It was much
more than a shop - it offered the promise of a warmer, more sun-filled way
of life.
This week, <PERSON>Habitat</PERSON> was 30 years old and celebrated its birthday by offering
a small selection of goods stocked by the original shop at the original
prices - Japanese rush bugs at 18p, director's chairs at Pounds 5 each, six
<LOCATION>Paris</LOCATION> glasses for 75p, bentwood chairs for Pounds 6.50.
All these things are marvellous illustrations of the longevity of what we
have come to call good design. The director's chair, the bentwood chair, the
paper lanterns, the plain linen, the rush or willow ware, the simple wooden
products - all have much the same timeless air as, say, an 18th century
piece of Wedgwood creamware, a piece of Shaker furniture, French bistro
pottery, 17th century English silverware. All of them should go on looking
good for years to come.
Tasteful, attractive, functional things, Habitat proved, did not have to
come with fancy price tags. We still have at home, doing sterling service,
some of the items we bought all those years ago - a couple of red
<PERSON>Magistretti</PERSON> rush-seated chairs, white painted bentwood chairs, a
black-stained ash desk top on trestles, storage units and countless
earthenware casseroles, white porcelain pots a la creme, white souffle
dishes. I am as pleased with them now as I was then.
If you look at Habitat today, it is good to see that <PERSON>Vittorio Radice</PERSON>, the
managing director, has kept to his avowed intention of taking Habitat back
to where it all began.
'Sir <PERSON>Terence Conran</PERSON>,' he told me a couple of years ago, 'had a wonderful
concept and as long as he kept to it the stores flourished. They were all in
beautiful buildings that were special to their towns. It was only when he
took his eye off the ball and they took Habitat into huge sheds in edge of
town sites that the merchandise deteriorated and the image became seriously
damaged.' The <DATE>1980s</DATE> Shabitat jokes began.
Look through a current catalogue - or better still, visit one of the stores
 -and you will see the original concept is alive and strong. The stores
today are light, bright airy places, just as I remember that first store in
the <LOCATION>Fulham Road</LOCATION>.
It has grown up a bit, in that the sofas look plumper, softer, more
welcoming. The textiles reflect our modern preoccupation with the earthy and
the natural. There is some lovely appliqued bed linen and plenty of the
attractive rushware that brought in the original customers - look for rattan
dining chairs, for storage chests, for tumbler covers, for picnic baskets
and a wonderful reclining chaise-longue for just Pounds 149.
There is, as always, a touch of the ethnic - galvanised iron baskets and
lanterns, an Edo paper lantern, a Dakari tray table from <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>. Having run
out of new cuisines to introduce us to (remember the tagine, the wok, the
pasta-maker?) kitchenware has reverted primarily to the simple and the
classic with the occasional exuberant burst of hand-painted Italian
ceramics.
In the Habitat of today you can find most of the basic ingredients a young
household needs. It has once again become a place that the design world
feels it needs to watch.
<PERSON>David Davies</PERSON>, the designer responsible for some of the most interesting
retailing projects around, firmly believes that today it is one of the best
home furnishing stores in the world. He says: 'I travel a lot and I do not
know of one to beat it for the mix of products, the incredible style and the
very affordable prices. The textiles, the cushions, the throws, the fabrics
are exceptionally well-priced and so is the furniture. Where else can you
buy a really good chair for Pounds 49? My office is full of them.'
The <DATE>1980s</DATE>' jokes are drying up.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>GBZ  United Kingdom, EC.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P5712 Furniture Stores.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XIV
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072789-0014 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 87142 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 27, 1989, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 6; Column 4; Letters Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
263 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SPOTTED OWLS AND LOGGERS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
I'm distressed that you published <PERSON>Mark A. Stein</PERSON>'s one-sided lament for loggers 
in Sweet Home, <LOCATION>Ore.</LOCATION>, who are supposedly losing work because environmentalists 
are trying to save the spotted owl. 
</P>
<P>
We in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> decry <LOCATION>Brazil</LOCATION>'s and <LOCATION>Indonesia</LOCATION>'s felling of their tropical rain 
forests while we decimate our own old-growth forest at an equally reckless 
rate, contributing to the same global crises: release of carbon dioxide, 
exacerbating the greenhouse effect; and loss of habitat, reducing species 
diversity. 
</P>
<P>
The "jobs vs. environment" dichotomy is a red herring. Most timber unemployment 
has resulted from modernization of mill equipment. More jobs are lost because 
so many logs are now shipped, unprocessed, to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. (We harvest more wood than 
we need and sell <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> to <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>. Yet the <ORGANIZATION>Forest Service</ORGANIZATION> proposes chopping <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> 
more over the next decade!) 
</P>
<P>
A study by resource economist <PERSON>Jeffrey T. Olson</PERSON> shows that taking <PERCENT>25%</PERCENT> less wood 
would eliminate only 2,300 jobs in 40 years. 
</P>
<P>
Industry "research" to duplicate spotted owl habitat in the monoculture tree 
plantations with which it replaces nature's forests is absurd. What about all 
the other old growth-dependent species whose survival is threatened by 
ever-shrinking habitat -- grizzly bear, gray wolf, mountain lion, mountain 
goat, wolverine, lynx, fisher, flying squirrel, red tree vole, bog lemming, 
rough-skinned newt, Olympic salamander, tailed frog, goshawk, harlequin duck, 
marbled murrelet, pileated, red-cockaded and three-toed woodpecker, elegant 
trogon, red crossbill, olive-sided flycatcher? 
</P>
<P>
DON <LOCATION>STRACHAN 
</P>
<P>
Topanga</LOCATION> 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Letter to the Editor 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890821-0183 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-21-89 0135EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-SPE--Mature:Northbound     08-21 0804</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-SPE--Mature: Northbound,0829</SECOND>
<HEAD>SPECIAL EDITION</HEAD>
<HEAD>Mature Years: Northbound Retirees</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAIGE St. JOHN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   Suburban <LOCATION>Detroit</LOCATION> was no place to retire, so <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and Tom
Powers packed up their belongings and moved.
   They didn't go to the Sun Belt.
   The Powers retired north, to <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Upper Peninsula</LOCATION>, a
flannel-shirted place even on <DATE>July</DATE> nights, famous for arduous
winters and mosquito-bit summers.
   ``Land of the Loon,'' the T-shirts say.
   The Powers could have flocked south like so much of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s
retiring public, but it was in these snowbirds' minds to head
instead toward <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   ``I think <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> is pretty crowded and in my opinion, there are
not enough young people there,'' she said. ``All you do in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>
is get behind some large car going 10 miles an hour.''
   Older Americans are a moving lot. The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Bureau</ORGANIZATION> of the Census
calculates that <DATE>last year</DATE>, <PERCENT>5.3 percent</PERCENT> of those over 65 changed
homes, one out of five of them settling in another state.
   From <DATE>1975</DATE> to <DATE>1980</DATE>, more than <PERCENT>9 percent</PERCENT> of those over 60 moved out
of their home cities while another <PERCENT>13.4 percent</PERCENT> moved within their
towns, said <PERSON>Dr. Charles Longino</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>University of Miami</ORGANIZATION> researcher
who spent six years studying the migration.
   Warmer, dryer weather and lifestyle amenities like year-round
golf continue to draw most retirees south and west, said <PERSON>Don Fowles</PERSON>,
a statistician for the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Administration</ORGANIZATION> on Aging in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,
