<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891006-0007 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-06-89 0149EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-PyramidPower     10-06 0812</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Pyramid Power,0840</SECOND>
<HEAD>Pyramids Attract Cultists Who Believe They Hold Mystic Powers</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some chant. Some meditate. Some
dance. Some sit in the lotus position and hum.
   Every year hundreds of devotees of the occult trek to <LOCATION>Giza
Plateau</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> to absorb mystical vibes said to be trapped
inside the pyramids of the pharaohs <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chephren</PERSON> and Mycerinus.
   Pyramid power is said to cure a host of ills, give glimpses into
the future, provide a better night's sleep, even halt aging _ all
for the price of admission, three Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$1.20</MONEY>).
   Until now.
   Under new rules, pyramid groupies are going to have to pay more
_ a lot more.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s director general, said groups of up
to 15 now are allowed ``to meditate or seek extrasensory powers''
in the pyramids for 1,000 Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$400</MONEY>) and only outside
normal tourist hours. Each extra participant pays <MONEY>50 pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$20</MONEY>).
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said seven to eight groups ask permission each month to
conduct seances inside the pyramids. Most want either to spend the
night inside or to enter at the first rays of dawn.
   ``In the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and elsewhere you have a lot of people with
problems, and these people are seeking solutions. They look to the
supernatural, and they think of the pyramids,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``But we can't let these groups interfere with tourists wanting
to look at the pyramids from a historical or architectural
standpoint.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said the most active pyramid-visiting mystical groups in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> are several from <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and from
the <ORGANIZATION>Edgar Cayce Foundation of Virginia Beach</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, named after the
American psychic who died in <DATE>1945</DATE>. Cayce taught that the secrets of
Atlantis and knowledge of the future are buried under the right
front paw of the Sphinx at the foot of <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>.
   In addition to Americans,theme cruises are organized in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
and growing numbers of Japanese tours come to <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> especially to
``tap pyramid power,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``This pyramid power stuff is really big,'' he said. ``People
want to believe in magic, and big structures give an air of magic.
I'm sure if I called myself the Pyramid Prophet I could have a
following larger than the most famous Indian guru.''
   Built about 4,600 years ago, the pyramids remain enigmas to
scientists as well as to seekers of the unknown.
   The first person to enter the Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> in
post-pharaonic times was the caliph of <LOCATION>Baghdad</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Abdullah</PERSON> al-Ma'mun,
in 820 A.D. He forced his way in by heating rocks, then breaking
them by pouring on vinegar.
   As generations of scientists and tourists, eccentrics and
treasure hunters followed him, pyramid mystique grew over the ages.
   Perhaps the most famous personality to enter in search of the
occult was <PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>, who spent the night of <DATE>Aug. 12,
1799</DATE>, inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' pyramid and emerged ashen and shaken.
   He went to his grave in <DATE>1821</DATE> without telling what he experienced.
   ``No! What's the use,'' <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON> was said to have told a friend.
``You wouldn't believe me anyway.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said many people, especially in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, have
ideas and theories about the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids, particularly <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>'
Great Pyramid.
   ``They read that <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> is made of 2.3 million blocks, each one
weighing 2{ tons to 15 tons, each side at an angle of 51 degrees,
50 minutes and 35 seconds,'' he said.
   ``They think nobody on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> could have built this. That the
pyramids were built by people from outer space, or survivors from
the lost continent of Atlantis.
   ``They never look at what's attached to the pyramids, the
structures, the organization necessary to build them, the cult of
the king.''
   He said more than 200 books about pyramid power have been
published in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, ``but fewer than half a dozen
contain any science of value.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>, who has a doctorate in Egyptology from the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> and has lectured throughout <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> about the
pyramids, said he'd never heard of pyramid power until he went
there in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   ``I was speaking to an audience in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, and as I
began to talk everyone in the front row held a pyramid above his
head. I asked, `What are you doing?,' and they explained about
power trapped inside the shape of a pyramid.
   ``OK. I try to be open-minded. When I returned, I tried some
experiments.''
   The first was to test the theory that pyramids can preserve
bodies.
   ``I bought some meat and put part of it in my office, part
inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>. The meat inside my office lasted longer than inside
the pyramid. That was one (myth) down.
   ``If the ancient Egyptians knew that flesh could be preserved by
placing a corpse under a pyramid, then why did they invent
mummification?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102289-0107 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 124143 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 22, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 35; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
762 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
PYRAMIDS PULL FAITHFUL SEEKING MYSTICAL VIBES TO EGYPT'S GIZA PLATEAU; 
</P>
<P>
OCCULT: HUNDREDS OF DEVOTEES TRAVELING TO GIZA WILL NOW HAVE TO PAY A LOT MORE 
TO GET THEIR BLAST OF PYRAMID POWER. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MIMI MANN, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Some chant. Some meditate. Some dance. Some sit in the lotus position and hum. 
</P>
<P>
Every year hundreds of devotees of the occult travel to <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> 
to absorb mystical vibes said to be trapped inside the pyramids of the <LOCATION>Pharaohs 
Cheops</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chephren</PERSON> and Mycerinus. 
</P>
<P>
Pyramid power is said to cure a host of ills, give glimpses into the future, 
provide a better night's sleep, even halt aging -- all for the price of 
admission, three Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$1.20</MONEY>). 
</P>
<P>
Until now. 
</P>
<P>
Under new rules, pyramid groupies are going to have to pay more -- a lot more. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s director general, said groups of up to 15 now are 
allowed "to meditate or seek extrasensory powers" in the pyramids for 1,000 
Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$400</MONEY>) and only outside normal tourist hours. Each extra 
participant pays <MONEY>50 pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$20</MONEY>). 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said seven to eight groups ask permission each month to conduct seances 
inside the pyramids. Most want either to spend the night inside or to enter at 
the first rays of dawn. 
</P>
<P>
"In the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and elsewhere you have a lot of people with problems, and these 
people are seeking solutions. They look to the supernatural, and they think of 
the pyramids," <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"But we can't let these groups interfere with tourists wanting to look at the 
pyramids from a historical or architectural standpoint." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said the most active pyramid-visiting mystical groups in the <LOCATION>United 
States</LOCATION> are several from <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and from the <ORGANIZATION>Edgar Cayce 
Foundation of Virginia Beach</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, named after the American psychic who died in 
<DATE>1945</DATE>. Cayce taught that the secrets of Atlantis and knowledge of the future are 
buried under the right front paw of the Sphinx at the foot of <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In addition to Americans, theme cruises are organized in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> and growing 
numbers of Japanese tours come to <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> especially to "tap pyramid power," 
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
"This pyramid power stuff is really big," he said. "People want to believe in 
magic, and big structures give an air of magic. I'm sure if I called myself the 
Pyramid Prophet I could have a following larger than the most famous Indian 
guru." 
</P>
<P>
Built about 4,600 years ago, the pyramids remain enigmas to scientists as well 
as to seekers of the unknown. 
</P>
<P>
The first person to enter the Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> in post-Pharaonic times 
was the caliph of <LOCATION>Baghdad</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Abdullah</PERSON> al-Ma'mun, in AD 820. He forced his way in 
by heating rocks, then breaking them by pouring on vinegar. 
</P>
<P>
As generations of scientists and tourists, eccentrics and treasure hunters 
followed him, pyramid mystique grew over the ages. 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps the most famous personality to enter in search of the occult was 
<PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>, who spent the night of <DATE>Aug. 12, 1799</DATE>, inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' 
pyramid and emerged ashen and shaken. 
</P>
<P>
He went to his grave in <DATE>1821</DATE> without telling what he experienced. 
</P>
<P>
"No! What's the use," <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON> was said to have told a friend. "You wouldn't 
believe me anyway." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said many people, especially in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, have ideas and 
theories about the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids, particularly <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' Great Pyramid. 
</P>
<P>
"They read that <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> is made of 2.3 million blocks, each one weighing 2 1/2 
tons to 15 tons, each side at an angle of 51 degrees, 50 minutes and 35 
seconds," he said. 
</P>
<P>
"They think nobody on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> could have built this. That the pyramids were built 
by people from outer space, or survivors from the lost continent of Atlantis. 
</P>
<P>
"They never look at what's attached to the pyramids, the structures, the 
organization necessary to build them, the cult of the king." 
</P>
<P>
He said more than 200 books about pyramid power have been published in the 
<LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, "but fewer than half a dozen contain any science of value." 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>, who has a doctorate in Egyptology from the <ORGANIZATION>University of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> 
and has lectured throughout <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> about the pyramids, said he had never 
heard of pyramid power until he went there in <DATE>1977</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"I was speaking to an audience in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, and as I began to talk 
everyone in the front row held a pyramid above his head. I asked, 'What are you 
doing?' and they explained about power trapped inside the shape of a pyramid. 
</P>
<P>
"OK. I try to be open-minded. When I returned, I tried some experiments." 
</P>
<P>
The first was to test the theory that pyramids can preserve bodies. 
</P>
<P>
"I bought some meat and put part of it in my office, part inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>. The 
meat inside my office lasted longer than inside the pyramid. That was one 
(myth) down. 
</P>
<P>
"If the ancient Egyptians knew that flesh could be preserved by placing a 
corpse under a pyramid, then why did they invent mummification?" 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890929-0209 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-29-89 1310EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i AM-PyramidPower Adv06   09-29 0827</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Pyramid Power, Adv 06,0853</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv06</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Friday AMs, Oct. 6, and thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Pyramids Attract Cultists Who Believe They Hold Mystic Powers</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Some chant. Some meditate. Some
dance. Some sit in the lotus position and hum.
   Every year hundreds of devotees of the occult trek to <LOCATION>Giza
Plateau</LOCATION> near <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> to absorb mystical vibes said to be trapped
inside the pyramids of the pharaohs <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chephren</PERSON> and Mycerinus.
   Pyramid power is said to cure a host of ills, give glimpses into
the future, provide a better night's sleep, even halt aging _ all
for the price of admission, three Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$1.20</MONEY>).
   Until now.
   Under new rules, pyramid groupies are going to have to pay more
_ a lot more.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s director general, said groups of up
to 15 now are allowed ``to meditate or seek extrasensory powers''
in the pyramids for 1,000 Egyptian pounds (<MONEY>$400</MONEY>) and only outside
normal tourist hours. Each extra participant pays <MONEY>50 pounds</MONEY> (<MONEY>$20</MONEY>).
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said seven to eight groups ask permission each month to
conduct seances inside the pyramids. Most want either to spend the
night inside or to enter at the first rays of dawn.
   ``In the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and elsewhere you have a lot of people with
problems, and these people are seeking solutions. They look to the
supernatural, and they think of the pyramids,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``But we can't let these groups interfere with tourists wanting
to look at the pyramids from a historical or architectural
standpoint.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said the most active pyramid-visiting mystical groups in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> are several from <LOCATION>Santa Barbara</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, and from
the <ORGANIZATION>Edgar Cayce Foundation of Virginia Beach</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, named after the
American psychic who died in <DATE>1945</DATE>. Cayce taught that the secrets of
Atlantis and knowledge of the future are buried under the right
front paw of the Sphinx at the foot of <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>.
   In addition to Americans, theme cruises are organized in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>
and growing numbers of Japanese tours come to <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> especially to
``tap pyramid power,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``This pyramid power stuff is really big,'' he said. ``People
want to believe in magic, and big structures give an air of magic.
I'm sure if I called myself the Pyramid Prophet I could have a
following larger than the most famous Indian guru.''
   Built about 4,600 years ago, the pyramids remain enigmas to
scientists as well as to seekers of the unknown.
   The first person to enter the Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> in
post-pharaonic times was the caliph of <LOCATION>Baghdad</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Abdullah</PERSON> al-Ma'mun,
in 820 A.D. He forced his way in by heating rocks, then breaking
them by pouring on vinegar.
   As generations of scientists and tourists, eccentrics and
treasure hunters followed him, pyramid mystique grew over the ages.
   Perhaps the most famous personality to enter in search of the
occult was <PERSON>Napoleon Bonaparte</PERSON>, who spent the night of <DATE>Aug. 12,
1799</DATE>, inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' pyramid and emerged ashen and shaken.
   He went to his grave in <DATE>1821</DATE> without telling what he experienced.
   ``No! What's the use,'' <PERSON>Napoleon</PERSON> was said to have told a friend.
``You wouldn't believe me anyway.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said many people, especially in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, have
ideas and theories about the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids, particularly <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>'
Great Pyramid.
   ``They read that <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> is made of 2.3 million blocks, each one
weighing 2{ tons to 15 tons, each side at an angle of 51 degrees,
50 minutes and 35 seconds,'' he said.
   ``They think nobody on <LOCATION>Earth</LOCATION> could have built this. That the
pyramids were built by people from outer space, or survivors from
the lost continent of Atlantis.
   ``They never look at what's attached to the pyramids, the
structures, the organization necessary to build them, the cult of
the king.''
   He said more than 200 books about pyramid power have been
published in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, ``but fewer than half a dozen
contain any science of value.''
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>, who has a doctorate in Egyptology from the <ORGANIZATION>University of
Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION> and has lectured throughout <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> about the
pyramids, said he'd never heard of pyramid power until he went
there in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   ``I was speaking to an audience in <LOCATION>Hartford</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION>, and as I
began to talk everyone in the front row held a pyramid above his
head. I asked, `What are you doing?,' and they explained about
power trapped inside the shape of a pyramid.
   ``OK. I try to be open-minded. When I returned, I tried some
experiments.''
   The first was to test the theory that pyramids can preserve
bodies.
   ``I bought some meat and put part of it in my office, part
inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>. The meat inside my office lasted longer than inside
the pyramid. That was one (myth) down.
   ``If the ancient Egyptians knew that flesh could be preserved by
placing a corpse under a pyramid, then why did they invent
mummification?''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Friday AMs, Oct. 6</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901010-0018 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-10-90 0044EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Egypt-EternalBoss Bjt   10-10 0600</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Egypt-Eternal Boss, Bjt,0741</SECOND>
<HEAD>Workers' Paradise in Ancient Egypt: Eternity with the Boss</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Even death couldn't free some workers
from their bosses, archaeologists are finding in a newly discovered
cemetery near the pyramids.
   It's the first burial ground ever found for the Egyptian working
man of 45 centuries ago.
   Five other cemeteries with 4,000 tombs flank the pyramids, on
the horizon above. But all 4,000 were reserved for royalty, their
families and officials, said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director-general of
antiquities for the pyramids area and the new dig's excavation
chief.
   ``What we haven't found until now is the working class,'' said
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>. ``We were shocked when we looked at inscriptions of who was
buried in the new tombs. Overseers holding their sticks. And
behind, skeletons of workers.''
   He said it appears the workers were members of the foremen's
crews.
   The first eight tombs, three miles south of the Sphinx, lie at
the base of sand hills stretching endlessly into the desert. <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>
said the cemetery undoubtedly extends deep into the dunes.
   Tombs date from the fourth dynasty - 4,600 years ago when the
<LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids were built - until the sixth, 300 years later. It's a
mysterious period when legend says workers grew tired of almighty
pharaohs and of building pyramids for them.
   Because no middle-class burials had been discovered on sacred
<LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> plateau, some Egyptologists have theorized that the afterlife
was perceived as off-limits to the working man. But the new
cemetery proves that pharaonic blue-collar workers prepared for
eternity as their betters did, being buried with amulets, limestone
tablets, offering tables, pottery vessels and more.
   The largest tomb, built for a fifth-dynasty overseer named
Ptah-Shepses, is 20 feet by 6{ feet with an arched ceiling.
   To the rear of the tomb, in a honeycomb of compartments,
excavators found six skeletons buried in the fetal position. <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>
said they were members of one work crew.
   Ancient Egyptians didn't practice human sacrifice, so the
workers were not killed and buried at the same time as their
bosses. And <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said there's no indication so far how a foreman
chose the workers to be buried near him.
   ``Perhaps they were his favorites. Or perhaps we'll find others
when we keep digging,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. ``We have no idea how many
people an overseer would have had on his staff.''
   Foremen handled day-to-day administration of the pharaohs'
estates, with responsibilities comparable to farm managers or
assembly-line supervisors in today's world. ``They dressed better,
ate better and wanted better tombs than the men who worked for
them,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``They looked at the pyramids and the fancy tombs of the
officials. They knew they couldn't afford such luxury. Still they
wanted a nice place to spend eternity.''
   More information about the ancient blue-collar workers will come
from medical tests Egyptian doctors are performing on the
skeletons. Data is expected to indicate the workers' general
appearance, their height and weight, what they ate, what diseases
bothered them, even what killed them.
   In <DATE>1987</DATE>, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> and Egyptologist <PERSON>Mark Lehner</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Yale University</ORGANIZATION>
began a search for homes of workers who built the three <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION>
pyramids. At a site some distance from the monuments, they
uncovered ruins of a business center and other artifacts.
   They stopped excavating in early <DATE>1988</DATE>. The recently discovered
tombs lay undetected only a few feet away.
   But early last <DATE>summer</DATE>, a tourist hired a saddle horse for a ride
around the pyramids. During the tour her horse fell through the
sand, ending on top of what proved to be the roof of the first
tomb.
   Nobody got the tourist's name, and chances are she still doesn't
know her outing made history.
   For years, riders heading for the most spectacular view of the
pyramids have passed in front of the Sphinx and through an ancient
stone gate into the desert.
   No records existed to explain the gate.
   But ``once we found the cemetery we understood,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
``The gate divided the world of the pharaohs from the world of the
average man.''
   He explained that the foremen and their crews lived and were
buried in their own world behind the gate. By day they passed
through the gate into their pharaoh's sacred world, then returned
at sunset to work on their own tombs.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890720-0211 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-20-89 0954EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a i PM-UnfoundTreasures Adv27   07-20 0983</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Unfound Treasures, Adv 27,1014</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv27</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Thurs PMs July 27 or Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Much of Ancient Egyptian World Remains Undiscovered</HEAD>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAIRO, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Treasures even greater than those in <LOCATION>King
Tut</LOCATION>'s tomb may still be lying under the desert sands of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   ``When I'm asked if there's another Tut's tomb out there, I
always answer at least one, maybe more,'' said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director
of the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids area outside <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> and the huge ancient
cemetery of <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, 11 miles to the south.
   ``My guess is we've found no more than <PERCENT>30 percent</PERCENT> of what's
buried. After all, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> is <PERCENT>97 percent</PERCENT> desert. ... We can't begin to
imagine what the sands have hidden.''
   The tomb of <ORGANIZATION>Pharaoh Tutankhamun _ King Tut</ORGANIZATION> _ was found almost
intact in <DATE>1922</DATE> by the British archaeologist <PERSON>Howard Carter</PERSON>.
   It took <PERSON>Carter</PERSON> 11 years more to document the hoard of gold,
semiprecious stones, furniture and knickknacks stuffed into the
makeshift tomb dug into the hills of southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s Valley of the
<LOCATION>Kings</LOCATION>.
   But <PERSON>Tutankhamun</PERSON> was a lesser king and the discovery of his tomb
left archaeologists to wonder what treasures might have accompanied
ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s great monarchs into the afterlife.
   Some intriguing trophies have eluded both early archaeologists
and their modern successors:
   _Mummies and relics of <LOCATION>Pharaoh Cheops</LOCATION>, whose pyramid on <LOCATION>Giza
Plateau</LOCATION> is among the world's best-known monuments.
   _The tomb of the architect Imhotep at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, where more than
4,600 years ago he built for Pharaoh Zozer a step pyramid, an
architectural feat that quickly evolved into the true pyramid.
Generations of later Egyptians worshipped Imhotep as a god.
   _At least seven tombs of royalty and officials from the <LOCATION>New
Kingdom</LOCATION>, the era of Tutankhamun and the <PERSON>Ramses</PERSON> line.
   _The tomb of Alexander the Great, the young Macedonian conqueror
who died at the age of 33 in 323 <ORGANIZATION>B.C. Records</ORGANIZATION> say he wanted to be
buried in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Siwa Oasis</LOCATION>, near <LOCATION>Libya</LOCATION>, but finally was encased in
a gold coffin in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION> city he founded.
   _The 50,000-man army of Persian conqueror Cambyses, which
vanished in a sandstorm in 525 B.C. while en route to <LOCATION>Siwa</LOCATION> to punish
the powerful priests of the temple of the <ORGANIZATION>Siwan Oracle</ORGANIZATION>.
   Egyptian officials realize the historical value that any of those
finds would entail. But the mammoth job of preserving what is said
already to be the world's greatest national storehouse of
antiquities has halted treasure hunts.
   ``I'm trying to keep what's standing, standing,'' said <PERSON>Sayed
Tawfik</PERSON>, chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>. ``What
I'd like to do is to keep what's buried, buried until we can deal
with it. It's usually safer for the pieces not to be exposed to
modern pollutants.''
   As <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s population rapidly expands, however, roadways, gas
lines and housing projects unearth a vast ancient legacy just
beneath the ground. Often, excavations are rescue missions.
   Archaeological work in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> generally is restricted to the
cooler winter months, and last season's work was filled with
surprises. Giza director <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said the results give a glimpse of
what lies ahead when archaeologists begin anew in <DATE>September</DATE>.
   In <DATE>January</DATE> five magnificent statues that rival the loveliest
artwork the ancient Egyptians produced were unearthed in a pit
beneath the tourist-trampled courtyard of <ORGANIZATION>Luxor Temple</ORGANIZATION>. Seventeen
more statues, many broken, later were discovered in the cache.
   In <DATE>March</DATE> a mummy of a young woman, her <PERSON>Mona Lisa</PERSON> smile frozen in
a gypsum mask, was found on <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> Plateau a few feet from a roadway
through the pyramids.
   Other discoveries ranged from gold to fortresses, some found on
sites once impenetrable except by camel or donkey, now accessible by
paved roads.
   One area to be surveyed in the fall is <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s East
Cemetery, a Pharaonic burial ground for royalty and officials beside
<LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> pyramid.
   ``I'm sure we're going to find an intact burial of a prince or
official, because the area never has been excavated properly,''
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``In <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>, where we know Imhotep is buried, you don't even
need to have shovels and picks to find tombs. You can just use your
hands, dig in the sand. They're there.''
   Modern man owes rich finds to the ingenuity of ancient priests,
who reburied important pieces to ensure survival during politically
troubled times, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. These caches, which may explain the
<ORGANIZATION>Luxor Temple</ORGANIZATION> statues, give clues to what may still be hidden.
   He believes the pyramids area contains at least one major cache
from the reign of Old Kingdom Pharaoh <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, whose relics include
the world's largest pyramid, a full-sized boat and an ivory statue
so small it can be held between two fingers.
   ``I think out there is <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' mummy, maybe statues, maybe
personal items,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   ``Four priests were in charge of their safety, but in the next
dynasty (after <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>) his memory soured. There was a revolt. His
monuments were damaged, perhaps because he made himself a god.''
   Hawass believes that like the <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION> find the <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> discovery
will be accidental.
   ``We have magnificent statues of his successors (and) delicate
funerary items of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' mother, ... so we know such things did
exist,'' he said.
   ``One day you'll be digging a power line, or cleaning, and there
they'll be.''
   Hawass thinks chance also may locate the long-sought tomb of
Alexander the Great in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>.
   ``We have early descriptions of his tomb, but <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION> has gone
through many changes,'' he said.
   ``We're not going to find the tomb, if it even still exists, by
going after it. We'll find it by accident, when somebody's digging a
foundation for a house or installing sewer lines.''
   Hawass insists that people who think incredible discoveries
remain to be found aren't dealing in fantasy.
   ``We've got too much evidence,'' he said: ``Kings without tombs,
places we know existed but never were found.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv Thurs PMs July 27</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890520-0084 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-05-20-89 1605EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-GreatPyramid     05-20 0533</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Great Pyramid,0548</SECOND>
<HEAD>Great Pyramid Looks Greater After Facelift</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, the most
famous of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s royal tombs, was declared safe for
tourists and reopened <DATE>Saturday</DATE> for the first time in nine months.
   A Dutch woman and an American student were the first of the
scores of tourists who waited under the hot Egyptian sun to tour
the pyramid.
   Since <DATE>August</DATE>, workers had been sealing cracks, reinforcing
limestone slabs for safety and clearing vermin from the inside of
the magnificent structure, which now boasts television monitors.
   The restoration project was the first step in a five-year plan
to transform the pyramid area, including the Sphinx, into an
open-air museum.
   Gasping after the 155-foot climb to the <PERSON>King</PERSON>'s Chamber, <PERSON>Sophie
D'Lang</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Rotterdam</LOCATION> said she and her husband were spending the <DATE>last
day</DATE> of a vacation in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   ``I didn't think we had a chance to see inside <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>,'' said
<PERSON>Mrs. D'Lang</PERSON>, who waited more than three hours for the re-opening.
``I think what they've done is great.''
   <PERSON>Michael Saxton</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Dayton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, said he waited four hours. ``For
me the pyramid has special meaning because of the way it's built.
It's amazing.''
   The Great Pyramid is <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s top tourist attraction, and tourist
officials protested when it was closed <DATE>Aug. 15</DATE>.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION> prevailed with the
argument that newly discovered cracks in blocks lining interior
passages and a half-inch layer of salt on inside walls had to be
fixed without interruption by tourists.
   With a base of 13.1 acres, it stood at 481.4 feet when it was
built 4,600 years ago. Today, it is 31 feet shorter after losing
about a dozen layers and its capstone. It also has lost almost all
its outer facing of hard, white limestone, stripped for use in
stone bridges, irrigation canals, houses, walls and buildings.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director general of the pyramids area, said nothing
had been done to restore the pyramid's interior since it was opened
in the late 1830s.
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said in removing salt from the limestone walls, restorers
found weak and cracking rock throughout the pyramid.
   In the <ORGANIZATION>Grand Gallery</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said, 500 limestone blocks were
restored and 16 granite slabs reinforced with stainless steel bars.
``Some of these slabs were in critical condition,'' he said.
   Cheops' lidless red granite sarcophagus, soiled by the touch of
generations of tourists, was cleaned of soot, grease and other
filth, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   He said insects and rats, which had invaded the pyramid, were
exterminated. Television monitors were installed to ensure that
visitors behave themselves.
   During the renovation, rubble was cleared and lighting added to
a chamber winding 396 feet beneath the pyramid, opening it to
tourists for the first time.
   Of the seven monuments listed as Wonders of the World by Greeks
of the second century <LOCATION>B.C.</LOCATION>, only <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> and the other two large
<LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids remain intact.
   The remaining monuments on the list _ the statue of Zeus in
<LOCATION>Olympia</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Artemis</ORGANIZATION>' temple in <LOCATION>Ephesus</LOCATION>, the Colossus of <LOCATION>Rhodes</LOCATION>, the
mausoleum of <LOCATION>Halicarnassus</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Asia Minor</LOCATION> and the Pharos lighthouse
in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION> _ were destroyed by warfare or earthquakes.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900111-0208 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-11-90 1158EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--TombDiscovery Adv15   01-11 0777</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Tomb Discovery, Adv 15,0794</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv15</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Monday, Jan. 15, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Archaeologists Discover New Tomb in Pyramids' Shadow</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A tomb built 4,300 years ago for a
palace official and his two wives has been found in the shadow of
the <LOCATION>Giza Pyramids</LOCATION>, the first unknown tomb discovered on the plateau
since the mid-1950s.
   ``This is the first time we've seen such a tomb,'' said <PERSON>Zahi
Hawass</PERSON>, director general of the pyramids area. ``We can find no
parallel to this tomb during the Old Kingdom.''
   Giza inspector <PERSON>Mahmoud Hassan Afife</PERSON> found the new tomb in
<DATE>October</DATE> when he chanced upon the edge of a limestone wall. ``We
looked at the old records to see what early excavators had recorded
in this spot. There was nothing.''
   Hieroglyphics revealed the tomb owner's name, that he was a
``purification priest'' who handled religious rituals, and that he
was a palace official.
   Hawass dates it to the end of the <ORGANIZATION>Fifth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>, about 200 years
after the death in <DATE>2528</DATE> B.C. of <LOCATION>Pharaoh Cheops</LOCATION>, builder of the
Great Pyramid.
   Built of limestone blocks, the 26-foot by 66-foot oblong tomb,
called a mastaba, stands over a shaft 23 feet deep that was sealed
with mud bricks after bodies were lowered into it. The mastaba had
no inner chambers.
   On one side, ancient artists carved two false doors with the
owner's name, Per-N-Ankh. The doors face a courtyard with six
limestone columns describing him and his wives <PERSON>Mitrt Nefer</PERSON> and
N-Hwy.
   The winter archaeology season was a month old when Afife found
the tomb, and vigorous excavation has continued since. On a recent
morning, a sandstorm so engulfed the dig that workers used rubber
buckets to shield their heads from the sand. Debris cascaded onto
the tomb's base faster than diggers could dig.
   Suddenly, from deep in a shaft, a workman yelled, ``gumgumah,''
Arabic for ``skull.'' As a man above slowly turned a pulley, a
reddish-gold skull creaked its way up the pit. It appears to be a
female's, in excellent condition.
   Such a find testifies to the site's value. Nearby pits have
yielded piles of pottery shards, bones and wooden pieces that
officials said might be part of a bed or other funerary furniture
to accompany the dead into the afterlife. In an adjacent tomb were
two limestone statues of wives of pharaonic officials.
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said he knew valuable leftovers would emerge from
re-excavation of the vast <ORGANIZATION>Western Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, begun in the fifth year
of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' reign. Officials and their families used the cemetery
over the centuries, building limestone and mud-brick tombs along
avenues of various sizes.
   ``Some Egyptologists thought the area wouldn't give anything
else, but they're wrong. Early excavators were in a hurry, <LOCATION>Indiana</LOCATION>
Jones-style. Some even used dynamite,'' he said. ``This tomb lies
at the edge of the cemetery. Earlier this century archaeologists
dumped their dirt onto these hills without checking to see if
anything interesting lay underneath.
   ``Chances are even more tombs still lie just over there.''
   Excavating leftovers is ``never a waste of time, never
busywork,'' said <PERSON>Amal Samuel</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION>'s chief inspector, who estimates
that as many as 4,000 tombs and pits exist in the area known as the
<ORGANIZATION>Western Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>. ``When people dug in the past they only searched
for treasure. Today, we're looking for history. We never think if
we'll find something or not.''
   Last <DATE>spring</DATE> archaeologists clearing another part of the cemetery
found the well-preserved, gypsum-masked head of a female mummy from
about the same period, her faint smile reminiscent of the <ORGANIZATION>Mona
Lisa's</ORGANIZATION>.
   <ORGANIZATION>Giza Plateau</ORGANIZATION> has two great cemeteries: the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>, between the
Great Pyramid and the <LOCATION>Sphinx</LOCATION>, and the Western, wedged between the
pyramids of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Chephren</ORGANIZATION>. Generally, queens and royal
offspring are buried in the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, officials and their
families in the Western.
   The cemeteries of mastabas were arranged in parallel rows
several feet apart, with ownership planned carefully. Everybody
wanted to be buried in the pyramids area, seeking special benefits
in life after death. Over the years, as demand increased, the
symmetry went askew. Small tombs of officials and priests were
placed among the once neat rows until the area was honeycombed.
   ``We have to think of these cemeteries as a community that
surrounded the king with the same feeling as when he was alive,''
said <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>. ``At the top of his pyramid is the pharaoh, the head
of his country. Around him lay those who would have been near him,
his family and officials. ... Those closest are in the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION>
cemetery, just like in a palace.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Jan. 15</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880610-0144 </DOCNO>
<HL> Sewage Identified As Main Threat To Egypt's Sphinx --- Investigation After Chunk Fell From Ancient Statue Blames Village, Hotel </HL>
<SO> </SO>
<CO> MDEST </CO>
<IN> ENV </IN>
<DATELINE> GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP)  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Specialists investigating why the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> is crumbling say the culprit is sewage from a tacky tourist village and a hotel favored by the rich and famous. 

   Cries of alarm were raised in early <DATE>February</DATE>, after a chunk of limestone fell from the 4,500-year-old statue's right shoulder. 
Suddenly, salt oozing through the limestone statue and previously ignored cracks in its pharaoh's face and lion's body were seen as evidence the monument was near collapse. 

   A committee of specialists from <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> probed, scraped and tested the stone for four months to see what is happening to one of the world's best-known ancient monuments. 

   The answer is quickened decay, and the reason is sewage, said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, an Egyptologist and director general of the pyramids area where the Sphinx has crouched since the <LOCATION>Old Kingdom</LOCATION>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> blamed sewage water flowing freely from the nearby tourist village of Nazlet al-Samman and an inadequate sewage system at the well-known <ORGANIZATION>Mena House Hotel</ORGANIZATION>. 

   Once a sleepy town at the edge of the desert, <ORGANIZATION>Nazlet</ORGANIZATION> al-Samman has mushroomed in the past 20 years with an injection of funds earned by locals in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> oil countries. 
The town boasts an ever-sprouting array of tourist shops selling pharaonic bric-a-brac, with names like <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>' Place, Pharaoh's Perfume Factory and <PERSON>Cleo</PERSON>'s Bazaar. 

   Just to the northwest is the <ORGANIZATION>Mena House Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, built in <DATE>1868</DATE> with 150 rooms to house dignitaries assembled for the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal</ORGANIZATION>. 

   The stately hotel's reputation grew over the decades, as it hosted <PERSON>Charlie Chaplin</PERSON>, British Field Marshal <PERSON>Bernard Montgomery</PERSON>, Presidents <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>, and <ORGANIZATION>Winston Churchill</ORGANIZATION> and others. 
In <DATE>1974</DATE>, 400 rooms were added. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> said that no sewage system was installed to meet the needs of the bustling village and that the hotel's system was inadequate for its expanded size. 
Thus, excess waste water entered the water table and undermined the Sphinx. 

   Before the recent study, <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> said, it was assumed the statue was deteriorating because of changes in the underground water table, caused by the <ORGANIZATION>Aswan High Dam</ORGANIZATION>'s regulation of the <ORGANIZATION>Nile River</ORGANIZATION>'s flow. 

   Now that the cause of the damage is determined, he said, work will begin on repairing it. 

   Egyptian specialists are being joined by others from <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Louisville</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> to formulate a long-term save-the-Sphinx plan. 

   The government already has allocated <MONEY>$2.3 million</MONEY> for a new sewage system aimed at halting the dirty-water flow beneath and around the Sphinx, <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> said. 

   A committee set up to oversee repairs met yesterday and approved plans to have a masonry support of limestone blocks laid just below where the chunk of rock fell in <DATE>February</DATE>, then to replace the rock on <DATE>July 9</DATE>. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> said restoration work in recent years, especially an effort that began in <DATE>1982</DATE> and that was stopped when the latest piece fell, didn't match ancient attempts to protect the monument. 
The first on record was a patch-up campaign that began 1,000 years after the Sphinx was created about 2,500 B.C. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Hawass</PERSON> said cement used to secure loose rocks after <DATE>1982</DATE> had turned the limestone to powder. 
"The cement didn't allow the rocks to breathe," he said. 
"Now we're removing all the cement and testing gypsum mixed with rocks from <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> itself to see if the mix can't protect sensitive areas." 

   The team of local and foreign specialists also is to study the effects on the Sphinx of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>'s air pollution, which on most days can be seen from <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> hovering in layers above the city of 12 million. 

   Next to the <LOCATION>Cheops Pyramid</LOCATION>, the Sphinx is the most popular among <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s thousands of monuments. 
But as Egyptians laugh at many of the modern world's tribulations, they have chuckled at the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s sewage problem through newspaper cartoons. 

   In one cartoon, the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> has lost his ever-present subtle smile and says, "I don't care whether they call it waste water or sewage runoff, this stuff stinks." 

   In another cartoon, pharaohs <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chephren</PERSON> and Mycerinus, builders of the world's three most famous pyramids on the plateau behind the Sphinx, stand before an immigration officer, obviously ready to leave town. 
"We don't care what country you choose," one pharoah says, "as long as it has a sewage system." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880919-0227 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-19-88 1249EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--PyramidRehab Adv22   09-19 0666</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--Pyramid Rehab, Adv 22,0694</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv22</NOTE>
<NOTE>For release Thursday, Sept. 22, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Restorers Tackle Massive Great Pyramid for First Time</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, pocked
by thousands of years of vandalism and stone-robbing, is finally
getting a facelift.
   The effort to clean rubbish from between the massive limestone
blocks and to tighten loose rocks marks the first restoration work
ever attempted on the outside of the sole survivor of the ancient
world's Seven Wonders.
   ``This is not just cosmetic work,'' said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, the
<ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>'s director-general for the
pyramids area. ``We're afraid unless we do something to stabilize
the outer stones, there could be a tragedy.
   ``People have a tendency to think that pyramids will be here
forever because they're so massive, but each is suffering from wind
and sand erosion, rain and salt (and) ... to a great extent because
of the hands of man.''
   Work began inside the <LOCATION>Great Pyramid</LOCATION> <DATE>last winter</DATE> to remove salt
that oozed through the limestone and accumulated along passageway
walls. The work on the outside began in late <DATE>August</DATE>.
   From a distance, the pyramid appears fine. Close up, it's
obviously far from healthy. Many of the massive blocks, weighing an
average 2{ tons, have eroded or disappeared. Others hang
precariously on uneven ledges.
   In <DATE>1976</DATE>, a stone weighing several tons fell from the southern
side. No one was injured because tourists were being kept away
during a dignitary's visit, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. ``We chose to begin
(restoration) with <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> Pyramid first, because we know there's a
chance more stones will fall.''
   When put in place 4,600 years ago, the estimated 2.3 million
blocks were assembled with such skill that only a thin sheet of
paper would pass between.
   The new project aims at duplicating such precision. Workers
skilled in climbing scurry over the rocks, binding loose stones
with natural mortar like that used by the ancients and repairing
damage caused by millenia of nesting birds, desert animals and
human ravagers.
   Historical records and legends indicate the first man-made
damage occurred as early as 500 years after the death of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>,
the second pharaoh of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Fourth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>. The Egyptians
were in revolt against tyrannical and oppressive practices of the
past, hacking and destroying statues and monuments from the earlier
days of the pharaohs.
   Less than a century later, the 12th-dynasty <PERSON>Pharoah Amenemhet</PERSON>
took many stones from <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' pyramid complex to build one for
himself at el-Lisht, south of <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>. Teams from <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
Metropolitan Museum, who excavated <PERSON>Amenemhet</PERSON>'s pyramid, found
hundreds of the decorated pieces.
   Nobody knows when or why, but the Great Pyramid at some time
lost 30 feet of height, leaving it still enormous at almost 453
feet. Its outer surface originally was covered with a protective
layer of fine, hard limestone, only traces of which survived
desecration and looting.
   Thousands of its stones were stolen over time, but the pyramid
remained structurally intact until the late ninth century, writes
<PERSON>I.E.S. Edwards</PERSON>, the British Egyptologist acknowledged as the
authority on Egyptian pyramids.
   At that time, Arab raiders broke a large hole just below the
main entrance and entered the monument in a vain search for
treasure, <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> wrote in his showpiece work ``The Pyramids of
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.''
   ``Subsequently it became a copious and convenient quarry,
providing the stone required for bridges over irrigation canals,
houses, walls and other buildings in the neighborhood of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>,'' he wrote.
   In the <DATE>early 19th century</DATE>, the <PERSON>Albanian Mohammed Ali</PERSON>, credited
with creating the modern Egyptian state as part of the <ORGANIZATION>Ottoman
Empire</ORGANIZATION>, thought nothing of using blocks from <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> and other
pyramids for construction.
   The English Egyptologist <PERSON>Flinders Petrie</PERSON> wrote in the 1880s of
watching as a steady stream of camels, hundreds daily, carried
massive blocks into <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> from nearby Abu Rawash pyramid, built by
<ORGANIZATION>Cheops</ORGANIZATION>' successor Djedefre.
   Today the pyramid area is littered with toppled building blocks.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sept. 22</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880609-0002 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-09-88 2341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Sphinx-Sewage     06-09 0738</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Sphinx-Sewage,0758</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sewage Identified As Sphinx's Chief Threat</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Friday AMs report.</NOTE>
<HEAD>An AP Extra</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Experts investigating why the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>
is crumbling say the culprit is sewage from a tacky tourist village
and a hotel favored by the rich and famous.
   Cries of alarm were raised in early <DATE>February</DATE> after a chunk of
limestone fell from the 4,500-year-old statue's right shoulder.
Suddenly, salt oozing through the limestone statue and previously
ignored cracks in its pharaoh's face and lion's body were seen as
evidence the monument was near collapse.
   A committee of specialists from <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION> probed, scraped and tested the stone for four months to see
what is happening to one of the world's best-known ancient
monuments.
   The answer is quickened decay, and the reason is sewage, said
<PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, an Egyptologist and director general of the pyramids
area where the Sphinx has crouched since the <LOCATION>Old Kingdom</LOCATION>.
   Hawass blamed sewage water flowing freely from the nearby
tourist village of Nazlet al-Samman and an inadequate sewage system
at the well-known <ORGANIZATION>Mena House Hotel</ORGANIZATION>.
   Once a sleepy town at the edge of the desert, <ORGANIZATION>Nazlet</ORGANIZATION> al-Samman
has mushroomed in the last 20 years with an injection of funds
earned by locals in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> oil countries. The town boasts
an ever-sprouting array of tourist shops selling pharaonic
bric-a-brac, with names like <PERSON>Moses</PERSON>' Place, Pharaoh's Perfume
Factory and <PERSON>Cleo</PERSON>'s Bazaar.
   Just to the northwest, the <ORGANIZATION>Mena House</ORGANIZATION> was built in <DATE>1868</DATE> to house
dignitaries assembled for the opening of the <ORGANIZATION>Suez Canal</ORGANIZATION>.
   The stately hotel's reputation grew over the decades as it
hosted <PERSON>Charlie Chaplin</PERSON>, British Field Marshal <PERSON>Bernard Montgomery</PERSON>,
Presidents <PERSON>Franklin D. Roosevelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jimmy Carter</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Winston
Churchill</ORGANIZATION> and others. In <DATE>1974</DATE>, 400 rooms were added to the original
150.
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said no sewage system was installed to meet the needs of
the bustling village, and the hotel's system was inadequate for its
expanded size. Thus, excess waste water entered the water table and
undermined the Sphinx.
   Before the recent study, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said, it was assumed the statue
was deteriorating due to changes in the underground water table,
caused by the <ORGANIZATION>Aswan High Dam</ORGANIZATION>'s regulation of the <ORGANIZATION>Nile River</ORGANIZATION>'s flow.
   Now that the cause of the damage is determined, he said, work
will begin on repairing it.
   Egyptian experts are being joined by others from <LOCATION>West Germany</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>University of Louisville</ORGANIZATION> in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to
formulate a long-term save-the-Sphinx plan.
   The government already has allocated <MONEY>$2.3 million</MONEY> for a new
sewage system aimed at halting the dirty-water flow beneath and
around the Sphinx, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   A committee set up to oversee repairs met <DATE>Thursday</DATE> and approved
plans to have a masonry support of limestone blocks laid just below
where the chunk of rock fell in <DATE>February</DATE>, then to replace the rock
on <DATE>July 9</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said restoration work in recent years, especially an
effort that began in <DATE>1982</DATE> and was stopped when the latest piece
fell, did not match ancient attempts to protect the monument. The
first on record was a patch-up campaign that began 1,000 years
after the Sphinx was created about 2,500 <PERSON>B.C.
   Hawass</PERSON> said cement used to secure loose rocks after <DATE>1982</DATE> had
turned the limestone to powder. ``The cement didn't allow the rocks
to breathe. Now we're removing all the cement and testing gypsum
mixed with rocks from <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> itself to see if the mix can't
protect sensitive areas.''
   The team of local and foreign experts also is to study the
effects on the Sphinx of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>'s air pollution, which on most days
can be seen from <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> hovering in layers over the city of 12
million.
   Next to the <LOCATION>Cheops Pyramid</LOCATION>, the Sphinx is the most popular among
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s thousands of monuments. But as Egyptians laugh at many of
the modern world's tribulations, they have chuckled at the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s
sewage problem through newspaper cartoons.
   In one cartoon, the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> has lost his ever-present subtle
smile. He says: ``I don't care whether they call it waste water or
sewage runoff, this stuff stinks.''
   In another, pharaohs <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Chephren</PERSON> and Mycerinus, builders of
the world's three most famous pyramids on the plateau behind the
Sphinx, stand before an immigration officer, obviously ready to
leave town.
   ``We don't care what country you choose,'' one pharoah says,
``as long as it has a sewage system.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900323-0126 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-23-90 2101EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Cheops     03-23 0522</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Cheops,0540</SECOND>
<HEAD>Sewer Workers Discover Remains of Cheops' Long-Lost Temple</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   NAZLETT EL-SAMMAN, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> (AP) _ Sewer workers have discovered
remains of a temple that <PERSON>Pharaoh Cheops</PERSON> built for his funeral 4,600
years ago, and Egyptologists are hoping it will tell them more
about the mysterious pharaoh of the <LOCATION>Great Pyramid</LOCATION>.
   The discovery this month of Cheop's <ORGANIZATION>Valley Temple</ORGANIZATION> confirms
theories about the layout of <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> for the 70-year period in
which the pharaoh, his son and grandson built their three pyramids
and monuments nearby.
   Nazlett el-Samman lies at the foot of the plateau, facing the
Sphinx, and sewage from the village often is mentioned as a cause
of the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s dangerous deterioration. A U.S.-financed sewage
project began last year, and Egyptologists were assigned to monitor
construction because of the probability of finding antiquities.
   They were on hand in early <DATE>March</DATE> as diggers began uncovering
mammoth granite and limestone blocks, a flint knife, Roman brick
walls and other relics.
   By mid-March, more remains were turning up, and finally the main
prize _ a 59-foot-long row of basalt rocks. The experts identified
it as the floor for <ORGANIZATION>Cheops' Valley Temple</ORGANIZATION>.
   Because basalt is difficult to carve and expensive, the stone
was reserved for royal use, often as flooring for sacred places.
   Although his pyramid was the largest ever built, <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> left few
other glimpses of his life or his 23-year reign, which ended in
<DATE>2528</DATE> B.C.
   ``With what we're finding now, we can piece together <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>'
history and reconstruct how this part of the pyramids area would
have looked,'' said <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities
Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   The newly found ruins lie 13 feet below street level, partially
covered with sewage.
   Getting to them will not be easy. Diggers already are excavating
two Roman-era sites in a Nazlett el-Samman alley only a foot from
village houses. Archaeologists have to contend with children at
play, donkeys and angry villagers worried that antiquities
officials might invoke their legal authority to force them from
their houses.
   <ORGANIZATION>Cheops' Valley Temple</ORGANIZATION> is proving an even greater challenge.
Engineers for the sewer project are pumping water from the drainage
ditch where the basalt flooring was found.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Giza Pyramids</ORGANIZATION> and the structures around them are thought by
some Egyptologists to be part of an elaborate blueprint for the
dead, precisely planned and executed. But their exact roles in the
death and resurrection of the pharaohs are debated.
   Burial was an elaborate ritual to ensure that neither the
pharaoh nor <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> would ever die.
   The journey to eternity began in the <ORGANIZATION>Valley Temple</ORGANIZATION>, where the
pharaoh's body was taken for ritual purification, perhaps
embalming. For the final rituals, the body was carried up the long
causeway to a mortuary temple next to the pyramid.
   Early travelers' descriptions of the pyramids area had given
modern egyptogists a good idea where <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' temple should be found.
   In the <DATE>fifth century B.C.</DATE>, the Greek Herodotus wrote that he saw
<LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' causeway, covered and decorated with carved animal scenes.
The German scholar <PERSON>Karl Richard Lepsius</PERSON> said only traces remained
of the ruined causeway by the early <DATE>1840s</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880302-0182 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-02-88 1712EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i AM-Sphinx     03-02 0567</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Sphinx,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Fallen Stone Causes Political Furor Over Antiquities</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The falling of a piece of rock from
the crumbling body of the Sphinx has caused an avalanche of debate
over the future of the 4,600-year-old monument and <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s other
ancient treasures.
   The principal casualty of the uproar has been <PERSON>Ahmed Kadry</PERSON>,
formerly chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>.
   Kadry lost his job after accusing his boss, Culture Minister
<PERSON>Farouk Hosni</PERSON>, of staging the falling rock incident to reflect badly
on <ORGANIZATION>Kadry</ORGANIZATION>'s stewardship of the Sphinx and the other relics of
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s rich past. Hosni did not reply to the accusation.
   The limestone slab fell from the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s right shoulder on <DATE>Feb.
7</DATE>, six days after a sandstorm buffeted <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>.
   A restoration plan is in the works. The Sphinx has been fitted
with sandbags for support and scaffolding to help in the early
stages of the effort, and a committee of experts has taken rock
samples for analysis to help decide what steps to take.
   The Sphinx, which is 66 feet high and 160 feet long, has the
head of a pharaoh and the body of a crouching lion. Many
Egyptologists think the face is that of <LOCATION>Chephren</LOCATION>, son of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> and
builder of the second pyramid on <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> next to <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' Great
Pyramid.
   A similiar accident six years ago brought down <ORGANIZATION>Kadry</ORGANIZATION>'s
predecessor, <PERSON>Fouad Oraby</PERSON>, and a Sphinx-restoration project that
<PERSON>Kadry</PERSON> began as antiquities chairman remained unfinished when the
latest rock fell.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, general director of the pyramids area and
archaeology adviser to <LOCATION>Hosni</LOCATION>, will direct the latest restoraton and
conservation efforts.
   The earliest restoration of the Sphinx began 3,600 years ago.
   ``Two hundred years from now all our monuments will be
finished,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> told <ORGANIZATION>The Associated Press</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``In the past the monuments were safe from many factors that
destroy them because they were buried in the sand. The monuments
were not subjected to pollution, the environment, tourists, the
things that are ruining them now.''
   The emergency work on the Sphinx should be finished by late
<DATE>March</DATE>, with fallen pieces of limestone replaced and weak places
beneath the neck and shoulders treated, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. Made of weaker
limestone than other parts, the neck long has been considered a
chronic problem.
   After the emergency work, experts will draw up an overall
restoration plan, <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said.
   A major problem, said <PERSON>Omar el-Arini</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION> representative of the
Washington-based <ORGANIZATION>National Science Foundation</ORGANIZATION>, is that previous
restorers have not learned why the Sphinx continues to decay.
   ``In a nutshell, we have been looking at symptoms of the
problems, not the problems themselves,'' he said.
   ``We have been treating it as a rock carved 4,600 years ago, but
the limestone is 40 million years old. Our approach should be to
look at an object of 40 million years.''
   One of the problems facing the team will be how to rid the
monument of salt, which is visible on many portions of the body.
   <PERSON>Shawky Nakhla</PERSON>, chief restorer for the <ORGANIZATION>Antiquity Organization</ORGANIZATION>,
said restoration efforts in the <DATE>1940s</DATE> and <DATE>1950s</DATE> added to the
<ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s salt problem.
   ``They used cement, and a lot of salt started appearing,'' he
said. ``We don't know if a high water table level below the Sphinx
is a real cause of the salt problems, or whether the salt is coming
out of the limestone itself.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880302-0083 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-02-88 0654EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r i PM-Egypt-Sphinx     03-02 0329</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Egypt-Sphinx,0343</SECOND>
<HEAD>Work Begins To Repair Sphinx</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Experts have started conducting tests
to determine how to repair the Sphinx, the ancient monument that
lost a chunk of stone from its right shoulder.
   The limestone slab fell from the Sphinx <DATE>Feb. 7</DATE>, six days after a
sandstorm buffeted <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>.
   Damage to the Sphinx caused heated political and scientific
debate over the future of the 4,600-year-old monument and <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s
other ancient treasures.
   Kadry lost his job after accusing his boss, Culture Minister
<PERSON>Farouk Hosni</PERSON>, of staging the rock fall to reflect badly on <ORGANIZATION>Kadry</ORGANIZATION>'s
stewardship of the Sphinx and, by extension, the other relics of
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s rich past.
   Restoration work began on the Sphinx on <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   The monument was fitted with sandbags for support and
scaffolding to help in the early stages of the effort.
   A committee of experts took rock samples to test for salt
content and damage and to see whether the stone is strong enough to
hold iron bars that will be inserted to strengthen it.
   Tests also are being conducted to determine what kind of mortar
should be used to cement the rock in place.
   ``We're not in a hurry. We want to do things right,'' said <PERSON>Zahi
Hawass</PERSON>, general director of the pyramids area and director of the
restoration.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> has the head of a pharaoh and the body of a crouching
lion. Many Egyptologists think the face belonged to <LOCATION>Chephren</LOCATION>, son
of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> and builder of the second pyramid on <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION> next to
<LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>' Great Pyramid.
   Any damage to the pyramids or the Sphinx _ symbols of the past
with deep emotional overtones for modern Egyptians _ brings instant
outcries in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>'s national press. The rock fall proved no
exception, to <ORGANIZATION>Kadry</ORGANIZATION>'s chagrin, and charges of incompetence and
corruption flooded the newspapers.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890206-0218 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-06-89 1334EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-CrumblingSphinx Adv12   02-06 0819</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Crumbling Sphinx, Adv 12,0844</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv12</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Feb. 12, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>Experts Still Not Sure How to Keep Sphinx from Falling Apart</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto Planned</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   After a year of scientific debate,
archaeologists still can't figure out how to keep the Sphinx from
falling apart.
   It's been almost six months since workmen made emergency repairs
and replaced a stone that fell <DATE>Feb. 7, 1988</DATE>, from the crouching
lion's right shoulder.
   But the experts can't decide what to do next.
   ``Scholars from <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> and around the world have given us good
advice, but not one has been able to come up with a sure way to save
our wonderful Sphinx,'' said <PERSON>Sayed Tawfik</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s top
archaeological official.
   As chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Tawfik</PERSON> is
caretaker of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s enormous treasurehouse of the past.
   ``In all the world there's only one Sphinx like this,'' he said.
``We love him and don't want to do anything to injure him. This is
why we have an international panel studying where to go from here.''
   The Sphinx, with its wide-eyed stare and smug expression, has
undergone the jabs and probes of restorers almost since anonymous
artisans sculpted the half-man, half-beast 4,600 years ago at the
base of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION>'s pyramids plateau.
   None of the intermittent remedies has been able to stop
occasional rock falls.
   Major falls touch off political uproars in <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>.
   A tumbling rock in <DATE>1982</DATE> cost the job of the antiquities chairman
at that time.
   Last year's rockfall brought the departure of Ahmed Kadry,
pressured out of office because of a vocal and highly public row
with his boss, <PERSON>Farouk Hosni</PERSON>, the minister of culture. Tawfik was
appointed to replace him in <DATE>December</DATE>.
   Such sensitivity illustrates the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s monumental importance
to the Egyptians. Ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> was a cat-worshiping country, and
the Sphinx remains a very personal and popular cat.
   At times mostly buried in desert sand, at times not, the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>
has survived into the <DATE>late 20th century</DATE> as one of world's best-known
relics, although bruised and battered.
   Nobody knows how or why or when it lost its nose and pharaoh's
beard, but they are the most obvious reminders of the unseen
stresses at work.
   Tawfik said he believes the ancient stonemasons knew the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>
wouldn't survive as long as the pyramids of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION>, which form a
backdrop against the horizon.
   Some of the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>'s building blocks are as strong as those of
the pyramids, he said, but others, especially in the neck, shoulder
and rear haunches, are weaker.
   ``Perhaps they knew after 4,000 years or so the Sphinx couldn't
survive any longer,'' said <PERSON>Tawfik</PERSON>, an archaeology professor. ``I
think the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> is a decoration of <ORGANIZATION>Giza Plateau</ORGANIZATION>, a unique one, not
a monument for eternity as were other monuments.''
   The first known effort to help the <LOCATION>Sphinx</LOCATION> was 3,400 years ago. As
recorded in stone, the prince who would become Pharaoh Tuthmosis IV
followed an order that came to him in a dream during a daytime nap
to remove the sand from the <LOCATION>Sphinx</LOCATION>. He did so and, as promised in
the dream, the Sphinx repaid him by arranging for him to usurp the
throne of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   Fourteen centuries later, Roman technicians performed emergency
restorations at a time when the pyramids and the Sphinx already were
drawing tourists from around the <LOCATION>Mediterranean</LOCATION>.
   In modern times, foreign and Egyptian teams have had a go at
stopping the decay. Applying mudpacks to remove salt clusters and
injecting glue down its throat didn't work. More drastic suggestions
like reburying the monument in sand or encasing it in glass arise
from time to time.
   In the year since the stone fell, experts from <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Italy</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and other countries have given
advice on how to proceed.
   Egyptian geologists are studying rock samples. Specialists are
monitoring desert winds that blast the Sphinx. Pollution experts are
studying the effects of dirty air. Water and soil technicians are
testing the water table level on and near <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>, checking
whether subterranean water is causing salt to weaken the limestone.
   Even so, the <ORGANIZATION>Giza Plateau</ORGANIZATION>'s antiquities director, <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>,
remains optimistic.
   ``I believe for the first time in its history we are able to save
the Sphinx,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said, explaining that advanced scientific
findings in many fields are being applied to archaeological work.
   But for the Sphinx, he said, time is passing fast.
   ``He's like a suffering old man who needs an operation. But what
kind? When the rock fell (last year), it was kind of a red flag,''
<PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. ``At that time the government appointed a committee to
decide what to do. We're still meeting.''
   And it will continue to meet, he said, until it comes up with a
plan that won't repeat the earlier restoration efforts that harmed
the Sphinx more than they helped.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Feb. 12</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881216-0221 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-12-16-88 1335EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-MediterraneanTourism Adv25-1stadd   12-16 0643</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Mediterranean Tourism, Adv25-1st add,0659</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv25</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Dec. 25, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>CAIRO: historic remains.</HEAD>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Lanny Bell</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>Chicago House</ORGANIZATION>, a special arm of the
<ORGANIZATION>University of Chicago's Oriental Institute</ORGANIZATION>, has wrestled for 11
years with how to save decaying monuments in southern <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>
area, the greatest concentration of monuments on earth.
   Using photography and hand drawings, <ORGANIZATION>Chicago House</ORGANIZATION> is recording
some of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s best-known monuments before they disappear.
   ``In many respects the modern Egyptians live in a huge outdoor
museum, and museums are to be visited,'' <PERSON>Bell</PERSON> said. ``The question
remains one of finding the best way to display an artifact, even an
artifact as large as a temple, to best advantage.''
   Most Egyptian monuments were built as places of worship with
restricted entry. <PERSON>Bell</PERSON> said the dilemma for antiquities officials is
keeping monuments in their natural settings while insulating them
against tourist hordes.
   ``Tourism is both necessary and desirable,'' he said. ``But if
the present rate of decay continues, as it has for 100 years, there
will be no need for tourists 200 years from now to visit <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION> for
its monuments.''
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, who controls <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s best-known
tourist area, is trying to make it safer both for tourists and its
monuments, the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids and the <LOCATION>Sphinx</LOCATION>. He hopes television
monitors being installed inside the pyramids can stop tourist antics
that began 1,100 years ago when treasure hunters forced their way
into <LOCATION>Cheops Pyramid</LOCATION>.
   ``For the past 100 years this place has been a zoo, and for the
past 50 years antiquities authorities have had no plans to protect
the monuments from tourists,'' <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said. ``Our biggest problem in
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> is we have no concept that a monument should be a national
park, where people come to enjoy but behave.''
   Tourism has become <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s second largest earner of foreign
currency, with almost 2 million visitors in <DATE>1988</DATE> spending more than
<MONEY>$2 billion</MONEY>. The <ORGANIZATION>Tourism Promotion Board</ORGANIZATION>'s Moussa wants to double the
number within a few years.
   Moussa said officials recognize the appeal of <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s monuments
but must look beyond history to encourage mass tourism.
   ``If you're thinking of coming to <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> only for its monuments,
you can always put it off, because the monuments will still be
here,'' he said.
   ``Our best bet to help both tourism and monuments is to provide a
number of alternative sites throughout the country, drawing tourists
away from congested monuments. We also can help find ways to stem
the tourist flow into popular sites.''
   Tourism officials and the <ORGANIZATION>World Bank</ORGANIZATION> have devised a plan they say
will ease congestion in the temples and tombs on <LOCATION>Luxor</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>West Bank</LOCATION>.
It includes new roads and a visitors' center that will control
visits to the main attractions by computer.
   Two of the most famous tombs in the Valley of the Kings _ Seti I
and Tutankhamun _ are endangered but remain open to the public.
   A year ago the frail tomb of Seti I was reopened after
restoration. A few weeks later, a zodiac design painted on its
ceiling, unique among Egyptian monuments, came crashing to the floor.
   Workers are restoring the zodiac behind a rope barrier, because
``every time we close Seti, we get objections from tourist
agencies,'' said Upper Egyptian antiquities director <PERSON>Balboush</PERSON>.
   In <PERSON>King Tut</PERSON>'s tomb, visited every day of the tourist season by
2,500 and more, scientists found in <DATE>November</DATE> that bacteria were
eating away the colorful wall paintings.
   To accommodate tourist traffic, plans were made for restorers to
apply an antidote to the infested walls before and after hours. Once
they saw how serious the infestation was, however, experts decided
to work nonstop for three days.
   Tourists didn't hamper the work: the antidote smelled so foul
that once visitors took a whiff, they rushed out, leaving restorers
to their work.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, Dec. 25</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890317-0099 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-17-89 1359EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u i AM-Mummy Bjt   03-17 0570</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Mummy, Bjt,0586</SECOND>
<HEAD>Smiling Mummy Found at Base of Great Pyramid</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>GIZA PLATEAU, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An ancient mummy of an aristocratic
young woman, her <PERSON>Mona Lisa</PERSON> smile frozen in a plaster death mask, has
been unearthed in a shallow pit at the foot of the <ORGANIZATION>Great Pyramid of
Cheops</ORGANIZATION>.
   ``She's really lovely,'' said <PERSON>Aly Hassan</PERSON>, director of pharaonic
monuments for the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities Organization</ORGANIZATION>. Hassan dated
the mummy as 4,400 years old, one of the earliest ever found in
<LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   Egyptologists expressed surprise at <DATE>Thursday</DATE>'s discovery, noting
the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> pyramids area has been looted repeatedly since antiquity
and excavated by some of the greatest archaeologists of the last two
centuries.
   Hassan said the seals of the grave were intact when an
antiquities inspector accidentally found the burial shaft.
   Officials who entered the grave found the mummy. She wore a
bronze crown covered with gold leaf on her head and jewelry around
her neck.
   Jewelry, pottery, wooden items, a piece of glass, flint,
obsidian, a clove of garlic and more than a dozen teeth lay nearby.
The wood and garlic may have been placed in the grave to keep
insects away.
   The mummy was not identified, but <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON> said the woman's
nobility was established both by the finery buried with her and the
site of her burial, a cemetery reserved for officials of the ruling
court.
   She was about 22 years old when she died and stood five feet
tall, <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON> said. He said the body dates from the <ORGANIZATION>Fifth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION>,
which lasted from <DATE>2465</DATE> B.C. to <DATE>2323</DATE> B.C. He said he dated her body
from that dynasty because other bodies in the cemetery were from
that period.
   Her body is so dried out that it has been wrapped in foam for
protection and bound beneath the head.
   <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, director general of the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> area, said the new
mummy might have been an important person reburied for safekeeping
in the shaft where she was found.
   Two vast cemeteries lie under <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>, one with royal tombs
to the east of the <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> pyramid. To the west lies the one with the
new mummy, put into use five years into the reign of <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION> 4,600
years ago.
   Inspectors have identified the owner of the complex in which the
shaft was found as S-ankh Ptah, but his position under the pharaohs
and his relation with the mummy remain mysteries.
   Egyptologists hope the mummy can provide clues into early
mummification, an art of preservation that spanned more than 3,000
years of Egyptian history into Christian times.
   ``Any find in the <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> area in such a condition is a great
addition to archaeology,'' said <PERSON>Hassan</PERSON>. ``This mummy changes our
concept of preservation and mummification and provides a new date
for (it).''
   The earliest true mummy is that of Waty, found in the tomb of a
court singer called Nefer at <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION>. Waty's mummy dates from the
late <ORGANIZATION>Fifth Dynasty</ORGANIZATION> and was preserved so well by resin-soaked
bandages that even a callus on the sole of a foot is visible.
   Egyptians mummified their dead for thousands of years and was
refined over the ages using a solution of naturally occurring
preservative compounds.
   An obstacle to unraveling mysteries that still surround the
mummification process is that the ancients left incomplete pictorial
records of the embalming ritual.
   Some say the art of mummification was too sacred to be revealed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06342091 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06342091 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  HISTORY; BUILDING; FOUND; EGYPT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Archaeologists have unearthed Egypt's oldest bakery, where bakers laboring in
smoke-filled rooms turned out thousands of loaves every day for hungry
pyramid-builders.;   "We're talking colossal baking here, easily enough to
feed 30,000 people a day," said Egyptologist Mark Lehner of the University of
Chicago's Oriental Institute.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  General News  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  ARCHAEOLOGISTS UNCOVER RUINS OF COLOSSAL BAKERY
THAT FED PYRAMID BUILDERS
DISCOVERY ILLUMINATES LIFE IN ANCIENT EGYPT  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The well-preserved bakery, with a hearth, dough vats and bread pots, dates
from <LOCATION>Giza Plateau</LOCATION>'s pyramid-building days, which began with the fourth dynasty
in <DATE>2575</DATE> B.C. Experts say it's the oldest bakery found in <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>, perhaps in the
world.;   To ancient Egyptians, king or commoner, bread was an everyday
staple, taken with a bit of onion or garlic and a swig of beer. Money didn't
exist, and bread was doled out as partial payment to those who inched massive
stones into the towering pyramids that still evoke awe after 4,600 years.;  
14 kinds of bread; Records from the period describe at least 14 kinds of
bread. So far the team of American and Egyptian Egyptologists working 1 1/2
miles from the <LOCATION>Sphinx</LOCATION> has found three kinds of bread molds: small and large
bell-shaped, and flat trays. The largest earthenware molds weigh 22 pounds.;  
The dig began in <DATE>October</DATE>, financed by business executives <PERSON>David Koch</PERSON> of <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Bruce Ludwig</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. Diggers found the bakery in <DATE>November</DATE>.
After the season's work ends this month, team members plan to study the art of
bread-making using ingredients available then.;   "I have to admit I'm not a
baking expert, which would help," said <PERSON>Lehner</PERSON>, the excavation's co-director.
He said tomb artists left some baking clues, though much was left to the
imagination.;   Bread-baking is pictured on tomb walls of a fifth-dynasty
official named Ty in the cemetery of <LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> south of the pyramids.;   "We
didn't know for sure until now that this scene was real. We didn't have a
bakery to compare it with," said expedition co-director <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON>, in charge
of antiquities in the pyramids-Sakkara area.;   Baked in clay pots; A room in
the bakery contains three large earthenware vats beside rows of grooves for
bread pots lined up like eggs in a carton.;   The excavation has revealed
generally how bakers did their work. They took a "bedja," a heated, greased
bread pot, and put the rounded end into a baking pit. They poured in the dough
and placed an inverted pot on top. Both pots were covered with heated coals
and ash, causing the dough to rise and bake.;   For those making the bread,
working conditions were nightmarish.;   Heat was intense. Smoke was so thick
"these rooms would have been like a night sky filled with rain," <PERSON>Lehner</PERSON> said.
"We've dug through 1 1/2 feet of black-velvet, built-up ash."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Giza Plateau, Egypt  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911207  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Saturday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  December  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  459  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Saturday, December 7, 1991
00342091,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06119010 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06119010 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; Tourists, camel drivers and buses
make for a monumental mess of a monument moment  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  EGYPT; TRAVEL  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  RENOWNED tourists spots are almost invariably disappointing. The Mona Lisa
bakes under glass, and reflections of tourists elbowing toward her ruin her
famous smile. The Grand Canyon is usually shrouded in haze. To get into the
Empire State Building, you have to maneuver past shady characters hawking
phony Rolex watches. The Tower of Pisa is closed, and London Bridge has been
moved to Arizona. Six of the seven original Wonders of the World no longer
exist.;    But the pyramids are still magic. Provided you get there before
dawn.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Travel  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SEE THE PYRAMIDS WHEN THE PRESIDENT DOES
-- AT DAWN  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Destination: Egypt
Additional information attached to the end of this article.  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Why get out of bed so early? Because at <TIME>5:45 a.m.</TIME>, you have 4,500 years of
history all to yourself. If 100,000 workers can lug 2.3 million stone blocks
without so much as a wheel, then you can get up before sunrise to see them in
their pastel beauty.;    Don't take my word for it. The guard says that
Egyptian President <PERSON>Hosni Mubarak</PERSON> often takes visitors to the site at <TIME>6 a.m.</TIME>
because that is when the Sphinx and the Pyramids of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> are in their best
light.;    In the cool desert before dawn, there's just enough moisture to wet
the back of a parched throat. As dawn approaches, a lone soldier, wrapped in a
sheet like a modern-day mummy, stands in front of the Sphinx. Behind the
66-foot-tall half-man, half-lion stand three dark, huge, mysterious triangles
eerily jutting out into the <TIME>night</TIME>. Soon the sun would rise from the desert
floor facing the Sphinx, and the Pyramids of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> would turn a soft golden
brown.;    Slipping in;  The tourist books tell you the pyramids open at <TIME>8
a.m</TIME>. But with a little baksheesh -- or tip -- you can go earlier.;    After <TIME>9
a.m.</TIME>, the desert begins to sizzle and the buses containing caravans of
invading tourists arrive. Tourists make fools of themselves trying to look
comfortable posing for photos on bony camels.;    The best views are those
with a little height, but climbing the pyramids is prohibited. That is, unless
you are there early and the night watchman offers to guide you to the top of
the pyramid for a little baksheesh. The views are stunning, although the
climbing is steep. The Great Pyramid of <LOCATION>Khufu</LOCATION>, or <LOCATION>Cheops</LOCATION>, rises 450 feet. Be
sure to bring bottled water, for once the sun emerges, it quickly gets hot.;  
 The ancient Egyptians built the pyramids to be tombs to preserve the bodies
of their kings. Believers in the occult say that mystical vibes are trapped in
the pyramids.;    But all is not well at this seventh wonder of the world. The
Sphinx, buried and unburied throughout the centuries, is deteriorating, having
been exposed to moisture, winds and traffic fumes. The pharaoh's beard is
gone, its nose has crumbled and its skin is pockmarked. Part of its right
shoulder caved in in <DATE>1988.</DATE>;    Serious business;  Egyptians don't take these
things lightly. A <DATE>1982</DATE> rockfall cost the chairman of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Antiquities
Organization</ORGANIZATION> his job. Now specialists say measures taken to help the Sphinx
may have hurt more than helped. So an international commission was formed to
save the Sphinx.;    Repairs are under way, but the poor <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION> now has
instruments attached to its rear end to monitor air pollution, wind and
moisture. National Geographic reports that, if you probe below the limestone
base, "a red powder appears, as if the Sphinx were bleeding.";    But, at
least, peddlers are no longer allowed on the pyramid grounds. They just wait
outside for the <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> starting time.;    An early-rising peddler spies an
American leaving the grounds, and says, "Ah, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, very good." He
reaches into his pocket and pulls out a silver-plated medallion of the <ORGANIZATION>Sphinx</ORGANIZATION>.
"I want to give this to you to take to <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, a souvenir," he says. "I want
to shake your hand. Can you give me a souvenir of some American dollars?" he
says.;    The <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> war was disastrous to <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s tourist industry. "So
far it hasn't picked up," says <PERSON>Hamdi Saad El-Din</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian
Tourist Authority</ORGANIZATION>. "People were afraid. But we have never had one incident of
terrorism involving an American. <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION> is a very strong ally. You get the best
value in the world here now because we floated the Egyptian pound.";    <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>
is remarkably inexpensive. For example, the cost for a car and driver for
three hours was <MONEY>$7.</MONEY>;    A deluxe hotel room at the Intercontinental with a
balcony overlooking the <ORGANIZATION>Nile</ORGANIZATION> is <MONEY>$100</MONEY> a night. Silver goods cost one-third of
prices in the States. A pair of engraved silver earrings goes for <MONEY>$9</MONEY>, a good
meal <MONEY>$10.</MONEY>;    At the pyramids, as <TIME>8 a.m.</TIME> nears, it's time to go. The sun is
already beating down on camel drivers, and the shopkeepers squint as they open
their stores. One Egyptian man kisses his camel for the cameras, hoping for a
tip. Another naps near the chairs set up for the evening's sight-and-sound
light show.;    We beat the traffic back into town and have breakfast near
tourists headed to the pyramids.;    Outside, the Nile shimmers and the buses
stutter inch by inch up the avenue toward the pyramids, just outside the city.
It's only <TIME>10 a.m.</TIME>, but there's another appointment to keep. It's at the health
club for a massage to soothe the aching muscles. Another bargain -- <MONEY>$6</MONEY> for an
hour.; IF YOU'RE INTERESTED; <ORGANIZATION>Egyptian Tourist Authority</ORGANIZATION>, 323 <ORGANIZATION>Geary St.</ORGANIZATION>, Suite
303, <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> 94102; (415) 781-7676.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  STAN GROSSFELD, Boston Globe  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910428  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9T  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  941  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 28, 1991
00119010,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900405-0229 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-05-90 2103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s i BC-AncientHaremPlot Adv15   04-05 0921</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Ancient Harem Plot, Adv 15,0951</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv15</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, April 15, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Did She Plot or Didn't She? New Dig May Solve Ancient Puzzle</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MIMI MANN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>SOUTH SAKKARA, Egypt (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 4,200 years ago, <PERSON>Pharaoh
Pepy</PERSON> I heard one of his queens was plotting against him. He sent
Weni the Scribe to find out.
   Weni did. History didn't.
   Guilty or innocent? Cunning or faithful?
   Pepy's hapless queens have been suspects ever since.
   Now a French-Egyptian archaeological team, digging and recording
a queenly pyramid field 20 miles south of <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, is on its way to
unraveling one of ancient <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s most tantalizing intrigues.
   ``We have mention of three Pepy queens'' in ancient texts, ``and
now we have three burials,'' said <PERSON>Vassil Dobrev</PERSON>, a Bulgarian-born
Egyptologist on the team led by French historian <PERSON>Jean Leclant</PERSON>. ``As
we search on, we'll find the answers.''
   Which was the queen in question, and did she do it?
   Weni went to his grave with the secret, leaving a record of his
investigation that ended: ``I know the truth.''
   The scribe's silence did not enhance the pharaoh's reputation.
Pepy I, who died in <DATE>2255</DATE> B.C. after a 34-year reign, is remembered
for two things: an ability to keep <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>'s far-flung, troublesome
colonies in line and an inability to do the same with his queens.
   Early grave robbers, peasants revolting against the pharaohs and
generations of stone thieves left few clues to the alleged
conspiracy intact. The pyramids of Pepy's queens were so completely
ransacked that restorers work alongside archaeologists to minimize
the danger of falling walls.
   Generations of sycophantic tomb artists depicted ancient
Egyptian queens as perfect mates: beautiful, submissive, adoring.
   Egyptologist <PERSON>Zahi Hawass</PERSON> said the story of Pepy and his queen
shows that some ancient royal marriages were less than ideal,
especially since pharaohs had to deal with multiple wives and had
both major and minor queens.
   A pharaoh's chief queen, as consort of a god, received special
privileges, including the title ``great royal wife.'' Because of
the numerous other royal offspring, a young pharaoh-to-be often
married his sister to enhance his right to the throne.
   A few queens even managed to rule <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>.
   ``We can understand the queens' importance by their tombs,''
said <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON>, who directs the pharaonic cemeteries of <LOCATION>Giza</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Sakkara</LOCATION> to the south. ``The largest was the pharaoh's tomb. After
all, he ruled <LOCATION>Egypt</LOCATION>. His tomb had to show that power.
   ``But directly after his tomb in size came the queens', then the
princes', then the nobles' and officials'; a cemetery easily shows
their ranks in life.''
   Allegations of a palace plot by a main queen was taken so
seriously that Weni was allowed inside the forbidden harem to
investigate the rumors. <PERSON>Hawass</PERSON> said <PERSON>Weni</PERSON> left no record of the
queen's name, referring to her only as a ``main consort'' of the
pharaoh.
   Until this dig, the only Pepy wives whose names were known were
Ankh-nes-meryre I and Ankn-nes-meryre II. Both were recorded by an
official named <PERSON>Khui</PERSON>, who said the king married two of his family
members. It is unlikely either sister would have been the main
queen because their blood wasn't royal enough.
   So who was the alleged plotter? <PERSON>Dobrev</PERSON> and his colleagues, who
are at the end of the dig for the season, hope the answer lies in
the third pyramid.
   The French-Egyptian expedition first came to <LOCATION>South Sakkara</LOCATION>, site
of the pyramids of Pepy I and his pharaoh sons Merenre and Pepy II,
in <DATE>1965</DATE>.
   Its task was to record the last of the Old Kingdom's great
pyramid complexes on the edge of a 3-square-mile stretch of desert
graves spanning 3,000 years.
   Pepy I's pyramid proved particularly important because of
intricately carved texts of spells, rituals and myths designed to
help propel the soul of the dead pharaoh into the afterlife.
   For two decades, archaeologists were too busy to look for his
queens, but by <DATE>1988</DATE> high technology was available to help. Experts
combed 50 acres of rubble-strewn dunes adjacent to <ORGANIZATION>Pepy</ORGANIZATION>'s pyramid
with ultrasound equipment developed in <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>.
   Soundings monitored by French technicians pinpointed two good
possibilities. The team started digging, and found two queens'
pyramids.
   A portion of a third pyramid was discovered last year, wedged
between the first two and roughly the same size, about 66 feet tall.
   Three pyramids. Three queens.
   Diggers began excavating the new pyramid early this year,
uncovering pottery shards, a chapel, a passageway and a burial
chamber.
   By the time digging ended <DATE>March 28</DATE>, there were two important
clues that could help solve the mystery of the accused queen.
   One was the name Nub-Unet on wall reliefs. The queen was unknown
to Egyptologists and may have been the royal wife Weni described.
She was buried in the eastern pyramid.
   The second clue was an empty basalt sarcophagus, its lid buried
beneath two massive boulders that once closed the burial chamber of
the middle pyramid.
   Dobrev hopes the lid, when uncovered, will bear the name of the
queen and something about her, but that is next season's work.
   Hawass thinks he knows what Weni the Scribe left unsaid about
Pepy's queen.
   ``Weni bragged that he alone investigated and he alone knew the
truth,'' the cemetery director said. ``He had solved the problem.
That's where the tale ends.
   ``I think Weni told Pepy his queen was not guilty, because Pepy
would never have allowed her to be buried next to him if she had
done something so evil.''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Sunday, April 15</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06161082 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06161082 </ACCESS>
<LEADPARA>  Egyptologists, probing beneath a tourist village at the foot of the Sphinx,
