<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881022-0056 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-22-88 0512EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales Bjt   10-22 0753</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, Bjt,0776</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>One of Three Trapped Whales Missing And Presumed Dead</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Operation expected to resume around 1:30 p.m. EDT.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BAR1, 3, 5</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of three trapped whales disappeared
under the ice and was presumed dead <DATE>today</DATE>, a biologist said only
hours after rescuers scored their greatest success in moving the
animals closer to open water.
   The whale named Bone was last seen late <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, said
<PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>North Slope Borough</ORGANIZATION> biologist helping lead the
effort to rescue the three <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales.
   By <TIME>midnight</TIME>, <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> and others on the ice near this small town
on the Arctic Ocean had given up hope that Bone might rejoin the
others. Bone, Crossbeak and Bonnet have stuck together since
becoming trapped in unseasonably heavy ice more than two weeks ago
during their annual migration southward.
   The missing whale got its name because skin on its snout had
been rubbed down to the bone by the rough ice surrounding a
breathing hole that kept the mammals alive. That condition may have
led to Bone's death, said biologist <PERSON>Craig George</PERSON>.
   ``Once they get a bone infection, they go pretty quick,'' <PERSON>George</PERSON>
said.
   Eskimos led the whales almost a half mile closer to open water
earlier <DATE>Friday</DATE> by carving a string of 24 breathing holes in the ice
away from the main hole the animals had been using.
   Meanwhile, a helicopter-dropped concrete ``bullet'' bashed a
trail from the direction of the open water.
   About two dozen Eskimo volunteers, many of them bowhead whale
hunters, worked about eight hours to cut the 10-by-30-foot holes
with chain saws.
   ``The whales have moved all the way to the 24th hole,'' said
Col. <PERSON>Tom Carroll</PERSON>, commander of the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Army National Guard</ORGANIZATION>'s
portion of the rescue effort. ``I'm not sure how they did it, but
leave it up to Eskimo ingenuity.''
   De-icers, which keep the holes open by agitating the water,
freed the Eskimos to work on new holes. Until two <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> men
brought the devices <DATE>earlier this week</DATE>, rescuers had spent all their
time keeping the original breathing holes from freezing up.
   Another dozen de-icing devices and a dozen more chain saws were
on the way to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>.
   A huge CH-54 Skycrane helicopter loaned by the Guard began
working toward the whales from about four miles away, so as not to
scare the mammals. It used a 5-ton, steel-tipped concrete block
suspended from its belly to punch four 15-to-20-foot holes in the
ice at 75-yard intervals.
   ``They hover the helicopter 20 feet over the ice, and drop the
`bullet','' said Spec. 4 <PERSON>Wade Palmer</PERSON>, a Guard spokesman. ``It drops
through the ice on the second or third try. Then they pull it back
out.''
   A second Skycrane abandoned the repeatedly frustrated effort to
tow a 185-ton icebreaking ``hover-barge'' 230 miles from <LOCATION>Prudhoe
Bay</LOCATION>, and was to fly to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> today to help bash more holes in the
ice, said <PERSON>Tom Carroll</PERSON>.
   The first helicopter began working just inside a troublesome ice
ridge that blocks the path to freedom and lies about a quarter-mile
from an area of open water leading to the sea.
   The ridge, formed when drifting pack ice collided with ice
anchored on the ocean bottom, is too thick to be punctured by the
helicopters, and demolition experts were on their way to assess the
situation, said <PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON>.
   ``We looked for an alternate route (bypassing the ridge) and
didn't find it,'' <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> said. ``If there's no way through it, it
will have to be tackled early while the whales still are some ways
from it.''
   <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Fisheries Service</ORGANIZATION> has
expressed reluctance to use explosives for fear they might harm
other marine mammals.
   The <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> offered <DATE>Friday</DATE> to send an icebreaking vessel
now 300 miles miles from <LOCATION>Point Barrow</LOCATION> to help carve a path for the
trapped whales. But <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> said water in the area may be too
shallow for the vessel.
   Easterly wind opened leads, or open water, through the ice to
within four miles of the whales <DATE>Friday</DATE>, giving added urgency to the
effort to free them before a shift in the wind could pinch off the
escape routes.
   The whales still would face a 200-mile trek through the leads to
reach open sea, and weather forecasts indicate the favorable wind
may end <DATE>this weekend</DATE>.
   The whales also have Eskimo names. Kanik (<ORGANIZATION>Snowflake</ORGANIZATION>) for Bone,
Putu (Icehole) for Crossbeak and Siku (Ice) for Bonnet.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881020-0159 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-88 1427EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales 2ndLd-Writethru a0541 10-20 0914</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0541,0932</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescuers Try De-Icers to Widen Whales' Breathing Holes</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 2 grafs to UPDATE with barge resuming voyage;
Picks up 3rd graf, `The 24- ...'</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A huge icebreaking barge today began its
journey to rescue three trapped whales as scientists worried that
plunging temperatures and polar bears would threaten the mammals
they have named Bonnet, Crossbeak and Bone.
   Early today, a <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter rigged to tow the
185-ton ``hover-barge'' resumed the 230-mile trip along the
desolate Arctic coast from <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION>. It moved about five miles
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> through sand bars, mud and shallow water.
   The 24- to 30-foot-long <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales, whose species is
endangered, became trapped in the ice two weeks ago while migrating
south.
   Eskimo whalers using chain saws in sub-zero temperatures have
been cutting holes in the thick Arctic Ocean ice to help the
mammals breathe. They got a boost <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> when two
brothers-in-law from <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> brought six <MONEY>$400</MONEY> de-icers to the
<MONEY>$500,000</MONEY> rescue effort.
   <PERSON>Greg Ferrian</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rick Skluzacek</PERSON>, of <LOCATION>Lakeland</LOCATION>, flew to <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> at
their own expense to demonstrate the devices, invented by
<ORGANIZATION>Skluzacek</ORGANIZATION>'s father, when rescue coordinators politely refused their
offer to help.
   Early today, under the skeptical supervision of the
coordinators, they quickly cleared ice and slush from the two
breathing holes, accomplishing in hours what had been taking the
rescue team, using chain saws, pickaxes and steel bars, a day to do.
   The cylindrical de-icer, about 9 inches around and 14 inches
long, floats in the water suspended beneath a styrofoam slab. A
small, double-blade propeller pulls warmer water up from below and
emits it with 34 pounds of thrust.
   Within 24 hours, the breathing holes should be about 30 feet by
70 feet _ three to four times the original size, <PERSON>Skluzacek</PERSON> said.
   The devices are used in marinas to keep boats from becoming
frozen in the <DATE>winter</DATE>, <PERSON>Ferrian</PERSON> said.
   The tired whales can survive for several more weeks despite
being battered and bleeding from grating against jagged ice, said
<PERSON>John Lien</PERSON>, professor of animal behavior at <ORGANIZATION>Memorial University</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>.
   ``They can bleed a barrel and still be fine,'' said <PERSON>Lien</PERSON>, who
has helped free whales from ice for 20 years. ``We're talking about
a big animal here, between five to 20 tons.''
   The whales also may have to contend with polar bears. Reporters
flying by helicopter <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> spotted five prowling the ice a few
miles from the whales.
   ``There are polar bears that are certainly going to be attracted
to this,'' said <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Fisheries
Service</ORGANIZATION>. ``If they're going to take the whales, we're not going to
stop them.''
   He said polar bears hunt at night, when biologists are usually
the only people near the breathing holes, 18 miles northeast of
this Eskimo village.
   The whales were named by biologists so the mammals' respiration
could be monitored when they surfaced. One was dubbed ``Bone''
because so much of its snout has been scraped away by the ice.
Eskimos have given them their own names: Siku (Ice), Putu (Icehole)
and Kanik (<ORGANIZATION>Snowflake</ORGANIZATION>).
   A <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> ice analysis showed no open water in
the whales' vicinity. But a lead, or pathway, through the ice had
been spotted about five miles from the whales, said <PERSON>Jim Brooks</PERSON>,
acting director of the fisheries service in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>.
   ``There are open water leads throughout the <LOCATION>Chukchi Sea</LOCATION> and
<LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION>, out for a long ways. The ice is always moving. It's
very dynamic,'' he said.
   <PERSON>Brooks</PERSON> said there was no guarantee the whales could reach open
water, about 200 miles southwest, even if they could get to the
leads.
   ``But the hope is that they will be able to make it through the
leads via these open leads used by bowheads and belugas in their
migration. But the gray whale is not an ice-adapted animal. It just
doesn't seem to be able to contend with the ice as well as other
species of whale,'' he said.
   Rescuers sought ways to coax the animals in the direction of
open water if icebreaking efforts were successful, including using
lights as a lure near two new breathing holes cut for them. But the
mammals have shown little interest.
   <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> representative <PERSON>Cindy Lowry</PERSON> said tape recordings of
the sounds of other gray whales were being shipped to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> to try
to lure the animals to open water. If they don't respond to that,
biologists said, they have tapes of killer whales that might spur
the three young whales to escape.
   The barge was not expected to reach Barrow at least until midday
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, officials said.
   ``We're pretty optimistic,'' said <PERSON>Pete Leathard</PERSON>, president of
<ORGANIZATION>Veco Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the oil service company that owns the propulsionless air
cushion vehicle. ``It looks like it will be moving a little faster
now that it's cleared most of the mud and sandbars in the harbor.''
   Another <ORGANIZATION>National Guard Skycrane</ORGANIZATION> helicopter assigned to the
towing mission may be used instead to lift a huge reinforced
concrete cylinder to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> where it will be dropped to smash holes
through the ice. The slabs are leftover supports from construction
of the trans-Alaska oil pipeline, fitted so they can be carried by
helicopters.
   ``That's going to Plan B,'' said <PERSON>Sheryl Deveau</PERSON>, a spokeswoman
for the guard. ``We have a 9,000- and a 14,000-pound concrete
reinforced slab. ... They'll start dropping that from the <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>
end.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881024-0101 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-24-88 1331EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales 3rdLd-Writethru a0506 10-24 0772</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0506,0793</SECOND>
<HEAD>Airlift Of Whales Weighed; Soviets Dispatch Icebreaker</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: INSERTS 1 graf after 11th graf, ``The icebreakers ...' with
State Department saying icebreaker could arrive tonight.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAR2</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet flotillas churned toward <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> to
offer help for two trapped whales as rescuers tried to lure the
mammals to freedom, but biologists said they may have to airlift
the animals to open water.
   ``We're having a net built right now'' to carry them, <PERSON>David
<ORGANIZATION>Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> said <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   He emphasized that an airlift was the least preferred
alternative, to be used only if rescuers fail to coax the
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales to open water though a series of freshly cut
air holes in the ice.
   A third whale, the smallest and the youngest of the mammals
trapped in moving ice more than two weeks ago before they could
migrate south, disappeared <DATE>Friday</DATE> and was presumed dead.
   A pontoon-mounted ice auger known as an Archimedes screw tractor
was delivered during the weekend by a huge <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> C-5A cargo
plane and was reassembled <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   The device was to begin work <DATE>today</DATE> on the outside edge of an ice
pressure ridge that stands between the whales and freedom.
   ``That's the next big project for us,'' said <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> biologist <PERSON>Ron
Morris</PERSON>, coordinator of the rescue.
   <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> asked the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> for help, and <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Arctic
neighbor ordered the icebreakers Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vladimir
Arseniev</PERSON> to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, said <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> Rear Adm. <PERSON>Sigmund R. Petersen</PERSON>,
director of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Marine Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   The ships were 140 nautical miles from the <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> area, the
Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> reported today.
   Another flotilla unloaded equipment for a Soviet station at the
<LOCATION>North Pole</LOCATION> before heading immediately for <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said. Tass
did not saw how many ships were in the second group.
   The icebreakers are expected to arrive <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>, Col.
<PERSON>Tom Carroll</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska National Guard</ORGANIZATION>, which is taking part in
the rescue effort, said on <ORGANIZATION>ABC</ORGANIZATION>'s ``Good Morning America'' today.
   In <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> today, <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Charles Redman</PERSON>
said the Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON> could arrive as early as tonight.
   It was unclear what good the icebreakers could do in the shallow
water near the whales. The ships need 39 feet of water to operate,
<ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION> said, and the whales were trapped in water 12 to 25 feet deep.
   Even if the icebreakers cannot reach the whales, the ships could
help clear a path to open water about 200 miles away, <PERSON>Petersen</PERSON> said.
   As high-tech heavy equipment poured into this whaling village
during the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, Eskimos used chain saws and muscle to make the
most progress toward freeing the animals.
   ``We're marching out to the lead with Inupiat (Eskimo) power,''
said <PERSON>Morris</PERSON>. ``The whales are responding to the holes.''
   The breathing holes extend more than 1{ miles from where the
whales were first trapped.
   The Eskimos connected several holes, converting them into a
narrow pool 250 feet long to give the whales more room to rest.
They made a similar slot in the ice over a shoal about 5 feet deep.
The shoal apparently deterred the whales from moving farther toward
open water.
   The whales appeared to be in good health, although a patch of
skin torn off one animal's snout appeared to be worsening, said <PERSON>Jim
Harvey</PERSON>, <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON>'s colleague.
   Biologists believe a bone infection may have contributed to the
death of the smallest whale, which had been named Bone.
   The surviving whales were named Crossbeak and Bonnet by
biologists. Eskimos have named the survivors Siku, or ice, and
<ORGANIZATION>Putu</ORGANIZATION>, or ice hole. The vanished whale was named Knik, or snowflake.
   Wind continued blowing from a more northerly direction <DATE>Sunday</DATE>,
threatening to close the lead in the ice that rescuers were trying
to move the whales to.
   The airlift will have to be considered if the pressure ridge
cannot be breached, biologists said.
   ``It's been done numerous times with killer whales and the
like,'' <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said as he and <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON> tried to accurately measure
the whales' lenghth.
   The whales were estimated at 27 to 35 feet long, the smaller a
yearling and the other 2 to 3 years old, <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON> said.
   ``Getting them in the net will be tricky,'' <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON> said.
   The icebreakers were dispatched under a <DATE>1976</DATE> cooperative
environmental agreement with the Soviets, <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Brian
Gorman</PERSON> said in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>
   <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> provided satellite photographs of polar ice to the Soviets
to help them map a route to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, the northernmost community in
the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Gorman</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881023-0004 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-23-88 2355EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TrappedWhales 3rdLd-Writethru a0811 10-23 1090</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Whales, 3rd Ld-Writethru, a0811,1119</SECOND>
<HEAD>Rescue Force Grows, Soviet Icebreakers En Route</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 2nd graf, `A National...', and 6th graf, `NOAA Rear...,'
to CLARIFY that open water three miles away is just a break in ice
and that open water still 200 miles away.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two young whales trapped by ice
tentatively tested a narrow escape route to open water <DATE>Sunday</DATE> that
was being carved with chain saws by Eskimos who ordinarily hunt
whales.
   A <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter hammered at the ice off <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s
northern coast with a 5-ton chunk of concrete. But the whales were
more than three miles from a strech of open water, with a massive
ice ridge in between and a wind shift threatening to push ice
around them and trap them further.
   Rescuers said that even if everything went as planned, it would
be at least <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> before they could get the whales as far
as the ridge.
   As crews concentrated on coaxing the whales to freedom, the
two Soviet icebreakers.
   The icebreakers, Admiral <PERSON>Makorov</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON>, however,
need about 39 feet of water to operate, the Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>TASS</ORGANIZATION>
reported. The whales are trapped in an area where water depth
varies from 12 to 25 feet.
   <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> Rear Admiral <PERSON>Sigmund R. Petersen</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Pacific
Marine Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, said even if the icebreakers cannot reach
the whales, they could help clear a path to the first opening, or
lead, from open water 200 miles away.
   <PERSON>Petersen</PERSON> said that depending on ice conditions, the ships could
reach Barrow by noon <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   While high-technology equipment poured into <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> during the
<DATE>weekend</DATE>, Eskimos using chain saws and their strong backs made the
most progress at freeing the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales from a tiny
breathing hole.
   About two dozen natives hacked 34 breathing holes <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, for
a total of about 60 holes extending more than 1{ miles from where
three whales were stranded by moving ice about two weeks ago before
they could migrate south.
   The smallest and youngest of the whales, named Bone, disappeared
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and was presumed dead.
   Just as the tedious hole-cutting hit its stride, the whales
balked, advancing only a few hundred feet past a large opening
where they spent <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and most of <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   Biologists said the animals had gone back to earlier breathing
holes, sometimes breaking up to 2 inches of ice to surface. They
said that was a good sign because the marine mammals still must
negotiate 200 miles of ice before hitting open water if they are
freed.
   ``If they know they are capable of doing that, they may continue
doing so,'' said biologist <PERSON>Jim Harvey</PERSON>.
   ``Basically, we have to condition them that their best chance of
survival is to move ahead to new holes,'' <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said.
   He said rescuers planned to begin filling or covering the holes
behind the whales to force them along the desired path.
   Rescuers said they feared the whales were spooked by an
underwater shoal. North Slope Borough biologist <PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON> said
most of the water in the area is about 20 feet deep, compared to
only 12 or 13 feet of water in the shoal.
   ``You figure two feet of ice and five feet of whale, and that
doesn't leave them too much room to swim,'' <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> said. ``I don't
blame them for not wanting to go through there.''
   Whaling captain <PERSON>Arnold Brower</PERSON>, whose crew used donated chain
saws to help free the animals, was frustrated by the whales'
reluctance.
   ``If we move them, then I'll call it progress,'' <PERSON>Brower</PERSON> said,
leaning down to push the snout of a surfacing whale in the
direction he wanted it to go.
   <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON>, a biologist with the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION>, said sonar would be used to see if
there is an easy way around the shoal.
   The surviving whales appeared to be healthy, immature whales
estimated at 27 to 35 feet long, said <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Marine
Mammal Institute</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>. He said one apparently was a yearling
and the other was 2 to 3 years old.
   Rescuers worked in the dark using portable lights, snowmobile
headlights and de-icing equipment dubbed ``the bubblers'' to keep
the holes open ahead of the whales.
   The Skycrane helicopter on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> used its concrete plunger to
probe the ridge, a jumble of ice blocks as big as a house, but the
battering ram seldom penetrated. The ridge formed by colliding ice
masses is several hundred yards wide.
   Of additional concern was a shift in the wind, which Eskimo
hunters said could turn the area where the whales were trapped into
an impassable jumble of ice rubble.
   <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Brian Gorman</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>D.C.</LOCATION>, said the agency
asked for the Soviet icebreakers and they were dispatched under a
<DATE>1976</DATE> cooperative environmental agreement with the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION>.
   He said the rescue effort also involves use of ``some of our own
<ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> satellites to take ice pictures. We are relaying that
information to the Soviets to assist them in determining the most
expeditious route.''
   Heavy ice in the Arctic Ocean earlier disabled two Canadian
icebreakers and the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> icebreaker Polar Star.
   The latest piece of high technology to be thrown into the battle
is a pontoon-mounted vehicle known as an Archimedes screw, which
pulls itself along by augers that eat into the ice.
   While marine biologists called the whales Bone, Crossbeak and
Bonnet, the Eskimos have named the two survivors Siku, or ice, and
<ORGANIZATION>Putu</ORGANIZATION>, ice hole. The vanished whale they named Knik, one of 28
Eskimo words for snowflake.
   The young whales' lack of experience apparently led them farther
north than the endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales normally go, and
caused them to stay too long before starting their annual migration
to the warm water off <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON> said.
   Harvey and <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON> said the whales have a reasonable chance of
survival if they can be freed within a week.
   <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said the whales condition <DATE>Sunday</DATE> appeared stable, but
that a wound on the snout of the larger whale appeared worse than
before.
   The rescue effort had attracted so many spectators and news
teams that a police officer was stationed out on the ice to direct
traffic.
   A giant <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> C5-A cargo plane sent in with fresh equipment
took up so much ground space at <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>'s airport that a commercial
flight didn't have room to land.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881029-0027 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-29-88 0234EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-TrappedWhales Bjt   10-29 0716</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, Bjt,0737</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whales Presumed Free But Fate May Remain Unknown</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: This story stands for a0444, which was not intended for this
circuit. Please discard the earlier version</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The outcome of the two-week effort to free
two <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales may never be known as the massive mammals
faced 200 miles of ice-clogged waters on the way to their winter
home.
   Indeed, the sentiment among rescuers <DATE>Friday</DATE> was that ignorance
would be bliss if the whales died soon after more than <MONEY>$1 million</MONEY>
and countless hours of labor were spent trying to save them.
   ``A lot of people just didn't want to know'' about their fate,
said federal marine mammal biologist <PERSON>Jim Harvey</PERSON>.
   Rescuers decided against affixing radio transmitters to the
animals. That entailed additional expense, and rescue coordinator
<PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> said little scientific knowledge could be gained from
tracking a pair of young, lost whales.
   But hopes were high they would survive. ``They had the will to
live. They should make it,'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said.
   The whales on <DATE>Friday</DATE> reluctantly took advantage of an escape
route from <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s ice-bound northern coast afforded them by an
alliance of groups that are often at odds with each other: Eskimo
whalers, the military, the oil industry, environmentalists, the
<LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>North Slope Borough</LOCATION>, a countylike government.
   The Soviet icebreaker <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON> made four runs late
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> through the last 300 yards of ice between open water and
the manmade breathing holes where the whales were resting when
darkness fell.
   On its final run during the night, the Arseniev reported that one
whale entered the channel the ship had left in its wake.
   But when Eskimos checked on the whales <DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, they still
were in the last breathing hole. The Eskimos were prepared to resume
leading the whales to open water by cutting more holes with chain
saws.
   Then the whales disappeared.
   ``They were looking good,'' North Slope Borough Mayor <PERSON>George
Ahmaogak</PERSON> said after the last sighting of the animals.
   It was several hours after dawn <DATE>Friday</DATE> before rescuers could take
to the air to confirm the whales were gone. No trace of them was
found, which was interpreted favorably.
   <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said he believed the whales were on their way, saying
there was at least three miles of open water in the direction they
had to go to resume their annual migration to <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION>.
   Originally, three whales were found trapped by an early freeze.
They were discovered <DATE>Oct. 13</DATE> after being stuck in the ice off Point
Barrow about a week. One disappeared <DATE>Oct. 21</DATE> nearly five miles from
open water and is presumed dead.
   The surviving whales, named Crossbeak and Bonnet by rescuers,
were bleeding from cuts and abrasions late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   Questions were raised about the whales' apparent dependence on
man's help and their attraction to the noise of the chain saws. But
<PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said he expected the whales to revert quickly to their
natural behavior.
   Gray whales generally migrate within sight of land, usually no
more than three miles offshore, <PERSON>Harvey</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Gary Hufford</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> said that might
present a problem, since the ice near shore was more solid than the
ice farther out.
   ``It's going to force them out,'' <PERSON>Hufford</PERSON> said. ``What that's
going to do to them, we don't know.''
   Because the whales no longer can rely on the regularly spaced
breathing holes provided by the Eskimos, they would have to be
willing to search out random openings in the unstructured and
constantly changing ice ahead of them, <PERSON>Hufford</PERSON> added.
   With the population of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales estimated at more
than 20,000 and growing, marine mammal experts here said there is no
scientific reason for special efforts to save the whales, even
though they are considered endangered.
   <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON>, a whale specialist from the government's <ORGANIZATION>Marine
Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>, said the species may actually be better off
without these two whales because they were not clever enough to
migrate in the right direction at the right time.
   In the time that <ORGANIZATION>United States</ORGANIZATION>' northernmost community became the
focus of worldwide attention, native craftsmen geared up to meet the
demand for souvenirs. The whale saga also spawned a T-shirt
industry, with at least three commemorative logos marketed.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881022-0158 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-22-88 2143EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TrappedWhales 3rdLd-Writethru   10-22 0998</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Whales, 3rd Ld - Writethru,a0643,1024</SECOND>
<HEAD>Ice-Bashing Continues, Pressure Ridge Stands In Way Of A
Breakthrough</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with four grafs to UPDATE with quote from biologist and
second helicopter on hold in Prudhoe Bay. Picks up 4th graf pvs,
`And at...'. SUBS grafs 15-18, `The ridge...new holes.' with seven
grafs to UPDATE with more holes carved Saturday and whales swimming
from hole to hole. DELETES outdated 23rd graf, `The two...'.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto BAR7, LaserColor BAR9</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   One of three trapped whales was presumed
dead <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, but its companions inched toward open water as
Eskimos cut a string of breathing holes and a helicopter battering
ram smashed a path through thick ice.
   ``They certainly have a very good fighting chance in their
battle to escape,'' <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON>, a federal marine mammal
biologist, said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   However, a huge ridge formed by colliding ice masses stood in
the way of a breakthrough for the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales, members
of an endangered species. The big marine mammals were about four
miles from open water.
   A second ice-smashing Skycrane cargo helicopter was standing by
two hours away in <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION> in case rescuers decided a second
concrete ice-bashing ``bullet'' was needed.
   And at <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> direction, the <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> assigned the largest
aircraft in its inventory _ the C-5A Galaxy _ to ferry more
equipment from <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Air Force</ORGANIZATION> Maj. <PERSON>Doug McCoy</PERSON>
said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The whale nicknamed Bone disappeared beneath the foot-thick ice
<DATE>Friday</DATE> <TIME>afternoon</TIME>. By <TIME>midnight</TIME> <DATE>Friday</DATE>, rescuers on the ice near this
small Eskimo town on the Arctic Ocean had given up hope Bone might
rejoin the others.
   North Slope Borough biologist <PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON> said the whale was
presumed dead.
   ``Everyone is sorry to hear about the whale, but I don't think
it was totally unexpected,'' <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> said <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. He had told
reporters earlier the whale was the weakest of the three, and had
some respiratory problems.
   Bone, <PERSON>Crossbeak</PERSON> and Bonnet became trapped at a small breathing
hole in unseasonably heavy ice more than two weeks ago during their
annual migration south. Open water was too far away for them to
reach it without surfacing to breathe.
   The missing whale got its name because skin on its snout had
been rubbed to the bone by the rough ice surrounding the breathing
hole. That condition may have led to Bone's death, said biologist
<PERSON>Craig George</PERSON>.
   ``Once they get a bone infection, they go pretty quick,'' <PERSON>George</PERSON>
said.
   The whale's body probably sank to the bottom but may float in a
few days because of gases from decomposition, <PERSON>George</PERSON> said. ``We'll
either find it or a (polar) bear will,'' he said. Polar bears feed
on whale carcasses.
   Something will have to be done about the ice ridge, and soon, if
the remaining whales are to be freed, said Col. <PERSON>Tom Carroll</PERSON>, in
charge of the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska National Guard</ORGANIZATION>'s two Skycrane helicopters on
loan for the rescue.
   ``We looked for an alternate route (bypassing the ridge) and
didn't find it,'' he said. ``If there's no way through it, it will
have to be tackled early while the whales still are some ways from
it.''
   The ridge lies about a quarter-mile from an area of open water
leading to the open sea.
   The ridge was believed to be too thick to be punctured by the
helicopters' five-ton, steel-reinforced concrete hammers, and local
ice specialists were assessing the situation <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, said <PERSON>Geoff
Carroll</PERSON>. ``I think we're going to blast,'' he said.
   Bone disappeared about the same time rescuers had their greatest
success.
   About two dozen Eskimo volunteers, many of them bowhead whale
hunters, led the whales almost a half-mile closer to open water
<DATE>Friday</DATE> by using chain saws to carve a string of 10-by-30-foot
breathing holes. They continued carving holes on <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   De-icers, which keep the holes open by agitating the water,
freed the Eskimos to work on new holes.
   ``After waiting so long for high tech equipment, it's the local
people who have kind of taken over and made some progress,''
<PERSON>Carroll</PERSON> said.
   The whales, meanwhile, were swimming from hole to hole,
apparently responding to efforts to lead them to open water,
biologists said.
   ``Their swimming patterns now are about what you'd expect them
to be,'' said <PERSON>Withrow</PERSON>, who is from <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   Biologists removed a de-icing machine from the whales' original
hole late <DATE>Friday</DATE> and started one of the machines in the most
distant new hole. They also shined a bright light in the farthest
hole.
   In a matter of minutes, the whales popped up in that hole,
touching off a chorus of cheers from people on the ice.
   Rescuers shoveled snow and ice into the original hole <DATE>Friday</DATE>
<TIME>evening</TIME> in an effort to seal it and discourage the whales from
returning. But late <DATE>Friday</DATE>, they did just that, nosing up through
the slush.
   ``That's OK,'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. ``It's just a little retrogression.
We're in good shape.''
   The first huge CH-54 Skycrane helicopter loaned by the Guard
worked in the opposite direction from the Eskimo crews, working
from the open water back toward the whales, so as not to frighten
the mammals.
   The aircraft, designed to haul heavy cargo, used a concrete
block suspended from its cargo hook to punch four 15- to 20-foot
holes in the ice at 75-yard intervals.
   ``They hover the helicopter 20 feet over the ice, and drop the
`bullet,''' said Spec. 4 <PERSON>Wade Palmer</PERSON>, a Guard spokesman. ``It drops
through the ice on the second or third try. Then they pull it back
out.''
   The second Skycrane abandoned the repeatedly frustrated effort
to drag a 185-ton, icebreaking ``hover-barge'' 230 miles from the
oil fields at <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION>.
   The population of endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales has risen to
about 20,000, growing at an annual average of <PERCENT>2.5 percent</PERCENT> for the
past decade, officials said.
   The whales spend their winters in the warm water off <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> and <DATE>summer</DATE> in the food-rich
northern seas.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881026-0021 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-26-88 0115EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-WhalesWorth     10-26 0783</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Whales Worth,0803</SECOND>
<HEAD>Saga Of Trapped Whales: Is All The Fuss Worth It?</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT DVORCHAK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP National Writer</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   The massive rescue effort to save two <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales
won't make a difference to the survival of the species, but it's
been a public relations dream for environmentalists trying to rouse
the world to save its oceans.
   ``What's the big deal? I don't know. It all of a sudden
exploded,'' said <PERSON>Howard Braham</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine
Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, the chief <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> research center on
whales.
   ``Only the individual can answer if it's worth it,'' <PERSON>Braham</PERSON> said.
``We're dealing with the human spirit. We allow some awfully damning
things to go unchecked and then we reach out to something with a
tear in our eye.''
   The leviathan rescue has thrown together an unlikely army of
would-be saviors: whale-hunting Eskimos, <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>
environmentalists, oil companies, the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> and Soviet governments,
wildlife experts, animal behavior specialists and chainsaw
mechanics. An international cast of some 40 to 60 reporters keeps
the world informed of any progress.
   The two surviving gray whales imprisoned by the ice are part of
an endangered species, meaning they are thought to be in imminent
danger of becoming extinct.
   But the population of grays is flourishing. There are about
21,000, which is near the historic peak of 25,000 reached before
whale hunters slaughtered all but a few thousand around the turn of
the century.
   The Soviets kill 169 gray whales each year to feed Eskimos under
an exemption granted by the <ORGANIZATION>International Whaling Commission</ORGANIZATION>, and
another 1,000 animals die of natural causes yearly, according to
government estimates.
   Despite the losses, the population of grays increases by <PERCENT>2.5
percent</PERCENT> a year, and the deaths of three wayward whales not yet old
enough to breed would be insignificant, scientists said.
   ``There's no loss from a biological standpoint,'' said research
biologist <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON> from the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>.
   But cold facts have no chance against heated emotions when human
nature fights Mother Nature.
   The whales have names. Biologists call the two survivors Bonnet
and Crossbeak. The Inupiat Eskimos who discovered them <DATE>Oct. 7</DATE> call
them Putu and Siku for Ice Hole and Ice. A third whale, Bone or
Kanik for <ORGANIZATION>Snowflake</ORGANIZATION>, apparently died <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   Television brought the whales into <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> homes. Nightly pictures
of their battered and bleeding snouts protruding from a breathing
hole cut like a harpoon into American hearts.
   ``These animals are turning out to be ambassadors for all marine
life,'' said <PERSON>Susan Vernon</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Whale Museum</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Friday Harbor</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION> ``I don't think it's overreaction. It's a catharsis. The
helping hand was extended. And it was extended in good faith.''
   Gray whales feed in the icy Arctic Ocean, then migrate 7,000
miles to breed off balmy <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION>. The three trapped whales
were migrating for the first time.
   Even experienced bowhead whales, equipped with thick skulls to
break through ice, get hemmed in. About 10 to 12 of them perish each
year off northern <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, biologists said.
   Some have questioned the expense of trying to save the whales _
which had reached upward of <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> and counting as of <DATE>Monday</DATE> _
while funding for <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> whale research has been cut. The annual
budget for the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> is <MONEY>$2 million</MONEY>, down
from <MONEY>$2.8 million</MONEY> in <DATE>1985</DATE>.
   ``However much money they're spending on the rescue is fine,''
said <PERSON>Patty Warhol</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>American Cetacean Society</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San
Pedro</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>.
   ``That money might be better used in research, but you just can't
buy that kind of public relations for whales,'' she said. ``Today,
there are people all over the country talking about whales who two
weeks ago didn't know they existed or thought they were big fish.''
   The mercy mission has melted hearts of grizzled oil field
roustabouts from the bone-chilling <LOCATION>North Slope</LOCATION>, who also have reaped
a public relations harvest of good will for their labors.
   <ORGANIZATION>VECO Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION> offered to send a 185-ton ice
pulverizing hoverbarge to smash a pathway to the sea, with <ORGANIZATION>ARCO
Alaska Inc.</ORGANIZATION> donating fuel to the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska National Guard</ORGANIZATION> helicopter
that tried vainly to coax it to the whales. The barge got stuck in
shallow water.
   ``It was a common cause to help the underdog. We're human too,''
said <PERSON>Marvin King</PERSON>, operations manager for <ORGANIZATION>VECO</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's not money.
It's not headlines. We wanted to do what we could to help another
mammal.''
   ``We did what we should have done,'' said <PERSON>Ben Odom</PERSON>, senior vice
president of <ORGANIZATION>ARCO Alaska</ORGANIZATION>. ``It's a sad sight to see them struggling
to stay alive. What's that worth to help them? We're not discouraged
by the naysayers.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881020-0190 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-20-88 1728EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TrappedWhales Bjt   10-20 0598</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Whales, Bjt,0610</SECOND>
<HEAD>Favorable Winds Good News for Whale Rescuers</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Favorable winds <DATE>Thursday</DATE> buoyed hopes for
three whales trapped in Arctic ice as a huge military helicopter
again headed out to slowly drag an icebreaking barge from <LOCATION>Prudhoe
Bay</LOCATION>.
   While the whales still were 200 miles away from the open water
of the <ORGANIZATION>Chukchi Sea</ORGANIZATION>, an easterly wind was breaking leads, or
pathways, in the vast expanse of pack ice near the whales, said
<PERSON>Gary Hufford</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION>. It was pushing the
ice east and north, away from shore, and the forecast called for
east winds and a slight warming trend until <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``But weather is an unpredictable beast,'' <PERSON>Hufford</PERSON> said.
   A satellite photograph <DATE>Thursday</DATE> showed the ice was cracking open
all over the Arctic Ocean and <ORGANIZATION>Chukchi Sea</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hufford</PERSON> said, but
sub-zero temperatures were quickly freezing any open water.
   The animals were trapped about 100 yards off the desolate Arctic
Ocean coast about two weeks ago by bitter cold and the constantly
shifting ice pack. They have been breathing through small air holes
about 18 miles northeast of this Inupiat Eskimo village.
   While biologists earlier worried that the animals were fading,
they said the giant mammals' respiration rates have stablilized.
   ``You can set your watch by them _ every 10 minutes,'' said
<PERSON>Craig George</PERSON>, a <ORGANIZATION>North Slope Borough</ORGANIZATION> biologist.
   Biologists named the whales Bonnet, Crossbeak and Bone _ the
latter having much of its snout scraped away by the ice. Eskimos
have given them their own names: Siku (Ice), Putu (Icehole) and
Kanik (<ORGANIZATION>Snowflake</ORGANIZATION>).
   The whales were at least three miles from the nearest lead, and
whether they would make it to open water was uncertain.
   ``Whether they will be able to navigate lead-to-lead to get to
the open water, I don't know,'' said <PERSON>Ted Meyers</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>National Marine
Fisheries Service</ORGANIZATION> chief of habitat conservation in <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>. ``They
must go through areas of ice for some distance before they reach
open sea.''
   At the <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION> oil fields, a huge <ORGANIZATION>Army National Guard
Skycrane</ORGANIZATION> helicopter lifted off after first light and prepared to
hook onto the 185-ton barge and begin the 230-mile journey to the
whales. The trip was expected to take 25-40 hours. That means the
barge could not arrive at Point Barrow before sometime <DATE>Friday</DATE>.
   The helicopter and propulsionless barge progressed only five
miles <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> before the operation was halted because of
darkness. The rescue effort had been delayed more than two days by
freezing weather, equipment repairs and mud bogging down the barge,
which had to be relieved of excess weight.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Army National Guard</ORGANIZATION> said a second Skycrane assigned to the
towing mission may be diverted to lift a 9,000-pound reinforced
concrete cylinder to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> where it will be used to smash holes
through the ice.
   ``They are not going to send it to <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> until they are sure
they will not need it here,'' said <PERSON>Sheryl Deveau</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for
the <ORGANIZATION>Alaska National Guard</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION>.
   Two generator-powered de-icers provided by a <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION> family
business were keeping the whales' breathing holes clear, allowing
biologists and whalers to take a break. They had been using
chainsaws around the clock to keep the holes open.
   The 24- to 30-foot-long <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales, whose species is
endangered, became trapped in the ice two weeks ago while migrating
south. The species, which numbers about 20,000 and has been growing
at an annual average of <PERCENT>2.5 percent</PERCENT> for the past decade, spends
winters in the warm waters off <LOCATION>Mexico</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881028-0173 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-28-88 1620EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales 2ndLd-Writethru a0636 10-28 0748</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0636,0761</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Rescuers To Give Troubled Whales Another Chance To Reach Sea</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Leads with 12 grafs to update with whales apparently swimming
to freedom, picking up at the 13th graf previous, beginning ``The
mammals' plight.''</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two whales trapped for more than two weeks
by encircling Arctic ice apparently swam to freedom before <TIME>daylight</TIME>
<DATE>today</DATE>, after days of effort by Eskimos and icebreakers, an official
said.
   ``They were last seen at <TIME>8:45 a.m</TIME>. They were looking good,''
North Slope Borough Mayor <PERSON>George Ahmaogak</PERSON> said after talking by
radio to Eskimos who had gone to open breathing holes for the
whales. The last sighting was about an hour before sunrise.
   ``I feel great. I feel like I got no more burden,'' said <PERSON>Arnold
Brower</PERSON>, the senior whaling captin who directed the Eskimo rescue
efforts of cutting breathing holes in the ice with chain saws.
   Asked if he was confident the two <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales swam to
freedom, actually open channels in the ice leading to ice-free water
200 miles away, rather than died, <PERSON>Brower</PERSON> replied: ``Yes.'' A third
whale disappeared a week ago and was presumed dead.
   As night fell <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in sub-zero temperatures, rescuers had
left the whales in a breathing hole just 330 yards from open water,
a distance that federal whale biologist <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON> called
``essentially one long dive.''
   Twice <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the giant mammals traveled more than 300 yards
under the ice to reach new breathing holes, he said. But they
appeared reluctant to traverse the distance <DATE>Thursday</DATE>.
   The Eskimos crews had gone out early today to cut additional
holes to coax the animals toward the open water, said <PERSON>Ahmaogak</PERSON>.
   The whales' condition appeared worse after they struggled through
the slush and ice left in the icebreakers' wake <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and
<DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Both bled from multiple but superficial cuts.
   The Soviet icebreaker <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON> and its companion ship,
the Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON>, had remained nearby and offered to lend further
assistance by cutting a second path through the ice off the northern
<LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> coast. The ships then planned to depart for their home port
of <LOCATION>Vladivostok</LOCATION>.
   Rear Adm. <PERSON>Sigmund Petersen</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION> said the Soviet crews were ``ready to go
home.'' Their ships had been at sea for nearly six months and were
diverted for the last three days to assist the whale-rescue effort.
   ``We're here until those whales depart from the area,'' <PERSON>Ron
Morris</PERSON>, the rescue coordinator, said before the whales disappeared
early today. He said that if it was evident the whales had reached
open water, then ``that's all we're going to do ... the whales are
on their own.''
   The whales were caught in the arctic ice for nearly three weeks
by an early freeze, halting their annual migration to their winter
home off <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION>.
   The mammals' plight triggered a massive rescue effort involving
chain saw-wielding Eskimos and the Soviet icebreakers that captured
worldwide attention. The effort has cost an estimated <MONEY>$1.3 million</MONEY>.
   Rescuers thought that after the icebreakers broke a channel to
open water <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> the whales would resume their migration. But
the pair lingered and parts of the channel refroze.
   The eventual fate of the creatures may never be known because
scientists turned down the option of attaching radio transmitters to
them. Some rescuers said they'd rather not know what happens to them.
   The temperature hovered at minus 15 degrees Fahrenheit <DATE>Thursday</DATE>
<TIME>night</TIME>, quickly refreezing escape channels cut by the Arseniev. The
plunging temperatures also were beginning to put a glaze of ice on
the open water to which rescuers were trying to lead the whales.
   <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> ice analyst <PERSON>Gary Hufford</PERSON> said the whales
had shown an ability to break newly formed ice, so he remained
optimistic they could survive if they got beyond the remnants of the
pressure ridge crushed earlier in the week by the Soviet icebreakers.
   When rescuers found the whales early <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, they were
maintaining a small breathing hole about 1{ miles from where they
were last seen <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   Concerned with the whales' inability to negotiate the partially
refrozen channel, Eskimo laborers cut more than three dozen new
breathing holes in a path toward open water. The whales followed
dutifully, and were resting in the last breathing hole when darkness
fell.
   The Eskimos were prevented from moving further because the ice
was unstable as a result of the icebreakers' earlier efforts.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881024-0151 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-24-88 1956EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-Soviets-Whales     10-24 0299</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Soviets-Whales,270</SECOND>
<HEAD>With AM-Trapped Whales Bjt a0701</HEAD>
<HEAD>Soviets Making Second Effort At Rescuing Whales</HEAD>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet icebreakers, trying to help rescue two
whales off <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>, also were involved in a whale rescue off
<LOCATION>Eastern Siberia</LOCATION> three years ago, an American official involved in
joint U.S.-Soviet ocean research said <DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   In <DATE>1985</DATE>, Soviet icebreakers broke through an ice barrier in the
<LOCATION>Gulf of Anadyr</LOCATION> trying to free several dozen beluga whales, said
<PERSON>Robert V. Miller</PERSON>, deputy director of the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Laboratory</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   ``Reports are mixed, but I think they did get some out,'' <PERSON>Miller</PERSON>
said in a telephone interview.
   Unlike the <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> whales, trapped under the ice, the <LOCATION>Anadyr</LOCATION>
whales were in a small area of water that was cut off from the
ocean by a ring of ice. Icebreakers had to break through the ring.
Belugas are smaller than the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales off <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>,
typically 15 feet long compared with 50 feet.
   <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said he did not know whether the Soviet vessels involved
in the <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> attempt were also involved at <LOCATION>Anadyr</LOCATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Gulf of Anadyr</ORGANIZATION> is in the western <LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> south of the
Chukchi peninsula, the easternmost portion of <LOCATION>Siberia</LOCATION>.
   The <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> have been cooperating on
whale and other marine mammal research in the northern <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Bering Sea</LOCATION> and Arctic Oceans since <DATE>1973</DATE> under the U.S.-Soviet
treaty on environmental protection.
   They have conducted at least 15 joint research cruises, and
scientists from the two countries visit each other's laboratories
about twice a year, <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said.
   Though the icebreakers at <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION> were not part of the research
agreement, the willingness of the <LOCATION>Soviet Union</LOCATION> to lend a hand shows
that its scientists are ``very much interested in marine mammals
and conservation of these animals,'' <PERSON>Miller</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881027-0001 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-27-88 2340EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TrappedWhales 2ndLd-Writethru a0803 10-27 0833</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Whales, 2nd Ld-Writethru, a0803,0854</SECOND>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<HEAD>Icebreakers Make Last Ditch Bid To Release Whales</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 13 grafs to UPDATE with plunging temperatures newly
endangering whales' escape, quotes, details; picks up 6th graf:
`Eskimos with ...</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto staffing</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Faced with thickening ice, plunging
temperatures and the imminent departure of two Soviet icebreakers,
rescuers late <DATE>Thursday</DATE> made a last-ditch effort to free two whales
threatened again by the arctic icepack.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales, freed from nearly three weeks
confinement in their icebound breathing hole off <LOCATION>Point Barrow</LOCATION>, moved
closer to open water via man-made breathing holes and channels cut
in the ice by the Soviet ships.
   But as night fell <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the whales were in the last breathing
hole cut for them, with about 300 meters of ice between the hole and
open water, said rescue coordinator <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON>.
   Temperatures <DATE>Thursday</DATE> hovered around 15 degrees below zero and
were expected to drop to minus 20 to 25 degrees below overnight,
cold enough to begin freezing over the adjoining open water of the
<ORGANIZATION>Arctic Ocean</ORGANIZATION>.
   Rescuers left a portable generator to power de-icing equipment at
the whale's last breathing hole and light a beacon for the
icebreaker <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON>, which was to make two or three final
runs to try to free the whales.
   ``This should free them,'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. ``Hopefully, the whales
will see the opportunity to leave. We've given them the best shot
tonight.'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said the Soviets had to leave <DATE>Thursday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>.
   The plunging temperatures quickly refroze the channels the
icebreaker had made earlier <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Eskimos broke out chain saws
and cut dozens more breathing holes leading away from the clogged
channel toward the open sea.
   By nightfall, the workers were encountering dangerously unstable
ice as a result of the icebreakers' earlier efforts.
   As they did <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, the whales readily followed the path cut
for them by the Eskimos. As night fell, they had advance as far as
the last breathing hole.
   In a new tactic, rescuers carved 30 new holes <DATE>Thursday</DATE> in hopes
that the whales would follow the holes away from the channel and
eventually reach open water via another route the Soviet ships were
clearing.
   ``They're ready to go home'' after nearly six months at sea, said
Rear Adm. <PERSON>Sigmund Petersen</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric
Administration</ORGANIZATION>. ``We felt also with the weather creeping in like
this, we had to do something tonight.''
   Everyone hopes that when daylight arrives <DATE>Friday</DATE>, both the
Soviets and the whales will be gone, <PERSON>Petersen</PERSON> said.
   <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION> ice analyst <PERSON>Gary Huffard</PERSON> said the open water was definitely
beginning to freeze, but he remained optimistic that the whales
could escape if they could get beyond the edge of the pressure ridge
battered down by the icebreakers earlier in the week.
   Eskimos with chain saws had cut a series of breathing holes that
allowed the whales to swim well away from the original hole to which
they had been confined.
   The whales grew accustomed to the cutting and during a frenzy of
work <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, in which 50 new holes were cut, the whales
repeatedly surfaced in the new holes before the last block of ice
was removed.
   Since the whales were accustomed to the noise of the saws, that
sound might be used to coax them forward toward open water, said
<PERSON>Morris</PERSON>, a biologist with the <ORGANIZATION>U.S. National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric
Administration</ORGANIZATION>.
   The Eskimos eventually worked the marine mammals to within a
quarter-mile of a channel carved through the 18-inch-thick ice by
two Soviet icebreakers late <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> and early <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>. Then the
icebreaker <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON> reopened the partially frozen channel.
   The man-made channel, aimed at guiding the whales to an natural
open ``lead'' through the ice and eventually to open water,
partially refroze during the night, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said.
   He said the whales were ``conditioning themselves back to
reality'' after nearly three weeks of confinement in the ice off the
coast near <LOCATION>Point Barrow</LOCATION>.
   He also announced a crackdown on access to the whales by
reporters and others. He said pilots entering restricted air space
over the whales were subject to fines of <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY>.
   A biologist for the <ORGANIZATION>North Slope Borough</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON>, said
<DATE>Thursday</DATE> that the whales continued to appear healthy.
   The fate of the whales may never be known. Scientists involved in
the rescue that cost more than <MONEY>$800,000</MONEY> didn't attach radio
transmitters to the whales to track them, in part because of concern
that the devices would only add to their stress, said federal marine
mammal biologist <PERSON>Jim Harvey</PERSON>.
   A whale that was trapped with the pair nearly three weeks ago
apparently died last week.
   The endangered <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales have one of the longest
migration routes of all mammals, 6,000 to 8,000 miles from <DATE>summer</DATE>
feeding grounds in the Arctic to the warm water off <LOCATION>Baja California</LOCATION>.
   Their population has risen to about 20,000, growing at an annual
average of <PERCENT>2.5 percent</PERCENT> for the past decade, officials said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881019-0143 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-19-88 1504EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales 3rdLd-Writethru a0664 10-19 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, 3rd Ld - Writethru, a0664,0918</SECOND>
<HEAD>Eskimos To The Rescue; More Help On The Way</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: SUBS 8-12th grafs, bgng `The trip...', with 5 grafs to UPDATE
with barge still in Prudhoe Bay, CORRECT that noon local time is 4
p.m. EDT. Picks up 13th graf pvs, `Officials hoped...'. Lead
prospects uncertain.</NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserPhotos BAR2,3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Eskimo whalers wielding chain saws donated
by an oil company cut new breathing holes for three beleaguered
whales trapped two weeks in thick ice near the top of the world.
   The Eskimos on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> cut three holes 75 yards apart in a line
leading away from the larger of two small breathing pools the
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales have used since being stranded in the
<LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION> while migrating south.
   The rescuers, who received a telephone pep talk <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> from
President <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>, hope the new holes will influence the endangered
mammals to move in the direction they must travel if they are ever
to escape their icy corral.
   ``It'll be interesting to see if it works,'' <LOCATION>North Slope Borough</LOCATION>
biologist <PERSON>Craig George</PERSON> said as he dodged the slushy spray from
chain saws chewing through foot-deep ice 18 miles northeast of this
Inupiat Eskimo community. By <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, the whales hadn't moved
to the new holes, officials said.
   <ORGANIZATION>Standard Oil of Alaska</ORGANIZATION> donated three chain saws, and planned to
send a digging machine by helicopter to speed the work.
   Meanwhile, a long-shot attempt to free the whales with an
icebreaking barge was delayed until today.
   Two <ORGANIZATION>Alaska Army National Guard</ORGANIZATION> Skycrane helicopters have been
rigged to tow the 185-ton hovercraft barge from <LOCATION>Prudhoe Bay</LOCATION>, an oil
field about 200 miles southeast, in a tricky trip across Arctic
Ocean ice.
   The trip, which is expected to take 25 to 40 hours, was to have
started <DATE>Monday</DATE> or <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, but was delayed when the barge got stuck
and was slowed again by refueling. Plans to get under way shortly
after daylight today were also put off, but rescuers were still
working through the <TIME>morning</TIME> and hoped to leave at about noon.
   Overnight, workers labored to decrease the amount of fuel on the
barge to reduce its weight by 70 tons.
   <ORGANIZATION>Army National Guard</ORGANIZATION> Chief Warrant Officer <PERSON>Tom Williams</PERSON>, a
helicopter copilot, said they hoped the barge, now that it's so
much lighter, wouldn't get bogged down in ``a goopy mess'' of mud
underneath ice close to shore, as it had <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``The barge doesn't operate well unless it's over water or ice.
It started blowing mud out the sides and bogged down,'' he said
<DATE>today</DATE> as workers began getting ready for another try.
   By midmorning <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION> time, the <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> office in <LOCATION>Prudhoe
Bay</LOCATION> said the much-delayed rescue mission was now scheduled to get
under way about noon (<TIME>4 p.m.</TIME> EDT), but few details of the morning's
efforts at the site were available. <ORGANIZATION>National Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Mike
Haller</PERSON> had said earlier that if the barge could not be moved by
about noon today, officials would consider alternatives.
   Officials hoped to use the barge to carve a 40-foot path to open
water and freedom for the whales. The barge pulverizes ice with its
bulk and the fans that provide lift.
   Leads in the ice that were as close as five miles <DATE>last weekend</DATE>
have been plugged by shifting winds, record low temperatures and
drifting ice. By <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> the nearest open water was believed
to be 100 miles away, officials said.
   The rescue effort, complicated by the harsh arctic conditions,
has become a race against time.
   The young whales are tired, and at least one has pneumonia.
Their barnacle-encrusted snouts have been worn raw from grating on
the jagged ice surrounding the breathing holes. The animals were in
shallow water only a few hundred feet from shore.
   Last week, ice around the holes was so thin biologists did not
dare walk on it. By <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, with a record low temperature of minus
13 degrees, the ice was 18 to 24 inches thick.
   The whales are 24 to 30 feet long, but have shown no inclination
to smash their way to freedom.
   Their plight has drawn international attention.
   On <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON> telephoned <ORGANIZATION>Army National Guard</ORGANIZATION> Col. <PERSON>Tom
Carroll</PERSON>, commander of the rescue, to wish him well.
   ``I just wanted to tell you that everybody down here, their
hearts are with you and our prayers are also with you,'' <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
told <PERSON>Carroll</PERSON>, who was at the helicopter staging area at <LOCATION>Prudhoe
Bay</LOCATION>. ``Anything that we can say or do to help you along with the
success of the operation, we'd be pleased to do it.'' Biologists
said they were overwhelmed by the interest shown in the whale
drama. Scores of people have called with ideas to free the mammals,
such as using explosives, dropping bowling balls to break the ice,
or netting the whales for transport elsewhere.
   ``Every year, probably dozens of grays drown or are crushed by
the ice, but nobody ever knows about it,'' said <PERSON>George</PERSON>.
   But <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Fisheries</ORGANIZATION> said this case
is different. The whales are a little more than 100 yards from
shore and are easily viewed.
   ``It's simple. It happens every time with whales ... with any
marine mammals,'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said. ``They're portrayed as gentle
creatures and the situation out there (on the ice) is sad; it's
really sad.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900908-0125 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-08-90 1932EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-DolphinProtest     09-08 0475</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dolphin Protest,0488</SECOND>
<HEAD>Animal Activists Protest Plan to Swap Dolphin With The Navy</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By FRANCIS HOPKINS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Animal rights activists picketed <ORGANIZATION>New England
Aquarium</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Saturday</DATE> over its proposal to send an antisocial
dolphin to a top-secret <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> research center, but the aquarium
director said no decision has been made.
   Rainbow, an 11-year-old, 8-foot-2, 450-pound male, blue-gray
bottlenose dolphin would be swapped for a partly deaf female in the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s secret underwater mammal program at the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Ocean Systems
Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>.
   ``We are vehemently opposed to any dolphin being given to the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> under any circumstances,'' said <PERSON>Doreen Close</PERSON>, a spokeswoman
for the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Marine Mammal Coalition</ORGANIZATION>. ``Once they get into the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s hands, we have no way of knowing what happens to them.''
   <PERSON>John H. Prescott</PERSON>, the aquarium's executive director, said public
concern over <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>'s future has led him to reconsider the trade.
   About 60 members of the coalition and other activists peacefully
picketed the aquarium, protesting the proposed swap of the dolphins.
   ``We capture them, we use them, we abuse them, then we dump
them,'' said <PERSON>Richard O'Barry</PERSON>, a former trainer of the dolphins on
the <DATE>1960s</DATE> television series ``Flipper.'' He was not affiliated with
the marine mammal coalition.
   Aquarium officials say <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow</ORGANIZATION> is too aggressive and has become
less compatible with other dolphins at the aquarium as he has
matured.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Naval Ocean Systems Center</ORGANIZATION> studies and trains 142 marine
mammals, 109 of which are dolphins, in underwater surveillance and
detecting and marking objects for recovery. Further details on the
center's purpose are classified.
   <PERSON>Prescott</PERSON> said the swap was considered because the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> could use
<ORGANIZATION>Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>'s sonar and hearing for its research, while the partly deaf
female from the center would be suitable with those at the aquarium.
   <PERSON>O'Barry</PERSON> said dolphins in captivity are abused simply by being
placed inside steel or concrete tanks. They become ill and
stressed, he said.
   ``You can't take a sonic creature and put it in a steel box.
It's different from every other animal in that aquarium,'' he said.
``They are animals of sound.''
   In <DATE>May</DATE>, a former trainer of the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> center alleged that the
<ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> was training bottlenose dolphins with .45-caliber guns mounted
on their snouts to kill enemy frogmen. Officials at the center
denied those claims.
   A federal <ORGANIZATION>Marine Mammal Commission</ORGANIZATION> probe found no major problems
with the center's program or dolphin deaths in the past 13 months.
That probe was initiated because of reports in <DATE>1988</DATE> that 13
dolphins in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> had died between <DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1988</DATE>.
   ``Any dolphin in the world is in more danger from swimming into
drift nets than (from) any training program of the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>,'' said
<PERSON>Kathy Krieger</PERSON>, curator of marine mammals at the aquarium.
   She said <ORGANIZATION>NOSC</ORGANIZATION> research has helped aquariums in caring for their
dolphins and whales.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881028-0219 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-28-88 1926EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-TrappedWhales 2ndLd-Writethru a0687 10-28 0582</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Trapped Whales, 2nd Ld - Writethru, a0687,0594</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whales Break For Freedom</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: LEADS with 10 grafs to UPDATE with authorities saying whales
gone; picks up 7th graf, `If the ...</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Two gray whales that were stranded in
arctic ice for nearly three weeks apparently swam to freedom <DATE>Friday</DATE>,
ending a million-dollar rescue effort watched around the world.
   ``There is no evidence of the whales in the immediate area,''
rescue coordinator <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> said. ``I think the whales are
definitely gone.''
   North Slope Borough Mayor <PERSON>George Ahmaogak</PERSON> said the whales were
last seen at <TIME>8:45 a.m.</TIME>
   ``They were looking good,'' <PERSON>Ahmaogak</PERSON> said after talking by radio
to Eskimos who had gone to open breathing holes for the whales. The
last sighting was about an hour before sunrise. Ahmaogak later made
an observation flight over 15 miles of the coastline south and west
of <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>.
   ``I feel great. I feel like I got no more burden,'' said <PERSON>Arnold
Brower</PERSON>, the senior whaling captain who directed the Eskimo rescue
efforts of cutting breathing holes in the ice with chainsaws.
   Asked if he was confident the two gray whales swam to freedom,
rather than died, <PERSON>Brower</PERSON> replied: ``Yes.''
   Morris called the whales' survival chances ``pure speculation.
They had the will to live. They should make it.''
   Whether the whales survive probably will never be known because
biologists chose not to tag them with radio transmitters to keep
track of them.
   <PERSON>Brower</PERSON> said he was confident the two whales had reached the
channel cut by two Soviet icebreakers.
   If the <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales followed the icebreaker's channel,
they would still have to navigate ``leads,'' natural breaks in the
ice that vary greatly in width and close or open according to the
wind, about 200 miles to open ocean.
   Biologist <PERSON>Howard Braham</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>National Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in
<LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, said he thought the whales could make the 200-mile journey
if they would get moving.
   ``This is an open water species, basically, and for whatever
reason, being in the ice is new to them,'' he said. ``They are not
adapted for it anatomically. They are in unfamiliar territory.''
   The icebreakers spent much of the night plowing through the ice
off <LOCATION>Alaska</LOCATION>'s northern coast to slice another escape route for the
whales, originally trapped at a small breathing hole four miles from
open water. A third whale trapped with them died earlier.
   The Arseniev and the larger Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON> had been expected at
first light to head for their home port of <LOCATION>Vladivostok</LOCATION>. But their
crews reported they could stay to help, rescuers said.
   Rescuers had thought that after the Soviet ships smashed a
channel to open water earlier this week, the relatively young marine
mammals would have resumed their migration south. But at first they
did not move, and parts of the channel refroze.
   The temperature early <DATE>Friday</DATE> was 14 degrees below zero.
   When last seen late <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, the whales' condition appeared
worse after they had struggled through the slush and ragged ice left
in the icebreakers' wake <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> and <DATE>Thursday</DATE>. Both bled
from multiple but superficial cuts.
   ``I think if they can stay in the small cracks and open leads
that are frequent on the front of the pack ice, frequently that ice
is thinner, and if they don't make wrong turns, they should make it
out. Still, they have some rough going,'' <PERSON>Braham</PERSON> said. ``They may
make mistakes.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP881025-0105 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-25-88 1322EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a PM-TrappedWhales 1stLd-Writethru a0458 10-25 1015</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Trapped Whales, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0458,1038</SECOND>
<HEAD>Whales Reverse Course As Path Is Sought Through Huge Pressure Ridge</HEAD>
<HEAD>URGENT</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDS: Leads with 8 grafs with Soviet icebreaker nearing scene; picks
up graf 2, ``It's discouraging </NOTE>
<HEAD>LaserColor BAR5; LaserPhoto BAR1</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By BRUCE BARTLEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BARROW, Alaska (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Soviet icebreakers today neared two whales
trapped in the high Arctic as rescuers prepared ``Operation
Breakthrough,'' a go-for-broke attempt to smash through an ice wall
blocking the animals' path to open seas.
   The vessels were reported about 20 miles northeast of Point
Barrow before first light in <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, about noon EDT, said <ORGANIZATION>Coast
Guard</ORGANIZATION> spokesman <PERSON>Ken Freeze</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Alameda</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif</LOCATION>. A helicopter was being
prepared to take representatives of the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Coast</ORGANIZATION> guard to the ship, along
with an interpreter, Freeze said.
   The Soviet news agency <ORGANIZATION>Tass</ORGANIZATION>, in a dispatch from <LOCATION>Moscow</LOCATION>, said the
larger of the two icrebreakers, the Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON>, had been slowed
by heavy ice and by fog which rduced visibility to less than 200
yards.
   Meanwhile, ice experts were trying to find a way through the
pressure ridge and rescuers were trying to coax the whales over a
shoal between them and ridge. The whales retreated from the shoal
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
   Anticipating the imminent arrival of two Soviet icebreakers, the
ice specialists were taking soundings <DATE>Monday</DATE> of the water depth on
either side of the ridge, a jumbled mass of ice chunks about 200
yards wide and some 30 feet high.
   The skipper of a <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Coast Guard</ORGANIZATION> icebreaker assigned to act as
liaison with the Soviets and a <ORGANIZATION>National Weather Service</ORGANIZATION> analyst were
among those looking for a place where the icebreaker could punch
through the ridge.
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales must get through the icy tangle if
they are to reach an open lead, or pathway, through the ice.
   The whales, stranded about 100 yards offshore more than two weeks
ago by shifting ice about 13 miles northeast of <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, were about
four miles from the ice ridge. A third whale disappeared <DATE>Friday</DATE> and
is presumed dead.
   ``It's discouraging,'' federal biologist <PERSON>David Withrow</PERSON> said
<DATE>Monday</DATE> as the mammals, apparently spooked by a shoal that has
stymied progress for three days, retreated about 800 yards. ``Why
come back here when they know it's open up there?''
   The <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> gray whales struggled up for air, tiring quickly
as they poked their way through large slabs of <LOCATION>Beaufort Sea</LOCATION> ice and
thick slush left by efforts to carve them a path to freedom.
   At one point, the 27-foot-long whale _ the smaller of the two _
rested the end of its huge snout on the edge of the ice. Blood oozed
from a raw spot on its snout, smearing the ice and staining the
water.
   Biologists called a temporary halt to opening new breathing holes
so the whales would have a chance to rest and perhaps seek the open
water on their own.
   Rescue coordinator <PERSON>Ron Morris</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>National Oceanic</ORGANIZATION> and
<ORGANIZATION>Atmospheric Administration</ORGANIZATION> remained optimistic.
   ``They always regress some before they learn,'' <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said of
the whales. ``They'll move.''
   Meanwhile, specialists determined through soundings that there is
about 40 feet of water beneath the pressure ridge, a jumbled mass of
ice chunks about 30 feet high and as wide as two football fields.
   ``There is a lot of water flowing beneath the ridge, which should
mean it will be easier (for the Soviet icebreakers) to break
through'' than had been expected, <PERSON>Morris</PERSON> said.
   The icebreakers Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON> and <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON> were
expected to arrive <TIME>this morning</TIME>. The Soviet help was requested by
the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> government and the environmental group <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>.
   The whales must make their way through the ridge if they are to
reach a lead, or pathway, through the ice. The nearest open water is
200 miles away in the <LOCATION>Chukchi Sea</LOCATION>.
   Breaching the ridge won't do any good if the whales can't be
coaxed past the shoal. The animals, stranded about 100 yards
offshore more than two weeks ago by shifting ice 13 miles northeast
of <LOCATION>Barrow</LOCATION>, were four miles from the ridge. A third whale, which
disappeared <DATE>Friday</DATE>, is presumed dead.
   A shift in tactics <DATE>Monday</DATE> proved disappointing.
   Eskimos connected a series of breathing holes to form a single
open channel about 600 yards long. Instead of pushing the broken ice
back under the ice sheet, they used long poles to guide it toward
the rear of the slot.
   The idea was to keep the whales from heading back. Initially, it
worked. The whales swam back and forth between the shoal's edge and
the rear of the channel.
   But when the channel behind them was nearly filled, the whales
turned back.
   About 12 feet of water lies over the 125-yard-wide shoal, said
biologist <PERSON>Geoff Carroll</PERSON>. The whales have been spending most of the
time in water 17 to 25 feet deep.
   ``As it gets shallower, it feels (to the whales) like they're
beaching themselves,'' said <PERSON>Jim Harvey</PERSON>, a biologist from the
<ORGANIZATION>National Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   Officials hope at least one of the Soviet icebreakers can breach
the ridge, said Rear Adm. <PERSON>Sigmund R. Petersen</PERSON>, director of <ORGANIZATION>NOAA</ORGANIZATION>'s
<ORGANIZATION>Marine Mammal Laboratory</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>.
   Charts indicate the water at the ridge is about 30 feet deep, and
the 443-foot-long Admiral <PERSON>Makarov</PERSON> needs about 35 feet to operate,
<PERSON>Petersen</PERSON> said. The smaller <PERSON>Vladimir Arseniev</PERSON> needs about 22 feet.
   ``It does seem that the Makorov would have more trouble doing
this,'' he said. ``But they may be able to assist each other. I'm
sure that these vessels, which have operated in the Arctic for
years, have all kinds of solutions to these things.''
   Biologists have a last-ditch option: airlifting the whales to
open water. Withrow emphasized that would be a last resort because
the whales could be injured or traumatized.
   Although rescuers said they were committed to freeing the whales,
the cost of the effort continues to mount.
   Most of those involved in the attempt seem reluctant to talk
about the tab but it appears substantial _ at least <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> by late
<DATE>Monday</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900905-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-05-90 1725EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-DolphinDuty     09-05 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Dolphin Duty,0663</SECOND>
<HEAD>Aquarium's Plan to Trade Dolphin to Navy Launches Protest Wave</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ARLENE LEVINSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   An aquarium director was reconsidering plans to
trade an aggressive, unsociable show dolphin to the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> after news
of the deal set off a wave of protests from animal-rights activists.
   The <ORGANIZATION>New England Aquarium</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> worked out the swap, which
would have enlisted <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>, an 11-year-old male, in the secret
underwater mammal program at the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Ocean Systems Center</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San
Diego</LOCATION>.
   Aquarium director <PERSON>John H. Prescott</PERSON> said <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> that the angry
public reaction prompted him to rethink the trade.
   ``I think the decision is good for the animals concerned,''
<PERSON>Prescott</PERSON> said. ``(But) if it's causing public concern, I must pay
attention. It's not a closed issue.''
   Rainbow, 8-foot-2 and 450 pounds, is a blue-gray bottlenose
dolphin. One of three show dolphins at the aquarium, it became
cantankerous as it matured.
   Prescott sought a swap: Rainbow for a female.
   Other aquariums refused. But the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> center, which looks after,
studies and trains 142 marine mammals including 109 dolphins,
eventually agreed to take Rainbow in exchange for a partly deaf
female.
   The center trains dolphins in underwater surveillance and
detecting, locating and marking objects for recovery. Other details
are are classified, said <PERSON>Tom LaPuzza</PERSON>, a spokesman at the <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>
center.
   The trade was delayed because the military buildup in the
<LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION> took <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> planes that could have been used to
transport <ORGANIZATION>Rainbow</ORGANIZATION>.
   News of the deal got out <DATE>Thursday</DATE>, and animal rights activists
raised an outcry.
   ``We have been attempting to persuade the aquarium not to
capture wild dolphins and whales ... Our efforts are more urgent
now that we learn that the aquarium is acting as a clearinghouse
for animals for the military,'' the <ORGANIZATION>Boston Marine Mammal Coalition</ORGANIZATION>
said in a statement.
   A protest at the aquarium was set for <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   The aquarium got so many calls it recorded a message to
intercept them, inviting anyone concerned about Rainbow to send a
letter.
   National interest in the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> dolphins was galvanized by reports
in <DATE>1988</DATE> that 13 dolphins in <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> training had died between <DATE>1986</DATE> and
<DATE>1988</DATE>. Nearly half the animals suffered from lack of appetite or
stomach ulcers before their deaths, the report said. Other causes
were hepatitis and pneumonia.
   A federal <ORGANIZATION>Marine Mammal Commission</ORGANIZATION> probe found no major problems
in the program. No <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> animals have died in the past 13 months,
<PERSON>LaPuzza</PERSON> said.
   Then in <DATE>May</DATE>, a former trainer told the media that bottlenose
dolphins with .45-caliber guns mounted on their snouts were being
trained by the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> to kill enemy frogmen.
   LaPuzza denies such claims.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> has ``never trained marine mammals to kill people and
will never do so,'' <PERSON>LaPuzza</PERSON> said. ``We do not train mammals to
perform operations that will put them in danger.''
   The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> did use dolphins for military work in <LOCATION>Vietnam</LOCATION> and in
<DATE>1986</DATE> and <DATE>1987</DATE> in the <LOCATION>Persian Gulf</LOCATION>, however, <PERSON>LaPuzza</PERSON> said. He
refused to say what the mammals did. There aren't any immediate
plans to use dolphins in the gulf crisis, he said.
   The aquarium has given the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> three dolphins since <DATE>1980</DATE>, all
animals it couldn't take for various reasons, <PERSON>Prescott</PERSON> said,
praising the care the military gives the animals.
   The <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> controversy coincides with a similar one in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> state. In <LOCATION>Silverdale</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
planned to hear public concerns about the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s intention to use
dolphins to guard Trident submarines at <LOCATION>Bangor</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash</LOCATION>.
   The hearing is part of a settlement reached after 15 animal
rights groups sued the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>April 1989</DATE>, claiming that bringing
the warm-water dolphins to the colder waters of <ORGANIZATION>Hood Canal</ORGANIZATION> required
an environmental assessment under the <ORGANIZATION>National Environmental Policy
Act</ORGANIZATION>.
   The suit was dropped when the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> agreed to make that
assessment.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ910918-0134
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
910918-0134.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Law -- Legal Beat:
   Aquarium in Boston Countersues
   Activists in Feud Over Dolphins
   ----
   By Stephen J. Adler
</HL>
<DATE>
09/18/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE B6
</SO>
<CO>
   TAXES WNEWS Z.ZIN
</CO>
<MS>
CONSUMER CYCLICAL (CYC)
FINANCIAL (FIN)
INDUSTRIAL (IDU)
</MS>
<IN>
BUILDING MATERIALS, CONCRETE, GLASS, PAINT (BLD)
ENTERTAINMENT AND LEISURE (ENT)
ENVIRONMENT (ENV)
FULL LINE INSURANCE (INF)
INSURANCE (INS)
LAW AND LEGAL AFFAIRS (LAW)
RECREATION, ENTERTAINMENT, TOYS, MOVIES, PHOTOGRAPHY (REC)
SECURITIES (SCR)
</IN>
<NS>
ENVIRONMENTAL NEWS (ENV)
LAW &amp; LEGAL ISSUES AND LEGISLATION (LAW)
PERSONNEL ANNOUNCEMENTS, PROMOTIONS, APPOINTMENTS (PER)
TAXES (TAX)
ANTITRUST NEWS (TST)
</NS>
<GV>
CONGRESS (CNG)
INTERNAL REVENUE SERVICE (IRS)
JUSTICE DEPARTMENT (JUS)
SUPREME COURT (SUP)
</GV>
<RE>
EUROPE (EU)
MASSACHUSETTS (MA)
MARYLAND (MD)
NORTH AMERICA (NME)
SCANDINAVIA (SCA)
SWEDEN (SW)
SWITZERLAND (SZ)
UNITED STATES (US)
WESTERN EUROPE (WEU)
</RE>
<LP>
   In a battle over the best interest of sea mammals, the New
England Aquarium and a group of animal-rights activists are
engaging in a land-mammal ritual: litigation.
   The Boston-based aquarium yesterday sued three
animal-rights groups, seeking $5 million for allegedly false
statements made about the aquarium's handling of dolphins.
The aquarium also accuses the animal-rights activists of
filing meritless lawsuits against it, including another one
last year, in a campaign of harassment.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   The aquarium's suit presents the latest example of
retaliatory litigation known as SLAPP suits -- Strategic
Lawsuits Against Public Participation -- launched by targets
of activist groups' attacks. <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> attorney <PERSON>David R.
Schmahmann</PERSON>, representing the <ORGANIZATION>New England Aquarium</ORGANIZATION>, said other
aquariums nationwide, which have also been sued by
animal-rights groups, supported the legal effort.
   The aquarium's suit comes in response to the animal-rights
groups' most recent legal complaint in <DATE>June</DATE> challenging the
aquarium's transfer of a dolphin named Kama to a <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
training program four years ago. The groups claim that, under
federal law, the aquarium should have sought a permit -- and
published its request in the Federal Register -- before
transferring the dolphin. The activists name 10-year-old <PERSON>Kama</PERSON>
as a plaintiff in their suit. The aquarium responds that,
because Kama was born in captivity, no permit is required
under federal law.
   The activist groups, including the <ORGANIZATION>Animal Legal Defense
Fund Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, also argue that the aquarium's program to rescue
beached marine mammals violates the permit law because the
aquarium keeps some of the mammals its saves for research and
display. The aquarium says it complies with federal rules and
that no permit is required for saving beached animals.
   Behind the dispute over the requirements of the federal
<ORGANIZATION>Marine Mammal</ORGANIZATION> Protection Act lies a far greater disagreement
over whether intelligent sea mammals, such as whales and
dolphins, should be held in captivity at all. <PERSON>Steven Wise</PERSON>, a
<LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> attorney for the animal-rights activists, says they
believe that sea mammals are far too sensitive and
intelligent to be placed on display. "They should remain in
the oceans with their families, not in aquariums," he says.
   As part of their campaign, the activist groups distributed
fliers claiming that "Kama . . . was violently removed from
his family group and put into captivity." In <DATE>1987</DATE>, the fliers
said, <PERSON>Kama</PERSON> "was secretly sent to war" at the <ORGANIZATION>Naval Ocean
Systems Center</ORGANIZATION>, where dolphins are allegedly taught "to plant
dangerous mines or to become lethal dolphin torpedoes."
   The aquarium noted in its lawsuit that Kama wasn't born in
the wild but in captivity, at <LOCATION>Sea World</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>San Diego</LOCATION>, and
that the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> facility was found by a panel of investigators
to treat its sea mammals well and to use them for appropriate
scientific research, such as studies of hearing. Responded
<PERSON>Mr. Wise</PERSON>, the animal-rights lawyer, "The dolphins are used in
a classified military program. The <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> says nothing is going
on. But we choose not to believe the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>."
   Aquarium officials say that the animal-rights campaign has
undermined public support for the facility, which receives
1.3 million visitors a year, and that some aquarium members
have dropped their membership because they believed false
statements in the fliers or in fund-raising materials
distributed by the animal-rights groups.
   Moreover, aquarium officials seem irked that the
animal-rights groups are trying to push aquarium reseachers
off the moral high ground when it comes to care of sea
animals and their habitats. According to the aquarium's legal
complaint, since <DATE>1972</DATE> the aquarium has rescued and
rehabilitated hundreds of sick and imperiled marine mammals,
including dolphins, whales and seals.
   If the animal-rights groups succeed in undermining that
program, said <PERSON>Mr. Schmahmann</PERSON>, "mammals will be stranded and
will die on beaches. And that is something the aquarium
cannot tolerate."
   ---
   ASBESTOS EXPOSURE triggers insurance coverage, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>
court rules.
   The ruling by the state's highest court came in a dispute
between a contracting company and its insurer over the issue
of what event triggers an insurance policy's coverage of
claims arising from asbestos-related disease.
   <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Casualty Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, had sought a ruling that
coverage wasn't triggered until an injury was discovered.
Such a ruling would have limited insurance coverage to the
policy in effect at the time of discovery, and thus have
freed <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Casualty</ORGANIZATION> of liability.
   But the <ORGANIZATION>Maryland Court of Appeals</ORGANIZATION> ruled that insurance
coverage begins with inhalation of asbestos because the fiber
can immediately cause the development of asbestos-related
diseases even if those diseases don't show themselves for
many years. In ruling as it did, the court joined a growing
number of courts that have taken a similar view.
   But lawyers for the insurance industry said the <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>
court didn't take the broadest view put forward by some other
courts -- that insurers who had provided policies after
exposure but before the disease became apparent were also
liable. The <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> dispute involved <ORGANIZATION>Lloyd E. Mitchell Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,
a <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> contracting firm that stopped operations in <DATE>1977</DATE>.
   "<PERSON>Mitchell</PERSON> will have no significant impact on the company"
financially, said <PERSON>John D. Cole</PERSON>, chief claims officer at
<ORGANIZATION>Maryland Casualty</ORGANIZATION>, a member of the <ORGANIZATION>Zurich U.S. Group</ORGANIZATION> and a
subsidiary of <ORGANIZATION>Zurich Insurance Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Zurich</LOCATION>. <PERSON>Mr. Cole</PERSON> added
that the company was pleased by the relatively narrow scope
of the decision.
   While the case doesn't break any legal ground nationally,
it may influence asbestos disputes in <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>. Currently, a
trial court in <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION> is hearing a consolidated case
involving nearly 9,000 <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> asbestos claims brought by
individuals against companies. Lawyers said the decision may
mean companies found liable in that case will be able to seek
coverage from their insurers.
   ---
   CLARENCE THOMAS presents mixed picture on antitrust law.
<PERSON>Judge Thomas</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>Supreme Court</ORGANIZATION> nominee, pledged fidelity to
the antitrust laws, particularly to protect small businesses.
Defining competition in terms of the health of small business
hasn't been fashionable in antitrust circles since the <DATE>1960s</DATE>.
   In an article to be published in the <ORGANIZATION>Fordham Law Review</ORGANIZATION>,
<PERSON>William Kovacic</PERSON>, a law professor at <ORGANIZATION>George Mason University</ORGANIZATION>,
argues that if confirmed, <PERSON>Judge Thomas</PERSON> "would be a voice for
disavowing . . . expansive enforcement" of antitrust laws.
<PERSON>Mr. Kovacic</PERSON> cites <PERSON>Judge Thomas</PERSON>'s one antitrust opinion as a
member of the federal appeals court in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. That
decision, a sharp defeat for federal antitrust prosecutors,
"assuredly reflects conservative antitrust values," asserts
<PERSON>Mr. Kovacic</PERSON>.
   ---
   SWEDISH LAW FIRM lures two <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> partners.
   <PERSON>Daniel L. Bernstein</PERSON> and <PERSON>James F. Farrington Jr.</PERSON>, will
leave the <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> law firm <ORGANIZATION>Reid &amp; Priest</ORGANIZATION> to join the <LOCATION>New
York</LOCATION> office of <ORGANIZATION>Mannheimer Swartling</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Stockholm</LOCATION>.
   Few, if any, <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> lawyers have joined European law firms,
in part because compensation at <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> law firms is typically
higher than at law firms abroad. Most law firms open
international outposts with lawyers from their own countries,
although increasingly <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> firms are bringing in European
partners.
   <PERSON>Mr. Bernstein</PERSON>, formerly <ORGANIZATION>Reid &amp; Priest</ORGANIZATION>'s managing partner,
