<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA071590-0058 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 247361 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 15, 1990, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part A; Page 9; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
659 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BIRDWATCHERS FLOCK TO NEW JERSEY CONTEST 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By HENRY STERN, ASSOCIATED PRESS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
CAPE MAY, N.J. 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
In the <ORGANIZATION>World Series of Birding</ORGANIZATION>, people do the migrating. 
</P>
<P>
Hoping to identify as many birds as possible in 24 hours, five-person teams 
came to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> for a weekend in <DATE>May</DATE> to cough like a clapper rail and squint 
through binoculars. 
</P>
<P>
A team sponsored by <PERSON>Carl Zeiss Optical</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, captured the seventh 
annual birdwatching title by identifying 210 birds after racing over 490 miles. 
</P>
<P>
"Stop! Please stop! Please stop the van!" shouted <PERSON>Julie Zickefoose</PERSON>, a bird 
illustrator from <LOCATION>Hadlyme</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION> "There's a tern hovering." 
</P>
<P>
The group identified the bird within 10 seconds and shouted: "Drive on." 
</P>
<P>
"You don't have time to enjoy the bird," said <PERSON>Rick Radis</PERSON>, a writer from 
<LOCATION>Denville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, who was on the winning team. "It was: 'There's a stilt 
sandpiper. Let's get back in the car.' " 
</P>
<P>
Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, the contest began at <TIME>12:01 a.m.</TIME> 
and ended the following <TIME>midnight</TIME>. The teams frantically crisscrossed hundreds 
of miles of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> from pinelands to shore marsh. 
</P>
<P>
Most started in northwestern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, relying on their ability to hear birds 
in the morning darkness. With daylight came a southward migration of 
birdwatchers, who hit the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> shore tired but eager by midday. The 
competition ended on the tip of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>'s southern shore in <LOCATION>Cape May</LOCATION>, a 
haven for migratory birds on their <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> flyway. 
</P>
<P>
The state attracts a variety of birds because of its varying terrain of 
coastline, small mountains and pinelands. Its location between <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the 
southern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> also makes it possible to find birds from those areas. 
</P>
<P>
On a sunny and windy afternoon -- wind hampers birdcalls -- the "birders" 
descended on the <ORGANIZATION>Edwin Forsythe National Wildlife Refuge</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oceanville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
The vans make their own formation by rumbling slowly along a dirt road until 
someone sights or hears a new bird species. 
</P>
<P>
Teams operate on the honor system, and all members are required to have seen or 
heard the bird for it to be marked off. Five percent of the birds do not have 
to be identified by all members. This year, 253 birds were identified by the 35 
teams. The clapper rail was heard but not seen. 
</P>
<P>
Would a birder lie? 
</P>
<P>
"It's the last of the honor sports," said <PERSON>Peter Alden</PERSON>, a tour group leader from 
<LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> who has visited more than 100 countries and seen more than 5,000 
bird species. "But you could have lied through your teeth, gotten up at 11 in 
the <TIME>morning</TIME> and figured out what you could have seen." 
</P>
<P>
Alden and <ORGANIZATION>Zickefoose</ORGANIZATION>'s group, which also included actress <PERSON>Jane Alexander</PERSON>, 
didn't seem like the lying kind. Bird identification books littered their van, 
and three hours of travel with them showed their love for mastering the coughs 
that will draw out a clapper rail and for whipping out binoculars fast enough 
to spot a snowy egret. 
</P>
<P>
The team ended up counting 168 birds, finishing 18th. 
</P>
<P>
For the weekend at least, the camaraderie disappeared between birders who 
ordinarily would gladly show another that barn owl in the refuge's 
pewter-colored waters set against the casino skyline of <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
"At the end of the day, everybody kind of laughs at the bird you didn't get," 
said <PERSON>Alf Wilson</PERSON>, co-owner of a <LOCATION>Walpole</LOCATION>, Mass.-based company putting out a bird 
identification video. 
</P>
<P>
Then he grew silent and cupped his ears while his teammates coughed, trying to 
attract the elusive clapper rail. 
</P>
<P>
As for the winners, they credited their victory to 500 hours of advance 
scouting and simple birders' luck at bird-spotting or "getting on the bird." 
</P>
<P>
For example, they found a red crossbill in northern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> even though the 
migratory bird is not usually found in the state in <DATE>spring</DATE> or <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
And members of the winning team -- who got a team trophy and a pair of 
binoculars apiece -- said they celebrated their victory by getting a jump on 
next year's scouting. They got up early the next day and spotted a <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> 
kite. 
</P>
<P>
"It's for enjoyment, but it's more of a game," <PERSON>Radis</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900628-0207 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-28-90 1201EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a BC-EXP--FortheBirds Adv02   06-28 0717</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-EXP--For the Birds, Adv 02,0736</SECOND>
<NOTE>$adv02</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Monday, July 2, and thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>It's a Plane! It's Superman! No, It's a Bird</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By HENRY STERN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CAPE MAY, N.J. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In the <ORGANIZATION>World Series of Birding</ORGANIZATION>, people do
the migrating.
   Hoping to identify as many birds as possible in 24 hours,
five-person teams came to <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> for a weekend in <DATE>May</DATE> to cough
like a clapper rail and squint through binoculars.
   A team sponsored by <PERSON>Carl Zeiss Optical</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Alexandria</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>,
captured the seventh annual birdwatching title by identifying 210
birds after racing over 490 miles.
   ``Stop! Please stop! Please stop the van!'' shouted <PERSON>Julie
Zickefoose</PERSON>, a bird illustrator from <LOCATION>Hadlyme</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Conn.</LOCATION> ``There's a tern
hovering.''
   The group identified the bird within 10 seconds and shouted,
``Drive on.''
   ``You don't have time to enjoy the bird,'' said <PERSON>Rick Radis</PERSON>, a
writer from <LOCATION>Denville</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, who was on the winning team. ``It was:
`There's a stilt sandpiper. Let's get back in the car.'''
   Sponsored by the <ORGANIZATION>New Jersey Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, the contest began
at <TIME>12:01 a.m.</TIME> and ended the following <TIME>midnight</TIME>. The teams
frantically criss-crossed hundreds of miles of <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> from
pinelands to shore marsh.
   Most started in northwestern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> relying on their ability
to hear birds in the morning darkness. With daylight came a
southward migration of birdwatchers, who hit the <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> shore
tired but eager by midday. The competition ended on the tip of <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>'s southern shore in <LOCATION>Cape May</LOCATION>, a haven for migratory birds on
their <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION> flyway.
   The state attracts a variety of birds because of its varying
terrain of coastline, small mountains and pinelands. Its location
between <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the southern <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> also makes it
possible to find birds from those areas.
   On a sunny and windy afternoon _ wind hampers birdcalls _ the
``birders'' descended on the <ORGANIZATION>Edwin Forsythe National Wildlife
Refuge</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Oceanville</LOCATION>.
   The vans make their own formation by rumbling slowly along a
dirt road until someone sights or hears a new bird species.
   Teams operate on the honor system and all members are required
to have seen or heard the bird for it to be marked off. Five
percent of the birds do not have to be identified by all members.
This year, 253 birds were identified by the 35 teams. The clapper
rail was heard but not seen.
   Would a birder lie?
   ``It's the last of the honor sports,'' said <PERSON>Peter Alden</PERSON>, a tour
group leader from <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION> who has visited more than 100
countries and seen more than 5,000 bird species. ``But you could
have lied through your teeth, gotten up at 11 in the <TIME>morning</TIME> and
figured out what you could have seen.''
   Alden and <PERSON>Ms. Zickefoose</PERSON>'s group, which also included actress
<PERSON>Jane Alexander</PERSON>, didn't seem like the lying kind. Bird
identification books littered their van and three hours of travel
with them showed their love for mastering the coughs that will draw
out a clapper rail and for whipping out binoculars fast enough to
spot a snowy egret.
   The team ended up counting 168 birds, finishing 18th.
   For the weekend at least, the camaraderie disappeared between
birders who ordinarily would gladly show another that barn owl in
the refuge's pewter-colored waters set against the casino skyline
of <LOCATION>Atlantic City</LOCATION>.
   ``At the end of the day, everybody kind of laughs at the bird
you didn't get,'' said <PERSON>Alf Wilson</PERSON>, co-owner of a <LOCATION>Walpole</LOCATION>,
Mass.-based company putting out a bird identification video.
   Then he grew silent and cupped his ears while his teammates
coughed, trying to attract the elusive clapper rail.
   As for the winners, they credited their victory to 500 hours of
advance scouting and simple birders' luck at birdspotting or
``getting on the bird.''
   For example, they found a red crossbill in northern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>
even though the migratory bird is not usually found in the state in
<DATE>spring</DATE> or <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   And members of the winning team _ who got a team trophy and a
pair of binoculars apiece _ said they celebrated their victory by
getting a jump on next year's scouting. They got up early the next
day and spotted a <LOCATION>Mississippi</LOCATION> kite.
   ``It's for enjoyment, but it's more of a game,'' <PERSON>Radis</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Monday, July 2</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06002232 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06002232 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (4); Lloyd Francis Jr. -- Mercury News; COVER PHOTO: LAKE ELIZABETH:
FREMONT FLYWAY; An elegant blue heron takes off from Duck Island in Lake
Elizabeth, home to more than 125 species of birds and mammals. The lake draws
birds because it lies along the Pacific flyway. But lately, politics are
ruffling the waters. The Bay Area Rapid Transit District plans to build a rail
extension either over the lake or near it. The Fremont City Council is urging
BART to change its route, but so far BART has refused.(color); PHOTO:
Cormorants perch on dead branches at Duck Island in the center of Lake
Elizabeth; PHOTO: Judy Felber, a park and animal services officer for the city
of Fremont, patrols the waters of Lake Elizabeth.; PHOTO: A flock of gulls
descends on Walter Schetlin, visiting from Maryland.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PARK; LAKE; BIRD; ENVIRONMENT; FREMONT  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  As a blustery wind pelted rain against her face, Judy Felber navigated the
small powerboat around the back of Duck Island in Lake Elizabeth. She cut the
motor, and as the boat rocked through the choppy water, pointed to the birds
on shore.;    "There's a black crown night heron," Felber said, gesturing
toward a large bird hidden in the bushes. "They are nocturnal, so they don't
do a lot in the daylight. At night they go to the edge of the shore and feed
on fish or frogs or whatever they can find."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  The Weekly, Part 2  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  AT TIMES, FREMONT LAKE IS FOR THE BIRDS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     As a park and animal services officer for the city of <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Felber</PERSON> makes
trips around the lake frequently. She and members of her staff go out at least
once a day to check the water level and make sure the birds are not disturbed.
They also count the birds on the lake once a week.;    But lately, politics
has disturbed the lake's tranquility. The <ORGANIZATION>Bay Area Rapid Transit District</ORGANIZATION>
plans to build a rail extension from downtown <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Warm Springs</LOCATION>, and the
plans call for the trains to run either over the lake or near it. The <ORGANIZATION>Fremont
City Council</ORGANIZATION> is urging BART to tunnel trains under <PERSON>Lake Elizabeth</PERSON>, but so far
BART has refused.;    As part of its strategy to show BART that trains will
damage <PERSON>Lake Elizabeth</PERSON> and <ORGANIZATION>Central Park</ORGANIZATION>, the city council is emphasizing the
area's wildlife. When the <ORGANIZATION>BART Board of Directors</ORGANIZATION> came to <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> recently to
tour the park, they saw a professionally produced video commercial for the
lake. Felber was featured prominently in the video, giving a tour of the
wildlife.;    Since the 80-acre lake sits in a major metropolitan area, many
people aren't aware it is home to more than 125 species of birds and mammals,
<PERSON>Felber</PERSON> said. Yet birds flock to the lake because it lies along the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>
flyway, and it is one of the few open bodies of fresh water around.;    Winter
is a particularly good time to see birds because there are few people around,
<PERSON>Felber</PERSON> said. And since no one is allowed on <LOCATION>Duck Island</LOCATION>, the birds tend to
congregate there to nest and eat.;    In the <DATE>winter</DATE>, "there are less people in
the park, " <PERSON>Felber</PERSON> said. "There's less danger for the birds. It's quiet, it's
protected. There's plenty of food here.";    As soon as <PERSON>Felber</PERSON> spotted one
black crowned night heron, she began to see more crouched among the branches
of barren trees, their feathers fluffed to keep warm. There are about 26
herons in the park, out of a bird population of about 2,500.;    Suddenly, a
great blue heron walked into a small clearing on the island. It lifted its
feet one at a time to its chest, as if trying to keep them warm. But as
<PERSON>Felber</PERSON>'s boat drew closer, the blue heron spooked and flew into the air. With
its six-foot wingspan, the bird was gone in a few seconds.;    No one knows
exactly how BART trains might affect the bird habitat. There are railroad cars
that run near the lake, but their noise is muffled. In the video, <PERSON>Felber</PERSON>
pointed out that birds do not like loud noises, and expressed concern that
BART trains might scare them away.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  FRANCES DINKELSPIEL, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Alameda County/AM  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910102  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  6  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  679  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday January 2, 1991
00002232,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900802-0055 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-02-90 0503EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-StarlingWars     08-02 0528</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Starling Wars,0545</SECOND>
<HEAD>Health Officials Wage Psychological Warfare Against Pesky Birds</HEAD>
<HEAD>LaserPhoto CX3</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By PAUL A. DRISCOLL</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>OAK PARK, Ill. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Health officials are employing
psychological warfare in a nearly decade-long battle against
thousands of noisy starlings that descend in dense flocks each
<DATE>summer</DATE> in certain elm-lined neighborhoods.
   The birds keep people awake, coat cars in messy droppings and
make <PERSON>Bob Mathis</PERSON>' life miserable each <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Mathis</PERSON>, the village's environmental health supervisor, has tried
everything over the years from wind machines to huge balloons
painted with ``terror eyes'' to resemble owls.
   He had limited success until he hit on a promising combination
two or three years ago of high-intensity search lights and a taped
starling distress call that fills the evening air with screeching
to scare away the birds.
   ``We use a physical assault and psychological warfare,'' he
said. ``The lights unsettle their environment and the starling
distress call is an eerie sound, like a bird being strangled.''
   For seven years or more in the warmer months, the birds in
flocks of 3,000 to 5,000 seem to favor the cathedral-arch canopies
of elms on two usually quiet blocks in this <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> suburb.
   The birds feast on beetles and caterpillars by day and head for
the trees at dusk for their evening shut-eye.
   Residents call the kids inside and park their cars down the
block, away from the splatter of bird droppings.
   ``It's a real mess here,'' one resident, <PERSON>Ken Radnitzer</PERSON>, said
<DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME>, during one of <PERSON>Mathis</PERSON>' regular trips to the
neighborhood with the lights and distress call.
   ``It's a health hazard,'' said another, <PERSON>Kathleen Dawson</PERSON>. ``The
droppings get so bad that if you're out in the <TIME>evening</TIME> and your kid
is in bare feet you're forever running after him. Or in the back
yard, the droppings get on the toys.''
   <PERSON>John Jones</PERSON> said he doesn't need an alarm clock in the <DATE>summer</DATE>.
   ``At 4, 5, 6 o'clock in the morning the birds start up,'' he
said. ``They'll take care of waking you up.''
   When the village first went after the birds, it suspended
balloons 6 feet around above trees. The balloons had reflective
``terror eyes'' stuck on, but the balloons blew away in wind storms
and the approach was abandoned.
   Wind machines were tried with little success. Ultimately,
<PERSON>Mathis</PERSON>, who doesn't want to kill the birds or tamper with the
trees, settled on the lights and taped screeches.
   The method chases the birds off the blocks under siege, but they
come back eventually or bother some other block. But <PERSON>Mathis</PERSON> isn't
ready to give up on the technique.
   ``You just have to be persistent,'' he said. ``It's a question
of who can last the longest and the <ORGANIZATION>Health Department</ORGANIZATION> so far is
keeping up with the birds.''
   Starlings, native to <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, were first released in <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>'s
<LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION> in <DATE>1890</DATE>. Two earlier attempts to introduce the birds
to <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> failed, but this one succeeded in a big way.
   Like the settlers before them, the starlings headed west and
reached the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> in 60 years. Now they occupy nearly every nook
and cranny of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>, numbering an estimated 200 million.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ880805-0145 </DOCNO>
<HL> And What to Do With the Birds? Well, NBC's Phone Number Is... </HL>
<AUTHOR> Lisa Ishikawa (WSJ Staff) </AUTHOR>
<SO> </SO>
<TEXT>
   La <LOCATION>Canada Flintridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, might gladly trade its peacocks for a few <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> pigeons. 

   The birds of beautiful plumage are Public Enemy No. 1 in the fashionable residential community in the hills northeast of <LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>. 
At a <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> meeting <DATE>earlier this week</DATE>, many of the 100 citizens present were there to demand that something be done about the wild fowl. 

   The birds, which bred in the wild after escaping captivity years ago, are charged with damaging property, creating a public nuisance, and other behavior unbecoming to a peacock. 

   Peacocks, native to <LOCATION>India</LOCATION>, were originally brought to <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION> to decorate the estates of the rich and famous. 
La Canadans say the particular birds in their community are descendants of peacocks imported mainly to help rid a local ranch of rattlesnakes. 

   Generally the La Canadans and peacocks got along until <DATE>1984</DATE>, when a brush fire drove away the wild birds' primary predators, coyotes. 
As the peacock population grew, however -- to an estimated 100 to 150 in <LOCATION>La Canada</LOCATION> today -- their popularity plummeted. 

   <PERSON>Virginia M. Gram</PERSON>, 49 years old, says the birds continually wreak havoc in her back yard. 
"They eat everything and drop messes like a small dog," says the lifelong resident. 
Their daily diet: <PERSON>Mrs. Gram</PERSON>'s lobelias, sweet williams and alyssums. 

   <PERSON>Donald B. Moser</PERSON>, 68, adds that the birds' crowing sounds "like a woman screaming, but only 10 times louder." 

   The birds also set off burglar alarms on occasion by pecking at their reflections in glass doors, says La <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Joan C. Feehan</PERSON>. 

   Several suggestions surfaced at the <ORGANIZATION>City Council</ORGANIZATION> meeting on how to resolve the problem. 
<PERSON>Walter R. Brant</PERSON>, a retired mechanical engineer, had a simple plan: "Just trap 'em with a snare, chop their head off, pluck 'em, clean 'em and stuff 'em." 

   Some compassion for the birds also was voiced. 
One resident suggested the peacock be named the official town bird to protect it from harm. 
And <PERSON>Susan Myers</PERSON>, identifying herself as "pro-peacock," recommended that residents put the birds to use by serving peacock eggs for breakfast. 
"I hear they're delicious," she said. 

   After more than two hours of discussion, the council instead decided to provide residents with live traps and to help relocate the birds to a nearby animal refuge. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06088105 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06088105 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  SAN-JOSE; NEIGHBORHOOD; UNUSUAL; BIRD  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  A peacock has visited a South San Jose neighborhood and the humans who usually
inhabit the place are worried.;    "I'm concerned the bird's going to get
hurt," said Mary Pollard. "I'm concerned the bird's going to hurt someone."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Local  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PEACOCK STRUTS INTO AREA
NEIGHBOR WORRIES ABOUT BIRD'S SAFETY  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     She called the <ORGANIZATION>Humane Society of Santa Clara Valley</ORGANIZATION> to come and take the
peacock away, but it only rescues sick or injured animals or accepts them if
someone brings them in.;    The peacock showed up <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> on <ORGANIZATION>Ariel
Drive</ORGANIZATION> near <LOCATION>Snell Avenue</LOCATION>, hopping from roof to roof and from car to car.
There's no evidence it is related to the peahen that has taken up residence
around Third and <LOCATION>San Carlos</LOCATION> streets in downtown <LOCATION>San Jose.</LOCATION>;    Flock at
cemetery;  <ORGANIZATION>Pollard</ORGANIZATION> thought her neighborhood bird might have wandered away from
<ORGANIZATION>Oak Hill Cemetery</ORGANIZATION>, where a flock of about 100 peacocks live, and used the
right of way for Highways 87 and 85 to get to <LOCATION>South San Jose.</LOCATION>;    But <PERSON>Doris
Bowdle</PERSON>, a spokeswoman for <ORGANIZATION>Oak Hill</ORGANIZATION>, doesn't think it's one of theirs.;    The
cemetery's peacocks usually just hop the fence and wander onto <PERSON>Curtner Avenue</PERSON>
or into a nearby mobile home park, she said. "They do come back or someone
brings them back," she said.;    <PERSON>Oak Hill</PERSON>'s peacocks, descendents of a pair
given to the cemetery nearly half a century ago, are fed by cemetery employees
and are "pretty tame," <PERSON>Bowdle</PERSON> said.;    The peahen who lives downtown seems to
have adapted well to the busy intersection she has called home for about five
months.;    After a story about her appeared in the <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION> <DATE>a month ago</DATE>,
<PERSON>Diane McCown</PERSON>, manager of a nearby <ORGANIZATION>Kinko</ORGANIZATION>'s, received some calls suggesting
places the peahen could live -- but someone would have to get her there. No
one has explained just how that might be done -- they are large birds -- so
the peahen continues to live in her adopted home.;    Peacocks love to preen;
<ORGANIZATION>Pollard</ORGANIZATION>, worried about the children who will be playing outdoors now that the
weather is warmer, hopes her visitor won't be quite so flexible.;    The birds
love reflection, and spend a lot of time preening in front of anything that
they can see an image of themselves in.;    <PERSON>Sue Howell</PERSON>, a wildlife specialist
with the <ORGANIZATION>Youth Science Institute</ORGANIZATION>, said peacocks are not native to the <LOCATION>Santa
Clara Valley</LOCATION> and any of the birds wandering around probably are someone's
pet.;    The recent storms disrupted a lot of animals, she said. And, it's the
mating season, a time when animals and birds might be expected to wander.;   
In any case, she said, peacocks "are very difficult to capture."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  JOANNE GRANT, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910328  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  March  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  3B  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  434  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday March 28, 1991
00088105,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880916-0042 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-16-88 0343EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Wishbone     09-16 0497</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Wishbone,0512</SECOND>
<HEAD>Mystery Solved: The Wishbone Is a Spring</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DANIEL Q. HANEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Science Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOSTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   A <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> scientist wanting to know why birds have
wishbones believes he has found the answer.
   ``The wishbone turns out to be a <DATE>spring</DATE>,'' said <PERSON>Farish A.
Jenkins</PERSON>, of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION>'s biology department.
   In a report published <DATE>today</DATE> in the journal Science, <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON>
described a new way of studying the inner mechanics of birds in
flight by taking movies of them with X-ray cameras. And he detailed
his first discovery with this tool _ the function of the wishbone.
impressed by the possibilities of X-ray movies as he was by their
initial revelation.
   ``It's a pioneering new method of studying birds,'' he said.
``We can actually see the movement of the skeletal elements during
flight. That's pretty exciting.''
   <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON> and two colleagues, <PERSON>Kenneth P. Dial</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> and
<PERSON>George E. Goslow Jr.</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Northern Arizona University</ORGANIZATION>, took X-ray
films of starlings flying in place against 20-45 mph winds in a
wind tunnel.
   The movies allowed the scientist to look at the birds' insides
and see how the various bones work during flight.
   Until now, researchers have tried to figure out such functions
by looking at the skeletons of dead birds or the outsides of live
ones.
   In their report, the researchers described the way the wishbone
bends each time a bird flaps its wings. At rest, the upper ends of
the starling's wishbone are 11 or 12 millimeters apart. But when
the wings descend, that distance stretches to 18 to 20 millimeters.
   Just why it bends this way is not clear. <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON> said the <DATE>spring</DATE>
doesn't seem to help the bird beat its wings more efficiently.
Instead, he theorized that it helps the bird breathe in more air
during flight so it can burn the extra energy it needs to stay
aloft.
   When a bird breathes, air flows first into air sacs scattered
throughout its body and then into its lungs. Among these sacs is
one between the two arms of the wishbone.
   The researchers speculate that as the bird beats its wings
downward, the wishbone spreads apart, opening the air sac so it
fills with air. Then, on the upswing, the bird's sternum squeezes
the air out again.
   ``What we suspect is that there is an alternating bellows
mechanism drawing air in and out of the sac and possibly in and out
of the lung,'' said <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON>.
   Not all birds have wishbones _ hummingbirds and some parrots are
among the exceptions _ but <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON> believes that the starling's
wishbone <DATE>spring</DATE> is typical of most feathered creatures, including
the turkey.
   Until now, scientists had assumed that the bone was simply a
strut between the bird's shoulders. However, <PERSON>Jenkins</PERSON> conceded that
the wishbone's springiness is obvious to Thanksgiving Day wish
makers.
   ``This is well known to everybody in the world,'' he said.
``It's only scientists who discover the obvious.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA030589-0254 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 27261 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 5, 1989, Sunday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 2; Column 5; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
492 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ENVIRONMENT: NOTES ABOUT YOUR SURROUNDINGS. 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
NESTING PLATFORMS: For more than 10 years, great blue herons have nested in 
eucalyptus trees at the <LOCATION>Santa Ana River Lakes</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION>. The "lakes," site of 
a fishing concession, are recharge basins controlled by the <ORGANIZATION>Orange County Water 
District</ORGANIZATION> near where <LOCATION>Tustin Avenue</LOCATION> crosses the <LOCATION>Riverside Freeway</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Last year, 14 nests produced 12 great blue heron chicks. And once the herons 
finished nesting, double-crested cormorants used the same nests and 
successfully raised young. Five nests produced 11 cormorant chicks, the first 
time the birds are known to have nested in the county. 
</P>
<P>
Ironically, increased nesting activity and perhaps other environmental factors 
have damaged the trees. In an effort to protect the bird habitat, artificial 
nesting structures will be built at the site by the <ORGANIZATION>County Environmental 
Management Agency</ORGANIZATION>, with advice from the state Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Game Department</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Erection of four nesting poles, each with three platforms, was to be completed 
in <DATE>February</DATE> but was delayed by a paper-work mix-up, according to <PERSON>Dale Dillon</PERSON> of 
the county environmental agency. His agency could put up the poles within two 
weeks, but that may be too late: herons at the site have already started to 
collect materials to reinforce nests from past seasons and will be laying eggs 
in the next few weeks. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Esther Burkett</PERSON>, a biologist for Fish and Game who is advising on the project, 
said erection of the poles may have to wait until next year if she decides the 
project will disturb the nesting birds too much. Whether the poles go up or not 
this year, the damaged trees will remain for the time being. 
</P>
<P>
Burkett believes this is the first time in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION> that nesting structures 
of this type will be tried for great blue herons, although they have been used 
successfully in <LOCATION>Minnesota</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The <LOCATION>Santa Ana River Lakes</LOCATION> site is the largest of several known great blue heron 
rookeries in the county (the rookeries are small, with only 24 to 30 total 
nests known in the county). Others include a few nests on an island in <LOCATION>Anaheim 
Lake</LOCATION>, some at undeveloped <ORGANIZATION>Wagon Wheel Regional Park</ORGANIZATION>, and at <LOCATION>Irvine Lake</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
SPEAKING OF BIRDS: Among the rare bird-sightings reported in <DATE>January</DATE> by <PERSON>Doug 
Willick</PERSON>, who compiles the sightings for American Bird magazine, is a pine 
warbler spotted at <ORGANIZATION>Yorba Regional Park</ORGANIZATION> on <DATE>Jan. 14</DATE> and presumed to be wintering 
there. A common bird of the <ORGANIZATION>Eastern</ORGANIZATION> pine forests, this marks the first time the 
pine warbler has been recorded in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
An immature bald eagle spotted flying through <LOCATION>Upper Newport Bay</LOCATION> on <DATE>Jan. 29</DATE> was 
only the second recorded sighting in the county in more than 10 years. 
Historically, the bird wintered in the county in small numbers. 
</P>
<P>
The American white pelicans that descended on the east <LOCATION>Anaheim</LOCATION> area in 
unprecedented numbers (several hundred were counted) peaked in <DATE>December</DATE> and 
have been gradually leaving the area. Several dozen of the impressive birds 
remain and are often seen in the <LOCATION>Santa Ana River Lakes</LOCATION> area. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA102390-0147 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 296723 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
October 23, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 2; Column 2; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
249 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CLIPBOARD; 
</P>
<P>
BREEDING BIRD: WHITE-THROATED SWIFT (AERONAUTES SAXATALIS) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Description: Easily recognizable from other North American swifts by its white 
underparts and contrasting black side patches below the wings. Length is six to 
seven inches. 
</P>
<P>
Habitat: Breeds mainly on coastal cliffs and canyons. 
</P>
<P>
Diet: Aerial foraging, captures flying insects. 
</P>
<P>
Displays: Mate in flight; pairs tumble together end-over-end as they copulate. 
</P>
<P>
Nest: Built deep inside crack or crevice of a canyon wall; feathers glued 
together and to wall with saliva. 
</P>
<P>
Eggs: Creamy white, unmarked; four-fifths of an inch in length. 
</P>
<P>
Conservation: Site tenacity (a tendency to return to nest site or breeding 
colony) has been disrupted by increased housing development on coastal cliffs 
and canyon areas, forcing swifts to nest in cracks of building walls. 
</P>
<P>
Voice: High-pitched jejejejejeje, in descending tones. 
</P>
<P>
Breeding bird atlas: To report bird breeding activity in your neighborhood, or 
to get information on the breeding bird atlas, call Sea and <ORGANIZATION>Sage Audubon 
Society</ORGANIZATION> members <PERSON>Sylvia Gallagher</PERSON>, (714) 962-8990, or <PERSON>Nancy Kenyon</PERSON>, (714) 
786-3160. 
</P>
<P>
Note: Map is divided into 5-kilometer squares so that <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> 
volunteers can more easily survey areas on a regular basis. 
</P>
<P>
Sources: Sea and Sage Audubon Society; "The Birder's Handbook," <PERSON>Ehrlich</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dobkin</PERSON> 
and Wheye, Fireside Books (<DATE>1988</DATE>); "Field Guide to the Birds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>," 
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1987</DATE>); "Birds of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>: Status and 
Distribution," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1981</DATE>). 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Areas where breeding activity has been confirmed.; Drawing, WHITE-THROATED 
SWIFT 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-16611</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EAIATAESFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940108
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  08 JAN 94 / Travel: A beautiful swamp - James Henderson enjoys the
wildlife of Trinidad's Caroni mangrove
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By JAMES HENDERSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
It took some persuasion to convince me that a trip to a swamp would be the
highlight of my visit to <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>. What do you do in 40 square miles of
mangrove and sumptuous black mud? But <PERSON>James Madoo</PERSON> was a salesman who loved
his subject, and I did not reckon with the depth of mystery and the variety
of the Caroni swamp.
<LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> has an extraordinary variety of birdlife (more than 400 species) in
its 1,800 square miles of coastal swamps, plains and forested mountains.
'Iere,' the old Indian name for <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>, meant 'Land of the Hummingbird,'
and there are 16 species on the island.
Aerodynamically they have about as much chance of flying as a helicopter. In
their efforts to keep airborne they must beat their wings about 50 times a
second. Their metabolic rate is so high that they must constantly top up
with nectar. At night, hummingbirds switch off and become stiff as a wooden
board.
Trinidad lies on a migratory route and so, not unlike the tourists,
thousands of birds flock there from the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> each year to avoid the
northern winter. Many other species have spilled over from <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>,
just seven miles away. These are truly exotic, adorned with bright tropical
colours and quirks of nature that only their mates could possibly find
attractive.
Some are designed for perfect flying, with built-in aerofoils and spoilers;
others are lumbered with ridiculous encumbrances. The poor wattled jacana
has silly-looking, overlong toes and an embarrassing red splurge on its
face. And just imagine having the bill of a toucan.
The diminutive male white bearded mannikin spends 90 per cent of its waking
hours displaying itself. It flits backwards and forwards, all to entice
female mannikins to its court. Deeper in the rain forest there is a bird
that strikes up chucka-chucka-chucka-chucka, like an unsuccessful
starter-motor, and another that calls boing, boing . . . boing. Heaven knows
what a violaceous trogon does back at the nest.
Of all the mournful, sceptical, quizzical-looking birds you see on the
island, the most majestic is the scarlet ibis, and it was this I went to see
in <LOCATION>Caroni</LOCATION> swamp. I travelled by mini-bus, or, as the contrary Trinidadians
prefer to call it, a maxi-taxi - more a mobile discotheque than a bus. The
carnival rhythms pumped relentlessly on, but soon the bustle of Port of
<LOCATION>Spain</LOCATION> receded and the overwhelming greens of the <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION> countryside loomed
around us.
At the swamp I met <ORGANIZATION>Winston Nanan</ORGANIZATION>, a stocky and quietly-spoken man. His
knowledge of Trinidadian wildlife is encyclopaedic. He began by telling us
of the swamp and its fragile ecosystem, of the 168 species of bird that can
be seen there and of the efforts being made to protect them. Anecdotes,
including hair-raising stories of disturbing armed poachers, were drawn from
30 years of swamp life.
We set off into the mangroves. <PERSON>James Madoo</PERSON> accelerated the outboard for a
moment and then left the boat to cruise as we listened. Suddenly, with a
splash, a spectacled cayman pushed off into the water and cruised away with
lazy movements of its tail.
A mangrove tree can cover whole acres. It is an endless tangle of brown
roots, sprouting willy-nilly from the mud, miniature flying buttresses run
riot topped with bushy leaves.
As we crept into each new spot, the favoured haunt of a particular species,
the peace would take a moment to return, but soon the birds would appear.
With a cock of the head the guides held our attention.
The swamp started to come alive. A white-necked heron stood perched on one
foot in a stretch of open water, shoulders hunched and immobile, as it had
been for hours (except occasionally to change legs), waiting to strike for
food. Skulking around the edge, a green-backed heron preferred to stalk,
holding its body horizontal over the water.
A lonesome boop-boop-boop rang out - a clapper rail - and a second later a
little character with a spiked haircut (called topknot) flitted past with a
grating hiss: a yellow-bellied elaenia. It fled shamelessly at the
appearance of a fearsome tiger heron. Suddenly, the wattled jacana's
rebellious toes made sense - they were perfect for keeping balance over
lilies.
As evening drew in we made our way to the scarlet ibis sanctuary. Moments
later the first pair breezed in, a flash of red as they flapped and landed.
Scarlet ibises are gregarious creatures, and as many as 5,000 return
nightly, after feeding in <LOCATION>Venezuela</LOCATION>, to roost in the mangroves.
The ibises are impossibly red, the strongest scarlet, like a British
postbox. The colour derives from the chemical carotin, which they find in
the little crustaceans in the swamp. They stand about 3ft high, with wings
3ft when outstretched; their 8in bills curve downwards.
For a while, as well as being <LOCATION>Trinidad</LOCATION>'s national bird, the scarlet ibis was
also something of a national dish, and in the <DATE>1960s</DATE> numbers were dangerously
low (they were also hunted for their feathers). Away from their own
environment, or in captivity, ibis fade to a dull pink, a wan reminder of
the real thing. Now that they have some protection in the sanctuary, they
have returned to the swamp to roost and have started to breed again.
The mating season lasts from the <DATE>end of April into June</DATE>, when you will see
pairs flying high, descending in ever- decreasing circles before they
disappear behind a curtain of mangrove leaves. Nesting lasts until <DATE>August</DATE>.
Soon there were 50 ibis in the air at a time, gliding in above us.
Momentarily a tree would burst aflame as they stretched their wings to the
full, flapping and settling. In the golden evening light the mangroves,
flecked white with the cattle egrets, took on a deep scarlet glow.
But it faded with the dusk. The oysters on the mangrove roots snapped shut
for the night and we returned home.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>TTZ  Trinidad and Tobago, Caribbean.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7999 Amusement and Recreation, NEC.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>NEWS  General News.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page XI
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901215-0085 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-12-15-90 1557EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-BirdCount     12-15 0334</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bird Count,0390</SECOND>
<HEAD>Birdwatchers Begin Holiday Bird Tally Of Western Hemisphere</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID GERMAIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEWTON HOOK, N.Y. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Three ruddy-cheeked people - burs stuck
in their clothes, snorting steam in the cold dawn - come hissing
and warbling out of the woods.
   But there's no need to flee - they're part of the <ORGANIZATION>National
Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>'s 91st annual Christmas Bird Count, in which bird
watchers across <LOCATION>North and South America</LOCATION> began their tallies
<DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   When it ends <DATE>Jan. 2</DATE>, 42,000 birdwatchers will have counted
upwards of 100 million birds.
   It doesn't seem so large when you watch a tiny piece of it, such
as the count along the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION> in the hamlet of <LOCATION>Newton Hook</LOCATION>,
about 100 miles north of <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>.
   ``<PERSON>Robins</PERSON>, four robins across the river,'' calls <PERSON>Becky Holberton</PERSON>,
one of three counters scanning the river with telescopes and
binoculars.
   ``Waterfowl on the flat!'' she cries moments later.
   ``Good spotting,'' answers her companion, <PERSON>Richard Guthrie</PERSON>.
``<LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> geese.''
   Earlier, <PERSON>Guthrie</PERSON> stood in a barn tugging on a rope from the
roof, trying to flush out roosting birds.
   ``I see rock doves,'' called <PERSON>Kathy Schneider</PERSON>, the third counter,
waiting outside to see what birds flew out. ``And you're scaring
the daylights out of them.''
   The annual count ``is a good indicator of the health of our
environment,'' said <PERSON>Holberton</PERSON>, an ornithology student at the <ORGANIZATION>State
University of New York</ORGANIZATION> at <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>.
   When populations dwindle, it generally means human development
is destroying birds' habitats, as in the destruction of tropical
rain forests in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, she said.
   ``We'd all like to point our fingers at <LOCATION>South and Central
America</LOCATION> without worrying about the destruction in our own
backyards,'' <PERSON>Holberton</PERSON> said. ``But we really can't do that anymore.
It's a global problem.''
   Birdwatching teams will cover birds in about 1,600 zones, each
15 miles in diameter, counting as many birds as they can in one
day. The results will be published next year in <ORGANIZATION>American Birds</ORGANIZATION>, a
<ORGANIZATION>National Audubon</ORGANIZATION> journal.
   The counts began in <DATE>1900</DATE>, when environmentalists rebelled
against Christmas hunting competitions, said <PERSON>Geoff LeBaron</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Christmas Bird Count</ORGANIZATION> editor at <ORGANIZATION>American Birds</ORGANIZATION>. Conservationist
<PERSON>Frank Chapman</PERSON> countered with a plan to ``count the birds rather
than try to shoot them,'' <PERSON>LeBaron</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010289-0079 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1989, Monday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part 2; Page 3; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
692 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BEAK COUNT; 
</P>
<P>
BIRDERS TALLY TEALS, LOONS AND THE LIKE IN ANNUAL RITUAL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By GEORGE FRANK, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Loren Hays</PERSON> had been in bed for hours when most people were just starting to 
celebrate New Year's Eve. 
</P>
<P>
His sleep was important. He got up in the darkness <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, made his way 
toward the coastal wetlands and waited for the sun to rise so he could look 
through a telescope and spot such species as the double-crested cormorant, 
northern shoveler, blue-winged teal, common loon and the long-billed dowitcher. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hays</PERSON>, a biologist at <LOCATION>Cal State Long Beach</LOCATION> and for the federal government, 
gathered with his wife, <LOCATION>Debra</LOCATION>, and five others, including <ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> 
and Game wildlife biologist <PERSON>Esther Burkett</PERSON>, for an annual bird count in a 
small, rain-soaked parking lot at the <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica Ecological Reserve</ORGANIZATION> near 
<LOCATION>Pacific Coast Highway</LOCATION> just south of <LOCATION>Huntington Harbour</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
The Christmas season count, conducted throughout the country by members of the 
<ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, collects valuable data on bird numbers and habitats. 
</P>
<P>
As the sun made its first appearance of the day, about the time many New Year's 
Eve revelers went to bed, <PERSON>Hays</PERSON>' group fanned out over the state <ORGANIZATION>Department of 
Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game's wetland reserve to count birds. 
</P>
<P>
Other groups met at other places along the coast to count birds and gather 
information about species. One group group went by boat to make its count 
<DATE>Sunday</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
"They used to have bird shoots around Christmas," <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> said. "They would go out 
and blast everything in sight. In the late '40s or early '50s, someone decided 
that counting the birds might be a better alternative than shooting them." 
</P>
<P>
So each year, members of the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> and others, who like to call 
themselves birders, go out and count the birds. There are two counts each year, 
one inland and one along the coast. 
</P>
<P>
"Much of the information that is gathered during the counts is now used as a 
scientific database," <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> said. 
</P>
<P>
The counters carry official tally sheets that list about 180 species of birds. 
</P>
<P>
The advanced birder in each counting group -- in this case <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> -- peers 
through a telescope scanning the wetlands for the birds. Hays called out their 
names as he found them. 
</P>
<P>
It went something like this: 
</P>
<P>
"Five northern harriers. Thirty-five long-billed dowitchers. Thirty-five common 
loon. One bufflehead and twelve northern pintail." 
</P>
<P>
As <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> rattled off the names, <PERSON>Debbie Hays</PERSON> thumbed through the pages to find 
the species and note the numbers. 
</P>
<P>
"A red-breasted merganser. A pied-billed grebe. Two surf scoters and an 
American coot." 
</P>
<P>
Then the group moved to a new position. Hays began his search again. He looked 
around the estuary for birds. When he found them, he called out their species 
too. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Hays</PERSON> did not need a book to identify the birds found <DATE>Sunday</DATE>. Asked how many 
species he could identify by sight, he modestly replied, "Less than a 
thousand." 
</P>
<P>
Last year was a particularly good one for the coastal counters. They spotted 
214 species, the second highest count in the nation. 
</P>
<P>
"I don't think we'll come close to that this year," <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> said. "Many of the 
mountain birds are not here this year." 
</P>
<P>
Counting birds is not an easy job, and prospective counters are warned ahead of 
time about the long hours. 
</P>
<P>
"Remember, every daylight hour counts," warned a newsletter for the <ORGANIZATION>Sea &amp; 
Sage Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, a local chapter. "One year, rough-winged swallows, 
northern water thrushes, lesser nighthawks and western screech owls were all 
found as the sun was setting or later. That means four species would have been 
missed if counters had quit early." 
</P>
<P>
"It is the world's greatest hobby, and I've tried about everything," <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> said 
of birding. "No day is ever the same. There's always a surprise. It's the 
thrill of seeing something new or rare, the number of species or the numbers in 
a particular species." 
</P>
<P>
Other birds spotted <DATE>Sunday</DATE> included some song sparrows, a black-billed plover, 
a <ORGANIZATION>Belding</ORGANIZATION>'s <LOCATION>Savannah</LOCATION> sparrow, a great blue heron, ruddy ducks and a brown 
pelican. 
</P>
<P>
Also spotted waddling along the water was one large, white, domestic goose. 
</P>
<P>
Pointing to the goose, which looked out of place surrounded by the smaller wild 
birds, <PERSON>Hays</PERSON> noted that people who abandon domestic birds in wildlife reserves 
can be arrested by a game warden. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Birdwatcher at Bolsa Chica, and San Gabriel Mountains. KEN HIVELY / Los 
Angeles Times; Photo, A black-necked stilt catches the first rays of the sun at 
Bolsa Chica. ; Photo, Keeping tabs on the teals are Arthur Davenport . . . ; 
Photo, . . . Debra Hays and . . . ; Photo, . . . her husband, Loren. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BIRDS; CENSUS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111789-0193 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 137291 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 17, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Orange County Life; Part N; Page 2; Column 3 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
326 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BREEDING BIRDS: EUROPEAN STARLING 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Clipboard researched by Kathie Bozanich Susan Davis Greene and Janice L. 
Jones / Los Angeles Times; Graphics by Doris Shields / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
EUROPEAN STARLING 
</P>
<P>
(Sturnus vulgaris) 
</P>
<P>
Description: Adult in breeding plumage is iridescent black with a yellow bill. 
In fresh fall plumage, feathers are tipped with white and buff, giving an 
overall speckled appearance; bill becomes brownish. Short, square tail, stocky 
body, and short, broad-based pointed wings that appear pale gray from below. 
</P>
<P>
Habitat: Mostly open fields, woodland, suburbia and cities. 
</P>
<P>
Diet: Other inverts and berries. 
</P>
<P>
Displays: Courting male 
</P>
<P>
adopts variety of postures while vocalizing; highest intensity includes 
flailing wings in hunched stance. 
</P>
<P>
Nest: In any handy cavity; slovenly cup of grass, twigs, forbs, rootlets and 
straw. 
</P>
<P>
Eggs: Pale bluish or greenish white, marked with browns. 
</P>
<P>
Natural history notes: Starlings were introduced in <LOCATION>New York City</LOCATION>'s <LOCATION>Central 
Park</LOCATION> one hundred years ago and quickly spread across the continent. Bold and 
aggressive, it often competes successfully with native species for nest holes. 
Varied call notes include squeaks, warbles, chirps and twittering; also 
imitates the songs of other species. Outside of nesting season, starlings are 
usually seen in large flocks, sometimes in company with grackles and 
blackbirds. Within one century, the 60 starlings introduced to <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION> 
have increased to over 200 million. 
</P>
<P>
Breeding bird atlas: To report bird breeding activity in your neighborhood, or 
to get information on the breeding bird atlas (now in its fifth and final 
year), call Sea and <ORGANIZATION>Sage Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> member <PERSON>Nancy Kenyon</PERSON>, (714) 786-3160. 
</P>
<P>
Note: Map is divided into 5-kilometer squares so that <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> 
volunteers can more easily survey areas on a regular basis. 
</P>
<P>
Sources: Sea and Sage Audubon Society; "The Birder's Handbook," <PERSON>Ehrlich</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dobkin</PERSON> 
and Wheye, Fireside Books (<DATE>1988</DATE>); "Field Guide to the Birds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>," 
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1987</DATE>); "Birds of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>: Status and 
Distribution," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1981</DATE>). 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Indicates 5-kilometer-square areas where breeding activity has been 
confirmed. ; Drawing, EUROPEAN STARLING, RUSS ARASMITH / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA111089-0111 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 132721 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 10, 1989, Friday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Orange County Life; Part N; Page 2; Column 4 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
317 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
BREEDING BIRDS: LONG-EARED OWL 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By Clipboard researched by Kathie Bozanich and Susan Davis Greene / Los Angeles 
Times; Graphics by Doris Shields / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
LONG-EARED OWL (<ORGANIZATION>Asio</ORGANIZATION> otus) 
</P>
<P>
Description: Slender with long, close-set ear tufts. Boldly streaked and barred 
on breast and belly; facial disk is rusty. 
</P>
<P>
Habitat: Conifer and mixed conifer- deciduous forest, especially near water, 
parks, orchards and farm woodlands. 
</P>
<P>
Diet: Mostly rodents; rarely amphibians, reptiles, fish and insects. 
</P>
<P>
Displays: The courting male flies erratic and zigzags with deep, slow 
wingbeats, occasionally gliding and clapping wings together beneath his body. 
</P>
<P>
Nest: Usually in abandoned nests (especially those of crow, also squirrel, 
hawk, magpie, heron, raven). Built of small sticks, inner bark strips and pine 
needles. Female selects the site. 
</P>
<P>
Eggs: White, 1.6 inches long. 
</P>
<P>
Natural history notes: This owl is a night hunter and is able to locate even 
faint sounds with remarkable accuracy. At night it flies over open fields and 
marshes, during the day it roosts in trees, close to the trunk. 
</P>
<P>
Familiarity with the environment, especially such things as the heights of 
favorite perches above the ground, seems to be essential to the owl's ability 
to pounce on prey. Hearing helps replace the absence of sight, but intimate 
knowledge of the habitat completes the job. 
</P>
<P>
Is more gregarious in winter; flocks may roost together. Generally a silent 
bird, except during breeding season. His common call is one or more long 
hooo's. 
</P>
<P>
Breeding bird atlas: To report bird breeding activity in your neighborhood, or 
to get information on the breeding bird atlas (now in its fifth and final 
year), call Sea and <ORGANIZATION>Sage Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> member <PERSON>Nancy Kenyon</PERSON>, (714) 786-3160. 
</P>
<P>
Sources: Sea and Sage Audubon Society; "The Birder's Handbook," <PERSON>Ehrlich</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dobkin</PERSON> 
and Wheye, Fireside Books (<DATE>1988</DATE>); "Field Guide to the Birds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>," 
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1987</DATE>); "Birds of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>: Status and 
Distribution," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1981</DATE>). 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Note: Map is divided into five-kilometer squares so that Audubon Society 
volunteers can more easily survey areas on a regular basis. Indicates 
five-kilometer-square areas where breeding activity has been confirmed.; 
Drawing, ILLUSTRATION BY RUSS ARASMITH / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA010290-0090 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 156591 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 2, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 3; Column 1; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
565 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
ORANGE COUNTY FOCUS: WILDLIFE. THE FIGHT FOR SPACE. ; 
</P>
<P>
AS HOMES MARCH UP HILLSIDES AND OFFICES SPROUT ON FIELDS, ORANGE COUNTY'S 
WILDLIFE BATTLES FOR ITS DWINDLNG HABITAT.; 
</P>
<P>
AUDUBON, IRVINE CO. PROTECT THE HERONS 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By SHANNON SANDS 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
<PERSON>Peter Bloom</PERSON> used to watch the great blue herons on <LOCATION>Irvine Lake</LOCATION> when he played 
there as a child. 
</P>
<P>
Today, <PERSON>Bloom</PERSON> is vice president of the Sea and Sage chapter of the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon 
Society</ORGANIZATION> and he is working with the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION> on a plan to build new homes in 
his childhood playground without disturbing the county's largest colony of the 
giant, graceful birds. 
</P>
<P>
Bloom and <PERSON>Ginny Chester</PERSON>, also of the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>, helped negotiate the East 
Orange General Plan, which was approved by the <ORGANIZATION>Orange City Council</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>December</DATE>, 
so that the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION>'s development plans would not endanger the heron. 
</P>
<P>
At <ORGANIZATION>Bloom</ORGANIZATION>'s suggestion, the company agreed to relocate two housing tracts and 
preserve 200 acres of wild oak groves near the proposed <ORGANIZATION>Limestone Canyon 
Regional Park</ORGANIZATION>. It also agreed to a five-year study and relocation plan for a 
colony of great blue herons that nest on the north shore of the lake where the 
company wants to build a road. 
</P>
<P>
About 30 pairs of herons nest in sycamore and oak trees along the shore of the 
<LOCATION>Irvine Lake</LOCATION>, also known as <ORGANIZATION>Santiago Reservoir</ORGANIZATION>. The <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION> has agreed to 
either get the birds to move to new nests or abandon its plans to build a road 
there, said <PERSON>Lee Jones</PERSON>, resource specialist for <ORGANIZATION>Michael Brandman Associates</ORGANIZATION>, 
which prepared the environmental impact report for the development. 
</P>
<P>
In the study, biologists will determine where the herons eat, how many are 
breeding successfully and where they go in the winter. They will also 
coordinate the study with the federal Fish and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> and the state 
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Fish</ORGANIZATION> and Game, <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> said. Leg bands will be placed on the young 
birds to keep track of them, he said. 
</P>
<P>
After studying the birds, the biologists hope to encourage the herons to nest 
somewhere else, either along the southwest edge of the lake, on an island in 
the lake or elsewhere in <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
In <LOCATION>Orange County</LOCATION>, herons are found along the <LOCATION>Santa Ana River</LOCATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Bolsa Chica 
Reserve</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Upper Newport Bay</LOCATION>, <PERSON>San Joaquin Marsh</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Anaheim Lake</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Dana Point 
Harbor</ORGANIZATION>. <PERSON>Bloom</PERSON> said the <LOCATION>Irvine Lake</LOCATION> rookery is the largest in the county. 
</P>
<P>
Jones said the relocation program might include the planting of vegetation at 
other sites and the use of nesting platforms or heron decoys to encourage the 
birds to breed elsewhere. 
</P>
<P>
After monitoring the new nesting site for three years and conducting annual 
counts of the breeding colonies, biologists will decide whether they can 
develop in the area without damaging the heron colony. 
</P>
<P>
Under an agreement between the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> and the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION>, the road 
could be built if at least <PERCENT>50%</PERCENT> of the birds from the <LOCATION>Irvine Lake</LOCATION> rookery are 
nesting elsewhere. If not, the company could continue the relocation program or 
abandon its plans to build the road. 
</P>
<P>
"If the <ORGANIZATION>Irvine Co.</ORGANIZATION> does this right, meaning funding the study properly, this 
could be a one-of-a-kind study," <PERSON>Bloom</PERSON> said. Not much is known about the habits 
of great blue herons, he said. 
</P>
<P>
Adult great blue herons stand three to four feet high, with a wing span of 
about six feet. Sometimes mistaken for cranes, herons can be distinguished from 
other birds by the U-shape of their neck in flight. 
</P>
<P>
Although they were hunted for their colorful blue-gray plumage earlier in the 
century, great blue herons are not now listed as endangered or threatened. But 
biologists say that development has reduced the habitat of herons, putting them 
at risk. SHANNON SANDS 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Pete Bloom of the Audubon Society is working to save the great blue 
heron. KARI RENE HALL / Los Angeles Times; Photo, The great blue heron, not yet 
endangered, is sometimes mistaken for a crane. MARK BOSTER / Los Angeles Times; 
Photo, FOCUS Peter Bloom of the Audubon Society is working with the Irvine Co. 
on a plan to build new homes in his childhood playground of Irvine Lake without 
disturbing the graceful great blue herons. 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column; Brief 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BIRDS; WILDLIFE MANAGEMENT; HABITATS; AUDUBON SOCIETY; IRVINE CO; ORANGE COUNTY 
-- DEVELOPMENT AND REDEVELOPMENT 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ911126-0118
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
911126-0118.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
   Flying Rat Trap Finds Home in Central Park
   ----
   By Marie Winn
</HL>
<DATE>
11/26/91
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A12
</SO>
<LP>
   New York -- It was around 7 a.m. on Sept. 24, that Dorothy
Poole, a Manhattan market researcher and a passionate bird
watcher, first saw the Central Park barn owl. A bird class
under the aegis of the American Museum of Natural History had
made its way to the Ramble, a little wilderness in the heart
of Central Park, when a sudden commotion arose. "Those
bluejays are mobbing something," said Steve Quinn, the
group's leader. "It might be a hawk or an owl." A moment
later Ms. Poole saw the barn owl sitting in plain sight on a
horizontal branch of a sweetgum tree. It was asleep.
   Accompanying Ms. Poole's group that morning was police
Officer Daniel Delia of the Central Park precinct. Though he
was there in the line of duty (the Ramble is not always a
safe place), he, too, was excited about the owl. Indeed,
Officer Delia was the first to find an owl pellet at the base
of the sweetgum tree. An owl pellet is not an appetizing
concept. Owls eat their prey whole. Then they regurgitate the
stuff they cannot digest -- fur, bones, claws, teeth and the
like -- in the form of a cylindrical mass called a pellet.
Officer Delia's find contained a recognizable rat skull and
some bones.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   A few days later the owl moved to a nearby paulownia tree.
There it sat day after day for almost two months, always on
the same branch some 30 feet off the ground. "Roost
fidelity," the bird books call such behavior. It means that
the bird has found a favorable hunting spot.
   The barn owl, Tyto alba, is easily distinguished from all
other owls by its long, heart-shaped white or golden facial
mask, which gives it a rather simian aspect. This has led to
one of its vernacular names, the monkey-faced owl. It has "a
slightly creepy expression," according to the Birdwatcher's
Companion, an encyclopedic handbook. Nevertheless it is
considered a beautiful bird. It is also an exceptionally
useful bird: In a life span of about 10 years, a single barn
owl can consume something like 11,000 rodents, according to
<PERSON>Paul Johnsgard</PERSON>, the author of "North American Owls."
   Indeed, the barn owl's entire evolutionary history has
designed it for catching rodents -- a flying rat-trap,
someone once called it. Its eyesight and hearing are
particularly adapted for hunting small prey in the dark. Its
wing design enables it to hover for over a minute without
stalling, as it homes in on its prey. And thanks to a special
layer of soft velvety feathers, the barn owl's flight, like
that of most other owls, is completely silent. This is bad
news for the hapless rodent in its path.
   The word "owl," by the way, is onomatopoeic in origin, and
descends from the same root as the word "ululate" which means
to howl. Most owls do howl, in some form or another. Some
give off the traditional "whoo, whoo" that owls are known
for. The barn owl's howl, however, is closer to a
bone-chilling shriek, according to <ORGANIZATION>Julio de la Torre</ORGANIZATION>, author
of "Owls: Their Life and Behavior."
   By now, the <LOCATION>Central Park</LOCATION> barn owl has become something of
a celebrity. Barn owls, after all, are rare visitors to the
park. Little crowds congregate in the clearing where the owl
is roosting. Passers-by observe people looking up into a
tree. They inquire, look up in turn, and suddenly exclaim "I
see it] My God] It's really an owl]" <PERSON>Joseph DiConstanza</PERSON>, a
research and field biologist at the natural history museum,
often "nips over" during his lunch break. His friend <PERSON>Sandy
Faison</PERSON>, a vice president at <ORGANIZATION>J.P. Morgan Securities</ORGANIZATION>, followed
his directions to the owl on <DATE>Nov. 3</DATE>. "I've been looking for a
barn owl for 14 years," he said with considerable feeling, as
he stood before the paulownia tree and gazed at the sleeping
raptor.
   Because the owl sits and sleeps quietly on its preferred
roost for most of the day, some people contend that it is a
fake, a cardboard decoy. But on one occasion a bird watcher
made mouse-like squeaking noises and suddenly the owl opened
its dark eyes. It looked from side to side several times,
swaying weirdly. Then it went back to sleep. So far, no one
has heard it utter a sound. Not a long-drawn scream, nor a
loud raspy hiss, sss-ksch, nor even the chuckling note which
is like a snore -- as its various utterances are described in
the <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society Encyclopedia of North American Birds</ORGANIZATION>.
   No one has seen it glide silently from its perch after
dark to go a-hunting. No one has seen it raise its wings
suddenly, then plummet down to grasp a doomed rat in its
cruel talons. No one has seen it return triumphantly to its
branch and swallow its prey whole, head first, tail
disappearing last. But serious victims of owl fever find
themselves imagining such events at odd moments, especially
after nightfall. That's the best they can do, for certainly
no one with any sense would enter the lawless Ramble at
night, not even the growing coterie of visitors captivated by
the owl's beauty and mystery.
   But love is inevitably accompanied by anxiety. Nearby
signs proclaiming "Caution: Rat Poison," cause many an owl
idolater to fear that the great winged ratter might eat a
tainted rodent and die. Not to worry, says <PERSON>Marc Matsil</PERSON> of the
<ORGANIZATION>Parks Department</ORGANIZATION>. Precisely to protect owl and hawk visitors
to the park, the department recently switched from a
decoagulant type of poison to a substance called Quintox that
is not toxic to birds. Yet all is not well for the barn owl,
according to <PERSON>Todd Culver</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Cornell Lab of Ornithology</ORGANIZATION>.
The species is declining across its entire range, due to
habitat loss and to farmers' increasing use of rodenticides
(rather than barn owls).
   By the <DATE>second week of November</DATE> the paulownia tree was
almost bare. Most of its large heart-shaped leaves lay on the
ground and only scattered clusters of its pecan-shaped fruit
remained. I knew perfectly well that the owl could not stay
there much longer -- it had lost its cover. Yet when I
arrived one day for my daily visit and found the owl missing
I couldn't accept the idea that it had gone for good. I
continued to check the clearing day after day, hoping against
hope that the bird would return.
   On <DATE>Nov. 16</DATE>, a <DATE>Saturday</DATE>, I had gone to look for the owl one
last time. As I was leaving, I ran into a man with
binoculars, the badge of the bird fraternity. "You haven't
seen the owl?" I asked without much hope. "Oh, yes, I just
found its new tree," he answered, explaining his success in
this way: "I asked myself: `If I were an owl, where would I
go?' Then I looked for the most foliated tree near its old
roost."
   The man turned out to be <PERSON>Curtis Berger</PERSON>, a law professor at
the <ORGANIZATION>Columbia Law School</ORGANIZATION> and a bird watcher with more than 600
birds on his life list. This, however, was his first barn
owl. He led me to a large <LOCATION>Norway</LOCATION> maple not far from the owl's
original roost. And there was my barn owl, sitting on a high
branch. Framed with dark green foliage, it was beautifully
visible. The sun glistened on its spotted golden breast and I
must admit that my heart actually jumped for joy at the
sight.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06252118 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06252118 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  BOOK; REVIEW  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  IF YOU hear the words "National Audubon Society," birds and bird-watchers
probably come to mind. It's an identity any environmental group would covet.
But to Peter A.A. Berle, the lawyer who took over the venerable conservation
organization in the mid-1980s, it's all wrong.;   "The bird image hurts us,"
declares one Berle associate. "The old school of conservationists, who were
interested in wildlife for wildlife's sake, are dying out. We're left with a
populace that is interested in the environment to the degree that it touches
their private lives, i.e., waste disposal."  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Arts &amp; Books  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  A HARD LOOK AT AUDUBON SOCIETY  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Magazines  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     However that may be, reporter Dyan Zaslowsky makes a persuasive case in the
<DATE>September-October Harrowsmith</DATE> Country Life that the changes <PERSON>Berle</PERSON> is carrying
out at the <ORGANIZATION>National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> court its self-destruction. As prominent
an old friend of the society as <PERSON>Roger Tory Peterson</PERSON> told Zaslowsky that <PERSON>John
James Audubon</PERSON> would be "absolutely bewildered" by the changes.;   Zaslowsky
acknowledges that <PERSON>Berle</PERSON> put a financially messy house in order. But she
wonders openly about his wisdom in spending members' contributions on a brand
new headquarters building, expensive image consultants and protracted legal
wrangling with the <ORGANIZATION>New York State Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>. Critics charge <PERSON>Berle</PERSON> with
empire building and <ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION> envy (<ORGANIZATION>Audubon</ORGANIZATION> claims 600,000 members to
<ORGANIZATION>Greenpeace</ORGANIZATION>'s 2 million).;   "We like birds," says <PERSON>Berle</PERSON>. "We just don't think
birds are the end of it." As part of his effort to broaden the appeal and
build the society membership, <PERSON>Berle</PERSON> recently abandoned its emblem. The
graceful egret in flight gave way to a corporate-style logo with a flag motif
that puts Les Line, whom <PERSON>Berle</PERSON> removed <DATE>last spring</DATE> after 25 years of editing
Audubon magazine, in mind of "a certain brand of roach killer.";   As a
casualty in <LOCATION>Berle</LOCATION>'s drive to remake the society's image through its most
visible platform, Line is not impartial. But his analysis of larger forces at
work in the environmental movement has a compelling ring: "The naturalists
have been replaced by ecocrats who are more comfortable on Capitol Hill than
in the woods, fields, meadows, mountains and swamps. You can certainly argue
that garbage and other issues are related, but there are organizations already
addressing those things. . . . Environmentalists have grown so homogenized
that there are fewer and fewer of them who want to place birds and wildlife
first.";   Souls for sale in <LOCATION>Hollywood</LOCATION>; An award-winning short story writer,
who also chooses to remain anonymous, sold her soul -- admittedly for lots of
money -- to create scripts for a TV sitcom with her friend <PERSON>Maxine</PERSON>. Her diary
of a descent into inanity is in the <DATE>September-October</DATE> Buzz: "I'm numb. I can't
tell any more if this script is any good; I can't even tell if it makes sense.
Why are we doing this? I think of a story <PERSON>Maxine</PERSON> told me about how her husband
spent hours pitching jokes to an impatient producer. " 'Yeah, yeah,' the
producer kept saying. "Like that. But funny.' Who knows what's funny any more?
In a world where everything's supposed to be ridiculous, can anything really
seem ridiculous?";   Compelling story of abuse; Yet another writer has reason
to remain anonymous. He's telling the painful story of his 7-year-old son's
sexual abuse by a trusted teacher's aide. Such stories are becoming
commonplace, regrettably. This one, in the <DATE>September-October</DATE> Mother Jones, is
different, and compelling, in at least two respects: The little boy's
agonizing experience of abuse triggers the father's memory of his own abuse as
a child -- by an older friend he still knows and sees regularly. And the
experience of bringing the boy's abuser to justice proves nearly as
destructive, in the hands of insensitive prosecutors and counselors, as the
abuse itself.;   The laws of reality; Now that computers have been able to
give us a plausibly pregnant <PERSON>Bruce Willis</PERSON>, and a good laugh, it's worth
wondering again -- as <PERSON>Marshall Blonsky</PERSON> does in the <DATE>September</DATE> Allure -- about
the implications of manipulating images of presumed reality. One professional
photographer quoted here, <PERSON>Barry Blackman</PERSON>, feels liberated by the technology:
"I am no longer hindered by the laws of physics and the laws of reality." <PERSON>Fred
Ritchin</PERSON>, a critic, worries: "If the photograph is thought of as a plaything to
be retouched, then when real photographs tell us something serious in the
future, who's going to believe them?" (box)  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  CHARLES TRUEHEART, Washington Post  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910908  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  September  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  24  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  726  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, September 8, 1991
00252118,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA110690-0169 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 303983 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
November 6, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 2; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
286 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
CLIPBOARD; 
</P>
<P>
BREEDING BIRD: GREEN-BACKED HERON (BUTORIDES STRIATUS) 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By DORIS SHIELDS / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Description: Small, stocky heron with short yellow legs (males' legs are bright 
orange during high mating plumage); glossy blue-green back; neck is deep 
chestnut. The immature heron is browner above, white chest and neck streaked 
with brown. 
</P>
<P>
Average length is 18 inches, wing span is 26 inches. Formerly called the <ORGANIZATION>Little 
Green Heron</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Habitat: Marshes, ponds, wetlands; often perch in tops of eucalyptus trees. 
</P>
<P>
Diet: Fish, insects, snails, crayfish, shrimp and small amphibians. 
</P>
<P>
Displays: Male raises crest and neck plumes, swells throat and calls while 
hopping from foot to foot in front of female. 
</P>
<P>
Nest: Woven twigs and branches near or over water. 
</P>
<P>
Eggs: Light green with bluish hue. Length is 1 1/2 inches. 
</P>
<P>
Notes: Green-backed herons have been observed using insects, berries or twigs 
(which are often trimmed to size) for bait. After casting the lures onto the 
water, the herons crouch and wait for curious or hungry fish to inspect the 
bait. This is a rare case of tool use and, especially, tool manufacturing in 
ornithology. 
</P>
<P>
Breeding bird atlas: To report bird breeding activity in your neighborhood, or 
to get information on the breeding bird atlas, call Sea and <ORGANIZATION>Sage Audubon 
Society</ORGANIZATION> members <PERSON>Sylvia Gallagher</PERSON>, (714) 962-8990, or <PERSON>Nancy Kenyon</PERSON>, (714) 
786-3160. 
</P>
<P>
Note: Map is divided into 5-kilometer squares so that <ORGANIZATION>Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> 
volunteers can more easily survey areas on a regular basis. 
</P>
<P>
Sources: Sea and Sage Audubon Society; "The Birder's Handbook," <PERSON>Ehrlich</PERSON>, <PERSON>Dobkin</PERSON> 
and Wheye, Fireside Books (<DATE>1988</DATE>); "Field Guide to the Birds of <LOCATION>North America</LOCATION>," 
<ORGANIZATION>National Geographic Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1987</DATE>); "Birds of <LOCATION>Southern California</LOCATION>: Status and 
Distribution," <PERSON>Garrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Dunn</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Los Angeles Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> (<DATE>1981</DATE>) 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, areas where breeding activity has been confirmed. ; Drawing, Green-backed 
heron, RUSS ARASMITH / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<TYPE>
<P>
Profile 
</P>
</TYPE>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
BIRDS 
</P>
</SUBJECT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA072290-0086 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 250732 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
July 22, 1990, Sunday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Travel; Part L; Page 13; Column 1; Travel Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
906 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
TRAIL RUNS DOWNHILL FROM MOUNTAINS TO BEACH 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By JOHN McKINNEY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Skyline to the <ORGANIZATION>Sea Trail</ORGANIZATION>, as its name suggests, drops from the crest of the 
<LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION> to the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
For the most part, it runs downhill on its scenic 35-mile journey from <ORGANIZATION>Castle 
Rock State Park</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Big Basin Redwoods State Park to Waddell Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Views from the <LOCATION>Skyline</LOCATION> -- redwood-forested slopes, fern-smothered canyons and 
the great blue <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> -- are superb. 
</P>
<P>
This gem of a trail has many friends. During one weekend in <DATE>1969</DATE>, dedicated 
members of the Sempervirens Fund and the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Trails Assn.</ORGANIZATION> turned out 
more than 2,000 volunteers to dig, clear, prune and otherwise improve the 
trail. Area volunteers put together an annual Trails Day that is now a model 
for trails organizations throughout the state. 
</P>
<P>
A fine backpack for a three-day weekend would be to trek the 35 miles of 
Skyline from <ORGANIZATION>Castle Rock State Park</ORGANIZATION> to <LOCATION>Big Basin</LOCATION>, then onward to the sea. 
</P>
<P>
Castle Rock, perched on the western ridge of the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz Mountains</LOCATION>, is in 
turn connected by trails to parks and open-space preserves in the <LOCATION>Santa Clara 
Valley</LOCATION>. With judicious use of a map, a longer backpacking trip could be 
planned. 
</P>
<P>
The wildest and most beautiful part of the Skyline stretches from park 
headquarters at <LOCATION>Big Basin</LOCATION> to <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Creek Beach</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Marsh</PERSON>. It winds through 
deep woods and explores the moist environments of <PERSON>Waddell</PERSON> and <PERSON>Berry</PERSON> creeks. 
</P>
<P>
Springtime, when the creeks are frothy torrents and <ORGANIZATION>Berry Creek Falls</ORGANIZATION> cascades 
at full vigor, is a particularly dramatic time to walk the Skyline to the Sea 
Trail; during <DATE>summer</DATE>, the cool world of the redwood canyons is a great place to 
escape the heat. 
</P>
<P>
Big Basin -- <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s first state park, set aside in <DATE>1902</DATE> -- survived last 
<DATE>October</DATE>'s <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> earthquake in pretty good shape. Park roads were cracked, 
electric lines went down and pipes ruptured. The park was closed immediately 
after the quake, but was soon reopened. 
</P>
<P>
Rangers believe that few, if any, of the tall redwoods toppled because of the 
quake, though many trees lost heavy branches. 
</P>
<P>
Directions to trailhead: From <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>, drive 12 miles north on Highway 9. 
Turn west on Highway 236 and proceed nine miles to <ORGANIZATION>Big Basin Redwoods State 
Park</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
If you're hiking from <LOCATION>Big Basin</LOCATION> to the sea, you'll need to arrange a car 
shuttle. <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Beach</ORGANIZATION>, at trail's end, is 18 miles upcoast from <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> on 
Highway 1. 
</P>
<P>
Better yet, take the bus, which stops at both the state park and <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
One suggestion: Leave your car at the <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION> bus station (920 <LOCATION>Pacific Ave.</LOCATION>) 
and take the <TIME>7:45 a.m.</TIME> (weekends) bus bound for the state park. You'll arrive 
about <TIME>9 a.m.</TIME> 
</P>
<P>
Hit the trail and take the <TIME>5:15 p.m.</TIME> bus from <LOCATION>Waddell Beach</LOCATION> back to <LOCATION>Santa Cruz</LOCATION>. 
Schedules are different on weekends and weekdays and change frequently. Call 
the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Metropolitan Transit District</ORGANIZATION> at (408) 425-8600 for the latest 
bus schedule. The <MONEY>$2</MONEY> daily ride pass is a good deal. 
</P>
<P>
The hike: The trail begins in the nucleus of the park on <PERSON>Opal Creek</PERSON> flatlands 
at the bottom of the basin. From park headquarters, join <ORGANIZATION>Redwood Trail</ORGANIZATION>, which 
crosses a bridge and travels a few hundred yards to a signed junction with 
Skyline to the <ORGANIZATION>Sea Trail</ORGANIZATION>. You'll turn toward the sea and begin a stiff climb 
out of the basin, passing junctions with other park trails. 
</P>
<P>
After climbing, the trail descends through deep and dark woods, first with 
<PERSON>Kelly Creek</PERSON>, then along the west fork of <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Creek</ORGANIZATION>. Ferns and mushrooms, 
salamanders and banana slugs occupy the wet world of the trail. 
</P>
<P>
Some four miles from the trailhead, just short of the confluence of <ORGANIZATION>Waddell 
Creek</ORGANIZATION> and <PERSON>Berry Creek</PERSON>, you'll intersect <ORGANIZATION>Berry Creek Falls Trail</ORGANIZATION>. The falls 
cascade over fern-covered cliffs into a frothy pool. 
</P>
<P>
An ideal lunch stop, or turnaround spot, is Sunset Trail Camp, located a mile 
up <ORGANIZATION>Berry Creek Falls Trail</ORGANIZATION> and near another falls -- Golden Falls. 
</P>
<P>
Skyline to the <ORGANIZATION>Sea Trail</ORGANIZATION> descends with <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Creek</ORGANIZATION> and passes through the 
heart of the beautiful <ORGANIZATION>Waddell Valley</ORGANIZATION>. Rancho del Oso, "Ranch of the Bears," as 
this region is known, has second-generation redwoods, <PERSON>Douglas</PERSON> fir and Monterey 
pine, as well as lush meadows. 
</P>
<P>
A mile and a half from the ocean, you'll reach Twin Redwoods Camp. As you near 
the sea, the redwoods give way to laurel groves and meadow land. Near trail's 
end is a freshwater marsh, a favorite stopping place for migratory birds on the 
<LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> flyway. 
</P>
<P>
A wildlife sanctuary, <PERSON>Theodore J. Hoover</PERSON> Natural Preserve, has been established 
in the heart of the marsh area for more than 200 kinds of native and migratory 
birds. 
</P>
<P>
The trail ends at Highway 1. West of the highway is a bus stop and wind-swept 
<ORGANIZATION>Waddell Beach</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Maps detailing the Skyline to the Sea Trail are available at park headquarters 
or by mail. 
</P>
<P>
One map covers Castle Rock to <LOCATION>Big Basin</LOCATION>, another covers Big Basin to the sea. A 
third is a general map of <ORGANIZATION>Big Basin Redwoods State Park</ORGANIZATION>. The maps, <MONEY>$1</MONEY> each, are 
available from the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Mountains Natural History Assn.</ORGANIZATION>, 101 N. Big Trees 
Park Road, <LOCATION>Felton</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> 95018. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Hiking / <ORGANIZATION>Santa Cruz Mountains 
</P>
<P>
Skyline</ORGANIZATION> to the Sea Trail 
</P>
<P>
WHERE: <ORGANIZATION>Big Basin Redwoods State Park</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Boulder Creek</LOCATION> 
</P>
<P>
LENGTH: 12 miles one way, 1,200-foot elevation loss. 
</P>
<P>
TERRAIN: Redwood-forested slopes. 
</P>
<P>
HIGHLIGHTS: Fern canyons, inviting trail camps, ocean views. 
</P>
<P>
DEGREE OF DIFFICULTY: Strenuous. 
</P>
<P>
PRECAUTIONS: Slippery trail. Bring drinking water. 
</P>
<P>
FOR MORE INFORMATION: Contact <ORGANIZATION>Big Basin Redwoods State Park</ORGANIZATION>, 21600 Big Basin 
Way, <LOCATION>Boulder Creek</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION> 95006, (408) 338-6132. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Map, Hiking / Santa Cruz Mountains 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06006179 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06006179 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (3); PHOTO: Cap Carpenter; Cap Carpenter -- Mercury News; The Bay Area
is a bird-watching hot spot; here, a group of birding enthusiasts gathers on a
stone bridge in Alum Rock Park; PHOTO: Audrey Stoye, left, and Betty Wyatt,
co-editors of a guide to bird-watching in the South Bay, spot an unusual
specimen. (color); PHOTO: Audrey Stoye, left, and fellow birders Alan K.
Thomas, Aaron Fink and Dave Johnston consult a field guide to identify a
feathered find. (color)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  BIRD; BEHAVIOR  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  AUDREY Stoye is trying to explain how she ended up as Betty Wyatt's birding
buddy, traveling to exotic locations all over the world -- Australia, Alaska,
the Brownsville, Texas, city dump -- to look not so much at the countryside as
at the birds in it.;    "We took this class in Fremont together 12 years ago,"
Stoye begins.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Living  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  BIRDS OF A FEATHER
A RARE BIRD IN THE BINOCULARS IS WORTH BEATING
THE BUSH FOR
BIRDING BUDDIES TRAVEL THE WORLD FOR 'LIFE
BIRDS'  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  See also related stories on pages 1L &amp; 6L in this section  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Wyatt, meanwhile, has trained her high-powered telescope, called simply a
"scope" by birders, on a hummingbird singing loudly at <LOCATION>Charleston Slough</LOCATION> on
the Palo Alto/Mountain View border.;    "He's the only North American
hummingbird that sings," <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> remarks. "Oh, you are pretty," she tells the
bird.;    Stoye immediately drops the story of what happened 12 years ago in
Fremont.;    "Isn't he pretty?" she says, training her binoculars on the tiny
bird.;    <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> takes her eye from the scope, leans toward her listener and
lowers her voice. "They're very, you'll pardon the expression, randy," she
says.;    It's just another day in the marsh for Stoye and <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON>, co-editors
of a guide to bird-watching hot spots in the <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> and two of an
estimated 61 million Americans who spend their leisure time sloshing through
marshes and beating up and down trails to catch a glimpse of an animal that
flies away when it notices them.;    "I'd say there are two birders now for
every bird," <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> says dryly, commenting on how fashionable bird watching has
become since she first got interested some 40 years ago. At that time, she
told everyone that her binoculars were for use in the cheap seats at sporting
events. In reality, she was a "closet birder.";    That has all changed. "It's
an acceptable thing to do now," <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> insists, adjusting the cap covered with
bird pins she wears in the field. Later, though, she admits that birders are
"a shade eccentric," especially when a rare bird is spotted.;    Then, she
says, the sighting will be announced on a recorded rare bird hot line
(415-524-5592) and the chase is on. When a wood stork was spotted in the delta
last year, for example, hundreds of birders ran for the levees until one
overzealous observer got too close and scared the bird away. He was very
unpopular in birding circles for a time.;    Eccentric behavior aside, looking
at birds is now so acceptable that the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>
(which has 5,000 paying members) usually schedules two birding field trips
each weekend, along with a <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> trip twice a month and a bird
discussion group that meets monthly. The field trips lately have been
attracting as many as 40 birders.;    "I don't know if it's from Earth Day or
what," says <PERSON>Cecily Harris</PERSON>, director of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara Valley Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>
and the third co-editor of "Birding at the Bottom of the Bay." "But it keeps
getting more and more popular.";    "People are more in tune with the
environment," says <PERSON>Jean Dobbins</PERSON>, a staff member in the <ORGANIZATION>American Birds
Department of the National Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION>. "They're more interested in
activities that go along with conservation.";    <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON> have other
ideas.;    "You think there's a lot wrong with the world, but there must be
something right if these birds keep coming back," says <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON> as she tries to
coax a sora rail out of some cattails. "Pssh, pssh, pssh," she hisses at the
elusive bird.;    "I think it's partly to do with TV," adds <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON>. "People see
these nature specials and they think, 'I'll go out for a bird walk.' ";    "It
has great appeal," <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON> says, unable to get the rail to show itself. "So many
things in life are predictable. This is unpredictable.";    "It's part of the
Protestant work ethic," <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> continues. "You can't just go and do something
because it's fun. You have to have an excuse.";    Which is why birders keep
lists, lots and lots of lists of the types of birds they've seen, where
they've seen them and when the bird appeared.;    "Usually you have a day list
and a year list," says Stoye. "Lots of people have a county list and a state
list.";    Almost everybody has a life list, a roster of all the species
they've seen since they started birding seriously. <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON>'s has about 695
species of birds on it. She's shooting for 700, which she calls "a
respectable" number.;    "It's just a form of discipline," <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON> says of the
lists. "It makes you really look at the bird and identify it." At the moment,
Stoye is identifying an Audubon's warbler.;    "Actually, they're really
called yellow-rumped warblers," says <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON>, explaining that the name was
changed recently in the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> to conform with the bird's name in other
countries.;    "But we just call them butter butts," <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> adds.;    Both
<PERSON>Stoye</PERSON> and <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> are at the point in their birding careers at which they are
searching for "life birds" -- the few they've chosen that will make their life
lists complete, or as complete as these things get.;    Luckily, they live in
an area that just might make the sightings possible. Although the drought in
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> and in bird breeding areas in <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION> and the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION> has had
an effect on bird populations, the <LOCATION>San Francisco Bay Area</LOCATION> is still known
internationally as a birding hot spot. The varied habitats of the bay and the
hills support more than 300 avian species. That's more than some entire
regions of the country, says Wyatt.;    "I just don't know what I'd do if I
lived somewhere like <LOCATION>Iowa</LOCATION>," she says.;    <PERSON>Wyatt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stoye</PERSON>'s "Birding at the
Bottom of the Bay" was written, in part, for frustrated birders from out of
state who find themselves in the promised land of the <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION> and don't
know where to find a Eurasian widgeon or ferruginous hawk. It's also good for
birding beginners, who may have lived in bird heaven all their lives and never
realized it.;    The book is divided into five sections corresponding to five
different habitats in the <LOCATION>Silicon Valley</LOCATION>. About 50 members of the <ORGANIZATION>Santa Clara
Valley Audubon Society</ORGANIZATION> helped write the guide, which lists 40 different spots
for birding within the county and gives lots of advice on day trips outside
<LOCATION>Santa Clara County</LOCATION>.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  KATHLEEN DONNELLY, Mercury News Entertainment Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  SAN JOSE MERCURY NEWS  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910106  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  January  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1L  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  1,131  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday January 6, 1991
00006179,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  0  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880621-0254 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-06-21-88 2150EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-WhoopingCranes 1stLd-Writethru a0797 06-21 0423</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Whooping Cranes, 1st Ld-Writethru, a0797,410</SECOND>
<HEAD>Senate Panel Approves Final Purchase Of Land Where Birds Winter</HEAD>
<NOTE>EDs: FIXES spelling of Giezentanner throughout</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By JENNIFER DIXON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Preservation of <LOCATION>Matagorda Island</LOCATION>, habitat for
wintering whooping cranes and other endangered species of birds,
entered the home stretch when a <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> committee approved
legislation to buy the last bit of privately held land on the
barrier island, officials said <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   ``This is important not only for whooping cranes, but for water
fowl, shore birds, and herons, egrets and song birds,'' said <PERSON>Brent
Giezentanner</PERSON>, manager of the nearby <ORGANIZATION>Aransas Pass National Wildlife
Refuge</ORGANIZATION>.
   A <ORGANIZATION>Senate</ORGANIZATION> appropriations subcommittee late <DATE>Monday</DATE> approved
spending <MONEY>$5.5 million</MONEY> to purchase 5,017 acres at the southern tip
of the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Gulf Coast</ORGANIZATION> island.
   The <ORGANIZATION>U.S. Fish</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Wildlife Service</ORGANIZATION> will buy the land at cost
from the <ORGANIZATION>Texas Nature Conservancy</ORGANIZATION>, and when the deal goes through
all the land on the island will be in either federal or state
ownership, according to the office of <PERSON>Sen. Phil Gramm</PERSON>, <LOCATION>R-Texas</LOCATION>.
   But a <PERSON>Gramm</PERSON> staffer said it still is unclear how the land will
be managed, with debate centering on whether it should be the state
or federal government or both. The state controls 24,893 acres, and
when the final purchase goes through, the federal government will
control 30,502 acres.
   As the whooping crane flock grows, some of the endangered birds
have wintered on <LOCATION>Matagorda Island</LOCATION> rather than at the Aransas refuge.
   ``This is going to preserve and protect their habitat from
development,'' said <PERSON>Giezentanner</PERSON>. ``There are only two barrier
islands in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> that are not developed to some degree _ Matagorda
and (adjacent) <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>.''
   More than 230 species of birds can be found on <LOCATION>Matagorda Island</LOCATION>,
including endangered song birds who make the island their first
landfall upon their northern spring migration from <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>,
<PERSON>Giezentanner</PERSON> said. A total of 20 endangered species of birds use
the island.
   He said 132 whooping cranes wintered last year at the Aransas
refuge or nearby, including <LOCATION>Matagorda Island</LOCATION>. Two other members of
the flock also spent the winter in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> _ a record high since the
early <DATE>1930s</DATE>.
   The record low was in <DATE>1941</DATE>, when 15 of the birds spent the
winter in <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> and six others in <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, he said.
   Of the 134 whooping cranes that left <ORGANIZATION>Wood Buffalo National Park</ORGANIZATION>
in the <LOCATION>Northwest Terrorities</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Canada</LOCATION>, for <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> <DATE>last fall</DATE>, 25 were
fledged birds _ those just able to fly _ and all made the 2,500 to
2,800-mile journey.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890914-0079 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890914 </DD>
<AN> 890914-0079. </AN>
<HL> LEISURE &amp; ARTS:
@  Raptor Report: Making a Secure World for Predators
@  ----
@  By Ruth Rudner </HL>
<DD> 09/14/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<DATELINE> Snake River Canyon, Idaho  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
