<DOC>
<DOCNO> LA031289-0080 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 29773 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
March 12, 1989, Sunday, Bulldog Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Part 1; Page 36; Column 1; Advance Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
674 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
HIDES BRING $37 A FOOT; 
</P>
<P>
ALLIGATOR FARMING NEW GROWTH INDUSTRY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By AUSTIN WILSON, Associated Press 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
NEW ORLEANS 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Call it toothy gold, a get-rich quick plan for an area devastated by the crash 
of the oil market. 
</P>
<P>
Across <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s marshes, once flush with profits from black gold, small 
patches of land increasingly are being turned into alligator farms, with 
investors hoping to quintuple their investments in short order. 
</P>
<P>
"Year before last, there were just under 9,000 farm-raised gators sold" by 37 
farms, said <PERSON>Dave Taylor</PERSON>, alligator research coordinator for <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Department of Wildlife</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fisheries</ORGANIZATION>. "That number is going to reach 60,000 
quickly and could be up to 100,000, certainly, within five years." 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
24,000 Trapped in Wilds 
</P>
<P>
That's in addition to the 24,000 wild alligators trapped each fall in carefully 
supervised hunts. 
</P>
<P>
Spurred by prices of <MONEY>$37</MONEY> a linear foot for hides, 21 new farms have opened in 
the <DATE>last two years</DATE>, and "We expect them to produce 18,000 gators," <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. 
The waiting list for permits for new farms is about 100. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Jerry Jones Jr.</PERSON>, 28, went into business two years ago near <LOCATION>Sweetlake</LOCATION> and 
expects to put 12,000 hides a year on the market. His farm is state-of-the-art: 
automated cleaning, water-source heat pumps, carefully supervised diets. 
</P>
<P>
The result is quicker growth at less cost. "We have some (that) are 5 to 6 feet 
long in a year and six months. We have 8-month-old gators that are 26 to 30 
inches." 
</P>
<P>
Skins of wild alligators average 7 feet in length, and are used for luggage. 
Farm-raised gators are skinned at 2 years old and about 4 feet long. Their 
hides are used for shoes, purses, belts and other smaller high-fashion 
accouterments requiring smaller patterns on the hides. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Windowless Buildings 
</P>
<P>
For about <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> a potential farmer can put up a couple of windowless 
cinder-block buildings on concrete slabs and be ready to raise 1,000 gators a 
year. It would take another <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> to operate until the gators grow 
enough to sell. At current prices, 1,000 4-foot hides would bring <MONEY>$148,000</MONEY>. 
</P>
<P>
"The minimum requirements are 1 square foot per alligator up to 2 feet in 
length and 2 square feet up to 4 feet in length," <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. Buildings must 
be able to hold a few inches of water and be kept about 89 degrees. 
</P>
<P>
The first thing is to gather alligator eggs from wild nests, paying landowners 
for the eggs and committing <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> of the hatch for return to the wild at 4 feet 
long. That's a carefully researched percentage designed for zero growth in the 
population of 1.5 million wild alligators -- reached after the alligator was 
taken off the endangered species list in the mid-1970s. 
</P>
<P>
The wild nests aren't easy to find, and female alligators guard their eggs -- 
about the only time in their lives that they show maternal instincts. 
</P>
<P>
No task for the timid, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> agreed. "But everybody's got to learn some time 
or another, if they want to get into farming. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Spot Nests From Air 
</P>
<P>
"Obviously, what would be best, for a guy's first involvement, would be to hire 
someone with a little experience in locating nests from the air. That's the 
only way to go: Rent a helicopter and go find them and pick them up." 
</P>
<P>
The success of farming ventures will almost certainly drive prices down, and 
there are risks any time a market depends on fashion or something volatile, he 
said. "I don't think the bottom will fall out of the price. I don't think 
they'll go to <MONEY>$2</MONEY> a foot. But it certainly could go to half of what it is now." 
</P>
<P>
Jones, a former trapper, commercial diver and underwater welder who now devotes 
full time to his farm, agrees with <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>'s analysis. "A lot of these farms, 
you'll see what happens. Prices are good right now, but with all these hides 
coming on the market, it's going to have to go down." 
</P>
<P>
But <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> believes he will survive when others fail because his expenses are 
low. "Look at it this way, you've got an electricity bill of <MONEY>$500</MONEY> a month to 
raise 1,000 alligators, and my bill is <MONEY>$150</MONEY> a month to raise 12,000." 
</P>
<P>
His major problem is finding enough nutria -- small water rodents -- to feed 
the gators. Nutria, or coypus, often are dyed like beaver, <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> said. 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Wire 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890301-0008 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-03-01-89 0025EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-ToothyGold     03-01 0770</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Toothy Gold,0787</SECOND>
<HEAD>The Gator Boom Is On Where Black Gold Tarnished</HEAD>
<HEAD>Eds: Also in Wednesday AMs report.</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AUSTIN WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Call it toothy gold, a get-rich quick plan for
an area devastated by the crash of the oil market.
   Across <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s marshes, once flush with profits from black
gold, small patches of land increasingly are being turned into
alligator farms, with investors hoping to quintuple their
investments in short order.
   ``Year before last, there were just under 9,000 farm-raised
gators sold'' by 37 farms, said <PERSON>Dave Taylor</PERSON>, alligator research
coordinator for <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Department of Wildlife</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fisheries</ORGANIZATION>.
``That number is going to reach 60,000 quickly and could be up to
100,000, certainly, within five years.''
   That's in addition to the 24,000 wild alligators trapped each
fall in carefully supervised hunts.
   Spurred by prices of <MONEY>$37</MONEY> a linear foot for hides, 21 new farms
have opened in the past two years, and ``We expect them to produce
18,000 gators,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. The waiting list for permits for new
farms is about 100.
   <PERSON>Jerry Jones Jr.</PERSON>, 28, went into business two years ago near
<LOCATION>Sweetlake</LOCATION> and expects to put 12,000 hides a year on the market. His
farm is state-of-the-art: automated cleaning, water-source heat
pumps, carefully supervised diets.
   The result is quicker growth at less cost. ``We have some are 5-6
feet long in a year and six months. We have 8-month-old gators that
are 26-30 inches.''
   Skins of wild alligators average seven feet in length, and are
used for luggage. Farm-raised gators are skinned at two years old
and about four feet long. Their hides are used for shoes, purses,
belts and other smaller high-fashion accoutrements requiring smaller
patterns on the hides.
   For about <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> a potential farmer can put up a couple
windowless cinder-block buildings on concrete slabs and be ready to
raise 1,000 gators a year. It would take another <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>
to operate until the gators grew enough to sell. At current prices,
1,000 four-foot hides would bring <MONEY>$148,000</MONEY>.
   ``The minimum requirements are 1 square foot per alligator up to
two feet in length and 2 square feet up to four feet in length,''
<PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. Buildings must be able to hold a few inches of water
and be kept about 89 degrees.
   The first thing is to gather alligator eggs from wild nests,
paying landowners for the eggs and committing <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT> of the
hatch for return to the wild at 4 feet long. That's a carefully
researched percentage designed for zero growth in the population of
1.5 million wild alligators _ reached after the alligator was taken
off the endangered species list in the mid-1970s.
   The wild nests aren't easy to find, and female alligators guard
their eggs _ about the only time in their lives they show maternal
instincts.
   No task for the timid, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> agreed. ``But everybody's got to
learn some time or another, if they want to get into farming.
   ``Obviously, what would be best, for a guy's first involvement,
would be to hire someone with a little experience in locating nests
from the air. That's the only way to go: rent a helicopter and go
find them and pick them up.''
   The success of farming ventures will almost certainly drive
prices down, and there are risks any time a market depends on
fashion or something volatile, he said. ``I don't think the bottom
will fall out of the price. I don't think they'll go to <MONEY>$2</MONEY> a foot.
But it certainly could go to half of what it is now.''
   Jones, a former trapper, commercial diver and underwater welder
who now devotes full time to his farm, agrees with <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>'s
analysis. ``A lot of these farms, you'll see what happens. Prices
are good right now, but with all these hides coming on the market,
it's going to have to go down.''
   But <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> believes he will survive when others fail because his
expenses are low. ``Look at it this way, you've got an electricity
bill of <MONEY>$500</MONEY> a month to raise 1,000 alligators, and my bill is <MONEY>$150</MONEY>
a month to raise 12,000.''
   His major problem is finding enough nutria _ small water rodents
_ to feed the gators. Nutria often are dyed like beaver, and <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>
said, ``The price of skins is so low, right now, that you can't get
all you want. Last year I got 40,000 pounds, and I could have used
140,000.''
   He had to supplement with fish and horse, and young alligators
don't grow as quickly on that diet. In addition, too much fish gives
alligators gout.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890223-0235 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-02-23-89 0608EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a AM-ToothyGold Adv01   02-23 0782</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Toothy Gold, Adv 01,0800</SECOND>
<HEAD>$Adv01</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Wed AMs, March 1, and Thereafter</HEAD>
<HEAD>The Gator Boom Is On Where Black Gold Tarnished</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By AUSTIN WILSON</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NEW ORLEANS (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Call it toothy gold, a get-rich quick plan for
an area devastated by the crash of the oil market.
   Across <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s marshes, once flush with profits from black
gold, small patches of land increasingly are being turned into
alligator farms, with investors hoping to quintuple their
investments in short order.
   ``Year before last, there were just under 9,000 farm-raised
gators sold'' by 37 farms, said <PERSON>Dave Taylor</PERSON>, alligator research
coordinator for <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Department of Wildlife</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Fisheries</ORGANIZATION>.
``That number is going to reach 60,000 quickly and could be up to
100,000, certainly, within five years.''
   That's in addition to the 24,000 wild alligators trapped each
fall in carefully supervised hunts.
   Spurred by prices of <MONEY>$37</MONEY> a linear foot for hides, 21 new farms
have opened in the past two years, and ``We expect them to produce
18,000 gators,'' <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. The waiting list for permits for new
farms is about 100.
   <PERSON>Jerry Jones Jr.</PERSON>, 28, went into business two years ago near
<LOCATION>Sweetlake</LOCATION> and expects to put 12,000 hides a year on the market. His
farm is state-of-the-art: automated cleaning, water-source heat
pumps, carefully supervised diets.
   The result is quicker growth at less cost. ``We have some are 5-6
feet long in a year and six months. We have 8-month-old gators that
are 26-30 inches.''
   Skins of wild alligators average seven feet in length, and are
used for luggage. Farm-raised gators are skinned at two years old
and about four feet long. Their hides are used for shoes, purses,
belts and other smaller high-fashion accoutrements requiring smaller
patterns on the hides.
   For about <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY> a potential farmer can put up a couple
windowless cinder-block buildings on concrete slabs and be ready to
raise 1,000 gators a year. It would take another <MONEY>$25,000</MONEY> to <MONEY>$30,000</MONEY>
to operate until the gators grew enough to sell. At current prices,
1,000 four-foot hides would bring <MONEY>$148,000</MONEY>.
   ``The minimum requirements are 1 square foot per alligator up to
two feet in length and 2 square feet up to four feet in length,''
<PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> said. Buildings must be able to hold a few inches of water
and be kept about 89 degrees.
   The first thing is to gather alligator eggs from wild nests,
paying landowners for the eggs and committing <PERCENT>17 percent</PERCENT> of the
hatch for return to the wild at 4 feet long. That's a carefully
researched percentage designed for zero growth in the population of
1.5 million wild alligators _ reached after the alligator was taken
off the endangered species list in the mid-1970s.
   The wild nests aren't easy to find, and female alligators guard
their eggs _ about the only time in their lives they show maternal
instincts.
   No task for the timid, <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON> agreed. ``But everybody's got to
learn some time or another, if they want to get into farming.
   ``Obviously, what would be best, for a guy's first involvement,
would be to hire someone with a little experience in locating nests
from the air. That's the only way to go: rent a helicopter and go
find them and pick them up.''
   The success of farming ventures will almost certainly drive
prices down, and there are risks any time a market depends on
fashion or something volatile, he said. ``I don't think the bottom
will fall out of the price. I don't think they'll go to <MONEY>$2</MONEY> a foot.
But it certainly could go to half of what it is now.''
   Jones, a former trapper, commercial diver and underwater welder
who now devotes full time to his farm, agrees with <PERSON>Taylor</PERSON>'s
analysis. ``A lot of these farms, you'll see what happens. Prices
are good right now, but with all these hides coming on the market,
it's going to have to go down.''
   But <PERSON>Jones</PERSON> believes he will survive when others fail because his
expenses are low. ``Look at it this way, you've got an electricity
bill of <MONEY>$500</MONEY> a month to raise 1,000 alligators, and my bill is <MONEY>$150</MONEY>
a month to raise 12,000.''
   His major problem is finding enough nutria _ small water rodents
_ to feed the gators. Nutria often are dyed like beaver, and <PERSON>Jones</PERSON>
said, ``The price of skins is so low, right now, that you can't get
all you want. Last year I got 40,000 pounds, and I could have used
140,000.''
   He had to supplement with fish and horse, and young alligators
don't grow as quickly on that diet. In addition, too much fish gives
alligators gout.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Wed AMs, March 1</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT922-3984</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-CFIBTAAAFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>920609
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  09 JUN 92 / The FT Review of Business Books (1): From cyber-brat to
superman - The extraordinary rise of Bill Gates, the founder of Microsoft
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By MAX WILKINSON
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   HARD DRIVE
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
BILL GATES AND THE MAKING OF THE <ORGANIZATION>MICROSOFT</ORGANIZATION> EMPIRE by <PERSON>James Wallace</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jim
Erickson John Wiley</PERSON>, Dollars 22.95, 426 pages
WHEN THE screens and keyboards which clutter office desks are finally
replaced by proper visicom robots, men will marvel that such crude and
cumbersome machines could have ordered the business affairs of the <DATE>late 20th
century</DATE>.
Yet the revolution which produced today's personal computers was itself a
marvel of ingenuity and persistence. And among the heroes of that epic none
is odder, nor more spectacularly successful, than <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>, the schoolboy
programmer, who became the billionaire chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>.
From his schooldays Gates was fascinated by the programming which makes
inanimate machines jump into life. In the early years this was a dreadfully
slow and painful task, both for the programmer and for the user: the machine
communicated in sullen and pedantic monosyllables.
Gates's and <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s most recent success is founded on the vision that
personal computers should be bright, alive and responsive to the user,
should communicate in a simple standard way and should anticipate the user's
needs wherever possible. These ideas were first embodied in the operating
system of <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> computers, which present the user with a screen of small
drawings (or 'ikons') representing tasks he might want it to perform. By
using a remote controlled pointer, or 'mouse', the user can give
instructions without any need for typing.
Microsoft developed its rival Windows system for use on <ORGANIZATION>International
Business Machines</ORGANIZATION> personal computers and compatible makes. After a hesitant
start, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Windows</ORGANIZATION> is now sweeping the computing world, consolidating
richest man in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, with a net worth of more than Dollars 8bn (Pounds
4.3bn).
Windows will no doubt come to be seen as an early form in the evolution of
intelligent desk-top machines to a point when they can understand the human
voice, can make suggestions and carry out many routine tasks unasked. Anyone
who thinks such ideas seem far fetched should read <PERSON>Wallace</PERSON> and <PERSON>Erickson</PERSON>'s
account of the extraordinary progress made during the 36 years of <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>'s
life and love for the soul of the machine.
It started when <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> was a bright, curious and highly competitive schoolboy
at Lakeside school, <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, playing games on a cumbersome terminal
connected to a computer owned by a local company called <ORGANIZATION>Computer Center
Corporation</ORGANIZATION>. Before long the 13-year-old Gates and his fellow pupils were
exploiting so many loopholes and faults in the machine that they were
invited by the company to go in after school to test the operating system to
destruction - while keeping a careful log. Gates then developed his lifelong
habit of working far into the <TIME>night</TIME>, but he did well in school also.
Gates even founded his first company, Traf-O-Data, at <LOCATION>Lakeside</LOCATION>, offering
analysis of urban traffic flows to local authorities. It might have
prospered, had not the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Government</ORGANIZATION> undercut him.
It was at <LOCATION>Harvard</LOCATION>, however, that <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> made his first serious business
venture with a fellow computer enthusiast, <PERSON>Paul Allen</PERSON>. They read that a
small company in <LOCATION>New Mexico</LOCATION> was to produce the first hobby computer in kit
form, the 'Altair', for the then amazingly low price of Dollars 397. No
matter that it lacked keyboard, screen, adequate memory, or programmes to
make it work, hobbyists were queueing to buy. Gates and <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> worked
feverishly at the <ORGANIZATION>Harvard</ORGANIZATION> computer to produce a version of the BASIC
programming language that would run on a machine of such meagre capacity. It
was a formidable task, since the computer understands only the simplest
instructions to open or shut switches. Gates and <PERSON>Allen</PERSON> completed the job,
formed a company called <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> and struck a deal with the maker of the
Altair.
In those early years, Gates displayed all the qualities of obsessive hard
work, vision, salesmanship, arrogance and temper tantrums which were so
develop a BASIC for the personal computer it was planning. <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> was
also to develop an operating system for the first IBM PC. This is the
central nervous system of a computer which silently organises the memory,
disk storage, and other 'bodily functions'. Devising an operating system is
a huge task which depends on excruciating detail, a combination suited to
<PERSON>Gates</PERSON>'s genius. Even so, his new Disk Operating System was derivative, and
<PERSON>Gates</PERSON> struck a very tough bargain with <ORGANIZATION>Seattle Computer</ORGANIZATION> for the rights to
MS-DOS, the system which was eventually used on millions of machines
throughout the world.
This was an epic success, which broke some men and came close to destroying
the company, but it led to greater things, the development of Windows, and
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s leading wordprocessing and spreadsheet packages, Word and Excel.
Wallace and <PERSON>Erickson</PERSON> have made this into an exciting tale, told in the racy
style of American business journalism, with plenty of detail and well
researched quotations, all focused on the enigmatic personality of Bill
Gates. He emerges as a mildly unpleasant night owl with few interests
besides writing and selling computer algorithms. He relaxes by breaking the
speed limit, but cannot, it seems, fit women into his busy schedule nor find
time for many of the usual forms of relaxation. He screams abuse at his
employees and forces them to work inhuman hours. Yet work they do, at a
frenzied pace, and many are now millionaires through stock options.
By the end of the book one cannot help liking this appallingly ambitious and
lonesome brat. And if one should ask: 'What shall it profit a man that he
should gain the whole world . . . ?', the answer is that <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>'s Dollars 8bn
represents, not just his winnings, but an important contribution to one of
the great revolutions in human history.
</TEXT>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page I
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ890802-0003 </DOCNO>
<DD> = 890802 </DD>
<AN> 890802-0003. </AN>
<HL> Alligator Farming
@  Shows There's a Lot
@  To Be Said for Cows
@  ---
@  But High Prices on Reptiles
@  Make Risks Worthwhile
@  For Louisiana Farmers
@  ----
@  By Mark Robichaux
<DD> 08/02/89 </DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J) </SO>
<IN> TEXTILES AND APPAREL (TEX) </IN>
<DATELINE> HOUMA, La.  </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Seven feet long, with a jaw full of evil teeth, the alligator lurking nearby is one mean matron. 
So <PERSON>Dane Ledet</PERSON> doesn't linger by the muddy mound of swamp grass where he has just landed in a helicopter. 
Within seconds, he scoops the 36 fresh eggs from her nest and scrambles back into the waiting copter. 

   A scene from "<LOCATION>Louisiana Jones</LOCATION> and the Jaws of Death?" 
No, this is farming. 
<PERSON>Mr. Ledet</PERSON> is merely replenishing his herd -- by raiding an alligator's nest. 
He is one of a new strain of courageous entrepreneurs who farms alligators. 

   Alligators have yet to find a welcome mat at <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> parish fairs. 
Who wants to hang a ribbon on a critter that might eat it, along with your arm? 
Nobody oohs and aahs over alligators at <ORGANIZATION>4-H Club</ORGANIZATION> exhibits, either. 
At <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s finest country clubs, gentlemen farmers still talk racehorses -- not alligators. 

   Nonetheless, alligators are becoming important livestock in this state. 
Farmers from <LOCATION>Natchitoches</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> have begun to raise them, forgoing blue ribbons for cash. 
Prices on alligator hides and meat have reached record highs, although they may not stay so high if the supply keeps increasing. 

   State wildlife officials expect that nearly 75,000 alligators will be raised this year on <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>'s farms, triple the herd in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 
Veteran alligator farmers complain that newcomers are constantly hounding them for advice. 
More than 200 people are on a waiting list for state alligator-farm permits. 
Alligator sections have been added to aquaculture classes in state universities. 

   Alligator skins once were the booty of poachers who devastated the alligator population and helped put "alligator mississippiensis" on the endangered species list and helped make alligator products unfashionable. 
But the wild population has exploded in recent years, and the alligator was delisted in <DATE>1987</DATE>. 

   By then, after years of experimental alligator husbandry, <PERSON>Ted Joanen</PERSON> and <PERSON>Larry McNease</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> wildlife researchers, had already successfully promoted alligator farming. 
They saw it as a way to stop poaching, ensure a supply of skins and foster new business that was desperately needed in a state whose economy was depressed by the oil glut. 
To protect the species, state law requires farmers to return a sizable portion -- <PERCENT>17%</PERCENT> this year -- of their nurtured, four-foot-long stock to the wild. 

   Raising alligators is different from raising cows. 
The alligator has a walnut-size brain. 
But its jaws can snap a farmer's arm like a breadstick; they exert a force of 3,000 pounds a square inch. 
Stealing their eggs, corralling the critters and hauling them to market are hazardous. 

   Alligators lack a strong herding instinct. 
About a month ago, <PERSON>Skeet Rogers</PERSON>, proud new part-owner of <ORGANIZATION>Bayou Pierre Gator Farm</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Natchitoches</LOCATION>, had to move half of his 2,000 alligator herd into a larger barn. 
He first thought to move them through a "chute" made from sheets of tin. 

   "We were going to herd 'em like cattle with sticks," he says. 
"It was a mess. 
They tried to climb over each other and they started fighting." 
With the help of 14 leery volunteers, each wearing two pairs of thick leather gloves to protect his hands, <PERSON>Mr. Rogers</PERSON> hand-carried the alligators from barn to barn. 

   At market time, <PERSON>Mr. Rogers</PERSON> loads some 200 live four-foot gators into an old, gutted school bus for the hour-and-a-half drive to Ville Platte. 
Only a sheet of plywood separates the driver from his passengers. 
The driver is "usually the guy who draws the shortest straw. 
I'm serious," says <PERSON>Mr. Rogers</PERSON>, adding: "Usually a car follows -- just in case." 

   Like most alligator farmers in <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Mr. Rogers</PERSON> houses his animals in half-sunken tin-sided structures of cinder blocks on concrete slabs. 
Inside one of these barns, the temperature is a humid 89 degrees, just about right for gators. 
They are at home in a few inches of water reeking of reptile urine. 

   The smell takes some getting used to. 
On their uncle <PERSON>Raywood Stelly</PERSON>'s <ORGANIZATION>Raywood</ORGANIZATION>'s Kajun Alligator Farms at <PERSON>Kaplan</PERSON>, the 17-year-old <PERSON>Stelly</PERSON> twins, <PERSON>Velma</PERSON> and <PERSON>Thelma</PERSON>, daily plop gobs of feed mix to the gators as part of their farm chores. 
The feed is one part nutria, a prolific swamp rat; one part croaker, an inexpensive fish, and one part vitamin-fortified dry food that a producer packs in sacks labeled Alligator Feed. 
"The first time we did this, I couldn't believe it," says <PERSON>Thelma</PERSON>, her arms sunk in a bucket of bloody nutria carcasses. 

   "Now we're used to it -- almost," says <PERSON>Velma</PERSON>, swatting at a swarm of flies around her head. 

   To build their herds without having to collect eggs, some farmers buy them for <MONEY>$5</MONEY> to <MONEY>$8</MONEY> each. 
But most collect their own, paying landowners for the rights to do so, and search by airboat and helicopter. 
They work over a three-week laying period that usually comes in <DATE>June</DATE>. 
Newly hatched alligators "come out mean as hell and biting," a farmer says. 

   In <LOCATION>Ville Platte</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Steele McAndrew</PERSON> collects eggs on his own pond, where he keeps his breeding stock. 
Checking the pond, he totes a 10-foot plastic pipe to fend off his ungracious wards. 
As he nears a nest, a seven-foot gator appears from nowhere, hissing and blowing at him in the heat of midmorning. 

   "These are like bears in a park," he says, easing the pipe a few feet from the reptile's snout. 
"They don't have any fear left in them." 
Before <PERSON>Mr. McAndrew</PERSON> can finish, the alligator jumps and sprints toward him in short bursts. 
Then it seizes the tooth-scarred pipe in its jaws. 

   So ferocious is the animal that <PERSON>Mr. McAndrew</PERSON> guesses her eggs lie nearby. 
He hatches the precious eggs he collects in an incubator. 
If the heat exceeds 91 degrees or drops below 89, the eggs are endangered, and a heat-sensitive alarm rings in <PERSON>Mr. McAndrew</PERSON>'s bedroom. 

   <PERSON>Mr. McAndrew</PERSON> was one of the pioneer <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> alligator farmers eight years ago. 
His farm, which is becoming part of a joint venture, will soon expand to 30,000 alligators from 6,000. 
He concedes that an alligator farm isn't exactly the Garden of <ORGANIZATION>Eden</ORGANIZATION>. 
"A 90-degree building, <PERCENT>100%</PERCENT> humidity, rancid meat, getting splashed with alligator urine and water -- it's just not ideal conditions," he says, adding that "a lot of people in <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> are desperate." 

   Alligator hides fetch the farmer <MONEY>$39</MONEY> a linear foot. 
Farm-bred gators, whose hides are used for handbags and other small goods, typically are slaughtered when they are four feet long. 
Hides from bigger, wild alligators, used for luggage, bring about <MONEY>$48</MONEY> a foot. 
A field-dressed four-foot-long alligator brings farmers about <MONEY>$20</MONEY> for the meat. 

   There are alligator farms in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION>, too. 
But alligator-farm technical knowledge and state support is centered here; for nearly 20 years, <PERSON>Messrs. 
Joanen</PERSON> and <PERSON>McNease</PERSON> did their research on alligators in captivity in the marsh at <ORGANIZATION>Rockefeller Refuge</ORGANIZATION> in southern <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION>. 
Foreign countries, mainly in <LOCATION>Africa</LOCATION>, have engineered their alligator and crocodile farming enterprises on the <LOCATION>Louisiana</LOCATION> model. 

   The market for alligators would be larger, alligator men say, if it weren't for the mistaken belief that the alligator is endangered. 
Even with increases in demand over the past few years, the world market for crocodile and alligator hides has regained only half the volume of 15 years ago. 
"It's not mass fashion right now," says <PERSON>Lee Goldman</PERSON>, president of <ORGANIZATION>Campaign Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, distributor of <ORGANIZATION>Polo Ralph Lauren Corp.</ORGANIZATION> alligator products. 
But, he says, "If there are more skins available, they're reasonably priced and they look good, I'm all in favor of it." 

   Nature lovers, <PERSON>Mr. Joanen</PERSON> says, should consider that the farmers who skin alligators also are returning healthy four-footers to the wild. 
"If you want to help the marsh, and the alligator," he says, "buy an alligator handbag." 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT934-9043</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DKLCNAC1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>931112
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  12 NOV 93 / Management: Microsoft's loud mouse - Bill Gates' number two
talks to Alan Cane and Tim Dickson about the future of the computer industry
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN CANE and TIM DICKSON
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
To comprehend the computer industry, it was once essential to understand
<ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines</ORGANIZATION>, hardware manufacturer par excellence and
industry leader for three decades.
Today, with <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> fighting red ink and loss of market share, the model is
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, the aggressive young pretender to <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s crown. Creator of MS/Dos
and Windows, the operating systems which control more than <MONEY>90 per cent</MONEY> of
the world's personal computers, the company has begun to influence others in
a way reminiscent of its older rival.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, however, is living in a changed world and the management and
strategic challenges are correspondingly different. While <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> wanted total
control of its customer, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is increasingly focusing on what it
believes it does best, designing and producing quality software. As <PERSON>Steve
Ballmer</PERSON>, responsible for the company's sales and marketing activities,
points out: 'We cannot do everything. As a result, to reach large businesses
the distributors we have always dealt with, but companies developing
specific software solutions to their customers' problems.'
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s management philosophy, explains <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON>, is 'ultimately
conservative'. Much of this is rooted in the personality of <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>,
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s 38-year-old co-founder, chairman and chief executive, whose
parsimony and competitiveness are equally notorious. But <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON>, a
37-year-old college friend of Gates and effectively <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s joint number
two, is clearly a thoughtful and assertive influence.
'When I started (in <DATE>1980</DATE>), <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> had 30 people. When I had been there
two months, I told Bill I thought we ought to hire 17 more people. He said:
'I think we are going to go bankrupt if I keep you here. I'm not sure this
is going to work out'.'
Ballmer stayed and <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> did not go bankrupt. The success of its
operating systems on IBM-style PCs, its computer languages and applications
programs turned it into the world's most successful packaged software
supplier. Last year it had sales of Dollars 3.7bn (Pounds 2.6bn), up 36 per
cent on the year before and net income of Dollars 953m.
The changing marketplace will test both its adaptability and technical
expertise. <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has proved itself the king of the electronic desktop,
providing operating systems, word processors and spreadsheets for people
using stand-alone personal computers. But as large companies seek to link
their computers together and establish enterprise-wide information networks,
how will the company react?
Windows NT, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s latest operating system, is the company's
technological answer, but <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, as <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> readily agrees, has less
experience of corporate data processing than, for example, <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION>.
<PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> says <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has more experience than many people realise, but
adds: 'I am not convinced that <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> or <ORGANIZATION>Unisys</ORGANIZATION> - where one company supplied
hardware, software and services - is the model for the <DATE>1990s</DATE>. In our model
we focus on what we do best, which is to build software products. Others
build hardware, deliver services and design custom developments.
'We have to mobilise an infrastructure around our products or people will
not design them into their systems. We have to explain that model to our
corporate customers. We are not going to be a cradle-to-grave supplier. If
people want a company to integrate their hardware or write a custom
application, that company is not going to be us.'
Can <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, however, continue to dominate the software business and avoid
'doing an <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'?
As <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> tells it - his style is engagingly direct, the decibel count
unusually high - the company can hardly be accused of complacency. He
describes a culture which reflects a nervous, almost paranoid concern with
staying ahead. 'We are certainly paranoid enough about the potential to fail
that we are looking very hard for the potholes in the road.'
Having Gates around evidently helps. 'Bill is good at saying: 'I don't care
how good things seem to most people. I see deep problems',' explains
<PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON>.
Conscious of the technological obsolescence pothole into which <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> stumbled,
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has one senior employee (<PERSON>Nathan Mirvald</PERSON>, vice-president of
advanced technology) constantly scanning the horizon for new business
threats.
Ballmer distinguishes three phases in the company's development. The first
was characterised by a focus on technology and on business ('before you hire
anyone or do anything, get a customer'), but there was little management
vision. 'Bill had all these envelopes with all the contracts written down
and everybody in the company and their salaries and he was doing these
calculations over and over to make sure there was enough of this to cover
that,' <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> recalls.
In the second phase, <PERSON>Jon Shirley</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Tandy Corporation</ORGANIZATION> was hired to inject
some business sense into a technologically aggressive company which was
being strangled by tight purse strings. 'Jon helped us grow the management
structure that enabled us to do the investing that I wanted and that <PERSON>Paul
Allen</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s co-founder, wanted. It was what Bill wanted to do as well
but he did not have the confidence.'
<PERSON>Shirley</PERSON> has since retired, although he keeps in close contact with the
company. A replacement did not work out and the company established an
'office of the president' last year to support Gates. It comprised <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON>
as head of sales, <PERSON>Mike Maples</PERSON>, head of the products group, and the late
<PERSON>Frank Gaudette</PERSON>, who had been chief financial officer.
The challenge now, <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> says, is how best to present a unified approach
to its customers, while allowing the separate divisions considerable
autonomy. 'We spend a lot of time pushing ourselves. How do we become a
global company? How do we measure the effectiveness of a sales operation
when we are working with partners? If there is a price war you don't want to
be the guy caught with higher overheads and processing costs than others
because you've been sloppy.'
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s success has made a lot of its employees potentially very rich
through share options and that has helped to maintain the youthful
aggression of the culture: 'Any senior executive at <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> can retire if
they want to. The nice thing about having people make money is that they
don't stick around unless they want to,' <PERSON>Ballmer</PERSON> says. 'They stick around
because they want to work hard and are excited about what we are doing. It
is a nice filtering process.'
He and <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>, he says, are good for at least another 10 years. 'We don't
work as hard as we used to, but we still work very hard and we love it.'
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Microsoft Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7372 Prepackaged Software.
    P3571 Electronic Computers.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>MGMT  Management &amp; Marketing.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    PEOP  People.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 12
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT944-18631</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EJCE7AC8FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>941003
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  03 OCT 94 / Media Futures: Magic market for Microsoft - The world's
biggest software company has a mission to 'edutain'
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN CANE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<PERSON>Bernard Vergnes</PERSON>, president of <LOCATION>Microsoft Europe</LOCATION>, describes his ambitions in
multimedia carefully. Without wanting to appear arrogant, he says, he wants
to be the leading supplier of educational and other programmes  - sometimes
known as 'edutainment' - published on CD-Rom. These are the building bricks
of the multimedia revolution.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, the world's largest software company, helped pioneer the genre in
<DATE>1992</DATE> with <ORGANIZATION>Musical Instruments</ORGANIZATION>, a CD-Rom ideally suited to demonstrating the
combination of text, video and quality sound which characterises multimedia
presentations.
Today, <ORGANIZATION>Musical Instruments</ORGANIZATION> still impresses but looks dated compared with
newer offerings such as The Magic School Bus, a series to be released
shortly. It is said to be <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> president <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>'s current
favourite, and features a yellow <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> school bus with driver and passengers
which can be shrunk to navigate through the digestive system in The Human
Body or the cosmos in The Solar System. <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s best-selling Dinosaurs
of 18 months ago included five moving video clips; Dangerous Creatures, a
new release, has more than 100.
<PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON>, who has worked for <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> since <DATE>1983</DATE> and has been its European
president since <DATE>1990</DATE>, believes that the domestic market for CD-Rom is about
to expand rapidly, especially in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. He reckons that personal computers
equipped for multimedia will reach the 'magic price<DATE>' this Christmas</DATE> at which
substantial domestic sales can be expected.
He defines that price as just below Pounds 1,000 in <LOCATION>Britain</LOCATION> or FFr10,000 in
<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>. For this, customers will get a PC built around a high-performance
<ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION> 486 or 'Pentium' chip with 16 megabytes of fast memory and a
300-megabyte hard disc together with a CD-Rom player and sound capabilities.
In <LOCATION>France</LOCATION>, he says, some 25 per cent of PC sales are now through
supermarkets. <ORGANIZATION>Carrefour</ORGANIZATION>, the large French chain, is marketing its own range
of five models, some of which can handle multimedia.
Microsoft is taking the home market seriously. It has some 500-600 people,
including educationists, psychologists and software specialists, in its
consumer group, and is spending just under Dollars 100m a year on developing
new titles. Sales are about Dollars 300m a year.
In total, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> spends about Dollars 600m on research and development,
most of it on software, which brings a much greater financial return. 'We
are over-investing for the future in these areas,' says <PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON>.
Success in consumer markets is critical to <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s plans. Its worldwide
sales - Dollars 4.7bn (Pounds 2.97bn) last year - comprise desktop
applications, PC operating systems, word processors, spreadsheets and
database managers. Revenue growth last year was 24 per cent.
However, <PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON> admits that 'the traditional PC software market will not
grow forever. One day, probably sooner rather than later, most desktops in
developed countries will have a PC with a complete suite of business
programs'.
The company plans to reach sales of Dollars 8bn by 1995-96, but <PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON> says
the extra Dollars 3bn will not come entirely from desktop applications.
'Unless we make at least Dollars 1bn from consumer products, we shall not
achieve our target.'
He is encouraged by research showing that each professional PC installed
leads to purchases of - on average - five software packages during its life.
But up to 15 purchases of software a year can be expected for domestic PCs
if the price is right. The consumer software division is turning out three
new titles a month.
The competition is not sitting idle. <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s principal competitors,
<ORGANIZATION>Lotus Development Corporation</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Novell</ORGANIZATION>, have their own consumer products
divisions. Recently <ORGANIZATION>Novell</ORGANIZATION>, the market leader in networking, announced a
series of home education CD-Roms focusing on reading, writing and
arithmetic.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s ambitions in multimedia, however, range across the board. It is
spending about Dollars 120m a year on software for the digital superhighway
through its advanced consumer technology research group, an elite operation
headed by chief technologist <PERSON>Nathan Myhrvold</PERSON> and reporting directly to Bill
Gates.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> interprets the highway as an electronic pipeline into each home
able to convey an almost limitless stream of information. Database computers
or servers provide the data which is unscrambled by a black box on top of
the television set. Earlier this year <ORGANIZATION>Myhrvold</ORGANIZATION>'s group announced 'Tiger':
video server software which <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> says is the first phase of a complex,
interactive video system.
It runs on conventional personal computers. According to <LOCATION>Vergnes</LOCATION>: 'We
believe that traditional PC technology will develop fast enough so that we
can build these servers from inexpensive hardware. We can share the
processing load between the network server and the set-top box which, after
all, is only a powerful personal computer.'
There is, thus, a close similarity between <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s model of the
information superhighways and the modern data-processing concept of
client-server computing where server computers provide data to a network of
PCs.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s latest operating software, Windows NT, is intended to manage
client-server networks. Indeed, <PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON> believes that business will be first
to find applications for the information superhighway, with domestic
applications following later.
He echoes <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>'s complaints that most multimedia trials involve only
video-on-demand (VOD) - the ability to call a video of choice to the TV
screen. While technically complex, he does not believe that VOD is a true
test of demand for multimedia services.
In consequence, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s own trials - to be held with the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> company <ORGANIZATION>TCI</ORGANIZATION>
in <LOCATION>Denver</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> next year - will be sophisticated and involve a range
of services. Example: <PERSON>Vergnes</PERSON> envisages an education forum where teachers
from a broad range of schools and colleges could exchange views and
experience.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Microsoft Europe.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>XGZ  Europe.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7372 Prepackaged Software.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>TECH  Products &amp; Product use.
    CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 15
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06281023 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06281023 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  WASHINGTON; COLLEGE; EDUCATION; MONEY; CHARITY; COMPUTER; SOFTWARE; COMPANY;
OFFICIAL; MEDICAL; GENETIC; TECHNOLOGY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Microsoft Corp. Chairman Bill Gates, the second-richest man in the United
States, shared some of his wealth today by donating $12 million to the
University of Washington.;   The gift will be used to create a department of
molecular biotechnology at the college's medical school and to hire noted
immunologist Leroy Hood of the California Institute of Technology as the
department's first chairman.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  GATES GIVES $12 MILLION TO SCHOOL  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Gates' donation also will be used to set up an intellectual venture capital
fund that will provide seed money for university scientists in molecular
biotechnology research.;   Molecular biotechnology is the study of DNA and
other major building blocks of life. Scientists are researching ways to modify
these building blocks to identify and treat diseases and other medical
problems.;   <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>' donation is the largest ever to the university, eclipsing
the <MONEY>$11 million</MONEY> donated three years ago by <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> co-founder <PERSON>Paul Allen.;  
Gates</PERSON> told a news conference that biotechnology is one of his chief interests
in addition to computers. Gates has invested in a small biotech company, <ORGANIZATION>ICOS
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION>, but he said that company won't be directly involved with the
university.;   <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>, 35, did not attend the <ORGANIZATION>University</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>, but his
mother, <PERSON>Mary Gates</PERSON>, is a regent of the university and a member of the board of
its medical center.;   The most recent issue of Forbes magazine lists Gates as
the second-richest man in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>, with an estimated worth of <MONEY>$4.8 billion</MONEY> --
a fortune he made as <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> became the world's biggest maker of computer
software.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  Seattle  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911007  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  October  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  9D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  252  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday, October 7, 1991
00281023,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT941-3331</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-ECQAKAG1FT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940316
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
'Evolutionary rather than revolutionary' - Multimedia in the office / Bill
Gates, founder and chairman of Microsoft, has poured scorn on most of the
multimedia trials in the US and Europe, reports Alan Cane. Microsoft is
meanwhile investing Dollars 100m a year in multimedia and aims to set the
agenda in the technology
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By ALAN CANE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
harnessing its resources to a new goal: leadership in the design of
multimedia systems.
It is already investing over Dollars 100m a year - out of an research and
development budget of Dollars 473m - on the critical operating software. <PERSON>Mr
Bill Gates</PERSON>, the company's founder and chairman, said <DATE>earlier this month</DATE> that
the company had more people working on multimedia than any other software
group.
The implication is that the company wants to establish its software as the
global standard in multimedia just as its MS/DOS and Windows operating
systems are the world standard for <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s design of personal computers.
There have been some early clues: <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is already working with <ORGANIZATION>Sega</ORGANIZATION>,
the Japanese games console manufacturer, on an operating system for a new
machine, although <PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> says the project is small and divorced from
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s mainline operating systems development.
Some weeks ago, it bought Soft Image, a Canadian company which is market
leader in the esoteric discipline of software for moving picture animation.
The special effects in the film <LOCATION>Jurassic Park</LOCATION> are its work.
Furthermore, it has announced it intends to test its multimedia software in
collaboration with <ORGANIZATION>Tele-Communications Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,( TCI), the largest <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> cable
operator. A first fruit from the venture will be a new channel of
programming aimed at the consumer market for computer hardware, software and
accessories.
What <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> intends to provide is the operating software which will
manage the flow of information of all kinds on to high speed networks and
the software which will connect it to personal computer operating systems in
the home or office. It may also provide some of the applications - a
personal money management program, for example.
<PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> says 'there are a lot of companies developing software for the
'information highway,' just as there were a lot of companies involved in
operating systems at the beginning of the personal computer business.
Everybody who is doing multimedia software will have lots of pilots. Based
on the quality of those pilots, some will emerge stronger than others'.
<PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> would begin testing home multimedia services in the
<LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> in <DATE>1995</DATE>. He did not expect substantial returns on his
investment for five years, although he thought that there would be
substantive developments in multimedia in <DATE>1996-97</DATE> with entire cities
converted to interactive networks.
Multimedia and the 'information superhighway,' the high-capacity network
which will link vast repositories of information with modified television
sets or personal computers, are creating intense interest among computer
companies, telecommunications organisations and entertainment firms. They
are jockeying to take advantage of what are expected to be lucrative new
business opportunities.
Bill Gates, however, argues that most are taking the wrong approach - 'dead
ends' were how he described them - 'because the user-interface is so simple,
and because they do not tie in to personal computers in the right way, the
results will be disappointing. The revenue and the usage that comes out of
them will not justify the huge infrastructure costs.'
most of the trials to date have been designed to exploit domestic
multimedia, offering, typically, menus of video films for home viewing, <PERSON>Mr
Gates</PERSON> says that business will make use of the multimedia first.
'The first widespread use of these capabilities will be in business,' he
predicted. 'It will involve things like video-conferencing and collaboration
which would enable you to do your job without going into the office. Or it
could help companies find expertise to help them out without the expert
having to travel.
'The network itself could create electronic markets able to find a resource
of any type.'
'So, what in the past we have seen as electronic markets for currencies or
stocks will move into items of all types where chequeing references and
other kinds of working together can be done very effectively in electronic
form.'
'This will be done by extending the range of the personal computer. One of
the early symptoms will be very low cost video conferencing where a PC is
connected up to an ISDN (integrated services digital network). Within two or
three years this will be extremely widespread.
(<ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION>, which makes the microprocessors used in the majority of the world's
personal computers, earlier this year announced a low-cost set of components
capable of turning a personal computer into a video-conferencing terminal).
<PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> thought that multimedia in the office would be evolutionary rather
than revolutionary, driven by proven technologies like electronic mail -
'the benefits of electronic mail are unbelievable. We could not run
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> without that capability.
'Today, some think of electronic mail and work group software and the
Internet (an open, publicly available computer network spanning several
continents) as separate things, but with some enhancements to Windows due in
less than a year, we will bring all these things together.'
Once the technology and benefits have been established in a business
environment, that would be the time to move into the home.
<PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> was critical of the narrow range of many of the current multimedia
trials: 'Some of the early pilots will be particularly embarrassing because
they will not have the breadth of applications,' he said.
'The network operators running these pilots are acting against their own
interests because they are going to prove exactly what they do not want to
prove - that there will not be enough revenue generated to justify building
the infrastructure.'
'Until you have a broad range of applications, you will never be able to
demonstrate the true potential of these systems. That is why instead of
doing crummy pilots in <DATE>1994</DATE>, we will start our trials in <DATE>1995</DATE>.'
He extended his criticism to <ORGANIZATION>Oracle</ORGANIZATION>, the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> database specialist with which
<ORGANIZATION>British Telecommunications</ORGANIZATION> has formed an alliance to test interactive
entertainment services in the home. <ORGANIZATION>Oracle</ORGANIZATION> will provide the software and
systems integration: 'I'm sure <ORGANIZATION>Oracle</ORGANIZATION> will change its approach because it is
a terrible approach,' he said.
Bill Gates' comments have to be seen against a background of intense
competition in the nascent multimedia business. Furthermore, he has never
been slow to promote <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s efforts and pick holes in the competition.
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Microsoft Corp.
    Tele-Communications Inc.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7372 Prepackaged Software.
    P4841 Cable and Other Pay Television Services.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>CMMT  Comment &amp; Analysis.
    RES  Capital expenditures.
    RES  R&amp;D spending.
    COMP  Strategic links &amp; Joint venture.
    TECH  Services &amp; Services use.
    MKTS  Market shares.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page III
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900521-0066
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900521-0066.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Microsoft Isn't Giving Up
   On OS/2 Operating System
</HL>
<DATE>
05/21/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   MSFT
</CO>
<IN>
SOFTWARE (SOF)
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
</IN>
<LP>
   OS/2, the new PC operating system Microsoft announced for
IBM three years ago, today is an also-ran. It requires too
much computer memory, and some promised features haven't
arrived. It also can't run Windows applications.
   Microsoft has sold only a few hundred thousand copies of
OS/2. Mr. Gates seems to be trying to lower expectations for
it, saying he now expects it to coexist with the current PC
standard, MS-DOS, for years instead of replacing it.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   With <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is at work on a new version of OS/2
that will run Windows. It will also make better use of the
most popular microprocessor, <ORGANIZATION>Intel</ORGANIZATION>'s 80386. "We have to
provide a seamless, easy transition from the old to the new,"
says <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> president <PERSON>Jon Shirley</PERSON>. "That's something we've
failed to do in prior versions of OS/2." <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> insists
OS/2 will emerge later in the decade as the operating
software of choice for PC users.
   "People said we'd fail" with Windows, he says. "Now
they're saying we'll fail with OS/2. We won't."
   For <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s sake, it better not. OS/2 is the only
operating system the company controls with as much power as
Unix, an older system created by <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp;
Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>, which is the standard for engineering and
scientific computers and is slowly catching on with
white-collar workers.
   (See related story: "Operating System: Opening of
`Windows' Shows How Bill Gates Succeeds in Software ---
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> Founder Bargains, Frets, <ORGANIZATION>Badgers Engineers</ORGANIZATION> and
Never Tires of Games --- An Early Zeal for Capitalism" -- WSJ
<DATE>May 21, 1990</DATE>)
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT943-13543</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-EGSDRAEJFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>940719
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  19 JUL 94 / Microsoft rises as Gates plays down settlement
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LOUISE KEHOE
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
   SAN FRANCISCO
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s settlement of anti-trust charges with the <ORGANIZATION>US Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>
and European competition authorities will have 'no material impact' on
financial performance, according to <PERSON>Mr Bill Gates</PERSON>, chairman and founder of
the software company.
The settlement, which requires <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> to modify its operating system
licensing practices, 'eliminates something that could have become a major
distraction', <PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> said yesterday.
He reiterated his belief that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> had never done anything
'inappropriate or illegal'. The company's success in selling operating
systems programs for PCs was based on demand, not on licensing terms.
Industry analysts said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> 'got off easy' on <ORGANIZATION>Justice Department</ORGANIZATION>
charges that it 'built a barricade of exclusionary and unreasonably
restrictive licensing agreements to deny others an opportunity to develop
and market competing products'.
Investors appeared to concur with this view as <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s share price rose
Dollars 1 7/8 yesterday to reach Dollars 50 1/2 by the close.
<PERSON>Mr Gates</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s future remained dependent upon its ability to
'continue to come up with great products'. The settlement provided the
company with an opportunity to do that without the burden of a costly legal
battle.
Competition authorities had examined several issues raised by competitors,
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> said. Most were not pursued and the settlement covered only
licensing practices and non-disclosure.
The settlement does not address concern in the software industry that
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> gains unfair advantages as a developer of both operating systems,
such as wordprocessors, games and spreadsheets.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is the largest seller of applications for use with its own Windows
operating system. This dual role is its principal advantage, according to
software industry executives, because <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s applications developers
have earlier and better access to details of next-generation systems than
their competitors.
However, <PERSON>Mr Bill Neukom</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s general counsel, said this issue did
not come up in the discussions. 'We can conclude that the government decided
that it had no basis on which to act on these complaints.'
For the <DATE>next six and a half years</DATE>, the duration of the settlement,
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s business activities will be monitored by the <ORGANIZATION>US Justice
Department</ORGANIZATION> and European competition authorities.
Editorial Comment, Page 15
Lex, Page 16
</TEXT>
<XX>
Companies:-
</XX>
<CO>Microsoft Corp.
</CO>
<XX>
Countries:-
</XX>
<CN>USZ  United States of America.
</CN>
<XX>
Industries:-
</XX>
<IN>P7372 Prepackaged Software.
</IN>
<XX>
Types:-
</XX>
<TP>MKTS  Market shares.
    TECH  Safety &amp; Standards.
</TP>
<PUB>The Financial Times
</PUB>
<PAGE>
London Page 17
</PAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>
WSJ900521-0090
</DOCNO>
<DOCID>
900521-0090.
</DOCID>
<HL>
   Latest From Microsoft Will Heighten
   Competition With Apple's Macintosh
   ----
   By G. Pascal Zachary
</HL>
<DATE>
05/21/90
</DATE>
<SO>
WALL STREET JOURNAL (J), PAGE A4
</SO>
<CO>
   MSFT AAPL
</CO>
<IN>
COMPUTERS AND INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY (CPR)
SOFTWARE (SOF)
</IN>
<LP>
   CUPERTINO, Calif. -- Bill Gates swears he doesn't mean
Apple any harm.
   Maybe so. But Windows 3.0, a product he's so proud of that
even his mother will be on hand when Microsoft unveils it
tomorrow, presents the most formidable technical challenge
ever to the Macintosh, Apple Computer's main computer family.
</LP>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> says he has always been interested in making PCs
easy to use. But he insists that only recently have they
grown powerful enough to handle the images and split-screens
needed to control them with simple, intuitive commands.
   Yet Apple did precisely this <DATE>six years ago</DATE>, and became the
second largest supplier of personal computers in the world.
Apple created for its Macintosh a new system software, the
program that controls basic operations such as storing files
and sending documents to a printer. The Macintosh operating
system was entirely different from <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s MS-DOS, the
standard for most other desktop computers.
   In MS-DOS, programs' effectiveness is restricted by memory
limitations, and users risk confusion if they forget arcane
command codes. The Macintosh gave the user visual cues to
simplify mundane tasks like copying documents or storing
files.
   Now <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s new Windows, after two earlier,
disappointing Windows versions, comes close to matching the
most compelling features of the <ORGANIZATION>Macintosh</ORGANIZATION>. And it does so
within the familiar MS-DOS standard, so consumers don't have
to jettison their old programs. Windows even promises a
feature that Macintoshes won't have until next year: the
ability to automatically exchange data between two different
programs.
   Computer experts say the Macintosh system still makes it
simpler to start up the machine, store files and hook up
printers, among other things. But those differences may not
overshadow the major advantage of PCs that use MS-DOS and
Windows: They are far less expensive.
   Apple has less-costly models on the way. It will introduce
a color Macintosh for less than <MONEY>$2,000</MONEY> as early as this <DATE>fall</DATE>.
And it doesn't concede that Windows is its equal: "Microsoft
is very good at comparing their intentions with our
realities," says <PERSON>Jim Davis</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>'s director of systems
software marketing.
   But Apple takes Windows seriously enough that it has sued
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> charging copyright infringement. Apple also worries
that it is too dependent on <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> for applications -- the
three best-selling packages for the Macintosh are made by
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> -- and that in the future <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> may give less
attention to <ORGANIZATION>Macintosh</ORGANIZATION> applications. Over the years, some at
<ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> have called for breaking with <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON>, fearing that
his secret plan is to weaken <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>'s position by imposing a
single software standard for all desktop users.
   Yet today <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> enjoys cordial relations with <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>
chief executive <PERSON>John Sculley</PERSON>. About two months ago, he even
spent several hours helping <PERSON>Mr. Sculley</PERSON> hash out <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION>'s
technical direction.
   <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> says the way for <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> to keep its edge is to
continue to deliver new ways of controlling the PC-voice,
handwriting, multimedia, whatever. But "Apple needs to
focus," he says. "John agrees. Now let's see if he picks the
right areas."
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06170020 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06170020 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press File Photograph; Gates admitted Microsoft's
customer support record was bad  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; SOFTWARE; COMPANY; PROFILE  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  For most people, nightmares end with the dawn. For Bill Gates, the
hard-driving chairman of Microsoft Corp., who is known to keep pictures of his
opponents in his office, they linger during the day as well.;    In a "state
of the company" memo written for his top staff, Gates said some of his worst
fears for his billion-dollar software company -- normally seen as being on top
of the world -- are coming true.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  LOOK WHO'S GAINING
2 MICROSOFT'S GATES EYES CHALLENGES  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     "Our nightmare -- <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> 'attacking' us in system software, <ORGANIZATION>Novell</ORGANIZATION> 'defeating'
us in networking and more agile, customer-oriented applications competitors
getting their Windows act together -- is a reality," Gates wrote.;    But
plucky in the face of those threats, <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has a simple
response to its competition -- the Windows software control program that has
been a runaway success since its introduction last year.;    "Just as <ORGANIZATION>DEC</ORGANIZATION>'s
strategy for the '80s was VAX, our strategy for the '90s is Windows -- one
evolving architecture, a couple of implementations. Everything we do should
focus on making Windows more successful," he wrote.;    The memo, issued last
month and obtained by the <ORGANIZATION>Mercury News</ORGANIZATION>, shows Gates not as the arrogant
multibillionaire of legend but instead as a CEO whose mind never strays far
from threats to the <LOCATION>Redmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, company he co-founded.;    His attention
runs to questions of long-term importance, such as the need to work with
Japanese companies on software for digital consumer electronics. But he's also
well-versed in industry minutiae, such as passing along rumors that Scotts
Valley-based <ORGANIZATION>Borland International Inc.</ORGANIZATION> will include a word-processing program
in the upcoming Windows version of its Quattro Pro spreadsheet.;    At the top
of Gates' list of problems are two legal disputes the company is involved in
-- a copyright suit brought by <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, which has so far gone well
for <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, and a <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trade Commission</ORGANIZATION> antitrust inquiry.;    "If the
judge (in the <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> case) rules against us without making it clear what we
have to change or asks us to eliminate something fundamental to all windowing
systems (like overlapping windows), it would be disastrous," he wrote.;    He
also wrote, "Certainly I take the <ORGANIZATION>FTC</ORGANIZATION> inquiry seriously, and I am sure it will
use up even more executive staff time than the <ORGANIZATION>Apple</ORGANIZATION> lawsuit has. However, I
know we don't get unfair advantages. I hope we can quickly educate the <ORGANIZATION>FTC</ORGANIZATION> on
our business.";    There was some blunt language reserved for <ORGANIZATION>International
Business Machines Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, with whom <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has had a well-publicized dispute
about future computer operating systems.;    While working with <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> has forced
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> to accept "poor code, poor design and other overhead," Gates wrote
that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> "will not attack <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> as a company, and even our public
'attacks' on (<ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>'s) OS/2 will be very professional.;    "Eventually we need
to have at least a neutral relationship with <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>. For the next 24 months, it
may be fairly cold. We can emerge as a better and stronger company where
people won't just say we are the standard because <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> chose us.";    But he
admitted that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s greatest risk will be if <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> uses its connections at
Fortune 500 companies to freeze it out.;    Gates also conceded that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>
has had a difficult time in making good on its promise of catching up to
<ORGANIZATION>Novell Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, the industry's leading networking software company.;    "We knew
it wasn't going to be easy, but it has been even harder than we expected to
build a position in networking. You will see us backing off on some of our
spending level, but don't doubt that we are totally committed to the
business.";    In other portions of the memo, Gates admitted <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s
customer support record was bad. "The number of customers who get a bad
impression because of this must be in the millions worldwide.";   
Microsoft-watchers who were shown the memo said it again revealed him to be on
top of all aspects of his business.;    "A lot of CEOs at successful companies
have a sense of complacency," said <ORGANIZATION>Dataquest</ORGANIZATION>'s <PERSON>Marshall Mosely</PERSON>. "But Gates has
a healthy respect for that which can harm him. I think that's commendable."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  LEE GOMES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910618  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Tuesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  703  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Tuesday June 18, 1991
00170020,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06162039 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06162039 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: GOING ALL OUT -- Chairman Bill Gates has rented a yacht and
hired the Dave Brubeck quartet for the rollout.  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; SOFTWARE; COMPANY  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Microsoft Corp. has rented a yacht and hired the Dave Brubeck quartet to
announce a new version of the world's most widely used computer software.;   
Microsoft says the rollout Tuesday will be the biggest launch of a new
software product in computer industry history.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business Monday  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  MICROSOFT PLANS SPLASHY LAUNCH FOR DOS 5.0  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     The new product is an update of MS-DOS, the base layer of software used on
an estimated 60 million IBM-type personal computers worldwide. It provides
enhanced features compared with older versions of DOS, including more
available memory and a new "help" feature.;    The new DOS also moves the
software closer in appearance and features to Windows, a <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> product
that makes IBM-type computers easier to use. Windows has been a runaway
success since <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> introduced an improved version a year ago.;    DOS is
a type of software called an operating system, which controls a computer's
internal functions. On top of it, a computer user runs application programs
importance <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> places on the new product, called DOS 5.0, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>
Chairman <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON> has rented the dinner-cruise yacht New Yorker for a news
conference in the <LOCATION>Hudson River</LOCATION>. Dining and dancing to the music of <PERSON>Dave
Brubeck</PERSON> is included.;    An extensive advertising and marketing campaign will
follow.;    <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, the largest software maker, hopes its splashy launch of
DOS 5.0 will help it overcome the disappointing sales of the last major DOS
update. DOS 4.0, announced three years ago, failed to take off -- partly
because it was riddled with bugs -- and most owners of IBM-type computers
continue to use earlier DOS versions.;    To avoid similar quality problems
with DOS 5.0, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> conducted what it called the most extensive testing
program in personal computer software history. About 7,000 users were given
advance copies to find bugs and make suggestions.;    "We learned from our
mistakes," said <PERSON>Brad Chase</PERSON>, the DOS 5.0 product manager.;    Another problem
with DOS 4.0 was that it actually took up more computer memory space than
previous versions. DOS 5.0 gives computer users more memory than all earlier
DOS versions so programs run better.;    <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> says it will make DOS 5.0
available to personal computer makers and, for the first time in a DOS
upgrade, directly to existing personal computer owners. Previous DOS upgrades
were available to personal computer owners only through the computer makers
themselves.;    <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> says it will sell a <MONEY>$99.95</MONEY> kit to upgrade earlier
versions of DOS to DOS 5.0 through about 7,000 computer stores. In addition,
130 personal computer makers worldwide have licensed DOS 5.0 for use in new
computers.;    Industry analyst <PERSON>Mary Meeker</PERSON> of <ORGANIZATION>Morgan Stanley &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. Inc. said
she believes DOS 5.0 will be a hit.;    "I think it's an important upgrade.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is going to market it aggressively," she said. "The feedback (from
testers) has been very strong.";    She said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> could sell about 8
million upgrade kits for DOS 5.0. She estimated <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> would make about <MONEY>$30</MONEY>
profit on each, or a total of <MONEY>$240 million.</MONEY>;    <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, based in <LOCATION>Redmond</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>, earned <MONEY>$279.2 million</MONEY> on revenue of <MONEY>$1.18 billion</MONEY> in the <DATE>fiscal year
ended June 30</DATE>, 1990.;    In addition to providing more memory and "help" text
that pops up in boxes on the computer screen, DOS 5.0 reconfigures the way the
screen looks to make it more user-friendly.;    DOS 5.0 borrows some of its
screen appearance from Windows, a program that is layered on top of DOS,
replacing DOS' arcane typed commands with graphical symbols (icons) and a
hand-held control device (a mouse) like those of <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s
Macintosh line of personal computers.;    But despite DOS 5.0's ease-of-use
features, <ORGANIZATION>Chase</ORGANIZATION> said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> doesn't believe it will compete with Windows.; 
  <ORGANIZATION>Chase</ORGANIZATION> said he believes corporations will install DOS 5.0 on older personal
computers that cannot use Windows to prepare employees for the conversion to
Windows-equipped personal computers.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  BART ZIEGLER, Associated Press  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<CITY>  New York  </CITY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910610  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Monday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  13D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  669  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Monday June 10, 1991
00162039,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> WSJ870320-0137 </DOCNO>
<HL> Results in Industry First
For Computer Whiz Kid
---
By Brenton R. Schlender
<DD> 03/20/87</DD>
<SO> WALL STREET JOURNAL (J)</SO>
<IN> MSFT </IN>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>William Gates</PERSON>, founder and chairman of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, became the personal computer industry's first billion-dollar man yesterday. 

   The 31-year-old <ORGANIZATION>Harvard University</ORGANIZATION> dropout holds 11,018,955 shares, or about a <PERCENT>42%</PERCENT> stake in <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, which supplies, among other things, the internal program that controls the basic functions of <ORGANIZATION>International Business Machines Inc.</ORGANIZATION>'s PC line of personal computers and compatible machines. 

   The magic number for the billion-dollar mark for <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON>'s stake was a share price of <MONEY>$90.75</MONEY>, and the stock rose above and dipped below that level during the day. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON>, who was traveling in <LOCATION>South America</LOCATION>, wasn't available for comment on his new distinction. 
In recent months, colleagues and competitors had begun to jokingly refer to <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> as "Billion Dollar Bill" as the paper value of his fortune swelled. 

   <PERSON>Mr. Gates</PERSON> is the biggest beneficiary of an astonishing run-up in the price of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> shares. 
The shares, which first were offered to the public a little more than a year ago for <MONEY>$21</MONEY> each, have been outpacing the booming stock markets in recent months, and have nearly doubled in value since the end of the year. 

   "Is there a premium in the stock price because of Bill Gates?" asked <PERSON>Richard Sherlund</PERSON>, an analyst who follows the company for <ORGANIZATION>Goldman, Sachs &amp; Co</ORGANIZATION>. 
"I'd have to say yes, because he is considered one of the brightest people in the industry." 
<PERSON>Mr. Sherlund</PERSON> also said <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s role "at the focal point of the personal computer industry" -- supplying operating system software to both <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> and other manufacturers -- has driven market enthusiasm for the stock. 

   Not even the founders of <ORGANIZATION>Apple Computer Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Steven P. Jobs</PERSON> and <PERSON>Steve Wozniak</PERSON>, came close to building billion-dollar fortunes in personal computers, even though they practically fathered that industry. 

   In high-technology businesses, only <PERSON>H. Ross Perot</PERSON>, who founded <ORGANIZATION>Electronic Data Systems Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, now the data-processing services division of <ORGANIZATION>General Motors Corp.</ORGANIZATION>, and <PERSON>David Packard</PERSON> and <PERSON>William Hewlett</PERSON>, founders of computer and scientific instrument maker <ORGANIZATION>Hewlett-Packard Co.</ORGANIZATION>, have the distinction of building personal fortunes estimated to exceed <MONEY>$1 billion</MONEY>. 

</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880716-0013 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-16-88 0032EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a AM-GatorHunt 1stLd-Writethru a0740 07-16 0465</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Gator Hunt, 1st Ld - Writethru, a0740,0472</SECOND>
<HEAD>Deadline Passes To Apply For Gator Licenses</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Subs 9th graf `Florida residents' to add that choice is by
lottery.</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By ED BIRK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>TALLAHASSEE, Fla. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   More than 5,000 hunters met <DATE>Friday</DATE>'s
deadline to apply for just 235 licenses in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION>'s first
alligator hunt in 25 years. The lucky winners won't be allowed to
use guns.
   Once an endangered species, the American alligator now numbers
about 1 million in <LOCATION>Florida</LOCATION> and is increasingly encountering humans
as the state's people population also grows.
   A 4-year-old girl was killed by an alligator in <DATE>May</DATE> near her
family's lakeside home in <LOCATION>Englewood</LOCATION>, in <LOCATION>southwest Florida</LOCATION>, but
planning for the hunt had been under way long before that.
   The Game and <ORGANIZATION>Fresh Water Fish Commission</ORGANIZATION> gave final approval
<DATE>Friday</DATE>, during a meeting in <LOCATION>Ocala</LOCATION>, for the trapping and killing of
up to 3,425 alligators in 20 wildlife management areas during the
30-day hunt this <DATE>fall</DATE>. That quote assumes that not every hunter
will get his full 15-animal limit.
   Commission spokesman <PERSON>Scott Ball</PERSON> said 15,000 applications were
printed and he was surprised that only 5,000 people applied.
   ``A lot of people have been calling up in the last few days that
have been procrastinating and kicking themselves for waiting until
the last minute,'' said Ball. ``They are asking about next year.''
   The sanctioned hunts will occur only at night and trappers will
have to use snares, harpoons, spears or similar weapons to get a
gator close enough to kill. The only firearm allowed will be a
``bangstick,'' a pole with a shotgun shell on the end that is used
to kill a gator once it is snared and brought up to a boat, said
Ball.
   Part of the motivation for hunting gators may be economic. Gator
meat sells for about <MONEY>$5</MONEY> a pound; hide sells for about <MONEY>$40</MONEY> a foot.
   Florida residents selected by lottery for the hunt will have to
pay a <MONEY>$250</MONEY> license fee, plus a <MONEY>$30</MONEY> tag fee for each gator they
catch up. Out-of-state hunters will have to pay <MONEY>$1,000</MONEY> for the
licenses.
   In addition to the license fees and tag fees, those awarded
licenses will have to go through a six-hour training course in
early <DATE>August</DATE>, said <LOCATION>Ball</LOCATION>.
   The targeted reptiles will have to be at least 4 feet long.
   The tag fee is to pay for inspection and verification that hides
being prepared for market are legal.
   ``It's tightly regulated so that only legal hides will be
brought to marketplace,'' said Ball. ``There are only a few
processors of hides. We keep an eye on them.''
   Since the mid-1960s, alligator hunting virtually has been banned
except for isolated experimental hunts since <DATE>1982</DATE> and the removal
of nuisance alligators in populated areas.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06172046 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06172046 </ACCESS>
<DESCRIPT>  COMPUTER; SOFTWARE; COMPANY; STOCK; COST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Candor has its price, and for Microsoft Corp. Chairman Bill Gates, it's
apparently $320 million.;    That was the amount that Gates' "paper fortune"
shrank Wednesday as the result of a 7 percent decline in Microsoft's stock
blamed on Wall Street reaction to Gates' memo on the numerous challenges
facing his company.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Business  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  PAPER LOSSES: GATES' MEMO COST HIM MILLIONS  </HEADLINE>
<TEXT>     Gates' six-page lament, originally intended for the <LOCATION>Redmond</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Wash.</LOCATION>,
software supplier's senior staff but later leaked, told how <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has
cultivated an opponent rather than an ally in <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION>; how <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has made no
inroads in the fast-growing networking marketplace; and how it stands to lose
sales to leaner competitors, such as <ORGANIZATION>Borland International Inc.</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Scotts
Valley.</LOCATION>;    <PERSON>Gates</PERSON>, who has a reputation as a competitor-obsessed worrier, ends
the memo on an upbeat note by trumpeting his strategy to make the Windows
control program an even bigger success. But <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> shares nonetheless fell
<MONEY>$8.13</MONEY> to close at <MONEY>$103.38</MONEY> in trading that was more than double normal levels.
At <DATE>midday today</DATE>, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> was down to <MONEY>$100.</MONEY>;    Gates owns about a third of
the 115 million outstanding shares of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> stock.;    Previously trading
at about 30 times earnings, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has long been one of Wall Street's
pricier stocks. Analysts said that by concentrating in a single document so
much bad news about <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, the memo brought to the surface a lingering
investor concern that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> might be overvalued.;    "The market is
pricing a new risk into the <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> story," said <PERSON>David Readerman</PERSON>, analyst at
<ORGANIZATION>Shearson Lehman</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>San Francisco.</LOCATION>;    Despite the dramatic drop in the stock
price, Gates -- who was traveling in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION> on <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> -- should not
despair, as there is life after a self-critical memo.;    <ORGANIZATION>Ask Autodesk Inc.</ORGANIZATION>,
the <LOCATION>Sausalito</LOCATION> design software company whose stock is close to its 52-week high
despite a blistering 44-page memo by founder <PERSON>John Walker</PERSON> released 2 1/2 months
ago -- a document <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> cited as inspiration for his own.;    <PERSON>Walker</PERSON> called
his memo "The Final Days" and compared <ORGANIZATION>Autodesk</ORGANIZATION> to <ORGANIZATION>NASA</ORGANIZATION> before the explosion
of the space shuttle.;    "I am deeply concerned about the future of the
company," <PERSON>Walker</PERSON> wrote. "<ORGANIZATION>Autodesk</ORGANIZATION> possesses all the prerequisites to lead the
next generation of the PC industry, yet it seems to have become stuck in the
past, mired in bureaucracy, paralyzed by unwarranted caution and to have lost
the edge of rapid and responsive product development and aggressive marketing
and promotion on which the success of Autocad (its key product) was founded.";
   <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>, who retired from formal management tasks at the <DATE>firm three years
ago</DATE> but who still owns <PERCENT>4 percent</PERCENT> of its stock, went on to make a number of
specific recommendations for the company, some of which have been implemented.
Others will be enacted in a reorganization planned for <DATE>July 1</DATE>, a spokesman
said.;    <PERSON>Walker</PERSON>'s memo is in a long tradition of public self-criticism at
<ORGANIZATION>Autodesk</ORGANIZATION>; it was given out freely to the firm's 1,100 employees, and a dozen
previous efforts have been published in a book.;    Discussing the chance of a
memo being given to a competitor or reporter, the memo called such risks
"unavoidable consequences of placing the issues on <ORGANIZATION>Autodesk</ORGANIZATION>'s agenda."  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  LEE GOMES, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Stock Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910620  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Thursday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  June  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1F  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  525  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Thursday June 20, 1991
00172046,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO>FT933-9460</DOCNO>
<PROFILE>_AN-DHJCNACCFT</PROFILE>
<DATE>930810
</DATE>
<HEADLINE>
FT  10 AUG 93 / Technology: Bruised but not beaten - Microsoft is giving
mixed signals about its future prospects
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
   By LOUISE KEHOE
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
For <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> chairman <PERSON>Bill Gates</PERSON>, these are trying times. His company is
under scrutiny for alleged anti-trust violations; Wall Street has soured on
the stock; and after 18 years of spectacular growth <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is planning
for a 'bumpy' year ahead. Could <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> have lost the golden touch that
has enabled it to become the largest software company in the world, made
Gates, 37, the richest man in the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> and created hundreds of millionaires
among its employees?
This is the sort of question that irritates Gates. From his perspective,
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s achievements to date have nothing to do with a Midas charm,
rather they reflect hard work and perseverance, long-term vision and
commitment.
He has no patience with 'simplistic analysis' that assumes <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> will
inevitably be successful in anything the company turns its hand to. Or, as
is now the case, that short-term expectations for slower growth may signal
that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s glory days are coming to a close.
Indeed, predicting the outlook for <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is complicated by numerous
issues. Not the least of these is whether <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> will face an anti-trust
suit. The <ORGANIZATION>US Justice Department</ORGANIZATION> is currently reviewing documents from a
three-and-a-half year investigation conducted by the <ORGANIZATION>US Federal Trade
Commission</ORGANIZATION>.
Other problems for <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> include a downward trend in software prices and
a weak market environment in <LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>, one of its largest markets. With no big
operating system software product introductions planned for the next 12
months, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> also faces an unusual dry spell. Revenues from the
company's core business - software for office PCs - may grow less rapidly
than in the past.
Yet the company is driving ahead with ambitious plans to enter new markets
such as programs for hand-held 'personal digital assistants,' software for
children, multimedia products and software for the 'digital highways' of the
future.
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is also developing two new generations of personal computer
operating systems; one for desktop PCs, codenamed <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION>, and a second,
called <LOCATION>Cairo</LOCATION>, for computer networks (see below).
But torn between blowing <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s trumpet, to impress customers and
investors, or highlighting its vulnerabilities, to appease <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
regulators, Gates and other <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> executives are delivering a mixed
message about the company's future prospects.
'In looking at this industry and <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s role in it, I am very
optimistic,' Gates says. 'We are investing in a very optimistic way.'
In the next breath, however, he is urging caution. 'A number of these
investments may take a long time to pay off,' he says. 'If these new things
kick in, then we will go back to higher growth. If we're wrong, then we
won't ever advance beyond the level we are at today.'
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s propensity to point out the risks associated with entering new
markets, and that even its new PC software products could 'bomb', has
contributed to Wall Street's uncertainties.
'That tone of conservatism is part of our culture. We expect good results,
but prefer them to come as surprises,' Gates says. Yet veteran <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>
watchers believe that the company's recent emphasis on potential problems is
at least in part aimed at the ears of anti-trust regulators in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>
DC.
For example, <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is at pains to point out that it does have
competitors. Executives even highlighted rival products in a presentation to
financial analysts less than two weeks ago. And in an attempt to win
political support, Gates reels off the benefits which the PC industry has
provided to the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> economy, such as growth in exports and the creation of
jobs.
'Today's software business is thriving, and it is not just <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>,' says
<PERSON>Gates</PERSON>. 'There are 750 software companies in the state of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> alone
and the majority of them write software (applications programs) for
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft Windows</ORGANIZATION>. Net employment went up by more than the size of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>
just in the last year. . .the incredible thing is how well the <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> has done
in this business.' The <PERSON>Clinton</PERSON> administration would be foolish to do
anything that threatened the future of <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>, Gates seems to be
implying.
Politics aside, the greatest challenges facing <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> lie in the
development of a series of ground-breaking technologies. Gates is placing a
big bet on software for 'digital highways' - which could deliver multimedia
information services to millions of businesses and homes.
His goal is to establish a software standard for the way people use
information services, whether they be entertainment services on interactive
television, public information services at a kiosk in a shopping centre or
business information services in the office.
Partnerships - with cable television companies, telephone companies and
companies in the entertainment field - will be an important aspect of
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION>'s involvement in digital highways. While denying reports that
<ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> has already struck a deal, <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> acknowledges that <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> is
talking to <LOCATION>US West</LOCATION> as well as other <LOCATION>US</LOCATION> telephone companies, and <ORGANIZATION>TCI</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Time
Warner</ORGANIZATION>, the two largest US cable television companies. The gold rush
surrounding 'digital convergence' also has movie moguls, newspaper
companies, <ORGANIZATION>AT&amp;T</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>IBM</ORGANIZATION> knocking on his door, <PERSON>Gates</PERSON> says.
'You will see us enter into all sorts of partnerships.' Some will merely be
agreements to collaborate in trials of interactive television service.
Others may be 'hard-core joint ventures'. <ORGANIZATION>Microsoft</ORGANIZATION> also plans to make
minority equity investments in companies involved in digital highways.
'I am not aware of any other company that is making the kind of bet that we
are on digital information highways,' Gates says. The company will spend
'many <MONEY>tens of millions of dollars</MONEY>' developing the technology, and 'won't get
any revenue for at least three years. And it could all be wasted, but that
is the name of the game'.
The 'game' of spotting new technology directions and turning them into
business opportunities is one at which Gates is a master and with Dollars
