<DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890119-0039 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-19-89 0346EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-Bush-WarBuddies     01-19 0602</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush-War Buddies,600</SECOND>
<HEAD>War Buddies Gave His Life Direction, Bush Says</HEAD>
<HEAD>PM-Inaugural Rdp Bjt</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By MATT YANCEY</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   In an emotional reunion 44 years later, <PERSON>George
Bush</PERSON> paid tribute to the his World War II <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> flying comrades and
the submarine crewmen who nicknamed him ``Ellie'' after pulling him
from the drink.
   Fireworks lit up the sky over the <LOCATION>Lincoln Memorial</LOCATION> as <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, about
to become the nation's 41st president, spent half an hour of quiet
reflection <DATE>Wednesday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> with about three dozen of his war buddies.
   ``He spoke with great feeling about what the squadron and the
<ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s crewmen meant to him,'' said retired Rear Adm. <PERSON>Lawrence
Heyworth</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION> ``<PERSON>Mrs. Bush</PERSON>'s eyes kind of teared up
a little. It was very intimate.''
   <PERSON>Heyworth</PERSON> was gunnery and torpedo officer aboard the <ORGANIZATION>USS Finback</ORGANIZATION>
in <DATE>September 1944</DATE> when <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was one of five young <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> aviators
rescued by the submarine after being shot down by the Japanese over
the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> has accorded the Finback veterans, the widows of a few
others and an equal number of members of his aircraft carrier
<ORGANIZATION>Torpedo Squadron</ORGANIZATION> VT-51 from World War II the choicest seats at
several inaugural events.
   But first he welcomed them to his temporary quarters at the <ORGANIZATION>Blair
House</ORGANIZATION> across <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> for a private
reunion.
   ``It was very emotional,'' said <PERSON>Don Kohler</PERSON>, 64, of <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>,
the submarine torpedoman who helped pull <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> out of his bobbing
orange life raft onto the deck of the Finback after he had bailed
out of his flaming torpedo bomber on <DATE>Sept. 2, 1944</DATE>.
   ``You have to remember that few of us had seen any of the others
from the Finback for 44 years,'' <PERSON>Kohler</PERSON> said. ``And meeting under
these circumstances where the president-elect personally welcomes
us, it was pretty moving.''
   <PERSON>Kohler</PERSON> said <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> told the group that ``the youngness that was
there all those years ago and the things we were fighting for had a
great deal to do with directing his life and ideas.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> spent a few moments with each of the veterans, signing
pictures, looking at their scrapbooks, swapping remembrances.
   Heyworth quoted <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> as saying: ``If it weren't for you people in
this room, I wouldn't be here and I certainly wouldn't have been
   <PERSON>Hugo Parkman</PERSON>, 69, of <ORGANIZATION>Stone Mountain</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ga.</LOCATION>, the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s
communications officer, recalled <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> as ``a very clean-cut young
man.''
   ``I shared my bunk with him,'' <PERSON>Parkman</PERSON> said. ``That is, when I
was on duty, he slept, and when he was on duty I slept. On a
submarine everything's so tight, bunks don't get cold.''
   ``He was a very regular guy,'' said <PERSON>Parkman</PERSON>. ``We never knew that
he came from a distinguished family. He didn't tell anybody anything
about that.''
   W.E. ``Bill'' <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Bay St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, an insurance agent
and retired <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> commander, recalled that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was nicknamed
``Ellie'' by the submarine's crewmen because he would imitate a
braying elephant. But it had nothing to do with his aspiring
politics.
   ``We had a nickname for everyone aboard, and <PERSON>George</PERSON> was a very
smart, fun loving guy,'' <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> said. ``He was always joking,
mimicking this elephant. I think he'd seen too many Tarzan movies.''
   Then a 20-year-old lieutenant and the <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>'s youngest pilot, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
was flying a bombing run against a Japanese radio communications
center in the <LOCATION>Bonin Islands</LOCATION> 600 miles south of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION> when enemy fire
struck his TBM Avenger. He later won a Distinguished Flying Cross
for completing the run before bailing out of the flaming plane.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880425-0032 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-88 0304EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r p PM-Dukakis     04-25 0709</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Dukakis,720</SECOND>
<HEAD>You Don't Know Me, But...</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By EVANS WITT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>STATE COLLEGE, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> was getting his early
morning exercise walking down a <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> street, when someone
gave a cry of recognition: ``Hey, isn't that <PERSON>Caliguiri</PERSON>?''
   No, it wasn't <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> Mayor <PERSON>Richard Caliguiri</PERSON>: It was the
   ``I guess the mayor and I look alike,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said as he
described the <DATE>Sunday</DATE> morning greeting. ``There's an old saying in
Italian: `One face _ one race.' We're all part of the same family.''
   Far ahead in the polls here for <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s primary, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said
the incident shows ``we need to do a lot of work to make sure
people know who <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> is on the ballot.''
   The <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION> governor himself is working hard _ taking a
whistle-stop train tour across western <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> and
making a six-city flying tour of the state today.
   Dukakis is looking for a fourth straight big-state win here over
his surviving competitor _ <PERSON>Jesse Jackson</PERSON> _ to tighten his grip on
the front-runner's crown and widen his margin in the delegate count.
   ``If we can win big here <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, it will give us a tremendous
boost,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> told a big crowd of students on the <ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania
State University</ORGANIZATION> campus, who were welcoming back his wife, <PERSON>Kitty</PERSON>, a
<ORGANIZATION>Penn State</ORGANIZATION> graduate.
   Through the cold, cloudy day in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Greensburg</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Johnstown</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Altoona</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> hit over and over again on his
message of good jobs and economic development in a region
devastated by changes in the steel and coal industries.
   ``If we can't bring good jobs and economic opportunity back to
the Johnstowns of this country, then there is something the matter
with us,'' he told a crowd there. ``I believe we can. I believe
we're going to.''
   Dukakis drew the parallels between <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>'s economic
troubles of the past and <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>'s troubles of the present.
   ``As a <LOCATION>New Englander</LOCATION>, we went through the same kind of pain and
economic distress as you have,'' he said in <LOCATION>Greensburg</LOCATION>. ``Our
communities have come back and these communities are going to come
back.''
   Drawing on the two <DATE>weekend</DATE> debates between the Democrats,
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> talked of how he and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> agree on many issues.
   ``Instead of investing in a lot of exotic weapon systems of very
marginal value, we've got to take these resources and put them _ as
both Rev. <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> and I said <DATE>Saturday</DATE> _ into our infrastructure.''
   But on <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> brushed off suggestions from <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> that
he should put out a budget.
   ``You can't prepare a budget now for next year _ that's
absurd,'' he told reporters on the chartered <ORGANIZATION>Amtrak</ORGANIZATION> train,
nicknamed the ``<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Presidential Unlimited.''
   And <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> resisted pressure from a new Jackson tactic, urging
massive new spending on education, drug control efforts and other
programs.
   The front-runner went down his own list of education programs _
which he says involve only modest spending increases _ while
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said the federal government should double its spending on
education.
   ``We're not going to run the nation's school system from
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said. ``The thing a president has to do is to
set some priorities and get after them.''
   The Democratic candidate also took a couple of swipes at <PERSON>George
Bush</PERSON>, saying that the Republican nominee-to-be seems more
interested in building aircraft carriers than in rebuilding the
nation's railroads and highways.
   ``<PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> was critical of me ... because I oppose spending <MONEY>$36
billion</MONEY> on two supercarrier task forces that we don't need and we
can't afford,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said. ``If he thinks that's where we ought
to put our scarce resources, then so be it. But it's going to be a
fundamental issue in this campaign.
   ``I think I know where the American people are _ they are tired
of crumbling bridges, congested airports, jammed highways, homeless
people on streets and in doorways ... and they want a change.''
   If <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> is the Democratic nominee, perhaps he will get a wish
expressed wistfully in <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>.
   ``All of you know me. I suppose we'd all like to suppose that
I'm a household word,'' he told the small crowd. ``I'd like one of
these days to come to <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION> and hear, `Hey, isn't that
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>?'''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA021590-0051 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 176542 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
February 15, 1990, Thursday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part E; Page 4; Column 1; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
587 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
SHAKING YOUR FAMILY TREE: GERMAN ANCESTOR'S ENGLISH NAME 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By MYRA V. GORMLEY 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
Question: My ancestor, <PERSON>William Felton</PERSON>, was born in the lowlands of <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> 
about <DATE>1770</DATE> and arrived in <LOCATION>America</LOCATION> in <DATE>1776</DATE> with his parents and two older 
brothers, <PERSON>John</PERSON> and <PERSON>Robert</PERSON>. The parents supposedly died shortly thereafter, 
probably in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>. What puzzles me is that <PERSON>Felton</PERSON> is not a German name, 
and I have been unable to find this family on ship passenger lists from 
<LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. My ancestor was bound to a man who raised him in the Presbyterian 
faith. Is it possible he took another name? 
</P>
<P>
Answer: Anything is possible in genealogy. Felton is an English location name; 
from Old English meaning feld (pasture or open country) plus tun (enclosure). 
It also is spelled <PERSON>Felten</PERSON>, and to add to the confusion, there is a German 
surname spelled <PERSON>Felten</PERSON> or Feldten. 
</P>
<P>
However, with sons named <PERSON>John</PERSON>, <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> and <LOCATION>William</LOCATION>, I suspect your family is of 
English origins even though your ancestor supposedly was born in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
You need to make a thorough check in the probate and orphans' court records in 
the county where your immigrant ancestors died. Therein may be additional 
information on this line's origins. 
</P>
<P>
Ship passenger records are not complete for this time period. Examine the <DATE>1790</DATE> 
Census for <PERSON>Felton</PERSON> and Feltin families. There were 53 heads of households with 
this surname -- most of them in <LOCATION>New England</LOCATION>, but four were in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> at 
that time. The older brothers probably were heads of household when the <DATE>1790</DATE> 
Census was taken, and it may be necessary to research them to learn more about 
your ancestor. 
</P>
<P>
Q: My maiden name was <PERSON>Musick</PERSON>, which my father says may have been of Czech 
origin. I have seen it spelled Muzik also. Great-grandpa was born in <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> 
about <DATE>1856</DATE> in <LOCATION>St. Joseph</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Jefferson City</LOCATION>. Do you have any clues to this 
name's origins? 
</P>
<P>
A: Musick or Music is Polish for peasant or vassal. However, <PERSON>Muzik</PERSON> is Czech -- 
an affectionate nickname for a man of short stature. 
</P>
<P>
These names would have sounded alike to American record-keepers, so your family 
tradition of being Czech is most likely correct. Since your family settled in 
<LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> in the mid-1800s, they probably came during the time of mass 
immigration of Czechs -- who came due to the drought and crop failures in the 
<DATE>1840s</DATE> and a revolution in <DATE>1848</DATE>. Possibly your family left from the ports of 
<LOCATION>Hamburg</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Bremen</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Germany</LOCATION> and sailed either to <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> or <LOCATION>Galveston</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Tex</LOCATION>. 
Many Czechs settled in small towns and villages in <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION>. Examine the <DATE>1850</DATE> 
and <DATE>1860</DATE> census records of <LOCATION>Missouri</LOCATION> for more clues; and check for 
naturalization papers. Look for all spellings of your name. 
</P>
<P>
Q: Can you tell me the origins of the surname <PERSON>Hendricks</PERSON>? 
</P>
<P>
A: <PERSON>Hendricks</PERSON>, also found spelled <ORGANIZATION>Hendrick</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Hendrich</PERSON> and <LOCATION>Hendrix</LOCATION>, is of German 
origins, meaning a descendant of <PERSON>Heinrich</PERSON>, the German form of <ORGANIZATION>Henry</ORGANIZATION>, which 
literally means "home, rule." German surnames were originally formed from two 
roots that often have unrelated meanings. 
</P>
<P>
Q: My surname is <PERSON>Fant</PERSON>, which I seldom find. My folks were Swedes, but this name 
does not sound Swedish. Is it? 
</P>
<P>
A: <PERSON>Fant</PERSON> has some English roots, as a nickname, meaning an immature person, one 
with the characteristics of a child. However, the name could have been derived 
from "Infante" of Italian and Spanish origins. 
</P>
<P>
How your father's Swedish family came to acquire this name will require a 
fascinating research into genealogical records. 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Myra Vanderpool Gormley</PERSON> is author of "Family Diseases: Are You at Risk?" 
available from <ORGANIZATION>Genealogical Publishing Co.</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>1001 N. Calvert</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Baltimore</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Md</LOCATION>. 
21202 for <MONEY>$17.45</MONEY> postpaid. 
</P><P></P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890913-0132 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-13-89 1341EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u w AM-Hookers'Digs Bjt   09-13 0745</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hookers' Digs, Bjt,710</SECOND>
<HEAD>Archeologists Uncover Remains of Capital's Red-Light District</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Archeologists digging just three blocks from
the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> have unearthed thousands of relics from <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s
notorious old red-light district, where Civil War prostitutes earned
their nickname entertaining Gen. <PERSON>Joseph Hooker</PERSON>'s troops.
   Shoveling beneath an asphalt parking lot just south of
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> in the shadow of the <ORGANIZATION>Commerce Department</ORGANIZATION> this
<DATE>summer</DATE>, investigators found perfume bottles, gaudy buttons, costume
jewelry, garter hooks and a long-forgotten cellar full of whiskey
and beer bottles.
   There was even a tiny, antique <PERSON>Bromo Seltzer</PERSON> bottle for treating
a morning-after malaise.
   Besides these artifacts of the hookers' trade, the investigators
discovered a wide assortment of everyday objects left by common
laborers, immigrants, runaway slaves and other poor folk who once
inhabited the crime-ridden neighborhood known as ``Murder Bay'' in
the mid-19th century.
   The six-week dig was completed just before <DATE>Labor Day</DATE>. Experts
have begun the year-long task of cleaning, cataloging and analyzing
the more than 250,000 objects recovered from the downtown site for
clues to the lifestyle of the humble people who lived there more
than a century ago.
   ``Nobody famous lived here. There's no `<ORGANIZATION>George Washington Slept
Here</ORGANIZATION>','' said <PERSON>Donna Seifert</PERSON>, principal archeologist with <ORGANIZATION>John Milner
Associates Inc.</ORGANIZATION>, a historic preservation firm based in <LOCATION>West Chester</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, which conducted the dig.
   ``These were ordinary working folk, and this is one of those rare
opportunities to learn more about what their lives were really
like,'' she said.
   They lived in a hotbed of vice, gambling and rum running in a
squalid community of row houses and alley shanties between 14th and
13th streets, across <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Avenue from the <ORGANIZATION>National Theater</ORGANIZATION>
and some of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s fanciest hotels and offices.
   Hooker, the <ORGANIZATION>Union</ORGANIZATION> commander defending the capital against
Confederate forces, tried to control the army of prostitutes
following his troops by herding the women into <LOCATION>Murder Bay</LOCATION>, away from
his encampment outside the city. The district became known as
``Hooker's Division,'' and its ladies of the night took the name of
``hookers.''
   A newspaper article from the <DATE>1890s</DATE>, which <PERSON>Ms. Seifert</PERSON> acquired
from the <ORGANIZATION>Library of Congress</ORGANIZATION>, declared that the area was ``the
plague spot of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'' with 109 brothels and 50 saloons.
   ``<PERSON>Grover Cleveland</PERSON> can sit in his bedroom window at the <ORGANIZATION>White
House</ORGANIZATION> and survey this entire territory,'' the paper said. ``He is
within sight and gunshot of each of these 109 dens which defy the
laws which he is supposed to execute through his commissioners.''
   The prostitutes packed their bags when <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> outlawed brothels
in the <ORGANIZATION>District of Columbia</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>1914</DATE>, and the site was razed in the
<DATE>late 1920s</DATE>. Plans to build a monumental plaza were abandoned in the
Depression, and the area was paved over in <DATE>1931</DATE> to create a
1,300-car parking lot.
   Construction is expected to begin in the <DATE>fall of 1990</DATE> on a
multimillion-dollar federal office building and international
cultural and arts center at the site.
   Because government funds are involved, the developer _ the
<ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corp.</ORGANIZATION> _ is required by the <DATE>1966</DATE>
National Historic Preservation Act to review the project for its
impact on cultural resources.
   The archeologists hired for the job consulted old maps, census
records and city directories, and began excavating in mid-July in
their search for backyard ``trash pits'' behind the former wooden
and brick rowhouses.
   They uncovered an old cellar from a rooming house whose boarders
included several prostitutes, and salvaged about 200 empty beer and
liquor bottles. Among the popular brands a century ago were <ORGANIZATION>Pabst
Milwaukee</ORGANIZATION>, <ORGANIZATION>Schlitz</ORGANIZATION> and ``<PERSON>John Fitzmorris</PERSON> Old Berwick Rye,'' plus
several earthenware jugs of German-brand ginger beer.
   Also found were fish, chicken and steak bones, many dating back
to the Civil War.
   <PERSON>Ms. Seifert</PERSON> says these and other mundane objects uncovered will
yield valuable information about the denizens of the former gambling
dens, saloons, brothels and boarding houses _ what they ate and
drank, what clothing they wore, how they spent their leisure time.
   ``We know how <PERSON>Thomas Jefferson</PERSON> set his table at <LOCATION>Monticello</LOCATION> and
who his guests were, for example, but we don't know very much about
the everyday dining habits of the ordinary people who lived in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>,'' she said.
   ``The documents tell us nothing about how they lived. And these
people did not save and cherish their household items, as the
wealthy did. They were used until they were broken or worn out, and
then thrown away.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880819-0249 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-19-88 0905EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a a PM-Digger'sDiner ADV23   08-19 0640</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Digger's Diner, ADV 23,0659</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv23</NOTE>
<NOTE>For Release Tuesday PMs, Aug. 23, and Thereafter</NOTE>
<HEAD>Giving Away Diner, But No Takers So Far</HEAD>
<NOTE>With LaserPhoto</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By TARA BRADLEY-STECK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BUTLER, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   The bumper stickers bragged, ``Nothing could
be finer than to eat at <ORGANIZATION>Digger</ORGANIZATION>'s Diner.'' Now it's a diner to go.
   Anyone willing to flip flapjacks and hamburgers _ and pay the
cost of moving it _ can have the 1940s-vintage restaurant free of
charge, says <PERSON>William</PERSON> ``Digger'' Young.
   He grew tired of the diner chores because he also was juggling
jobs as a mortician, <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> County coroner, and ``Clown on Roller
Skates'' at children's hospitals and nursing homes.
   ``It's just that I wore too many hats. I'd ... put an apron on
over my suit and pour coffee. You didn't catch me cooking, but I'd
be running the cash register. I liked to be where the money was,''
he said.
   Young, 55, got his nickname from the funeral business his family
has owned since <DATE>1896</DATE>.
   His funeral home is next to the diner, painted brown and yellow
to match. But the location is purely coincidental. Unlike the
funeral business, <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>'s diner brought customers back, before it
closed a few years ago.
   ``We had great food. Some of my customers were seven days a
week. Some would have breakfast and their evening meals there,
too,'' he said.
   Young wants to use the land occupied by the diner to expand the
funeral home and has been trying to sell the all-steel building for
two years. When no buyers nibbled, he decided to give it away and
placed newspaper ads that offered it ``free for the moving.''
   So far, the response has been pretty dead because no one has
been willing to pay the <MONEY>several thousand dollars</MONEY> necessary to have
the diner dismantled and moved, <PERSON>Young</PERSON> said.
   ``When they find out what it will cost to move it, they don't
seem to want to go any further,'' he said.
   The diner is the all-American variety, a <ORGANIZATION>Jerry O'Mahoney Inc.</ORGANIZATION>
special from <LOCATION>Elizabeth</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>N.J.</LOCATION>, with curvaceous lines, stainless
steel trim, vinyl-covered stools and formica counters. It arrived
in <PERSON>Butler</PERSON> on two flatbed trucks in the early <DATE>1940s</DATE> and had several
owners until Young bought it seven years ago.
   The pie was homemade, the burgers thick and the cereal came in
little boxes.
   But now all that's left is the building. Young sold the
refrigerators and countertops to a pizza restaurant in <LOCATION>Illinois</LOCATION>,
the pizza oven to a <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> campground, and the stoves, grill
and cash register to a <LOCATION>Youngstown</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, restaurant.
   ``Nobody would come in and take the whole place,'' he said.
``Then it got to be that I just started stripping things apart.''
   Stale cake donuts, paper doilies and a baby's yellow rattle
litter the dirty floor, and the walls in the kitchen area are
coated with decades of grease.
   But Young says there's still plenty of life in the diner, which,
with its concrete floor and industrial-strength walls, seems built
to last.
   ``There's stainless inside, good stainless,'' he said, picking
through the rubble to reveal an old menu. ``Paint that steel and
polish the stainless and you have a pretty good looking building.''
   But more than anything, it was an institution in this bustling
western <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> city of about 17,000. As a teen-ager, <ORGANIZATION>Young</ORGANIZATION>
remembers well the lines that formed outside.
   ``People waited to get in. It was a very busy diner,'' he said.
   When Young ran the diner, it featured such culinary specialties
as the ``Digger Special'' _ a hamburger topped with a fried egg and
sauteed mushrooms, his favorite.
   Speaking of his decision to give the diner away, he said, ``I'd
like to see it used someplace, and I'd go past and say, `That used
to be mine.'''
</TEXT>
<NOTE>End Adv for Tuesday PMs, Aug. 23</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880425-0119 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-25-88 1300EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u p PM-PoliticalRdp 4thLd-Writethru a0617 04-25 0899</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Political Rdp, 4th Ld-Writethru, a0617,890</SECOND>
<HEAD>Jackson Says He'd Negotiate on Hostages; Dukakis Says `No
Concessions'</HEAD>
<NOTE>Eds: Updates with Jackson comment on negotiating with terrorists,
subbing 2 grafs for 6th graf pvs, Jackson said; cuts last 2 grafs</NOTE>
<BYLINE>By EVANS WITT</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Political Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Democrat <PERSON>Michael Dukakis</PERSON> said today he would
talk with terrorists holding hostages but ``never make
concessions,'' commenting one day after campaign rival <PERSON>Jesse
Jackson</PERSON> criticized what he said was <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>' view that ``we should
not negotiate with terrorists.''
   Jackson set off the exchange <DATE>Sunday</DATE> when he said, ``I've raised
the point in several debates this year. Every time a question comes
up about terrorism, <PERSON>Mr. Dukakis</PERSON> says, `I'm against terrorism. ...
We should not negotiate with terrorists. ... In the <LOCATION>Middle East</LOCATION>,
never negotiate with terrorists.'
   ``I disagree with that; If I could get the hostages out, I'd do
it.''
   Dukakis, in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, told reporters today after being asked
about <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>'s statement, ``I think we need a tough anti-terrorist
policy. ...
   ``I don't have a problem with talking, but you never make
concessions to terrorists _ ever. If you do, what you end up with
is hostage-taking and terrorism all over the world.''
   Jackson, asked today about negotiating with terrorists, said he
would not make ``material concessions'' to them but could conceive
of situations in which he would grant hostage-takers safe passage.
   ``I would never exchange arms for hostages,'' he said, a
reference to the Iran-Contra operations steered by <PERSON>Reagan</PERSON>
administration officials.
   <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> policy holds that American officials ``will talk to any
official or group about the safety and release of hostages but we
will not make concessions,'' a <ORGANIZATION>State Department</ORGANIZATION> spokesman said
<DATE>today</DATE>.
   The gentle battling between the surviving Democratic candidates
got more direct as the candidates closed in on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>'s
delegate-rich <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> primary.
   A new poll, sponsored by <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>'s KYW-TV and <LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>'s
KDKA-TV, showed <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> apparently increasing his lead among likely
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Democratic voters. In the new poll, taken by telephone
over the <DATE>weekend</DATE>, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> led <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION> <PERCENT>57 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>31 percent</PERCENT> with
<PERCENT>12 percent</PERCENT> still undecided.
   Last week, with <PERSON>Sen. Albert Gore Jr.</PERSON> still being counted,
<PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> led <LOCATION>Jackson</LOCATION> <PERCENT>45 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT>, with <PERCENT>14 percent</PERCENT>
undecided and <PERCENT>7 percent</PERCENT> for Gore. The polls, with a margin of error
of five percentage points either way, were conducted by <ORGANIZATION>KRC
Research</ORGANIZATION> of <LOCATION>Cambridge</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Mass</LOCATION>.
   It was <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> who has stirred the biggest controversy in recent
days with his call on <DATE>Sunday</DATE> for negotiation with anyone to free
hostages.
   ``In this world, in this ambiguous world, you must not set up
preconditions that stop effectiveness,'' <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said at a rally in
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. ``I would meet with anyone I could meet with to get the
hostages out of <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.''
   Eight Americans are currently held hostage by Moslem extremists
in <LOCATION>Beirut</LOCATION>.
   On <DATE>Sunday</DATE>, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> did a whistle-stop tour of <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, but
he was switching to the air <DATE>today</DATE>, hitting six cities to make an
impression in every media market in the state before the voters go
to the polls <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>.
   Jackson raised money in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> before returning late <DATE>Sunday</DATE>
for a final push in the <ORGANIZATION>Keystone State</ORGANIZATION>.
   <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> has a big lead in the polls in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, where 178
delegates are at stake. The complicated process _ with delegates
elected individually _ offers a challenge to voters who may have to
pull the lever up to 12 times. But it also offers <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON>, if he
does well, a chance to win as many as 100 more delegates than
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON>.
   ``You've got to vote more than once. This is the one time you
can do so legally,'' he told students at <ORGANIZATION>Penn State University in
State College</ORGANIZATION>. ``Vote early and often _ vote for me and vote for my
delegates.''
   Dukakis is more than half the way to a delegate majority,
holding 1,075.15 national convention votes. <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> has 836.1 while
599.75 were uncommitted. A tally of 2,081 or more is needed to win
the nomination at the <DATE>July</DATE> convention in <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION>.
   Guam's three convention votes entered the uncommitted column
<DATE>Sunday</DATE> evening following caucuses on the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> island.
   On the Republican side, Vice President <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> is virtually
unchallenged on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, when he may win enough of
the 78 delegates at stake to go over the magic majority mark _
1,139 _ needed to win the <ORGANIZATION>GOP</ORGANIZATION> nomination in <LOCATION>New Orleans</LOCATION> in <DATE>August</DATE>.
   A new poll by <ORGANIZATION>Time magazine</ORGANIZATION> indicates that a Dukakis-Jackson
ticket would get <PERCENT>47 percent</PERCENT> of the vote nationwide to <PERCENT>42 percent</PERCENT>
for a Republican ticket headed by <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>.
   A Dukakis-Gore ticket would defeat Bush <PERCENT>49 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>39
percent</PERCENT>, but <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> would defeat <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> by <PERCENT>52 percent</PERCENT> to <PERCENT>34 percent</PERCENT>,
according to the poll released <DATE>Sunday</DATE>.
   On the Democratic side, <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> and <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> have been unusually
cordial recently, but the best-friends atmosphere thinned when
<PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> urged <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> to release a proposed budget.
   ``I'm not just for Head Start, I'm willing to pay for Head
Start,'' <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> said during the debate <DATE>Saturday</DATE> <TIME>night</TIME> in
<LOCATION>Pittsburgh</LOCATION>. ``I have put numbers together to pay for my dreams.''
   Dukakis strongly disagreed.
   ``You can't prepare a budget now for next year _ that's
absurd,'' he told reporters <DATE>Sunday</DATE> on his chartered <ORGANIZATION>Amtrak</ORGANIZATION> train,
nicknamed the ``<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Presidential Unlimited.''
   ``I'll lay out where I'm going to make the cuts _ I've done that
in great detail,'' <PERSON>Dukakis</PERSON> said as he toured western <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890811-0157 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-11-89 2103EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-HoboGathering     08-11 0638</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Hobo Gathering,0655</SECOND>
<HEAD>Hobos Reunite In Iowa</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By GREG SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BRITT, Iowa (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Midwest <PERSON>John</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Ohio Ned</LOCATION>, Steam Train <PERSON>Maury
Graham</PERSON> and others are spreading their bedrolls this weekend in
<LOCATION>Britt</LOCATION>, home of the <ORGANIZATION>National Hobo Convention</ORGANIZATION>.
   About 40 hobos from across the country hitchhiked and hopped
freights to be on hand for ceremonies, including funerals for two
``brothers'' buried in the town cemetery.
   ``It's a homecoming of sorts. We're a vanishing breed. There's
no young guys out here anymore,'' said 36-year-old <PERSON>John Becker</PERSON> of
<LOCATION>Sterling</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ill.</LOCATION>, known as <LOCATION>Midwest John</LOCATION>.
   Becker's traveling partner, <PERSON>Ned McNamer</PERSON> of <LOCATION>London</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, said
life on the road is getting more dangerous. Both men wear long
sheath knives hidden underneath sleeveless jean jackets covered
with souvenir buttons.
   ``We came here from the <LOCATION>North Town</LOCATION> rail yards in <LOCATION>Minneapolis</LOCATION>.
That's a real jungle,'' said <PERSON>McNamer</PERSON>, who sports the name <ORGANIZATION>Ohio Ned</ORGANIZATION>.
``In some parts of the country you could get killed for anything _
rings, shoes _ you name it.''
   ``It's a little lonely, sure. But it all depends on what your
tastes are. If you like a 9 to 5 job, fancy slacks, that's nice,
too,'' <PERSON>Becker</PERSON> said. ``But for some of us there's always that urge
to see what's up over the hill.''
   The hobos, mostly men, wore red bandanas, caps and many carried
sturdy walking staffs. They gathered <DATE>Friday</DATE> at the <ORGANIZATION>Evergreen
Cemetery</ORGANIZATION> for services for the <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Kid and <LOCATION>Hafey</LOCATION> the Bo.
They are the fourth and fifth hobos to be buried at the Britt
cemetery. A tombstone also sits in the cemetery for all unknown
hobos who have died.
   ``We remember all of our deceased hobos, those who in hobo
terminology, `have caught the westbound,''' said a hobo named
<ORGANIZATION>Frisco Jack</ORGANIZATION>.
   Members of the <ORGANIZATION>Britt American Legion</ORGANIZATION> fired a rifle salute and
blew taps for the Kid, whose real name was <PERSON>Paul Wilson</PERSON>. <PERSON>Wilson</PERSON>, a
World War II veteran from <LOCATION>Franklin</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, died in <DATE>June</DATE> at age 80.
   Whiskey was sprinkled on his tombstone.
   ``I know some people may look down on it, but it was what he
requested,'' <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> told the other hobos and a crowd of about 50
who attended the hourlong service.
   ``People think hobos don't make friends. But that is the main
point of our lives. Friends are the wealth of life,'' said <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>,
a short man with a long white beard and mustache who was crowned
King of the Hobos in <DATE>1973</DATE>.
   ``<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Kid was the only man I knew who shaved with
broken glass. He'd get a piece from a broken bottle, wrap it up in
toilet paper and put it in his pocket,'' said <PERSON>Graham</PERSON>, a <LOCATION>Toledo</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Ohio</LOCATION>, native.
   Hafey the Bo, whose real name was <PERSON>Al Zale</PERSON>, was a hobo from <LOCATION>Los
Angeles</LOCATION> who got his nickname because he suffered from chronic hay
fever. He was remembered as a kind and gentle man.
   ``We're going to miss those guys,'' said the <ORGANIZATION>El Paso Kid</ORGANIZATION>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>National Hobo Convention</ORGANIZATION> first came to Britt in <DATE>1900</DATE> when
Thos. A. Way, <PERSON>T.A. Potter</PERSON> and <PERSON>W.E. Bradford</PERSON> decided to do something
to show the world that <PERSON>Britt</PERSON> was a lively little town capable of
doing anything larger cities could do. The convention became a
fixture in <DATE>1933</DATE>.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Britt Chamber of Commerce</ORGANIZATION>, which runs a small hobo museum in
the lobby of the defunct Old Chief Theatre, plans to expand the
museum to honor hobos, said <PERSON>Marian Malek</PERSON>, chamber secretary. Plans
also call to move the five graves of the hobos to a reserved
section of the cemetery.
   ``Hobos are a decent lot. We are not bums,'' said <PERSON>Joe Baker</PERSON>, 59,
a hobo from <LOCATION>North Carolina</LOCATION>. ``I've known no other life since I was
13.''
   ``Hobos have hearts, too, and they cry and laugh like everybody
else,'' <PERSON>Graham</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP891002-0260 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-10-02-89 1439EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>s a BC-APN--ShipyardDown Adv15-2Takes   10-02 0767</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--Shipyard Down, Adv 15-2 Takes,0786</SECOND>
<HEAD>$adv15</HEAD>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<HEAD>For Release Sunday, Oct. 15</HEAD>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<HEAD>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 2 b&amp;w photos.)
   </HEAD>
<NOTE>EDITOR'S NOTE </NOTE>
<TEXT>
   It was once called the ``American Clyde,'' after
the <PERSON>Clyde River</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, then a major shipbuilding center in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Now the <LOCATION>Delaware River</LOCATION> is losing the last of its once-proud
shipbuilding yards, partially because of a general slump in the
industry brought on by new government policies.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>By ERICH SMITH</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>CHESTER, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   It was once called the ``American Clyde,'' after
the <PERSON>Clyde River</PERSON> in <LOCATION>Scotland</LOCATION>, then a major shipbuilding center in
<LOCATION>Europe</LOCATION>. Now the <LOCATION>Delaware River</LOCATION> is losing the last of its once-proud
shipbuilding yards, partially because of a general slump in the
industry brought on by new government policies.
</TEXT>
<NOTE>MORE</NOTE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890113-0109 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-13-89 1234EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w AM-BushBuddies     01-13 0566</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Bush Buddies,560</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush's Wartime Rescuers Remember Him as `Ellie the Elephant'</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   <PERSON>George Bush</PERSON> may be the Big Elephant in the
inaugural parade next week, but his buddies on a World War II
submarine remember him as ``Ellie the Elephant,'' the fun-loving
young <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot they rescued from the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION> <DATE>44 years ago</DATE>.
   Surviving crew members of the USS Finback are looking forward to
a nostalgic reunion with <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> here next <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>, two days before
they watch him take the presidential oath of office on the <LOCATION>West
Front</LOCATION> steps of the Capitol.
   Inaugural planners have passed the word to several Finback
veterans that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> is setting aside time to meet with them at <ORGANIZATION>Blair
House</ORGANIZATION>, across the street from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, to swap war stories
and renew old acquaintances.
   Prime bleacher seats have been reserved for the inaugural parade
<DATE>Friday</DATE> down <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> for nearly 30 survivors of the
Finback crew, plus several of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s old fellow pilots, who are
expected to attend the inauguration.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was nicknamed ``Ellie'' by the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s officers for his
wardroom imitation of a trumpeting elephant.
   ``It wasn't because we all sat around thinking we were
Republicans,'' said retired Rear Adm. <PERSON>Lawrence Heyworth</PERSON>, 67, of
<LOCATION>Virginia Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, who was the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s torpedo and gunnery
officer.
   ``We must have seen one in a Tarzan movie. We just thought
elepants were funny. We kept asking <PERSON>George</PERSON> to do it over and over
again.''
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was plucked from the <LOCATION>Pacific</LOCATION> on <DATE>Sept. 2, 1944</DATE>, shortly after
he bailed out of his flaming Grumman Avenger torpedo bomber over the
<LOCATION>Bonin Islands</LOCATION> 600 miles south of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>.
bombing raid against an enemy radio communications center. The
citation noted that <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>, then only 20, completed his dive and hit
his target even after his plane was hit and engulfed in smoke. His
two crew members were lost.
   ``At that time, he was just another downed pilot,'' said <PERSON>Don
Kohler</PERSON>, 64, of <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, the torpedoman who helped pull <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> out
of his bobbing orange life raft to the safety of the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s deck.
``Nobody back then knew he'd become president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   During the month he spent on the Finback before saying goodbye at
<LOCATION>Midway Island</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> eagerly took his turn at night lookout watches
and other seagoing duties, watched <PERSON>Betty Grable</PERSON> movies in the
wardroom and donned earphones to listen in awe as the submarine's
torpedoes sank two enemy ships.
   Retired <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> Cmdr. <PERSON>W.E.</PERSON> ``Bill'' <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON>, who filmed <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
rescue with a <ORGANIZATION>Kodak</ORGANIZATION> movie camera from the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s conning tower,
remembers <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s surprise that his first meal on the submarine that
night was filet mignon and fresh strawberry shortcake with whipped
cream.
   ``He said he'd been eating nothing but Spam and beans on the
carriers,'' <PERSON>Edward</PERSON>, 67, said in a telephone interview from his
retirement home at <LOCATION>Bay St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss</LOCATION>.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was one of three <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilots rescued by the Finback during
<LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> carrier raids against the <LOCATION>Bonin Islands</LOCATION> in early <DATE>September</DATE>.
   ``I remember he was very lively, obviously intelligent and very
personable,'' said <PERSON>Heyworth</PERSON>. ``All three pilots we rescued were
bright, bright-eyed young men, but <PERSON>George</PERSON> seemed the most outgoing
and had the most ebullient personality. He was the most
entertaining, and he made us laugh a lot.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA060789-0034 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 66903 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
June 7, 1989, Wednesday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Sports; Part 3; Page 2; Column 1; Sports Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
543 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
MORNING BRIEFING: PLEADING THE CASE FOR MAN'S BEST FRIEND 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
The <ORGANIZATION>University of Virginia</ORGANIZATION> was criticized by the <ORGANIZATION>American Society</ORGANIZATION> for the 
Prevention of Cruelty to Animals because its veterinary school used stray dogs 
from pounds for research. 
</P>
<P>
Said <PERSON>Alan Williams</PERSON>, the school's faculty athletic representative: "So now we're 
using lawyers. There's more of them, and nobody cares how they're treated." 
</P>
<P>
Name game: <PERSON>Chris Berman</PERSON>, the <ORGANIZATION>ESPN</ORGANIZATION> announcer who pins those goofy nicknames on 
ballplayers, is at it again this season, and here are some early offerings: 
</P>
<P>
<PERSON>Roberto</PERSON> (Remember the) <PERSON>Alomar</PERSON>, <PERSON>David</PERSON> (Sili) <PERSON>Cone</PERSON>, <PERSON>David</PERSON> (Death) <LOCATION>Valle</LOCATION>, <PERSON>John</PERSON> 
(<ORGANIZATION>Hia</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Wathan</PERSON>, <PERSON>Tom</PERSON> (Cotton) <PERSON>Candiotti</PERSON>, Chili (<ORGANIZATION>Con Carne</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Davis</PERSON>, <PERSON>Todd</PERSON> (Mercedes) 
<PERSON>Benzinger</PERSON>, <PERSON>Craig</PERSON> (For What It's) <LOCATION>Worthington</LOCATION> and <PERSON>Rob</PERSON> (Double) <PERSON>Dibble</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Then there's Bill (<ORGANIZATION>Beethoven</ORGANIZATION>) <PERSON>Schroeder</PERSON>, <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> (Nova) <LOCATION>Scioscia</LOCATION>, Gene (Full) 
<LOCATION>Nelson</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Bob</PERSON> (Intentional) Walk, <PERSON>Dennis</PERSON> (Fluorescent) Lamp, <PERSON>John</PERSON> (I Am Not a) 
<PERSON>Kruk</PERSON>, <PERSON>Marty</PERSON> (Grin and) <PERSON>Barrett</PERSON> and <PERSON>Kirt</PERSON> (What Was That) <PERSON>Manwaring</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
He even has separate nicknames for the <PERSON>Maddux</PERSON> brothers -- <PERSON>Mike</PERSON> (<PERSON>Matha</PERSON>) <PERSON>Maddux</PERSON> 
and <PERSON>Greg</PERSON> (Appo) <PERSON>Maddux</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Add Berman: He recently ventured into golf with this one: <PERSON>Bob</PERSON> (Curds And) <PERSON>Tway</PERSON>. 
And, a nickname to end all nicknames: <PERSON>Larry Mize</PERSON> (Have Seen the Glory). Get it? 
</P>
<P>
Trivia time: Which player had the longest hitting streak in the major leagues 
last season? 
</P>
<P>
He got the point: When told that <PERSON>Tony Mandarich</PERSON>, 300-pound <ORGANIZATION>Green Bay Packers</ORGANIZATION> 
draftee, was being ballyhooed as an opponent for <PERSON>Mike Tyson</PERSON>, former <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> 
Jets star <PERSON>Joe Klecko</PERSON>, who boxed at <ORGANIZATION>Temple</ORGANIZATION>, recalled an afternoon with <PERSON>Joe 
Frazier</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
"I'd never sparred with <PERSON>Frazier</PERSON> before but now I was in there banging with him 
and I guess I got a little too loose," <PERSON>Klecko</PERSON> told the <ORGANIZATION>New York Times</ORGANIZATION>. "He 
threw a left hook but he stopped it right there next to my head, then he 
laughed. That one left hook was enough for me to realize that I didn't really 
want to be a boxer." 
</P>
<P>
Radar Ryan: <ORGANIZATION>Texas Rangers</ORGANIZATION> Manager <PERSON>Bobby Valentine</PERSON> says of <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON>: "On our 
radar gun at <LOCATION>Arlington Stadium</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Nolan</PERSON> has topped out at 97 m.p.h. And he's 
averaged 93 m.p.h. Averaged." 
</P>
<P>
Says <ORGANIZATION>Minnesota Twins</ORGANIZATION>' hitting coach <PERSON>Tony Oliva</PERSON>, a former batting champion: 
"He's the fastest I've faced, and that includes <PERSON>Sandy Koufax</PERSON>, <PERSON>Don Drysdale</PERSON>, <PERSON>Sam 
McDowell</PERSON>, <PERSON>Jim Palmer</PERSON>, <PERSON>Bob Gibson</PERSON> and <PERSON>J.R. Richard</PERSON>." 
</P>
<P>
Add Ryan: He struck out <PERSON>Bo Jackson</PERSON> six straight times before the <LOCATION>Kansas City</LOCATION> 
Royals slugger hit a 461-foot shot off him last month. It was the longest 
measured home run in <LOCATION>Arlington Stadium</LOCATION> history. 
</P>
<P>
Ryan had thrown a couple of knockdown pitches before <PERSON>Jackson</PERSON> unloaded, and <PERSON>Bo</PERSON> 
said, "I don't know if he was wild or not. But <PERSON>Nolan Ryan</PERSON> has been pitching 
longer than I've been alive. If he wanted to hit me, he could have." 
</P>
<P>
Says <PERSON>Terry Francona</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Milwaukee Brewers</ORGANIZATION>: "When I see his name in the 
pitching probables, I don't exactly hurry to the ballpark. 
</P>
<P>
Would-you-believe-it Dept.: <PERSON>Johnny Bench</PERSON>, voted into the <PERSON>Hall</PERSON> of Fame this 
year, is younger than <ORGANIZATION>Royal</ORGANIZATION> catcher <PERSON>Bob Boone</PERSON>. Boone will be 42 on <DATE>Nov. 19</DATE>, or 
18 days before Bench. 
</P>
<P>
Trivia answer: <PERSON>John Shelby</PERSON> of the <ORGANIZATION>Dodgers</ORGANIZATION>, 24 games. 
</P>
<P>
Quotebook: Former heavyweight champion <PERSON>George Foreman</PERSON>, on his comeback: "There 
are those that say I don't fight a guy unless he's on a respirator. That's a 
big lie. He has to be eight days off the respirator." 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Column 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890806-0011 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-08-06-89 0842EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>u a BC-PhoneTalks     08-06 0428</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-Phone Talks,0443</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bell Atlantic Workers Join NYNEX, PacTel In Striking; BellSouth Settles</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<TEXT>
   A union representing 41,000 telephone workers at <LOCATION>Bell Atlantic</LOCATION>
walked off the job <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME>, joining counterparts at <ORGANIZATION>NYNEX
Corp.</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Pacific Telesis</LOCATION> who had begun a strike hours earlier,
union and company spokesmen said.
   <PERSON>Mary O'Hara</PERSON>, district coordinator in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION> for the
<ORGANIZATION>Communications Workers of America</ORGANIZATION>, said talks with <ORGANIZATION>Bell Atlantic</ORGANIZATION>
broke up around <TIME>6:45 a.m.</TIME> and pickets were being set up.
   Bell <LOCATION>Atlantic</LOCATION>, based in <LOCATION>Philadelphia</LOCATION>, is parent to local phone
companies in <LOCATION>Delaware</LOCATION>, the <LOCATION>District of Columbia</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New
Jersey</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>West Virginia</LOCATION>.
   Talks continued <DATE>Sunday</DATE> <TIME>morning</TIME> between another union, the
Atlantic</ORGANIZATION> subsidiaries in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION>, said <PERSON>Tom
Duddy</PERSON>, a spokesman for <ORGANIZATION>Bell of Pennsylvania</ORGANIZATION>. That union represents
11,000 operators and clerical workers at the two subsidiaries.
   Hours earlier, more than 100,000 <ORGANIZATION>CWA</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>IBEW</ORGANIZATION> workers walked out
at New York-based <ORGANIZATION>NYNEX</ORGANIZATION> and San Francisco-based <LOCATION>Pacific Telesis</LOCATION>.
   A tentative agreement was reached between the <ORGANIZATION>CWA</ORGANIZATION> and a fourth
regional telephone company, Atlanta-based <ORGANIZATION>BellSouth</ORGANIZATION>, which employs
64,000 union workers and provides phone service in nine states in
the Southeast.
   Officials have said that most direct-dial telephone calls would
not be affected by phone company walkouts, because they are handled
by automated equipment, but customers could expect delays in
directory assistance calls, operator-assisted calls and in service
and installation jobs.
   In all, 221,000 telecommunications workers were covered by the
talks to replace contracts that expired at <TIME>11:59 p.m.</TIME> <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. The
four companies provide service to 24 states and the nation's
capital.
   The regional telephone companies, nicknamed ``Baby Bells,'' were
created by the <DATE>1984</DATE> breakup of <ORGANIZATION>American Telephone &amp; Telegraph</ORGANIZATION>.
   Contracts with three of the other ``Baby Bells'' _ <ORGANIZATION>Ameritech</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>US
West</LOCATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Southwestern Bell</ORGANIZATION> _ expire next <DATE>Saturday</DATE>. Those three
companies employ 131,000 union workers and provide phone service in
24 states.
   The unions announced the strike against New York-based <ORGANIZATION>NYNEX</ORGANIZATION>
well before the 11:59 EDT deadline, saying myriad differences
remained. So great were the differences that no formal talks were
held <DATE>Saturday</DATE>.
   <ORGANIZATION>NYNEX</ORGANIZATION> serves seven Northeast states: <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Massachusetts</LOCATION>,
<LOCATION>Rhode Island</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Maine</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>New Hampshire</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Vermont</LOCATION> and parts of
<LOCATION>Connecticut</LOCATION>. <ORGANIZATION>CWA</ORGANIZATION> represents 40,000 <ORGANIZATION>NYNEX</ORGANIZATION> workers; <ORGANIZATION>IBEW</ORGANIZATION> 20,000.
   Talks with <LOCATION>Pacific Telesis</LOCATION>, based in <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION>, were held
throughout the day but the unions announced the strike there at
<TIME>midnight _ 3 a.m. EDT</TIME>.
   <LOCATION>Pacific Telesis</LOCATION> is parent company of <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>'s <ORGANIZATION>Pacific Bell
Co.</ORGANIZATION> and <ORGANIZATION>Nevada Bell Telephone Co</ORGANIZATION>. <ORGANIZATION>CWA</ORGANIZATION> represents 42,000 <LOCATION>Pacific
Telesis</LOCATION> workers; <ORGANIZATION>IBEW</ORGANIZATION> 2,500.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06325248 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06325248 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photos (2); PHOTO: Lloyd Francis Jr. -- Mercury News; FACE IN THE CROWD -- The
Fremont High mascot helps lead cheers but isn't receiving them from area
Indian leaders. (color); PHOTO: Lloyd Francis Jr. -- Mercury News; Fremont's
'grotesque' mascot reinforces negative stereotypes, Indian leaders say  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  FREMONT; HIGH-SCHOOL; FOOTBALL; CLUB; ...; NAME; AMERICAN-INDIAN; PROTEST;
NAME; LIST  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  PERHAPS it was just a matter of time before the controversy surrounding the
Atlanta Braves' nickname and tomahawk-chopping fans extended to high schools
in Santa Clara and Southern Alameda counties.;   And for the three schools in
the area that have Indian-related nicknames -- the Fremont Indians, Yerba
Buena Warriors and Mission San Jose Warriors -- that time may be soon.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  INDIAN ISSUE MAY SOON COME TO A HEAD  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  High School Report; Additional information attached to the end of this article  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     "At some phase, we'll be reacting to those types of issues at schools,"
<PERSON>Larry Gorospe</PERSON>, the new executive director of the <ORGANIZATION>American Indian Center of San
Jose</ORGANIZATION>, said Tuesday.;   At issue is not only the use of Indian nicknames, but
also the way the nicknames are portrayed by team mascots.;   In particular,
members of the center believe that <ORGANIZATION>Fremont High</ORGANIZATION>'s bug-eyed, huge-nosed mascot
is demeaning.;   "It's really quite grotesque," <PERSON>Gorospe</PERSON> said after being
showed photos of the mascot. "It's not even a good caricature. The problem
with something like this, and in most forms of the media, is that it's a
negative stereotype of Indian people. And what this does is reinforce it. It
has a big nose. It looks almost like a monster.";   Added <PERSON>George Martin</PERSON>, a
local leader of the <ORGANIZATION>American Indian Movement</ORGANIZATION>, "That's the most disgraceful
thing I've seen in a long time. Is that supposed to be an Indian?";   The
mascot head was purchased from <LOCATION>Blackford</LOCATION> -- whose nickname was the Braves --
when that school closed last <DATE>spring</DATE>, according to <ORGANIZATION>Cipriano Sena</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>'s
student activities director.;   Said Sena: "The kids were interested in it. .
. . We talked about it administratively, and we weren't too pleased about it,
either.";   Though <PERSON>Martin</PERSON> said his group could picket schools or organizing
protests, <PERSON>Gorospe</PERSON> and <PERSON>Rosemary Cambra</PERSON>, chairwoman of the Muwekma-Ohlone tribe
of <LOCATION>San Jose</LOCATION>, said the best process is to educate people about Indians. <PERSON>Cambra</PERSON>
said she would like to see a partnership developed between Indian and other
community organizations.;   "I believe there is something wrong when certain
teams can use Indians, Braves and Warriors without the consent of the Indian
people," said <PERSON>Cambra</PERSON>, who hadn't seen the <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION> mascot.;   (Like Yerba
Buena, three other area schools use the nickname Warriors. But <ORGANIZATION>Westmont High</ORGANIZATION>'s
is a Spartan-type warrior, and <ORGANIZATION>Valley Christian</ORGANIZATION>'s and <ORGANIZATION>Fremont Christian</ORGANIZATION>'s
nicknames are intended as biblical warriors.);   The complaint of racial
insensitivity was the basis of Stanford changing its nickname from Indians to
Cardinals in <DATE>1972</DATE> (it became Cardinal in <DATE>'81</DATE>). In the <DATE>past two years</DATE>, three
<LOCATION>California</LOCATION> high schools dropped Indian nicknames. Tamalpais of <LOCATION>Mill Valley</LOCATION>
went from the Indians to the <ORGANIZATION>Red Tailed Hawks</ORGANIZATION>, the Encina Apaches of
<LOCATION>Sacramento</LOCATION> became the <LOCATION>Bulldogs</LOCATION>, and <PERSON>Lowell</PERSON> of <LOCATION>San Francisco</LOCATION> dropped Indians
and has no official nickname.;   <PERSON>Bernie Schneider</PERSON>, athletic director at
<ORGANIZATION>Tamalpais</ORGANIZATION>, said his school was caught up in the controversy for nearly a year
before changing nicknames.;   "We went through quite an investigation and had
many different discussions at different levels," said <PERSON>Schneider</PERSON>, whose
school's "Indians" nickname dated to <DATE>1908</DATE>. "We brought Native American groups
on campus to talk. . . . Even though our nickname glorified the bravery of
Indians, the Native American feeling was that they didn't want to be
stereotyped. They just wanted to be people.;   "It caused a lot of division
among our students. Mostly all of our alumni wanted to keep it.";   The only
battle in the <LOCATION>South Bay-Southern Alameda County</LOCATION> area that has already begun is
at <ORGANIZATION>Ohlone College</ORGANIZATION> in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>. Two students, <PERSON>Hector Miecznikowski</PERSON> and <PERSON>Charmaine
Leonard</PERSON>, are leading an attempt to replace the school's nickname, the
Renegades. Miecznikowski said not only doesn't Renegades fit with the heritage
of the Ohlone Indians, but more important, it doesn't represent the school's
students.;   "I looked it up, and 'Renegades' basically means traitors," said
<PERSON>Miecznikowski</PERSON>. "That's totally different than what you'd think. We call
ourselves the <ORGANIZATION>Ohlone Traitors</ORGANIZATION>. That's grounds for change itself.";  
Meanwhile, at <ORGANIZATION>Yerba Buena</ORGANIZATION> and <LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION> in <LOCATION>Fremont</LOCATION>, the only issues
that have been raised regarding their nicknames have centered on their logos.
<PERSON>Brook Vasconcellos</PERSON>, <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> and football coach at <LOCATION>Yerba Buena</LOCATION>, said he is
changing his team's logo to make it look like "a more dignified" Indian.;  
<PERSON>Benny Breazeale</PERSON>, student activities director at <LOCATION>Mission San Jose</LOCATION>, said the
only complaint he has heard in his four years at the school is that some
students want to use a female Indian logo in addition to the male Indian.;  
<PERSON>Vasconcellos</PERSON> and <PERSON>Breazeale</PERSON> said their schools represent Indians in a positive
manner. <PERSON>Phil Kelly</PERSON>, <LOCATION>A.D.</LOCATION> at <ORGANIZATION>Fremont High</ORGANIZATION>, said basically the same.;   "When
you take a nickname and don't demean it," <PERSON>Kelly</PERSON> said, "I have a hard time with
(any flap).";   <PERSON>Gorospe</PERSON> doesn't.;   "Even if a mascot showed a traditional
Indian headdress and was noble looking," he said, "I still don't believe in
Indian people being mascots. People shouldn't be mascots, period.";  
<PERSON>Vasconcellos</PERSON> added that if the controversy filters down from <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Yerba
Buena</LOCATION>, he and other school officials wouldn't ignore it.;   "If something like
this was very upsetting to the community," he said, "we'd listen."; Name that
team; The most popular nicknames among the state's 912 schools playing
football:;   Eagles 43;   Warriors 33;   <ORGANIZATION>Panthers</ORGANIZATION>, Mustangs 30;   Vikings 29; 
 Tigers, Cougars 28;   Bulldogs 26;   Spartans 25;   Knights, Wildcats 21;
...; Here are the Indian-related nicknames and how many schools use them:;  
Indians 16;   Braves 13;   Redskins 6;   Apaches, Chieftains 4;   <LOCATION>Cherokees</LOCATION>,
Comanches, <LOCATION>Chiefs</LOCATION>, Mohicans 1; ...; Here are some of the more unusual
nicknames in <LOCATION>California</LOCATION>:;   <LOCATION>Laguna Beach</LOCATION> Artists;   <PERSON>Mayfair</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Lakewood</LOCATION>)
<LOCATION>Monsoons</LOCATION>;   <LOCATION>Hollister Haybaylers</LOCATION>;   <PERSON>Chester Volcanoes</PERSON>;   <ORGANIZATION>Moorpark Musketeers</ORGANIZATION>; 
 <LOCATION>Venice</LOCATION> (<LOCATION>Los Angeles</LOCATION>) Gondoliers; -- Source: Cal-Hi Sports  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  SCOTT VIGALLON, Mercury News Staff Writer  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   911120  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Wednesday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  November  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  1C  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  981  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Wednesday, November 20, 1991
00325248,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06231220 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06231220 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Mercury News File Photograph; (Matt Williams)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  PROFESSIONAL; BASEBALL; NAME; LIST; QA  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  If you're a real Giants fan, then you believed in May that the Giants would be
in a pennant race. And if that is the case, then surely you can match most of
the players with their nicknames on this list.;   The nicknames are written on
the Giants' helmet rack in their Candlestick Park dugout. Nos. 12 and 13
correspond with one player. Some players are omitted because they have no
nickname on the rack.  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SO YOU THINK YOU KNOW YOUR GIANTS  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Off the Wall  </MEMO>
<TEXT>     Guess more than 17 correct and you're an insider; between 14 and 16, ardent
follower; 13 or fewer, bandwagon fan.;   1. Olly; 2. JB; 3. KD; 4. Burky; 5.
Bobcat; 6. Harry; 7. Rags; 8. Caveman; 9. Thrill; 10. Benji; 11. TK; 12. Tiny
(right-handed helmet); 13. Stevie Wonder (left-handed); 14. Nino; 15. KB; 16.
Lit; 17. Hondo; 18. Big Marine; 19. Mitch; 20. RT; 21. D.Lew; 22. Dino; 23.
Man-o-War; a. <PERSON>Greg Litton; b. Will Clark</PERSON>; c. <PERSON>Robby Thompson</PERSON>; d. <PERSON>Darren Lewis</PERSON>;
e. <PERSON>Jose Uribe</PERSON>; f. <PERSON>Kevin Mitchell</PERSON>; g. <PERSON>Kelly Downs</PERSON>; h. <PERSON>Francisco Oliveras</PERSON>; i.
<PERSON>Mike Benjamin</PERSON>; j. <PERSON>Willie McGee</PERSON>; k. <PERSON>Don Robinson</PERSON>; l. <PERSON>Trevor Wilson</PERSON>; m. <PERSON>Matt
Williams</PERSON>; n. <PERSON>Jeff Brantley</PERSON>; o. <PERSON>Mike Felder</PERSON>; p. <PERSON>Kirt Manwaring</PERSON>; q. <PERSON>John
Burkett</PERSON>; r. <PERSON>Dave Anderson</PERSON>; s. <PERSON>Kevin Bass</PERSON>; t. <PERSON>Dave Righetti</PERSON>; <PERSON>u. Terry Kennedy</PERSON>;
v. Bud Black; Answers; 1-h, 2-n, 3-g, 4-q, 5-l, 6-v, 7-t, 8-k, 9-b, 10-i,
11-u, 12/13-o, 14-e, 15-s, 16-a, 17-r, 18-m, 19-f, 20-c, 21-d, 22-j, 23-p.;
THE FEW, THE PROUD . . .; If you've taken the adjacent quiz, you surely are
wondering what person was behind this <ORGANIZATION>Big Marine</ORGANIZATION> business. And what about
<PERSON>Dino?</PERSON>;   <PERSON>Matt Williams</PERSON>, above, said "Big Marine" was just one of the tags
given by former <ORGANIZATION>Giants</ORGANIZATION> pitcher and clubhouse leader <PERSON>Mike Krukow.</PERSON>;   Now that
he's out of <LOCATION>St. Louis</LOCATION>, <PERSON>Willie McGee</PERSON> goes from "E.T." to "Dino."; FUNNIEST ROAD
VIDEO; <PERSON>Bill Craib</PERSON> and <PERSON>Sue Easler</PERSON>, who are trying to visit 178 major and minor
league stadiums in one season, experienced a Wall of Fame moment in <LOCATION>San
Antonio</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Texas.</LOCATION>;   Puffy the Taco, the home team's mascot, was racing a little
girl around the bases. "She was supposed to tackle him before he got to home,"
<PERSON>Craib</PERSON> recounted. "She missed him and smacked the dirt. Everyone started
booing. The little girl got up, walked over slowly and punched the taco. The
crowd went wild."; '. . . At <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt</ORGANIZATION>, our system is academically sound
while the football program is corrupt. Most schools in the <ORGANIZATION>Southeastern
Conference</ORGANIZATION> are academically corrupt and athletically sound.  '-- <PERSON>Gerry
DiNardo</PERSON>, <ORGANIZATION>Vanderbilt</ORGANIZATION>'s new football coach, who was reprimanded by the
<ORGANIZATION>Southeastern Conference</ORGANIZATION> for making the remark.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Information for this column was compiled from Mercury News wire services.
Mercury News Staff Writer Mark Newman contributed.  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910818  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  August  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  469  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday, August 18, 1991
00231220,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890113-0016 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-01-13-89 0131EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r w PM-BushBuddies Bjt   01-13 0680</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Bush Buddies, Bjt,680</SECOND>
<HEAD>Bush Known as `Ellie the Elephant' After Wartime Rescue</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By ROBERT M. ANDREWS</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>WASHINGTON (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Surviving crew members of the World War II
submarine Finback are looking forward to a nostalgic reunion with
<PERSON>George Bush</PERSON>, the young <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION> pilot they dubbed ``Ellie the Elephant''
after rescuing him from the <LOCATION>Pacific Ocean</LOCATION> more than 44 years ago.
   <PERSON>Don Kohler</PERSON>, 64, of <ORGANIZATION>Rogers</ORGANIZATION>, <LOCATION>Ark.</LOCATION>, the torpedoman who helped pull a
grateful <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> to safety from his orange life raft onto the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s
deck, remembers offering a smile and a hearty ``welcome aboard,''
but recalls little else about the incident.
   ``At that time, he was just another downed pilot,'' said <PERSON>Kohler</PERSON>,
a retired <LOCATION>Chicago</LOCATION> businessman. ``Nobody back then knew he'd become
president of the <LOCATION>United States</LOCATION>.''
   Rescued after his plane was shot down by Japanese fire, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>
eagerly took his turn at night lookout watches and other seagoing
duties, watched <PERSON>Betty Grable</PERSON> movies in the wardroom and donned
earphones to listen in awe as the submarine's torpedoes sank two
enemy ships.
   Former Finback officers remember the 20-year-old <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> as a
gregarious jokester who earned the nickname ``Ellie'' for his comic
wardroom imitation of a trumpeting elephant, they said in recent
telephone interviews.
   ``I remember he was very lively, obviously intelligent and very
personable,'' said retired Rear Adm. <PERSON>Lawrence Heyworth</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Virginia
Beach</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Va.</LOCATION>, who was the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>'s torpedo and gunnery officer when
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> was hauled aboard on <DATE>Sept. 2, 1944</DATE>.
   Said <PERSON>Heyworth</PERSON>: ``All three pilots we rescued were bright,
bright-eyed young men, but <PERSON>George</PERSON> seemed the most outgoing and had
the most ebullient personality. He was the most entertaining, and he
made us laugh a lot.
   ``We called him <PERSON>Ellie</PERSON> because of his outstanding imitation of an
elephant trumpeting. Ellie the Elephant. It wasn't because we all
sat around thinking we were Republicans. We must have seen one in a
Tarzan movie. We just thought elephants were funny. We kept asking
<PERSON>George</PERSON> to do it over and over again.''
   ``He had a tremendous sense of humor,'' recalled <PERSON>W.E.</PERSON> ``Bill''
<PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> of <LOCATION>Bay St. Louis</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Miss.</LOCATION>, an insurance agent and retired <ORGANIZATION>Navy</ORGANIZATION>
commander. As a bearded ensign aboard the <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION>, <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> filmed
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s rescue with an 8mm <ORGANIZATION>Kodak</ORGANIZATION> movie camera.
   <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> said that at last count, nearly 30 surviving officers and
enlisted crewmen of the Finback were planning to attend <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s
swearing-in at noontime <DATE>Jan. 20</DATE> at the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION>.
   They and a few of <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s former flying buddies plan to sit
together in prime bleacher seats on <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> for the
inaugural parade after <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> takes the presidential oath of office.
   Inaugural officials reportedly were trying to arrange a reunion
for <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> and his old submarine buddies at <ORGANIZATION>Blair House</ORGANIZATION>, the
presidential guest quarters across the street from the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>,
possibly next <DATE>Wednesday</DATE>.
   <PERSON>Heyworth</PERSON> and <PERSON>Edwards</PERSON> have stayed in touch with <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> over the
years. But most of the Finback veterans haven't seen or spoken to
<PERSON>Bush</PERSON> since he left the submarine at <LOCATION>Midway Island</LOCATION> after a month-long
combat patrol.
   <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> won the Distinguished Flying Cross for completing his
bombing run against a Japanese radio communications center in the
<LOCATION>Bonin Islands</LOCATION>, about 600 miles south of <LOCATION>Japan</LOCATION>, after his Grumman
Avenger torpedo bomber was struck by enemy fire and engulfed in
flames. <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> bailed out over the water but his two crew members were
lost.
   According to his autobiography, <PERSON>Bush</PERSON>'s only injuries were a gash
on the forehead and a painful sting from a Portuguese man-of-war. He
was picked up by the Finback less than two hours after his parachute
hit the ocean.
   ``I'm proud of what I was able to do to help <PERSON>Mr. Bush</PERSON> on board
our boat,'' said <PERSON>Kohler</PERSON>.
   But <PERSON>Dan Moody</PERSON>, 71, a <ORGANIZATION>Finback</ORGANIZATION> veteran and retired radiation
laboratory technician living in <LOCATION>Albany</LOCATION>, <LOCATION>Calif.</LOCATION>, gave little thought
to <PERSON>Bush</PERSON> at the time.
   ``We brought him aboard, dried him out and gave him hot coffee,''
he said, and then forgot him.
   ``I was 26 years old and a first class torpedoman,'' <ORGANIZATION>Moody</ORGANIZATION> said.
``Who'd pay any attention to a 20-year-old kid?''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP901022-0198 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NY-10-22-90 1427EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>a e BC-APN--TVWeek ADV04   10-22 0697</FIRST>
<SECOND>BC-APN--TV Week, ADV 04,0911</SECOND>
<NOTE>$Adv04</NOTE>
<HEAD>AGENCIES AND RADIO OUT</HEAD>
<NOTE>For Release Sunday, Nov. 4</NOTE>
<HEAD>From AP Newsfeatures</HEAD>
<NOTE>(APN SUNDAY ILLUSTRATIONS: Mailed print subscribers get 1 b&amp;w
photo.)</NOTE>

<BYLINE>By JERRY BUCK</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>AP Television Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>LOS ANGELES (AP) </DATELINE>

<NOTE>END ADV</NOTE>

</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA050890-0036 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 215614 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
May 8, 1990, Tuesday, Orange County Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
Metro; Part B; Page 8; Column 2; Metro Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
136 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
THE NICKNAME PLOY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
I have just received my sample ballot for the upcoming (<DATE>June 5</DATE>) election. In 
reviewing the various candidates I note that entirely too many of them have 
cute little nicknames in parentheses. 
</P>
<P>
Perhaps it is old-fashioned to run for public office using your proper name. 
</P>
<P>
If the individuals in question were known better by the nickname it might be 
acceptable. However, in most cases the individuals have simply included the 
common informal name, i.e., <PERSON>Robert</PERSON> -- "Bob" or <PERSON>John</PERSON> -- "<PERSON>Jack</PERSON>." If this is a 
current ploy to win elections, I, for one, will not fall for it. 
</P>
<P>
If these individuals really think this will help voter recognition, I question 
their intelligence. I will vote for the "less cute" candidate and/or the one 
with the less placards attached to utility poles. 
</P>
<P>
FREDERICK J. (FRED) RICHARDS 
</P>
<P>
Orange 
</P></TEXT>
<TYPE>
<P>
Letter to the Editor 
</P>
</TYPE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP880918-0036 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-09-18-88 1155EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a AM-Radon     09-18 0823</FIRST>
<SECOND>AM-Radon,0849</SECOND>
<HEAD>Radon's Shadow Remains Over Town That Put It on The Map</HEAD>
<BYLINE>By DAVID S. MARTIN</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Associated Press Writer</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>BOYERTOWN, Pa. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Nearly four years after radon from his
house caused <PERSON>Stanley Watras</PERSON> to set off radiation detectors at the
<LOCATION>Limerick</LOCATION> nuclear power plant, he wonders daily about his family's
health.
   ``There's a fine line between making yourself sick by worrying
and having a genuine concern and doing the best you can,'' said
<PERSON>Watras</PERSON>, 37, a technical adviser at the plant.
   Radon levels in <PERSON>Watras</PERSON>' home of 800 times the concentration
deemed hazardous first alerted environmental officials and
residents of southeastern <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> to the danger of indoor
radon concentration. Last week, the head of the <ORGANIZATION>Environmental
Protection Agency</ORGANIZATION> said the problem is more widespread than
previously believed and urged that every home in the country be
tested.
   Radon is a radioactive gas produced by the natural decaying of
uranium found in all soil and rock and usually dissipated
harmlessly into the atmosphere. It poses a health threat when it
seeps through the ground and collects in homes.
   The colorless, odorless gas could be responsible for 20,000 of
the nation's 130,000 annual lung cancer deaths, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> estimates.
It kills by leaving its own radioactive decay products in the lung,
irradiating the organs for a lifetime.
   Environmental officials first believed radon to be concentrated
along a geological formation known as the Reading Prong, a narrow
area of high-uranium soil stretching from Reading, <LOCATION>Pa.</LOCATION>, across
northern <LOCATION>New Jersey</LOCATION> into <LOCATION>New York</LOCATION> state.
   But a recent <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> survey in seven states and Indian land found
health-threatening levels of radon in <PERCENT>29 percent</PERCENT> of 11,000 homes
tested.
   The <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> has set 4 picocuries of radon per liter of air as a
guideline for determining when long-term exposure poses a health
threat. A picocurie is a measure of radiation. Exposure to 15
picocuries of radon for a lifetime is equivalent to smoking a pack
of cigarettes a day, the <ORGANIZATION>EPA</ORGANIZATION> says.
   A reading taken in the living room of <PERSON>Watras</PERSON>' modest,
split-level house in <DATE>December 1984</DATE> was 3,200 picocuries, the
highest ever recorded at a private home. <PERSON>Watras</PERSON>, his wife and two
young children were evacuated soon afterward.
   <PERSON>Tim Hartman</PERSON>, administrator of the state Radon Monitoring Program
set up several miles away in late <DATE>1985</DATE>, said the Watrases' house
was built inches above uranium-laden granite.
   ``He just had an ungodly concentration of radon spewing into his
home,'' <PERSON>Hartman</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Watras</PERSON> and his family returned to the house in <DATE>August 1985</DATE> after
a <MONEY>$32,600</MONEY> research project dramatically reduced the radon level.
Watras and his wife have since had a third child.
   ``At the beginning, we were saying, `Why us?' We were looking at
the children saying, `What did we do to you?''' Watras recalled in
an interview at his home last week.
   Watras now believes God put his family in the home for a purpose.
   ``What we've got to do from now on is try to help other
people,'' he said, calling his efforts to bring attention to radon
``a crusade.''
   Some of the other residents in his suburban <LOCATION>Berks County</LOCATION>
neighborhood, nicknamed <ORGANIZATION>Radon Hills</ORGANIZATION>, agree with him and have
organized to push for legislation protecting homes from the toxic
gas. Others believe the threat is overblown.
   <PERSON>Kay Jones</PERSON>, who lives down the street from <PERSON>Watras</PERSON>, is president
of <ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvanians Against Radon</ORGANIZATION>, a group with about 150 members.
   <PERSON>Ms. Jones</PERSON> believes national building codes should include radon
guidelines, wants public service advertisements that warn people
about the danger of radon and supports a law that would force a
family to leave a home when radon levels reach a certain point.
   Unless the government acts, people will forget about radon as
media interest wanes, she said.
   ``Right now, everything you pick up, it's radon, radon, radon,
but in two or three days it's going to die out,'' <PERSON>Ms. Jones</PERSON> said.
   <PERSON>Dennis Hess</PERSON>, another neighbor, is one of those skeptical about
the radon threat.
   ``I don't think I'm walking into a gas chamber when I walk into
my home. I'd like to think something else will get me before the
radon,'' said <PERSON>Hess</PERSON>, a 34-year-old machinist at a chemical plant.
   <PERSON>Hess</PERSON> hasn't measured the radon level in his home, and he said
environmental officials haven't been able to convince him that the
problem can't be alleviated by opening a few windows.
   No records exist of the number of people who have had their
homes refitted in <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> to reduce the amount of radon in the
air. Hartman estimated the number was in the thousands, most of
them along the <LOCATION>Reading Prong</LOCATION>, where <PERCENT>60 percent</PERCENT> of the homes tested
had levels above 4 picocuries.
   Even when houses have been fixed, health worries remain.
   ``The fear never goes away,'' said <PERSON>Ms. Jones</PERSON>, whose family spent
five years in a home that recorded a radon level of 450 picocuries
before being fitted with a ventilation system. ``We're living in
the unknown.''
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP900704-0034 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-07-04-90 0316EDT</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-Deaths     07-04 0298</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Deaths,0311</SECOND>
<BYLINE>By The Associated Press</BYLINE>
<BYLINE>Snooky Lanson</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>NASHVILLE, Tenn. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Snooky Lanson, a singing star of
television's ``Your Hit Parade'' in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, is dead at age 76.
   Lanson, whose real name was <PERSON>Roy Landman</PERSON>, was nicknamed
``Snooky'' at age 2 after the <PERSON>Irving Berlin</PERSON> tune ``Snooky-Ookums.''
   He got his first singing job with band leader <PERSON>Francis Craig</PERSON> at
<LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> radio station <ORGANIZATION>WSM</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, Lanson was hired by the <ORGANIZATION>Ray Noble Band</ORGANIZATION>, and <DATE>a year
later</DATE> recorded the hit record ``By the Light of the <PERSON>Silvery Moon</PERSON>.''
   In the late <DATE>1940s</DATE>, he had a hit with ``The Old Master Painter,''
which helped him land the spot on ``Your Hit Parade.'' He sang on
the show from <DATE>1950</DATE> to <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   Lanson died <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> where he had lived since <DATE>1967</DATE>.
</TEXT>
<BYLINE>George Peters</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>PHILADELPHIA (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Snooky Lanson, a singing star of
television's ``Your Hit Parade'' in the <DATE>1950s</DATE>, is dead at age 76.
   Lanson, whose real name was <PERSON>Roy Landman</PERSON>, was nicknamed
``Snooky'' at age 2 after the <PERSON>Irving Berlin</PERSON> tune ``Snooky-Ookums.''
   He got his first singing job with band leader <PERSON>Francis Craig</PERSON> at
<LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> radio station <ORGANIZATION>WSM</ORGANIZATION>.
   In <DATE>1940</DATE>, Lanson was hired by the <ORGANIZATION>Ray Noble Band</ORGANIZATION>, and <DATE>a year
later</DATE> recorded the hit record ``By the Light of the <PERSON>Silvery Moon</PERSON>.''
   In the late <DATE>1940s</DATE>, he had a hit with ``The Old Master Painter,''
which helped him land the spot on ``Your Hit Parade.'' He sang on
the show from <DATE>1950</DATE> to <DATE>1957</DATE>.
   Lanson died <DATE>Monday</DATE> in <LOCATION>Nashville</LOCATION> where he had lived since <DATE>1967</DATE>.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> SJMN91-06098126 </DOCNO>
<ACCESS> 06098126 </ACCESS>
<CAPTION>  Photo; PHOTO: Associated Press; (Mets on plane)  </CAPTION>
<DESCRIPT>  SPORT; HUMOR; BRIEF  </DESCRIPT>
<LEADPARA>  Keith Hernandez and Darryl Strawberry are gone but not forgotten. That's why
the Mets insist on performing their annual re-enactment of the 1989
team-picture fight.;   'OIL CAN' BOYD HAS NOTHING ON THESE GUYS  </LEADPARA>
<SECTION>  Sports  </SECTION>
<HEADLINE>  SOME FUN  </HEADLINE>
<MEMO>  Off the Wall  </MEMO>
<TEXT>  In the old days, when nicknames were nicknames, baseball idols were guys such
as "Old Aches and Pains" <PERSON>Luke Appling</PERSON> and <PERSON>Stan</PERSON> "The Man" <PERSON>Musial</PERSON>. Stars all,
but like <DATE>today</DATE>, stars didn't have a monopoly on monikers. Our crack research
staff came up with a few relatively unknown (at least to most young folks)
nicknames from yesteryear:;    "Death to Flying Things" -- <PERSON>Bob Ferguson</PERSON>;
"Hippity" -- <PERSON>Johnny Hopp</PERSON>; "Puddin' Head" -- <PERSON>Willie Jones</PERSON>; "The Freshest Man on
Earth" -- <PERSON>Arlie Latham</PERSON>; "Earache" -- <PERSON>Benny Meyer</PERSON>; "Losing Pitcher" -- <PERSON>Hugh
Mulcahy</PERSON>; "Twinkletoes" -- <PERSON>George Selkirk</PERSON>; "Dr. Strangeglove" -- <PERSON>Dick Stuart</PERSON>;
"Big Poison" -- <PERSON>Paul Waner</PERSON>; "Little Poison" -- younger brother <PERSON>Lloyd Waner</PERSON>;
and "The Arkansas Hummingbird" -- Lon Warneke.;    Then there's our personal
favorite, though not too old, "Eyechart" -- <PERSON>Doug Gwosdz.</PERSON>;  WHAT MONEY CAN BUY;
Whoever the bonehead was who said money can't buy happiness never hung out
with <PERSON>Roger Clemen</PERSON>$. We can't tell you what <PERSON>Mr. Rocket</PERSON> has planned for his
soon-to-be-outdated <MONEY>$21,521,000</MONEY> contract, but here are some possibilities:;   
(check) Make a chain of <MONEY>$1</MONEY> bills that would stretch from <LOCATION>Fenway Park</LOCATION> to just
short of <LOCATION>Las Vegas</LOCATION>, more than 2,080 miles.;    (check) Buy every seat at
<LOCATION>Fenway Park</LOCATION> for 57 games this season. His friends would miss 24 games; <PERSON>Clemens</PERSON>
might miss five because of his suspension.;    (check) Pay the salaries of all
big league umpires for the next five years.;    (check) Fly everyone in his
hometown of <PERSON>Katy</PERSON>, <LOCATION>Texas</LOCATION> -- population 6,000 -- to <LOCATION>Boston</LOCATION> and back for opening
day, the first game of the playoffs and the first game of the World Series.;  
 (check) Get a hot dog, soft drink and bag of peanuts for everyone who saw the
<ORGANIZATION>Red Sox</ORGANIZATION> play in person last season.;  'He's somewhere in the heel or the boot.
 '-- <LOCATION>Atlanta</LOCATION> Coach <PERSON>Bob Weiss</PERSON>, after the Hawks waived missing forward <PERSON>Trevor
Wilson</PERSON> when he left to join an Italian team.  </TEXT>
<BYLINE>  Information for this column was compiled from Mercury News wire services.  </BYLINE>
<COUNTRY>  USA  </COUNTRY>
<EDITION>  Morning Final  </EDITION>
<CODE>  SJ  </CODE>
<NAME>  San Jose Mercury News  </NAME>
<PUBDATE>   910407  </PUBDATE> 
<DAY>  Sunday  </DAY>
<MONTH>  April  </MONTH>
<PG.COL>  2D  </PG.COL>
<PUBYEAR>  1991  </PUBYEAR>
<REGION>  WEST  </REGION>
<FEATURE>  PHOTO  </FEATURE>
<STATE>  CA  </STATE>
<WORD.CT>  353  </WORD.CT>
<DATELINE>  Sunday April 7, 1991
00098126,SJ1  </DATELINE>
<COPYRGHT>  Copyright 1991, San Jose Mercury News  </COPYRGHT>
<LIMLEN>  1  </LIMLEN>
<LANGUAGE>  ENG  </LANGUAGE>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> AP890420-0019 </DOCNO>
<FILEID>AP-NR-04-20-89 0210EST</FILEID>
<FIRST>r a PM-QueenCity     04-20 0227</FIRST>
<SECOND>PM-Queen City,0233</SECOND>
<HEAD>Officials Want To Change Town's Queen City Nickname</HEAD>
<DATELINE>MARQUETTE, Mich. (AP) </DATELINE>
<TEXT>
   Municipal leaders want to change their
town's ``Queen City'' nickname to ``Superior Location'' because
they think the current moniker might be misinterpreted.
   ``It has come to my attention that there has been a resurgence
of the use of the phrase `<ORGANIZATION>Queen City</ORGANIZATION>' to describe the city of
<LOCATION>Marquette</LOCATION>,'' City Manager <PERSON>David Svanda</PERSON> said in a recent letter to
community leaders.
   ``The term's negative connotations conjured by many people do
not give justice to all that the <LOCATION>Marquette</LOCATION> area has to offer.''
   Visitors might think <LOCATION>Queen City</LOCATION> refers to homosexuals, said
Mayor <PERSON>Robert Berube</PERSON>.
   Marquette historian <PERSON>Fred Rydholm</PERSON>, who is writing a history of
the Lake Superior port of 23,280 people, said that was silly.
Svanda's request is ``the most ridiculous thing I've ever heard,''
<PERSON>Rydholm</PERSON> said.
   The <ORGANIZATION>Queen City</ORGANIZATION> nickname originated after a <DATE>1868</DATE> fire, when an
ordinance required all buildings in the center city area to be
rebuilt with stone or masonry, he said.
   Visitors expecting to see the wood construction of other <LOCATION>Upper
Peninsula</LOCATION> towns in <LOCATION>Michigan</LOCATION> instead were greeted with tall spires
of stone.
   ``There was nothing from <LOCATION>Seattle</LOCATION> to <LOCATION>Buffalo</LOCATION> like it in the
north, and it was also the best port on Lake Superior, so it was
called the <LOCATION>Queen City</LOCATION> of the North,'' <PERSON>Rydholm</PERSON> said.
</TEXT>
</DOC><DOC>
<DOCNO> LA012089-0115 </DOCNO>
<DOCID> 7913 </DOCID>
<DATE>
<P>
January 20, 1989, Friday, Home Edition 
</P>
</DATE>
<SECTION>
<P>
View; Part 5; Page 1; Column 3; View Desk 
</P>
</SECTION>
<LENGTH>
<P>
1410 words 
</P>
</LENGTH>
<HEADLINE>
<P>
WHAT THE PARADE WILL PASS BY 
</P>
</HEADLINE>
<BYLINE>
<P>
By BETTY CUNIBERTI, Times Staff Writer 
</P>
</BYLINE>
<DATELINE>
<P>
WASHINGTON 
</P>
</DATELINE>
<TEXT>
<P>
When <PERSON>George</PERSON> and <PERSON>Barbara Bush</PERSON> set out from the Capitol in their new <MONEY>$600,000</MONEY> 
armored limousine for today's inaugural march, they'll travel a 
much-transformed <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION>. 
</P>
<P>
As they near the parade's end and turn toward the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, they'll view the 
crown jewel of the avenue's <MONEY>$1.5-billion</MONEY> renovation, the <ORGANIZATION>Willard Hotel</ORGANIZATION>, the 
once vacant Beaux-Arts hotel that was restored to its original opulence and 
reopened in <DATE>1986</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
The hotel and a host of other buildings and parks are among the major new 
sights that have swept <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> since <DATE>1961</DATE>, when President <PERSON>John F. 
Kennedy</PERSON> rode the boulevard for his inaugural and saw a historic street so 
battered, filthy and dreary that he demanded that it be rebuilt to an image 
befitting <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>'s Main Street. 
</P>
<P>
It has taken almost 30 years, more than <MONEY>$1.5 billion</MONEY> and the efforts of a 
public agency working with private developers to fulfill <LOCATION>Kennedy</LOCATION>'s demand. 
</P>
<P>
But now, gone are the shuttered shops, saloons and cheap hotels. New parks and 
lights, as well as restorations of historic buildings, have given <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> 
Avenue a clean, expensive look on the inaugural parade route. When the Bushes 
set out today on that path, stretching from the <LOCATION>Capitol</LOCATION> to the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, to 
their right will be the newly completed <PERSON>Meade Plaza</PERSON>, featuring the relocated 
18-foot marble monument to Civil War Maj. Gen. <PERSON>George Gordon Meade</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
To their left will be the dramatic, angular East Building of the <ORGANIZATION>National 
Gallery of Art</ORGANIZATION>, designed by architect <PERSON>I. M. Pei</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
The parade will continue past the <ORGANIZATION>Andrew Mellon Memorial Fountain</ORGANIZATION>, whose 
54-foot wide bronze basin is the largest ever cast in the world. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Cages of <ORGANIZATION>Canaries 
</P>
<P>
The Bushes</ORGANIZATION> will zip by <PERSON>John Marshall Park</PERSON>, one of five new park plazas 
completed since the last parade. The park connects the avenue to <LOCATION>Judiciary 
Square</LOCATION>, where cages of yellow canaries lined the walls of <PERSON>Ulysses S. Grant</PERSON>'s 
<DATE>1873</DATE> inaugural ball. 
</P>
<P>
Next to <ORGANIZATION>Marshall Park</ORGANIZATION>'s stair-stepped garden and fountains is the gleaming, new 
<ORGANIZATION>Postmodern Canadian Embassy</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Moving up past 6th Street, the Bushes will ride past two elaborately 
refurbished office buildings. 
</P>
<P>
Next they will see <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s most laughed-at monument. The <ORGANIZATION>Temperance 
Fountain</ORGANIZATION>, featuring entwined dolphins beneath a water crane, symbolizes the 
superiority of water over demon rum. It was donated to <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION> by <LOCATION>San 
Francisco</LOCATION> dentist <PERSON>Henry Cogswell</PERSON> in the <DATE>1800s</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
Moving along, the Bushes will pass the <ORGANIZATION>Federal Trade Commission</ORGANIZATION> and another new 
park, <ORGANIZATION>Market Square Park Navy Memorial</ORGANIZATION>. The park features a 100-foot-wide disk 
inlaid with a map of the world, fountains and a 7-foot statue titled, "Lone 
Sailor." Military bands give concerts there in the <DATE>summer</DATE>. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Houses <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Constitution 
</P>
<P>
Across the street, on the south side, will be the sprawling <ORGANIZATION>National Archives</ORGANIZATION>, 
designed by <PERSON>John Russell Pope</PERSON>, architect of the <ORGANIZATION>Jefferson Memorial</ORGANIZATION>. Built in 
the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, its 75-foot-high exhibit hall houses the <LOCATION>U.S.</LOCATION> Constitution, the 
Declaration of Independence and the Bill of Rights. 
</P>
<P>
As much as those documents are a part of American history, <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> 
has been a key, colorful byway of the nation's capital. 
</P>
<P>
City planner <PERSON>Pierre L'Enfant</PERSON> -- hired by <PERSON>George Washington</PERSON> to plot a capital in 
the 10 square miles ceded from <LOCATION>Virginia</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Maryland</LOCATION> -- envisioned <LOCATION>Pennsylvania 
Avenue</LOCATION> as a sparkling boulevard of foreign embassies with unobstructed, 
breath-taking views between the Capitol at one end and the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, 14 
blocks away. 
</P>
<P>
But the avenue evolved differently. During the Civil War, a section of 
<LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> Avenue at 14th Street became the city's red-light district. The 
man selected to care for this area was Gen. <PERSON>Joseph Hooker</PERSON>, who distinguished 
himself to such an extent that ladies of the night became known as hookers. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Commissions Appointed 
</P>
<P>
By the <DATE>1930s</DATE>, the shops and boarding houses began to make way for a wall of 
Neoclassical office buildings. In the <DATE>1960s</DATE>, the avenue was a hodgepodge of 
drab office buildings and run-down stores. 
</P>
<P>
Presidents <PERSON>Kennedy</PERSON>, <PERSON>Lyndon B. Johnson</PERSON> and <PERSON>Richard M. Nixon</PERSON> appointed a series 
of commissions to address the problem. 
</P>
<P>
But a turning point did not come until <DATE>1972</DATE>, when <ORGANIZATION>Congress</ORGANIZATION> established the 
<ORGANIZATION>Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corp.</ORGANIZATION> to supervise the refurbishing of the 
avenue in tandem with the private sector. 
</P>
<P>
Many of the agency's major plans have come to fruition since the last inaugural 
parade in <DATE>1981</DATE>. (<PERSON>Ronald Reagan</PERSON>'s <DATE>1985</DATE> parade was canceled because of bitter 
cold weather.) Many feel the street has never looked better. 
</P>
<P>
But amid the beauty of the boulevard, there is also a lingering sadness. On a 
normal day, the homeless roam up and down the street. One man has set up a 
permanent residence of sorts, a configuration of plastic and cardboard, right 
His scrawled sign proclaims him to be a war veteran. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Homeless to Be Removed 
</P>
<P>
On parade day, the homeless will be removed from the avenue, though police have 
refused to discuss their plans for how this will be done. 
</P>
<P>
The Bushes, on the inaugural march, will pass between the <PERSON>J. Edgar Hoover</PERSON> FBI 
Building on their right and the <ORGANIZATION>Department of Justice</ORGANIZATION> on their left. The chunky 
FBI Building may not be pretty but it's one of <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s most intriguing 
tourist attractions, especially the display of the "10 Most Wanted" criminals 
list. 
</P>
<P>
To spruce up the sprawling <ORGANIZATION>FBI</ORGANIZATION> building's <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION> facade, the 
development agency is installing panels with eight life-sized figures of <LOCATION>George 
Lincoln</PERSON>, <PERSON>Theodore Roosevelt</PERSON> and <PERSON>Woodrow Wilson</PERSON>. 
</P>
<P>
Another new office development, 1001 <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Ave.</LOCATION>, will pop into view 
next. The 785,000-square foot facility includes a central atrium and 
incorporates a number of old architectural facades. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Saved from Wrecking Ball 
</P>
<P>
On the left is a building that dominates this area of the avenue, the 
Romanesque-style Old Post Office Building, whose soaring observation tower 
brought it the nickname "Old Tooth" and made it the tallest building in 
<LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>. Preservation groups had to fight to save it from the wrecking ball 
before an enormous restoration effort turned the building into a shopping 
gallery and 10-story office complex. 
</P>
<P>
Across the street from the Old Post Office is the Evening Star Building, built 
in <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s Beaux-Arts style to house the afternoon newspaper. Its finely 
detailed white marble facade is being spruced up as part of a rehabilitation 
project that eventually will contain 212,000 square feet of office and retail 
space. 
</P>
<P>
Another new office complex appears next, across from the massive Federal 
Triangle office building complex. The Bushes then pass yet another park, 
renamed Freedom Plaza in <DATE>1988</DATE> in honor of <ORGANIZATION>Dr. Martin Luther King Jr</ORGANIZATION>. A block 
long, Freedom Plaza is one of the major public spaces on the avenue and is the 
first of three parks spanning the next three blocks. 
</P>
<P>
Just beyond Freedom Plaza, the Bushes can see a brand-new shopping, hotel and 
office complex, and the restored <ORGANIZATION>National Theater</ORGANIZATION>. <LOCATION>Washington</LOCATION>'s oldest theater, 
it first opened in <DATE>1835</DATE> and reopened in <DATE>1984</DATE> after a major face lift. 
</P>
<P>
</P>
<P>
Lincoln Held Meetings 
</P>
<P>
The next block contains Pershing Park and just beyond it, the dazzling, 
renovated <ORGANIZATION>Willard Hotel and Office Building</ORGANIZATION>. 
</P>
<P>
Lincoln held occasional staff meetings in the Willard lobby. <PERSON>Franklin Pierce</PERSON>, 
<PERSON>Calvin Coolidge</PERSON> and <PERSON>Harry S. Truman</PERSON> all stayed in the hotel, where King wrote 
his "I Have a Dream" speech and where guest <PERSON>Julia Ward Howe</PERSON> wrote the words to 
the "Battle Hymn of the Republic" on hotel stationery. 
</P>
<P>
Howe might have written another battle hymn if she could have looked into a 
crystal ball and seen the coming of the <DATE>1989</DATE> inaugural prices. The Presidential 
Suite, which has been rented out this week and includes a separate dining room, 
a grand piano, four-poster king size bed and a spa, goes for <MONEY>$2,300</MONEY> a night. 
</P>
<P>
The parade route then makes a right turn where <LOCATION>Pennsylvania</LOCATION> is rerouted to jut 
around the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, passing the giant Treasury Building and <PERSON>Garfinckel</PERSON>'s 
<ORGANIZATION>Department Store</ORGANIZATION> before taking a left back onto <LOCATION>Pennsylvania Avenue</LOCATION>, now in 
front of the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION> grounds. 
</P>
<P>
Across the street will be <LOCATION>Lafayette Square</LOCATION>, a large park that has become the 
parking spot for protest groups a lunch spot for office workers and home to 
many homeless. 
</P>
<P>
The parade ends just past the <ORGANIZATION>White House</ORGANIZATION>, and the Bushes then can move into 
their new home. 
</P></TEXT>
<GRAPHIC>
<P>
Photo, Harry Truman traveling along Pennsylvania Ave. in 1949. Distributed by 
Pennsylvania Avenue Development Corp.; Photo, This is George Bush's view of 
avenue toward White House. ANACLETO RAPPING / Los Angeles Times 
</P>
</GRAPHIC>
<SUBJECT>
<P>
PENNSYLVANIA AVENUE DEVELOPMENT CORP; WASHINGTON DC -- CELEBRATIONS; PARADES; 
